<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Pediatr</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Pediatrics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">1187897</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2431-5-27</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16033643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2431-5-27</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Otitis media in young Aboriginal children from remote communities in Northern and Central Australia: a cross-sectional survey </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Peter S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>peterm@menzies.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>Amanda J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>amanda@menzies.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silberberg</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>petersilberberg@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mellon</surname><given-names>Gabrielle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>neil.gab@bigpond.net.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Cate</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>catew@menzies.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>emhamilton@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beissbarth</surname><given-names>Jemima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Jemima.Beissbarth@menzies.edu.au</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Ear Health and Education Unit, Menzies School of Health Research, Darwin, Australia</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institute of Advanced Studies, Charles Darwin University, Australia</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Northern Territory Clinical School, Flinders University, Darwin, Australia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2431/5/27"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2005 Morris et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Morris et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Middle ear disease (otitis media) is common and frequently severe in Australian Aboriginal children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>There have not been any recent large-scale surveys using clear definitions and a standardised middle ear assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The aim of the study was to determine the prevalence of middle ear disease (otitis media) in a high-risk population of young Aboriginal children from remote communities in Northern and Central Australia. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>709 Aboriginal children aged 6–30 months living in 29 communities from 4 health regions participated in the study between May and November 2001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Otitis media (OM) and perforation of the tympanic membrane (TM) were diagnosed by tympanometry, pneumatic otoscopy, and video-otoscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We used otoscopic criteria (bulging TM or recent perforation) to diagnose acute otitis media. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>914 children were eligible to participate in the study and 709 were assessed (78%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Otitis media affected nearly all children (91%, 95%CI 88, 94). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Overall prevalence estimates adjusted for clustering by community were: 10% (95%CI 8, 12) for unilateral otitis media with effusion (OME); 31% (95%CI 27, 34) for bilateral OME; 26% (95%CI 23, 30) for acute otitis media without perforation (AOM/woP); 7% (95%CI 4, 9) for AOM with perforation (AOM/wiP); 2% (95%CI 1, 3) for dry perforation; and 15% (95%CI 11, 19) for chronic suppurative otitis media (CSOM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The perforation prevalence ranged from 0–60% between communities and from 19–33% between regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Perforations of the tympanic membrane affected 40% of children in their first 18 months of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These were not always persistent. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Overall, 1 in every 2 children examined had otoscopic signs consistent with suppurative ear disease and 1 in 4 children had a perforated tympanic membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Some of the children with intact tympanic membranes had experienced a perforation that healed before the survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In this high-risk population, high rates of tympanic perforation were associated with high rates of bulging of the tympanic membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Middle ear disease (otitis media) is common and frequently severe in Australian Aboriginal children [1,2] In the worst affected communities, perforation of the tympanic membrane (TM) may affect more than 50% of children [3,4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Such high rates have not been described consistently in any other population in the world. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>We have previously reported the early onset of otitis media with effusion (OME) within the first few weeks of life in a remote Northern Australian community [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In the same community, we found acute otitis media (AOM) occurred frequently, was usually asymptomatic, and predicted subsequent perforation [6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Normal TM mobility was almost never seen in the first few years of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Whether the same pattern of disease exists in other remote Aboriginal communities in our region is not clear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>There have been at least 9 surveys of ear disease in children living in Northern and Central Australia [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The most comprehensive survey was conducted as part of the National Trachoma and Eye Health Program in the late 1970's [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This study found that around 30% of Aboriginal children 0–9 years in Central Australia and around 20% in the rest of the Northern Territory had severe otitis media (associated with a perforated tympanic membrane). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The investigators did not identify many children with OME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This may have been because their assessment did not include either tympanometry or pneumatic otoscopy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>There have not been any recent large-scale surveys using clear definitions and a standardised middle ear assessment in young Australian children living in remote Aboriginal communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>As clinicians in developed countries recognize that episodes of otitis media often do not require treatment, there is a need to identify the clinical features of otitis media associated with poor outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A better understanding of otitis media in populations with high rates of perforation of the TM is likely to be helpful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The primary aim of this study was to measure the prevalence of different types of otitis media in young Aboriginal children across a range of communities in Northern and Central Australia using a standardised assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Secondary aims included the provision of diagnostic and management training for health staff in the participating communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The survey was conducted prior to the introduction of the 7 valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine so the impact of this vaccine and other interventions could be assessed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The survey was conducted from May to November 2001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>While most of the survey took place over the Australian winter, daytime temperatures are warm to hot (around 20–30°C) in the central desert and northern tropical climates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We visited in 29 remote Aboriginal communities from four different regions: Darwin Rural (6), East Arnhem (7), Katherine District (5) and Central Australia (11 communities). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The Central Australian communities included 4 communities from the Nganampa health region which is located in South Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We approached community councils and clinics if we believed that: i) most clients were Aboriginal; ii) most children in the community used the clinic as their primary source of health care; iii) the infant immunisation program was operating effectively; and iv) medical records documenting all clinic presentations were maintained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We did not approach communities in the Barkly region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Each community received 1–2 scheduled visits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Visits were extended if a large proportion of families who were known to be in the community were not seen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Children were identified from the Northern Territory birth register, immunisation register, and clinic records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Children were eligible to participate in the study if they were: i) Aboriginal (self-identified); ii) aged between 6 and 30 months on the first day of the visit to their community; iii) resident in the community according to clinic staff (not including out-stations). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Non-Aboriginal children (&lt;5% of permanent residents) and children visiting the community were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>These remote Aboriginal communities are extremely disadvantaged by Australian standards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>English is generally spoken as a second language, housing is overcrowded, and employment and educational opportunities are limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Nearly all mothers breast feed their infants for &gt;12 months and many smoke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Very few communities are able to offer child care services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Most houses do not have indoor heating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Exposure to outdoor fires in the dry season is frequent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Children are generally part of large extended families and have many 'siblings'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Malnutrition, lower respiratory tract infections, diarrhea, and skin infections are common illnesses and the main causes of admission to hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Uptake of scheduled immunisations is very good. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Primary health care in all the participating communities follows the clinical practice guidelines of the Central Australian Rural Practitioners Association Standard Treatment Manual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>This recommends antibiotic treatment of all episodes of acute otitis media for 5 days with either amoxicillin 40–60 mg/kg/day or cotrimoxazole 2.4/12–4/20 mg/kg/day or procaine penicillin 40–60 mg/kg/day [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Episodes of severe otitis media were most often associated with infection with one or more types of Streptococcus pneumoniae or Haemophilus influenzae (and frequently both). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>At the time of this survey, infection with penicillin resistant pneumococci and treatment failure were common [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Clinical assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We conducted a parental questionnaire, review of clinic medical records, and a clinical assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The following information was recorded: date of birth, history of past ear infections, last audiological assessment, pneumococcal immunisation status, and any health problems at the time of examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Additional OM risk factor data were not collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All clinical assessments were made by ear health research officers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Assessments were made using a tympanometer (Grason Stadler GSI 38), a voroscope (WelchAllyn LumiView) with Siegel's speculum for pneumatic otoscopy, and a video-otoscope (WelchAllyn). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Ear canals were cleaned under direct vision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Data were collected using standardised forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Video-otoscope images were stored as ATI files using ATI TV Player Version 6.0 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All video-otoscope images and tympanograms were later reviewed by a second trained observer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Any disagreements in the assessments were resolved by discussion with the study paediatrician. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We categorised middle ear states as follows: (1) normal; (2) otitis media with effusion (OME); (3) acute otitis media without perforation (AOM/woP); (4) AOM with perforation (AOM/wip); (5) dry perforation; and (6) chronic suppurative otitis media (CSOM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We based our criteria for diagnosis on recommendations for clinical practice in this population:[12] (i) OME – intact and non-bulging TM and Type B tympanogram; (ii) AOM/woP – any bulging of the TM and Type B tympanogram; (iii) AOM/wiP – middle ear discharge observed and perforation present for less than six weeks or covering less than 2% of the pars tensa of the tympanic membrane; (iv) dry perforation – TM perforation without any discharge observed; (v) CSOM – middle ear discharge observed and perforation present for longer than six weeks and covering at least 2% of the pars tensa of the TM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The diagnostic criteria for AOM/woP are the most controversial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Our otoscopic criteria (middle ear effusion plus bulging of the TM) are consistent with national clinical practice guidelines [12] and previous studies in this population [4], a systematic review of international literature [13], and diagnostic studies using tympanocentesis [14-16] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The final middle ear diagnosis reflected the child's more severely affected ear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Perforation of the TM was present if the child had either AOM/wiP, dry perforation, or CSOM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We considered children with a perforation of the TM to have severe OM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We considered children with AOM/woP, AOM/wiP, or CSOM to have suppurative otitis media (presence of a pus producing infection). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Ethical considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Each community was visited by an Aboriginal Liaison Officer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Community involvement was confirmed following negotiation with the local Heath Clinic and Community Council. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committees of the Menzies School of Health Research and the Northern Territory Department of Health and Community Services, and the Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The study was also approved by the research advisory committees of the Tiwi Health Board, Katherine West Health Board, and the Nganampa Health Council. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Individual informed consent was obtained from each parent or guardian by a project officer or an Aboriginal Liaison Officer using oral, pictorial, and written explanations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We used Stata Version 8.0 to analyse all data [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The overall numbers and percentages of children with different types of otitis media were described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The 95% confidence intervals (95%CI) for these estimates were adjusted to allow for the clustering effect of living within the same community using robust standard errors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Comparisons of the prevalence of severe OM between different regions and communities were made using Fisher's exact test and Pearson's chi-squared test adjusted for the design effect of clustering by community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The cumulative probability of experiencing a perforation was estimated by using a Kaplan-Meier survival curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The first perforation was assumed to occur on the day it was documented in the medical records or on the day of the assessment if it had not been recorded before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A p value of &lt;0.05 was considered significant and all statistical tests were two-sided. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>We initially consulted with 38 communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>29 agreed to be in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Of the 9 communities who decided not to participate in the study, three did not regard ear disease in young children as a priority, five regarded ear disease as a priority and were interested in participating (but were unable to confirm approval prior to the proposed visit), and one regarded ear disease as a priority but had insufficient resources to support research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>We examined 709 of the 916 (78%) children who were eligible to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The proportion of eligible children seen in individual communities ranged from 42% to 100%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Of the 207 eligible children who were not seen, 145 were absent from the community at the time of the visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The other 62 children either could not be found in the community or were unable to attend the clinic as arranged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The children from the different health regions were similar in terms of age and gender (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Very few children were acutely unwell or febrile at the time of the examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four children (3%) were noted to have another health problem that required medical treatment (mainly skin infections). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Parents usually preferred to defer the examination of sick children until they were feeling better. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics of children seen by region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td/><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Darwin Rural </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>East Arnhem </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Katherine District </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Central Australia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>All Regions </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Total Children Listed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>347 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>330 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>144 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>229 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>1050 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Eligible Children </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>299 (100%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>310 (100%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>123 (100%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>184 (100%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>916 (100%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Eligible Children present during study visit </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>270 (90%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>253 (82%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>87 (71%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>161 (88%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>771 (84%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Eligible Children present during study visit and examination performed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>260 (87%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>230 (74%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>83 (67%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>136 (74%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>709 (77%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Mean Age (months) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>18.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>15.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>16.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>19.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>17.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>123 (48%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>126 (55%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>44 (52%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>67 (49%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>360 (51%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>History of AOM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>216 (83%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>157 (68%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>49 (59%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>106 (78%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>528 (76%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>History of perforation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>110 (42%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>86 (37%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>36 (43%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>70 (51%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>302 (44%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: No. = number; % = percent; AOM= acute otitis media. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of middle ear disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The ear examination was completed successfully in 698 children (98%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In 11 children, neither tympanic membrane (TM) could be seen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Nearly all children examined (91%, 95%CI 88, 94) had some form of otitis media (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Otitis media (all types) was as common in the children aged 6 to 18 months of age (352/378, 93%) as in the older children aged 18 to 30 months of age (304/331, 92%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Severe OM (TM perforation) was less common in younger children (22% versus 26%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Boys had a similar prevalence to girls for any OM (92% versus 93%) and slightly lower for severe OM (22% versus 25%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Children of parents who reported they did not have ear infection on the day of examination were much less likely to have severe OM (48/499, 10% versus 119/204, 58%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Similarly, children who did not have a previous perforation documented in their clinic notes were also much less likely to have severe OM (24/407, 6% versus 145/302, 48%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of any OM was similar for both groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of the different types of otitis media in Aboriginal children aged 6–30 months from remote communities in Northern and Central Australia (95% confidence intervals adjusted for the clustering effect of living in the same community). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Diagnosis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Children (N = 709) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Percentage (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Not determined </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>2% (0.4, 3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Normal </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>8% (5, 10) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Unilateral OME </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>10% (8, 12) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Bilateral OME </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>219 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>31% (27, 34) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>AOM/woP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>185 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>26% (23, 30) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>AOM/wiP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>7% (4, 9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Dry Perforation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>2% (1, 3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>CSOM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>107 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>15% (11, 19) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Any suppurative OM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>339 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>48% (44, 52) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Any Perforation (Severe OM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>169 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>24% (19, 29) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Any OM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>647 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>91% (88, 94) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: N = number; % = percent; CI = confidence interval; OME = otitis media with effusion; AOM/woP = acute otitis media without perforation; AOM/wiP = acute otitis media with perforation; CSOM = chronic suppurative otitis media; OM = otitis media. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Eight percent (95%CI 5, 10) of all children had 2 normal middle ears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>10% (95%CI 8, 12) had unilateral OME and 2% (95%CI 1, 3) had a dry perforation in their worst affected ear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The remaining 80% of children had either bilateral disease or a suppurative infection (AOM or CSOM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Those children with a suppurative infection were treated with antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Bilateral OME was the most common diagnosis and affected 31% (95%CI 27, 34) of children (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Another 26% (95%CI 23, 30) of children (generally well at the time of assessment) had a bulging TM and were classified as having AOM/woP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>7% (95%CI 4, 9) had recent middle ear discharge (AOM/wiP) and 15% (95%CI 11, 19) had chronic middle ear discharge (CSOM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Overall, 24% (95%CI 19, 29) of children had a perforation of the TM and 48% (95%CI 44, 52) of children had a suppurative ear infection (ie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>AOM/woP, AOM/wiP, or CSOM). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Community and regional variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In 27 of the 29 communities, at least one child examined had a perforation in one or both tympanic membranes (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The two communities where no child had a perforation were relatively small (community Q- 7 children examined and community ZA- 13 children examined). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>At the other end of the spectrum, in one community three of five of children (60%) had perforations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Since the number of children seen in individual communities was generally small, estimates of perforation prevalence at the community level lack precision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>However, the range in perforation rates was substantial (0–60%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Seven communities had a perforation prevalence &gt;35% and six communities had a perforation prevalence &lt;15% (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>These differences in perforation prevalence between communities were unlikely to have occurred by chance (Pearson's chi-squared test adjusted for design effect, p = 0.07). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Percentage of children examined with a perforation in each of the 29 communities at the time of examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>(Number at top of bar represents the total number of children examined). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2431-5-27-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Perforation of the TM affected 58/260 children (22%) in Darwin Rural, 43/230 (19%) in East Arnhem, 28/83 (34%) in Katherine, and 40/136 (29%) in Central Australia (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>These regional differences were only statistically significant when you assumed that children living within communities were independent (Fisher's exact test, p = 0.015; Pearson's chi-squared test adjusted for design effect, p = 0.12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The community prevalence of severe OM varied from 0–38% in Darwin Rural, 11–27% in East Arnhem, 0–44% in Katherine, and 6–60% in Central Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The risk of perforation for an individual child was associated with community of residence in the Darwin Rural and Katherine regions (Fisher's exact test, p = 0.022 and p = 0.028 respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Percentage of young children from remote communities in Northern and Central Australia with severe otitis media by health region (error bars represent 95% confidence intervals adjusted for the clustering effect of living in the same community). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2431-5-27-2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Onset of severe otitis media </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Perforation of the TM remains extremely common in this population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Perforations were documented in the medical records from 19 days of age (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Most perforations were first documented in children aged 3–18 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>By 6 months of age, 14% (95%CI 12, 17) of children had a documented perforation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>This increased to 31% (95%CI 27, 34) by 12 months and 40% (95%CI 36, 45) by 18 months of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Initial perforations were less commonly documented after 18 months of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>By 24 months of age, 45% (95%CI 41, 50) of children had a documented perforation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Overall, 43% of children aged 6–30 months in this study had a perforation documented and 24% had a perforation at the time of our assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Time in days to 1st perforation recorded in medical records in young Aboriginal children from 29 remote communities in Northern and Central Australia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2431-5-27-3"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This is the first study in over twenty years to document the middle ear state of young Aboriginal children from a range of remote communities in Northern and Central Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the rates of OM (all types), TM perforation, and suppurative OM (AOM/woP, AOM/wiP or CSOM) remain extremely high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The impact of severe otitis media on hearing is likely to be significant and may contribute to poor educational and employment outcomes [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>In this study, only 20% of children were likely to have normal hearing and did not require medical or audiological treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Importantly, there was considerable variation in the prevalence of perforation of the TM and suppurative OM between communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Relatively few community-based surveys anywhere in the world have described a prevalence of TM perforation higher than 5% [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Based on our results, it would appear that infections associated with middle ear effusion begin early in life and are persistent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Children who are well at routine assessment will often have a bulging TM consistent with AOM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Initial perforations occur early in life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>These perforations can heal but a substantial proportion progress to CSOM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Strength of evidence and applicability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This survey was conducted in communities across 4 geographically diverse regions (including the tropical north and central desert). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Examinations were standardised and performed by trained observers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We used clear, mutually exclusive definitions for each diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>While some children were absent from the community at the time of our visit, a more comprehensive survey would not have altered the conclusions of this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The rates of different types of OM are always dependent on the diagnostic criteria used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The diagnosis of OME generally requires either tympanometry or pneumatic otoscopy [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Tympanometry is likely to be a reliable and objective method of identifying middle ear effusion in this age group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The distinction between a bulging tympanic membrane and a neutral or retracted tympanic membrane in a young child is more difficult [13,21] The use of video-otoscopy and review of all images by a second trained observer improved the consistency of our assessments and allows for our findings to be easily verified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>We are therefore confident that bulging TMs are extremely common in this population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Other studies have shown that bulging TMs are excellent predictors of AOM in children (positive likelihood ratio 51, 95% CI 36, 73) [13,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>However, we accept that clinicians who define AOM/woP as a condition that requires the recent onset of symptoms would describe different rates of AOM/woP and OME [23,24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of severe OM (TM perforation) can be compared to the only other large scale survey of children in this age group [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Since the previous survey also found 20–30% of children in the same region had a perforated TM, it would appear that there have not been substantial improvements over the last 25 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>While other Indigenous populations (in New Zealand, USA and Canada) have reported reductions in rates of TM perforation, the reasons for this are not clear [25-27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>While we can be confident that the overall rates of TM perforation are extremely high in this population (95%CI 19 to 29%), it is more difficult to predict the perforation prevalence for other individual communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>We found substantial variation in rates of TM perforation between communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>There were no obvious reasons for this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The more disadvantaged desert communities did tend to have higher perforation rates but this was not always consistent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>In all regions, some communities that appeared to be similar had very different rates of TM perforation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>While severe otitis media in remote Aboriginal children is thought to be a disease of poverty, this can be difficult to establish empirically [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>In the analysis of the only national survey of middle ear disease in Aboriginal Australians, low socioeconomic status of community (odds ratio 3.3) and inequality within community (odds ratio 1.8) were both found to be important risk factors [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>For studies limited to remote Aboriginal communities in our region, the uniformly high levels of unemployment, the lack of educational opportunities, and childrearing within large extended families mean that an accurate assessment of the impact of poverty is difficult. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The variation in rates of TM perforation means a local survey using a standardised assessment (including tympanometry and trained observers) or the development of a perforation register would be needed to establish the extent of the problem in a community outside this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>We would strongly recommend focusing on children under 3 years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>This is the time when: i) infections are most likely to be acute and thus responsive to treatment; ii) the impact of hearing loss associated with severe ear disease is greatest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Other relevant information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The problem of severe OM affecting young Aboriginal children in rural and remote communities around Australia has been appreciated for some time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>In addition, suppurative otitis media is a good marker of increased risk for other suppurative respiratory infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Aboriginal children in this region are known to have extremely high rates of rhinosinusitis, bronchitis, pneumonia, and bronchiectasis [9,29-31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Interventions that are effective in preventing suppurative OM are likely to provide substantial benefits for respiratory health in general. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for research </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>A follow-up survey of children resident in the same communities after the introduction of the 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine is in progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In addition to studies evaluating immunisation, we also need investigations into the impact of i) changes in hygiene practices; and ii) changes in antibiotic prescribing and compliance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>These studies must focus on young children, especially those under 18 months of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Studies assessing the accuracy of diagnosis in remote communities, and the ability of prognostic tools to predict severe OM are also appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The relationship between a bulging TM and perforation needs to be described through longitudinal studies with frequent assessment in a high-risk population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Further surveys in this population should be linked to prioritisation of service delivery, improvements in the quality of health care, or well-designed intervention studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for practice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The primary health care priorities in remote communities should be to: i) support strategies that reduce the transmission of bacterial infections to infants and toddlers; ii) encourage timely immunisation; iii) advise on effective communication strategies for hearing impaired children; iv) provide frequent and accurate assessment of middle ear disease in the first 18 months of life; v) educate families about the appropriate management for different types of ear disease; and vi) help families give prolonged antibiotic treatment to their children with persistent suppurative otitis media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Evidence-based recommendations for clinical practice guidelines for otitis media in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Populations are now available [12] A training video and workbook have been developed to improve the quality of diagnostic assessment in remote communities[21] However, even with perfect primary health care, rates of severe OM may remain high unless we address the extreme poverty, the paucity of educational opportunities, and high unemployment in remote Aboriginal communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>This will require substantial investment into a range of services that include health, education, housing, transportation, and recreation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In this standardised assessment of middle ear state in 29 remote Aboriginal communities, 1 in every 2 children (aged between 6 and 30 months) had otoscopic signs consistent with suppurative ear disease and 1 in 4 children had a perforated tympanic membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Some of the children with intact tympanic membranes had experienced a perforation that healed before the survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>In this high-risk population, high rates of tympanic perforation were associated with high rates of bulging of the tympanic membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Wyeth Vaccines approved the protocol and funded the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The final decision about the content of the submitted paper was made by the authors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Wyeth Vaccines has also provided travel funding to the Ear Health and Education Unit to attend conferences on pneumococcal disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>All the authors contributed to the development of the study protocol and the writing of the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>PM and AL prepared the initial funding application, supervised the protocol development and data collection, completed the analysis, and wrote the first draft of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>PS wrote the first draft of the study protocol an assisted with the data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>GM managed the project, organized the field trips, and provided feedback of results to participating communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>GM, CW, EH collected the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>JB prepared the database and cleaned all the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Pre-publication history </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2431/5/27/prepub"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted by the Ear Health and Education Unit of the Menzies School of Health Research in collaboration with the Cooperative Research Centre of Aboriginal and Tropical Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>The study was supported by the Northern Territory Department of Health and Community Services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Funding was provided by Wyeth Vaccines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>We are extremely grateful to Ms Marie Munkara for coordinating and conducting the community consultation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The study would not have been possible without the support and assistance of the following communities and their health staff: Amata, Angurugu, Belyuen, Bickerton Island, Bulla, Ernabella, Fregon, Galiwin'ku, Milingimbi, Harts Range, Hermansburg, Indulkana, Kalkarinji, Lajamanu, Laramba, Maningrida, Milikapiti, Nguiu, Papunya, Pirlangimpi, Port Keats, Ramingining, Santa Teresa, Timber Creek, Titjikala, Umbakumba, Yarralin, Yirrkala, and Yuendemu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>We would also like to thank these communities for reviewing this document prior to publication and advising the appropriate presentation of individual community data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to the following individuals for their assistance with data collection and data management: Robyn Liddle, Sam Bullen, Chris Wigger, Edna Gadil, Brad Palmer, Heather Cook, Cyndi Cole, and Margie King; and advice on study design: Paul Torzillo, Christine Selvey, Kim Mulholland, Jonathan Carapetis, and Mathuram Santosham. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>CouzosSMetcalfSMurrayRSystematic review of existing evidence and primary care guidelines on the management of otitis media in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander populations2001Canberra: Office of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>CoatesHLMorrisPSLeachAJCouzosSOtitis media in Aboriginal children: tackling a major health problemMed J Aust200217717717812175319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>WatsonDSClapinMEar health of aboriginal primary school children in the Eastern Goldfields Region of Western AustraliaAust J Public Health19921626301627706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>MorrisPSA systematic review of clinical research addressing the prevalence, aetiology, diagnosis, prognosis and therapy of otitis media in Australian Aboriginal childrenJ Paediatr Child Health199834487497992863510.1046/j.1440-1754.1998.00299.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>LeachAJBoswellJBAscheVNienhuysTGMathewsJDBacterial colonization of the nasopharynx predicts very early onset and persistence of otitis media in Australian aboriginal infantsPediatr Infect Dis J1994139839897845752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>MorrisPSImproving the medical management of otitis media and other chronic bacterial respiratory diseases in rural and remote Aboriginal children: a systematic approach1998University of SydneyPhD </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="?"><plain>MorrisPSYonovitzALeachAJMathewsJDTos MAre respiratory mucosal diseases the same in developing countries? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Diagnosing acute otitis media in a high risk populationOtitis Media Today1999The Hague: Kugler Publications4753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>MoranDJWaterfordJEHollowsFJonesDLEar disease in rural AustraliaMed J Aust19792210212514144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The Royal Australian College of OpthalmologistsNational Trachoma and Eye Health Program1980NSW: Promail Printing Group </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Central Australian Rural Practioners Association (CARPA)CARPA Standard Treatment Manual19973Alice Springs: Central Australian Rural Practitioners Association </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>GibneyKBMorrisPSCarapetisJRSkullSASmith-VaughanHCStubbsEThe clinical course of acute otitis media in high-risk Australian Aboriginal children: a longitudinal studyBMC Pediatr20055161595525110.1186/1471-2431-5-16 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>MorrisPBallingerDLeachAKoopsHHayhurstBStubbsLRecommendations for Clinical Care Guidelines on the Management of Otitis Media in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Populations2001Canberra: Office of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>RothmanROwensTSimelDLDoes this child have acute otitis media?JAMA2003290163316401450612310.1001/jama.290.12.1633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>HalstedCLepowMLBalassanianNEmmerichJWolinskyEOtitis media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Clinical observations, microbiology, and evaluation of therapyAm J Dis Child19681155425514384577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>KarmaPHPenttilaMASipilaMMKatajaMJOtoscopic diagnosis of middle ear effusion in acute and non-acute otitis media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>The value of different otoscopic findingsInt J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol1989173749270797710.1016/0165-5876(89)90292-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>LeibovitzESatranRPiglanskyLRaizSPressJLeibermanACan acute otitis media caused by Haemophilus influenzae be distinguished from that caused by Streptococcus pneumoniae?Pediatr Infect Dis J2003225095151279950710.1097/00006454-200306000-00006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>StataCorpStata Statistical Software: Release 7.02001College Station, Texas: Stata Corporation </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>LeachAJOtitis media in Australian Aboriginal children: an overviewInt J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol199949S173S178S173-81057780010.1016/S0165-5876(99)00156-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>BluestoneCDEpidemiology and pathogenesis of chronic suppurative otitis media: implications for prevention and treatmentInt J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol199842207223946622410.1016/S0165-5876(97)00147-X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>RosenfeldRMBluestoneCDEvidence-Based Otitis Media1999Hamilton: B.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Decker Inc </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>McCallumGWilsonCThomsenPAngelesGLeachAMorrisPThe Ear Video Workbook- Trainer Version. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Improving the diagnosis and treatment of otitis media in young Aboriginal children2002Darwin, Australia: Cooperative Research Centre in Aboriginal and Tropical Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>ParadiseJLOn classifying otitis media as suppurative or nonsuppurative, with a suggested clinical schemaJ Pediatr19871119489513681566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>ChanLSTakataGSShekellePMortonSCMasonWMarcySMEvidence assessment of management of acute otitis media: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Research gaps and priorities for future researchPediatrics20011082482541148378410.1542/peds.108.2.248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>McCormickDPDefinition and diagnostic criteria for acute otitis mediaPediatrics20021097177181192772310.1542/peds.109.4.717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>GilesMAsherIPrevalence and natural history of otitis media with perforation in Maori school childrenJ Laryngol Otol19911052572602026935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Todd-NWJBowmanCAOtitis media at Canyon Day, Ariz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>A 16-year follow-up in Apache IndiansArch Otolaryngol19851116066084026678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>BaxterJDOtitis media in Inuit children in the Eastern Canadian Arctic – an overview – 1968 to dateInt J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol199949S165S168S165-81057779810.1016/S0165-5876(99)00154-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>HudsonHMRockettIRAn environmental and demographic analysis of otitis media in rural Australian aboriginesInt J Epidemiol19841373826698706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>MaxwellGMChronic chest disease in Australian aboriginal childrenArch Dis Child1972478979014647045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>TorzilloPJWaterfordJEHollowsFCJonesDLRespiratory disease amongst Aborigines in the PilbaraInt J Epidemiol1983121051066840950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>ChangABGrimwoodKMulhollandEKTorzilloPJBronchiectasis in indigenous children in remote Australian communitiesMed J Aust200217720020412175325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
