<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ppat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">1971115</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLPA-RA-0118R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plpa-03-09-02</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Immunology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Eukaryotes</subject><subject>In Vitro</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Hemoglobin Is a Co-Factor of Human Trypanosome Lytic Factor </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Trypanosome Lytic Factor</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Widener</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>Marianne Jensby</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiflett</surname><given-names>April</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moestrup</surname><given-names>Søren Kragh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hajduk</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label> Program in Pathobiology, Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island, United States of America
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label> Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, United States of America
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label> Department of Medical Biochemistry, University of Aarhus, Aarhus, Denmark
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Beverley</surname><given-names>Stephen M</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Washington University School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>shajduk@bmb.uga.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e129</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement> © 2007 Widener et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Trypanosome lytic factor (TLF) is a high-density lipoprotein (HDL) subclass providing innate protection to humans against infection by the protozoan parasite Trypanosoma brucei brucei. Two primate-specific plasma proteins, haptoglobin-related protein (Hpr) and apolipoprotein L-1 (ApoL-1), have been proposed to kill T. b. brucei both singularly or when co-assembled into the same HDL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>To better understand the mechanism of T. b. brucei killing by TLF, the protein composition of TLF was investigated using a gentle immunoaffinity purification technique that avoids the loss of weakly associated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>HDL particles recovered by immunoaffinity absorption, with either anti-Hpr or anti-ApoL-1, were identical in protein composition and specific activity for T. b. brucei killing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, we show that TLF-bound Hpr strongly binds Hb and that addition of Hb stimulates TLF killing of T. b. brucei by increasing the affinity of TLF for its receptor, and by inducing Fenton chemistry within the trypanosome lysosome. These findings suggest that TLF in uninfected humans may be inactive against T. b. brucei prior to initiation of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We propose that infection of humans by T. b. brucei causes hemolysis that triggers the activation of TLF by the formation of Hpr–Hb complexes, leading to enhanced binding, trypanolytic activity, and clearance of parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="st1"><title/><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomes are parasites that can infect a wide range of mammals, including domestic animals and humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Several hundred thousand humans are infected with African sleeping sickness, but this number would be much higher if not for a natural defense molecule found in human blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The trypanosome lytic factor (TLF) is a minor subclass of high-density lipoprotein that contains two proteins found only in primates, apolipoprotein L-1 and haptoglobin-related protein (Hpr). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In this paper, we show that Hpr contributes to TLF toxicity to trypanosomes because it binds hemoglobin (Hb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We found that when Hb is bound to TLF, it is rapidly taken up by the parasite and activated within the acidic environment of the parasite's digestive organelle, the lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Within the lysosome, Hb releases iron, inducing a chemical reaction that produces free radicals that damage membranes and contributes to trypanosome killing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Usually, free Hb is rapidly cleared from the circulation of mammals because of the organ damage free Hb can cause. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Trypanosome infection results in breakage of red blood cells and the release of large amounts of Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We postulate that trypanosome infection causes increased vascular levels of Hb, resulting in the formation of TLF–Hb complexes that may be important in “arming” the human innate immune system to clear the circulation of certain African trypanosomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Widener J, Nielsen MJ, Shiflett A, Moestrup SK, Hajduk S (2007) Hemoglobin is a co-factor of human trypanosome lytic factor. PLoS Pathog 3(9): e129. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.ppat.0030129">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030129</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomes are blood parasites of mammals in sub-Saharan Africa that cause chronic wasting diseases in both humans and domestic animals [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The three subspecies of Trypanosoma brucei are defined by their host range, geographical distribution, and course of disease [1–3]. Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense and Trypanosoma brucei gambiense infect humans and cause African sleeping sickness, while Trypanosoma brucei brucei infects non-primate mammals and causes nagana in cattle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>All African trypanosomes are able to evade the host adaptive immune system through a process called antigenic variation, which is a consequence of periodic changes in the variant surface glycoprotein that covers the entire parasite [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>T. b. brucei does not cause human disease because of its susceptibility to an innate immune activity in human serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This protection is conferred by trypanosome lytic factor (TLF), a minor subclass of human high-density lipoprotein (HDL) [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>TLF contains apolipoprotein A-I (ApoA-1), a protein found in all subclasses of HDL, and two proteins, haptoglobin-related protein (Hpr) and apolipoprotein L-1 (ApoL-1) that are unique to primates [8–19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Both Hpr and ApoL-1 have been reported to be toxic to T. b. brucei [8,14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The cellular pathway for TLF killing of T. b. brucei initiates with binding of TLF to high-affinity receptors located in the flagellar pocket of the parasite [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Bound TLF is endocytosed via coated vesicles and traffics to the parasite lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Within the acidified lysosome, TLF is activated and causes parasite lysis [22–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>ApoL-1 and Hpr have been proposed to have different mechanisms of toxicity and may act synergistically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>ApoL-1 is a colicin-like protein that kills trypanosomes through the formation of ion pores [10,25–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Hpr is a hemoglobin (Hb)-binding protein that has been proposed to induce an iron-dependent, Fenton-like reaction within the acidic lysosome of T. b. brucei that leads to the formation of free radicals and peroxidation of the lysosomal membranes [15,24,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>When ApoL-1 and Hpr are present in the same HDL particle, the specific activity for T. b. brucei killing is enhanced 800-fold [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Hpr is 91% identical to haptoglobin (Hp), an abundant (∼0.45–3 mg/ml in normal human serum) acute phase serum protein, possessing very high affinity for Hb [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Complexes of Hp and Hb that form when Hb is released from erythrocytes undergoing intravascular hemolysis are removed from the circulation by the CD163 scavenger receptor [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In contrast to Hp–Hb, the Hpr–Hb complex does not bind CD163 [31,33], and the Hpr serum concentration appears to be unaffected by hemolysis [32,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A role for Hb in trypanolysis has previously been speculated but this view was subsequently debated [12,15,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In light of this, the biological significance of the recently reported high-affinity binding of recombinant Hpr to Hb remains enigmatic. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In the present study we have re-investigated a potential function of Hb in relation to TLF and trypanolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Hb was absent from TLF purified from freshly collected human plasma using a gentle immunoabsorption protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, Hb bound to purified native Hpr, as well as TLF, with high-affinity and stimulated T. b. brucei killing in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The association of Hb with Hpr significantly increased TLF binding to T. b. brucei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, both an iron chelator and a free radical scavenger inhibited cell lysis, suggesting a direct role for Hb-derived iron in T. b. brucei killing by TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A combination of the ion pore–forming activity of ApoL-1 and free radical production of Hpr–Hb may account for the synergy observed in HDLs containing these proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Analysis of TLF Protein Components </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In order to define the protein composition of native TLF, freshly prepared human plasma was fractionated by “one-step” immunoaffinity chromatography with antibodies against Hpr or ApoL-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Unlike the “two-step” method that initially uses high-salt density ultracentrifugation followed by immunoaffinity chromatography to purify TLF, the one-step method eliminates the possible loss of apolipoproteins during the high-salt centrifugation step [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These methods allowed us to make two comparisons: First, a comparison of proteins purified by the one-step purification protocol with proteins purified by the two-step purification protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Second, it allowed us to compare the composition of TLF purified by the one-step purification method using antibodies to ApoL-1 or Hpr. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Previous analysis of the protein composition of TLF, purified by the two-step procedure, demonstrated the presence of ApoA-1, ApoL-1, Hpr dimer, and Hpr tetramer (Figure 1A) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Comparison of proteins purified by the two procedures by SDS-PAGE and western blot analysis showed that the protein compositions were similar in both cases (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>This shows that high-salt density ultracentrifugation used in the two-step protocol does not dramatically change the protein composition of the TLF particle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Two differences were noticed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>First, the ratio of Hpr dimer to tetramer was higher in samples purified using the single-step immunoabsorption method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Second, there was a reduction in sub-stoichiometric proteins in preparations of TLF purified by the two-step purification method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Specifically, a significant amount of Hp, albumin, and transferrin was detected by SDS-PAGE, western blotting, and liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry/mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) in the one-step purified material (Figure 1A–1C, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In addition to these serum proteins, other human serum proteins, including angiotensinogen and intellectin, were detected at low abundance by LC-MS/MS analysis (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Notably, no Hb was detected in any of the TLF preparations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Differentially Purified Human Serum HDLs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>(A) TLF analyzed by non-reducing 10% SDS-PAGE and Coomassie brilliant blue staining after purification by a two-step purification process that includes high-salt density centrifugation and antibody affinity chromatography with anti-Hpr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The presence of albumin (Alb) and immunoglobulin (Ig) are indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(B) HDL purified from serum using a single-step affinity purification method with antibodies to ApoL-1, Hpr, or ApoA-1 and analyzed by non-reducing 10% SDS-PAGE and stained with Coomassie brilliant blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Tf, transferrin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(C) The same gel as in (B) transferred to nitrocellulose and probed with antibodies to transferrin (Tf), Hpr, ApoL-1, and ApoA-1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-0030129-t001" content-type="1col" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Mass Spectroscopy Analysis of TLF </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.t001"/></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In order to determine whether the protein composition of HDLs containing Hpr or ApoL-1 differed significantly, samples were purified from human plasma by the one-step immunoaffinity method using antibodies to Hpr, ApoL-1, or ApoA-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All samples were analyzed by Coomassie staining, western blot, and LC-MS/MS (Figure 1; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The protein composition of samples purified by anti-Hpr or anti-ApoL-1 absorption was indistinguishable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The similar ratio of Hpr and ApoL-1, in the samples purified with anti-Hpr and anti-ApoL-1, indicates that most serum Hpr and ApoL-1 are assembled into the same HDL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The major proteins present in samples purified by anti-ApoA-1 immunoaffinity chromatography were ApoA-1, Hp, and transferrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Only trace amounts of ApoL-1 and Hpr were detected in these samples, consistent with TLF being a minor subclass of human HDL [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>These findings rule out the possibility that a significant amount of human plasma Hpr or ApoL-1 is free in the circulation and suggests a pathway for co-assembly of these two apolipoproteins into the same HDL particle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Differentially Purified TLF Lytic Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The specific activity of TLF purified by the one-step method using antibodies to either Hpr or ApoL-1 was similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In our standard lysis assay, 0.5 μg resulted in 40% lysis in 2 h at 37 °C (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Human plasma samples purified with anti-ApoA-1 were also trypanolytic, but the specific activity for killing was reduced over 10-fold (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The low specific activity of the ApoA-1-purified samples was due to the relatively low ratio of TLF to non-lytic HDL in this preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous estimates of TLF abundance, suggesting it represents less than 0.1% of total human serum HDL [6,14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Lysis and Morphology of T. b. brucei Killed with Purified HDL </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>(A) Human HDLs were purified by a single-step immunoaffinity method with either anti-Hpr, anti-ApoL-1, or anti-ApoA-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The specific activity for T. b. brucei killing was similar for TLF purified with the single-step protocol with either anti-Hpr (closed circles) or anti-ApoL-1 (open circles) (∼0.5 μg/ml killed 40% of the trypanosomes in our standard assay). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The specific activity of samples purified with single-step immunoabsorption with anti-ApoA-1 (closed squares) was over 10-fold reduced in specific activity for T. b. brucei killing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>(B) TLF purified by a two-step method using both high-salt density gradient ultracentrifugation and immunoaffinity absorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>TLF first subjected to high-salt gradient ultracentrifugation was 10-fold more toxic to T. b. brucei than TLF purified by the single-step immunoabsorption directly from serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Similar specific activities were obtained when the second immunoaffinity step was conducted with either anti-Hpr (closed circles) or anti-ApoL-1 (open circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The specific activity of HDLs purified with anti-ApoA-1 (closed squares) was over 100-fold lower. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>(C–F) Cell morphology of T. b. brucei treated with TLF purified by single-step immunoaffinity with anti-ApoL-1 or anti-Hpr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Following incubation at 37 °C for 2 h, cells were either smeared on microscope slides and methanol fixed (C and E) or directly viewed following imbedding in 1% agarose (D and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Incubation with TLF purified either by anti-Hpr (C and D) or anti-ApoL-1 (E and F) immunoabsorption showed similar morphologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Prior to lysis all cells progressed through a series of morphological changes that included transition to a kite-shaped form and continued swelling until lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The position of the kinetoplast (k) and nucleus (n) was determined by DAPI staining in the fixed preparations (C and E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The nucleus (n) was clearly visible in the unfixed cells (D and F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>doi:110.1371/journal.ppat.0030129.g002 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>When plasma samples were purified by the two-step protocol that included high-salt density ultracentrifugation followed by either anti-ApoL-1 or anti-Hpr immunoaffinity purification, the specific activity for trypanosome killing was approximately 10-fold higher than samples purified by the one-step methods (0.025 μg and 0.04 μg giving ∼50% lysis, respectively) (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The increased lytic activity of the samples purified by the two-step procedure may be due to the increased purity of these samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This is because gradient centrifugation employed in the two-step purification process reduces the amount of contaminating, high-abundance serum proteins, such as albumin and transferrin (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In addition, Hp, a potent inhibitor of TLF killing of T. b. brucei [9], is weakly associated with all human HDL and is effectively removed by high-salt density ultracentrifugation (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of Hp inhibition of human serum lysis of T. b. brucei is not known; based on results presented later, inhibition may be a direct consequence of Hp binding to free Hb in serum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Two different morphological phenotypes have been reported for human HDL killing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>One is defined by lysosomal membrane breakdown, cell swelling, and trypanosome death [13,24,30,35,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The other, recently reported by Pays and co-workers, involves extensive lysosome swelling, creating a large cytosolic vacuole that is proposed to exert enough pressure on the plasma membrane that the cell ruptures [8,10,25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples purified by either anti-Hpr or anti-ApoL-1 immunoaffinity produced identical morphological changes in T. b. brucei preceding lysis (Figure 2C–2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>After a lag phase of approximately 20 min, the overall morphology of the cells changed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Swelling was accompanied by an overall change in the shape of the cells, first resulting in a kite-like appearance followed by continued swelling and rounding of the cells until the cells ruptured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The formation of a large cytoplasmic vacuole was not observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In live cell imaging, the nucleus, nucleolus, flagella, and other organelles are visible (Figure 2D and 2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The morphology of T. b. brucei treated with intact human plasma produces the same morphological changes, leading to T. b. brucei lysis, like those seen with purified TLF (Figure 8C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The reason for the discrepancies between the morphological changes observed by the Pays lab and those observed by us and others following treatment with either purified TLF or intact human serum/plasma remains unresolved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>TLF Binding to Hb </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Previous studies suggested Hpr, despite being highly homologous to Hp, did not bind Hb [12,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>It is likely that Hpr–Hb complexes were not detected in these studies because of the presence of mild, non-ionic detergents in the immunoprecipitation assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>More recently, it has been shown that native and recombinant Hp and recombinant Hpr bind Hb with high affinity and that Hb-coupled Sepharose can precipitate Hpr-containing HDLs from plasma [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Although our analysis of TLF revealed the presence of Hpr, no Hb was detected in any of the purified HDL preparations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In order to determine whether native TLF and purified native Hpr could bind Hb, surface plasmon resonance (SPR) analysis was performed with purified preparations of native TLF, Hpr, and Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>TLF and Hpr both bound immobilized Hb with high affinity (the Kd for the Hpr–Hb interaction was 2–5 nM as estimated by SPR) (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The horizontal progress of the curves representing the dissociation phase (after arrows in Figure 3A) indicates an almost irreversible binding of Hpr as well as binding of TLF to Hb. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Binding of Purified Hpr and TLF to Hb </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>(A) SPR analysis of the binding of purified Hpr (left panel) and TLF purified by the two-step procedure (right panel) to immobilized Hb A0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The concentration of Hpr and TLF is shown to the right of the binding curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The BIAevaluation 4.1 software estimated a Kd of 2–5 nM for the Hpr–Hb complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate the beginning of the dissociation curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>(B) Silver-stained SDS-polyacrylamide (8%–16% gradient) gel of proteins eluted from Hb-coupled Sepharose (Hb), BSA-coupled Sepharose (BSA), or underivatized Sepharose (blank) after incubation with purified TLF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>doi:110.1371/journal.ppat.0030129.g003 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>To ensure that the SPR response observed upon incubation with TLF (Figure 3A, right panel) could not be attributed to binding between Hb and Hpr released from the TLF particle, binding of purified TLF to Hb was also studied in a pull-down assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As revealed in Figure 3B, Hb-coupled Sepharose beads specifically bound the entire TLF particle containing Hpr as well as ApoL-1 and ApoA-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the recent finding that recombinant Hpr in complex with Hb does not bind the human Hp–Hb receptor CD163, the complex between native Hpr and Hb did not bind to immobilized purified human CD163 in the SPR analysis (unpublished data) [31,33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Hb Involvement in TLF Killing of T. b. brucei </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The observation that Hb binds to purified Hpr and TLF led us to re-investigate the role of Hb in TLF-mediated killing of T. b. brucei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Since fetal bovine serum (FBS), a component of our standard trypanosome assay, typically contains small amounts of Hb released by hemolysis during serum preparation, we modified the standard trypanosome lysis assay to eliminate FBS (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The killing activity of TLF was drastically reduced when bovine serum albumin (BSA) was substituted for FBS in our in vitro lysis assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Addition of FBS restored maximal tyrypanosome killing activity in the assay (Figure 4B and 4C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Effect of FBS on TLF Killing of T.b. brucei </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(A) FBS (1 μl), BSA (1 μg), and Hb (1.0 μg) were fractionated on 15% SDS-PAGE gels and stained with Coomassie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The presence of Hb in FBS was verified by mass spectroscopy of the appropriate sized bands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Both Bos aurus alpha and gamma subunits of Hb were identified, and five of the gamma globin tryptic fragments are shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>(B) FBS is required for maximum in vitro lysis of T. b. brucei with highly purified TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>FBS was titrated into a 300-μl assay containing 1% BSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Addition of 5 μl FBS restored lytic levels to those seen in standard lysis assays [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(C) The effect of FBS addition is concentration dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To determine whether Hb was the co-factor supplied by the FBS in the in vitro lysis reactions, we titrated Hb into the modified serum-free assay (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Hb restores the killing activity of TLF, while the addition of Hb alone is non-toxic to T. b. brucei even at very high concentrations (Figure 5A; Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, if the Hb-binding protein, Hp, is added to the reactions, it inhibits lysis in a concentration-dependent fashion (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Together, these results indicate that Hb is a necessary co-factor for maximal TLF killing of T. b. brucei and that direct binding of Hb to Hpr may be required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Hb Is the Co-Factor in FBS Necessary for Maximal TLF Killing of T. b. brucei </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(A) Titration of Hb into in vitro lysis reactions containing highly purified TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Samples contained TLF (1.5 units) in 10% FBS (open circles); TLF (1.5 units) in 1% BSA and 1% glucose (closed circles); Hp in 1% BSA and 1% glucose without TLF (closed squares); and no TLF (Hb only) (open squares). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In the presence of TLF, Hb addition results in a concentration-dependent increase in T. b. brucei killing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>No increase is seen when Hb is added to FBS-containing reactions because FBS contains approximately 0.5 μg/μl of Hb. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(B) Addition of Hp inhibits Hb-dependent killing by TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Hp was titrated into reactions containing TLF (1.5 units), 1% BSA and 1% glucose, and 0.1 pmol of Hb (closed circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Addition of Hp and Hb (0.1 pmol) to T. b. brucei in the absence of TLF had no effect on cell viability (open circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>TLF–Hb Binding to Trypanosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Hb could stimulate trypanosome killing either a) by increasing the affinity of TLF for the trypanosome receptor, b) by playing a direct role in the lytic process, or c) by a combination of the above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>To test whether Hb was necessary for trypanosome binding, Alexa Fluor 488-labeled TLF was incubated with trypanosomes at 4 °C for 1 h, cells were washed, and then cell-associated fluorescence was measured by flow cytometery (Figure 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Addition of Hb increased binding of TLF to T. b. brucei. Maximum stimulation of binding was reached at a concentration of approximately 30 μg/ml, which represents a 1:10 molar ratio of TLF to Hb, assuming an average molecular mass of 500 kDa for TLF [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Addition of an equimolar concentration of Hp to Hb severely inhibited binding of TLF to cells, resulting in binding levels similar to the TLF binding observed in the absence of Hb, either by sequestering all available Hb or by competition for the trypanosome TLF–Hb receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These experiments suggest that Hb binding to TLF stimulates receptor-mediated binding to T. b. brucei, and that TLF–Hb binding to the receptor is specific and saturable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Hb Is Required for Binding and Uptake of TLF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>(A) Alexa Fluor 488–labeled TLF was incubated with trypanosomes and increasing amounts of Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Binding was measured by flow cytometry and the relative mean fluorescence intensity determined following binding for 1 h at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Hp, there is a dose-dependent increase of binding of Alexa Fluor 488–labeled TLF in the presence of Hb (closed circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Addition of Hp inhibited TLF–Hb binding to T. b. brucei (open circles). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(B) Uptake of TLF–Hb by T. b. brucei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes were pretreated with chloroquine for 30 min to block acidification of the lysosome and activation of TLF, followed by the addition of Alexa Fluor 594–labeled Hb and Alexa Fluor 488–labeled TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated for an additional hour at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The TLF–Hb complex was endocytosed and traffics to the lysosome (Figure S2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Killing of T. b. brucei by TLF requires trafficking of the toxin to the acidic trypanosome lysosome [22,24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>To determine whether both TLF and Hb co-localize to the lysosome, Alexa Fluor 488–conjugated TLF and Alexa Fluor 594–conjugated Hb were incubated with trypanosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>When TLF or Hb alone was incubated with cells, no intracellular fluorescence was observed (Figure S2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Co-incubation of TLF and Hb resulted in the rapid uptake and intracellular co-localization to the lysosome (Figures 6B and S2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>These results illustrate that TLF needs to be associated with Hb in order to be endocytosed by T.b. brucei, and that both TLF and Hb traffic to the lysosome of the cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>TLF–Hb Toxicity to Trypanosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Heme is toxic to trypanosomes presumably through production of free radicals that lead to lipid peroxidation of trypanosome membranes [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Previous studies suggested that the toxicity of TLF might involve lysosomal membrane peroxidation [15,24,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Since Hb traffics with TLF to the trypanosome lysosome, we asked whether Hb could initiate a Fenton-like reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Fenton chemistry requires ferrous iron, hydrogen peroxide, and low pH to produce hydroxyl radicals that peroxidate lipid and can lead to membrane degradation and cell death [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>All of these conditions are present if TLF transports Hb to the trypanosome lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>To test whether TLF–Hb induces a Fenton reaction, we performed lysis assays in the presence of the iron chelator deferiprone and in the presence of the free radical scavenger N,N′-diphenyl-1,4-Benzenediamine (DPPD) (Figure 7A and 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Both iron chelation and the scavenging of free radicals inhibited lysis by about 50%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-0030129-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>TLF–Hb Induces Iron-Dependent Lysosomal Membrane Breakdown </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(A) T. b. brucei was treated with increasing concentration of the iron chelator deferiprone in the presence (closed circles) and absence (open circles) of TLF–Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of trypanosome lysis by deferiprone is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We normalized the data to indicate that the addition of no deferiprone gave zero inhibition of TLF–Hb lysis after 2 h at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>(B) Trypanosomes were treated with increasing concentrations of the antioxidant DPPD in the presence (closed circles) or absence (open circles) of TLF–Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of trypanosome lysis by DPPD is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We normalized the data to indicate that the addition of no DPPD gave zero inhibition of TLF–Hb lysis after 2 h at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(C) Effect of human serum and TLF–Hb treatment on T. b. brucei lysosomal membrane structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In order to label the lysosome with a size-selective membrane-permeable marker, T. b. brucei was pre-incubated for 30 min at 37 °C with fluorescein-conjugated dextrans (500 kDa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Normal human serum (NHS) or purified TLF–Hb was then added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>After 30 or 120 min, cells were formaldehyde fixed and stained with anti-p67 to localize the lysosomal membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>After treatment with normal human serum or TLF–Hb for 30 min, dextrans are localized to a single cytoplasmic structure that stained with an antibody against the lysosomal marker p67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes treated for 120 min with either normal human serum or TLF–Hb continued to show p67 staining largely restricted to a single structure in the cell, but the 500-kDa dextrans are widely distributed in the cells, indicating a breakdown in lysosomal membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.0030129.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the mechanism of TLF killing, we returned to morphological analysis of TLF–Hb-treated trypanosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We have shown that TLF killing of T. b. brucei results in cell swelling, changes in overall cell morphology, and eventually lysis (Figure 2C–2F) [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Consistent with earlier electron microscopy of cells treated with gold-conjugated TLF [24,36], these results suggest that TLF–Hb causes the breakdown of lysosomal membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>To determine whether TLF–Hb caused extensive lysosomal membrane breakdown, T. b. brucei was incubated with fluorescein-labeled 500-kDa dextrans, which trafficked to the lysosome by bulk phase endocytosis (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>After the cells were pre-loaded with dextrans for 30 min, TLF–Hb or human plasma was added to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>After 30 min of exposure, the fluorescent dextrans were found predominately in a single vesicle co-localizing with the lysosomal membrane marker p67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>By 120 min post-treatment with either TLF–Hb or human serum, the dextrans were visible throughout the cell, while the p67 remained predominantly associated with the singular lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Since the fluorescently labeled dextrans escape the lysosome in the presence of TLF, the lysosomal membrane must be open to allow release of the large dextrans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The increased intensity of the fluorescein-labeled dextrans at 120 min post TLF treatment is likely due to their release into the neutral pH of the cytoplasm [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Incubation with normal human plasma also resulted in release of pre-loaded dextrans into the cytoplasm prior to trypanosome lysis (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>These results show that TLF–Hb causes lysosomal membrane breakdown prior to cell lysis, as does normal human serum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We have identified Hb as a critical co-factor in the killing of T. b. brucei by human TLF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Analysis of purified TLF indicates that TLF is a subclass of human HDL containing ApoA-1, and two primate-specific apolipoproteins, Hpr and ApoL-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Hpr binds human Hb with high affinity, and the formation of the TLF–Hb complex enhances binding to the trypanosome TLF receptor and triggers lysosome breakdown by an iron-dependent, free radical–mediated pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Despite the role of Hb in TLF binding and toxicity, no Hb is detected in TLF prepared from healthy human donors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>This indicates that activation of TLF occurs upon the release of free Hb in the circulation during intravascular hemolysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>TLF Contains Both Hpr and ApoL-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>A major question concerning the killing of T. b. brucei by human serum has centered around whether the toxin was Hpr, ApoL-1, or both of these proteins [10,14,25,40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In this paper, the protein composition of human TLF was determined by western blot and LC-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>While several studies have previously identified protein components of this subclass of trypanolytic human HDL, all have used samples that have been subjected to lengthy purification protocols involving high-salt density ultracentrifugation [6,34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>We were concerned that these procedures would dissociate proteins from TLF that might provide information on the native composition of this innate killing factor and on the mechanism of killing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>When TLF was isolated directly from freshly prepared human plasma by immunoaffinity chromatography with antibodies against either human ApoL-1 or Hpr, the major protein components were identical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The specific activity and morphology of T. b. brucei lysis was also identical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This analysis indicates that Hpr and ApoL-1 are assembled into the same HDL particle and that the amount of Hpr or ApoL-1 found free in the human circulatory system is extremely low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Thus, the native toxin in humans is not ApoL-1 or Hpr alone but is an HDL particle containing both of these apoliproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous studies showing that Hpr and ApoL-1 were present in the same HDL and both were required for maximal trypanosome killing [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In addition, recent analysis of the trypanolytic activity of human serum from individuals deficient in either ApoL-1 or Hpr suggests that both proteins play distinct and important roles to achieve maximal lytic activity [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The Role of Hb in T. b. brucei Killing by TLF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Several early studies reported that TLF did not bind Hb [12,30], but recently it was shown that recombinant Hpr bound Hb with high affinity [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Consistent with these results, we found that purified native TLF and purified native Hpr bound Hb with high affinity (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, MS analysis failed to detect Hb as a component of purified TLF, most likely because the low levels of Hb that are released into the plasma of individuals with normal erythrocyte turnover are instantly bound by Hp, which is present in large excess compared to Hpr (the concentration of Hp is roughly 10- to 100-fold higher than Hpr in normal human serum) [12,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The rapidly formed Hp–Hb complex is then removed by CD163. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Hence, despite its high affinity for Hb, Hpr may only compete well for free Hb under physiological conditions where Hp levels were low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>As we discuss below, infection by trypanosomes causes declines in Hp levels in animals [41–44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the role of Hb as a co-factor in TLF-mediated killing of T. b. brucei, we developed an in vitro lysis assay without FBS, a standard component of our in vitro trypanosome lysis assays, and a source of contaminating free Hb (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>We found that substitution of BSA for FBS in lysis assays dramatically reduced the activity of TLF, but that maximal activity could be restored by addition of human Hb to the assays (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Hb stimulation of T. b. brucei killing by TLF is due to both enhanced binding to the trypanosome cell surface receptor for TLF and direct cytotoxicity of lysosomally localized Hb (Figures 6 and S2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The basis for the enhanced trypanosome receptor recognition of the TLF–Hb complex is unknown, but the mammalian CD163 receptor shows a similar binding preference for the Hp–Hb complex [32,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Our studies show that not only is trypanosome binding of TLF stimulated by Hb association but that the trafficking of both TLF and Hb to the lysosome is enhanced (Figures 6 and S2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of TLF-induced cell lysis is controversial, but studies from our lab have shown that both freshly prepared normal human serum and TLF produce peroxidated lipids in T. b. brucei, suggesting a mechanism of killing [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Based on the findings reported here, we propose that Hb, bound to Hpr within the TLF particle, contributes directly to the established ApoL-1-mediated toxicity of TLF [8,10,28,29,40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Following binding and lysosomal localization, Hb may contribute iron that reacts with H2O2 in a Fenton-based reaction that leads to free radical formation and lysosomal membrane breakdown (Figure 7) [9,15,24,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, earlier studies using an in vitro TLF assay containing 0.2% BSA, and no Hb, did not kill T. b. brucei by a Fenton-based mechanism ([46]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The morphological analysis of T. b. brucei treated with TLF–Hb showed cells swelling into a kite-shape prior to the bursting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>We were able to directly test the permeability of the lysosomal membrane following TLF–Hb treatment by pre-loading cells with defined size (500 kDa) fluorescein-conjugated dextrans then adding TLF–Hb (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Prior to lysis, dextrans were seen throughout the cytoplasm indicating that TLF–Hb caused the lysosomal membrane to breakdown, releasing the large fluorescein-conjugated dextrans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Based on the pharmacological inhibition of TLF–Hb killing by deferiprone and DPPD, we postulate that membrane lipid peroxidation plays a major role in lysosomal membrane breakdown followed by cell lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>This does not argue against a role of ApoL-1 in TLF killing of T. b. brucei [8,10,19,25–28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Recombinant and native ApoL-1 are toxic to T. b. brucei and the evidence that it creates ion pores in trypanosome membranes is convincing [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Activation of the Innate TLF Response by Hb </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="?"><plain>Does Hb stimulation of TLF binding and killing of T. b. brucei occur in humans, and is this important in protection against these parasites? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In vitro studies reported here leave little doubt that Hb association with Hpr enhances TLF binding to and killing of T. b. brucei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>However, when TLF is isolated from normal human donors, Hb is absent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This apparent paradox can be explained when one carefully considers the early physiological events associated with trypanosome infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>During infection of animals by African trypanosomes, there is substantial hemolysis, and in some cases, the hematocrit can drop by as much as 50% [42–44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The exact cause of hemolysis is not known, but blood cell production increases during infection, so the decrease in hematocrit is not due to decreased erythrocyte production but rather to hemolysis [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Hemolysis results in the release of large quantities of Hb, most of which will be bound and removed by circulating Hp [42,48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>During a trypanosome-induced acute phase response in calves, levels of Hp are reduced to undetectable levels 8 d post-infection, presumably due to removal of Hp from the circulation after Hp–Hb complexes have formed [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In mice, Hp levels initially increase after trypanosome infection, and then decline [48,49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the studies in animals, human trypanosome infections also result in substantial hemolysis and release of free Hb [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>While Hp initially binds all free Hb, the clearance of the Hp–Hb complex would result in a significant drop in Hp levels to the point where Hpr would become a major Hb-binding protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Thus, as Hp levels decrease and TLF–Hb levels increase, there may be a substantial stimulation of TLF activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>A second factor may influence the formation of TLF–Hb complexes in the circulation of humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have reported the incidence of both genetic and phenotypic ahaptoglobinemia in African populations, perhaps due to reduced severity of malaria infection in Hp-negative individuals [51–53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In some regions where malarial infections are prevalent, the frequency of ahaptoglobinemic individuals can be as high as 48% [51,54,55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>In these individuals, Hpr-associated TLF could be the primary Hb-binding protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We have previously postulated that ApoL-1 and Hpr act synergistically in T. b. brucei killing [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>We now propose an avenue by which TLF activity is increased when Hpr and ApoL-1 are present in the same HDL particle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>First, Hb binding to TLF stimulates endocytosis of TLF–Hb by increased receptor affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Second, TLF–Hb provides iron that initiates Fenton chemistry, leading to lysosomal membrane breakdown while ApoL-1 forms pores in membranes, disrupting the ability of the cell to regulate osmosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The results presented here support the hypothesis that formation of the Hpr–Hb complex within the TLF particle plays a role in human serum killing of T. b. brucei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Hb seems to induce increased binding of TLF to the parasite and contributes directly to toxicity in the lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>This suggests that parasite-induced hemolysis stimulates innate immunity against the parasite in humans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Human serum preparation and immunoaffinity chromatography. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Blood was collected from healthy human volunteers and was maintained on ice or at 4 °C throughout the fractionation procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Plasma was separated from blood cells by centrifugation at 3,500 rpm in a SLA-3000 rotor (Sorvall, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thermo.com/">http://www.thermo.com/</ext-link>) for 10 min at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The plasma supernate was removed and re-centrifuged in an SS-34 rotor (Sorvall) at 9,500 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C to remove any residual blood cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Plasma was kept on ice for no more than 3 h prior to antibody affinity chromatography. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Monoclonal antibodies were raised against TLF particles, and the specificity of the antibodies for Hpr and ApoL-1 has been previously described [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The monoclonal antibodies were purified from mouse ascites by Protein G affinity chromatography according to the manufacturer's recommendations (Pierce Biotechnology, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.piercenet.com/">http://www.piercenet.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Affinity-purified polyclonal antibodies against human ApoA-1 were purchased from Rockland Immunochemicals (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rockland-inc.com/">http://www.rockland-inc.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The three antibodies (200 μg) were coupled to Affigel 15 (50 μl) (Bio-Rad, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio-rad.com/">http://www.bio-rad.com/</ext-link>) according to the manufacturer's recommendations and 100 μl of the AffiGel slurry (corresponding to approximately 200 μg of antibody) was transferred to 1.5-ml microfuge tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Human plasma (1 ml) was added to each antibody containing tube and incubated for 30 min at 4 °C on a rotating platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>AffiGel/antibody resin was recovered by centrifugation for 90 s at 1,000g at 4 °C and the immuno-depleted plasma discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Additional 1-ml samples of plasma were added to each sample and immuno-depletion steps were repeated until 5 ml of plasma had been treated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The AffiGel/antibody resin was then washed seven times with 1 ml of PBSE (137 mM NaCl, 2.7 mM KCl, 10 mM Na2HPO4, 10 mM KH2PO4, 3 mM EDTA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Following the washes, the AffiGel/antibody resin was treated with 200 μl of 100mM glycine (pH 2.0) for 5 min at 4 °C to elute bound human plasma proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The eluate was dialyzed against PBSE at 4 °C prior to analysis for protein composition and trypanolytic activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis of TLF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Following elution from anti-ApoL-1, anti-Hpr, and anti-ApoA-1 AffiGel resin, samples were precipitated with 100% ice-cold acetone and proteins were separated on a 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gel under non-denaturing conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Gels were either Coomassie stained or western blotted onto nitrocellulose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>For western blot analysis, membranes were blocked with 5% milk in TTBS (20mM Tris, 500mM NaCl, 0.05% Tween-20) and were probed with antibodies diluted with 5% milk in TTBS: Hpr (1:10,000), ApoL-1 (1:10,000), ApoA-1 (1:5000), Hb (1:2000), and transferrin-Hrp (1:2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>After incubation with secondary antibodies (goat anti-rabbit and goat anti-mouse at 1:10,000 in all cases except transferrin), (Pierce Biotechnology) proteins were detected following reaction with ECL Plus (GE Healthcare, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gelifesciences.com/">http://www.gelifesciences.com/</ext-link>) and were visualized by autoradiography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Protein concentrations were determined by Bradford assay (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>LC-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>For mass spectroscopy analysis, protein bands were excised from Coomassie-stained gels, trypsin digested, and fractionated by reverse phase chromatography (C-18 PepMap100, 75 um ID × 15 mm, 3-um particle size, LC Packings/Dionex, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dionex.com/">http://www.dionex.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The column eluate was introduced onto a QSTAR XL mass spectrometer (Applied Biosystems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbiosystems.com/">http://www.appliedbiosystems.com/</ext-link>, and MDS Sciex, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mdssciex.com/">http://www.mdssciex.com/</ext-link>) by electrospray ionization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Ions were selected and fragmented using a standard information dependent acquisition method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>An ion had to be assigned a charge in the +2 to +4 range to be considered a candidate for fragmentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Identification of proteins was performed using ProID software (Applied Biosystems) and experimental spectra were matched against in silica trypsinizations of the NCBI non-redundant database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>T. b. brucei cultivation and lysis assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Bloodstream T. b. brucei (Lister strain 427, MiTat 1.2) were cultured in HMI-9 media supplemented with 10% FBS (heat inactivated, 58 °C for 30 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Trypanolytic activity of fractionated HDLs was determined by in vitro microscopic assays as previously described [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>All samples were dialyzed exhaustively against PBSE, at 4 °C, prior to incubation with the parasites (1 × 107 cells per 300-μl assay) for 2 h at 37 °C in HMI-9 media containing 10% FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>To determine whether FBS contributed to TLF-mediated killing of T. b. brucei some lysis assays contained 1% BSA and 1% glucose without intact FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Hb A0 and Hp 1–1 were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>In this paper and in previous papers, we define a lytic unit of activity as the amount of material necessary to lyse 50% of the parasites, in a 300-μl assay containing 1 × 107 cells after incubation for 2 h at 37 °C [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The iron chelator 1,2-dimethyl-3-hydroxypyrid-4-one (deferriprone) was used in the chelation inhibition studies and DPPD was the antioxidant used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Cell imaging. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Lysis of live parasites was visualized by the addition of TLF to T. b. brucei imbedded in 1% low melting point agarose (Sigma) made with PBSE containing 1% glucose following 2 h of incubation at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Samples were prepared for microscopy by the addition of 10 μl of low melting point agarose to 10 μls of T. b. brucei at a final concentration of 1 × 107/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Both the agarose and trypanosome samples were maintained at 37 °C, gently mixed, and transferred to a microscope slide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>To further reduce the motility of trypanosomes, the slide was chilled at 4 °C for 10 min and then imaged using a motorized Zeiss Axioplan2 and an MRm camera interfaced with the Axiovisions 4.4 software (Zeiss, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zeiss.com/">http://www.zeiss.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Methanol-fixed samples were also visualized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Cells incubated with TLF samples as above were washed with PBSE containing 10% FBS, then resuspended and smeared on a microscope slide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Slides were rapidly air dried, and cells were fixed for 5 min in methanol (−20°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Following methanol fixation, slides were air dried and mounted with 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) containing antifade reagent ProlongGold (Invitrogen, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.invitrogen.com/">http://www.invitrogen.com/</ext-link>) and imaged as above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Lysosomal morphology studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes were resuspended at a concentration of 1 × 107/ml in F12-FBS and were incubated with 300 μg/ml 500-kDa fluorescein-labeled dextrans (Invitrogen) for 30 min at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Cells were then washed three times with 1X PBSE and were incubated at 3 × 106/ml in F12-FBS with either 2 units of normal human serum (1.7% total human serum) or 2 units of purified TLF (0.017% TLF), and cells were examined after 30 min or 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Aliquots were treated with 0.001% formaldehyde on ice for 5 min, rinsed with PBS, and resuspended in PBS-10% FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Cells were then smeared onto a slide and air dried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>For co-localization with anti-p67, cells were rehydrated in PBS-10% FBS and incubated in 1:1000 anti-p67 (a gift of Jay Bangs, University of Wisconsin, Madison,Wisconsin, United States) for 1 h at room temperature, followed by staining with a goat anti-mouse secondary antibody labeled with Alexa Fluor 594 (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Slides were rinsed in PBS containing 1% glucose, air dried, and viewed using a motorized Zeiss Axioplan2 and an MRm camera interfaced with the Axiovisions 4.4 software (Zeiss). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Hb binding. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>SPR analysis was conducted essentially as described in [31] except that native TLF and Hpr were used in the binding assays instead of recombinant Hpr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Hpr and TLF were purified from fresh human plasma using the two-step purification method [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>In the case of Hpr purification, human HDLs were solubilized using 10mM CHAPS and purified using an anti-Hpr column as described [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The Kd for the Hpr–Hb interaction was estimated by the BIAevaluation 4.1 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biacore.com/lifesciences/index.html">http://www.biacore.com/lifesciences/index.html</ext-link>) using a Langmuir 1:1 binding model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>For precipitation experiments, purified TLF was incubated with Hb-coupled Sepharose, BSA-coupled Sepharose, or underivatized Sepharose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>After extensive washing in a solution containing 2 mM CaCl2, 1 mM MgCl2, 10 mM Hepes, and 140 mM NaCl (pH 7.8), bound proteins were eluted in SDS-containing sample buffer and visualized by SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>TLF binding and localization. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Binding studies of TLF to trypanosomes was conducted with Alexa Fluor 488 (Invitrogen) labeled TLF, and Hb and Hp noted above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes were incubated with labeled TLF, unlabeled Hb, and Hp at 4 °C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>The cells were then washed three times at 1,400g for 7 min at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The cells were resuspended in 2% formaldehyde at 4 °C until measured by flow cytometry using the CyAn ADP (Dako, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dako.com/">http://www.dako.com/</ext-link>) and analyzed using FlowJo software (TreeStar, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.treestar.com/">http://www.treestar.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Immunofluoresence microscopy was employed to localize TLF and Hb in the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Alexa Fluor 488 (Invitrogen)–labeled TLF and Alexa Fluor 594 (Invitrogen)–labeled Hb were incubated with trypanosomes pre-incubated with 50 μM chloroquine for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>TLF and Hb were added at the concentrations noted in Figure 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>LysoTracker Red DND99 (Invitrogen) was used to identify the lysosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>These studies were done on a Zeiss Axioplan and the images analyzed using IPLab Spectrum version 3.9.4r2 from Scanalytics–BD Biosciences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scanalytics.com/">http://www.scanalytics.com/</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat-0030129-sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Hb Is Necessary for Maximal TLF Killing of T. b. brucei </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Trypanosome killing by TLF in the presence (open circles) and absence (closed circles) of Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Hb alone is not toxic to T. b. brucei at the concentrations tested (open squares). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>(25 KB PPT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.0030129.sg001.ppt"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat-0030129-sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Neither Hb nor TLF Alone Are Efficiently Taken Up by T. b. brucei </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>(A) Alexa Fluor 594–labeled Hb or Alexa Fluor 488–labeled TLF was incubated with T. b. brucei for 1 h at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>No uptake of was seen at either 488 nm or 594 nm excitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>(B) When cells were co-incubated with TLF and Hb, both TLF and Hb can be seen in the trypanosome lysosome by co-localization with LysoTracker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>TLF used in these studies was purified by the two-step procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>(283 KB PPT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.0030129.sg002.ppt"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>We thank Christian Jacobsen and Anne Marie Bundsgaard for assistance with the SPR analysis and the Center for Tropical and Emerging Global Diseases Flow Cytometry Facility at the University of Georgia for assistance with binding experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>We also thank Sara Faulkner, Natalie Stevens, and other members of the Hajduk laboratory for helpful discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn id="ack1" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Author contributions. JW, MJN, AS, SKM, and SH conceived and designed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>JW, MJN, and AS performed the experiments and analyzed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>JW and MJN contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>JW, AS, SKM, and SH wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn id="ack2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Funding. MJN is supported by a grant from the Danish Medical Research Council, and work in the laboratory of SLH on TLF is supported by the Ellison Medical Foundation and the National Institutes of Health (AI39033). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><fn id="ack3" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Competing interests. The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ApoA-1</term><def><p>apolipoprotein A-I</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ApoL-1</term><def><p>apolipoprotein L-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BSA</term><def><p>bovine serum albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DPPD</term><def><p>N,N′-diphenyl-1,4-Benzenediamine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBS</term><def><p>fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Hb</term><def><p>hemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDL</term><def><p>high-density lipoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Hp</term><def><p>haptoglobin, Hpr, haptoglobin-related protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC-MS/MS</term><def><p>liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry/mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPR</term><def><p>surface plasmon resonance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TLF</term><def><p>trypanosome lytic factor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat-0030129-b001"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain> HoareCA 1972 The Trypanosomes of mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>A zoological monograph Oxford Blackwell Scientific Publications  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b002"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain> GibsonW 2002 Will the real Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense please step forward? Trends Parasitol 18 486 490 12473364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b003"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain> GibsonWC 1986 Will the real Trypanosoma b. gambiense please stand up Parasitol Today 2 255 257 15462856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b004"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain> PaysEVanhammeLPerez-MorgaD 2004 Antigenic variation in Trypanosoma brucei: Facts, challenges and mysteries Curr Opin Microbiol 7 369 374 15288623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b005"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain> HajdukSLHagerKEskoJD 1992 High-density lipoprotein-mediated lysis of trypanosomes Parasitol Today 8 95 98 15463583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b006"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain> HajdukSLMooreDRVasudevacharyaJSiqueiraHTorriAF 1989 Lysis of Trypanosoma brucei by a toxic subspecies of human high density lipoprotein J Biol Chem 264 5210 5217 2494183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b007"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain> RifkinMR 1978 Identification of the trypanocidal factor in normal human serum: High density lipoprotein Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 75 3450 3454 210461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b008"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain> VanhammeLPaturiaux-HanocqFPoelvoordePNolanDPLinsL 2003 Apolipoprotein L-I is the trypanosome lytic factor of human serum Nature 422 83 87 12621437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b009"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain> SmithABHajdukSL 1995 Identification of haptoglobin as a natural inhibitor of trypanocidal activity in human serum Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 92 10262 10266 7479764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b010"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain> Perez-MorgaDVanhollebekeBPaturiaux-HanocqFNolanDPLinsL 2005 Apolipoprotein L-I promotes trypanosome lysis by forming pores in lysosomal membranes Science 309 469 472 16020735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b011"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain> HawkingFRamsdenDBWhytockS 1973 The trypanocidal action of human serum and of baboon plasma Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 67 501 516 4206525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b012"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain> MuranjanMNussenzweigVTomlinsonS 1998 Characterization of the human serum trypanosome toxin, haptoglobin-related protein J Biol Chem 273 3884 3887 9461571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b013"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain> RaperJPortelaMPLugliEFrevertUTomlinsonS 2001 Trypanosome lytic factors: Novel mediators of human innate immunity Curr Opin Microbiol 4 402 408 11495802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b014"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain> ShiflettAMBishopJRPahwaAHajdukSL 2005 Human high density lipoproteins are platforms for the assembly of multi-component innate immune complexes J Biol Chem 280 32578 32585 16046400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b015"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain> SmithABEskoJDHajdukSL 1995 Killing of trypanosomes by the human haptoglobin-related protein Science 268 284 286 7716520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b016"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain> TomlinsonSJansenAMKoudinovAGhisoJAChoi-MiuraNH 1995 High-density-lipoprotein-independent killing of Trypanosoma brucei by human serum Mol Biochem Parasitol 70 131 138 7637693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b017"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain> TomlinsonSMuranjanMNussenzweigVRaperJ 1997 Haptoglobin-related protein and apolipoprotein AI are components of the two trypanolytic factors in human serum Mol Biochem Parasitol 86 117 120 9178275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b018"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain> LugliEBPouliotMPortela MdelPLoomisMRRaperJ 2004 Characterization of primate trypanosome lytic factors Mol Biochem Parasitol 138 9 20 15500911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b019"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain> PoelvoordePVanhammeLVan Den AbbeeleJSwitzerWMPaysE 2004 Distribution of apolipoprotein L-I and trypanosome lytic activity among primate sera Mol Biochem Parasitol 134 155 157 14747153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b020"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain> DrainJBishopJRHajdukSL 2001 Haptoglobin-related protein mediates trypanosome lytic factor binding to trypanosomes J Biol Chem 276 30254 30260 11352898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b021"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain> GreenHPDel Pilar Molina PortelaMSt JeanENLugliEBRaperJ 2003 Evidence for a Trypanosoma brucei lipoprotein scavenger receptor J Biol Chem 278 422 427 12401813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b022"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain> LorenzPBarthPERudinWBetschartB 1994 Importance of acidic intracellular compartments in the lysis of Trypanosoma brucei brucei by normal human serum Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 88 487 488 7570851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b023"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain> ShimamuraMHagerKMHajdukSL 2001 The lysosomal targeting and intracellular metabolism of trypanosome lytic factor by Trypanosoma brucei brucei  Mol Biochem Parasitol 115 227 237 11420109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b024"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain> HagerKMPierceMAMooreDRTytlerEMEskoJD 1994 Endocytosis of a cytotoxic human high density lipoprotein results in disruption of acidic intracellular vesicles and subsequent killing of African trypanosomes J Cell Biol 126 155 167 8027174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b025"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain> PaysEVanhollebekeBVanhammeLPaturiaux-HanocqFNolanDP 2006 The trypanolytic factor of human serum Nat Rev Microbiol 4 477 486 16710327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b026"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain> VanhammeLPaysE 2004 The trypanosome lytic factor of human serum and the molecular basis of sleeping sickness Int J Parasitol 34 887 898 15217727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b027"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain> VanhollebekeBPaysE 2006 The function of apolipoproteins L Cell Mol Life Sci 63 1937 1944 16847577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b028"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain> VanhollebekeBTrucPPoelvoordePPaysAJoshiPP 2006 Human Trypanosoma evansi infection linked to a lack of apolipoprotein L-I N Engl J Med 355 2752 2756 17192540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b029"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain> Molina-Portela MdelPLugliEBRecio-PintoERaperJ 2005 Trypanosome lytic factor, a subclass of high-density lipoprotein, forms cation-selective pores in membranes Mol Biochem Parasitol 144 218 226 16202458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b030"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain> BishopJRShimamuraMHajdukSL 2001 Insight into the mechanism of trypanosome lytic factor-1 killing of Trypanosoma brucei brucei  Mol Biochem Parasitol 118 33 40 11704271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b031"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain> NielsenMJPetersenSVJacobsenCOxvigCReesD 2006 Haptoglobin-related protein is a high-affinity hemoglobin-binding plasma protein Blood 108 2846 2849 16778136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b032"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain> KristiansenMGraversenJHJacobsenCSonneOHoffmanHJ 2001 Identification of the haemoglobin scavenger receptor Nature 409 198 201 11196644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b033"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain> NielsenMJPetersenSVJacobsenCThirupSEnghildJJ 2007 A unique loop extension in the serine protease domain of haptoglobin is essential for CD163 recognition of the haptoglobin-hemoglobin complex J Biol Chem 282 1072 1079 17102136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b034"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain> McVicarJPKunitakeSTHamiltonRLKaneJP 1984 Characteristics of human lipoproteins isolated by selected-affinity immunosorption of apolipoprotein A-I Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 81 1356 1360 6424116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b035"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain> ShiflettAMFaulknerSDCotlinLFWidenerJStephensN 2007 African trypanosomes: Intracellular trafficking of host defense molecules J Eukaryot Microbiol 54 18 21 17300512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b036"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain> RifkinMR 1984  Trypanosoma brucei: Biochemical and morphological studies of cytotoxicity caused by normal human serum Exp Parasitol 58 81 93 6745390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b037"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain> MeshnickSRChangKPCeramiA 1977 Heme lysis of the bloodstream forms of Trypanosoma brucei  Biochem Pharmacol 26 1923 1928 911346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b038"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain> SadrzadehSMGrafEPanterSSHallawayPEEatonJW 1984 Hemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>A biologic fenton reagent J Biol Chem 259 14354 14356 6094553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b039"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain> OhkumaSPooleB 1978 Fluorescence probe measurement of the intralysosomal pH in living cells and the perturbation of pH by various agents Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 75 3327 3331 28524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b040"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain> VanhollebekeBNielsenMJWatanabeYTrucPVanhammeL 2007 Distinct roles of haptoglobin-related protein and apolipoprotein L-I in trypanolysis by human serum Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 4118 4123 17360487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b041"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain> EckersallPDRodgersJMurrayMKennedyPG 1999 Haptoglobin, the acute phase response and natural human immunity to trypanosomes Parasitol Today 15 251 252 10366834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b042"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain> EsievoKASarorDIAdegokeOO 1984 Depleted serum haptoglobin in acute bovine trypanosomiasis Vet Parasitol 15 181 185 6541835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b043"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain> GodfreyDGLeachTMRobertsCJKillick-KendrickR 1968 Plasma protein and haemoglobin levels in Zebu cattle infected with trypanosomiasis in the field Bull Epizoot Dis Afr 16 205 212 5750917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b044"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain> GoossensBOsaerSKoraSNdaoM 1998 Haematological changes and antibody response in trypanotolerant sheep and goats following experimental Trypanosoma congolense infection Vet Parasitol 79 283 297 9831952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b045"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain> GutteridgeJM 1986 Iron promoters of the Fenton reaction and lipid peroxidation can be released from haemoglobin by peroxides FEBS Lett 201 291 295 2423372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b046"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain> Molina PortelaMPRaperJTomlinsonS 2000 An investigation into the mechanism of trypanosome lysis by human serum factors Mol Biochem Parasitol 110 273 282 11071282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b047"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain> OjokLKaeufer-WeissIWeissE 2001 Bone marrow response to acute and chronic Trypanosoma congolense infection in multimammate rats (Mastomys coucha) J Comp Pathol 124 149 158 11222012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b048"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain> Ndung'uJMEckersallPDJenningsFW 1991 Elevation of the concentration of acute phase proteins in dogs infected with Trypanosoma brucei  Acta Trop 49 77 86 1680282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b049"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain> NgureRMEckersallPDJenningsFWBurkeJMStearMJ 1997 Major acute phase response of haptoglobin and serum amyloid-P following experimental infection of mice with Trypanosoma brucei brucei  Parasitology Int 46 247 254  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b050"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain> ChisiJEMisiriHZverevYNkhomaASternbergJM 2004 Anaemia in human African trypanosomiasis caused by Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense  East Afr Med J 81 505 508 15715127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b051"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain> FowkesFJImrieHMigot-NabiasFMichonPJusticeA 2006 Association of haptoglobin levels with age, parasite density, and haptoglobin genotype in a malaria-endemic area of Gabon Am J Trop Med Hyg 74 26 30 16407342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b052"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain> TeyeKQuayeIKKodaYSoejimaMPangH 2004 A novel I247T missense mutation in the haptoglobin 2 beta-chain decreases the expression of the protein and is associated with ahaptoglobinemia Hum Genet 114 499 502 14999562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b053"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain> TeyeKQuayeIKKodaYSoejimaMTsuneokaM 2003 A-61C and C-101G Hp gene promoter polymorphisms are, respectively, associated with ahaptoglobinaemia and hypohaptoglobinaemia in Ghana Clin Genet 64 439 443 14616769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b054"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain> TrapeJFFribourg-BlancA 1988 Ahaptoglobinemia in African populations and its relation to malaria endemicity Am J Epidemiol 127 1282 1288 3369425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat-0030129-b055"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain> AllisonACBlumbergBSApR 1958 Haptoglobin types in British, Spanish Basque and Nigerian African populations Nature 181 824 825 13526678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
