<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2386054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-9-S1-S12</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18366601</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-9-S1-S12</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>An integrative approach to characterize disease-specific pathways and their coordination: a case study in cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mxu@usc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>Ming-Chih J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>mckao@med.umich.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nunez-Iglesias</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>nunezigl@usc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nevins</surname><given-names>Joseph R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>nevin001@mc.duke.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>Mike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>mike@isds.duke.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Xianghong Jasmine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>xjzhou@usc.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Program in Molecular and Computational Biology, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>School of Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Institute for Genome Sciences and Policy, Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Institute of Statistics and Decision Sciences, Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">The 2007 International Conference on Bioinformatics &amp; Computational Biology (BIOCOMP'07)</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-editor">Jack Y Jang, Mary Qu Yang, Mengxia (Michelle) Zhu, Youping Deng and Hamid R Arabnia</named-content></supplement><fpage>S12</fpage><lpage>S12</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/9/S1/S12"/><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2008 Xu et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Xu et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The most common application of microarray technology in disease research is to identify genes differentially expressed in disease versus normal tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, it is known that, in complex diseases, phenotypes are determined not only by genes, but also by the underlying structure of genetic networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Often, it is the interaction of many genes that causes phenotypic variations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In this work, using cancer as an example, we develop graph-based methods to integrate multiple microarray datasets to discover disease-related co-expression network modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We propose an unsupervised method that take into account both co-expression dynamics and network topological information to simultaneously infer network modules and phenotype conditions in which they are activated or de-activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Using our method, we have discovered network modules specific to cancer or subtypes of cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Many of these modules are consistent with or supported by their functional annotations or their previously known involvement in cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In particular, we identified a module that is predominately activated in breast cancer and is involved in tumor suppression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>While individual components of this module have been suggested to be associated with tumor suppression, their coordinated function has never been elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Here by adopting a network perspective, we have identified their interrelationships and, particularly, a hub gene PDGFRL that may play an important role in this tumor suppressor network. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Using a network-based approach, our method provides new insights into the complex cellular mechanisms that characterize cancer and cancer subtypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>By incorporating co-expression dynamics information, our approach can not only extract more functionally homogeneous modules than those based solely on network topology, but also reveal pathway coordination beyond co-expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><conference><conf-date>25–28 June 2007</conf-date><conf-name>The 2007 International Conference on Bioinformatics &amp; Computational Biology (BIOCOMP'07)</conf-name><conf-loc>Las Vegas, NV, USA</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The recent development of microarray technology has significantly facilitated the identification of disease-related genes [1-4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, many disease phenotypes are determined not by individual genes, but by the coordinated effect of many genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Insight into the structure and coordination of disease-related pathways is crucial to understanding the pathophysiology of complex diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, it has proved difficult to infer pathways from microarray data by deriving modules of multiple related genes, rather than individual genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The major challenges are: (1) Genes involved in a pathway may exhibit complex expression relationships beyond co-expression, which may be overlooked by standard microarray analysis methods such as clustering [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>(2) Pathways are dynamic and the current static annotation of pathways may not serve as a good template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In fact, pathways are manual dissections of the underlying dynamic gene regulatory network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Under different conditions, different segments of the ensemble network will be activated, leading to condition-specific activation of pathways [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In this study, by integrating many microarray datasets we propose a novel method to simultaneously infer pathways and disease/phenotypic conditions under which the pathways are activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The identified pathways may comprise genes with complex expression relationships beyond co-expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Due to the existence of a large amount of cancer microarray data, we used cancer as our case study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We collected a series of microarray datasets measuring different types of cancers, and a series of datasets measuring other cellular/physiological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>We first construct a differential co-expression network, in which each node represents a gene and each edge indicates a gene pair that is frequently co-expressed in cancer datasets but not in non-cancer datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We then dissect the networks into cancer-subtype specific network modules by considering (1) co-expression dynamics and (2) network topology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Figure 1a illustrates the conceptual pipeline of our method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Overview of analysis procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>(A) Flow chart of the analysis pipeline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>(B) Schematic illustration of the concept of second-order similarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>It is obvious that the overall expression similarity between the two gene pairs (genes 1 and 2 versus genes 3 and 4) is not significantly high, but their first-order expression correlation profiles exhibit high second-order similarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>(C) Schematic illustration of the dissection of differential co-expression networks into network modules based on the co-expression dynamics and network connectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In the heat map, every column corresponds to a dataset and every row corresponds to a gene pair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Red, black, green and grey corresponds to positive, low, negative and missing correlations, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>By hierarchical clustering, the gene pairs fall into two major second-order clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The 9 gene pairs in the green cluster comprise three connected network components, whereas the 6 gene pairs in the red cluster give rise to three connected components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, by considering the second order cluster of a higher level of the hierarchy, which consists of both green and red clusters, the six networks are united to form two connected networks, reflecting the hierarchical modularity of cancer co-expression networks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-S1-S12-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>To measure co-expression dynamics, we use second-order expression similarity, which we proposed previously [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Briefly, if we define first-order expression similarity as the expression similarity of two genes from one dataset, then second-order similarity measures whether two gene pairs simultaneously exhibit either high or low expression similarity across multiple datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In general, high first-order similarity suggests the existence of a functional link between two genes, and clustering based on the second-order similarity captures multiple functional links always activated and deactivated under similar conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Such functional links are likely to comprise a functional module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, genes in a second-order cluster may not always have high first-order similarity (see an example in Figure 1b); therefore, second-order analysis allows us to identify functional modules that are inaccessible to co-expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Given multiple gene pairs sharing high second-order similarity, we further divide them into network components based on their connectivity on the differential co-expression graph (see an example in Figure 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We observe that genes within a connected network component are more likely to participate in the same specific pathway than those between different components (see Supplementary document in Additional file 1), which, in turn, are likely to be involved in different relevant pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This may reveal high-order cross-pathway coordination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In fact, hierarchical clustering of differentially co-expressed gene pairs based on their second-order similarity results in a hierarchical modularity in terms of relevance of functional links. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We designed a linear scaling model to select modules by considering both module size (number of edges) and within-module second-order similarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Then, given selected modules, we can further infer datasets (phenotypic conditions) in which a module is activated, i.e. in which genes in the module coordinate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Applying our methods to 32 cancer-related microarray datasets, and 23 non-cancer related datasets, we derived 162 second-order clusters consisting of 224 network modules, activated either in cancer or in specific cancer subtypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In particular, we identified a breast cancer specific network module that involved in tumor suppression via platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF)-like signaling, more importantly, a hub gene PDGFRL that may play an important role in this tumor suppressor module. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Network properties of the cancer differential co-expression network </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We curated 32 human microarray datasets (1,764 expression profiles in total) measuring cancers of 12 tissues, and 23 datasets (1,158 expression profiles) not related to cancer (e.g. normal tissues, chronic granulomatous disease, Huntington's disease, inflammatory response). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For details of the datasets refer to the Supplementary Table 1 in Additional file 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We first identify gene pairs which consistently demonstrate higher correlation in cancer versus non-cancer datasets based on a robust correlation estimator, the normalized Percentage Bend correlation (for details see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In following sections, if not specified, the term correlation will by default refer to the normalized Percentage Bend correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>These criteria result in 6,035 gene pairs covering 1,967 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The 6,035 gene pairs, each representing a potential conditional functional link, can be represented as a differential co-expression network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In this network, each gene is represented as a node and each differential co-expression relationship is represented as an edge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that co-expression networks follow a scale-free node degree distribution [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We observed that the differential co-expression network also follows such a topology, where only a small number of nodes act as “highly connected hubs” (see node degree distribution in Supplementary Figure 1 in Additional file 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This indicates that most gene-gene co-expression relationships differing between cancer and other phenotypes are associated with only a few “hub” genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Such hub genes exhibit a high degree of coordination with many other genes in neoplastic states, and are therefore likely to play important roles in carcinogenesis and cancer progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In fact, most hub genes fall into two main functional categories: 1) core processes of neoplastic states such as cell division and chromosome organization; or 2) dynamic interactions between cancer cells and their microenvironment such as angiogenesis, immune response, and cell adhesion (see Supplementary Table 2 in Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For those hub genes with unknown functions, we can predict their cancer-related functions based on their neighbor genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>For example, the 16 out of the 33 interacting partners of the ADP-ribosylation factor-like 6 interacting protein (ARL6IP) are involved in cell division (hypergeometric test p-value 1.6 × 10-24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Thus, ARL6IP is likely to be involved in cell proliferation, consistent with its initial characterization as an interaction partner of the Ras superfamily member ARL6 [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>As another example, while microfibrillar-associated protein 2 (MFAP2) has long been known to bind to various components of the elastic extracellular matrix [9], it has not been clear whether it serves more than a mechanical function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We found that 6 out of its 24 neighbor genes are involved in cell adhesion (p-value 7.7 × 10-5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In fact, a recent study found that MFAP2 binds to a neighbor gene Notch1 and activates it [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Identification of pathway modules specific to cancer or cancer subtypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The differential co-expression network provides a summary of co-expression links frequently active across all types of cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>However, it does not provide clues as to which set of links tend to be simultaneously active and inactive under which types of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>That is, the edges of a differential co-expression network may not be active in the same subset of datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In fact, the largest connected component of the differential co-expression network contains 5944 edges, which comprises 98% of all the edges in the network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Thus, based on connectivity alone we cannot break the network into functionally coherent and cancer-subtype specific modules. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>To dissect the networks, we integrate two types of information, the co-expression dynamics and the network connectivity, to extract cancer-subtype specific network modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>First, we employ the second-order clustering approach to utilize the co-expression dynamics information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This includes two steps: (i) for any two genes connected with an edge in the differential co-expression network, we calculate the expression correlation in each of the 32 cancer microarray datasets and store it in a vector, termed the first-order expression correlation profile of the genes; (ii) we then perform hierarchical clustering of all the gene pairs based on the Euclidean distance between the first-order expression correlation profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Unlike commonly used clustering approaches, the unit of the second-order clustering is a gene pair instead of a gene, and the distance between units is computed based on the first-order expression correlation profiles instead of the original gene expression profiles, hence the term “second-order” clustering [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Since each edge represents a frequently occurring co-expression relationship in multiple cancer datasets, it likely represents a functional link. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>If a cluster of gene pairs follows the same co-expression pattern across multiple cancer datasets, it represents a module of functional links being turned on or off simultaneously across different cancer phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Given a second-order cluster of gene pairs, we further identify connected network components among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We suggest that a set of gene pairs is more likely to be functionally related if they form a connected component (see Supplementary document in Additional file 1 for supporting analysis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Given a second-order hierarchical clustering tree, we traverse the tree bottom up to retrieve connected network components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In general, the size of a connected component (S, the number of edges) decreases with the second-order diameter (D), defined as the largest pairwise second-order distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We found that S and D show a linear scaling relationship in a logarithm scale (see Supplementary Figure 2 in Additional file 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We are especially interested in outliers – network components small in D but large in S, which represent tightly clustered network modules relative to their size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>We define the modularity score λ of a subnetwork using a linear scaling model λ = α log2(S) – log2(D) – β, where α and β are estimated using linear fitting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>With our data, we obtain α = 0.13 and β = 2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We select the top 60% of networks (S &gt;= 4) ranked by λ scores, removing those networks having D &gt;= 0.34, and merging heavily overlapping networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This procedure resulted in 162 second-order clusters comprising 224 connected network modules, with size ranging from 4 to 64 edges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Their composition, network topology, and activation status across various cancer phenotypes can be seen in Supplementary table 3 in Additional file 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>175 (78%) modules are statistically significantly functionally homogenous based on the GeneOntology Biological Process annotation (hypergeometric test p-value &lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The most predominant functional categories are cell cycle, cell division, cell proliferation, response to stress, immune response and cell adhesion (see Supplementary Table 4 in Additional file 2), consistent with known pathological mechanisms of cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>General cancer and solid tumor network modules. (A) A network module that tend to activate in most of cancer datasets, consisting 24 genes and 28 edges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Average correlation across all data sets is 0.42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Most of genes in the module are related to cell division and genetic stability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>(B) Another network module that is activated in most of cancer datasets, consisting 9 genes and 9 edges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The module is located in the same second order cluster as the one in figure 2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Its average correlation across all datasets is 0.39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Most of genes in the module are related to nucleobase, nucleoside, nucleotide and nucleic acid metabolism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(C) Left : a network that tends to be activated only in solid tumor datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Right, the co-expression heatmap of the edges across datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Six datasets are not shown in the heatmap due to lack of valid co-expression estimations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Average correlation in solid tumor datasets and other datasets are 0.61 and 0.17, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-S1-S12-2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>One main feature of our approach is that it can simultaneously discover network modules and the types of cancer in which the modules are activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Figure 2a shows a module that is activated in most of the cancer datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The genes of the module are mostly involved in cell division and genetic stability, representing a cell proliferation signature, a key feature of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Figure 2c shows a network module which tends to be activated in only solid tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The genes of the module are mostly involved in cell adhesion and organogenesis, which is specific to solid tumor versus blood cancers or neoplastic cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In the next section, we will detail two network modules which are activated predominately in breast cancer data sets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Network modules in the breast cancer cluster </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Our analysis resulted in a second-order cluster containing two connected network modules that tend to be more active in all seven breast tumor datasets relative to the rest of the datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The average correlation of these modules in breast tumor and other cancer datasets are 0.49 and 0.23 respectively (the t-test of co-expressions between breast tumor and the rest of cancer datasets gives a p-value of 1.56 × 10-95). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A tumor suppressor network related to PDGF superfamily signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The module in Figure 3a contains 52 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Most of them are extracellular or membrane proteins, and 23 genes have previously been found to be involved in breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>A number of such examples are listed in Supplementary document in Additional file 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Among the 52 genes, 16 are involved in cell adhesion (p-value 7.4 × 10-11), and 14 are involved cell-cell signalling (p-value 7.9 × 10-6), suggesting a role in tumor invasiveness of the module [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Coordinated breast tumor network modules (A) A breast tumor network module that involved in PDGF signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Genes in round shape have promoter regions that are predicted to be bound by transcription factor ZNF148. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(B) A breast tumor network module related to inflammatory response, located in the same second-order cluster as the one in Figure 3a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Genes in round shape have promoter regions that are predicted to be bound by transcription factor POU2F1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-S1-S12-3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Most interestingly, we found one main function of this network module appears to be tumor suppression via the inhibition of PDGF superfamily signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>A hub gene with high degree of this module is the gene PDGF receptor-like (PDGFRL) (degree 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>While its precise biological function is not known, PDGFRL encodes a 375aa product with significant sequence similarity to the extracellular domain of PDGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Indeed, mutations in PDGFRL have been found in individual cancer samples [12-15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>PDGFRL is located in chromosome 8p22-8p21.3, where multiple studies have suggested the existence of a putative breast cancer tumor suppressor gene [16], [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Recently, an in-depth study of the region using microcell-mediated chromosome transfer found that indeed PDGFRL expression is decreased in the majority of breast cancer cells [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Many genes in this network module have been found to be involved in PDGF superfamily signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For example, Cysteine-rich protein (SPARC) binds to PDGF-AB and PDGF-BB dimers, inhibiting the binding of these growth factors to their cell surface receptors [20] and inhibiting PDGF-induced vascular smooth muscle proliferation [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Also, connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) has structural similarities with PDGF [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Recently, two new PDGF ligands were discovered that have a N-terminal complement subcomponent C1R/C1S, UEGf, BMP1 (CUB) domain [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Interestingly both C1R and C1S are members of this network module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Also, LRP1 is a physiological modulator of the PDGF signaling pathway [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In total, we found direct Pubmed literature support for 19 out of the 52 member genes to be involved in (or related to) the PDGF-superfamily signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it is known that zinc finger protein (ZNF148) binds to the PDGFR [25] gene promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>We screened the promoter regions of the 52 member genes, and found that the binding sites of ZNF148 are significantly enriched (hypergeometric p-value 0.016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In addition, it has been reported that PDGFR positively regulates collagen production (for example [26], [27]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Our module showed the breast tumor specific co-expression between PDGFRL and collagens COL3A1, COL5A2 and COL6A3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Many of the above evidences support the hypothesis that PDGFRL has an agonistic function to PDGFR signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Although abundant evidence suggests the individual involvement of many of these genes in tumor suppression, their coordinated function has never been elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Here by adopting a network perspective, we have identified their interrelationships and a gene (PDGFRL) that may play a central role in this tumor suppressor network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>A network module related to inflammatory response </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Another identified breast cancer-specific network module (Figure 3b) may be involved in the coordination of the inflammatory response to cancer pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>This network consists of 5 genes: tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily member 1B (TNFRSF1B); vascular cell adhesion molecule 1 (VCAM1); leukocyte-associated immunoglobulin-like receptor 1 (LAIR1); and Cathepsin L1 (CSTL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>They are arranged around the macrophage-associated antigen (CD163). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Several lines of evidence have implicated these genes individually in breast cancer, for example: increased plasma levels of VCAM1 is associated with advanced breast cancer [28]; genetic variation in TNFRSF1B may predict the late onset of breast carcinoma, and relapse and death for patients with breast carcinoma [29]; finally, the breast cancer cell line exhibiting the highest in vitro invasiveness also expressed the highest amount of CTSL1 splice variant L-A3 [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Most of the genes of this module are related to tumor necrosis factor (TNF), an inflammatory cytokine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that activation of rat CD163 on peritoneal macrophages induces the production of pro-inflammatory mediators including TNF [31]; TNF directly interacts with TNFRSF1B [32] and is a mediator of TNF function in the mouse ovary [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Finally, transcription of VCAM1 in endothelial cells can be induced by TNF [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A transcription factor, octamer-binding transcription factor-1 (POU2F1, also known as Oct-1) has been predicted to bind promoter region of VCAM1, LAIR1 and CTSL (hypergeometric p-value 0.012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The binding of POU2F1 to VCAM1 promoter is indeed supported by the literature [35-37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Also, POU2F1 has been found to bind SP3 [38], which is reported to activate the transcription of CSTL [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The tight and coordinated expression of the genes in this network module reveals an induced inflammatory response that may be important in breast tumor progression [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Identification of pathway coordination beyond co-expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>A major advantage of second-order clustering is that it can identify functionally related genes beyond co-expression, as illustrated in Figure 1b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>We elaborate on this point in this section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>To allow readers to easily assess the magnitude of the correlation, only in this section we use the Pearson correlation to measure the co-expression level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Based on the definition of second-order clustering, connected network components within the same second-order cluster show coordinated activities, which implies their functional relevance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In the example of the two modules in the general cancer cluster in Figure 2a and 2b, each module may play different roles in the regulation of specific biological processes -- cell division and nucleic acid metabolism, respectively; the latter is clearly required for cell division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Given the fact that these processes belong to the same second-order cluster, they may represent facets of the same underlying neoplastic process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>However, member genes of the two modules exhibit distinct expression patterns: The average Pearson correlation between genes of the two modules is only 0.13. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>As another example, the two breast cancer modules described in last section are also related. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the collaboration of PDGF signalling and TNF have long been known to be required for tissue repairing [41], and their abnormal expression play important but partially defined roles in breast tumor development and progression [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, member genes of the two modules exhibit relatively distinct expression patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For example, two hub genes of modules, PDGFRL and CD163, also show very weak expression similarities across all seven breast cancer datasets: the average Pearson correlation between these two genes is only 0.24. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Besides the above examples, we found coordinated modules within the majority of identified second-order clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Overall, from the total 162 second-order clusters, 25% give rise to more than one connected network module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>To estimate the amount of cross module co-expression within second-order clusters, for each second order cluster, we first determined the active cancer datasets, in which the average Pearson correlation of gene pairs in the cluster is greater than 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>For 72% of those module pairs within the same second-order cluster, the average gene pairwise Pearson correlation between modules in the active datasets is less than 0.5 (normalized Percentage Bend correlation approximately &lt; 0.35), and for 30% module pairs the cross-module average gene pairwise Pearson correlation is less than 0.3 (normalized Percentage Bend correlation approximately &lt; 0.19). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, even genes in the same network module are not necessarily highly co-expressed when the module is active, despite their high degree of functional homogeneity, as discussed previously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We found that in 32 of 224 (14 %) modules, the average pairwise Pearson correlation of any two genes in the module is &lt; 0.5 in the corresponding active datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Such modules could therefore easily be overlooked by traditional clustering methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The rapid accumulation of microarray data provides unprecedented opportunities to study the molecular mechanisms underlying disease pathogenesis and progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Although many studies utilized multiple microarray datasets to derive consistent lists of genes specific for (subtypes of) cancer [43-45], little attention has been paid to derive genetic networks characterizing different types of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Segal et al. [46] used predefined biologically meaningful gene sets including known biological pathways, and have successfully identified activated or repressed biological modules in a wide variety of neoplastic conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The approach, however, relies on the knowledge of pre-defined biological modules and has limited use in the discovery of novel association between genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>A recent study by Choi et al. [47] compared the two co-expression networks summarized from 10 tumor and normal datasets, respectively, and have identified functional differences between normal growth and cancer in terms of gene coexpression changes in broad areas of physiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>However, due to the multifaceted nature of cancer, interactions in such a derived summary network may not be simultaneously active in individual datasets, i.e. specific cancer conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In this study, we propose an unsupervised method that integrates both co-expression dynamics and network topology information to characterize cancer (subtype) specific network modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The identified modules, such as modules activated across all cancer subtypes or only in solid tumors, are novel, but consistent with known molecular mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we have discovered a potential tumor suppressor network particularly active in breast tumors, and provide compelling evidence that the hub gene PDGFRL is a true tumor suppressor gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Compared to commonly used differential or co-expression analysis, our approach has the following advantages: (1) our unsupervised approach simultaneously discovers network modules and the conditions (e.g. cancer subtypes) in which they are activated, thus providing new insights into the complex cellular mechanisms that characterize cancer and cancer subtypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(2) Compared to existing approaches [47-51] which can only identify densely connected network modules based solely on network topology information, our approach incorporating co-expression dynamics information (second-order similarity) can extract more diverse types of modules regardless of network density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It is known that many biological pathways do not necessarily form densely connected modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(3) Our approach can reveal coordination of pathways beyond co-expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(4) Our method can be applied to any types of molecular networks beyond co-expression network, when data of multiple networks under different conditions are available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In the current framework, the selection of biologically meaningful modules still need certain amount of manual intervention from biology expert. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We are looking for more systematic ways for module selection, especially by putting the framework into the context of network statistics to improve the robustness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>For example, although the scaling model we constructed is based on direct observation of the distribution of network properties S and D, their log-linear relationship suggests that it should be straightforward to make use of the exponential random graph models that have been used in recent years to study statistical aspects of networks [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In essence, such models linearly combine network properties and assign the probability of observed networks as the exponential of such linear combinations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Integrating this work with the exponential family probabilistic models may provide both better estimation of the coefficients in the linear scaling model and more accurate selection of network modules via hypothesis testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>We intend to explore this direction in future work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The choice of datasets depends on the research question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Ideally there should be a balanced and sufficient sampling of different phenotypes (in particular different tissues for this cancer study). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Particularly, a paired Wilcoxon test between cancer and normal samples of the same tissue would significantly eliminate the amount of tissue-specific co-expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>However, due to the limited amount and the heterogeneity of existing data it is currently impractical to achieve this goal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Using a weighted sampling scheme could potentially bypass the imbalance effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>We aim to investigate this strategy, and use statistical models of the correlation values to determine the weighting factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Datasets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We curated 32 cancer and 23 non-cancer human gene expression datasets mainly from the Stanford Microarray Database (SMD) and Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) databases, each containing more than 15 microarrays, on either Affymetrix or cDNA platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>In each dataset, if there are multiple probes that correspond to the same gene, we choose the one that contains the least amount of missing values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>For datasets containing absolute expression measurements, we convert all values &lt;= 10 to 10, then perform a base 2 log transform. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Estimation of Pairwise gene co-expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We used Percentage Bend Correlation [53] (with β=0.05) to obtain a robust correlation estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Percentage Bend Correlation first detects outliers in expression values of each gene then reduces the effects of those outliers in the correlation calculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Only gene pairs with a large number of valid samples m&gt;= 15 are used to calculate correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>To make the correlation estimates comparable across different datasets of variable sample sizes and among different gene pairs of different amount of missing expression measures within the same dataset, we performed Fisher's z-transform [54] to reduce sample size effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Given a correlation estimate r and sample size n, the Fisher's Z scores (divided by its theoretical standard deviation) is calculated as z=n−32log⁡(1+r1−r), which theoretically has an asymptotically standard normal distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Note that sample size n may be different from gene pair to gene pair due to missing values, and from dataset to dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>In reality, we observed that the distributions of the z-score are still different from dataset to dataset: we therefore normalized z-scores to enforce the standard normal distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>After that, standardized correlations r' are obtained by inverting the z-score with a fixed n of 30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Select differentially co-expressed gene pairs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We define a gene pair to be differentially co-expressed between cancer and non-cancer if it satisfies the following two criteria: (1) their expression correlation in cancer datasets is sufficiently strong (can be either positively or negatively high). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>This is done by setting threshold for average summed square of correlations in cancer datasets. i.e, 1c∑k(ri(k))2≥0.35 for the gene pair i, where there are c valid correlation estimations (c=32 if there are no missing values) and k is dataset index corresponding to all valid correlation estimations; and (2) the Wilcoxon ranksum test of correlations between cancer and non-cancer datasets gives a p-value &lt;= 0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Identify conditionally activated network module candidates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>We hierarchically clustered the differentially co-expressed gene pairs based on their expression correlation profiles using the CLUSTER program [55] with complete linkage and Euclidean distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The Euclidean distance is averaged to provide a simple estimation given the existence of missing correlations (due to the missing value problem). di,j=1c∑k(ri(k)−rj(k))2 where ri(k) and rj(k) are the correlations of gene pairs i and j in the dataset k, respectively, and c is number of valid correlations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In the hierarchical tree, each leaf node represents a gene pair, and each inner node corresponds to a second-order cluster of gene pairs (edges) which may comprise zero, one, or more connected network components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In cases where the size of the differential network is too big to be processed using hierarchical clustering (HC), the gene pairs were first separated using k-means clustering then processed the smaller clusters separately by hierarchical clustering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>As for our experience, the biologically meaningful modules normally contain less than a few hundred edges, thus k-means clustering will keep most of modules intact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology function and transcription factor enrichment of modules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The functional enrichment analysis is done by the hypergeometric test on genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We selected 419 Gene Ontology (GO) functions (i.e. biological process terms) which are 4 levels below the root in the GO hierarchy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Each gene may be directly or indirectly associated with some of these functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>A set of genes will be considered to have a enriched function when (1) the functional homogeneity modeled by the hypergeometric distribution [56] is significant at a significance level 0.01 and (2) there are at least 2 genes in the set are associated with the function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Identification of transcription factor binding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>10kb upstream sequences for each gene were obtained from NCBI Gene database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>After applying RepeatMasker [57], we used the MATCH program of TRANSFAC [58] (version 9.2) to scan the sequences for the presence of transcription factor binding sites based on position weight matrices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>We used vertebrate-specific matrices, and chose cut-offs to minimize the sum of false positives and false negatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We kept only the top 3,000 hits per matrix, sorted by the matrix similarity score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Altogether we obtained 349,178 predicted transcription factor target relationships of 180 transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>A hypergeometric test was performed for each network module to search for over-represented transcription factor binding sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>XJZ conceived the research problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>MX and XJZ designed the methodology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>JNI and MW provided suggestions for the design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>MX developed programs, collected and processed data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>JNI curated data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>XJZ, MX and JNI provided general interpretation of results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>MJK, XJZ and JNI analyzed specific examples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>MX, XJZ, MJK, and JNI drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>JRN commented on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>MW and JRN suggested more applications of the method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This document includes 1) description of selection of hub genes, 2) analysis of functional network homogeneity, 3) description of supplementary tables and 4) supplementary figures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-9-S1-S12-S1.PDF" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Additional file 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-9-S1-S12-S2.XLS" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We thank Xiaotu Ma, Reza Alaghband and Adrian Dobra for helpful advices on method design, Yu Huang, Haiyan Hu and Mike Mehan for providing technical help, Jen-Tsan Chi and Chao Cheng for advise on result interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>We also thank anonymous reviewers for their suggestions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>This work is supported by the NIH grants U54CA112952, R01GM074163, and the NSF grant 0515936. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>This article has been published as part of BMC Genomics Volume 9 Supplement 1, 2008: The 2007 International Conference on Bioinformatics &amp; Computational Biology (BIOCOMP'07). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The full contents of the supplement are available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/9?issue=S1"/>. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>SevenetNCussenotODNA microarrays in clinical practice: past, present, and futureClin Exp Med20033131274887210.1007/s102380300008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>ChenXCheungSTSoSFanSTBarryCHigginsJLaiKMJiJDudoitSNgIOGene expression patterns in human liver cancersMol Biol Cell200213192919391205806010.1091/mbc.02-02-0023. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>GolubTRSlonimDKTamayoPHuardCGaasenbeekMMesirovJPCollerHLohMLDowningJRCaligiuriMAMolecular classification of cancer: class discovery and class prediction by gene expression monitoringScience19992865315371052134910.1126/science.286.5439.531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>LiuZMaasKAuneTMIdentification of gene expression signatures in autoimmune disease without the influence of familial resemblanceHum Mol Genet2006155015091637142010.1093/hmg/ddi466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>ZhouXJKaoMCHuangHWongANunez-IglesiasJPrimigMAparicioOMFinchCEMorganTEWongWHFunctional annotation and network reconstruction through cross-platform integration of microarray dataNat Biotechnol2005232382431565432910.1038/nbt1058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>YanXMehanMHuangYWatermanMSYuPSZhouXJA Graph-based Approach to Systematically Reconstruct Human Transcriptional Regulatory ModulesBioinformatics (ISMB 2007)2007To appear </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>JordanIKMarino-RamirezLWolfYIKooninEVConservation and coevolution in the scale-free human gene coexpression networkMol Biol Evol200421205820701528233310.1093/molbev/msh222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>PetterssonMBessonovaMGuHFGroopLCJonssonJICharacterization, chromosomal localization, and expression during hematopoietic differentiation of the gene encoding Arl6ip, ADP-ribosylation-like factor-6 interacting protein (ARL6)Genomics2000683513541099557910.1006/geno.2000.6278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>JacobMPSauvageMOsborne-PellegrinM[Regulation of elastin synthesis]J Soc Biol200119513114111723825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>MiyamotoALauRHeinPWShipleyJMWeinmasterGMicrofibrillar proteins MAGP-1 and MAGP-2 induce Notch1 extracellular domain dissociation and receptor activationJ Biol Chem200628110089100971649267210.1074/jbc.M600298200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>RossJSLinetteGPStecJClarkEAyersMLeschlyNSymmansWFHortobagyiGNPusztaiLBreast cancer biomarkers and molecular medicine: part IIExpert Rev Mol Diagn200441691881499590410.1586/14737159.4.2.169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>KomiyaASuzukiHUedaTAidaSItoNShiraishiTYataniREmiMYasudaKShimazakiJPRLTS gene alterations in human prostate cancerJpn J Cancer Res1997883893939197531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>LereboursFOlschwangSThuilleBSchmitzAFouchetPBuecherBMartinetNGalateauFThomasGFine deletion mapping of chromosome 8p in non-small-cell lung carcinomaInt J Cancer1999818548581036212910.1002/(SICI)1097-0215(19990611)81:6&lt;854::AID-IJC3&gt;3.0.CO;2-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>AnQLiuYGaoYHuangJFongXLiuLZhangDZhangJChengSDeletion of tumor suppressor genes in Chinese non-small cell lung cancerCancer Lett20021841891951212769110.1016/S0304-3835(02)00204-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>KahngYSLeeYSKimBKParkWSLeeJYKangCSLoss of heterozygosity of chromosome 8p and 11p in the dysplastic nodule and hepatocellular carcinomaJ Gastroenterol Hepatol2003184304361265389210.1046/j.1440-1746.2003.02997.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>YaremkoMLKutzaCLyzakJMickRRecantWMWestbrookCALoss of heterozygosity from the short arm of chromosome 8 is associated with invasive behavior in breast cancerGenes Chromosomes Cancer199616189195881445210.1002/(SICI)1098-2264(199607)16:3&lt;189::AID-GCC6&gt;3.0.CO;2-V </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>SeitzSWernerSFischerJNothnagelASchlagPMScherneckSRefined deletion mapping in sporadic breast cancer at chromosomal region 8p12-p21 and association with clinicopathological parametersEur J Cancer200036150715131093079810.1016/S0959-8049(00)00135-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>RennstamKAhlstedt-SoiniMBaldetorpBBendahlPOBorgAKarhuRTannerMTirkkonenMIsolaJPatterns of chromosomal imbalances defines subgroups of breast cancer with distinct clinical features and prognosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>A study of 305 tumors by comparative genomic hybridizationCancer Res2003638861886814695203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>SeitzSKorschingEWeimerJJacobsenAArnoldNMeindlAArnoldWGustavusDKlebigCPetersenIGenetic background of different cancer cell lines influences the gene set involved in chromosome 8 mediated breast tumor suppressionGenes Chromosomes Cancer2006456126271655277310.1002/gcc.20325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>RainesEWLaneTFIruela-ArispeMLRossRSageEHThe extracellular glycoprotein SPARC interacts with platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF)-AB and -BB and inhibits the binding of PDGF to its receptorsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19928912811285131109210.1073/pnas.89.4.1281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>MotamedKFunkSEKoyamaHRossRRainesEWSageEHInhibition of PDGF-stimulated and matrix-mediated proliferation of human vascular smooth muscle cells by SPARC is independent of changes in cell shape or cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitorsJ Cell Biochem2002847597711183540110.1002/jcb.10095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>KanazawaSMiyakeTKakinumaTTanemotoKTsunodaTKikuchiKThe expression of platelet-derived growth factor and connective tissue growth factor in different types of abdominal aortic aneurysmsJ Cardiovasc Surg (Torino)20054627127815956925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>UstachCVKimHRPlatelet-derived growth factor D is activated by urokinase plasminogen activator in prostate carcinoma cellsMol Cell Biol200525627962881598803610.1128/MCB.25.14.6279-6288.2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>TakayamaYMayPAndersonRGHerzJLow density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 1 (LRP1) controls endocytosis and c-CBL-mediated ubiquitination of the platelet-derived growth factor receptor beta (PDGFR beta)J Biol Chem200528018504185101575309610.1074/jbc.M410265200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>De BustosCSmitsAStrombergBCollinsVPNisterMAfinkGA PDGFRA promoter polymorphism, which disrupts the binding of ZNF148, is associated with primitive neuroectodermal tumours and ependymomasJ Med Genet20054231371563507210.1136/jmg.2004.024034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ChaudharyNIRothGJHilbergFMuller-QuernheimJPrasseAZisselGSchnappAParkJEInhibition of PDGF VEGF and FGF signalling attenuates fibrosisEur Respir J200717301095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>ZymekPBujakMChatilaKCieslakAThakkerGEntmanMLFrangogiannisNGThe role of platelet-derived growth factor signaling in healing myocardial infarctsJ Am Coll Cardiol200648231523231716126510.1016/j.jacc.2006.07.060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>SilvaHCGarcaoFCoutinhoECDe OliveiraCFRegateiroFJSoluble VCAM-1 and E-selectin in breast cancer: relationship with staging and with the detection of circulating cancer cellsNeoplasma20065353854317167725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>MestiriSBouaouinaNBen AhmedSChouchaneLA functional polymorphism of the tumor necrosis factor receptor-II gene associated with the survival and relapse prediction of breast carcinomaCytokine2005301821871586339210.1016/j.cyto.2005.01.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>CasermanSKenigSSloaneBFLahTTCathepsin L splice variants in human breast cell linesBiol Chem20063876296341674013510.1515/BC.2006.080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>PolflietMMFabriekBODanielsWPDijkstraCDvan den BergTKThe rat macrophage scavenger receptor CD163: expression, regulation and role in inflammatory mediator productionImmunobiology20062114194251692048110.1016/j.imbio.2006.05.015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>MedvedevAEEspevikTRangesGSundanADistinct roles of the two tumor necrosis factor (TNF) receptors in modulating TNF and lymphotoxin alpha effectsJ Biol Chem199627197789784862165810.1074/jbc.271.16.9778 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>GreenfeldCRRobyKFPeplingMEBabusJKTerranovaPFFlawsJATumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) Receptor Type 2 Is an Important Mediator of TNF alpha Function in the Mouse OvaryBiol Reprod2007762242311706560210.1095/biolreprod.106.055509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>NeishASReadMAThanosDPineRManiatisTCollinsTEndothelial interferon regulatory factor 1 cooperates with NF-kappa B as a transcriptional activator of vascular cell adhesion molecule 1Mol Cell Biol199515255825697537851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>SchwachtgenJLRemacleJEJanelNBrysRHuylebroeckDMeyerDKerbiriou-NabiasDOct-1 is involved in the transcriptional repression of the von willebrand factor gene promoterBlood199892124712589694713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>SyderAJOhJDGurugeJLO'DonnellDKarlssonMMillsJCBjorkholmBMGordonJIThe impact of parietal cells on Helicobacter pylori tropism and host pathology: an analysis using gnotobiotic normal and transgenic miceProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2003100346734721262922510.1073/pnas.0230380100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>OrtegoMHernandezAGBustosCBlanco-ColioLMHernandez-PresaMATunonJEgidoJ3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A reductase inhibitors increase the binding activity and nuclear level of Oct-1 in mononuclear cellsEur J Pharmacol20024481131211214493010.1016/S0014-2999(02)01938-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>LiuMLeibowitzJLClarkDAMendicinoMNingQDingJWD'AbreoCFungLMarsdenPALevyGAGene transcription of fgl2 in endothelial cells is controlled by Ets-1 and Oct-1 and requires the presence of both Sp1 and Sp3Eur J Biochem2003270227422861275244710.1046/j.1432-1033.2003.03595.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>SriramanVRichardsJSCathepsin L gene expression and promoter activation in rodent granulosa cellsEndocrinology20041455825911456370310.1210/en.2003-0963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>CoussensLMWerbZInflammation and cancerNature20024208608671249095910.1038/nature01322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>OttavianiEMalagoliDFranchiniAInvertebrate humoral factors: cytokines as mediators of cell survivalProg Mol Subcell Biol20043412514979662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>ChalaEManesCIliadesHSkaragkasGMouratidouDKapantaisEInsulin resistance, growth factors and cytokine levels in overweight women with breast cancer before and after chemotherapyHormones (Athens)2006513714616807226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>RhodesDRBarretteTRRubinMAGhoshDChinnaiyanAMMeta-analysis of microarrays: interstudy validation of gene expression profiles reveals pathway dysregulation in prostate cancerCancer Res2002624427443312154050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>RhodesDRYuJShankerKDeshpandeNVaramballyRGhoshDBarretteTPandeyAChinnaiyanAMLarge-scale meta-analysis of cancer microarray data identifies common transcriptional profiles of neoplastic transformation and progressionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2004101930993141518467710.1073/pnas.0401994101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>ChoiJKChoiJYKimDGChoiDWKimBYLeeKHYeomYIYooHSYooOJKimSIntegrative analysis of multiple gene expression profiles applied to liver cancer studyFEBS Lett2004565931001513505910.1016/j.febslet.2004.05.087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>SegalEFriedmanNKollerDRegevAA module map showing conditional activity of expression modules in cancerNat Genet200436109010981544869310.1038/ng1434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>ChoiJKYuUYooOJKimSDifferential coexpression analysis using microarray data and its application to human cancerBioinformatics200521434843551623431710.1093/bioinformatics/bti722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>LiuCCChenWSLinCCLiuHCChenHYYangPCChangPCChenJJTopology-based cancer classification and related pathway mining using microarray dataNucleic Acids Res200634406940801691443710.1093/nar/gkl583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>CarterSLBrechbuhlerCMGriffinMBondATGene co-expression network topology provides a framework for molecular characterization of cellular stateBioinformatics200420224222501513093810.1093/bioinformatics/bth234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>SteuerRKurthsJFiehnOWeckwerthWObserving and interpreting correlations in metabolomic networksBioinformatics200319101910261276106610.1093/bioinformatics/btg120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>ButteAJTamayoPSlonimDGolubTRKohaneISDiscovering functional relationships between RNA expression and chemotherapeutic susceptibility using relevance networksProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20009712182121861102730910.1073/pnas.220392197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>CarringtonPJScottJWassermanSModels and methods in social network analysis2005Cambridge ; New York: Cambridge University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>WilcoxRRIntroduction to robust estimation and hypothesis testing1997San Diego, CA: Academic Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>AndersonTWAn introduction to multivariate statistical analysis20033rd edn.Hoboken, N.J.: Wiley-Interscience </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>de HoonMJImotoSNolanJMiyanoSOpen source clustering softwareBioinformatics200420145314541487186110.1093/bioinformatics/bth078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>WuLFHughesTRDavierwalaAPRobinsonMDStoughtonRAltschulerSJLarge-scale prediction of Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene function using overlapping transcriptional clustersNat Genet2002312552651208952210.1038/ng906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>SmitAFAHubleyRGreenPRepeatMasker </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>MatysVFrickeEGeffersRGosslingEHaubrockMHehlRHornischerKKarasDKelAEKel-MargoulisOVTRANSFAC: transcriptional regulation, from patterns to profilesNucleic Acids Res2003313743781252002610.1093/nar/gkg108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
