<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2935479</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838661</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-20123R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biophysics</subject><subject>Plant Biology</subject><subject>Biophysics/Membrane Proteins and Energy Transduction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Sucrose- and H+-Dependent Charge Movements Associated with the Gating of Sucrose Transporter ZmSUT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Charge Movements in ZmSUT1</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carpaneto</surname><given-names>Armando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koepsell</surname><given-names>Hermann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bamberg</surname><given-names>Ernst</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hedrich</surname><given-names>Rainer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>Dietmar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Istituto di Biofisica-CNR, Genova, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institut für Anatomie und Zellbiologie, Universität Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Max-Plank-Institute for Biophysics, Frankfurt am Main, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Julius-von-Sachs-Institut, Molekulare Pflanzenphysiologie und Biophysik, Universität Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Heidelberg, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>geiger@botanik.uni-wuerzburg.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: AC HK EB RH DG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AC DG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: AC DG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AC HK EB RH DG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e12605</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Carpaneto et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In contrast to man the majority of higher plants use sucrose as mobile carbohydrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Accordingly proton-driven sucrose transporters are crucial for cell-to-cell and long-distance distribution within the plant body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Generally very negative plant membrane potentials and the ability to accumulate sucrose quantities of more than 1 M document that plants must have evolved transporters with unique structural and functional features. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>To unravel the functional properties of one specific high capacity plasma membrane sucrose transporter in detail, we expressed the sucrose/H+ co-transporter from maize ZmSUT1 in Xenopus oocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Application of sucrose in an acidic pH environment elicited inward proton currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Interestingly the sucrose-dependent H+ transport was associated with a decrease in membrane capacitance (Cm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In addition to sucrose Cm was modulated by the membrane potential and external protons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In order to explore the molecular mechanism underlying these Cm changes, presteady-state currents (Ipre) of ZmSUT1 transport were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Decay of Ipre could be best fitted by double exponentials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>When plotted against the voltage the charge Q, associated to Ipre, was dependent on sucrose and protons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The mathematical derivative of the charge Q versus voltage was well in line with the observed Cm changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Based on these parameters a turnover rate of 500 molecules sucrose/s was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In contrast to gating currents of voltage dependent-potassium channels the analysis of ZmSUT1-derived presteady-state currents in the absence of sucrose (I = Q/τ) was sufficient to predict ZmSUT1 transport-associated currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Taken together our results indicate that in the absence of sucrose, ‘trapped’ protons move back and forth between an outer and an inner site within the transmembrane domains of ZmSUT1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This movement of protons in the electric field of the membrane gives rise to the presteady-state currents and in turn to Cm changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Upon application of external sucrose, protons can pass the membrane turning presteady-state into transport currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For long distance transport from the side of production (source) in leaves to the user (sink) tissues, sucrose is loaded into the tube-like phloem network [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Phloem loading of sucrose, synthesized in photosynthetic cells (mesophyll) within the leaves, takes place in the sieve tube adjacent to companion cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>These transport-active cells appear to be interconnected via plasmodesmata to the sieve tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The flux and direction of sucrose is regulated by SUC/SUT type sucrose cotransporters [2], . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Plant and animal sugar carriers shuttle their substrates in cotransport with protons or sodium ions, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In contrast to animal cells, plants cells establish a pH gradient (acidic extracellular space) and very negative membrane potentials via plasma membrane proton pumps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>From this electromotive force sucrose transporters gain energy to drive sucrose accumulation of more than 1 M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Recently detailed biophysical studies of ZmSUT1 revealed that this carrier is working like a perfect thermodynamic machine by which the proton gradient drives sucrose transport and vice versa on the basis of a 1∶1 H+:sucrose stoichiometry [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>As a matter of fact ZmSUT1 is capable to mediate sucrose loading and unloading of the phloem [6] under physiological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The ZmSUT1 behavior is in contrast to the animal counterpart SGLT1, which mediates sugar uptake only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>These fundamental physiological differences between plant phloem- and animal blood stream sugar transporters are harbored in their unique structure-function relationships. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The knowledge about the transport cycle of plant sucrose transporters is, however, still very limited and dates back to the 1990s [8], [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Cotransporters characteristically display three main kinds of electrical activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Besides the membrane current associated with the ion-coupled translocation of the organic substrate (transport-associated current, Itr), most cotransporters exhibit two further kinds of current in the absence of organic substrate: an ‘uncoupled’ (steady) current and a presteady-state current (Ipre) [10], [11], [12], [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>While the presteady-state current is best observed in the absence of substrate, it disappears when the substrate is present in saturating amounts [14], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Using presteady-state measurements and voltage clamp fluorometry the Wright lab [11], [16], [17], [18] examined the transport cycle of the Na+ driven glucose cotransporter SGLT1 during sugar transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>They recorded changes in charge movement in response to rapid membrane potential jumps in the presence and absence of sugar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In Na+ buffers and in the absence of glucose, stepwise jumps in the membrane voltage elicited presteady-state currents (charge movements). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Application of glucose, however, induced transport-associated inward Na+ currents and reduced the maximal charge movements (Qmax). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents were completely inhibited by saturating sugar concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Based on their results the authors developed an ordered eight-state model for the transport mechanism of SGLT1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Therein charge movements of SGLT1, giving rise to the observed presteady-state currents, were shown to be associated with the binding of sodium to the empty transporters (e.g. [16], [18]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In addition to the conductance, the capacitance of biological membranes (Cm) represents a basic electrical property. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Changes in Cm arise from changes of the membrane surface area (endo- or exocytosis) or charge displacement in the electrical field of the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The latter occurs e.g. when charged domains of integral membrane proteins undergo conformational changes or when ions bind to the protein within the electrical field of the membrane [19], [20], [21], [22], [23], [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Thus charge displacements can turn membranes into highly nonlinear, time-varying capacitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In this respect membrane proteins can be seen as insulators with specific dielectric properties and not only as conductors for ions/substrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In this study we combined Cm and presteady-state current measurements to elucidate the transport mechanism of ZmSUT1 in Xenopus oocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Cm measurements at various sucrose concentrations revealed a dose-dependent, reversible decrease of Cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Furthermore Cm was modulated by the membrane potential and the external proton concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To explore the molecular mechanism underlying the Cm changes, presteady-state currents (Ipre) of ZmSUT1 transport were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Thereby we observed pronounced charge movements in the absence of the substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The decay rate constant (τ) of Ipre and the quantity of displaced charges (Q) depended on the voltage and proton concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The quantitative comparison of transport-associated currents and Ipre revealed that sucrose-induced transport currents can be predicted solely by the analysis of Ipre in the absence of sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>This relation suggests that charge movements at zero sucrose and sucrose-induced transport of protons arise from the same molecular mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Ligands Induce Voltage Dependent Capacitance Changes in ZmSUT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The expression of ZmSUT1 in Xenopus oocytes and the application of 0.5, 1, 3 and 100 mM sucrose to the external medium induced dose-dependent inward currents (see Fig. 1 [7]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In addition to the current recorded via the two-electrode voltage-clamp technique (TECV) membrane capacitance changes were monitored [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In the absence of external sucrose at V = −20 mV, Cm for the depicted, representative oocyte was 190 nF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Upon addition of sucrose the membrane capacitance decreased reversibly in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Upon application of external sucrose the membrane capacitance decreased at all voltages tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In water injected oocytes Cm was not influenced by the addition of sucrose (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In absence of sucrose, voltage-dependent Cm changes were characterized by a bell-shaped curve with a maximum around –80 mV (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>During a stepwise increase in sucrose concentrations, the Cm drop saturated above 3 mM of the disaccharide at pH 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>ZmSUT1 represents a proton/sucrose cotransporter that drives sucrose at the expense of the proton gradient and vice versa [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We, thus, investigated whether and how external protons modulate Cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>With the representative oocyte clamped to −20 mV and sucrose-free bath solution buffered to pH 4, Cm was 178 nF (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A decrease in the proton concentration from pH 4 to pH 5, 6, and 7 was followed by a drop in capacitance characterized by a maximum at pH 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The significant decrease of Cm upon a shift from pH 4 to pH 3, equivalent to 1 mM protons, was less pronounced than a similar shift of one pH unit from 4 to 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The voltage-dependence of the membrane capacitance at different pH values appeared nonlinear (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For a wide voltage range, from –120 to 0 mV, Cm peaked at pH 4 dropping at both lower (pH 5 and 6) and higher (pH 3) external proton concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Moreover at pH 5 when compared to pH 3 an opposite voltage-dependence was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Upon depolarization Cm decreased at pH 5 while it increased at pH 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The application of saturating sucrose concentration lowered Cm at all voltages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In order to interpret the results obtained so far, we assumed that changes in membrane capacitance in ZmSUT1 expressing oocytes were associated with charge movements inside the transporter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Sucrose dependent membrane capacitance changes in ZmSUT1 expressing oocytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A) While continuously recording the membrane capacitance (Cm) at −20 mV and pH 4, various external solutions (indicated in the figure) were applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Upon perfusion with sucrose containing external media the Cm decreased in a dose dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>B) When plotting Cm against the membrane potential it became apparent that at all tested voltages, Cm decreased in the presence of sucrose in a dose dependent manner (standard solution pH 4, sucrose concentrations are indicated in the figure, n≥4, ±SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Capacitance changes in response to varying proton concentrations. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A) Continuous recording of Cm at −20 mV and indicated pH values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>When exchanging the bath solution by stepwise decreasing proton concentrations from pH 4 to 7 in the absence of sucrose, Cm decreased reversibly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Increasing the proton concentration from pH 4 to 3 at −20 mV led to a decrease of Cm as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Subsequent application of saturating sucrose concentrations decreased Cm to similar levels as in the presence of neutral buffers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>B) Cm/voltage plot at various pH values without sucrose and at pH 4 in the presence of sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Decreasing the proton concentration resulted in a shift of the Cm peak towards more negative membrane potentials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>At pH 4 and in the presence of saturating sucrose concentrations Cm was depressed at all voltages tested (n≥5, ±SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Cm values were normalized to values at pH 4 in the absence of sucrose. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Charge Movements in ZmSUT1 Generate Presteady-State Currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Charge movements (presteady-state currents) inside membrane proteins have been observed with ion channels [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>These ‘presteady-state- or gating currents’ precede the opening and closing of voltage-dependent channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>To investigate the molecular basis of sugar-dependent modulation of Cm with ZmSUT1, we monitored voltage-dependent presteady-state currents of the sugar/proton co-transporter with high resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Thereby currents in response to membrane potential changes from a holding potential of −20 mV to −80 mV in the absence and presence of saturating sucrose concentration were compared (inset of Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>As a matter of fact the stationary current in the presence of sucrose was significantly higher than in the absence of the sugar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>These stationary sucrose-induced currents were named transport-associated currents (Itr). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The transient current right after the voltage jump in the absence of sucrose, appeared slower in reaching the stationary level than with sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This is better visible when subtracting the stationary currents (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents (Ipre) associated to the ZmSUT1 activities were gained by subtracting the current transients at different voltages in the presence and absence of sucrose (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The integral of the presteady-state currents over time plotted against the voltage reflect the associated charge-voltage curve (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Note, that there is no significant difference from the “on” (integral of Ipre during the application of the voltage pulse) and the “off” charge (integral of Ipre during repolarisation; Fig. 3D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents of ZmSUT1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>A) Inset: currents recorded in the absence (No suc) and in the presence of saturating sucrose concentration (+suc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Same currents presented in the inset after forcing their stationary level to zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Holding and pulse voltages were –20 and –80 mV respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>B) Presteady-state currents versus time obtained after subtracting the stationary currents in the absence and in the presence of saturating sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Holding voltage –20 mV, voltage pulses from +40 mV to –120 mV (step –40 mV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Inset: presteady-state current elicited by a voltage of –80 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>C) Charge associated to presteady-state currents plotted versus the voltage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The charge was obtained from integration of the presteady-state currents (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The continuous line is the fit of Q with the Boltzmann function shown in Material and Methods with, in this oocyte, Qmax = −9 nC, Vh = −80 mV and s = 103 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Inset of panel C: Capacitance (empty symbols) measured using the method of Adrian and Almers (1976). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The continuous line is the capacitance derived from the Q-V plot of panel C (see materials and methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>D) Qon and Qoff, the charge movements during the on and off response of the voltage steps obtained from the integrals of the presteady-state currents in 20 different oocytes, are plotted for various membrane voltages from –120 and +60 mV in 10 mV steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The dotted line has a slope of 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The linear fits (not shown) of the experimental points for each single oocyte give regression coefficients with a minimum value of −0.993, indicating very strong correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>E) Time constants of the decay of the on and off presteady-state currents versus the applied voltage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The final decay of the presteady-state currents can be fitted by a two-exponential function with a fast and a slow τ (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The value of the fast time constants (▪ for the on and  for the off presteady-state current) is under 1 ms and is limited by the speed of the voltage-clamp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Symbols • and + represent the slow time constants of the on and off presteady-state currents respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>F) Transported (measured, empty symbol) and predicted (filled symbol) currents plotted against voltage for a single oocyte. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>When fitting Q vs V with the Boltzmann equation (continuous line in Fig. 3C, see materials and methods) a half activation voltage of –59±4 mV (mean±SEM, n = 20) was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Using the derivative of the charge over time the capacitance change associated with the presteady-state current, was obtained (Fig. 3C inset, open circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Note, that the calculated capacitance changes were well in agreement with the experimentally determined capacitance (black line) using small voltage steps according to the methods developed by Adrian and Almers [28] (see materials and methods, Fig. 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The good agreement between these two quantities guarantees that the mentioned experimental approach does not harbor significant problems of voltage-clamp due to the large potential pulses (ΔV up to 100 mV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The slope of the Boltzmann fit of 98±3 mV (mean±SEM, n = 20) is equal to KT/ezδ where K and T have the usual meaning, e is the elementary charge, z the valence of the moving charge and δ the fraction of the membrane field through which the charge moves; therefore zδ is equal to 0.26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>If the moving charge is monovalent, then it moves 26% of the electrical distance from the external solution to the cytoplasmic side of the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The decay of the presteady-state currents could be described by two exponential functions (inset of Fig. 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The exponential fitting identified two reliable time constants (Fig. 3E, see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The fast component of less than 1 ms is biased by the speed of the clamp of the amplifier (squares). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The slow time constant was around 2 ms at negative voltages and up to 3 ms at positive voltages (circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The cross symbols in Fig. 3E represent the slow time constants derived from the exponential fitting of Ipre “off”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Their averages served as an estimate of the time constant of the “on” presteady-state current at the holding voltage of −20 mV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Relationship between Ipre and Itr </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The transport-associated currents in the presence of external sucrose were apparently different to the presteady-state currents obtained in the absence of sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The gating currents of voltage dependent ion channels appear independent from the presence or absence of the permeating ion [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Therefore these gating charges and the transport-associated currents are clearly distinct and not predictable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>To test whether there exists a relation between Ipre in the absence of sucrose and Itr in the presence of sucrose with ZmSUT1, we used the relationship I = Q/τ to predict the transport-associated currents solely from the Ipre parameters obtained without sucrose (cf. [30], ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Indeed we could obtain a very good agreement between the measured transport-associated currents (open circles) and predicted currents (filled symbols, Fig. 3F) indicating that there is an inter-relation between Ipre and Itr. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>ZmSUT1 Turns Over 500 Sucrose Molecules per Second </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In Fig. 4A we plotted the transport-associated currents (Itr), recorded at −120 mV in 20 oocytes differing in their individual level of ZmSUT1 expression, against the corresponding charges (Q-120). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The linear fit showed a clear correlation between the two quantities (regression coefficient of 0.92), indicating that both Itr and Q depend on the total number of transporters present on the membrane of the oocyte. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, and as expected from our previous analysis (Fig. 3F), the slope of the fit was 520 s−1 very close to the reciprocal of the slow time constant shown in Fig. 3E (about 500 s−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The transport-associated currents of ZmSUT1-expressing oocytes with different levels of expression in Fig 4B were obtained by the subtraction of the currents in the absence from the currents in the presence of saturating sucrose concentration (open symbols). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The filled symbols were again calculated using the ratio Q/τ based only on parameters obtained from the presteady-state currents in the absence of sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The good agreement between the measured and predicted currents confirms that the prediction of Itr from Ipre is independent from the expression level of ZmSUT1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In this respect, the turnover rate of the transporter is about 500 s−1 at negative (physiological) voltages which was calculated from the reciprocal of the slow time constant (see Fig. 3E) or from the slope of the linear fitting of I-120mV vs Q-120mV (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Moreover we can estimate the average number of transporters from the equation: Qmax = Nezδ where Qmax is the total charge movement, N the number of transporter per oocyte, e the elementary charge and zδ was obtained by the Boltzmann analysis performed above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Considering a mean Qmax of 8 nC, N is 2×1011 transporter molecules per oocytes, a value well in line with other transporters (i.e. GAT1 [15], KAAT1 [14]) confirming the capability of the oocyte system to express foreign proteins at very high densities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In our experiments the average capacitance of oocytes was 170 nF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Using the specific capacitance of 1 µF/cm2 of biological membranes we obtain an average oocyte area of 1.7×107 µm2 and a transporter density of about 104/µm2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>If each transporter effectively covers an approximate area of 5 nm2 (Abramson, 2003), ZmSUT1 would cover about 25% of the total oocyte area. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Properties of charge movement. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>A) Relation between I-120 and Q-120 for 20 individual oocytes; the linear regression (r = 0.92) gives a slope of 520±53 nA nC−1 or s−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>C) Transported (measured, empty symbols) and predicted (filled symbols) currents plotted against voltage for two oocytes with different level of ZmSUT1 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Sucrose Affects ZmSUT1-Derived Presteady-State Currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The presteady-state currents of ZmSUT1, obtained in a similar manner as those shown in Fig. 3, appeared modulated by the external sucrose concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Application of 0.5 and 1 mM external sucrose resulted in a sucrose-dependent reduction of Ipre (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The charge associated to Ipre versus voltage decreased upon increasing the external sucrose concentration (Fig. 5B) and its derivative was in agreement with the measured capacitance (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>S1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>There was, however, no significant effect of external sucrose at concentration equal to 0.5 and 1 mM on the slow time constant (Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The relationship I = Q/τ previously used to predict the transport currents solely from the knowledge of the presteady-state currents can be written as: (1)where Isat and I0 represent the transport-associated currents in the presence and absence of saturating sucrose, Qnosuc and Qsat are the charges associated to the transient component of the transporter current in the absence and presence of the sugar and τ represents the slow time constant of the exponential fitting of Ipre. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Equation 1 can be extended to predict the ZmSUT1 response to given external sucrose concentration (X):(2)where IX and QX are respectively the stationary current and the charge associated to the transient component of the ZmSUT1 current in the presence of a sucrose concentration equal to X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>To compare the measured and the predicted transport currents the Isat – IX values, obtained from the transport-associated currents, were normalized (see Materials and Methods) and plotted as a function of voltage (open symbols, Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The filled symbols were calculated using equation 2 with parameters obtained from the experimentally recorded Ipre (for the normalization procedure see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Please note the good agreement between the experimental and predicted data over a broad voltage range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This agreement strongly suggests a similar origin of the presteady-state currents and the transport-associated currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>One might thus conclude that Ipre in the absence of sucrose reflect proton movements from an external to an inner position of the transporter and that Itr reflects the proton permeation across the membrane when sucrose is added [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Sucrose dependence of ZmSUT1 presteady-state currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>A) Presteady-state currents of a single oocyte at varying external sucrose concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>For the sake of clarity only currents recorded from +40 to –120 mV, in 40 mV step, are shown; the holding voltage was –20 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>B) Charge associated to presteady-state currents versus voltage at different sucrose concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The continuous lines are fit of Q using a Boltzmann function (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Data for each oocyte were normalized to the maximum charge obtained in the absence of external sucrose, Qmax(No suc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The fits gave the following parameters (mean±SEM, n = 4): no external sucrose: V1/2 = −65±8 mV, s = 96±5 mV; 0.5 mM sucrose: V1/2 = −123±17 mV, Qmax(suc = 0.5 mM)/Qmax(No suc) = 0.69±0.02; 1 mM sucrose V1/2 = −159±20 mV, Qmax(suc = 1 mM)/Qmax(No suc) = 0.50±0.02. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>At 0.5 and 1 mM sucrose the slope s of the fit was fixed at the value obtained at 0 external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>C) Isat – IX against the applied membrane potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Isat is the current at saturating external sucrose concentration; Ix are the currents in the presence of 0, 0.5 mM and 1 mM external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Empty and filled symbols refer to the measured and predicted currents respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The following relationship was used in order to evaluate the predicted currents: Isat – IX = QX/τ where X represents the external sucrose concentration and τ is the slow time constant at zero external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Protons Affect the Gating of ZmSUT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>When the proton concentration was reduced from pH 4 to pH 7 a strong reduction of Ipre was observed (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>To gain the voltage dependence of this process we plotted the Ipre-associated charge Q in different external pH buffers against the applied voltage (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Plotting the half activation voltage, obtained in panel B, against decreasing external proton concentration (Fig. 6C) visualized the shift of Q(V) towards negative voltages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>A linear fit from pH 7 to pH 4 resulted in a slope of 83±5 mV per pH unit (n = 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with our notion that protons generate ZmSUT1 presteady-state currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>As expected, the derivative of the charge is in line with the actually measured capacitance as shown in Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The slow time constants of Ipre at pH 5 and 4 are not significantly different (Fig. 5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In line with our experiments at pH 4, the agreement between the predicted and measured stationary currents at pH 5 were satisfactory (Fig. 6, see Materials and Methods for details). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012605-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012605.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>pH dependence of ZmSUT1 presteady-state currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>A) Presteady-state currents of a single oocyte at varying external pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Holding voltage –20 mV, voltage pulses from +40 mV to –120 mV (step –40 mV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>B) Normalized charge associated to presteady-state currents at different external pH versus voltage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>For the details of the pH analysis see Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Qmax(pH = 3)/Qmax(pH = 4) = 0.85±0.03. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Data were obtained by four different oocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>C) Half activation voltages (V1/2) obtained by data in panel B versus external pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The slope of the linear fit from pH 7 to 4 is equal to 83±5 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>D) Slow time constant τ recorded at pH 4 and 5 plotted against applied voltage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>E) Predicted (filled symbols) and measured (empty symbols) transported currents versus voltage (see Materials and Methods for details). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012605.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The capacitance (Cm) of biological membranes represents a basic electrical property. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Using the paired ramp technique [26] we could in real-time monitor changes in Cm of Xenopus oocytes over a broad range of physiological conditions such as pH-, sucrose- and membrane potentials changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The robustness of the Cm measurement technique allowed us to measure Cm even under conditions where presteady-state measurements were biased by the speed of the voltage-clamp and therefore beyond the resolution limit of the method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The Wright lab in 1996 recorded presteady-state currents of the potato H+/sucrose cotrasporter StSUT1 [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In contrast to ZmSUT1 those of StSUT1 appeared sucrose independent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In the presence of saturating extracellular sucrose steady state currents increased without affecting the transient component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Compared to water-injected oocytes, StSUT1 expressing ones exhibited a large, pH-dependent transient component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Acidification of the extracellular solution did not change both the total charge (Qmax) and the apparent valence (z) but shifted the Boltzmann curve 30 mV more negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Therefore it was not possible with the weak StSUT1 activity in oocytes to correlate the effect of the membrane voltage and the H+ concentration on presteady-state kinetics with those of transport currents (steady-state). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="?"><plain>How can this discrepancy to the situation with ZmSUT1 be explained? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The transient components in StSUT1 could reflect structural arrangements of the carrier protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>With ZmSUT1 expressing oocytes, sucrose-independent presteady-state currents were not apparent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The transient component in the presence of saturating sucrose was rather comparable to those of water injected oocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Stationary currents with StSUT1 injected oocytes were 20–50 times smaller than those obtained with ZmSUT1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The discrepancy between Zea maize and Solanum tuberosum transporter may thus reflect a problem of resolution only. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Taking advantage of the high transport activity of ZmSUT1, we could measure presteady-state currents with a shift of the associated charge by about 80 mV upon acidification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The Ipre voltage-dependence of ZmSUT1 is in agreement with the range of physiological membrane potential of the plant cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>E.g. at an extracellular pH of 5–5.5, the half-activation voltage V1/2 of Ipre is more negative than –120 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Since ZmSUT1 is capable to mediate sucrose loading as well as unloading [7], the slope of about 100 mV indicates that the H+/sucrose cotransporter might indeed operate in a wide voltage range. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The experimental analysis of the sugar and proton dependent ionic currents associated with the gating and solute movement of ZmSUT1 point to the following transport mechanism: the proton entrance into the transporter is far from the electric field (indicated by the voltage-independence of τ) and was the rate limiting step with respect to the overall transport mechanism under our specific experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>It is worth noting that this rate limiting step is not necessarily caused by the diffusion and/or binding of the protons inside ZmSUT1 but could be influenced by the accessibility of the proton binding site due to conformational changes of the transporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>As proposed by Kaback's lab (e.g. [32], [33]) for ion-coupled cotransporters, in the absence of substrate the transporter can have two main conformations for the proton binding site, respectively facing the extracellular (outward-facing) and the cytosolic side (inward-facing). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The slow time constant measured in this work could represent the transition between these two states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In the absence of sugar the proton is trapped inside the transporter and can move up to 25% of the electrical distance across the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>This voltage-dependent movement is the origin of the presteady-state currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In this case the transporter can be seen as a pure capacitor and the protons are the relative charges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>When saturating sucrose concentrations are present at the extracellular surface of ZmSUT1, the proton inside the transporter is released into the cytoplasm from the inward-facing conformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>When crossing the barrier one proton moves one sugar molecule into the cytoplasm [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Very likely this step is associated with a conformational change of the transporter [11], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>From our data we predict that the conformational change that moves the protons from the extracellular to the cytosolic side in the presence of sucrose has to be faster than 2 ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>In this scenario the transporter can be seen as a pure resistor and the protons are the charges giving rise to the electrical transport current. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Under conditions of limiting sugar in the extracellular milieu the transporter behaves like a capacitor as well as a resistor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Furthermore the relationship between presteady-state and transport-associated currents suggests that the proton entry into the electric field across ZmSUT1 is not influenced by the presence of external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>This link points to a common origin of the presteady-state and the transport-associated currents, which is underpinned by the fact that the reduction of the external H+ concentration decreased both the presteady-state and the transport-associated currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Transporters both from animal (SGLT1, PepT1, [24], [34]) and plant kingdoms (STP1, [35]) are characterized by presteady-state currents which are apparent in the absence of external substrate and disappear under substrate saturation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In GAT1 and GlyT1 transporters (respectively a sodium/chloride GABA and glycine cotransporter present in synapses of animal cells) a possible inter-conversion between the two kinds of currents was recently explored [30], [31], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents of GAT1 and GlyT1 result from the displacement of Na+ or chloride ions within the electrical field of the membrane traveling between the extracellular space and a binding site in the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Interestingly Fesce et al. (2002, [30]) and Cherubino et al. (2010, [36]) could predict transport-associated currents in the presence of GABA or glycine by analyzing presteady-state currents in the absence of substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>For these animal cotransporters it was proposed that in the absence of substrate sodium/chloride could move, with a rate-limiting speed represented by τ, from an external to an internal site of the transporter generating the presteady-state currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Upon addition of substrate the ‘trapped’ ion is able to cross the membrane with the same rate-limiting step. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Our analyses with ZmSUT1 point to a similar relationship between the transient current component and the transport-associated currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Future studies will thus need to focus on the question whether similar relationships between charge movement and transport-associated currents found in different cotransporter types have common grounds. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>An ethics statement is not required for this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>TEVC analysis in Xenopus Oocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>ZmSUT1 cRNA was prepared using the mMESSAGE mMACHINE™ RNA Transcription kit (Ambion Inc., Texas, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Oocyte preparation and cRNA injection have been described elsewhere [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In two-electrode voltage-clamp studies oocytes were perfused with a standard-solution containing 30 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl2, and 1.5 mM MgCl2 based on Tris/Mes buffers for pH values from 5.5 to 7.5 or based on citrate/Tris buffers for the pH values 3.5 to 5.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Solutions were adjusted to 220 mosmol kg−1 using D-sorbitol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Transport Current and Membrane Capacitance Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Simultaneous measurements of transport currents (Itr) and membrane capacitance (Cm) were performed using an TEC-10X amplifier (NPI Electronic, Tamm, Germany) controlled by the PULSE and X-Chart software (HEKA Electronics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Cm was measured using a previously described paired ramps approach [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Sucrose-induced proton currents and sucrose-induced capacitance changes were recorded at −20 mV while the oocytes were super-fused with different external solutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>When the bath medium was completely exchanged Cm and Itr were determined in the voltage range between +20 and −120 mV in 10 mV decrements. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Alternatively we use the method developed by Adrian and Almers (see also [14]): a small voltage step of 20 mV (ΔV) and duration of 20 ms was superimposed to a given applied voltage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The amount of moved charge ΔQ was obtained by integrating the current transient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The slope of the membrane capacitance at the applied voltage was approximated by the ratio ΔQ/ΔV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>We verified that the two methods of measuring membrane capacitance described above gave similar results (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Presteady-State Currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents were obtained using the two-electrode voltage-clamp technique (TECV) subtracting the traces at saturating sucrose concentration (typically 100 mM) and forcing the steady level at the end of each voltage pulse to zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The holding potential was maintained at –20 mV and voltage pulses of 20 ms from 60 mV to –120 mV in –10 mV steps were applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Signals were sampled at 100 kHz and filtered at 20 kHz. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The charge (Q) associated to each presteady-state currents was obtained using the following procedure: a) the charge Qexp was calculated by the integral of the presteady-state currents and fitted by the Boltzmann equation Qmax/(1+ exp[(V-V1/2)/s]) + Qi, where Qi represents the charge offset, Qmax the maximum charge, V1/2 the half-activation voltage and s is linked to the slope of the Boltzmann curve at V = V1/2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The charge Q was Qexp – Qi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The “on” charge, the charge calculated when the voltage pulse was applied, and the “off” charge, calculated when the potential was again set to the holding value, did not differ considerably (see Fig. 3D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The last part of the decay of the presteady-state currents was fitted by the two exponential function Ifast exp(−t/τfast) + Islow exp(−t/τslow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>In order to verify the reliabilty of τ, the starting time of the fit was increased in step of 50 µs; in each step the fitting procedure was applied (up to 10 steps) and τ was calculated as the average value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>When the relative error (SD/mean) of τ was greater that 10% the point was discarted; this was the case for sucrose concentrations equal to 0.5 and 1 mM at voltages more positive than –60 mV and external pH of 7, 6 and 3 (see Fig. 5 and 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>To obtain τ at the holding voltage (Vhold) a similar fitting procedure was performed on the off charge at voltages different from Vhold. τ(Vhold) was calculated as the average value of τoff(V). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The transported currents induced by sucrose were calculated as the difference of the stationary currents in the presence and the absence of sucrose respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The predicted current was obtained using the following relationship: I = Q/τ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Changes in capacitance associated with the presteady-state currents (Cp) were evaluated as the derivative of Q with respect to V and compared with the measured capacitance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Only the experiments with Cpred∼Cm were considered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s4c1"><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the sucrose dependency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>For the analysis of the sucrose dependency shown in Fig. 5 presteady-state currents at 0, 0.5 and 1 mM sucrose were obtained from the experimental currents subtracting the traces at saturating sucrose concentration and forcing the steady level to zero at the end of each voltage pulse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The integral of the presteady-state currents from a single oocyte was fitted by the Boltzmann equation shown above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>At 0.5 and 1 mM sucrose the slope s of the fit was fixed at the value obtained at 0 mM external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>QX was calculated as (Qexp(X) - Qi(X))/Qmax(0) with X equal to 0, 0.5 and 1 mM external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The predicted currents were calculated using equation 2 (see Results session) with the slow time constant obtained in the absence of external sucrose; as a matter of fact τ was not significantly affected by external sucrose concentrations of 0.5 and 1 mM (see Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The predicted and measured currents for a single oocyte were normalized at the value of (Isat- I0) evaluated at –120 mV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Data from four different oocytes were averaged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c2"><title><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the proton dependency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The sequence of external solutions perfusing the ZmSUT1-expressing oocyte was the following: 1) from pH 3 to 7 in steps of one pH unit in absence of external sucrose, 2) going to pH 4, in the absence of external sucrose and finally 3) applying saturating concentration of external sucrose at pH 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Presteady-state currents were obtained using the standard procedure after subtraction of traces recorded at pH 4 in saturating external sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The charge (Q) was obtained by the integral of the presteady-state currents and fitted by the Boltzmann function shown above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The slope s was fixed to 98 mV, the average value at pH 4 from 20 different oocytes, see text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The maximum charge, Qmax, was fixed at the values obtained at pH 4; at pH 3 Qmax was considered as a free parameter of the fit and was normalized to the value at pH 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>We used the relationship I = Q/τ, where Q and τ are the charge and the slow time constant at pH 4 and 5, to calculate I(pH = 5) i.e. the transported current at pH 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>I(pH = 5) was divided by I(pH = 4, V = −120 mV) and compared, as shown in Fig. 6E, with the stationary currents at pH 5 normalized to the value of the current at pH 4 and V = −120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Stationary currents were obtained by a different set of experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Data are given as mean±SEM together with the number, n, of different oocyte investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The TECV set-up was equipped by a home-made system to control the temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Experiments were performed at a temperature of 22.0±0.1°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012605.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The empty symbols are the capacitance measured using the method of Adrian and Almers (1976) in response to different external sucrose (A) or pH (B) conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Continuous lines were derived from the Q-V plot of Fig. 5B in (A) and of Fig. 6B in (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>(4.27 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012605.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>We are indebted with Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Antonio Peres (University of Insubria, Italy) for his availability, fruitful discussions and suggestions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Franco Conti and Dr. Michael Pusch (IBF-CNR Italy) for useful discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>We gratefully acknowledge Gregory Harms for critical reading and comments on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dfg.de/index.jsp">http://www.dfg.de/index.jsp</ext-link>) grants within SFB487 to RH and HK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>DG was supported by DFG grant GE2195/1-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>AC was supported by Italian Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche (CNR, Short-term Mobility program 2007 and 2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cnr.it/sitocnr/Englishversion/CNR/Dataandstatistics/Internationalactivities/Shorttermmobilityprogram.html">http://www.cnr.it/sitocnr/Englishversion/CNR/Dataandstatistics/Internationalactivities/Shorttermmobilityprogram.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0012605-VanBel1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>1 Van BelAJE 2003 The phloem, a miracle of ingenuity. Plant, Cell &amp; Environment 26 125 149  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Sauer1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>2 SauerN 2007 Molecular physiology of higher plant sucrose transporters. FEBS Letters 581 2309 2317 17434165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Aoki1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>3 AokiNHiroseTTakahashiSOnoKIshimaruK 1999 Molecular cloning and expression analysis of a gene for a sucrose transporter in maize (Zea mays L.). Plant Cell Physiol 40 1072 1078 10589520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Riesmeier1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>4 RiesmeierJWHirnerBFrommerWB 1993 Potato sucrose transporter expression in minor veins indicates a role in phloem loading. Plant Cell 5 1591 1598 8312741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Sauer2"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>5 SauerNStolzJ 1994 SUC1 and SUC2: two sucrose transporters from Arabidopsis thaliana; expression and characterization in baker's yeast and identification of the histidine-tagged protein. Plant J 6 67 77 7920705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Slewinski1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>6 SlewinskiTLMeeleyRBraunDM 2009 Sucrose transporter1 functions in phloem loading in maize leaves. J Exp Bot 60 881 892 19181865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Carpaneto1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>7 CarpanetoAGeigerDBambergESauerNFrommJ 2005 Phloem-localized, proton-coupled sucrose carrier ZmSUT1 mediates sucrose efflux under the control of the sucrose gradient and the proton motive force. J Biol Chem 280 21437 21443 15805107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Boorer1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>8 BoorerKJLooDDFrommerWBWrightEM 1996 Transport mechanism of the cloned potato H+/sucrose cotransporter StSUT1. J Biol Chem 271 25139 25144 8810269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>9 ZhouJTheodoulouFSauerNSandersDMillerAJ 1997 A kinetic model with ordered cytoplasmic dissociation for SUC1, an Arabidopsis H+/sucrose cotransporter expressed in Xenopus oocytes. J Membr Biol 159 113 125 9307438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Hilgemann1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>10 HilgemannDWLuCC 1999 GAT1 (GABA:Na+:Cl−) cotransport function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Database reconstruction with an alternating access model. J Gen Physiol 114 459 475 10469735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Loo1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>11 LooDDHirayamaBAGallardoEMLamJTTurkE 1998 Conformational changes couple Na+ and glucose transport. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 95 7789 7794 9636229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Parent1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>12 ParentLSupplissonSLooDDWrightEM 1992 Electrogenic properties of the cloned Na+/glucose cotransporter: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>A transport model under nonrapid equilibrium conditions. J Membr Biol 125 63 79 1294062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Su1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>13 SuAMagerSMayoSLLesterHA 1996 A multi-substrate single-file model for ion-coupled transporters. Biophys J 70 762 777 8789093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Bossi1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>14 BossiECentinaioECastagnaMGiovannardiSVincentiS 1999 Ion binding and permeation through the lepidopteran amino acid transporter KAAT1 expressed in Xenopus oocytes. J Physiol 515 Pt 3 729 742 10066900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Mager1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>15 MagerSNaeveJQuickMLabarcaCDavidsonN 1993 Steady states, charge movements, and rates for a cloned GABA transporter expressed in Xenopus oocytes. Neuron 10 177 188 7679914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Loo2"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>16 LooDDHirayamaBAChaABezanillaFWrightEM 2005 Perturbation analysis of the voltage-sensitive conformational changes of the Na+/glucose cotransporter. J Gen Physiol 125 13 36 15596535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Meinild1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>17 MeinildA-KHirayamaBAWrightEMLooDDF 2001 Fluorescence Studies of Ligand-Induced Conformational Changes of the Na+/Glucose Cotransporter. Biochemistry 41 1250 1258  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Loo3"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>18 LooDDHirayamaBAKarakossianMHMeinildAKWrightEM 2006 Conformational dynamics of hSGLT1 during Na+/glucose cotransport. J Gen Physiol 128 701 720 17130520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Armstrong1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>19 ArmstrongCM 1975 Evidence for ionic pores in excitable membranes. Biophys J 15 932 933 1182266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Birnir1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>20 BirnirBLooDDWrightEM 1991 Voltage-clamp studies of the Na+/glucose cotransporter cloned from rabbit small intestine. Pflugers Arch 418 79 85 2041729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Forster1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>21 ForsterIHernandoNBiberJMurerH 1998 The voltage dependence of a cloned mammalian renal type II Na+/Pi cotransporter (NaPi-2). J Gen Physiol 112 1 18 9649580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Keynes1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>22 KeynesRD 1994 The kinetics of voltage-gated ion channels. Q Rev Biophys 27 339 434 7540309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Klamo1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>23 KlamoEMDrewMELandfearSMKavanaughMP 1996 Kinetics and stoichiometry of a proton/myo-inositol cotransporter. J Biol Chem 271 14937 14943 8663013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Loo4"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>24 LooDDHazamaASupplissonSTurkEWrightEM 1993 Relaxation kinetics of the Na+/glucose cotransporter. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 90 5767 5771 8516326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Parent2"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>25 ParentLSupplissonSLooDDWrightEM 1992 Electrogenic properties of the cloned Na+/glucose cotransporter: I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Voltage-clamp studies. J Membr Biol 125 49 62 1542106 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Schmitt1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>26 SchmittBMKoepsellH 2002 An improved method for real-time monitoring of membrane capacitance in Xenopus laevis oocytes. Biophys J 82 1345 1357 11867451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Stuhmer1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>27 StuhmerWContiFSuzukiHWangXDNodaM 1989 Structural parts involved in activation and inactivation of the sodium channel. Nature 339 597 603 2543931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Adrian1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>28 AdrianRHAlmersW 1976 The voltage dependence of membrane capacity. J Physiol 254 317 338 1082508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Bezanilla1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>29 BezanillaF 2000 The voltage sensor in voltage-dependent ion channels. Physiol Rev 80 555 592 10747201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Fesce1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>30 FesceRGiovannardiSBindaFBossiEPeresA 2002 The relation between charge movement and transport-associated currents in the rat GABA cotransporter rGAT1. J Physiol 545 739 750 12482883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Peres1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>31 PeresAGiovannardiSBossiEFesceR 2004 Electrophysiological insights into the mechanism of ion-coupled cotransporters. News Physiol Sci 19 80 84 15016908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Kaback1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>32 KabackHRDuntenRFrillingosSVenkatesanPKwawI 2007 Site-directed alkylation and the alternating access model for LacY. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 491 494 17172438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Majumdar1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>33 MajumdarDSSmirnovaIKashoVNirEKongX 2007 Single-molecule FRET reveals sugar-induced conformational dynamics in LacY. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 12640 12645 17502603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Nussberger1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>34 NussbergerSSteelATrottiDRomeroMFBoronWF 1997 Symmetry of H+ binding to the intra- and extracellular side of the H+-coupled oligopeptide cotransporter PepT1. J Biol Chem 272 7777 7785 9065440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Boorer2"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>35 BoorerKJLooDDWrightEM 1994 Steady-state and presteady-state kinetics of the H+/hexose cotransporter (STP1) from Arabidopsis thaliana expressed in Xenopus oocytes. J Biol Chem 269 20417 20424 8051137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Cherubino1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>36 CherubinoFBossiEMisznerAGhezziCPeresA 2010 Transient currents in the glycine cotransporter GlyT1 reveal different steps in transport mechanism. J Mol Neurosci 41 243 251 19711201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012605-Becker1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>37 BeckerDDreyerIHothSReidJDBuschH 1996 Changes in voltage activation, Cs+ sensitivity, and ion permeability in H5 mutants of the plant K+ channel KAT1. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 8123 8128 8755614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
