<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.0.1//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art501.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.0.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_PARA2621 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEfx2 jpg ?><?FILEfx3 jpg ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Parasitol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Parasitol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal for Parasitology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0020-7519</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1879-0135</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2474741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0020-7519(07)00098-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2007.03.005</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Minimum requirements for ookinete to oocyst transformation in Plasmodium </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nacer</surname><given-names>Adéla M.L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinden</surname><given-names>Robert E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>Hilary</given-names></name><email>h.hurd@keele.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Centre for Applied Entomology and Parasitology, Institute for Science and Technology in Medicine, Huxley Building, Keele University, Staffordshire ST5 5BG, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Infection and Immunity Section, Department of Biological Sciences, Sir Alexander Fleming Building, Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine, Imperial College Road, London SW7 2AZ, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +44 1782 583034; fax: +44 1782 583516. <email>h.hurd@keele.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Present address: Department of Infectious &amp; Tropical Diseases, Pathology Molecular Biology Unit, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, Keppel Street, London WC1E 7HT, UK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>11-3</issue><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1232</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2007 Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Australian Society for Parasitology Inc.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>Open Access under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">CC BY 3.0</ext-link> license</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>During their passage through a mosquito vector, malaria parasites undergo several developmental transformations including that from a motile zygote, the ookinete, to a sessile oocyst that develops beneath the basal lamina of the midgut epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This transformation process is poorly understood and the oocyst is the least studied of all the stages in the malaria life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We have used an in vitro culture system to monitor morphological features associated with transformation of Plasmodium berghei ookinetes and the role of basal lamina components in this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We also describe the minimal requirements for transformation and early oocyst development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A defined sequence of events begins with the break-up of the inner surface membrane, specifically along the convex side of the ookinete, where a protrusion occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>A distinct form, the transforming ookinete or took, has been identified in vitro and also observed in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Contrary to previous suggestions, we have shown that no basal lamina components are required to trigger ookinete to oocyst transformation in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated that transformation does not occur spontaneously; it is initiated in the presence of bicarbonate added to PBS, but it is not mediated by changes in pH alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Transformation is a two-step process that is not completed unless a range of nutrients are also present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A minimal medium is defined which supports transformation and oocyst growth from 7.8 to 11.4 μm by day 5 with 84% viability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We conclude that ookinete transformation is mediated by bicarbonate and occurs in a similar manner to the differentiation of sporozoite to the hepatic stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic></kwd><kwd>Ookinete</kwd><kwd>Oocyst</kwd><kwd>Basal lamina</kwd><kwd>Laminin</kwd><kwd>In vitro</kwd><kwd>Transformation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Malaria remains a major life-threatening disease in tropical and sub-tropical parts of the world, causing 300–500 million clinical cases, over one million deaths and severe economic and social losses (Sachs and Malaney, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The causative agents of the disease, apicomplexans of the genus Plasmodium, are amongst the most studied parasites because of their devastating impact on human health and welfare. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium parasites cycle between a vertebrate host and mosquito vector, experiencing changing environmental conditions as they develop from invasive to intracellular forms in the vertebrate, and invasive, intracellular and extracellular forms in the mosquito. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Despite the importance of mosquito stages for malaria transmission, the majority of research on Plasmodium is focused upon the asexual stages that invade vertebrate erythrocytes; studies facilitated by the development, in 1976 (Trager and Jensen, 1976), of an in vitro culture technique that has rendered these stages more accessible to experimentation (Hurd et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In the mosquito, gametocytes complete their differentiation, fertilisation occurs and the zygote transforms into a motile ookinete within 24 h of having imbibed a blood meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>This extracellular ookinete migrates out of the blood bolus, traverses the midgut epithelium and transforms into a vegetative oocyst in the basal subepithelial space between the midgut epithelium and the basal lamina (BL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The young oocyst grows and undergoes sporogony, producing sporozoites that migrate to the salivary glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Experimentation with systems that substitute for conditions in the vector for a period of some 50 years finally led to the development of methods to culture all the mosquito stages of several malaria species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Species that have been successfully cultured from gametocyte to sporozoite include Plasmodium falciparum (Warburg and Schneider, 1993), Plasmodium gallinaceum (Warburg and Miller, 1992), Plasmodium berghei (Al-Olayan et al., 2002a) and Plasmodium yoelii (Porter-Kelley et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For one of these species, P. berghei, a method for the efficient production of ookinetes in vitro has been developed (Rosales-Ronquillo and Silverman, 1974; Weiss and Vanderberg, 1977) and this has provided material for detailed studies of gametogenesis, fertilisation and zygote development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated that initiation of Plasmodium gametogenesis requires specific triggers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The change in environment from a mammalian to insect host provides cues such as a drop in temperature, and a mosquito factor identified as xanthurenic acid (Nijhout and Carter, 1978; Arai et al., 2001) which can regulate gametogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These triggers, or substitutes for them, are present in the in vitro systems used to produce ookinetes (Weiss and Vanderberg, 1977; Carter et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The next critical event in the development of the sporogonic stages of Plasmodium is that of the transformation of ookinete to oocyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Our knowledge of this phase of development is minimal and the process of rounding up of the ookinete to form an oocyst had not been studied in vitro previous to this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>We have identified components of the culture system that are essential requirements to initiate and sustain the formation of young oocysts from ookinetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It had been proposed that contact with components of the BL may act as a trigger for ookinete transformation in vivo (Weathersby, 1952; Meis and Ponnudurai, 1987; Ramasamy et al., 1997; Adini and Warburg, 1999; Schneider and Shahabuddin, 2000; Dessens et al., 2003; Arrighi et al., 2005; Vlachou et al., 2006) and culture systems that allow the transformation of ookinetes to oocysts, oocyst growth and sporozoite production have included a BL substitute, Matrigel and a co-cultured cell line such as Drosophila melanogaster S2, that may also contribute molecules present in the mosquito BL (Warburg and Miller, 1992; Warburg and Schneider, 1993; Al-Olayan et al., 2002a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Matrigel, an extracellular matrix derived from Engelbreth–Holm–Swarm mouse sarcoma, is comprised of laminin (56%), collagen IV (31%), enactin (8%), heparan sulfate proteoglycans and growth factors (BD Biosciences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Several ookinete proteins, such as the surface proteins P25/P28 (Siden-Kiamos et al., 2000), secreted ookinete adhesive protein (SOAP) (Dessens et al., 2003), circumsporozoite- and TRAP-related protein (CTRP) (Dessens et al., 1999) and von Willebrand factor A domain-related-protein (WARP) (Yuda et al., 2001), that are reportedly essential for ookinete and oocyst development in vivo, have been shown to bind to BL components such as laminin and collagen (Adini and Warburg, 1999; Arrighi et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This binding could provide a signal that induces transformation, thus adding weight to the hypothesis that contact with the BL may be essential for parasite development (Dessens et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, other components of the culture system such as those present in the insect cell medium used as a substitute for haemolymph, may be essential requirements for ookinete transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In vivo, ookinete transformation is a transient and unsynchronised event but in vitro we can observe the process occurring in thousands of ookinetes at any one time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Additionally, controlled interventions that enable careful dissection of putative transformation signals can be made and the minimal nutritional/environmental requirements for sporogonic development can be assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Using ookinetes that had been obtained in vitro (Carter et al., 2003) as a starting point, we have been able to describe the process of transformation and to identify a novel transient stage that we have called a transforming ookinete or took. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated that, contrary to previous suggestions, BL components, and in particular laminin, are not required for transformation and early oocyst growth and that transformation appears to be a two-step process in which initiation is bicarbonate-dependent and complete transformation requires a range of nutrients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><label>2</label><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>All reagents were purchased from Sigma unless otherwise specified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><label>2.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Parasites and ookinete harvesting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Experiments were carried out in accordance with the UK Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986 using approved protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>CD mice were treated with phenylhydrazine 2 days prior to infection by i.p. inoculation with P. berghei (clone 259cl2 expressing green fluorescent protein (Franke-Fayard et al., 2004)) obtained from a donor mouse between the second and sixth passage from cryopreserved stock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Infected blood was collected from mice with a parasitaemia of 10–20% via cardiac puncture into a heparinised syringe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Gametocytaemic blood was passed through a pre-equilibrated, 5 ml sterile column containing 1 ml glass wool and 3 ml of Whatman CF11 cellulose powder (Beckton &amp; Dickenson) to remove white blood cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The blood was collected into T25 culture flasks with RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 24 mM sodium bicarbonate, 0.4 mM hypoxanthine, 10,000 U penicillin/10 mg streptomycin and 20% FBS in a 1:10 ratio (blood: media). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Gametocytes developed into ookinetes after 18 h of culture at 19 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Ookinetes were separated on a MidiMacs (Miltenyi Biotec, Germany) separation system as previously described (Carter et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Briefly this involved passing the blood and supplemented RPMI mixture through a pre-separation filter (to remove cellular debris and coagulated blood) and a MidiMac LS column mounted on a magnet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Ookinetes adhere to magnetised beads packed within the column and can be eluted by removing the column from the magnet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The rate of blood flow was reduced by adding a 23G needle to the base of the LS column to increase parasite contact time with the column. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Culture conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Culture conditions were as previously described (Al-Olayan et al., 2002a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Ookinetes were seeded at a density of 1 × 104 per well into 8-well LabTek chamber slides or into 48-well plates (IWAKI) and cultured in oocyst culture medium (OCM: see Table 1) unless otherwise stated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Wells were either pre-coated with Matrigel diluted 1:1 with Schneider’s Drosophila insect medium or incubation took place in non-coated chamber slides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Parasites were either co-cultured in a 10:1 ratio with D. melanogaster S2 cells (Matrigel + S2), cultured in non-coated chamber slides with S2 cells (no-coating + S2), or in non-coated slides without co-cultured cells (no-coating − S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Parasites were maintained at 19 °C for 5 days, unless otherwise stated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Media was replenished on day 3 (100 μl removed and replaced). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed with six replicate wells on two or three separate occasions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Drosophila melanogaster S2 cells were maintained in T25 culture flasks (Griener Bio-One) at 27 °C in supplemented Schneider’s insect cell culture medium (ICM) with 10% heat-inactivated insect cell culture tested FBS, penicillin (50 U/ml) and streptomycin (50 μg/ml). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Assessment of viability and transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Initially, a comparison was made between a Live/Dead viability/cytotoxicity kit (Molecular Probes) used according to the manufacturers’ instructions, and Erythrosin B (0.1% in PBS diluted 1:1 with the parasite culture medium) exclusion (Krause et al., 1984). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>No difference was detected between the results for cell viability between these tests (data not shown) and the latter test was used routinely in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Material was removed from culture wells and centrifuged at 2000g for 1 min to pellet parasites or insect cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>For parasite transformation rates, sample pellets were resuspended in 5 μl of PBS and 5 μl of Erythrosin B and mounted onto a glass slide for quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>One-hundred live parasites were counted for each condition under oil immersion, and classified according to their morphological appearance of ookinete (banana), transforming ookinete (snail-like) or oocyst (sphere with a minimum diameter of 7 μm and highly motile internal contents). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Counts were performed on triplicate samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Transformation rates were determined by counting the number of live (Erythrosin B-excluding) ookinetes present on the initial day of culture, compared with the number after transformation (disappearance of ookinetes with concomitant increase in young oocysts denotes transformation as non-transforming ookinetes remain intact for several days). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For visualisation of nuclear material, ookinetes were fixed for 10 min in 1:1 ice cold acetone:methanol, washed and then incubated with anti-P28 monoclonal antibody for 1 h at room temperature before further washing and incubation with an anti-mouse IgG antibody diluted 1:200 for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Samples were washed again then mounted in Vectashield containing DAPI (Vector Laboratories) and visualised on an inverted Lieca DM IRB fluorescence microscope (Lieca Microsystems, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium berghei samples were pelleted at 500g for 4 min 2 days post-culture and fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde in sodium cacodylate buffer (0.1 M, pH 7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Samples were post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide dispersed in 3% agar, dehydrated in graded ethyl alcohols and embedded in Spurr’s resin following standard protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Ultrathin sections, cut with a diamond knife on a Reichart “Ultracut E”, were mounted on grids and stained with uranyl acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Grids were examined with a JOEL 1230 TEM and images recorded using “analySIS” software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.5</label><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Ookinete rescue </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Ookinetes were observed to remain viable when cultured in PBS alone for up to 7 days, as determined by Erythrosin B exclusion, but did not transform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>To initiate transformation, PBS (100, 200 or 300 μl) was removed from the culture well and replaced with 100, 200 or 300 μl of full-oocyst medium on day 1, 2 or 3 of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Samples were centrifuged at 2000g for 1 min and parasite viability was assessed as above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.6</label><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Mosquito infections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Anopheles stephensi were starved for 24 h prior to bloodfeeding for 20 min on gametocytaemic CD mice infected with P. berghei (PbGFPCON clone 259cl2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The mosquitoes were thereafter maintained on a 4% glucose solution and dissected in PBS 26–27 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Midguts from infected mosquitoes were cut open and the blood meal vigorously washed out with PBS before examination under oil emersion on the inverted fluorescence microscope for the presence of tooks on the BL side of the gut. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.7</label><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Drosophila S2 cells have been reported to secrete laminin (Fessler et al., 1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To confirm secretion of laminin by our cell line, Drosophila S2 cells from a confluent flask were counted on a haemocytometer and the total volume of supernatant from the culture was measured to calculate the number of cell equivalents per 100 μl of medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Additionally, conditioned medium was collected from wells in which 1 × 105 cells were incubated for 1, 3, 5, 7 or 9 days at 19 °C in 400 μl of OCM (2.5 × 104 cells per 100 μl) to determine if laminin secretion could be detected in parasite culture conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>ELISA plates were coated with 100 μl of conditioned medium, diluted 1:50 in coating buffer (15 mM Na2CO3, 35 mM NaHCO3, pH 9.6) and serial dilutions made thereafter to 1:2000 and allowed to bind overnight at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Plates were washed, blocked and incubated with antibodies raised against the β- and γ-chains of Drosophila laminin (Kumagai et al., 1997) diluted at 1:1000 in milk/PBS/Tween. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Plates were then washed, incubated with an alkaline phosphatase (AP)-conjugated secondary antibody (Sigma) diluted 1:1000 in milk/PBS/Tween, and washed again. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The substrate, p-nitrophenylphosphate, was used for visualisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Control wells had primary antibody omitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In addition, Schneider’s medium and FBS were tested for laminin and its absence confirmed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.8</label><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Detection of laminin bound to culture plates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To establish whether laminin could bind to culture plates, making it unavailable in solution to developing parasites, culture plates were incubated for 24 h at 19 °C with 100 μg of mouse laminin in PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The plates were washed with PBS and assayed for laminin by immunofluorescence using a polyclonal anti-laminin antibody directed against all three chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Similarly, Drosophila S2 cells were cultured in OCM for 24 h, the cells were then removed, and the culture plates assayed to determine whether laminin secreted by the cells was bound to the plate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.9</label><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Minimal media </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Using sterile PBS as a base, components of OCM (Schneider’s medium, heat-inactivated FBS, lipoprotein and cholesterol, NaHCO3 and hypoxanthine) were added singularly or in combination at appropriate concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>During further medium minimisation, Albumax II (Invitrogen) was used as a replacement for FBS and Schneider’s medium was replaced by individual components in groups of (i) amino acids, (ii) inorganic salts and (iii) other components, as listed by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.10</label><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Media pH </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Full-media were used for studies on the effects of the media pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Media were adjusted by adding 5 M NaOH at room temperature before filtration (0.22 μm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>However, as pH was found to steadily rise during the culture period, 25 mM N-2-hydroxyethylpiperazine-N′-2-ethanesulfonic acid (Hepes) was also used as a buffer to maintain initial pH values of 6, 7, 8 and 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>PBS adjusted to pH 6, 7, 8 or 9 was used for comparison. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.11</label><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Culture vessels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In the absence of either Matrigel or co-cultured cells, ookinetes were observed to adhere to the surface (IWAKI Cat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>No. 3830-048); as determined by no movement upon gentle agitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>To eliminate possible cues received from adhesion, ookinetes were seeded into non-treated IWAKI multiwell plates (Cat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>No. 1830-048) at the same density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>To remove potential transformation cues received from mutual adhesion, ookinetes were placed one per well in treated and non-treated plates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>2.12</label><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Data were analysed using Minitab version 14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The Anderson-Darling and Bartlett’s test were used to test for normal distribution and equality of variance, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Data from repeat experiments were compared using a General Linear Model and, if not significantly different, pooled, tested for normality and equality of variance and analysed using the General Linear Model to compare transformation rates, growth and viability across conditions and across time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><label>3</label><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><label>3.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Markers for viability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A major constraint in characterising the process of transformation has been to demonstrate conclusively that an ookinete has undergone differentiation to become an oocyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Using P. berghei (PbGFPCON clone 259cl2) that constitutively expresses green fluorescent protein (GFP), we have observed that GFP expression, although becoming faint, often persists in parasites permeable to Erythrosin B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>GFP expression was therefore deemed a less reliable viability indicator in our culture system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Viability of ookinetes at the outset typically ranged from 80% to 90%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Parasites continued to exclude the vital dye Erythrosin B after rounding up to form oocysts, thus supporting the view that the changing morphology that we observe during transformation is not associated with dying ookinetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Markers for transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>A P. berghei ookinete transforms from a banana-like shape, approximately 10 μm in length, to become a spherical young oocyst with a diameter of 7–8 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In an attempt to find mRNA markers that would help to identify a newly transformed oocyst and distinguish it from other parasite stages that may be present in the culture, we looked at the following well-characterised housekeeping or putative ookinete/early oocyst-specific molecules for signs of changes in transcription: CTRP, WARP, sporozoite microneme protein essential for cell traversal (SPECT), Myosin A, hypoxanthine–guanine phosphorybosyltransferase (HGPRT), scavenger receptor, P28, RNA S and circumsporozoite protein (CSP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, none of these were suitable as no change in transcript abundance occurred during the transformation process or in the early oocyst (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We were therefore unable to positively identify the presence of early oocyst-specific features by PCR analysis and assessment has relied on morphological observations and the demonstration of growth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Morphological and ultra-structural description of transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The in vitro transformation of P. berghei ookinetes to young oocysts follows a precise morphological pattern, distinct from that of zygote through retort to ookinete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Whereas immature ookinetes form via an extension from a spherical zygote, projecting from just one region (Sinden et al., 1985, 1987), fully mature, banana-shaped ookinetes progress to oocysts by rounding up via the formation of a protrusion in the middle of the ookinete that always originates on the outer convex edge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We have identified this phase as a transforming ookinete (took) (see Fig. 1A–C and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The nucleus is in the hump, the two-tail ends of the ookinete are still visible in late tooks (Fig. 1B and D) and DAPI-positive material appears to increase in size when in the newly forming oocyst (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We regarded fully rounded tooks as having completed transformation to an early oocyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Within each culture, the process of transformation of mature ookinetes to oocysts is asynchronous but all viable ookinetes have become oocysts in 24–48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Ookinetes that have permeable membranes do not complete transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium berghei (PbGFPCON) tooks have also been observed in vivo on mosquito midguts 28 h post-feeding on gametocytaemic blood (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>At the ultra-structural level, in vitro, the single plasmalemma of the newly forming oocyst can be distinguished from the triple membrane of the ookinete pellicle and microtubules are no longer visible in this area (Fig. 2B–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A distinct junction between the ookinete pellicle and the single plasmalemma can be seen (Fig. 2D and E) and the nucleus can be observed in the hump of the took (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The role of basal lamina components and co-cultured cells in ookinete to oocyst transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Following incubation of gametocytaemic blood for 18 h, cultures were enriched for ookinetes; however, they still contained asexual stage parasites, gametocytes and zygotes in the process of transforming into ookinetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The proportion of ookinetes in the total parasite population decreased from ∼25% on day 0 to ∼3% on day 1 and less than 1% on day 2 post-culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>No tooks were present on day 0 but they represented approximately 10% of the total fluorescing parasites when viewed on days 1 and 2, and a concomitant increase in diameter of spherical parasites from approximately 7 to 8 μm occurred from day 1 to day 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As development can only proceed in one direction, these spheres were regarded as newly transformed oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Over 90% of the ookinetes cultured with Drosophila S2 cells in the presence of the basal lamina substitute, Matrigel, transformed into young oocysts (termed maximal transformation rate) over a 1 to 2 day period and underwent some growth in diameter by day 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Two potential sources of BL components had been identified; namely Matrigel and the Drosophila S2 cells, which have been reported to produce basal lamina components such as laminin (Fessler et al., 1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In our hands, S2 cells secreted the β- and γ-chains of laminin into supplemented Schneider’s medium (Fig. 3A) and laminin was detected at levels more than twofold above background from 200 cell equivalents from a confluent flask of Drosophila S2 cells (Fig. 3B), thus confirming that the cell line used can secrete laminin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, when cells were cultured with OCM no laminin was detectable in the medium or bound to the culture plate (IFAT) on days 1–9 post-culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Taken together these results suggest that laminin is not secreted in detectable amounts by the Drosophila S2 cells in our in vitro culture conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Upon removal of Matrigel or Matrigel and Drosophila S2 cells from the cultures, no significant difference was detected in the percentage of transformed parasites between culture conditions (with and without cells or Matrigel) (ANOVA, F(2,2) = 0.90, P = 0.422) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This suggests that transformation cues/triggers, if required, are not provided by the BL-like substitute Matrigel or the co-cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Thus, BL components such as laminin do not initiate transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Transforming ookinetes often clump together and sink to the bottom of the culture wells, thus physical contact with other parasites or a solid surface may be required for transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis was not upheld as parasites cultured in culture plates treated to become hydrophilic or non-treated plates and parasites maintained singly or at various densities still transformed into oocysts by day 2 of culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.5</label><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="?"><plain>Is an extrinsic trigger required for transformation? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Following removal of both BL and co-cultured cells, we sought to determine whether ookinetes would transform into oocysts spontaneously, without any added trigger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>PBS alone did not support transformation, therefore precluding time-dependent transformation in these minimal conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Viable ookinetes could be maintained in PBS for up to 7 days (e.g. viability on day 1, 84%; day 3, 65% and day 6, 5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Removal of 100, 200 or 300 μl of the PBS and replacement with the same quantity of OCM stimulated transformation in a time and volume dependent manner (see Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>If still viable, ookinetes could be induced to transform up to 3 days post-PBS culture, thus suggesting that the transformation process will not be supported unless appropriate cues are received by the parasite, and that these cues are present in OCM in limiting amounts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.6</label><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Minimal requirements for ookinete to oocyst transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The addition of single OCM components to PBS had varying effects on parasite development (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Notably, sodium bicarbonate (23.8 mM) alone supported transformation of ookinetes to live tooks, but parasites failed to complete the entire rounding-up process to form young oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In contrast, a 0.2% lipid/cholesterol component was toxic to ookinetes, killing approximately 25% within 4 h of culture and all ookinetes within 24 h, and although a tenth of the concentration was not toxic, it did not stimulate transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The addition of combinations of heat-inactivated FBS (HI FBS) and sodium bicarbonate or Schneider’s medium and sodium bicarbonate to PBS permitted complete transformation at maximal rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, the latter combination resulted in the appearance of a white precipitate, obscuring views of ookinetes and leading to the death of parasites within 2–3 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Transformation also occurred when sodium bicarbonate was replaced with sodium carbonate, although a precipitate was again formed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Growth of viable oocysts proceeded for 5 days in PBS containing 15% HI FBS and 23.8 mM sodium bicarbonate (minimal media) The mean diameter of young oocysts increased from 7 to 8 μm on day 1 post-culture to 11–12 μm on day 5 (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>However, maintaining the parasites in minimal media did not permit complete sporogonic development and oocysts were no longer viable after 7 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>As serum is notoriously difficult to define, we substituted 15% FBS in PBS with 15% Albumax, but this failed to support transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>We therefore tried to identify groups of components of Schneider’s medium (e.g. amino acids, salts, sugars or yeast) that alone might sustain development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>None of these groups permitted oocyst development, however partial transformation did occur in the inorganic salts group (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that, whilst bicarbonate alone may initiate transformation, complete transformation requires a combination of essential nutrients and thus transformation may be a two-stage process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><label>3.7</label><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Media pH and transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>As the pH of bicarbonate buffers is strongly influenced by pCO2 and hence sodium bicarbonate concentration, we adjusted the pH of OCM to establish if this alone was critical for transformation (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>A high pH (9.0) greatly accelerated the rate of transformation; which began within 4 h of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, at pH 9.0, GFP fluorescence was less intense and oocyst plasma membrane breakdown occurred from day 2 post-culture, after oocysts had attained diameters of 10–15 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Low pH (6.0) severely impaired oocyst growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Transformation was maximal at pH 7 and 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><label>4</label><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Using our in vitro system, we have been able to observe many thousands of ookinetes undergo transformation to young oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Our observations of tooks in vivo have been far less frequent, as only a few of an invading population will be transforming at any one time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, it is clear that this method of transformation certainly occurs in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It would appear that the break-up of the inner surface membrane of the ookinete begins specifically along the convex side of the ookinete and spreads from this point, and there is likely to be an increase in the surface area of the single plasmalemma during this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We were unable to detect remnants of the inner surface membrane in areas where a single plasmalemma was visible and the apical complex did not appear to undergo immediate de-differentiation (Canning and Sinden, 1973) but persisted until late into the took phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The process of transformation thus appears to be similar to that of the sporozoite to the exoerythrocytic stage in the hepatocyte (Meis et al., 1983). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Ookinete to oocyst transformation represents one of the most severe bottlenecks for the malaria parasite, often reducing ookinete numbers to single digits (Dimopoulos et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Culturing the mosquito stages of the rodent malaria parasite in vitro, in the absence of the unfavorable conditions generated in the blood meal bolus and by the insects’ innate defence system, permits transformation of the majority of live ookinetes to the oocyst stage and thereby suggests that most parasites have the potential to develop rather than undergoing apoptosis as they do in the midgut lumen (Al-Olayan et al., 2002b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The investigations reported here suggest that this transformation is not internally controlled but that specific external compounds are required to stimulate this process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Some authors have made observations that suggest that the BL provides the necessary cues for oocyst transformation (Adini and Warburg, 1999; Arrighi et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>For example, when gametocytes are injected directly into the haemocoel, ectopic oocysts develop attached to the BL surrounding tissues such as the fat body and Malpighian tubules (Weathersby, 1954; Beaudoin et al., 1974). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>For these reasons, many culture protocols have employed a BL substitute (Matrigel) and it has been proposed that interactions between ookinete surface or microneme proteins and the mosquito BL play some role in oocyst development (for review see Siden-Kiamos and Louis, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Here, we demonstrate conclusively that ookinetes will transform in the absence of any source of BL components such as laminin or collagen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Additionally, adhesion to a solid substrate or other cells is not required to trigger transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This may indicate that ookinete transformation is driven by soluble factors derived from the haemolymph. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Developing below the BL, in the subepithelial space, ookinetes and oocysts are bathed in haemolymph components, although direct contact with haemocytes is unlikely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Haemolymph from infected or non-infected A. stephensi mosquitoes has been recorded to have a pH ranging from 6.5 to 6.8 (Mack and Vanderberg, 1978). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Whilst our in vitro investigation indicates that maximal initiation of ookinete to oocyst transformation and subsequent growth occurs within a pH range of 7–8 we did not examine events at pHs between 6 and 7, leaving the possibility that a pH in this range may be more favourable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>With the addition of sodium bicarbonate alone, ookinetes proceed to early stages of transformation as indicated by a change in shape, but do not complete development to young oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>It would appear that sodium bicarbonate is important for transformation and we suggest it may be a requirement for the first part of a two-step process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Following took formation, nutrients such as amino acids and sugars are needed for transformation to be completed and some growth to occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>These findings appear to reflect those reported in an investigation of triggers for in vitro exflagellation in P. berghei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Exflagellation could be stimulated in an extracellular bicarbonate concentration of 28 mM, whereas variation of the pH from 7.2 to 8.6 in a solution depleted of bicarbonate did not, alone, provide the stimulus (Claudianos et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The requirement for a range of nutrients for the second step of transformation suggests metabolite stores are severely limited in the ookinete and insufficient to sustain the immediate morphological changes that occur during complete transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the majority of parasites that infect mosquitoes, both Hepatozoon caiman (Lainson et al., 2003) and Plasmodium spp. develop underneath the BL on the midgut of their respective vectors, namely Culex fatigans and Anopheles spp., and do not enter the haemocoel immediately after exiting the gut lumen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This suggests that there may be an advantage to be gained by developing in this site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Recently, using double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) gene silencing technology, Arrighi et al. (2005) demonstrated that depletion of mosquito laminin led to a substantial decrease in oocyst numbers and suggested that the presence and integrity of the BL is vital for parasite development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>So far, its role has not been elucidated but it may be of importance in vivo but not in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The proposal that interactions between mosquito laminin and molecules in the oocyst capsule may result in the masking of the oocyst from the mosquito’s immune system, thereby protecting the developing oocyst from being melanised, has been recently supported by findings of Warburg et al. (2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>They demonstrated that beads coated in laminin or the ookinete surface protein P28 are protected from melanisation when injected into the mosquito haemocoel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It would be useful investigate this hypothesis further using a refractory, melanizing, strain of mosquito. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we believe we present the first description of an intermediary form between ookinete and oocyst, namely the took. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Transformation of P. berghei ookinetes to young oocysts in vitro is not a simple time-dependent phenomenon; it requires a precise environmental stimulus, but not one provided by basal lamina components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The first stage of transformation is bicarbonate dependent, yet full transformation also requires nutrients and a suitable pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Minimal requirements for transformation have been reduced in this culture system to 15% HI FBS and 23.8 mM sodium bicarbonate adjusted to pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>These findings advance our understanding of the least studied phase of malaria parasites, that of the oocyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>They demonstrate the benefit that an in vitro system can bring to investigations of the biology of the mosquito stages of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In addition, re-evaluation of the potential for attenuated sporozoite-based malaria vaccines (Good, 2005; Waters et al., 2005) has brought to the forefront the need for competent systems to culture sporogonic stages of the life cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>AdiniA.WarburgA.Interaction of Plasmodium gallinaceum ookinetes and oocysts with extracellular matrix proteinsParasitology1999199933133610581609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Al-OlayanE.M.BeetsmaA.L.ButcherG.A.SindenR.E.HurdH.Complete development of mosquito phases of the malaria parasite in vitroScience295200267767911809973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Al-OlayanE.M.WilliamsG.T.HurdH.Apoptosis in the malaria protozoan, Plasmodium berghei: a possible mechanism for limiting intensity of infection in the mosquitoInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.3220021133114312117496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>AraiM.BillkerO.MorrisH.R.PanicoM.DelcroixM.DixonD.LeyS.V.SindenR.E.Both mosquito-derived xanthurenic acid and a host blood-derived factor regulate gametogenesis of Plasmodium in the midgut of the mosquitoMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.1162001172411463462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>ArrighiR.B.LycettG.MahairakiV.Siden-KiamosI.LouisC.Laminin and the malaria parasite’s journey through the mosquito midgutJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Biol.20820052497250215961736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>BeaudoinR.L.StromeC.P.TubergenT.A.Plasmodium berghei berghei: ectopic development of the ANKA strain in Anopheles stephensiExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.3619741892014606913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>CanningE.U.SindenR.E.The organization of the ookinete and observations on nuclear division in oocysts of Plasmodium bergheiParasitology67197329404579580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>CarterV.CableH.C.UnderhillB.A.WilliamsJ.HurdH.Isolation of Plasmodium berghei ookinetes in culture using Nycodenz density gradient columns and magnetic isolationMalar J.220033514613512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>ClaudianosC.DessensJ.T.TruemanH.E.AraiM.MendozaJ.ButcherG.A.CromptonT.SindenR.E.A malaria scavenger receptor-like protein essential for parasite developmentMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.4520021473148412354219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>DessensJ.T.BeetsmaA.L.DimopoulosG.WengelnikK.CrisantiA.KafatosF.C.SindenR.E.CTRP is essential for mosquito infection by malaria ookinetesEMBO J.1819996221622710562534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>DessensJ.T.Siden-KiamosI.MendozaJ.MahairakiV.KhaterE.VlachouD.XuX.J.KafatosF.C.LouisC.DimopoulosG.SindenR.E.SOAP, a novel malaria ookinete protein involved in mosquito midgut invasion and oocyst developmentMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.49200331932912828632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>DimopoulosG.ChristophidesG.K.MeisterS.SchultzJ.WhiteK.P.Barillas-MuryC.KafatosF.C.Genome expression analysis of Anopheles gambiae: responses to injury, bacterial challenge, and malaria infectionProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>USA9920028814881912077297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>FesslerL.I.CampbellA.G.DuncanK.G.FesslerJ.H.Drosophila laminin: characterization and localizationJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol.1051987238323913119602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Franke-FayardB.TruemanH.RamesarJ.MendozaJ.van der KeurM.van der LindenR.SindenR.E.WatersA.P.JanseC.J.A Plasmodium berghei reference line that constitutively expresses GFP at a high level throughout the complete life cycleMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.1372004233315279948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>GoodM.F.Vaccine-induced immunity to malaria parasites and the need for novel strategiesTrends Parasitol.212005293415639738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>HurdH.Al-OlayanE.M.ButcherG.A.In vitro methods for culturing vertebrate and mosquito stages of PlasmodiumMicrobes Infect.5200332132712706445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>KrauseA.W.CarleyW.W.WebbW.W.Fluorescent erythrosin B is preferable to trypan blue as a vital exclusion dye for mammalian cells in monolayer cultureJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Histochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Cytochem.321984108410906090533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>KumagaiC.KadowakiT.KitagawaY.Disulfide-bonding between Drosophila laminin beta and gamma chains is essential for alpha chain to form alpha betagamma trimerFEBS Lett.41219972112169257722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>LainsonR.PapernaI.NaiffR.D.Development of Hepatozoon caimani (Carini, 1909) Pess a, De Biasi &amp; De Souza, 1972 in the Caiman Caiman C. crocodilus, the frog Rana catesbeiana and the mosquito Culex fatigansMem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Inst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Oswaldo Cruz98200310311312700868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>MackS.R.VanderbergJ.P.Hemolymph of Anopheles stephensi from noninfected and Plasmodium berghei-infected mosquitoes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Collection procedure and physical characteristicsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.64197891892331425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>MeisJ.F.PonnuduraiT.Ultrastructural studies on the interaction of Plasmodium falciparum ookinetes with the midgut epithelium of Anopheles stephensi mosquitoesParasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Res.7319875005063321042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>MeisJ.F.VerhaveJ.P.JapP.H.SindenR.E.MeuwissenJ.H.Malaria parasites – discovery of the early liver formNature30219834244266339945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>NijhoutM.M.CarterR.Gamete development in malaria parasites: bicarbonate-dependent stimulation by pH in vitroParasitology761978395323512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Porter-KelleyJ.M.DinglasanR.R.AlamU.NdetaG.A.SacciJ.B.Jr.AzadA.F.Plasmodium yoelii: axenic development of the parasite mosquito stagesExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.11220069910816289466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>RamasamyM.S.KulasekeraR.WanniarachchiI.C.SrikrishnarajK.A.RamasamyR.Interactions of human malaria parasites, Plasmodium vivax and P. falciparum, with the midgut of Anopheles mosquitoesMed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Entomol.1119972902969330262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Rosales-RonquilloM.C.SilvermanP.H.In vitro ookinete development of the rodent malarial parasite, Plasmodium bergheiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.6019748198244610107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>SachsJ.MalaneyP.The economic and social burden of malariaNature415200268068511832956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>SchneiderD.ShahabuddinM.Malaria parasite development in a Drosophila modelScience28820002376237910875925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Siden-KiamosI.LouisC.Interactions between malaria parasites and their mosquito hosts in the midgutInsect Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Biol.34200467968515242709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Siden-KiamosI.VlachouD.MargosG.BeetsmaA.WatersA.P.SindenR.E.LouisC.Distinct roles for pbs21 and pbs25 in the in vitro ookinete to oocyst transformation of Plasmodium bergheiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Cell Sci.113Pt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>1920003419342610984433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>SindenR.E.HartleyR.H.WingerL.The development of Plasmodium ookinetes in vitro: an ultrastructural study including a description of meiotic divisionParasitology91Pt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>219852272443906519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>SindenR.E.WingerL.CarterE.H.HartleyR.H.TirawanchaiN.DaviesC.S.MooreJ.SluitersJ.F.Ookinete antigens of Plasmodium berghei: a light and electron-microscope immunogold study of expression of the 21 kDa determinant recognized by a transmission-blocking antibodyProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Roy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Sci.23019874434582440053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>TragerW.JensenJ.B.Human malaria parasites in continuous cultureScience1931976673675781840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>VlachouD.SchlegelmilchT.RunnE.MendesA.KafatosF.C.The developmental migration of Plasmodium in mosquitoesCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Dev.16200638439116793259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>WarburgA.MillerL.H.Sporogonic development of a malaria parasite in vitroScience25519924484501734521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>WarburgA.SchneiderI.In vitro culture of the mosquito stages of Plasmodium falciparumExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.7619931211268454020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>WarburgA.ShrernA.CohenN.DahanN.Laminin and a Plasmodium ookinete surface protein inhibit melanotic encapsulation of sephadex beads in the hemacoel of mosquitoesMicrobes Infect.9200719219917224290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>WatersA.P.MotaM.M.van DijkM.R.JanseC.J.Parasitology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Malaria vaccines: back to the future?Science307200552853015681372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>WeathersbyA.B.The role of the stomach wall in the exogenous development of Plasmodium gallinaceum as studies by means of haemocoel injections of susceptible and refractory mosquitoesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Dis.91195219820512981280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>WeathersbyA.B.The ectopic development of malarial oocystsExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.3195453854313210371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>WeissM.M.VanderbergJ.P.Studies on Plasmodium ookinetes: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>In vitro formation of Plasmodium berghei ookinetesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.63197793293421234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>YudaM.YanoK.TsuboiT.ToriiM.ChinzeiY.von Willebrand Factor A Domain-related Protein, a novel microneme protein of the malaria ookinete highly conserved throughout the Plasmodium parasitesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Biochem.l Parasitol.11620016572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>We are grateful for the kind gifts of P. berghei clone 259cl2 from Andy Waters, for Drosophila anti-laminin antibodies from Yasuo Kitagawa and for polyclonal anti-laminin antibodies from Charles Strueli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>We also thank Karen Walker for assistance with electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Funding for this project was provided by The Wellcome Trust (069128/Z/02/Z and 069162/Z/02/Z). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>We thank them for their support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Formation of young Plasmodium berghei oocysts in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>(A–C) P28 (surface) and DAPI (nuclear) staining of ookinetes (A), tooks (B) and young oocysts (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>(D) PbGFPCON tooks during late transformation in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>(E) PbGFPCON early transforming ookinetes in Anopheles stephensi midguts 27 h post-blood feeding (composite of three images). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(F) Image adapted from Sinden et al. (1987) (i–iv) to incorporate ookinete to oocyst transformation (v–vii). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Transformation begins with a small hump forming on the outer, convex, edge of the ookinete, often towards the apical end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Transforming ookinetes (tooks) then take on a snail-like appearance (v) and the nucleus is observed to move into the developing oocyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Remnants of the ookinete tips are clearly visible (distinguishing these forms from zygotes; (vi) just prior to the formation of spherical young oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The entire population of ookinetes transform in 12–36 h, depending on nutrient availability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>TEM images of an ookinete (A), and tooks (B–F) in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>(A) Ookinete, with nucleus (N), pellicle (P) and apical complex (AC) visible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>(B) Early took: the AC is still clearly visible as are the microtubules (MT) and the beginning of the early oocyst wall, forming a hump on the outer ookinete edge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Membrane generated during this process differs from the ookinete pellicle (single arrow), and forms the basis of the oocyst wall (OW). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>(C) Early took: nuclear material can be seen to have moved into the newly formed area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Double and single membranes define the new OW and ookinete pellicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Broken arrows indicate the transition areas from double to newly formed single membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>(D and E) Mid-stage tooks showing microtubules below the remaining pellicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>(F) Late took: remnants of the ookinete tips with double membranes can be seen at either end of the forming oocyst: scale bar: A–C, 2 μm; D–F, 1 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Production of laminin by Drosophila melanogaster S2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured at 27 °C in Schneider’s Insect Cell Medium supplemented with FBS and Pen/Strep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>(A) Western blot to visualise laminin secreted into the medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The supernatant from a confluent flask was subjected to SDS–PAGE and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The blots were probed with anti-D. melanogaster laminin-1 (β- and γ-chains) polyclonal antibodies (lane 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Molecular markers are shown on the right (lane 2) and the corresponding molecular weight labelled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>(B) Laminin secretion by S2 cells was determined by ELISA and readings are expressed as cell equivalents per 100 μl of medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Error bars = SEM and n = 3 wells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Maximal ookinete to oocyst transformation rates 24-h post-culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Transformation rates were assessed by counting the number of parasites out of 100 that had changed from ookinete shape to young oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>No significant difference (ANOVA, F(2,2) = 0.90, P = 0.422) was observed between full-culture conditions, culture without Matrigel and culture without Matrigel and Drosophila S2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Bars represent SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>The experiment was repeated three times and parasites counted in three separate wells for each condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Components of full-oocyst medium (OCM) per 100 ml </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Oocyst medium component </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Final concentration/100 ml </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Sodium bicarbonate (mM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>23.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Hypoxanthine (mM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>3.68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Penicillin (U)/streptomycin (mg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>10,000; 10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Gentamicin (mg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Para-aminobenzoic acid (μM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>44 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Foetal bovine serum (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Lipid/cholesterol (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>0.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Schneider’s medium (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Media were adjusted to pH 7 prior to filtration.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Transformation of ookinetes to oocysts maintained in PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Oocyst medium added </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Day 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Day 4 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Day 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>400 μl added day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>   </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>100 μl added day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>100 μl added day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>100 μl added day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>   </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>200 μl added day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>200 μl added day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>200 μl added day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>   </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>300 μl added day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>300 μl added day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>300 μl added day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Ookinetes were incubated in 400 μl of PBS which was then replaced with oocyst medium as indicated. A dose-dependent response was seen in the amount and speed of transformation. Data from ookinetes cultured in 400 μl of oocyst medium from the day of culture are displayed for comparison. Samples were taken from three independent experiments and media was replaced on day 3.</p><p>–, no transformation; ✓, partial transformation (tooks); ✓✓, complete transformation of the majority of ookinetes to oocysts.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Minimal requirements for triggering ookinete to oocyst transformation in PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Oocyst medium component </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Day 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Full-media </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>PBS alone </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>PBS + hypoxanthine </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>PBS + PABA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>PBS + lipids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>× </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>× </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>× </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>PBS + sodium bicarbonate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>PBS + Schneider’s medium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>PBS + HI FBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>PBS + Schneider’s + sodium bicarbonate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>PBS + HI FBS + sodium bicarbonate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Stages of transformation (compared with full-media) were assessed on days 0, 1, 2 and 3 post-culture when single and dual components of oocyst medium were added to PBS (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for concentrations). Samples were observed from three independent experiments.</p><p>–, no transformation; ✓, partial transformation (tooks); ✓✓, complete transformation to oocyst; ×, death of parasites.</p><p>HI FBS, heat-inactivated FBS; PABA, <italic>para</italic>-aminobenzoic acid.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float" orientation="landscape"><?landscape?><?legal?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Growth and viability of Plasmodium berghei oocysts over a 5 day period of culture in minimal media </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Time post-culture </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Day 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Day 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Viability (n = 100) (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Mean oocyst size (n = 100) (μm) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>7.80 ± 0.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>9.51 ± 0.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>11.36 ± 0.15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>   </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Example of oocyst </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Parasites were cultured in PBS containing 15% HI FBS and 23.8 mM sodium bicarbonate. One-hundred viable-oocyst diameters were measured each day, observed under phase contrast. Sizes are expressed as means ± SEM.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>Effects of pH on transformation rates </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>pH </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Day 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Day 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Day 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>Day 4 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Day 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Full-media </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>✓✓ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>× </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>× </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>   </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="char"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Hepes (25 mM) was added to full-oocyst medium to retain the appropriate pH. PBS alone, irrespective of pH, does not permit ookinete to oocyst transformation. Full-oocyst media permits transformation at a wide pH range, but is inefficient or toxic at low and high pH’s, respectively.</p><p>–, no transformation; ✓, partial morphological transformation; ✓✓, complete transformation to oocyst; ×, death of parasites.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
