<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Cell Fact</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Cell Factories</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2859</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2806293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1475-2859-8-68</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20028556</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2859-8-68</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Scale-up from microtiter plate to laboratory fermenter: evaluation by online monitoring techniques of growth and protein expression in Escherichia coli and Hansenula polymorpha fermentations </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Kensy</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>kensy@m2p-labs.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Engelbrecht</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>christoph_engelbrecht@yahoo.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A3"><name><surname>Büchs</surname><given-names>Jochen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Jochen.Buechs@avt.rwth-aachen.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>AVT-Biochemical Engineering, RWTH Aachen University, Sammelbau Biologie, Worringerweg 1, 52074 Aachen, Germany</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>m2p-labs GmbH, Forckenbeckstraße 6, 52074 Aachen, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2009 Kensy et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kensy et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/8/1/68"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In the past decade, an enormous number of new bioprocesses have evolved in the biotechnology industry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>These bioprocesses have to be developed fast and at a maximum productivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Up to now, only few microbioreactors were developed to fulfill these demands and to facilitate sample processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>One predominant reaction platform is the shaken microtiter plate (MTP), which provides high-throughput at minimal expenses in time, money and work effort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>By taking advantage of this simple and efficient microbioreactor array, a new online monitoring technique for biomass and fluorescence, called BioLector, has been recently developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The combination of high-throughput and high information content makes the BioLector a very powerful tool in bioprocess development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the scalabilty of results from the micro-scale to laboratory or even larger scales is very important for short development times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Therefore, engineering parameters regarding the reactor design and its operation conditions play an important role even on a micro-scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the scale-up from a microtiter plate scale (200 μL) to a stirred tank fermenter scale (1.4 L), two standard microbial expression systems, Escherichia coli and Hansenula polymorpha, were fermented in parallel at both scales and compared with regard to the biomass and protein formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Volumetric mass transfer coefficients (kLa) ranging from 100 to 350 1/h were obtained in 96-well microtiter plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Even with a suboptimal mass transfer condition in the microtiter plate compared to the stirred tank fermenter (kLa = 370-600 1/h), identical growth and protein expression kinetics were attained in bacteria and yeast fermentations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The bioprocess kinetics were evaluated by optical online measurements of biomass and protein concentrations exhibiting the same fermentation times and maximum signal deviations below 10% between the scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In the experiments, the widely applied green fluorescent protein (GFP) served as an online reporter of protein expression for both strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The successful 7000-fold scale-up from a shaken microtiter plate to a stirred tank fermenter was demonstrated in parallel fermentations for standard microbial expression systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This confirms that the very economical and time efficient platform of microtiter plates can be very easily scaled up to larger stirred tank fermenters under defined engineering conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>New online monitoring techniques for microtiter plates, such as the BioLector, provide even more real-time kinetic data from fermentations than ever before and at an affordable price. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This paves the way for a better understanding of the bioprocess and a more rational process design. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Industrial bioprocesses mainly involve microbial or mammalian fermentations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>To develop a productive bioprocess, it is necessary to screen a vast number of different clones and media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Moreover, for industry, it is crucial to develop the bioprocess as fast as possible to reduce time to market. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, companies are pressured by regulatory authorities (e.g. FDA, EMEA) to substantiate the actual knowledge of the process applied [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The Process Analytical Technology Initiative (PAT) by the FDA is one of the major programs to improve process understanding, and, therefore, the quality of pharmaceutical products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Consequently, in recent years high-throughput technologies have become well-established in research laboratories to perform high-throughput experimentation and to gain more insights into bioprocesses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Microtiter plates (MTPs) play the predominant role as the microbioreactor of choice for high-throughput screening applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>They are applied for drug discovery, cell cultivation, enzymatic assays and immunoassays [3-7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This microbioreactor platform is mainly used as a batch reactor, and the experimental results are very often simply evaluated by endpoint analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The application of MTPs under shaken conditions can further improve mixing and mass transfer conditions in cultivations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Recognizing the great potential of MTPs as a serious reaction platform, some groups have started to characterize engineering parameters in these formats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Besides the mixing time, the oxygen transfer capacity (OTRmax) and the volumetric mass transfer coefficient (kLa) are generally characterized [4,8-11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In order to better exploit the results of MTP experiments, it is important to precisely ascertain the scalability of MTPs to standard laboratory fermenters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Only if the microbioreactor performs identically to laboratory stirred tank fermenters (STF), it is possible to scale-up the data generated in high-throughput screenings and, thus, speed up the development timeline. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Micheletti et al. [12] and Islam et al. [13] compared microbial and mammalian fermentations as well as biotransformations in MTPs with those in a STF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The kLa-value hereby emerged as one of the key scale-up factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Using matched kLa-values, they obtained comparable results at both the MTP and STF scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Their research could be considered as the starting point of the scale-up from MTP to STF fermentations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This research, however, was based on laborious and error-prone sampling methods from the different reactor scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In general, MTPs are recognized as being inexpensive, highly standardized and easy to handle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, MTPs would be an ideal platform for all tasks in fermentation science and bioprocess development if sampling and process data acquisition were easier to automate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Thus, Samorski et al. [14] introduced a new online monitoring technique for continuously shaken microtiter plates which was further advanced and validated by Kensy et al. [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>This technique, called BioLector, was able to resolve this lack of online information from MTPs and facilitated the processing of high-throughput fermentations; it now provides all relevant fermentation parameters online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study is to elaborate a scale-up methodology from microtiter plate to stirred tank fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The validation of the performed microbial fermentations was based on defined mass transfer conditions and online monitoring signals of biomass and protein concentrations at both reactor scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Parallel fermentations of standard microbial expression systems such as the bacteria Escherichia coli and the yeast Hansenula polymorpha were performed in MTP with 200 μL and STF with 1.4 L scale and compared with each other. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Microorganisms and Media </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Standard microbial expressions systems, the bacteria Escherichia coli and the yeast Hansenula polymorpha, were used for the scale-up experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the widely used green fluorescent protein (GFP) was chosen as a model protein for protein expression, because it can be monitored online [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The strain E. coli BL21(DE3) pRSET B GFP-S65t which expresses GFP was kindly delivered by Markus Sack from Fraunhofer IME, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The E. coli GFP expression was controlled by the strong, inducible T7 promoter (inducer: isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranosid - IPTG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The GFP-S65T mutant processes a point mutation at position 65 from Serine to Threonine, which results in a single red shifted excitation peak, a more intensive fluorescence, and in an approximately four times faster fluorescence response than wild type GFP [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The strain Hansenula polymorpha RB11-pC10-FMD-GFP expresses GFP under the control of the FMD promoter [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The FMD promoter is repressed under the presence of glucose and derepressed under the presence of glycerol in the culture medium [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>It was kindly provided by Carsten Amuel from the Institute of Microbiology, Heinrich-Heine-University Düsseldorf, Germany. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The E. coli experiments were carried out with the synthetic medium Wilms-Reuss (WR) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The medium had the following composition: WR medium: 20 g/L glycerol, 2.0 g/L Na2SO4, 2.68 g/L (NH4)2SO4, 0.5 g/L NH4Cl, 14.6 g/L K2HPO4, 4.0 g/L Na2HPO4 × 2 H2O, 1.0 g/L (NH4)2-H-citrate, 0.5 g/L MgSO4 × 7 H2O, 0.01 g/L thiamine chloride hydrochloride, 3 ml/L trace element solution (TES), pH-value was adjusted to 7.2 with 1 M NaOH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>TES contains: 0.5 g/L CaCl2, 0.18 g/L ZnSO4 × 7H2O, 0.1 g/L MnSO4 × H2O, 10.05 g/L Na2-EDTA, 8.35 g/L FeCl3, 0.16 g/L CuSO4, × 5H2O, and 0.18 g/L CoCl2 × 6H2O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The E. coli cultures were induced with 0.5 mM isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranosid (IPTG, Biomol GmbH, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The Hansenula polymorpha experiments were carried out with the synthetic medium SYN6- MES, which had the following composition [20]: 20 g/L glycerol, 1.0 g/L KH2PO4, 7.66 g/L (NH4)2SO4, 3.3 g/L KCl, 3.0 g/L MgSO4 × 7H2O, 0.3 g/L NaCl, 27.3 g/L MES Pufferan (Carl Roth GmbH &amp; Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>KG, Karlsruhe, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>After dissolution of all medium components, the pH-value was adjusted to 6.4 with 1 M NaOH or 1 M H2SO4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Then, the medium was autoclaved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>After autoclaving of the basic medium, 6.67 mL/L micro element stock solution, 6.67 mL/L vitamin stock solution, 3.33 mL/L trace element stock solution (that have all been filter sterilized) and 6.67 mL/L calcium stock solution (that has been autoclaved) were added to the medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The stock solutions had the following compositions: micro element stock solution: 10 g/L (NH4)2Fe(SO4)2 × 6 H2O, 0.8 g/L CuSO4 × 5 H2O, 3.0 g/L ZnSO4 × 7 H2O, 4.0 g/L MnSO4 × H2O, 10 g/L EDTA (Titriplex III, Merck, Darmstadt, Germany); vitamin stock solution: 60 mg/L D-Biotin, 20 g/L thiamine chloride hydrochloride; trace elements stock solution: 100 mg/L NiSO4 × 6 H2O, 100 mg/L CoC12 × 6 H2O, 100 mg/L H3BO3, 100 mg/L KJ, 100 mg/L Na2MoO4 × 2H2O; calcium stock solution: 150 g/L CaCl2 × 2H2O. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The preculture for the fementations of both bacterial and yeast strains were prepared by using 5 cryo vials which were inoculated into 100 mL of the respective fermentation medium (WR for E. coli or Syn6-MES for H. polymorpha). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Each inoculated culture volume (100 mL) was then distributed equally among five 250 mL Erlenmeyer shake flasks and was respectively incubated at a shaking frequency of 300 rpm, a shaking diameter of 50 mm, and a temperature of 30°C on an orbital shaker (LS-X, Kühner AG, Birsfelden, Switzerland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The starting optical density (OD0) of the E. coli preculture was 0.5, and that of the H. polymorpha preculture was 1.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The precultivation of H. polymorpha took 18 hours and that of E. coli took 16 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>After the preculturing, the five shake flasks were again pooled and 90 mL of the pool were inoculated into the fermenter resulting in a starting fermenter volume of 1.4 L after inoculation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The precultures for the Respiration Activity Monitoring System (RAMOS) experiments were prepared by using only one cryo vial for inoculating 20 mL of the respective fermentation medium (WR for E. coli and Syn6-MES for H. polymorpha). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The incubation conditions were the same as mentioned above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All chemicals were of analytical grade and were delivered by Fluka/Sigma-Aldrich Chemie GmbH (Buchs, Switzerland) unless specified otherwise. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Microtiter plate fermentation (BioLector) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The microtiter plate fermentations were conducted in the BioLector which was originally introduced by Samorski et al. [14] and recently improved and validated by Kensy et al. [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The general set-up of the BioLector is depicted in Figure 1A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The BioLector mainly consisted of an optical measurement unit (Fluostar, BMG Lab Technologies, Offenburg, Germany), an optical Y-fiber bundle (Prinz Optics GmbH, Stromberg, Germany), a X-Y mover (BMG Lab Technologies, Offenburg, Germany) and an orbital shaker (LS-X, Kühner AG, Basel, Switzerland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In the presented experiments the above described BioLector prototype was exclusively applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The complete device has now been commercialized by m2p-labs GmbH, Aachen, Germany [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The biomass concentrations were measured via scattered light at 620 nm excitation without an emission filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The GFP concentrations were monitored using an excitation filter of 485 nm and an emission filter of 520 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The sensitivity of the photomultiplier (gain) was adapted to the different measurement tasks and the detailed data is mentioned in the respective figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The BioLector possessed a data reproducibility of below 5% standard deviation, upon cultivating the same clone in the same medium on a microtiter plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Due to small standard deviation and the high information content, error bars in the figures were omitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The experiments were exclusively carried out with black, standard round 96-well microtiter plates with an optical bottom from Greiner Bio-One GmbH (μClear, article number: 655087, Frickenhausen, Germany) that were covered with a gas permeable membrane from ABgene Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>(article number: AB-0718, Epsom, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>If not otherwise specified, the experiments were conducted with 200 μL working volume of culture or medium, a shaking frequency of 995 rpm and a shaking diameter of 3 mm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the experimental set up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>(A) Measurement principle of the microtiter plate fermentation in the BioLector via back scattering of light from cells and fluorescence emission of molecules; (B) Measurement principle of the stirred tank fermentation with online measurement of OD and fluorescence in the bypass. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Stirred tank fermenter </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>As standard stirred tank fermenter, a Visual-Safety-Fermenter (VSF, Bioengineering AG, Wald, Switzerland) with a nominal volume of 2 L was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The fermenter possessed a standard in-situ dissolved oxygen tension (DOT) and pH electrode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The system was sterilized by autoclaving with an in-situ rod heater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The fermenter had a height-to-diameter ratio of 3 and two six-bladed Rushton turbines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The fermenter was aerated at a constant gas flow of 1 vvm controlled by a mass flow controller (5850TR, Brooks Instruments, Hatfield, PA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The offgas from the fermenter was additionally analyzed by an online offgas analyzer (O2 by Magnos 106, ABB AG, Mannheim, Germany and CO2 by Unor 6N, Maihak AG, Hamburg, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>For the online measurement of OD and GFP, a liquid bypass was connected to the fermenter (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The fermentation broth was pumped from a bottom sample port of the fermenter by using a peristaltic pump (Fixo, Ismatec Laboratoriumstechnik GmbH, Wertheim-Mondfeld, Germany) through the bypass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>This bypass contained a bubble trap (self-made) to avoid gas bubbles entering the optical detection line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For the OD detection, a flow cuvette with 0.5 mm path length (170-QS, Hellma GmbH&amp; Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>KG, Müllheim, Germany) and a photometer (Photometer 6000, Skalar Analytical B.V., Breda, The Netherlands) were applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The OD was measured with a 630 nm interference filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a flow cuvette (176.051-QS Hellma GmbH &amp; Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>KG, Müllheim, Germany) and a fluorimeter (Fluorimeter 6300, Skalar Analytical B.V., Breda, The Netherlands) were applied for the GFP fluorescence measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The GFP was detected using an excitation filter of 480 nm and an emission filter of 530 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After passing through the flow cuvettes, the fermentation broth was recycled into the fermenter (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>All online detected data were collected via a data acquisition module ADAM-4520 (Advantech Europe GmbH, Düsseldorf, Germany) and controlled by a self-developed bioprocess control program under LabVIEW (National Instruments Germany GmbH, München, Germany) on a PC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The oxygen transfer rate (OTR) and carbon dioxide transfer rate (CTR) of the fermentation was calculated corresponding to the following equations (1) and (2), respectively [22,23]: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>where y is the mole fraction of oxygen or carbon dioxide in the gas phase of the in or out flowing gas stream,  the norm gas flow rate and Vm is the molar gas volume. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>From the online derived OTR measurement, the kLa-value of the fermenter could be determined as follows, assuming a completely mixed gas phase [22]: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>where HeO2 stands for the Henry constant for oxygen, pR for the reactor pressure, DOT for the dissolved oxygen tension and yO2, cal for the mole fraction of oxygen from the calibration gas of the DOT electrode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>A Henry constant for oxygen of 1012 bar L/mol for the H. polymorpha fermentation and 993 bar L/mol for the E. coli fermentation was applied in the calculations (estimated from [24]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The E. coli fermentation was conducted at a working volume of 1.4 L, a specific aeration rate of 1 vvm, a stirring speed of 1000 rpm and a temperature of 32°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Unlike this fermentation, the H. polymorpha fermentation was operated at a working volume of 1.4 L, a specific aeration rate of 1 vvm, a stirring speed of 800 rpm and a temperature of 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>After the initial inoculation of the fermenter and a 5 min delay time for mixing of the cell suspension, a 10 mL sample was taken from the fermenter and was then distributed on the MTP to guarantee the same inoculation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The same procedure was repeated with the E. coli fermentation after inducing the culture to have a second point of reference between the fermenter and the MTP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Respiration Activity Monitoring System </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In the presented study, the Respiration Activity Monitoring System (RAMOS) was applied to determine the correlation between oxygen transfer rates (OTRs) obtained from the chemical sulfite system and biological cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>RAMOS was first introduced and described in detail by Anderlei and Büchs [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Basically, the system consists of particular shake flasks, that in the lower part resemble equal to a standard Erlenmeyer shake flask and, in the headspace, contains an oxygen sensor in the gas phase to measure the respiration activity of cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>With this technique, the OTRs of the sulfite system, the E. coli fermentation in WR medium and the H. polymorpha fermentation in SYN6-MES medium (the same media later applied in the fermenter) were measured at different filling volumes of 10 mL, 15 mL and 20 mL at a shaking frequency of 250 rpm and a shaking diameter of 50 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The sulfite oxidation was performed at 25°C and the fermentations at 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Under oxygen limiting conditions, the OTR curve of the sulfite oxidation and the fermentations forms a plateau. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This plateau level of the different filling volumes can be correlated to each other, thereby giving a proportionality factor (f) between the OTRs of the biological media and the sulfite system as follows in equation (4) [11,26]: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The proportionality factor (f) represents the ratio between the different oxygen solubilities (C*) and diffusion coefficients (DO2) of the applied media. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Determination of oxygen transfer rates (OTR) in surface-aerated bioreactors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>For years, the sulfite oxidation served very well as a model system for the characterization of small-scale, surface-aerated bioreactors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Hermann et al. introduced this technique together with a simple color shift of a colorimetric pH-indicator making it possible to read out the reaction kinetics with a simple camera [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In the presented work, this sulfite oxidation method from Hermann was again applied to characterize the oxygen mass transfer conditions in 96-well microtiter plates with various filling volumes ranging vom 100 μL up to 260 μL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The 96-well microtiter plate was operated with a gas-permeable cover membrane (ABgene Ltd., article number: AB-0718, Epsom, UK) at a temperature of 25°C, a shaking frequency of 995 rpm and a shaking diameter of 3 mm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Calibration alignment between different optical measurement methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Due to different optical measurement methods applied in this study, the obtained measurement signals had to be calibrated with a standard analytical method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The scattered lights intensities from the BioLector and OD from the fermenter bypass were correlated to cell dry weight (CDW) as the biomass calibration unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The cell dry weight was determined gravimetrically after washing the cells twice in physiological salt solution (9 g/L NaCl) and drying the cells at 105°C until the mass remained constant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The calibration of the measurement signals, i.e. scattered light and OD, with cell dry weight was conducted at the end of the fermentations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The contents of the fermenter analogous to the normal fermenter operation were recycled through the fermenter bypass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Simultaneously, the measurements, OD and GFP fluorescence, were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>During the calibration procedure, the fermenter contents were continuously diluted with new medium, directed through the bypass and again measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>After each dilution step, a 5 mL sample was taken from the well mixed fermenter in order to collect scattered light intensities in the BioLector and to analyze cell dry weights from the same samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>This procedure was repeated for the fermentations of E. coli and H. polymorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Finally, these measurement signals could be correlated to each other (Figure 2A and 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Since no offline protein analysis was available in our laboratory for the detection of GFP concentrations, the GFP fluorescence signals of both measurement systems, the fermenter and the MTP, were directly correlated with each other (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>From the literature, it is known that the GFP fluorescence signals can be well correlated with real GFP protein concentrations in well aerated systems such as fermenters [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Calibration of measurement signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>(A) Cell dry weight versus scattered light intensities measured in microtiter plates; (B) Cell dry weight versus OD measured in the fermenter bypass; (C) GFP fluorescence in the microtiter plate versus GFP fluorescence in the fermenter of the H. polymorpha fermentation; Operation conditions: MTP (H. polymorpha/E. coli): 200 μL filling volume, at 30°C/32°C temperature, 995 rpm shaking frequency and 3 mm shaking diameter, scattered light (ex: 620 nm/em: -, gain: 20) and GFP (ex: 485 nm/em: 520 nm, gain: 10); fermenter (H. polymorpha/E. coli): 1.4 L filling volume, at 30°C/32°C temperature, 800/1000 rpm shaking frequency, 1 vvm specific aeration rate, OD (Absorption: 630 nm) and GFP (ex: 480 nm/em: 530 nm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-2"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Calibration of the measurement apparatus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In order to compare the growth and protein expression of both studied cultivation systems, i.e. the shaken microtiter plate and the stirred tank fermenter, it is very important to align the online measured parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the biomass measurements of scattered light intensities in the MTP and those of OD in the STF bypass were all correlated to the cell dry weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In the case of the protein expression parameter, GFP was applied as a model protein for simplifying the detection by fluorescence. GFP was not correlated to any offline laboratory method such as ELISA or Western Blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Both the BioLector and the STF measurement systems were directly correlated to each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 presents the calibration of the measurement signals for the E. coli and H. polymorpha fermentations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 demonstrates that all correlations are highly precise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This is confirmed by the coefficient of determination value (R2) of approximately 0.99 which was calculated for all linear equations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Each R2 is presented below the respective linear equations in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>For the measurement of scattered light in the MTP and of OD in the bypass, it was necessary to perform separate calibrations for the distinct microorganisms, E. coli and H. polymorpha, because the optical biomass measurement depends strongly on the morphology of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>For the GFP fluorescence measurements, however, it was only necessary to perform one calibration, because, in this case, it served only to align the different measurement systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The calibrations performed here were subsequently used to calculate the cell dry weight and the GFP fluorescence (based on the MTP fluorescence unit) for each fermentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Thus, the kinetic data from both fermentation systems, MTP and STF, were actually comparable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Transformation of chemical OTRmax to biological OTRmax </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The sulfite oxidation method is a very good and simple method to characterize the maximum oxygen transfer capacity (OTRmax) in small-scale, surface-aerated fermentation systems as was reported by Hermann et al. [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, this chemical model system does not truly reflect the composition of biological media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In general, the actual medium composition interferes with the oxygen diffusion coefficient (DO2) and the oxygen concentration at the gas-liquid interface (C*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>To determine the influence of the hereby applied fermentation media, additional RAMOS experiments with the sulfite system, the E. coli medium and H. polymorpha medium were necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Since no dissolved oxygen can be measured in the RAMOS device, it is important to run the experiments under oxygen-limiting conditions, where the oxygen concentration in the bulk liquid (CL) becomes very small. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the sulfite oxidation and the fermentation were run with different filling volumes (10 mL, 15 mL and 20 mL) in the RAMOS shake flasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The results of this experiment are presented in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Determination of the different oxygen transfer rates (OTR) in RAMOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(A) for the chemical 0.5 mM sulfite system; (B) for the E. coli fermentation in WR medium; (C) for the H. polymorpha fermentation in SYN6-MES medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Operation conditions: 10 mL, 15 mL and 20 mL filling volume, 250 mL Erlenmeyer shake flask for RAMOS, 250 rpm shaking frequency, 50 mm shaking diameter, at 25°C temperature with the sulfite system and 30°C temperature with the microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The E. coli cultures were induced at 7.17 h with 0.5 mM IPTG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 clearly depicts that most of the OTR curves possess a plateau, which implies the oxygen limitation [25,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Only the E. coli fermentation with 10 mL filling volume does not become limited and thus, forms a sharp peak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The graphs also depict that the sulfite system reached an OTR plateau directly after the start of the experiment, because the oxidation is driven by a constant concentration of the cobalt catalyst under almost constant reaction conditions [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the reaction runs at an almost constant rate until the end of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the fermentation cultures pass through the typical exponential growth phase until they reach the oxygen limitation and the mentioned OTR plateau. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In general, it is obvious that lower filling volumes attain higher OTRmax-values than larger filling volumes due to the higher specific surface area assessable for oxygen diffusion [26,29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For both microorganisms, i.e. E. coli and H. polymorpha, the maximum OTR necessary to supply sufficient oxygen to the culture ranges from 0.045-0.050 mol/L/h as is observed with the 10 mL filling volume. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>From these graphs the OTR plateau values for the different media were correlated to each other and inserted into Equation (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Table 1 presents the evaluated proportionality factor (f): </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Evaluated proportionality factor (f) between fermentation and the sulfite system </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Proportionality factor (f) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>E. coli in WR medium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>H. polymorpha in SYN6-MES medium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>1.22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These proportionality factors (f) were subsequently applied for calculating the maximum oxygen transfer capacities in MTPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Characterization of kLa in MTPs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Upon cultivating microorganisms in small-scale bioreactors, it is very important to conduct the experiments under well-characterized operating conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>To meet this requirement, the operation conditions in MTPs were first characterized using the sulfite oxidation method introduced by Hermann et al. [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Whereas, the shaking frequency and diameter were kept constant at 995 rpm and 3 mm, respectively, the filling volumes of the wells of the MTP were varied between 100 μL and 260 μL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The results of this characterization are presented in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Maximum oxygen transfer capacity (OTRmax) and kLa-values versus the filling volume. for the chemical 0.5 mM sulfite system, the E. coli fermentation in WR medium and the Hansenula polymorpha fermentation in SYN6-MES medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The method from Hermann et al. [9,10] was applied for the determination and calculation of OTRmax and kLa-values for the sulfite system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The OTRmax and kLa-values for the fermentations were calculated by applying the proportionality factor (f) from table 1 on the OTRmax-values of the sulfite system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Operation conditions (Sulfite system/E. coli/H. polymorpha): various filling volumes between 100-260 μL, at 25°C/30°C/30°C temperature, 995 rpm shaking frequency and 3 mm shaking diameter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>It is notable that a linear correlation between the maximum oxygen transfer capacity (OTRmax) and the filling volume was obtained, analogously as was reported previously [10,30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The OTRmax ranges from 0.017 mol/L/h (kLa = 97 1/h) at 260 μL up to 0.052 (kLa = 297 1/h) at 100 μL for the sulfite system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>These values correlate very well to those reported from Hermann et al. [10] and John et al. [30] for standard round 96-well MTPs and also correlate well in magnitude with other formats such as square 24-deepwell plates [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Applying both aforementioned proportionality factors (f) for the fermentation media (Figure 4), the OTRmax and kLa-values achievable in E. coli and H. polymorpha fermentations lie above the line of the sulfite system, whereby H. polymorpha always shows the highest values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Even though, it would be better to apply filling volumes of 100-120 μL with regard to optimize the oxygen transfer (0.045-0.050 moL/L/h from Figure 3), an actual filling volume of 200 μL was applied in order to ensure that sufficient liquid was available for further offline analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Moreover, for a precise optical detection it was important to have enough liquid on the well bottom during the continuous shaking of the MTP [11,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>This implies operating the MTP at a suboptimal kLa-value of 180-190 1/h compared to that of the stirred tank fermenter (kLa = 370-600 1/h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the RAMOS experiments (Figure 3B and 3C) depicted that even oxygen-limiting OTRs of greater than 0.030 mol/L/h (kLa = 175 1/h) simply result in a prolongation of the fermentation by 1 h for E. coli and H. polymorpha, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>This is regarded as being non significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Comparison of parallel E. coli fermentations in MTP and fermenter </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Figure 5 presents the direct comparison of parallel E. coli fermentations in the MTP and STF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Comparison of parallel E. coli fermentations in microtiter plate and stirred tank fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Operation conditions: MTP: 200 μL filling volume, at 32°C temperature, 995 rpm shaking frequency and 3 mm shaking diameter, scattered light (ex: 620 nm/em: -, gain: 20) and GFP (ex: 485 nm/em: 520 nm, gain: 10); fermenter: 1.4 L filling volume, at 32°C temperature, 1000 rpm shaking frequency, 1 vvm specific aeration rate, induction with 0.5 mM IPTG (end concentration in the fermenter) at 7.3 h, OD (Absorption: 630 nm) and GFP (ex: 480 nm/em: 530 nm) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Four different curves are plotted in Figure 5A and 5B: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>• (I) MTP, non induced - the same E. coli fermentation without induction as a negative control </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>• (II) MTP, induced - the inoculated E. coli culture was taken from the fermenter and were distributed on the MTP, induction was performed at 7.3 h in the MTP </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>• (III) MTP, induced in fermenter - the E. coli culture was sampled from the fermenter after induction and then distributed on the MTP </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>• (IV) Fermenter, induced - the fermentation was completely running in the fermenter with an induction at 7.3 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Figure 5C presents the online process parameters from the fermenter and the offgas analyzer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The development of the biomass concentrations (Figure 5A) depicts that, in the pre-induction phase, all three cultures (I, II and IV) have the same slope and reach a biomass concentration of 4.5 g/L at the induction point of 7.3 h (please note: the monitoring of the culture (III) - MTP, induced in fermenter - started after the induction, in the pre-induction phase this culture is displayed as the fermenter curve). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In the post-induction phase, a clear separation of the negative control (I), which was not induced, is notable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>All other cultures (II, III and IV), which were induced, follow the same trend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Obviously, the E. coli strain seems to be growth-inhibited after induction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Only at the very end of the fermentation, the fermenter curve (IV) deviates slightly from the MTP curves (II and III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This both induced cultures running in the MTP (II and III) show exactly the same growth behavior at a slightly deviating biomass concentration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Analyzing the protein expression (Figure 5B) results in a very similar behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In the pre-induction phase, all three cultures (I, II and IV) follow the same slope resulting in a GFP fluorescence of 6500 at the induction point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>It seems, that E. coli constitutively produces the product GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Then, after the induction, the curves of the different cultures deviate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The negative control (I) continues to produce GFP up to 10 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Then, the GFP formation stagnates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the induced cultures (II, III and IV) continue producing the GFP up to 19 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>All induced cultures (II, III and IV) follow exactly the same slope of GFP formation, which means that the cultivation conditions are indeed comparable for the MTP and the fermenter system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>It cannot be excluded that GFP inclusion bodies have been formed in this expression experiment, but due to the steady slope of the GFP fluorescence signals it is expected that GFP is produced in soluble form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Figure 5C exhibits the corresponding process parameters measured in the fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>All these parameters correspond very well to the different culture phases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Due to the missing availability of pH-control in the MTP, the fermenter was also operated without pH-control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>This results in a pH decrease from 7.2 to 5.9 over the course of fermentation, which did not limit the culture growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The OTR curve points out that in this fermentation, a maximum OTR of 0.043 mol/L/h was reached which is comparable to those values detected in shake flasks with RAMOS. kLa-values of 600 1/h were calculated with equation (3) for the STF which were almost three times higher than that applied in the MTP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The DOT curve in Figure 5C demonstrates that at this high kLa-value in the fermenter the E. coli culture reached a minimum DOT of 55%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This signifies that the culture is far away from an oxygen limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Even at the reduced kLa-value of the MTP (180 1/h), the culture experienced only a slight oxygen limitation which did not sustainably effect the culture growth nor protein expression as mentioned before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>This minor influence of a slight oxygen limitation was also observed in the RAMOS experiments comparing the 10 mL and the 15 mL filling volumes (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In this case, a short prolongation of the fermentation with 15 mL filling volume in comparison to the 10 mL fermentation was noticeable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Overall, the results of the parallel E. coli fermentations in MTP and STF demonstrate that the cultivation conditions are very comparable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>All induced cultures behave very similarly and show the same growth and protein expression kinetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The negative control of a non-induced culture depicts which differences in kinetics could normally appear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Comparison of parallel yeast fermentations in MTP and fermenter </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The same experiment as for E. coli was also performed with the yeast H. polymorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Here, no induction of the promoter was necessary due to the different promoter regulation of H. polymorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The applied FMD promoter was simply derepressed by the substrate glycerol [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Very comparable growth and protein expression kinetics were also found in these parallel fermentations (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In Figure 6A, for both cultivation systems, MTP and STF, almost identical exponential growth curves could be observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Exactly at about 16 h, both fermentations enter the stationary phase at a biomass concentration of 11.4 g/L CDW (MTP) and 10.7 g/L CDW (STF) resulting in a relative error of 6.3%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Both systems also showed consistent protein expression of GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Even small changes in the expression rate appeared synchronously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>In general, the protein expression mirrored the exponential growth curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The protein formation was subjected to a derepression as known from the literature [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>At the synchronous entry into the stationary phase at 16 h, both fermentations differ only by 9.5% with regard to the GFP fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Comparison of parallel H. polymorpha fermentations in microtiter plate and stirred tank fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Operation conditions: MTP: 200 μL filling volume, at 30°C temperature, 995 rpm shaking frequency and 3 mm shaking diameter, scattered light (ex: 620 nm/em: -, gain: 20) and GFP (ex: 485 nm/em: 520 nm, gain: 10); fermenter: 1.4 L filling volume, at 30°C temperature, 800 rpm shaking frequency, 1 vvm specific aeration rate, OD (Absorption: 630 nm) and GFP (ex: 480 nm/em: 530 nm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The process parameters of the fermenter (Figure 6C) again correspond very well to the biomass and protein formation kinetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The OTR and CTR indicate an exponential development similar to the growth curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>All dynamics terminate at 16 h, when the substrate is exhausted and the metabolic activity decreases immediately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The uncontrolled pH-value decreases from 6.4 to 5.5, which does not limit growth of H. polymorpha [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>A maximum OTR of 0.052 mol/L/h was reached, which is slightly higher than the values attained in the shake flasks in RAMOS (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The calculated kLa-value applied in the fermenter were 370 1/h which is double of that applied in the MTP (kLa = 180-190 1/h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>In the fermentation the DOT dropped down to a minimum of 21% (Figure 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This might mean that the yeast culture in the MTP fermentation could run into a slight oxygen limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Again here, no significant influence is noticeable concerning culture growth and protein expression in comparison to the STF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Similar ratios of OTR between the 10 mL and 15 mL filling volumes in the RAMOS experiments (Figure 3C) as that applied in the STF and MTP only led to a minor prolongation of fermentation in RAMOS of 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>This could not be observed in the comparison of the STF and the MTP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>In summary, the MTP can mimic the fermenter very well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Besides the E. coli fermentations, the parallel H. polymorpha fermentations in the MTP and STF also produced very comparable growth and protein expression kinetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>During metabolic activity, all online-measured data show deviations of below 10% between the two cultivation systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Characterization of specific product formation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>As it was demonstrated in the previous figures, fermentations in MTPs can mimic growth and protein expression kinetics very well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it could be very interesting to apply the online measurement data of the MTP-based BioLector to characterize clones and fermentation conditions with respect to their specific product formation capacities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Figure 7 gives an example of a different presentation of the online data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>With the BioLector, it is now possible to present the product formation data as a function of biomass concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>This is rarely possible with fermenters, because laboratories often lack online biomass and fluorescence sensors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>This online biomass measurement would be possible by applying an online OD measurement (like in our case in the bypass, Figure 1) or an online impedance sensor (e.g. from Aber Instruments, UK or Fogale, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>For the detection of fluorescent proteins an online fluorescence sensor could be installed (e.g. BioView from Delta, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>These sensors, however, would require a much higher investment, because two additional sensors for each fermenter will be needed beside the common pH and DOT electrodes and the temperature probe. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Protein expression as function of cell dry weight - characteristics of different expression systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Direct correlation of the protein expression via GFP fluorescence to the biomass concentration of the fermentations of figures 5 and 6; calibrated data from measurements in the BioLector: scattered light (ex: 620 nm/em: -, gain: 20), GFP (ex: 485 nm/em: 520 nm, gain: 10) and in the fermenter bypass: OD (Absorption: 630 nm) and GFP (ex: 480 nm/em: 530 nm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-68-7"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Figure 7 presents the fluorescence development of GFP versus the cell dry weight of the E. coli and the H. polymorpha fermentation in both reactor scales, STF and MTP, which has been described earlier in this paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Whereas, the H. polymorpha strain shows only a linear correlation between biomass and GFP protein, the E. coli strain experiences a boost in protein production after the induction (as indicated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The graphs in Figure 7 clearly depict the derepressed, almost constitutive, expression for the H. polymorpha strain and the induced expression for the E. coli strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the graphs in Figure 7 provide the specific product yield (YP/X) of the strains by deriving the slope of the graphs as YP/X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>This evaluation criteria is very often used to consider the productivity of a fermentation process [2,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>This novel way of data presentation, i.e. protein concentration as a function of biomass concentration, has first been made possible even on a micro-scale by using new online measurement techniques such as the BioLector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>This can help to facilitate the selection of a potent clone or a very productive fermentation medium or process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>After the validation of the online monitoring capacity of the new high-throughput fermentation system [15], called BioLector, it was challenging to investigate the scalability from a microtiter plate to a stirred tank fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the present study was focused on the scale-up of common microbial expression systems, such as the bacteria E. coli and the yeast H. polymorpha, from microtiter plate to stirred tank fermenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The prerequisite to perform such a study was the comprehensive characterization of mass transfer conditions in microtiter plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>In recent years, many of the common microtiter plates were already characterized by several groups, whereby a few new methods for the characterization of engineering parameters were developed [9-11,29,34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>In this work, the maximum oxygen transfer capacity (OTRmax) and the volumetric mass transfer coefficient (kLa) were determined with the sulfite oxidation method from Hermann et al. [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the OTRmax and kLa were measured for various filling volumes in a standard 96-well microtiter plate at a constant shaking frequency of 995 rpm and a shaking diameter of 3 mm, because only little information was available at these conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Finally, it was necessary to convert the chemical OTRmax-values into biological OTRmax-values, which could be achieved with the help of a RAMOS device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Even though more practical but suboptimal filling volumes of 200 μL were applied instead of superior 100-120 μL with regard to the OTR-demand of the cultures, excellent scalability results could be attained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The comparison of the online measurement signals, biomass concentration and the GFP fluorescence as a model protein, in parallel fermentations using microtiter plate and stirred tank fermenter proved that the kinetics of growth and protein expression are well comparable between both reactor scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed not only by the bacteria fermentation of E. coli, but also by the yeast fermentation of H. polymorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Both expression systems showed nearly identical kinetics in the microtiter plate and the stirred tank fermenter, showing a maximum of 10% deviation between the measurement signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Taking into account that the scale-up factor applied here was 7000, this was a surprisingly good result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, the presented study pointed out that the scale-up from microtiter plates and stirred tank fermenters is possible for standard microbial expression systems with general low viscosity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>As previously mentioned, one of the key factors for successful scale-up was the kLa-value [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>This proven scalability of MTPs to STFs could make them ideally suited as a microbioreactor and a scale-down reactor unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>This scalability combined with high-throughput and online monitoring of important process parameters, i.e. biomass and protein concentrations when using fluorescent proteins or fusions thereof, creates a very powerful tool in screening and bioprocess development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Even though kLa- values of up to 350 1/h have been reported for round 96-well MTPs in this paper and for square 24-well MTPs in other publications [13], these kLa-values are still not sufficient to mimic a full industrial fermenter in a scale-down model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Higher kLa-values of up to 1000 1/h would be desirable to attain higher cell concentrations and to operate a fedbatch process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>New microtiter plate formats with new geometrical well designs such as the recently presented Flowerplate could probably solve these limitations in the future [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>FK conceived the study and drafted the figures and the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>CE performed all fermentations, calibrations and data analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>JB participated in its design, coordination, and drafting of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>GnothSJenzschMSimutisRLubbertAProcess Analytical Technology (PAT): batch-to-batch reproducibility of fermentation processes by robust process operational design and controlJ Biotechnol2007132218018610.1016/j.jbiotec.2007.03.02017559961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>MandeniusCFBrundinABioprocess optimization using design-of-experiments methodologyBiotechnol Prog20082461191120310.1002/btpr.6719194932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>HoustonJGBanksMThe chemical-biological interface: developments in automated and miniaturised screening technologyCurr Opin Biotechnol19978673474010.1016/S0958-1669(97)80128-09425665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>DuetzWARuediLHermannRO'ConnorKBuchsJWitholtBMethods for intense aeration, growth, storage, and replication of bacterial strains in microtiter platesAppl Environ Microbiol20006662641264610.1128/AEM.66.6.2641-2646.200010831450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>MinasWBaileyJEDuetzWStreptomycetes in micro-cultures: growth, production of secondary metabolites, and storage and retrieval in the 96-well formatAntonie Van Leeuwenhoek2000783-429730510.1023/A:101025401335211386352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>GirardPJordanMTsaoMWurmFMSmall-scale bioreactor system for process development and optimizationBiochem Eng J20017211711910.1016/S1369-703X(00)00110-811173299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Ferreira-TorresCMichelettiMLyeGJMicroscale process evaluation of recombinant biocatalyst libraries: application to Baeyer-Villiger monooxygenase catalysed lactone synthesisBioprocess Biosyst Eng2005282839310.1007/s00449-005-0422-416208497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>WeissSJohnGTKlimantIHeinzleEModeling of mixing in 96-well microplates observed with fluorescence indicatorsBiotechnol Progr200218482183010.1021/bp0200649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>HermannRWaltherNMaierUBüchsJOptical method for the determination of the oxygen-transfer capacity of small bioreactors based on sulfite oxidationBiotechnology and Bioengineering200174535536310.1002/bit.112611427937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>HermannRLehmannMBüchsJCharacterization of gas-liquid mass transfer phenomena in microtiter platesBiotechnology and Bioengineering200381217818610.1002/bit.1045612451554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>KensyFZimmermannHFKnabbenIAnderleiTTrauthweinHDingerdissenUBuchsJOxygen transfer phenomena in 48-well microtiter plates: determination by optical monitoring of sulfite oxidation and verification by real-time measurement during microbial growthBiotechnol Bioeng200589669870810.1002/bit.2037315696519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>MichelettiMBarrettTDoigSDBaganzFLevyMSWoodleyJMLyeGJFluid mixing in shaken bioreactors: Implications for scale-up predictions from microlitre-scale microbial and mammalian cell culturesChemical Engineering Science2006612939294910.1016/j.ces.2005.11.028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>IslamRSTisiDLevyMSLyeGJScale-up of Escherichia coli growth and recombinant protein expression conditions from microwell to laboratory and pilot scale based on matched k(L)aBiotechnol Bioeng20089951128113910.1002/bit.2169717969169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>SamorskiMMuller-NewenGBuchsJQuasi-continuous combined scattered light and fluorescence measurements: a novel measurement technique for shaken microtiter platesBiotechnol Bioeng2005921616810.1002/bit.2057315988771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>KensyFZangEFaulhammerCTanRKBuchsJValidation of a high-throughput fermentation system based on online monitoring of biomass and fluorescence in continuously shaken microtiter platesMicrob Cell Fact200983110.1186/1475-2859-8-3119497126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>SuWWFluorescent proteins as tools to aid protein productionMicrob Cell Fact2005411210.1186/1475-2859-4-1215850488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>HeimRCubittABTsienRYImproved Green FluorescenceNature199537366366410.1038/373663b07854443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>AmuelCGellissenGHollenbergCPSuckowMAnalysis of Heat Shock Promoters in Hansenula polymorpha: The TPS1 Promoter, a Novel Element for Heterologous Gene ExpressionBiotechnol Bioprocess Eng2000524725210.1007/BF02942181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>WilmsBHauckAReussMSyldatkCMattesRSiemannMAltenbuchnerJHigh-cell-density fermentation for production of L-N-carbamoylase using an expression system based on the Escherichia coli rhaBAD promoterBiotechnology and Bioengineering20017329510310.1002/bit.104111255157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>HellwigSSCGellissenGBüchsJGellissen GComparative fermentationProduction of recombinant proteins: novel microbial and eukaryotic expression systems2005287317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>m2p-labs GmbH<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.m2p-labs.com">http://www.m2p-labs.com</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>KnollAMaierBTscherrigHBuchsJThe oxygen mass transfer, carbon dioxide inhibition, heat removal, and the energy and cost efficiencies of high pressure fermentationAdv Biochem Eng Biotechnol200592779915791933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>KnollABartschSHusemannBEngelPSchroerKRibeiroBStockmannCSeletzkyJBuchsJHigh cell density cultivation of recombinant yeasts and bacteria under non-pressurized and pressurized conditions in stirred tank bioreactorsJ Biotechnol2007132216717910.1016/j.jbiotec.2007.06.01017681630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>WeisenbergerSSchumpeAEstimation of gas solubilities in salt solutions at temperatures from 273 K to 363 KAiche J199642129830010.1002/aic.690420130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>AnderleiTBuchsJDevice for sterile online measurement of the oxygen transfer rate in shaking flasksBiochem Eng J20017215716210.1016/S1369-703X(00)00116-911173305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>MaierULosenMBüchsJAdvances in understanding and modeling the gas-liquid mass transfer in shaking flasksBiochemical Engineering Journal200417315516810.1016/S1369-703X(03)00174-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>LiJXuHHerberWKBentleyWERaoGIntegrated bioprocessing in Saccharomyces cerevisiae using green fluorescent protein as a fusion partnerBiotechnol Bioeng200279668269310.1002/bit.1033112209816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>AnderleiTZangWBüchsJOnline respiration activity measurement (OTR, CTR, RQ) in shake flasksBiochemical Engineering Journal200417318719410.1016/S1369-703X(03)00181-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>MaierUBuchsJCharacterisation of the gas-liquid mass transfer in shaking bioreactorsBiochem Eng J2001729910610.1016/S1369-703X(00)00107-811173296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>JohnGTKlimantIWittmannCHeinzleEIntegrated optical sensing of dissolved oxygen in microtiter plates: A novel tool for microbial cultivationBiotechnology and Bioengineering200381782983610.1002/bit.1053412557316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>KensyFJohnGTHofmannBBuchsJCharacterisation of operation conditions and online monitoring of physiological culture parameters in shaken 24-well microtiter platesBioprocess Biosyst Eng2005282758110.1007/s00449-005-0010-716240130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>StöckmannCMaierUAnderleiTKnockeCGellissenGBüchsJThe oxygen transfer rate as key parameter for the characterization of Hansenula polymorpha screening culturesJ Ind Microbiol Biotechnol20033061362210.1007/s10295-003-0090-914586804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>SchmidtFROptimization and scale up of industrial fermentation processesAppl Microbiol Biotechnol200568442543510.1007/s00253-005-0003-016001256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>DoigSDOrtiz-OchoaKWardJMBaganzFCharacterization of oxygen transfer in miniature and lab-scale bubble column bioreactors and comparison of microbial growth performance based on constant k(L)aBiotechnol Prog20052141175118210.1021/bp050064j16080699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>FunkeMDiederichsSKensyFMullerCBuchsJThe baffled microtiter plate: increased oxygen transfer and improved online monitoring in small scale fermentationsBiotechnol Bioeng200910361118112810.1002/bit.2234119449392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
