<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2639708</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225568</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-07712</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Adhesion</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Signaling</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Developmental Molecular Mechanisms</subject><subject>Oncology/Breast Cancer</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 and -ΔN89β-Catenin Induce Canonical Signaling in Distinct Progenitors and Differentially Activate Hedgehog Signaling within Mammary Tumors </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Wnt/Hh in Mammary Tumors</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Teissedre</surname><given-names>Brigitte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pinderhughes</surname><given-names>Alicia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Incassati</surname><given-names>Angela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hatsell</surname><given-names>Sarah J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hiremath</surname><given-names>Minoti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>Pamela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Departments of Cell Biology and Dermatology, New York University School of Medicine, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>Syed A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Health Canada, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>cowinp01@nyumc.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: PC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: BT AP AI SH MH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: BT AP AI SH PC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: PC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e4537</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Teissedre et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Canonical Wnt/β-catenin signaling regulates stem/progenitor cells and, when perturbed, induces many human cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A significant proportion of human breast cancer is associated with loss of secreted Wnt antagonists and mice expressing MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin develop mammary adenocarcinomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Many studies have assumed these mouse models of breast cancer to be equivalent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here we show that MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin transgenes induce tumors with different phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Using axin2/conductin reporter genes we show that MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin activate canonical Wnt signaling within distinct cell-types. ΔN89β-catenin activated signaling within a luminal subpopulation scattered along ducts that exhibited a K18+ER−PR−CD24highCD49flow profile and progenitor properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MMTV-Wnt1 induced canonical signaling in K14+ basal cells with CD24/CD49f profiles characteristic of two distinct stem/progenitor cell-types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 produced additional profound effects on multiple cell-types that correlated with focal activation of the Hedgehog pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We document that large melanocytic nevi are a hitherto unreported hallmark of early hyperplastic Wnt1 glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>These nevi formed along the primary mammary ducts and were associated with Hedgehog pathway activity within a subset of melanocytes and surrounding stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Hh pathway activity also occurred within tumor-associated stromal and K14+/p63+ subpopulations in a manner correlated with Wnt1 tumor onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These data show MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin induce canonical signaling in distinct progenitors and that Hedgehog pathway activation is linked to melanocytic nevi and mammary tumor onset arising from excess Wnt1 ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>They further suggest that Hedgehog pathway activation maybe a critical component and useful indicator of breast tumors arising from unopposed Wnt1 ligand. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Wnts are a family of secreted proteins that regulate tissue patterning and homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The canonical Wnt pathway operates by inhibiting proteolysis of cytoplasmic β-catenin, which enters the nucleus and regulates transcription through Lef/Tcf DNA binding partners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is well documented that canonical Wnt/β-catenin signaling is required for the viability of particular stem cells, and forced activation of this pathway can expand stem/progenitors, alter cell fate and induce tumorigenesis [1]–[3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Multiple lines of evidence demonstrate roles for Wnt/β-catenin signaling in mammary development and breast cancer [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Multiple Wnts are expressed throughout mammary development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Mice expressing Wnt inhibitors, or deficient in Lef-1, show defective embryonic mammary development, and loss of the Wnt coreceptor, LRP5/6, impairs postnatal development [6]–[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Both loss- and gain-of-function studies have established roles for Wnt4 and Wnt5a in ductal side branching and for β-catenin signaling in alveologenesis and survival [10]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Although β-catenin mutations have not been found in breast cancer, pathway activation due to loss of the extracellular Wnt antagonist, sFRP1, is a frequent event [4], [5], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In mice, expression of Wnt1 and stabilized β-catenin (ΔN89β-catenin) under the control of the mouse mammary tumor virus LTR (MMTV) induces precocious mammary development and adenocarcinoma formation [13], [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Tumors induced by both transgenes are enriched in side-population content and cells expressing primitive cell markers that exhibit greater colony-forming capabilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these studies have lead to the hypothesis that canonical Wnt/β-catenin signaling predisposes mice to breast cancer by amplifying stem/progenitor populations [4], [18]–[22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have shown that only a minor subpopulation of human breast tumor cells can propagate tumors [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Such tumor-initiating cells (TICs) share with normal stem cells the ability to self-renew and to generate differentiated progeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Although commonly referred to as cancer stem cells (CSCs), it is unclear whether TICs derive from stem cells and/or from less potent progeny that acquire stem cell properties during transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the contribution of distinct cancer stem cells to breast cancer heterogeneity remains obscure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Candidate mammary stem and progenitor populations have been identified by ultrastructural features, expression of stem cell antigen-1 (Sca-1), and ability to efflux Hoechst 33342 dyes, which upon cell sorting generates a side-population [24]–[26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Recent sorting studies of murine mammary cells have identified a subpopulation, with a lineage-depleted (Lin−)/CD24low/CD29/49fhigh/ Sca-1−/keratin (K)14+ profile, that are enriched in “mammary repopulating units” (MRUs), which have a parent-progeny relationship with a second Lin−/CD24high/CD29/49flow subpopulation of alveolar-limited progenitors expressing a predominantly luminal K18+ profile [21], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Other studies have described luminal progenitor populations with CD24high/CD133−/K18+ and Lin−/CD24+/CD29low/CD61+ K14+ profiles [28], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>A study on human breast strongly supports the concept of a multipotent stem cell located within a ductal luminal niche that expresses multiple keratins [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Recently the connection between the physiological role of Wnt signaling in stem cells and its capacity to induce cancer when upregulated has been exploited to identify intestinal stem cells by virtue of their expression of a Wnt-responsive gene, Lgr5, that was initially found to be upregulated in colonic tumors [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>This study suggests that identifying cell-types that respond to Wnt signaling may be an alternative route to identify and illuminate the relationship between mammary stem/progenitor cells and cancer stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>With this aim in mind, we employed Wnt-responsive conductin/Axin2 reporter genes to identify and isolate cells showing transcriptional response to expression of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 transgenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Our results show that these transgenes lead to activation of the canonical Wnt pathway in distinct cell-types displaying progenitor and stem cell characteristics and induce tumors with different phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A further source of disparity between these tumors arises from the unique ability of Wnt1 to influence multiple cells types within the gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>We show that these profound effects correlate with focal induction of Hedgehog (Hh) pathway activity within subpopulations of stromal and basal (K14+/p63+) cells found exclusively within the Wnt-1 tumor microenvironment, as well as, in and around melanocytic hyperplastic nevi, which form a hallmark of all MMTV-Wnt1 mammary glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>These data show that Hh pathway activation is linked to Wnt-1-induced mammary tumor onset and nevi formation and suggest that Hedgehog pathway activation maybe a critical component and useful marker of breast tumors arising from unopposed Wnt1 ligand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin show phenotypic disparity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin induce precocious mammary development and adenocarcinoma formation [13], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>However, the two types of transgenic lines differ in their lactational competence [13], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This functional disparity led us to examine the respective mammary phenotypes for morphological differences that may yield insight into the corresponding pathobiological mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In glands expressing MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin acini budded directly from ductal borders (Fig. 1A), and were associated with spindle-shaped K14+ basal cells (Fig. 1B), which resembled flattened myoepithelial cells of normal alveoli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, the ducts, visualized by a ductal luminal cell marker, latent transforming growth factor-β-binding protein (LTBP)1-lacZ (Fig. 1C, E), were similar to those of controls (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MMTV-Wnt1 expression induced pronounced ductal changes, including hyperbranching (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These hyperplasias were encased in a coherent thick K14+ cell layer (Fig. 1G), which resembled the myoepithelial layers ensheathing normal ducts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Ductal contortion (Fig. 1H), cyst formation (Fig. 1I), and lumenal occlusions (Fig. 1J) were prominent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The cellular composition and architecture of the tumors induced by the transgenes also showed subtle but important differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Tumors from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice contained many more K18+ than K14+ cells and were hormone receptor-negative (Fig. 2A–C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>These frequently retained well-differentiated acinar polarization, with luminal cells expressing apical mucin (MUC)1 (Fig. 2D) and showing basal deposition of laminin V (Fig. 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Stromal cells, detected by vimentin antibodies, were sparse (Fig. 2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Tumors from MMTV-Wnt1 mice displayed bi-layered papillary arrays of cells, showed an equal ratio of K14+/K18+ cells and expressed hormone receptors (Fig. 2G–I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>They showed loss of polarized organization; indicated by reduced MUC1 expression (Fig. 2J), frequent laminin V accumulation in patches (Fig. 2K), and stromal hypertrophy (Fig. 2L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, expression of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin induced expansion of hormone-receptor-negative, K18+ cells, which maintained alveolar features and were lactationally competent, whereas MMTV-Wnt1 expression significantly expanded K14+ cells in addition to both hormone-receptor-positive and -negative K18+ cells and lead to perturbed ductal formation and lactational failure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic differences between MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 hyperplasias. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Mammary glands from 12 week-old virgin MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin (MMTV-ΔN89β-cat) (A–E) and MMTV-Wnt1 (F–J) mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Mammary whole mounts stained with carmine (A, F) or X-Gal (C, D, H, I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Sections stained immunohistochemically with anti-K14 antibodies to detect the basal cells (B, G) or with X-Gal to detect luminal LTBP1-lacZ expression and nuclear fast red (E, J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Note mammary glands from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice show alveolar hyperplasia (A, B) but their ductal system (C, E) is comparable to controls (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Mammary glands from MMTV-Wnt1 mice show hyperbranching (F), K14+ cell ensheathment (G), ductal constriction (arrows H, J) and large ductal cysts (arrows F, I). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 tumors have distinct cellular composition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Tumor sections from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin (MMTV-ΔN89β-cat) (A–F) and MMTV-Wnt1 (G–L) stained with antibodies as indicated against K14, K18, estrogen receptor (ER), MUC1, laminin, and vimentin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Note distorted laminin deposition (Arrows in K) and stromal hyperplasia (L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin activate the canonical signaling pathway within different cell-types </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Based on the disparate phenotypes described above, we hypothesized that ΔN89β-catenin and Wnt1 transform different progenitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The MMTV-LTR is expressed within mammary luminal epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Therefore β-catenin's transcriptional effects are restricted to cells within this layer, whereas Wnt1, a secreted factor, can act in an autocrine and/or paracrine fashion in any cells that expresses a Wnt1 receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To determine which cell-types respond to the expression of these transgenes via activation of the canonical pathway, we crossed MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 mice to Axin2-d2EGFP transgenic and Conductin+/lz heterozygous lacZ knock-in reporter lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The Axin2/Conductin gene is expressed constitutively in response to canonical Wnt/β-catenin signaling and its product negatively regulates the pathway [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Despite uniform expression of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin within the luminal epithelium [13], transcriptional response, detected by Conductin-lacZ reporter expression, was restricted to a subpopulation of luminal cells scattered along secondary and tertiary ducts (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In early hyperplasia, approximately one luminal cell per alveolus expressed Conductin-lacZ (Fig. 3B) and these cells became more prominent as the hyperplasia increased but the main ducts remained devoid of β-catenin signaling (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In contrast, mammary glands from MMTV-Wnt1 mice showed a strikingly uniform Conductin-lacZ expression pattern along the entire mammary ductal system (Fig. 3D and F) and the reporter was found exclusively within basal cells (Fig. 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>These distinct cellular patterns of transcriptional response were maintained in tumors (Fig. 4A–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In tumors from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice, Conductin-lacZ was expressed within cells expressing the luminal marker K18 and absent from K14+ cells (Fig. 4A–C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Wnt1 tumors showed the converse expression pattern; Conductin-lacZ expressing cells were restricted to a single K14+/K18− layer of the bilayered papillary tumors (Fig. 4D–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, these data show that a subset of K18+ cells respond to ΔN89β-catenin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>K18+ luminal epithelial cells from MMTV-Wnt1 mice fail to respond, suggesting they lack a Wnt1 receptor, or that autocrine canonical pathway activity is suppressed by non-canonical antagonism within this cell-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In contrast, K14+ cells show a robust paracrine canonical response to Wnt1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Conductin-lacZ is expressed in K18+ subpopulations in MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and K14+ subpopulations in MMTV-Wnt1 hyperplasia. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Canonical signaling is activated in disparate cell-types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Sections of hyperplastic glands from (A–C) Conductin+/lz/MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice, and (D–F) Conductin+/lz/MMTV-Wnt1 mice stained with X-gal to detect Conductin-lacZ expression (blue), a reporter of canonical Wnt signaling, and stained with antibodies against K14 and K18 (brown) as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Note the stromal hypertrophy surrounding Wnt1 hyperplastic ducts (E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Conductin-lacZ is expressed in K18+ subpopulations in MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and K14+ subpopulations in MMTV-Wnt1 tumors. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Sections of tumors from (A–C) Conductin+/lacZ/MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin, and (D–F) Conductin+/lacZ/MMTV-Wnt1 mice stained with X-gal to detect Conductin-lacZ expression (blue), a reporter of canonical Wnt signaling, and stained immunohistochemically with antibodies against K14 and K18 (brown) as indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 amplify cells with distinct CD24/49f stem/progenitor profiles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To further compare the cell-type composition of tumors, we isolated mammary epithelial cells (MECs) from tumors of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 mice and investigated their expression of CD24 and CD49f. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>These markers separate MECs from wt mice into two roughly equal populations by flow cytometry: CD24highCD49flow and CD24lowCD49fhigh (Fig. 5G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The most rightward and upward shifted cells within each of these populations have been reported to be enriched in colony-forming cell (CFC) comprising alveolar progenitors and multipotent mammary repopulating units (MRUs), respectively [27]. ΔN89β-catenin tumors were enriched for CD24highCD49flow MECs (Fig. 5A) (62% compared to 37% CD24lowCD49fhigh). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Wnt1 tumors were enriched for CD24lowCD49fhigh MECs (Fig. 5D) (65%, compared to 35% CD24highCD49flow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>To characterize cells undergoing an active transcriptional response to expression of these transgenes, we crossed MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin lines to the Axin2-d2EGFP reporter mouse, isolated tumor MECs from the bitransgenic progeny and analyzed them for enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and CD24/CD49f expression by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the even distribution of EGFP− cells from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice between the two major CD24/CD49f cell populations (Fig. 5B), cells expressing high levels of EGFPhi (top 15%) (Fig. 5C) fell exclusively within the CD24highCD49flow subpopulation and showed an upward rightward shift in mean fluorescence intensity, suggestive of CFCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To test the functional significance of these observations, we compared the ability of EGFP+, EGFP− and total MECs from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice to form colonies at limiting dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>EGFP+ cells showed 3-5-fold greater colony forming efficiency compared to total sorted cells, and a corresponding depletion of colony-forming efficiency was found within the EGFP− cell population (Fig. 5H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence analysis showed that EGFP+ cells produced colonies composed of mixed progeny, with some cells expressing K8 and others K14 (Fig. 5I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>We conclude that ΔN89β-catenin signaling cells within tumors show marker expression profiles that mirror those of CFC alveolar progenitors from normal gland and are bipotent, giving rise to luminal and basal cell types in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In contrast, EGFP− (Fig 5E) and EGFPhi (Fig. 5F) cells from MMTV-Wnt1 mice were distributed in both CD24/CD49f subpopulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>However, the EGFPhi (Fig. 5F) cells were skewed to the right side of the CD24highCD49flow population and those within the CD24lowCD49fhigh subpopulation showed an upward rightward shift. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>These shifts are consistent with the profiles of CD61+/K14+ progenitors and of MRUs that have been shown in previous reports to have CSC capabilities [22], [27], [28], [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 tumors show expansion of distinct CD24/CD49f cell populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>CD24/CD49f marker profile of (A) total, (B) EGFP- and (C) EGFPhi cells from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Note the enrichment and upward shift of EGFPhi cells within the CD24high/CD49flow subpopulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>CD24/CD49f marker profile of (D) total, (E) EGFP- and (F) EGFPhi cells from MMTV-Wnt1 tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Note EGFPhi cells are shifted rightward within the CD24high/CD49flow subpopulation and upward within the CD24low/CD49fhigh subpopulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>CD24/CD49f marker profile of (G) total cells from a wt littermate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>(H) EGFP+ cells from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin tumors show higher colony forming efficiency than EGFP(−) and total sorted cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>(I) Immunofluorescence analysis shows these EGFP+ cells are generate colonies containing K14+ and K8+ cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 expression induces Hh pathway activation within the tumor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Wnt and Hh pathways are frequently coupled in the cross-talk between stem cells and their stromal niche and an essential linkage between these pathways has been documented recently in basal cell skin cancer [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To determine if the Hh pathway was activated in hyperplasia and tumors of MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice, we crossed these lines to Gli1+/lz reporter mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Hh signals are transduced by members of the Gli protein family, (Gli1-3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Gli1 is both a transcriptional target gene and positive amplifier of the pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Its expression is strictly dependent upon Hh signaling and thus provides a reliable reporter of Hh pathway activation [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Hh pathway activity is repressed within the mammary tree of non-transgenic Gli1+/lz control glands and Gli1-lacZ reporter expression was restricted to lymphatics (Fig. 6A) [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Similarly, hyperplasia and tumors from MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin;Gli1+/lz mice showed no evidence of Gli1-lacZ expression within the epithelial and stromal compartments (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In contrast, tumors derived from MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mice showed robust Gli1-lacZ expression within stromal cells and a minor subset of basal cell-types, some of which expressed p63 (Fig. 6C, D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Importantly, this reporter expression was restricted to the tumor bed and not observed in hyperplasia (Fig. 6E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrate that Wnt1 expression leads to aberrant Hh pathway activation within the Wnt1 tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Hh pathway activity within the MMVT-Wnt1 tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Gli1-lacZ expression is restricted to lymphatic vessels (arrow) in mammary whole mounts of (A) control Gli1+/lz mice, and absent from tumor sections from (B) MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin;Gli1+/lz mice, but is strongly expressed in (C) MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz tumor whole mounts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In sections of MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz tumors (D) Gli1-lacZ expression is found within stromal cells and occasional p63+ cells (arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(E) Hyperplastic MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mammary whole mounts from 12 week-old mice show lack of reporter expression within unstained mammary hyperplasia and restriction to lymphatics and melanocytic hyperplasia (boxed area). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 expression results in dramatic accumulation and differentiation of melanocytes along the lactiferous sinus and primary ducts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Another striking linkage between Hh pathway activation and MMTV-Wnt1 expression was found in melanocytic hyperplasia under the nipple region (Fig. 6E box). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>A hallmark of mammary glands from pigmented MMTV-Wnt1 mice was accumulation of melanin around the trunk and primary mammary branches (Fig. 7A, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Large black aggregates emanating from the nipple mesenchyme formed spider-like extensions into the mammary fat-pad that could be observed by eye (n = 29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>These were absent from mammary glands of pigmented wt (n = 17) and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin (n = 5) mice and from all albino mice regardless of genotype (n = 34 Wnt; n = 10 ΔN89β-catenin; n = 13 wild-type). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Mammary whole-mounts (Fig. 7A) and sections (Fig. 7B–C) from pigmented MMTV-Wnt1 mice revealed melanin deposition within the basal layer, stromal cells and occasionally within the secretions of the primary lactiferous ducts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>However, immunohistochemical analysis with antibodies against the S100β melanocyte marker revealed large numbers of dendritic melanocytes in albino as well as pigmented Wnt1 mice (Fig. 7C, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>We conclude that Wnt-1 expression leads to migration, accumulation and differentiation of melanocytes along the primary mammary ducts and that these cells are not present in MMTVΔN89β-catenin and wt mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0004537-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004537.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Melanocytic hyperplasia associated with Hh pathway activity is a hallmark of all MMTV-Wnt1 mammary glands. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Mammary whole mount and sections from pigmented MMTV-Wnt1 mice show melanin deposition (A, B) and presence of melanocytes (C) detected by anti-S100β (DAKO #Z0311). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Whole mounts and sections from albino (D, G) and pigmented (E) MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1lz/+ mice show Gli1-lacZ expression around the primary ducts localizing with melanin (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Conductin-lacZ expression (blue) does not colocalize with S100β+ (brown) (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However a minor subset of S100β+ melanocytes (brown) (red arrows) and many of their neighboring stromal cells express the Gli1-lacZ reporter (blue) (G). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004537.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>To investigate whether Wnt1 induces these effects on melanocytes through canonical signaling and/or involves Hh pathway activation, we examined whole mounts of bitransgenic MMTV-Wnt1;Conductin+/lz and MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mice for reporter expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Conductin-Gal was restricted to basal cells and absent from the underlying stroma where melanocytes reside (Fig. 7F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In contrast, prominent Gli1-lacZ reporter expression was observed exclusively around the primary ducts of all MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mice (n = 8) (Fig. 7D, E), colocalizing with the melanotic aggregates of pigmented MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mice (n = 4) (Fig. 7E) and within a subset melanocytes identified by S100β staining and many neighboring fibroblasts in albino MMTV-Wnt1;Gli1+/lz mice (n = 4) (Fig. 7D, G). Gli1-lacZ expression was absent from corresponding regions of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin;Gli1+/lz (n = 4) and control Gli1+/lz (n = 2) glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We conclude that MMTV-Wnt1 expression induces aberrant melanocyte accumulation and differentiation within the fatpad and this event does not involve canonical pathways but correlates with robust Hh pathway activity within the stroma and a minor melanocyte subpopulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The key findings of this study are that MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 induce distinct tumors, activate canonical signaling in disparate cell-types, and MMTV-Wnt1 alone results in focal Hh pathway activity within the mammary tumor microenvironment and in and around melanocytic hyperplasia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 induce canonical signaling in distinct cell-types </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 tumors express primitive cell markers and are enriched in cell populations with stem/progenitor features [19]–[21], [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Our work extends these findings by identifying the cell-types that undergo a canonical response to transgene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Despite uniform MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin expression within the luminal epithelium [13], our results show that a specific subset of luminal cells express the transcriptional reporter, Conductin-lacZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These β-catenin-responsive cells display a hormone-receptor-negative [38], K18+CD24highCD49flow profile, and generate colonies containing both K8+ and K14+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Thus, they exhibit the expected location, molecular profile and functional bipotency ascribed to alveolar progenitor populations from normal mammary glands [21], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>These features, in conjunction with the overwhelmingly alveolar-like phenotype of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin hyperplasia, strongly support the hypothesis that MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin acinar tumors develop from expansion of alveolar progenitors, or by skewing the lineage of a bipotent alveolar/ductal progenitor towards an alveolar fate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>This concept is reminiscent of K14-ΔN80β-catenin effects on skin appendage fate and consistent with our previous findings that known regulators of alveolar progenitor determination, expansion and differentiation influence the MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin-phenotype [18], [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Many studies have assumed that MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 exert a similar tumorigenic effect and have studied these models interchangeably. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Where phenotypic differences have been noted Wnt1's potential to activate non-canonical pathways has been speculated upon but not experimentally addressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Our results show that one definitive source of disparity between these models lies in the failure of Wnt1 to induce autocrine canonical signaling and its ability instead to induce a robust paracrine canonical response within a basally located K14+ cell population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Several pieces of data suggest that this Wnt1-responsive K14+ cell population consists of a stem cell or early bipotent progenitor population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>First, the EGFPhi expressing cells within the CD24lowCD49high subpopulation is skewed towards higher CD49f expression, a feature associated with MRU capacity, and depleted of cells with lower CD49f expression, a feature associated with mature myoepithelial populations [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>EGFPhi responding cells that segregate into the CD24highCD49low group are also skewed rightwards and express K14, a profile recently ascribed to a CD61+ bipotent progenitor population shown to have cancer stem cell properties [22], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Second, luminal and basal cell-types from MMTV-Wnt1 tumors share common genetic changes suggesting that the cell-type transformed by Wnt1 is a progenitor of both lineages [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Third, Wnt1 produces ductal defects (see fig 1) in addition to suppressing alveolar secretory differentiation [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these results suggest that MMTV-Wnt1 induces expansion of a multipotent basal cell-type that precedes commitment to the ductal/alveolar as well as luminal/basal lineages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Wnt1 leads to Hh pathway activity in melanocytic hyperplasia and their surrounding stroma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A further source of disparity between the MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin and MMTV-Wnt1 phenotypes relates to the ability of the latter to affect additional surrounding cell-types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Of note, stromal hyperplasia (see Fig. 2L and 3E) is prominent within the early hyperplastic glands and tumors of MMTV-Wnt1 mice but is absent from glands and tumors of MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Another striking example is the dramatic effect on melanocyte populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Our results show that massive melanotic deposits within the mammary fatpad are a hallmark of pigmented MMTV-Wnt1 mice and that large numbers of amelanotic melanocyte precursors accumulate around the primary lactiferous ducts of both pigmented and albino MMTV-Wnt1 animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Murine melanocyte precursors normally reside in the hair follicle bulge and are not detected in the mammary fatpads of wt or MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Although both canonical and non-canonical Wnt signaling have been implicated in promoting melanocyte proliferation, migration and differentiation at other body sites [40], the lack of Conductin-lacZ reporter expression within the mammary melanocytic hyperplasia strongly favors non-canonical signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, our results show a tight correlation between positive Hh signaling within a minor melanocytic subpopulation and their surrounding stromal neighbors and the massive accumulation of mobilized, differentiating melanocytes in MMTV-Wnt1 glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Current literature highlights a dualistic role for Hh signaling in melanocyte biology [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Gli3R repression of Hh signaling is essential for melanoblast specification at certain body regions during development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>However, consistent with our suggestion that Hh pathway activity is linked to melanocytic hyperplasia, one report has shown that positive Hh signaling is a critical determinant of melanoma growth and metastasis [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Importantly, our observations show that Wnt and Hh pathway activity are linked in the induction of these melanocytic accumulations and suggest that these pathways may contribute to pigmentary changes arising close to the nipple in association with an underlying breast carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Wnt1 leads to Hh pathway activity within the mammary tumor microenvironment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A second major site of focal Hh pathway activity is found within MMTV-Wnt1 tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Of note, Hh pathway activity was restricted to the Wnt-1 tumor microenvironment and was not observed within the Wnt-1 hyperplasia and thus correlated with Wnt1 tumor onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Hh pathway repression is essential for embryonic mammary development and repression remains critical to homeostasis in the postnatal gland [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Pathway activation distorts mammary development, and is found in both epithelial and stromal compartments of human breast cancers [37], [43]–[46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, Gli1-lacZ is expressed within a minor subset of p63+ basal cells in Wnt1 tumors and Ihh has been proposed to regulate proliferation of progenitors from stem cells via regulation of p63 isoform expression and to promote human mammosphere formation, considered to be a surrogate in vitro assay of stem cell proliferation [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However the most prominent site of Hh pathway activity in MMTV-Wnt1 mice occurs in stromal cells exclusively within the tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Whether stromal Hh pathway activation is essential for breast tumor onset remains to be determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>However, the importance of this possibility has been underscored by a recent study showing an essential role for stromal Hh pathway activity in supporting tumor cell growth of xenografted pancreatic and colonic human cancers and cell lines [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Given that MMTV-Wnt1 tumors are enriched in cells with stem/progenitor characteristics, we speculate that stromal Hh pathway activity may be indicative of the step when CSCs co-opt bystanders to become complicit in tumor formation by forming a supportive CSC niche. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Currently the relative importance of Hh pathway activity within epithelial and stromal compartments of tumors is a matter of heated debate [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>As MMTV-Wnt1 tumors recapitulate the pattern of activity reported for human breast tumors they may provide as a useful genetic model to dissect the contribution of Hedgehog signaling within these different cell types to tumor onset and progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In summary our data show that Wnt1 and ΔN89β-catenin generate distinct tumors at least in part through activating canonical signaling in distinct progenitors and through Wnt-specific paracrine effects on multiple cell-types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Our data also show that Wnt 1 expression is linked with focal Hedgehog pathway activation in melanocytic nevi and mammary tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>These data suggest Hh pathway activity and pigmentary changes may have utility as indicators of breast tumor onset induced by excess or unopposed Wnt ligand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Animal maintenance and experimental procedures were in accordance with the NIH Guidelines for Animal Care and Use and were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of New York University Medical School. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>MMTV-Wnt1 and MMTV-ΔN89β-catenin mice were as described [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Axin2-d2EGFP, Conductin+/lz, Gli1+/lz, Ltpb1L+/lz were provided by Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Franke Costantini, Columbia University, Alexandra Joyner, Sloan Kettering Institute and Velocigene, Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc. [32], [33], [36], [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Mammary Whole Mount Staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>To detect lacZ expression, mammary glands and tumors were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 1× phosphate buffered saline (PBS) (PFA; Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) for 1 h, washed thrice in rinse buffer (2 mM MgCl2, 0.1% sodium deoxycholate, 0.2% NP40 in PBS) for 1 h each and stained overnight at room temperature in X-gal staining solution (50 mg/ml 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-β-D-galactopyranoside in rinse buffer containing 5 mM potassium ferricyanide, 5 mM potassium ferrocyanide) (Applichem, Cheshire, CT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>After staining, glands and tumors were rinsed in 1× PBS, post-fixed in 4% PFA overnight and processed for paraffin embedding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The tissues were sectioned, counterstained with Nuclear Fast Red (Polyscientific, Bay Shore, NY) and mounted for histological analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>For whole mount analysis, X-gal stained mammary glands were counterstained with carmine, cleared and mounted as described <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mammary.nih.gov/tools/">http://mammary.nih.gov/tools/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Histology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Tissues were either fixed in PFA and X-gal stained as described above or fixed in 10% phosphate buffered formalin overnight, then processed and embedded in paraffin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>4 µ sections were deparaffinized with xylene (or citrosolve for X-gal stained tissue) and rehydrated through a graded series of ethanol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Citric acid antigen retrieval was performed for all antibodies by microwaving in 6.53 mM sodium citrate pH 6.0 for 30 min at 1.21 kilowatts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Rabbit antibodies against K14 (cat# PRB155P, Covance, Berkeley, CA) (1∶2000), MUC1 (1∶500) (Abcam), laminin (1∶100) (Sigma), S-100β (1∶4000)(Dako #Z0311), mouse antibodies against K18 (cat# 61028, Progen Biotechnik, Heidelberg, Germany), estrogen receptor (1∶500) (DAKO, Carpinteria, CA), and guinea-pig anti-vimentin (1∶1000)(Progen) were detected using biotin labeled secondary antibodies (Vector Labs, Burlingame, CA) (1∶1000) in conjunction with streptavidin peroxidase (Fisher Scientific, Suwanne, GA) that was colorimetrically detected using diaminobenzidine (cat# K3466, DakoCytomation, Carpinteria, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>For S-100β staining, sections were subjected to antigen retrieval with 0.1% trypsin (Sigma #T0303), 0.1% CaCl2 in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.6 at 37°C for 45 min in a humidified chamber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Slides were washed continuously under running tap water for 5 min and processed for immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Azure B staining was performed as described [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Mammary Epithelial Cell Isolation and Flow Cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Mammary glands and tumors were minced and digested for 6–7 h at 37°C in EpiCult-B Medium supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum (FBS) containing 300 U ml−1 collagenase and 100 U ml−1 hyaluronidase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Digests were pipetted 8–12 times and vortexed for 5 seconds every hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>After dissociation, cells were pelleted at 350×g for 5 min and resuspended in a 1∶4 mixture of Hanks' Balanced Salt Solution containing 2% FBS (HF) and ammonium chloride and centrifuged again. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Cell pellets were gently dissociated for 3 min in 5 ml of pre-warmed 0.25% trypsin-EDTA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>10 ml of cold HF was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Cells were pelleted by centrifugation and resuspended for 1 min in 5 mg ml−1 of pre-warmed dispase II containing 0.1 mg ml−1 DNase I, then diluted with 10 ml of cold HF and filtered through a 40-µm mesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>All reagents were from StemCell Technologies Inc. [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>All antibodies were purchased from BD Pharmingen unless otherwise noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Cells at a concentration of 2.5×106 per 100 µl of 2% bovine serum albumin (BSA) were incubated on ice for 30 min with primary antibodies: 0.5 ng/ml of biotinylated TER119 (cat# 553672), CD31 (cat# 558737), CD45 (553078), CD24-phycoerythrin (PE) (cat# 553262), and 0.25 ng/ml of CD49f-allophycocyanin (APC) (cat# FAB13501A, Minneapolis, MN, R&amp;D Systems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed once in 200 µl 2% BSA, stained with 1.5 ng/ml of streptavidin-Alexa488 on ice for 30 min, washed again and resuspended in 2% BSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>1 µg/ml of 7-aminoactinomycin D (7-AAD) (cat# 00-6993-50, San Diego, CA, eBioscience) was added just prior to data acquisition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometric data was acquired on a FACS Caliber cytometer at the NYU Skirball FACS Core Facility and analyzed using FlowJo software [27] </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Colony-Forming Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>NIH-3T3 cells were irradiated in suspension at 20Gy and seeded as a feeder layer 24 h prior to assay, at a concentration of 1.9×104 cells/well in 24-well plates (Corning Incorporated, Corning, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Lineage+ cells were depleted prior to sorting using the EasySep Cell Biotin Selection Kit (StemCell Technologies Inc.) using TER119, CD31, and CD45 and CD140A (eBioscience) antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>GFP+, GFP− and Total Sorted tumor cells were sorted into 1 ml of 100% FBS using a MoFlo cell sorter, excluding cell debris, cell doublets, and autofluorescent cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Sorted cell populations were centrifuged at 350 g for 3 mins, resuspended in a 300 µl, assessed for viability in 50% Trypan Blue and plated at limiting dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Media (EpiCultB+bullet, 5% FBS, 100 U/ml Penicillin/Streptomycin, 1 µg/ml Ciprofloxacin, 0.25 µg/ml Fungizone) was changed 48 h later to medium lacking FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Colonies were fixed after 6 days in 50∶50 acetone∶methanol at −20°C for 3 min and counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Cells were stained with primary antibodies to K8 (Progen Cat#65138) and K14 (1∶2,000, Covance PRB-155P) for 30 min, washed three times in PBS, stained with goat anti-mouse (1∶100, Invitrogen Cat#A11801) and donkey anti-rabbit (1∶100, Chemicon Cat#AP182C) followed by three washes in PBS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We thank Irina Pechenkina for technical assistance and Peter Lopez, NYU Cancer Center FACS Core and Shane Meehan, Department of Dermatopathology for advice and assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by NIH-R01-GM47429, Susan G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Komen Foundation BCTR0504557 and by training awards from Philip Morris International, Kimmel Foundation, and DOD-BC074763, Susan G Komen PDF0707333, NIH-NRSA F31CA119940-02 and F31CA130137. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0004537-Gat1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>1 GatUDasguptaRDegensteinLFuchsE 1998 De novo hair follicle morphogenesis and hair tumors in mice expressing a truncated β-catenin in skin. Cell 95 605 614 9845363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Huelsken1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>2 HuelskenJVogelRErdmannBCotsarelisGBirchmeierW 2001 beta-Catenin controls hair follicle morphogenesis and stem cell differentiation in the skin. Cell 105 533 545 11371349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Malanchi1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>3 MalanchiIPeinadoHKassenDHussenetTMetzgerD 2008 Cutaneous cancer stem cell maintenance is dependent on beta-catenin signalling. Nature 452 650 653 18385740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Hatsell1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>4 HatsellSRowlandsTHiremathMCowinP 2003 Beta-catenin and Tcfs in mammary development and cancer. J Mammary Gland Biol Neoplasia 8 145 158 14635791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Cowin1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>5 CowinPRowlandsTRHatsellS 2005 Cadherins and Catenins in Breast Cancer. Current Opinions in Cell Biology in press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Andl1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>6 AndlTReddySTGaddaparaTMillarSE 2002 WNT signals are required for the initiation of hair follicle development. Dev Cell 2 643 653 12015971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-vanGenderen1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>7 van GenderenCOkamuraRMFarinasIQuoR-GParslowTG 1994 Development of several organs that require inductive epithelial-mesenchymal interactions is impaired in Lef-1 deficient mice. Genes and Development 8 2691 2704 7958926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Buhler1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>8 BuhlerTADaleTCKiebackCHumphreysRCRosenJM 1993 Localization and quantification of Wnt-2 gene expression in mouse mammary development. Developmental Biology 155 87 96 8416847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Lindvall1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>9 LindvallCEvansNCZylstraCRLiYAlexanderCM 2006 The Wnt signaling receptor Lrp5 is required for mammary ductal stem cell activity and Wnt1-induced tumorigenesis. J Biol Chem 281 35081 35087 16973609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Bradbury1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>10 BradburyJMEdwardsPANiemeyerCCDaleTC 1995 Wnt-4 expression induces a pregnancy-like growth pattern in reconstituted mammary glands in virgin mice. Dev Biol 170 553 563 7649383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Brisken1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>11 BriskenCHeinemanAChavarraTElenbaasBTanJ 2000 Essential function of Wnt-4 in mammary gland development downstream of progesterone signaling. Genes and Development 14 650 654 10733525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Roarty1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>12 RoartyKSerraR 2007 Wnt5a is required for proper mammary gland development and TGF-beta-mediated inhibition of ductal growth. Development 134 3929 3939 17898001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Imbert1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>13 ImbertAEelkemaRJordanSFeinerHCowinP 2001 ΔN89ß-catenin induces precocious development, differentiation, and neoplasia in mammary gland. J Cell Biology 153 555 568  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Hsu1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>14 HsuWShakyaRCostantiniF 2001 Impaired mammary gland and lymphoid development caused by inducible expression of Axin in transgenic mice. J Cell Biol 155 1055 1064 11739413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Tepera1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>15 TeperaSBMcCreaPDRosenJM 2003 A beta-catenin survival signal is required for normal lobular development in the mammary gland. J Cell Sci 116 1137 1149 12584256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Ugolini1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>16 UgoliniFCharafe-JauffretEBardouVJGeneixJAdelaideJ 2001 WNT pathway and mammary carcinogenesis: loss of expression of candidate tumor suppressor gene SFRP1 in most invasive carcinomas except of the medullary type. Oncogene 20 5810 5817 11593386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Tsukamoto1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>17 TsukamotoAGrosschedlRGuzmanRParslowTVarmusH 1988 Expression of the int-1 gene in transgenic mice is associated with mammary gland hyperplasia and adenocarcinomas in male and female mice. Cell 55 619 625 3180222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Rowlands1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>18 RowlandsTMPechenkinaIVHatsellSJPestellRGCowinP 2003 Dissecting the roles of beta-catenin and cyclin D1 during mammary development and neoplasia. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100 11400 11405 13679587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Li1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>19 LiYWelmBPodsypaninaKHuangSChamorroM 2003 Evidence that transgenes encoding components of the Wnt signaling pathway preferentially induce mammary cancers from progenitor cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100 15853 15858 14668450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>20 LiuBYMcDermottSPKhwajaSSAlexanderCM 2004 The transforming activity of Wnt effectors correlates with their ability to induce the accumulation of mammary progenitor cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 101 4158 4163 15020770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Shackleton1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>21 ShackletonMVaillantFSimpsonKJStinglJSmythGK 2006 Generation of a functional mammary gland from a single stem cell. Nature 439 84 88 16397499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Vaillant1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>22 VaillantFAsselin-LabatMLShackletonMForrestNCLindemanGJ 2008 The mammary progenitor marker CD61/beta3 integrin identifies cancer stem cells in mouse models of mammary tumorigenesis. Cancer Res 68 7711 7717 18829523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-AlHajj1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>23 Al-HajjMWichaMSBenito-HernandezAMorrisonSJClarkeMF 2003 Prospective identification of tumorigenic breast cancer cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100 3983 3988 12629218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Chepko1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>24 ChepkoGSmithGH 1997 Three division-competent, structurally-distinct cell populations contribute to murine mammary epithelial renewal. Tissue Cell 29 239 253 9149446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Welm1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>25 WelmBETeperaSBVeneziaTGraubertTARosenJM 2002 Sca-1(pos) cells in the mouse mammary gland represent an enriched progenitor cell population. Dev Biol 245 42 56 11969254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Alvi1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>26 AlviAJClaytonHJoshiCEnverTAshworthA 2003 Functional and molecular characterisation of mammary side population cells. Breast Cancer Res 5 R1 8 12559051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Stingl1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>27 StinglJEirewPRicketsonIShackletonMVaillantF 2006 Purification and unique properties of mammary epithelial stem cells. Nature 439 993 997 16395311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-AsselinLabat1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>28 Asselin-LabatMLSutherlandKDBarkerHThomasRShackletonM 2007 Gata-3 is an essential regulator of mammary-gland morphogenesis and luminal-cell differentiation. Nat Cell Biol 9 201 209 17187062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Sleeman1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>29 SleemanKEKendrickHRobertsonDIsackeCMAshworthA 2007 Dissociation of estrogen receptor expression and in vivo stem cell activity in the mammary gland. J Cell Biol 176 19 26 17190790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Villadsen1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>30 VilladsenRFridriksdottirAJRonnov-JessenLGudjonssonTRankF 2007 Evidence for a stem cell hierarchy in the adult human breast. J Cell Biol 177 87 101 17420292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Barker1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>31 BarkerNvan EsJHKuipersJKujalaPvan den BornM 2007 Identification of stem cells in small intestine and colon by marker gene Lgr5. Nature 449 1003 1007 17934449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Lustig1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>32 LustigBJerchowBSachsMWeilerSPietschT 2002 Negative feedback loop of Wnt signaling through upregulation of conductin/axin2 in colorectal and liver tumors. Mol Cell Biol 22 1184 1193 11809809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Jho1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>33 JhoEHZhangTDomonCJooCKFreundJN 2002 Wnt/beta-catenin/Tcf signaling induces the transcription of Axin2, a negative regulator of the signaling pathway. Mol Cell Biol 22 1172 1183 11809808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Cho1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>34 ChoRWWangXDiehnMSheddenKChenGY 2008 Isolation and molecular characterization of cancer stem cells in MMTV-Wnt-1 murine breast tumors. Stem Cells 26 364 371 17975224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Yang1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>35 YangSAndlTGratchtchoukVWangALiuJ 2008 Pathological responses to oncogenic Hedgehog signaling in skin are dependent on canonical Wnt/b-catenin signaling. Nature Genetics 40 1130 1135 19165927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Bai1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>36 BaiCBAuerbachWLeeJSStephenDJoynerAL 2002 Gli2, but not Gli1, is required for initial Shh signaling and ectopic activation of the Shh pathway. Development 129 4753 4761 12361967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Hatsell2"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>37 HatsellSJCowinP 2006 Gli3-mediated repression of Hedgehog targets is required for normal mammary development. Development 133 3661 3670 16914490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Hiremath1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>38 HiremathMLydonJPCowinP 2007 The pattern of beta-catenin responsiveness within the mammary gland is regulated by progesterone receptor. Development 134 3703 3712 17881490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Howe1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>39 HoweLRWatanabeOLeonardJBrownAM 2003 Twist is up-regulated in response to Wnt1 and inhibits mouse mammary cell differentiation. Cancer Res 63 1906 1913 12702582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Yanfeng1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>40 YanfengWSaint-JeannetJPKleinPS 2003 Wnt-frizzled signaling in the induction and differentiation of the neural crest. Bioessays 25 317 325 12655639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Matera1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>41 MateraIWatkins-ChowDELoftusSKHouLIncaoA 2008 A sensitized mutagenesis screen identifies Gli3 as a modifier of Sox10 neurocristopathy. Hum Mol Genet 17 2118 2131 18397875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Stecca1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>42 SteccaBMasCClementVZbindenMCorreaR 2007 Melanomas require HEDGEHOG-GLI signaling regulated by interactions between GLI1 and the RAS-MEK/AKT pathways. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 5895 5900 17392427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Moraes1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>43 MoraesRCZhangXHarringtonNFungJYWuMF 2007 Constitutive activation of smoothened (Smo) in mammary glands of transgenic mice leads to increased proliferation, altered differentiation and ductal dysplasia. Development  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Lewis1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>44 LewisMTRossSStricklandPASugnetCWJimenezE 1999 Defects in mouse mammary gland development caused by conditional haploinsufficiency of Patched-1. Development 126 5181 5193 10529434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Fiaschi1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>45 FiaschiMRozellBBergstromAToftgardRKlemanMI 2007 Targeted expression of GLI1 in the mammary gland disrupts pregnancy-induced maturation and cause lactation failure. J Biol Chem  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Hatsell3"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>46 HatsellSFrostAR 2007 Hedgehog signaling in mammary gland development and breast cancer. J Mammary Gland Biol Neoplasia 12 163 173 17623270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Li2"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>47 LiNSinghSCherukuriPLiHYuanZ 2008 Reciprocal intraepithelial interactions between TP63 and hedgehog signaling regulate quiescence and activation of progenitor elaboration by mammary stem cells. Stem Cells 26 1253 1264 18292212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Dontu1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>48 DontuGWichaMS 2005 Survival of mammary stem cells in suspension culture: implications for stem cell biology and neoplasia. J Mammary Gland Biol Neoplasia 10 75 86 15886888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Yauch1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>49 YauchRLGouldSEScalesSJTangTTianH 2008 A paracrine requirement for hedgehog signalling in cancer. Nature 455 406 410 18754008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-RuiziAltaba1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>50 Ruiz i AltabaA 2008 Therapeutic Inhibition of Hedgehog-Gli Signaling in Cancer: pithelial, Stromal, or Stem Cell Targets. Cancer Cell 14 281 283 18835029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Todorovic1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>51 TodorovicVFrendeweyDGutsteinDEChenYFreyerL 2007 Long form of latent TGF-beta binding protein 1 (Ltbp1L) is essential for cardiac outflow tract septation and remodeling. Development 134 3723 3732 17804598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0004537-Kamino1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>52 KaminoHTamST 1991 Immunoperoxidase technique modified by counterstain with azure B as a diagnostic aid in evaluating heavily pigmented melanocytic neoplasms. J Cutan Pathol 18 436 439 1723081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
