<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-6906</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-6914</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2481430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gb-2008-9-6-r98</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18554412</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-6-r98</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Neo-sex chromosomes in the black muntjac recapitulate incipient evolution of mammalian sex chromosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>zhouq03@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>wangj@genomics.org.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>huangdling@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Wenhui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>kcb@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jinhuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>kcb@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>kcb@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Xiangyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zxy72ct@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Fengtang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref><email>fy1@sanger.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A9" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>wwang@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>CAS-Max Planck Junior Research Group, State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), 32# Jiao-chang Road, Kunming, Yunnan 650223, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Graduate School of Chinese Academy Sciences, 19# Yu-quan Road, Beijing 100039, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>The Institute of Human Genetics, University of Aarhus, Nordre Ringgade 1, DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Southern Denmark, Campusvej 55, DK-5230, Odense M, Denmark</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Beijing Genomics Institute, Bei-shan Road, Shenzhen 518083, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Kunming Cell Bank, State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, 32# Jiao-chang Road, Kunming, Yunnan 650223, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Ickleton Road, Hinxton, Cambridge, CB10 1SA, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>R98</fpage><lpage>R98</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomebiology.com/2008/9/6/R98"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2008 Zhou et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhou et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="short"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The nascent neo-sex chromosomes of black muntjacs show that regulatory mutations could accelerate the degeneration of the Y chromosome and contribute to the further evolution of dosage compensation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The regular mammalian X and Y chromosomes diverged from each other at least 166 to 148 million years ago, leaving few traces of their early evolution, including degeneration of the Y chromosome and evolution of dosage compensation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We studied the intriguing case of black muntjac, in which a recent X-autosome fusion and a subsequent large autosomal inversion within just the past 0.5 million years have led to inheritance patterns identical to the traditional X-Y (neo-sex chromosomes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We compared patterns of genome evolution in 35-kilobase noncoding regions and 23 gene pairs on the homologous neo-sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We found that neo-Y alleles have accumulated more mutations, comprising a wide variety of mutation types, which indicates cessation of recombination and is consistent with an ongoing neo-Y degeneration process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Putative deleterious mutations were observed in coding regions of eight investigated genes as well as cis-regulatory regions of two housekeeping genes. In vivo assays characterized a neo-Y insertion in the promoter of the CLTC gene that causes a significant reduction in allelic expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>A neo-Y-linked deletion in the 3'-untranslated region of gene SNX22 abolished a microRNA target site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Finally, expression analyses revealed complex patterns of expression divergence between neo-Y and neo-X alleles. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The nascent neo-sex chromosome system of black muntjacs is a valuable model in which to study the evolution of sex chromosomes in mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Our results illustrate the degeneration scenarios in various genomic regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Of particular importance, we report - for the first time - that regulatory mutations were probably able to accelerate the degeneration process of Y and contribute to further evolution of dosage compensation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It is believed that in human and other eutherian mammals, the heteromorphic sex chromosomes evolved from a pair of ordinary autosomes between 166 and 148 million years ago [1-4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>After the birth of the sex-determining gene, extensive recombination suppression evolved between proto-X and proto-Y to prevent the sexual reversal along the entirety of the chromosome pair, with the exception of a short 'pseudoautosomal region' (PAR) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Theoretical models predict that proto-Y chromosomes would further suffer a rapid accumulation of deleterious mutations and be subjected to drastic gene loss [6], consistent with only 45 genes surviving on the human Y chromosome as compared with 1,000 functional genes on the X [1,3,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Y degeneration is expected to be driven by multiple forces, including Muller's ratchet, background selection, the Hill-Robertson effect with weak selection, and the 'hitchhiking' of deleterious alleles by favorable mutations [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>These factors can work on both ancient Y and heterosynaptic autosomes with suppressed recombination because of the diminished efficiency of natural selection along them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Newly evolved sex chromosome systems are required to test hypotheses about Y degeneration because ancient Y chromosomes bear few remaining traceable ancestral sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Such cases include the recently originated sex determination system, like that of Silene [8], or 'neo-sex chromosomes', formed through a recent fusion or translocation between an autosome and a sex chromosome followed by extensive recombination suppression, and thus showing inheritance patterns like that of the better known ancient sex chromosomes [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Our current knowledge of neo-sex chromosome evolution is primarily due to extensive work in Drosophila and plants [8,10-12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Most of them focused on degeneration patterns in protein-coding regions of neo-Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, given the elaborate regulation of gene expression [13,14], the scenarios of Y degeneration involving both gradual loss of functions of protein products as well as regulatory disorders remain to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, sex chromosome systems have evolved independently in different phyla many times, creating a need to examine their evolution in different taxa [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Sex chromosomes in mammals, including our own, have different autosomal origins from those of other organisms, involving entirely distinct gene sets in the process of sex determination and dosage compensation [15,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of recombination between the mammalian proto-X and proto-Y was achieved through chromosomal inversions on the Y chromosome, whereas it was achieved through zero crossover in male germline cells in Drosophila [5,17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Finally, different generation time and population size between mammals and other species would have great impact on the rate and patterns of mammalian Y-chromosome degeneration [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Thus, direct investigation of a neo-sex chromosome system in a mammal promises new insights into several fundamental issues, including both mode and tempo of mammalian Y degeneration, and how mammals cope with degenerated Y alleles before the creation of Xist-dependent dosage compensation [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In this study we sought to address these questions using the black muntjac (Muntiacus crinifrons), an Asian barking deer, as the model [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this species, a male-specific extensive chromosome inversion on autosome 4 and fusion of its homolog to the ancient X [21,22] has led to the very recent creation (within the past approximately 0.5 million years) [23] of a neo-sex chromosome system, similar to the inferred creation of the ancient mammalian X-Y system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Such a rare nascent mammalian neo-sex chromosome system provides an unprecedented opportunity to study sex chromosome evolution in mammals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Neo-sex chromosomes in the black muntjac </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The black muntjac is endemic to a narrow region of southeastern China [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Habitat disruption in recent decades has rendered the species one of the most endangered mammals in the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Cytogenetic analysis revealed a compact karyotype, with 2n = 8♀/9♂, and half of the genome forms a pentavalent (Figure 1a) during male meiosis [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The chromosome 4 pair has been shaped by several large chromosomal events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>First, one copy experienced a centric fusion to the regular X chromosome, forming a new 'X+4' (see Additional data file 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In addition, the short arm of chromosome 1 has undergone a male-specific translocation to the homologous chromosome 4, creating a primitive '1p+4' chromosome [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, subsequent inversions involving large part of the primitive 1p+4 were proposed to take place in male black muntjacs (regions from '22a' to '17a'; Additional data file 1) [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We further confirmed this chromosomal rearrangement using dual-color fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) with two bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) clones of the Indian muntjac (Muntiacus muntjac vaginalis) as probes (Figure 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The green signal in the middle of X+4 has switched its location to the distal end of 1p+4 as a result of the inversion (Figure 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Because no inversion loop has been detected during meiosis of male black muntjacs [24], the whole 1p+4 should remain heterosynaptic except for the two distal ends, which are not involved in the inversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These two ends are analogous to those of ancient human Y chromosome, which can still synapse with each other and can thus be regarded new 'PAR's. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The X+4 chromosome can thus be regarded as a 'neo-X', and the 1p+4 as a 'neo-Y' chromosome, because of probable lack of recombination in the inverted region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Neo-sex chromosomes of Muntiacus crinifrons. (a) Paring patterns in male and female black muntjacs during meiosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The black areas on chromosomes represent homosynapsis regions, whereas gray areas represent heterosynapsis regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Cross lines between chromosomes represent homologous recombination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A pentavalent involving five chromosomes will form during meiosis of male black muntjacs, whereas such structures are absent in female black muntjac. (b) Inversion on the neo-Y chromosome revealed by fluorescence in situ hybridization using two Indian muntjac bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) clones, 06G7 (green) and 07B3 (red), as probes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The black muntjac X+4:1p+4 neo-sex chromosome pair comprises approximately one-fifth of the entire genome and thus bears thousands of neo-sex gene pairs [21,24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Although X-autosome fusions were also detected in other muntjac species, such 1p+4 inversion is found exclusively in male black muntjacs [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The absence of such a system within Muntiacus genus, from which black muntjac is estimated to have diverged within the past 0.5 million years [23], indicates a very recent origin, and makes this system the youngest known mammalian neo-sex systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Variation pattern in neo-Y noncoding regions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>To seek molecular evidence for inhibition of recombination and to compare the evolutionary patterns of neo-X and neo-Y chromosomes, we sequenced the intergenic and intronic fragments from the inverted region composing a total of 35.1 kilobases (kb), as well as 12.6 kb from the new 'PAR's and autosomal regions for two male and one female black muntjacs, as well as the orthologous segments from one male Indian muntjac, which is taken as the outgroup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Under neutrality, intraspecific genetic diversity (θ) is expected to be proportional to the effective population size (Ne) times the mutation rate (μ; specifically, θ = 4Neμ) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Therefore, if recombination has authentically ceased between neo-Y and neo-X, then we would expect a reduced DNA polymorphism caused by reduced Ne for the neo-Y regions [6,27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, the polymorphism level of neo-Y should be similar to that of 'PAR' regions or autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the former expectation, we found a significantly lower number of segregating sites (χ2 test, P &lt; 0.01; see Materials and methods [below]) and a lower polymorphism level of neo-Y regions (0.00168 ± 0.00120 versus 0.00190 ± 0.00029) compared with regions that undergo homologous meiotic pairing (Table 1), indicating suppression of recombination between neo-Y and neo-X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Of course, other factors including the Hill-Robertson effect, background selection, hitchhiking effect, or Muller's ratchet could have all reduced the polymorphism level within the investigated noncoding regions [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the 'male-driven evolution' effect, which proposes that the neo-Y would undergo more rounds of cell division per generation in male than in female germlines, would increase the mutation rate and polymorphism level of neo-Y alleles compared with those of neo-X and autosomes [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Our phylogenetic analysis of neo-X and neo-Y sequences in the male black muntjac confirms that the neo-Y alleles have accumulated far more mutations than neo-X (Figure 2; statistically significant, by Tajima's relative rate tests, P &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Dendrogram constructed using noncoding sequences of neo-Y and neo-X fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A total of 35.1-kilobase noncoding sequences of neo-Y and neo-X alleles in the black muntjac and the orthologous sequences in the Indian muntjac as the outgroup were used to construct the dentrogram. 'BM' stands for 'male black muntjac'; 'IM' stands for 'Indian muntjac'; '1'and '2' represent the two male black muntjac individuals separately. (a) Tree constructed by neighbor-joining method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Branch lengths calculated using Kimura's two-parameter method are shown above the corresponding branches. (b) Tree constructed by maximum likelihood method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Branch lengths calculated by baseml in PAML package using 'HKY85' method were shown above the corresponding branches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Segregating sites and polymorphism in noncoding sequences of different genomic regions in two male black muntjacs </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td/><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>neo-Y regions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>PAR/autosomal regions </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Sequenced length (bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>35,156 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>12,653 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Segregating sitesa </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>44 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Segregating sites/kb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>1.68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>3.48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Polymorphism (θw) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>0.00168 ± 0.00120 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>0.00190 ± 0.00029 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>aSegregating sites means total sites with substitutions in the investigated alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Standard deviations calculated based on variance (see Materials and methods) were shown for polymorphism data. bp, base pairs; kb, kilobases; PAR, pseudoautosomal region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>A direct estimate of the degree of male-driven evolution effect (α) on neo-Y can be derived from the comparison of branch lengths of homologous neo-Y and neo-X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We calculated the ratios of neo-Y to neo-X mutations separately from internal, external, and summed branch lengths of neo-Y and neo-X, and we further estimated the α values based on the method proposed by Miyata and coworkers [29] (Table 2; see Materials and methods [below]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Because all of the ratios are higher than 3, the α values estimated from different branches all approach to infinity [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>This indicates a strong male-driven effect on the neo-Y chromosome in the male black muntjac, and a small effect of ancestral polymorphism on the estimate [29-31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that great variation in mutation rates in different genomic regions greatly affect the estimation of α value [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>However, such effects may be limited in our case because the investigated regions are randomly sampled along the neo-Y chromosome and then concatenated together to represent a chromosome-wide estimate (see Materials and methods [below]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Male-specific methylation effects in the germline may also make little contribution to such differences in mutation rate between neo-X and neo-Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>It predicts a greater GC content on neo-X alleles and an elevated rate of C → T transitions on neo-Y alleles [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>However, we detected a similar GC content and an almost identical ratio of GC → AT versus AT → GC substitutions between the neo-Y and neo-X alleles (Additional data file 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Estimation of α (male:female ratio of mutation rate) from different branch lengths in the neo-sex system of black muntjac </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td/><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>neo-Y/neo-X </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>α </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>95% CI of α </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Internal branches </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>4.0442 ± 1.2633 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>25.3848 to ∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>External branches </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3.2768 ± 1.2356 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>4.2578 to ∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Summed branches </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>3.6857 ± 0.8867 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>27.8507 to ∞ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Note that we calculated neo-Y:neo-X ratios of mutation rate from branch lengths designated in Figure 2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>We further calculated their confidence intervals (CIs) and estimated α values following [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The net effect of all of these factors explains why the polymorphism of neo-Y region (0.00168) is one-quarter higher than that of recombining regions (0.00190/4; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Finally, other factors, including sexual selection and population subdivisions, could have effects on the polymorphism pattern [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that it is highly likely that recombination has ceased between the inverted neo-Y region and its homolog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Degeneration in coding regions of neo-Y-linked genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Because of the limited sample size of neo-Y alleles, the polymorphism data exhibit a high degree of variance, and differences between recombining and nonrecombining noncoding regions may only be indicative rather than statistically significant (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>That stated, we continued to seek for other typical evidence of recombination inhibition (accumulation of deleterious mutations due to reduced efficiency of natural selection) [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the degeneration effects of such mutations on neo-Y-linked genes, we characterized 23 gene pairs that are located in the inverted region on the neo-Y chromosome (Additional data file 1), one pair in the neo-Y 'PAR' region, and six pairs on autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>These genes were selected based on the annotations of BAC sequences of the Indian muntjac and cow genomic information in order to represent a diversity of regions across the neo-sex chromosomes [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In total, we obtained about 25 kb cDNA sequences in the inverted region and 6.3 kb in noninverted regions from two male black muntjacs, one female black muntjac, and one male Indian muntjac. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Among the 23 gene pairs located in the inverted region, we observed 14 mutations in eight genes shared by the two males in the protein-coding or untranslated regions (UTRs) of the neo-Y alleles (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In contrast, we detected no variation in genes located in the neo-Y 'PAR' region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>For the autosomal region, only one out of six genes is heterozygous at one site in both the two male black muntjacs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Such an elevated rate of gene evolution exhibited by neo-Y alleles relative to their neo-X homologs and other autosomal genes is consistent with reduced efficiency of natural selection against deleterious mutations in the neo-Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Combined with the variation patterns in intronic and intergenic regions (see the section above), these findings confirmed the recombination inhibition on the neo-Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Summary of neo-Y specific mutations occurred in the cDNA of investigated genes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Gene symbol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Positions on neo-Ya </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Shared mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Polymorphic mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>MYO1D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>17a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>RPL19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>17a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>CACNB1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>17a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>A to Sb </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>CLTC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>17a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Two synonymous substitutions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>ZNF24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>17a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>AKAP7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>3b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Three synonymous substitutions; V to M </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>SYNE1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution; I to V; V to Eb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Two synonymous substitutions </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>SNX22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>46 bp deletion in 3'-UTR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>RIC8B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>1a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>S to Pb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>SCN1A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>3a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>D to Gb </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>MPPE1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>4a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>One synonymous substitution </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>aPositions correspond to chromosomal regions depicted in Figure 1a. bMissense mutations with drastic change of biochemical property of amino acid (polarity or charge), and those in bold represent sites that are highly conserved in other eutherian mammals with published sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We defined 'shared mutations' as those mutations detected in neo-Y alleles in both male black muntjacs, whereas 'polymorphic mutation' are those detected in only one male black muntjac. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Specifically, four nonsynonymous substitutions shared by the two male black muntjacs and two polymorphic nonsynonymous substitutions in one of the males were observed (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Of these six changes, four are highly conserved in amino acids across six other eutherian mammals (human, chimpanzee, dog, mouse, rat, and cow; Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>These four mutations change the polarity or charge of the amino acid, which might severely affect the protein function of the neo-Y copies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We also detected a neo-Y-linked deletion in 3'-UTR of the gene SNX22 in both males investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This deletion abolishes a microRNA target site (see below) and thus may affect stability of the neo-Y allele's mRNA [36,37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>By taking into account the above-described four possible deleterious nonsynonymous mutations and the deletion in the 3'-UTR of SNX22, we conservatively estimate the rate of accumulation of deleterious mutations in exon regions of neo-Y genes to be approximately 0.4 mutations/kb per million years (5 mutations/25 kb per 0.5 million years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>We also estimated that only about 1.3 nonsense mutations would be expected within 25 kb of investigated cDNA sequences, assuming equal chance of mutation at each site (see Materials and methods [below]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Such a low probability of nonsense mutation plus the effect of possible purifying selection give credence to our observation that there were no coding frame-disrupting mutations among the investigated muntjac neo-Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This finding differs from that of a recent investigation conducted in the neo-sex system of Drosophila miranda [38], which found that the neo-Y alleles of 24 out of 64 genes contain premature stop codons and/or frameshift mutations, suggesting an average loss rate of 20 genes per million years in the proto-Y of Drosophila. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Such a drastic difference in the degeneration rate between neo-Y chromosomes of mammals and Drosophila could be attributable to the great differences in their mutation rates (2.2 × 10-9 versus 3.1 × 10-7 per base per year for mammal and Drosophila, respectively) [39,40], generation time, DNA repair efficiencies [41], and effective population size [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>It also suggests that, during the nonlinear process of mammalian Y degeneration [3], the rate of gene loss might be very slow in the early stage of mammalian Y chromosome evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Multiple factors can fix the above neo-Y specific mutations in populations in both coding and noncoding regions, such as Muller's ratchet, background selection, hitchhiking effects on linked deleterious mutations, and faster mutation rate in males [6,28,42,43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Muller's ratchet must have had strong effect on accumulation of these mutations, given that the number of mutant-free chromosomes in a population is positively correlated with the effective population size (Ne) [6,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Because of the usual small Ne values of mammals, mutant-free neo-Y alleles should be vulnerable to an irreversible loss by random drift by the 'ratchet' process, which further leads to accumulation of deleterious mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>It is less likely that the observed neo-Y variations were from either ancestral polymorphism or gene conversion between neo-X and neo-Y, because we used both female black muntjac and Indian muntjac genes as the references to define neo-Y mutations [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It is also less likely that there were recent selective sweeps on the neo-Y of the black muntjac, based on the DNA polymorphism data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Recent strong positive selection would homogenize the neo-Y chromosomes among individuals [6], but we observed many polymorphic sites existing in both noncoding and coding regions of the muntjac neo-Y chromosome (Tables 1 and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Regarding other processes, because of the difficulty associated with collecting population data for such a rare species, we cannot currently test the existence of either a slower rate of adaptive evolution [44] or background selection [6], as previously proposed for D. miranda [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Degeneration in cis-regulatory regions of neo-Y-linked genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have revealed that cis-regulatory regions more often underlie the expression divergence between species and evolution of morphologic diversity [14,45,46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Apart from the direct evidence of degeneration in coding regions presented above, we sought to survey degeneration in regulatory regions on the neo-Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>We analyzed putative promoters expanding 1.5 kb around transcriptional start sites (TSSs) of eight neo-Y genes, which have mutations shared by the two male black muntjacs in their protein-coding/UTR regions (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>We detected neo-Y specific mutations shared by both males present in the investigated regions in three out of eight genes (see Additional Data File 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In order to assess the effect of these mutations on gene expression, allelic promoters were subsequently cloned into pGL3-Basic plasmid in front of a firefly luciferase reporter gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Each plasmid was mixed with a plasmid (pRLs-TK) containing a constitutive promoter driving sea-pansy luciferase reporter gene and co-transfected into Hela cells and male black muntjac fibroblast cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The ratios of firefly luciferase to sea-pansy luciferase, representing normalized promoter activity, were compared between neo-Y-linked promoters and neo-X-linked promoters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We found a significant decrease in neo-Y promoter activity in both Hela and black muntjac cell lines for the CLTC gene (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>We did not detect promoter activities for the cloned fragments of other two genes; specifically, there is no detectable expression of the reporter genes using the cloned fragments as the promoters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The only detected neo-Y specific mutation is a 1 base pair (bp) insertion 55 base pairs upstream of the putative TSS of the CLTC gene shared by both males (Additional data file 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>It is probably the mutation responsible for reducing the transcription level of neo-Y, given that this region was proposed to contribute positively to the core promoter activity by a recent comprehensive analysis of 387 promoter structures in humans [47]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Mutation in the promoter of CLTC gene severely causes downregulation of the neo-Y copy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Dual-reporter assay of promoter activities of CLTC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Standard error among triplicates was shown on the bar. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In addition to mutations in promoter regions, we also detected a neo-Y specific deletion shared by both male black muntjacs in the 3'-UTR of the gene SNX22 as mentioned above (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The abundance of microRNA targeted sequences in this region drove us to investigate whether this deletion would affect such motifs [36,37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Using human microRNA database as a reference, we found that the deleted region on the neo-Y is in fact predicted to be a binding motif targeted by the microRNA hsa-mir-210 [48], which also has orthologs in cow and mouse with validated expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, we found evidence that this same microRNA targeted motif is also deleted because of male-specific RNA editing in intact neo-X alleles (see Additional data file 4); 23 bp overlapping the target sequence are absent from transcripts in males (the edited form is much less frequent in females; see Additional data file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The diminutive size of the involved sequence and lack of splicing boundaries suggest that it is a true RNA editing event rather than a splicing event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>It could be a result of selection against allelic expression imbalance between neo-X and neo-Y or a sign of degeneration of trans factors on neo-Y in males, which control the RNA-editing degree in the 3'-UTR of SNX22. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>One of the fundamental issues in the process of Y-chromosome degeneration is whether it is mainly driven by direct degradation of the protein products (for example, in D. miranda) or reducing gene expression levels on an evolving Y [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that these two processes may work in concert after the immediate recombination suppression on the neo-Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>It is proposed that deleterious mutations with mild fitness effects have a higher rate of fixation on a degenerating Y [6], as illustrated in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>After accumulation of such mutations in the protein coding regions, a subsequent reduced expression of Y would be favored by natural selection to prevent the production of defective Y-linked products [6,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, reduced expression of Y may take place before the accumulation of deleterious mutations in protein products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In the case of CLTC and SNX22, both are broadly expressed genes in most of the human tissues, with orthologs present in all vertebrates whose genomes have been sequenced. CLTC plays an critical role through coating membrane vesicles during endocytosis [49] and SNX22 is a member of the protein family responsible for protein trafficking [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The protein coding regions of these housekeeping genes must be under strong selective constraints, in which no amino acid replacement substitution was detected (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, recent studies showed that cis-regulatory regions - especially microRNA and transcription factor binding sites - usually have lower interspecies sequence conservation compared with protein coding regions, suggesting that regulatory mutations can be more easily fixed [46,51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>This suggests a scenario involving two independent steps of degeneration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>First, mutations in regulatory regions (for example, the promoter of CLTC) would decrease or even turn off the gene expression of the Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Second, decreased expression could reduce selective constraints acting on the protein products of proto/neo-Y-linked genes [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>We note that both these processes could in fact be favored to maintain the optimal gene dose between males and females after the establishment of dosage compensation in X [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Also, both processes would further accelerate the degeneration process in the Y-linked coding regions, which is supported by the recent finding that lower expressed neo-Y genes appear to have a faster accumulation rate of deleterious mutations in D. miranda [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Transcription divergence between neo-Y and neo-X alleles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We semi-quantified and compared the mRNA abundance of neo-Y and neo-X alleles in 11 genes with mutations listed in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Consistent with our promoter assay, CLTC exhibits a lower expression level on neo-Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We found significant expression difference between neo-Y and neo-X allele only in the gene SNX22 (Fisher's exact test, P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>However, this gene was further excluded from the result, together with SCN1A, because of their effects of allelic-biased amplification (see Materials and methods [below]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Eight of the remaining nine genes exhibited differential expression; interestingly, as many showed higher expression on neo-Y as on neo-X (4 versus 4; Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests that neo-Y alleles can be distorted from normal expression level, either downregulated or upregulated, as a result of degenerating control of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Together with the mutation analysis results presented above, the expression patterns of the nine investigated genes exhibit a similar random inactivation mode of gene evolution on a degenerating Y chromosome proposed for D. miranda [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>This model predicts that neo-Y genes are randomly inactivated, regardless of their level of adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 4, the regulation direction of neo-Y genes fluctuates along the neo-Y chromosome, and between some adjacent genes it is even opposite, suggesting that there is no large segment inactivation in the black muntjac's neo-Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Two genes (CLTC and ZNF24) with only synonymous neo-Y mutations exhibited lower expression level, whereas two genes (SYNE1 and AKAP7) with nonsynonymous neo-Y mutations exhibited higher expression level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In addition, the human orthologs of all nine investigated genes are widely expressed housekeeping genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Therefore, whether a neo-Y allele is subjected to expression alteration or the direction of alteration may be not strongly correlated with the characteristics of the gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Expression divergences between nine neo-Y and neo-X gene pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>All expression assays were done in duplicate and double checked in both male individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Mean expression ratios of neo-Y to neo-X are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The genes are arranged following the order from the centromere to the distal region of the 1p+4 chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>This random inactivation pattern indicates that the Xist-dependent dosage compensation[19] has not spread across the whole neo-X chromosome in females within the past 0.5 million years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>This could be attributed to a lack of sufficient time for the establishment of action of Xist on neo-X regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Concordantly, there is also clear molecular evidence that neo-X chromosome in male D. miranda is only partially dosage compensated [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>A recent study [56] showed that even in the 'ancient' sex determination system, such as that of human, 15% of X-linked genes would escape the X inactivation, suggesting that the mammalian dosage compensation mechanism is leaky and its evolution process might be slow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>As suggested by our results in male black muntjacs described above, not all the neo-Y alleles have been subjected to the reduction of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>A nonspecific whole-set dosage compensation mechanism is likely to be seriously deleterious for genes that are transcriptionally active or are undergoing degeneration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that a major regulator of dosage compensation, such as Tsix gene, counteracted Xist RNA on neo-X regions to prevent such deleterious effects [57,58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>However, such delicate regulation is less likely to have been established within such a short evolutionary time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Overall, we propose here that in the early stages, dosage compensation in males might have evolved gradually in a gene-by-gene fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This model is also consistent with the conjecture that evolution is accomplished more through small steps than large changes [59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Charlesworth [18] has proposed two models to describe evolution of dosage compensation in manners similar to the two paths of Y-chromosome degeneration mentioned above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The common features of both models involve the upregulation of gene expression from the proto-X chromosome at the initial stage of Y degeneration [18], which has been suggested by recent global expression analyses conducted in Drosophila, worm, and mammals [60,61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>One model proposed by Charlesworth suggests that there would be selection promoting upregulation of the transcription of X alleles to compensate for defective products, with mutations accumulated in the coding regions of Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, mutations could arise to make the Y alleles less responsive to the regulatory molecules, as exemplified by the case of CLTC in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>It would consequently be a passive process, upregulating the X alleles' expression as a result of the excess of regulatory molecules from the Y alleles [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Further study into the paths of Y chromosome degeneration and comparison of neo-X expression between males and females using more gene pairs would be able to uncover which model mainly contributes to the Y degeneration and evolution of dosage compensation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Here we characterize the recently formed neo-sex system of the black muntjac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This unprecedented system is valuable for studying mammalian Y-chromosome degeneration and evolution of dosage compensation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Our results provided molecular evidence for recombination suppression in the neo-Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>As a result, excess of putatively deleterious mutations were observed in the coding regions of the investigated genes, probably because of the Muller's ratchet effect or background selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, we report here the first study of the role of regulatory mutations during the degeneration process of mammalian Y, and we provide empirical data showing their degenerative effect on gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Such mutations might further accelerate the degeneration and give rise to the evolution of dosage compensation in a gene-by-gene manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that mammalian Y degeneration is a complex gradual process spanning diverse genomic structures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>FISH, separation of 1p+4 by cell Sorter, PCR, and sequence analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Frozen kidney from a male black muntjac, and fibroblast cell lines of another male (KCB82001) and a female black muntjac (KCB81002E) were provided by Kunming Cell Bank of the Chinese Academy of Sciences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Total genomic DNA was extracted using the PURRGENE® DNA Isolation Kit (Gentra Systems Inc., Minneapolis, MN USA), and total RNA was extracted using RNeasy® Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Based on the syntenic relationship among black muntjac, Indian muntjac, and cow and annotation results of Indian muntjac [35], we selected genes randomly distributed along the neo-Y chromosome, PAR region, and autosomal regions for primer designs (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The investigated noncoding regions are introns or flanking intergenic regions of these selected genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>We prepared cell suspensions of the male black muntjac for further FISH and flow sorting of 1p+4 chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The sorting procedure using a FACStar Plus flow sorter (Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ USA) and FISH analysis using Indian muntjac BAC clones (06G7 and 07B3) as probes were performed as previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We used two strategies to discriminate neo-X and neo-Y alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>First, we compared genomic DNA PCR products of Indian muntjac, and female and male black muntjacs, and we inferred neo-Y-specific alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We also used flow-sorted 1p+4 chromosomes as PCR templates to confirm the neo-Y-specific mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The products were subject to sequencing with BigDye Terminators v3.0 (Applied Biosystems) after purification (QIAquick® PCR Purification Kit; Qiagen, Valencia, CA USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Trace data were manually trimmed and aligned from both directions using Lasergene suite (DNASTAR Inc., Madison, WI USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>We concatenated sequences of noncoding regions together for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Segregating sites in these regions were counted and polymorphism data were analyzed using DnaSP 4.0 [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Confidence intervals for polymorphisms were calculated by variance [63]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>If we assume the 1p+4 chromosome can recombine with its homologous chromosome, then its polymorphism level is expected to be similar to that of other autosomes or 'PAR' regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Under such a null hypothesis, we test the significance of difference for polymorphism between 1p+4 and other chromosome regions with χ2 test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Sequences of neo-Y and neo-X alleles were subjected to construction of phylogenetic trees and distance calculation with MEGA 3.1 [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>After removing regions with indels, gene tree was constructed using the neighbour joining and maximum likelihood method, and distances were calculated with Kimura's two-parameter and HKY85 model, respectively [65]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>We used internal, external, and summed branch lengths in Figure 2a to estimate α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Comparison of α estimates from different branch lengths can be used to test whether the ancestral polymorphism have affected the calculation [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>According to the method proposed by Miyata and coworkers [29], Y/X = 3α/(2 +α), where Y and X stand for mutation rate for Y-linked and X-linked sequences, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The variance of Y is V(Y) = Y(1 - Y)/(L [1-4Y/3]2) and the variance of X is V(X) = Y(1 - X)/(L [1-4X/3]2), where L is the length of the sequence [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The variance of Y/X is V(Y/X) = V(Y)/E(X)2 + E(Y)2V(X)/E(X)4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The 95% confidence interval of α was estimated, following the method proposed by Huang and coworkers [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Because Y/X(0.001189/0.000294, internal branches) is greater than 3 based on branch lengths of neo-Y and neo-X in this study, the α value approaches infinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>To estimate expected stop condon number E(S) in the investigated coding regions, we assume that only one substitution would arise per codon, given the extremely young age of this neo-sex system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Assuming the chances of mutation are equal across the sequences, E(S) would be given by the following: E(S)=3μt∑i=1npi, where μ is the estimated mammalian mutation rate measured per base [39], t is the age of the neo-sex system, n is the number of the codon in the investigated region and pi is the probability of a certain codon becoming a stop codon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Promoter assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We predicted the TSS information for black muntjac genes with ClustalW [66], using orthologous human, mouse, and cow sequence as reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Regions expanding 1 kb upstream and 500 bp downstream of the predicted TSS were amplified as putative promoter regions in black muntjacs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The PCR products were subject to TA cloning using pMD19-T vector (TaKaRa, Dalian, Shangdong China) for screening products without PCR artifacts and further enzyme digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The digested PCR product was cloned into pGL3-Basic firefly luciferase vector (Promega, Madison, WI USA) using T4 ligase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Then the vector was transformed into competent cell (TOP10; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA USA) and purified by QIAprep® Spin Miniprep Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Hela and male black muntjac fibroblast cell lines were respectively seeded into 24-well plates to reach densities of 104 to 105 cells per well 24 hours before transfection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Generally, 0.2 μg pGL3-Basic vector with cloned promoter and 0.04 μg Renilla (sea-pansy) luciferase vector (pRL-TK; Promega, Madison, WI USA) were mixed in Opti-MEM® I Reduced Serum Medium (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA USA) and co-transfected into cells with Lipofectamine™ 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>We used pGL-Basic vector as negative control and assayed the luciferase signal with the Dual-Luciferase® Reporter 1000 Assay System (Promega, Madison, WI USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>The ratios of firefly luciferase to sea pansy luciferase were compared between neo-Y-linked promoters and neo-X-linked promoters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>All of the assays for each promoter were done in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Expression abundance analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>We amplified coding regions containing neo-Y-linked mutations from genomic DNA and total RNA (One Step RNA PCR Kit, TaKaRa, Dalian, Shangdong China), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The genomic PCR was used as a control to exclude PCR biases caused by allelic preferential amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Out of 11 genes, we observed biased amplification for only two genes, namely SCN1A and SNX22; the extent of the amplification bias is similar to the copy abundance difference observed in the mRNA assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The reaction was done for 25 to 30 cycles, and the PCR products were cloned into pMD19-T vector (TaKaRa, Dalian, Shangdong China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Twenty to 30 white clones were randomly picked and were subject to further sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The expression ratio of neo-Y and neo-X alleles was determined by counting the number of separate alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>All assays were conducted in duplicate and double checked in both male individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>We further compared the mean expression ratio of duplicates for different genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>BAC, bacterial artificial chromosome; bp, base pair; FISH, fluorescence in situ hybridization; kb, kilobases; Ne, effective population size; PAR, pseudoautosomal region; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; TSS, transcriptional start site; UTR, untranslated region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>WW and FY designed the project, analyzed the data, and wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>QZ, JW, and LH performed the PCR experiments, and expression and promoter assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>WN, JW, YL, and XZ cultivated the fibroblast cells and performed the FISH experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>QZ and JW analyzed the data and wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Additional data files </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The following additional data are available with this paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 1 is a schematic ideogram showing the neo-sex system of Muntiacus crinifrons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 2 is a description with a table showing substitution patterns on noncoding sequences of neo-Y and neo-X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 3 is a table showing neo-Y linked mutations in promoter regions and their effects on allelic expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 4 is a figure showing the RNA editing process of neo-X allele in 3'-UTR of SNX22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 5 is a table showing the RNA editing degree of SNX22 neo-X allele in male black muntjacs is higher than that in female. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Numbers beside the chromosomes represent homologous chromosomes of Muntiacus reevesi defined by comparative chromosomal painting [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Only the proximal region 17b and the distal region below 17a can form homologous pairing and thus recombine with their homologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Regions spanning from '22a' to '17a' cannot recombine because of a large intrachromosomal inversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Regions '8', '17a', and '17b' were derived from short arm of autosome 1 (1p) and further experienced rearrangements, forming the current order along 1p+4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>We also showed location information for the investigated 23 genes [22,35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-S1.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Presented is a description with a table showing substitution patterns on noncoding sequences of neo-Y and neo-X. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-S2.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Presented is a table showing neo-Y linked mutations in promoter regions and their effects on allelic expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-S3.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The UTR region is designated in lower case, whereas the protein-coding region is presented in uppercase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Splicing is unlikely because there is no splicing signal at the boundaries of deleted region and an intron shorter than 30 bp is scarce in mammals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-S4.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Additional data file 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Presented is a table showing the RNA editing degree of SNX22 neo-X allele in male black muntjacs is higher than that in female. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2008-9-6-r98-S5.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>We thank B Charlesworth, D Charlesworth, D Bachtrog, S Roy, K Zeng, and X Li for incisive discussions during preparing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>We thank W Su and H Yu for assistance during cultivating muntjac fibroblast cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>We are also thankful to two anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a CAS-Max Planck Society Fellowship, a NSFC award (No. 30325016), a NSFC key grant (No. 30430400), a 973 Program (No. 2007CB815703-5), and a key project of the State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution of China to WW. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>SkaletskyHKuroda-KawaguchiTMinxPJCordumHSHillierLBrownLGReppingSPyntikovaTAliJBieriTChinwallaADelehauntyADelehauntyKDuHFewellGFultonLFultonRGravesTHouSFLatriellePLeonardSMardisEMaupinRMcPhersonJMinerTNashWNguyenCOzerskyPPepinKRockSThe male-specific region of the human Y chromosome is a mosaic of discrete sequence classes.Nature2003423825U8221281542210.1038/nature01722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>GravesJAEvolution of the testis-determining gene: the rise and fall of SRY.Novartis Found Symp20022448697discussion 97-101, 203-106, 253-107.11990800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>GravesJASex chromosome specialization and degeneration in mammals.Cell20061249019141653003910.1016/j.cell.2006.02.024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>RensWO'BrienPGrutznerFClarkeOGraphodatskayaDTsend-AyushETrifonovVSkeltonHWallisMJohnstonSVeyrunesFGravesJFerguson-SmithMThe multiple sex chromosomes of platypus and echidna are not completely identical and several share homology with the avian Z.Genome Biol20078R2431802140510.1186/gb-2007-8-11-r243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>LahnBTPageDCFour evolutionary strata on the human X chromosome.Science19992869649671054215310.1126/science.286.5441.964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>CharlesworthBCharlesworthDThe degeneration of Y chromosomes.Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci2000355156315721112790110.1098/rstb.2000.0717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>RossMTGrafhamDVCoffeyAJSchererSMcLayKMuznyDPlatzerMHowellGRBurrowsCBirdCPFrankishALovellFLHoweKLAshurstJLFultonRSSudbrakRWenGJonesMCHurlesMEAndrewsTDScottCESearleSRamserJWhittakerADeadmanRCarterNPHuntSEChenRCreeAGunaratnePThe DNA sequence of the human X chromosome.Nature20054343253371577265110.1038/nature03440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>NicolasMMaraisGHykelovaVJanousekBLaporteVVyskotBMouchiroudDNegrutiuICharlesworthDMonegerFA gradual process of recombination restriction in the evolutionary history of the sex chromosomes in dioecious plants.PLoS Biol20053e41563047610.1371/journal.pbio.0030004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>SteinemannMSteinemannSEnigma of Y chromosome degeneration: neo-Y and neo-X chromosomes of Drosophila miranda a model for sex chromosome evolution.Genetica1998102-103409420972029210.1023/A:1017058119760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>BachtrogDCharlesworthBReduced adaptation of a non-recombining neo-Y chromosome.Nature20024163231190757810.1038/416323a </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>LiuZMoorePHMaHAckermanCMRagibaMYuQPearlHMKimMSCharltonJWStilesJIZeeFTPatersonAHMingRA primitive Y chromosome in papaya marks incipient sex chromosome evolution.Nature20044273483521473716710.1038/nature02228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>BachtrogDExpression profile of a degenerating neo-Y chromosome in Drosophila.Curr Biol200616169416991695010510.1016/j.cub.2006.07.053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>BirneyEStamatoyannopoulosJADuttaAGuigoRGingerasTRMarguliesEHWengZSnyderMDermitzakisETThurmanREKuehnMSTaylorCMNephSKochCMAsthanaSMalhotraAAdzhubeiIGreenbaumJAAndrewsRMFlicekPBoylePJCaoHCarterNPClellandGKDavisSDayNDhamiPDillonSCDorschnerMOFieglerHIdentification and analysis of functional elements in 1% of the human genome by the ENCODE pilot project.Nature20074477998161757134610.1038/nature05874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>WittkoppPJHaerumBKClarkAGEvolutionary changes in cis and trans gene regulation.Nature200443085881522960210.1038/nature02698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>OhnoSSex Chromosomes and Sex Linked Genes1967Berlin, Germany: Springer Verlag </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>ZarkowerDEstablishing sexual dimorphism: conservation amidst diversity?Nat Rev Genet200121751851125606910.1038/35056032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>GethmannRCCrossing over in males of higher Diptera (Brachycera).J Hered198879344350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>CharlesworthBModel for evolution of Y chromosomes and dosage compensation.Proc Natl Acad Sci USA1978755618562228171110.1073/pnas.75.11.5618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>PlathKMlynarczyk-EvansSNusinowDAPanningBXist RNA and the mechanism of X chromosome inactivation.Annu Rev Genet2002362332781242969310.1146/annurev.genet.36.042902.092433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>OhtaishiNGaoYTA review of the distribution of all species of deer (Tragulidae, Moschidae and Cervidae) in China.Mammal Rev19902012514410.1111/j.1365-2907.1990.tb00108.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>YangFO'BrienPCWienbergJFerguson-SmithMAEvolution of the black muntjac (Muntiacus crinifrons) karyotype revealed by comparative chromosome painting.Cytogenet Cell Genet199776159163918651010.1159/000134535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>HuangLChiJWangJNieWSuWYangFHigh-density comparative BAC mapping in the black muntjac (Muntiacus crinifrons): molecular cytogenetic dissection of the origin of MCR 1p+4 in the X1X2Y1Y2Y3 sex chromosome system.Genomics2006876086151644334610.1016/j.ygeno.2005.12.008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>WangWLanHRapid and parallel chromosomal number reductions in muntjac deer inferred from mitochondrial DNA phylogeny.Mol Biol Evol2000171326133310958849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>MaKShiLMComparative studies on synaptonemal complexes in spermatocytes of Chinese muntjac Muntiacus reevesi, black muntjac M. crinifrons and Indian muntjac M. muntjak.Yi Chuan Xue Bao1988152822893273674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>YangFCarterNPShiLFerguson-SmithMAA comparative study of karyotypes of muntjacs by chromosome painting.Chromosoma1995103642758758710.1007/BF00357691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>KimuraMThe Neutral Theory of Molecular Evolution1983Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>CaballeroAOn the effective size of populations with separate sexes, with particular reference to sex-linked genes.Genetics1995139100710117713404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>LiWHYiSMakovaKMale-driven evolution.Curr Opin Genet Dev2002126506561243357710.1016/S0959-437X(02)00354-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>MiyataTHayashidaHKumaKMitsuyasuKYasunagaTMale-driven molecular evolution: a model and nucleotide sequence analysis.Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol1987528638673454295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>HuangWChangBHGuXHewett-EmmettDLiWSex differences in mutation rate in higher primates estimated from AMG intron sequences.J Mol Evol199744463465908908710.1007/PL00006166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>MakovaKDLiWHStrong male-driven evolution of DNA sequences in humans and apes.Nature20024166246261194834810.1038/416624a </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>BerlinSBrandstromMBackstromNAxelssonESmithNGEllegrenHSubstitution rate heterogeneity and the male mutation bias.J Mol Evol2006622262331647498510.1007/s00239-005-0103-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>HuttleyGAJakobsenIBWilsonSREastealSHow important is DNA replication for mutagenesis?Mol Biol Evol20001792993710833199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>LaporteVCharlesworthBEffective population size and population subdivision in demographically structured populations.Genetics200216250151912242257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>ZhouQHuangLZhangJZhaoXZhangQSongFChiJYangFWangWComparative genomic analysis links karyotypic evolution with genomic evolution in the Indian Muntjac (Muntiacus muntjak vaginalis).Chromosoma20061154274361679163110.1007/s00412-006-0066-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>XieXLuJKulbokasEJGolubTRMoothaVLindblad-TohKLanderESKellisMSystematic discovery of regulatory motifs in human promoters and 3' UTRs by comparison of several mammals.Nature20054343383451573563910.1038/nature03441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>KuerstenSGoodwinEBThe power of the 3' UTR: translational control and development.Nat Rev Genet200346266371289777410.1038/nrg1125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>BachtrogDSex chromosome evolution: molecular aspects of Y-chromosome degeneration in Drosophila.Genome Res200515139314011616992110.1101/gr.3543605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>KumarSSubramanianSMutation rates in mammalian genomes.Proc Natl Acad Sci USA2002998038081179285810.1073/pnas.022629899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Haag-LiautardCDorrisMMasideXMacaskillSHalliganDLCharlesworthBKeightleyPDDirect estimation of per nucleotide and genomic deleterious mutation rates in Drosophila.Nature200744582851720306010.1038/nature05388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>WoodRDDNA repair in eukaryotes.Annu Rev Biochem199665135167881117710.1146/annurev.bi.65.070196.001031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>BartolomeCMasideXYiSGrantALCharlesworthBPatterns of selection on synonymous and nonsynonymous variants in Drosophila miranda.Genetics2005169149515071554565310.1534/genetics.104.033068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>VicosoBCharlesworthBEvolution on the X chromosome: unusual patterns and processes.Nat Rev Genet200676456531684746410.1038/nrg1914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>OrrHAKimYAn adaptive hypothesis for the evolution of the Y chromosome.Genetics1998150169316989832543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>WrayGAThe evolutionary significance of cis-regulatory mutations.Nat Rev Genet200782062161730424610.1038/nrg2063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>BornemanARGianoulisTAZhangZDYuHRozowskyJSeringhausMRWangLYGersteinMSnyderMDivergence of transcription factor binding sites across related yeast species.Science20073178158191769029810.1126/science.1140748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>CooperSJTrinkleinNDAntonEDNguyenLMyersRMComprehensive analysis of transcriptional promoter structure and function in 1% of the human genome.Genome Res2006161101634456610.1101/gr.4222606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>RusinovVBaevVMinkovINTablerMMicroInspector: a web tool for detection of miRNA binding sites in an RNA sequence.Nucl Acids Res200533W696W7001598056610.1093/nar/gki364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>DodgeGRKovalszkyIMcBrideOWYiHFChuMLSaittaBStokesDGIozzoRVHuman clathrin heavy chain (CLTC): partial molecular cloning, expression, and mapping of the gene to human chromosome 17q11-qter.Genomics199111174178176537510.1016/0888-7543(91)90115-U </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>SongJZhaoKQNewmanCLVinarovDAMarkleyJLSolution structure of human sorting nexin 22.Protein Sci2007168078141740091810.1110/ps.072752407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>ChenKRajewskyNThe evolution of gene regulation by transcription factors and microRNAs.Nat Rev Genet20078931031723019610.1038/nrg1990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>DrummondDABloomJDAdamiCWilkeCOArnoldFHWhy highly expressed proteins evolve slowly.Proc Natl Acad Sci USA200510214338143431617698710.1073/pnas.0504070102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>BachtrogDA dynamic view of sex chromosome evolution.Curr Opin Genet Dev2006165785851705524910.1016/j.gde.2006.10.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>BartolomeCCharlesworthBEvolution of amino-acid sequences and codon usage on the Drosophila miranda neo-sex chromosomes.Genetics2006174203320441702831810.1534/genetics.106.064113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>MarinIFrankeABashawGJBakerBSThe dosage compensation system of Drosophila is co-opted by newly evolved X chromosomes.Nature1996383160163877487810.1038/383160a0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>CarrelLWillardHFX-inactivation profile reveals extensive variability in X-linked gene expression in females.Nature20054344004041577266610.1038/nature03479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>LeeJDavidowLSWarshawskyDTsix, a gene antisense to Xist at the X-inactivation centre.Nat Genet1999214004041019239110.1038/7734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>SadoTWangZSasakiHLiERegulation of imprinted X-chromosome inactivation in mice by Tsix.Development20011281275128611262229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>FisherRAThe Genetical Theory of Natural Selection1930Oxford, UK: Clarendon Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>GuptaVParisiMSturgillDNuttallRDoctoleroMDudkoOKMalleyJDEastmanPSOliverBGlobal analysis of X-chromosome dosage compensation.J Biol2006531650715510.1186/jbiol30 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>NguyenDKDistecheCMDosage compensation of the active X chromosome in mammals.Nat Genet20063847531634122110.1038/ng1705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>RozasJSanchez-DelBarrioJCMesseguerXRozasRDnaSP, DNA polymorphism analyses by the coalescent and other methods.Bioinformatics200319249624971466824410.1093/bioinformatics/btg359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>TajimaFMeasurement of DNA polymorphism.Mechanisms of Molecular Evolution1993Sunderland, UK: Sinauer Associates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Inc3759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarSMEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0.Mol Biol Evol200724159615991748873810.1093/molbev/msm092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>YangZPAML: a program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood.Comput Appl Biosci1997135555569367129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>ThompsonJDHigginsDGGibsonTJCLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice.Nucleic Acids Res19942246734680798441710.1093/nar/22.22.4673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
