<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2443369</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2180-8-107</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18588667</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-8-107</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Cytokine responses in primary chicken embryo intestinal cells infected with Campylobacter jejuni strains of human and chicken origin and the expression of bacterial virulence-associated genes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yi-Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yiping.li@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ingmer</surname><given-names>Hanne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>hi@life.ku.dk</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>Mogens</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>MOGMA@dianova.dk</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>Dang D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ddb@vet.dtu.dk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Poultry, Fish and Fur Animals, National Veterinary Institute (VET), Technical University of Denmark (DTU), Hangøvej 2, DK-8200 Aarhus N, Denmark</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Dianova, Technical University of Denmark (DTU), Hangøvej 2, DK-8200 Aarhus N, Denmark</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Veterinary Pathobiology, Life Science Faculty, University of Copenhagen, Stigboejlen 4, DK-1870 Frederiksberg C, Denmark</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/8/107"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2008 Li et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Campylobacter jejuni is a major cause of inflammatory diarrhoea in humans and is considered a commensal of the gastroenteric tract of the avian host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, little is known about the interaction between C. jejuni and the avian host including the cytokine responses and the expression of the bacterial genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We have investigated the invasiveness of primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) by C. jejuni strains of human and chicken origins and the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines as well as the expression of the bacterial virulence-associated genes during co-cultivation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>C. jejuni strains are capable of invading the CEICs and stimulate these cells in a pro-inflammatory manner and during this interaction the expression of the bacterial virulence-associated genes ciaB, dnaJ and racR is increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, incubation of bacteria with conditioned cell- and bacteria-free media from another co-cultivation experiment also increased the expression of the virulence-associated genes in the C. jejuni chicken isolate, indicating that the expression of bacterial genes is regulated by component(s) secreted upon co-cultivation of bacteria and CEICs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We show that under in vitro culture condition C. jejuni strains of both human and chicken origins can invade avian host cells with a pro-inflammatory response and that the virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni may play a role in this process. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Campylobacter is a spiral Gram-negative, thermophilic, obligate microaerobic bacterial genus that is ubiquitous in temperate environments [1]. Campylobacter jejuni is recognized as the leading cause of bacterial food-borne and water-borne enteric diarrhea in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In the United States and Great Britain, more than 1% of the population is infected with C. jejuni each year [2,3], and the incidence of C. jejuni-induced disease may be even higher in developing countries, where infection often goes unreported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The clinical symptoms of Campylobacter infection include watery to bloody diarrhea, abdominal pain, fever, headache, nausea and vomiting in acute infection, even a severe inflammation of the intestinal mucosa with an influx of professional phagocytes [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Mostly the infection of Campylobacter is self-limiting, but some infections are associated with more serious medical sequels such as Reiter's syndrome (reactive arthritis), Miller-Fisher syndrome (MFS) and Guillain-Barré syndrome (GBS) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The Campylobacter-associated illness has become an economic and health burden in the world [3,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Although knowledge about the organism and host responses to infection has been growing rapidly in the past decades, the pathogenesis of C. jejuni is not yet well understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>C. jejuni colonizes the intestinal mucosa of warm-blooded hosts, including farm animals and humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Among these hosts the favored environment appears to be the intestines of avians, including chickens, that provide optimal temperature conditions for growth, e.g. 42°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Unlike in the colonization of humans, C. jejuni colonizes the intestinal tracts of most mammals and birds at a high level with little or no pathology [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The differences of pathology between human and chicken may relate partly to the host immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Cytokines are central to the development of effective immunity against microbial pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that C. jejuni can invade human-derived epithelial cell cultures [8,9] and induce the production of a number of cytokines and chemokines during the course of experimental infections [10-15], as well as in clinical Campylobacter infections [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In general, cytokine responses have mainly been monitored on human-derived cell lines with only a few studies performed on chicken cells [15,17] and none involving C. jejuni isolates of chicken origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, experimental colonization experiments have shown that passage through the chicken gut enhances the colonization potential and virulence of C. jejuni [18], suggesting that it is important to use C. jejuni of chicken origin in order to more closely mimic the interactions taking place in the avian gut. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we used primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) as a model to compare the cytokine responses of CEICs elicited by C. jejuni strains of human and chicken origin, as well as the concomitant expression of the virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Intracellular bacterial counts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>With the aim of determining whether C. jejuni is able to invade primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs), intracellular bacterial counts were performed using the gentamicin protection method [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>For this purpose two C. jejuni strains, a Danish chicken isolate SC11 and a clinical human isolate HM5040, were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Prior to the infection experiment, the motility and morphology of both isolates was checked under light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The results of invasion are shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The number of intracellular bacteria for both SC11 and HM5040 were gradually increased from 1 to 4 h p.i. and declined to a lower level at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The percentage of internalized SC11 overall was lower than that of HM5040 from 1 to 4 h p.i., with the exception of the 24 h p.i. where the number of internalized SC11 was higher than that of HM5040. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant difference between SC11 and HM5040 was observed only at 1 and 2 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>(p ≤ 0.011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Invasion of primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) by C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Cells grown at equivalent levels (1.7 × 105 cells/well) were inoculated at an MOI of 100:1 with either C. jejuni strain SC11 (chicken isolate) or HM5040 (human isolate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The number of internalized bacteria was assessed by the gentamycin protection assay at 1, 2, 3, 4 and 24 h post inoculation (p.i.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments (average ± SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-8-107-1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Production of cytokines by CEICs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>When human cells are in contact with C. jejuni a strong cytokine response is induced [10,11,14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In order to determine if a similar response can be monitored with chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs), the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, CXCLi1 (K60), CXCLi2 (CAF/IL-8) [19] and TGF-β4 transcripts were measured in CEICs at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 and 24 h p.i. with C. jejuni strains SC11 and HM5040. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Mock-inoculated cells and those inoculated with LPS (5 μg/ml) were used as controls throughout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 shows that both bacterial strains induced the production of IL-1β, IL-6, CXCLi1 and CXCLi2, but not of TGF-β4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The level of IL-1β, IL-6 and CXCLi1 transcripts increased gradually from 1 to 4 h p.i. and declined slightly at 24 h p.i., whereas CXCLi2 transcript increased steadily throughout the observation period and reached a high level at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Significant differences induced by SC11 and HM5040 were observed only at some particular time points: IL-1β at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.042), IL-6 at 4 p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.012) and 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.046) and CXCLi2 at 1 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.025) and 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.019) while IL-2 and IL-4 transcripts were undetectable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The transcript of IFN-γ was detected only at some particular time points (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Quantification of cytokine and chemokine transcripts from primary chicken ebmryo intestinal cells (CEICs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>CEICs were inoculated with C. jejuni strain SC11 (chicken isolate) and HM5040 (human isolate) at a MOI of 100:1, RNA were isolated at various hours post inoculation (p.i.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>LPS E. coli 055:B5 (5 μg/ml) and mock inoculation were used as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments and present as relative to mock inoculations (average ± SD) (see Methods for details). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-8-107-2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Induction of iNOS and production of NO by CEICs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To study whether there are inflammatory responses in CEICs, the cellular iNOS transcripts and the presence of NO product in the medium were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The level of iNOS transcripts was altered by both strains and increased gradually from 1 to 4 h p.i., followed by a decline at 24 h p.i (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The production of NO from the inoculated CEICs was determined at 4 and 24 h p.i. using the Griess assay [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The results were presented as a net nitrite production over the background of the mock-inoculated CEICs (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Nitric oxide was produced by inoculated CEICs, while as expected, the CEICs treated with LPS also showed NO induction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Production of nitric oxide (NO) by primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>CEICs were inoculated with C. jejuni strain SC11 (chicken isolate) and HM5040 (human isolate) at an MOI of 100:1, and NO in supernatants were measured at 4 and 24 hours post inoculation (p.i.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>LPS E. coli 055:B5 (5 μg/ml) and mock inoculation were used as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments and are presented as net increases of NO, from which the NO of the mock inoculations has been subtracted (average ± SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-8-107-3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Expression of the virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>To study whether the contact between C. jejuni and CEICs induce bacterial virulence-associated genes, the expression of bacterial virulence-associated genes ciaB, dnaJ and racR was quantitatively determined during co-cultivation with CEICs, relative to 16S rRNA, and the fold change of the gene expression was determined relative to the mock-incubated bacteria in the absence of CEICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The results are shown in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The transcription of the virulence-associcated genes was increased following co-cultivation with CEICs, and the amount of present in the invaded/adhered bacteria was generally higher than that present in the suspended bacteria, especially the transcripts of dnaJ and racR. ciaB transcription was increased at 1 and 2 h p.i. in SC11 and HM5040, respectively, and declined to a background level at 4 h p.i., followed by a slight increase at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In the suspended bacteria, the expression of ciaB was changed slightly, increased in SC11 and decreased in HM5040. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A significant difference between SC11 and HM5040 was observed at 24 h p.i., where SC11 had a higher fold change than HM5040 had (p = 0.041). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The transcripts of dnaJ and racR in invaded/adhered bacteria were increased in both strains throughout the course of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant difference was observed only for racR at 1 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.020), the level of racR and dnaJ in SC11 was higher than that in HM5040 with the exception of dnaJ at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In suspended bacteria, the expression of dnaJ and racR was altered slightly during the inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The racR transcript in SC11 was significantly higher than in HM5040 at 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>(p = 0.029). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Quantification of the expression of the virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) were inoculated with C. jejuni chicken strain SC11 and human strain HM5040 at a MOI of 100:1, total RNA was isolated, and the expression of ciaB, dnaJ and racR of C. jejuni in internalized/adhered (IA) and suspended (SU) bacteria were measured at various time points post inoculation (p.i.) (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Mock inoculation was used as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of those from three independent experiments relative to mock inoculations (average ± SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-8-107-4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To examine whether the induction of the virulence-associated genes is contact dependent, the expression of the selected virulence-associated genes was also measured in the bacteria that had only been incubated with bacteria- and cell-free supernatant prepared from another co-cultivation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The bacteria incubated with the medium from non-inoculated CEICs and mock-incubated bacteria were used as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The level of expression of the virulence-associated genes in mock-incubated bacteria was defined as 1, to which the expression of the genes in the bacteria incubated with bacteria- and cell-free supernatant and cultured medium was calculated (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>After 4 hours of incubation, expression of the three virulence-associated genes ciaB, dnaJ and racR of SC11 was increased slightly as compared to the mock-incubated bacteria and those bacteria incubated with the medium of non-inoculated CEICs (p ≤ 0.170). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The medium of non-inoculated CEICs decreased the expression of ciaB and dnaJ in SC11 (p ≤ 0.081), but did not alter the level of racR transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For HM5040, expression of the three genes showed a slight increase in both bacteria incubated with the medium of non-inoculated CEICs and bacteria- and cell-free supernatant (p ≤ 0.30). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Quantification of the expression of virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni under different conditions. ciaB, dnaJ and racR of C. jejuni strains SC11 and HM5040 were measured in the bacteria incubated under different conditions, A) mock control, B) primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) cultured medium, and C) bacteria- and cell-free supernatant from another co-cultivation experiment (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>At 4 h post incubation (p.i.), total bacterial RNA was isolated, and the genes were quantitatively determined by real time quantitative PCR, relative to 16S rRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The level of the transcripts of mock control bacteria (A) was defined as 1, to which the level of the genes in other bacteria (B and C) was relative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of those from three independent experiments (average ± SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-8-107-5"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In this study, primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) were used to study the commensal interaction between chicken intestinal cells and C. jejuni of human and chicken origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The results clearly show that both C. jejuni strains of chicken (SC11) and clinical (HM5040) origin can invade CEICs to a level approximate to that seen with human-derived cell lines [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>However, HM5040 demonstrated a higher percentage of internalized bacteria than SC11 at early stage after inoculation (1 and 2 h p.i., Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The internalized bacteria did not persist, and declined to a low level at 24 h p.i.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with previous studies, in which only a few viable bacteria remained intracellularly in human dendritic cells [22] and human peripheral monocytes/macrophages [23] after a prolonged infection period (24 or 48 h) with C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In contrast, other studies have demonstrated that C. jejuni may survive intracellular for relatively long periods of time in both phagocytes and intestinal epithelial cells [24,25], and the phagocytosis may even promote the survival of C. jejuni [24], which has lead to its suggested classification as a facultative intracellular pathogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The intracellular survival may enhance the ability of C. jejuni to evade the host immune system, possibly favoring its long-term persistent infections [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>However, to survive, the intracellular bacteria also have to overcome certain challenges, such as hydrogen peroxide [26] and ferrous iron [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For C. jejuni and some other enteric pathogens, it is however still largely unclear as to which primary factor(s) determines intracellular bacterial survival. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>We further studied the interaction of C. jejuni-avian host in the aspect of the cytokine responses to C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The results showed that both C. jejuni strains investigated were capable of inducing the expression of the pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-1β and IL-6 and the pro-inflammatory chemokines CXCLi1 and CXCLi2 in CEICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we measured the production of iNOS and NO from CEICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Inducible NOS was increased transcriptionally in CEICs at 4 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(Figure 2), and an increased NO level was also detected in the co-cultivated medium at 4 and 24 h p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>(Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Inducible NOS, IL-1β, IL-6, and CXCLi2 are major markers of inflammatory disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Thus, it appears that C. jejuni can stimulate inflammatory responses in CEICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with previous reports using avian cells, in which Campylobacter induced pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines in avian primary chick kidney cells and the avian macrophage cell line HD11 [15], as well as in primary intestinal chick cells [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Interleukin-8 is a pro-inflammatory cytokine, a potent chemotactic factor for many immune effector cells, and a mediator of localized inflammatory responses [28]. Campylobacter strains have exhibited variability in the induction of CXCL8, and those strains with a high ability to invade intestinal epithelial cells frequently induce the high levels of CXCL8 [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Although HM5040 showed higher invasion efficiency than SC11 shortly after inoculation, we did not observe any convincing correlation linking the invasion efficiency to the induction of cytokines and chemokines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In addition, a previous study has demonstrated that the induction of CXCL8 from INT407 cells may be regulated by two independent mechanisms, one of which requires adherence and/or invasion and the other requires cytolethal distending toxin (CDT) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The functional role of the avian CXCLi2 measured in this study awaits further investigations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Potential virulence properties of Campylobacter include motility, chemotaxis, colonization ability, adhesion to intestinal cells, invasion and epithelial translocation, intracellular survival, and formation of toxins and a number of putative virulence genes have been reported among the Campylobacter isolates [30]. CiaB gene and racR gene are highly prevalent in Campylobacter isolates from various sources [31], and conserved across the species [32]. DnaJ is a functional homologue of the dnaJ gene from E. coli and plays a role in C. jejuni thermotolerance and colonization of chickens [33,34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The RacR-RacS (reduced ability to colonize) system is a two-component regulatory system and is involved in the ability to colonize the chicken intestinal tract [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>It is important to study how these genes react to the co-cultivation as they could provide more information about Campylobacter-host interaction and the pathogenesis of Campylobacter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>We thus measured the expression of these virulence-associated genes at the transcriptional level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>All the three virulence-associated genes were up-regulated in invaded/adhered bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The level of the expression in the suspended bacteria in contact with CEICs was generally lower than that in the internalized/adhered bacteria, which is likely a consequence of less direct contact than experienced by the internalized/adhered bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Expression of ciaB gene of the internalized/adhered bacteria was induced to a lower extent as compared to that of dnaJ and racR (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Previously, in in vitro studies have shown that ciaB is involved in the internalization of C. jejuni into host cells and required for the protein secretion process [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The up-regulation of the virulence-associated genes during the co-cultivation with and/or invasion into CEICs may suggest that these genes play a role in the invasion process of C. jejuni. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Although few statistical differences were observed, SC11 showed in general a higher level of expression of these virulence-associated genes than observed in HM5040 except with a few differences (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Shortly after inoculation (1 and 2 h p.i., Figure 1), the invasion efficiency of SC11 was significantly lower than that of HM5040. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>It is likely that the virulence-associated genes in SC11 are more inducible by co-cultivation with CEICs and this induction may decrease the invasion efficiency of SC11. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>To study whether the induction of the virulence-associated genes is contact dependent, the bacteria were incubated with the bacteria- and cell-free supernatant from another co-cultivation experiments and with the medium of non-inoculated CEICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The bacteria-and cell-free supernatant induced the expression of the genes tested to a greater extent in SC11 (p ≤ 0.170) than in HM5040 (p ≥ 0.30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The medium of non-inoculated CEICs suppressed the expression of the virulence-associated genes in chicken strain SC11, especially for genes ciaB and dnaJ (p ≤ 0.081), while slightly increased in human strain HM5040 (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have showed that both host cell components and a cell-free serum-supplemented tissue culture medium can induce Cia proteins secretion, and the secretion of C. jejuni Cia proteins is contact dependent [37,38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In our study, the results from SC11 may indicate that a physically contact of bacteria and CEICs is not necessary for the transcriptional up-regulation of the genes tested, since the induction of the genes occurred in those bacteria inoculated only with bacteria- and cell-free media prepared from an another co-cultivation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>These results may indicate that CEICs and/or bacteria secrete components into the environment after physical contact event(s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The secreted component(s) may subsequently initiate the expression of the virulence-associated genes in other bacterium that had never been physically contacted with either CEICs or invaded/adhered bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Thus, the up-regulation of these virulence-associated genes may not be bacteria-cell contact dependent, but the secretion of the active component(s) is bacteria-cell contact dependent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In summary, we have demonstrated that both C. jejuni strains of human and chicken origin can invade CEICs and stimulate CEICs to undergo an inflammatory response in a similar manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The expression of virulence-associated genes of C. jejuni is increased during the course of invasion, and may play a role in the invasion process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Bacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Two C. jejuni strains SC11, a Danish chicken isolate, and HM5040, a human isolate, were used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These two strains were the most common serotype (Penner serotype 2) and flaA type (flaA type 1) among isolates from broilers and human cases in Denmark [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Both strains were taken from -80°C stock and streaked on modified CCDA (mCCDA) (blood-free agar base with cefoperazone [32 mg/liter] and amphotericin B [10 mg/liter]) (CM739 plus SR155; Oxoid, Basingstoke, UK) agar plates and incubated under microaerobic condition (10% CO2, 2–4% H2 and 86%–88% N2) at 42°C for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The bacteria were then sub-cultured on a new mCCDA plate for another 24 h prior to experimentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The bacteria were harvested and well suspended in room temperature PBS (10 mM) to an OD595 = 1.0 (approximately 109 bacteria/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The bacteria were then diluted in pre-warmed Dulbecco's modified Eagle's growth medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen, UK) without antibiotics to the desired density for inoculation of cell cultures at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 100 bacteria per cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Cell cultures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Primary chicken embryo intestinal cells (CEICs) were prepared from 19-day-old specific pathogen free (SPF) chicken embryos (Lohmann Tierzucht GmbH, Cuxhaven, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Briefly, SPF chicken embryos were dissected, and intestines were separated and cut into small pieces in PBS prior to being digested with 0.25% trypsin-EDTA (Invitrogen, UK) for 3 times, 5 min for each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The cells were then collected by centrifugation at 500 × g for 10 min at room temperature (~25°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The cells were seeded in 12-well plates at a density of 3.5 × 105 cells/ml (1 ml per well) in DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Invitrogen), 0.3% (w/v) tryptose phosphate broth (containing 0.13% pancreatic digest of casein, 0.07% proteose peptone No. 3, 0.02% dextrose, 0.05% sodium chloride, 0.026% disodium phosphate), and 0.02% penicillin and streptomycin each (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The cells were incubated in a humidified environment at 37°C with 5% CO2 throughout the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>At 24 h the medium was replaced with fresh growth medium, the cells were incubated for anther 72 h prior to bacterial inoculation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The cells were washed three times with pre-warmed PBS, freshly prepared 300 μl of antibiotic-free medium containing the desired number of bacteria was added and co-cultivated with cells to various time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>All inoculations were carried out at a MOI of 100:1, unless stated otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Controls consisted of mock infections using antibiotic-free medium alone or positive controls of lipopolysaccharide (LPS, 5 μg/ml) (Sigma, Schnelldorf, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>To prepare bacteria- and cell-free cultured medium, cells were inoculated with the desired number of bacteria for 4 h (MOI = 100), the medium was collected, the bacteria was removed by centrifugation three times at 10,000 × g, 3 min for each, or filtration through a 0.22 μm filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Three hundred μl of this medium was added to freshly harvested bacteria of ~1.7 × 107 and incubated for 4 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>As controls, the bacteria incubated with fresh and CEICs-cultured medium were included in parallel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The incubated bacteria were collected by centrifugation and subject to bacterial total RNA isolation as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Intracellular bacterial counts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The number of intracellular bacteria per eukaryotic cell culture was assessed by the gentamicin protection assay [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>At 1, 2, 3, 4 and 24 h post inoculation (p.i.), the culture medium was removed, Hank's Buffered Salt Solution (HBSS, Invitrogen) containing gentamicin (200 μg/ml) was added, and incubated at 37°C, 5% CO2 for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The cells were then washed three times with pre-warmed PBS and lysed with 500 μl of 0.2% (v/v) Triton X-100 at room temperature for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The bacteria counts were numerated by plates counting and were present as a percentage of invaded bacteria to total inoculated bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction, reverse transcription, and PCR conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Total cellular and bacterial RNA was extracted using TRIZOL LS Reagent (Invitrogen) and re-purified using RNeasy Mini RNA isolation kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the manufacturers's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>At 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 and 24 h p.i., both the medium of the inoculation and the suspended bacteria were collected by centrifugation at 10,000 × g for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The bacteria pellets and cells were lysed in 300 μl of TRIZOL LS reagent and proceed to RNA isolation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>RNA was eluted into 50 μl of RNase-free water and treated with 0.1 U/ml Dnase I Amplification Grade (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The treated RNA was further tested for DNA contamination by PCR using the primer pairs of β-actin and 16S rRNA (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>DNA-free RNAs were transcribed to complementary DNA (cDNA) using the iScript™ cDNA Synthesis Kit (Bio-Rad, USA) with pre-blended RNase inhibitor, oligo (dT) and random hexamer primers, according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real time PCR (qPCR) was performed in the Mx3005P thermocycler (Strategene, Denmark) using primers listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>PCR mixtures (25 μl) contained 0.625 units of Taq DNA Polymerase (Promega, Denmark), 5 mM MgCl2, 200 μM dNTPs, 400 nM of each primer, 10 nM fluorescein (Bio-Rad), 50000 × diluted SYBR green (Invitrogen), and 2 μl of diluted cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The thermal cycling conditions included an initial heat-denaturing step at 94°C for 3 min; 45 cycles of 94°C for 15 s, optimal annealing temperature for appropriate primer pair (Table 1) for 20 s and 72°C for 20 s; followed by an elongation step at 72°C for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>A single fluorescence measurement was taken after each thermo cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The specificity of amplifications was checked by melting curve analyses and 2% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>All primers gave specific melting curves and electrophoresis bands as expected (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The efficiency of the amplification for each primer pair was assessed by a slope of the equation of a standard curve generated from the serial dilutions of the pooled samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>A slope of -3.32 indicates the PCR reaction has 100% efficiency [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The slopes of all primer pairs are close to each other, from -3.35 to -3.12 (Table 1), suggesting a close efficiency of the amplification between reference and target genes in qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The close efficiency of amplification between target and reference validates the quantification of genes by either the standard curve or the 2-ΔΔCt methods in further experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Genes and primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Genes (Species) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences (5'-3') </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Annealing temperatures (°C) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Amplicons (bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Standard curves </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Correlation coefficient (r2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>GenBank access no. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>β-actin (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>GAGAAATTGTGCGTGACATCA CCTGAACCTCTCATTGCCA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>152 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>y=-3.312x+19.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>0.997 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>L08165 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>IL-1β(Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>CTGGGCATCAAGGGCTACA GGCTGTCCAGGCGGTAGA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>62 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>142 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>y=-3.359x+25.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>0.990 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>AJ245728 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>IL-6 (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>GTTCGCCTTTCAGACCTAC ACCACTTCATCGGGATTTA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>138 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>y=-3.288x+23.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>0.985 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>AJ309540 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>CXCLi1 (K60) (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>CAAGCACGTTCAGCGATT ATTCTTGCAGTGAGGTCCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>y=-3.246x+24.79 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>0.994 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>AF277660 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>CXCLi2 (CAF/IL-8) (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>TTGGAAGCCACTTCAGTCAGAC GGAGCAGGAGGAATTACCAGTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>120 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>y=-3.234x+22.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>0.993 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>AJ009800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>TGF-β4 (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>AGGATCTGCAGTGGAAGTGGAT CCCCGGGTTGTGTTGGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>61 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>y=-3.145x+23.54 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>0.990 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>M31160 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>iNOS (Gallus gallus/chicken) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>CAGCTGATTGGGTGTGGAT TTTCTTTGGCCTACGGGTC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>58 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>158 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>y=-3.245x+25.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>0.944 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>U46504 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>16S (C. jejuni) rRNA (C. jejuni) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>AACCTTACCTGGGCTTGATA CTTAACCCAACATCTCACGA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>122 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>y=-3.149x+15.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>0.998 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>NC_002163 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>ciaB (C. jejuni) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>ATATTTGCTAGCAGCGAAGAG GATGTCCCACTTGTAAAGGTG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>157 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>y=-3.357x+23.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>0.996 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>NC_002163 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>dnaJ (C. jejuni) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>AGTGTCGAGCTTAATATCCC GGCGATGATCTTAACATACA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>y=-3.166x+26.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>0.996 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>NC_002163 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>racR (C. jejuni) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>CTTAAGCGATAAAGTTGTGG CTTTTTGTGCGACGAAT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>114 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>y=-3.122x+23.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>0.996 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>NC_002163 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Quantification of cytokines and bacterial virulence-associated genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The transcripts of cytokine interleukin 1β (IL-1β), IL-6, CXCLi1, CXCLi2, tumor growth factor β4 (TGF-β4) and the inducible nitric oxide synthese (iNOS) were measured in inoculated and mock-inoculated cells using qPCR relative to β-actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The transcripts of bacterial virulence-associated genes ciaB, dnaJ and racR in invaded/adhered, suspended and those bacteria treated with various media were quantitatively determined by qPCR relative to 16S rRNA, by use of the 2-ΔΔCt method previously described [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed in duplicate including no-template controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Measurement of NO production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Nitric oxide production was determined by measuring nitrite in cell culture media using the Griess Reagent System (Promega) assay according to the manufacture's instruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The absorbance was read at 550 nm, using a Multiskan EX microtiter plate reader (Thermo Labsystem, Multiskan EX, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The values were expressed as the average ± standard deviation (SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The data were analyzed for statistical significance using one-way ANOVA (ANalysis Of VAriance, Microsoft Excel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>A p-value ≤ 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>YPL participated in the development of study design, performed the experiments, collected and interpreted the data, and wrote the manuscripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>HI and MM contributed to the editing of the manuscript and discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>DDB participated in the development of study design and discussions, interpreted the data and editing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>We thank Jonas Hoeberg for his assistance in RNA isolation and real time RT-PCR experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Danish Research Council. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>SkirrowMBDiseases due to Campylobacter, Helicobacter and related bacteriaJ Comp Pathol1994111113149780670010.1016/S0021-9975(05)80046-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>AltekruseSFSternNJFieldsPISwerdlowDLCampylobacter jejuni--an emerging foodborne pathogenEmerg Infect Dis19995283510081669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Ruiz-PalaciosGMThe health burden of Campylobacter infection and the impact of antimicrobial resistance: playing chickenClin Infect Dis2007447017031727806310.1086/509936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>WassenaarTMBlaserMJPathophysiology of Campylobacter jejuni infections of humansMicrobes Infect19991102310331061793410.1016/S1286-4579(99)80520-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>NachamkinIAllosBMHoTCampylobacter species and Guillain-Barre syndromeClin Microbiol Rev1998115555679665983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>BuzbyJCAllosBMRobertsTThe economic burden of Campylobacter-associated Guillain-Barre syndromeJ Infect Dis1997176 Suppl 2S192S197939671010.1086/513785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>NewellDGFearnleyCSources of Campylobacter colonization in broiler chickensAppl Environ Microbiol200369434343511290221410.1128/AEM.69.8.4343-4351.2003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>EverestPHGoossensHButzlerJPLloydDKnuttonSKetleyJMWilliamsPHDifferentiated Caco-2 cells as a model for enteric invasion by Campylobacter jejuni and C. coliJ Med Microbiol1992373193251433253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>FernandezHTrabulsiLRInvasive and enterotoxic properties in Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli strains isolated from humans and animalsBiol Res1995282052109251750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Al-SalloomFSAlMAIsmaeelABottaGABakhietMCampylobacter-stimulated INT407 cells produce dissociated cytokine profilesJ Infect2003472172241296338310.1016/S0163-4453(03)00076-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>BakhietMAl-SalloomFSQareiballaABindaynaKFaridIBottaGAInduction of alpha and beta chemokines by intestinal epithelial cells stimulated with Campylobacter jejuniJ Infect2004482362441500130210.1016/j.jinf.2003.11.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>HickeyTEBaqarSBourgeoisALEwingCPGuerryPCampylobacter jejuni-stimulated secretion of interleukin-8 by INT407 cellsInfect Immun19996788939864200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>HuLHickeyTECampylobacter jejuni induces secretion of proinflammatory chemokines from human intestinal epithelial cellsInfect Immun200573443744401597254510.1128/IAI.73.7.4437-4440.2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>JonesMATotemeyerSMaskellDJBryantCEBarrowPAInduction of proinflammatory responses in the human monocytic cell line THP-1 by Campylobacter jejuniInfect Immun200371262626331270413710.1128/IAI.71.5.2626-2633.2003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SmithCKKaiserPRothwellLHumphreyTBarrowPAJonesMACampylobacter jejuni-induced cytokine responses in avian cellsInfect Immun200573209421001578455010.1128/IAI.73.4.2094-2100.2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>EnockssonALundbergJWeitzbergENorrby-TeglundASvenungssonBRectal nitric oxide gas and stool cytokine levels during the course of infectious gastroenteritisClin Diagn Lab Immunol2004112502541501397110.1128/CDLI.11.2.250-254.2004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>BorrmannEBerndtAHanelIKohlerHCampylobacter-induced interleukin-8 responses in human intestinal epithelial cells and primary intestinal chick cellsVet Microbiol20071241151241754051710.1016/j.vetmic.2007.04.041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>SangFCShaneSMYogasundramKHagstadHVKearneyMTEnhancement of Campylobacter jejuni virulence by serial passage in chicksAvian Dis198933425430277509210.2307/1591100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>KaiserPPohTYRothwellLAverySBaluSPathaniaUSHughesSGoodchildMMorrellSWatsonMBumsteadNKaufmanJYoungJRA genomic analysis of chicken cytokines and chemokinesJ Interferon Cytokine Res2005254674841610873010.1089/jir.2005.25.467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>GriessPBemerkungen zu der abhandlung der H.H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Weselsky und Benedikt,Ueber einige azoverbindungen.Chem Ber187912426428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>KnudsenKNBangDDAndresenLOMadsenMCampylobacter jejuni strains of human and chicken origin are invasive in chickens after oral challengeAvian Dis20065010141661797410.1637/7376-051005R.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>HuLBrayMDOsorioMKopeckoDJCampylobacter jejuni induces maturation and cytokine production in human dendritic cellsInfect Immun200674269727051662220610.1128/IAI.74.5.2697-2705.2006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>WassenaarTMEngelskirchenMParkSLastovicaADifferential uptake and killing potential of Campylobacter jejuni by human peripheral monocytes/macrophagesMed Microbiol Immunol1997186139144940384210.1007/s004300050056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>KiehlbauchJAAlbachRABaumLLChangKPPhagocytosis of Campylobacter jejuni and its intracellular survival in mononuclear phagocytesInfect Immun1985484464513988342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>KonkelMEHayesSFJoensLACieplakWJr.Characteristics of the internalization and intracellular survival of Campylobacter jejuni in human epithelial cell culturesMicrob Pathog199213357370129791410.1016/0882-4010(92)90079-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>DayWAJr.SajeckiJLPittsTMJoensLARole of catalase in Campylobacter jejuni intracellular survivalInfect Immun200068633763451103574310.1128/IAI.68.11.6337-6345.2000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>NaikareHPalyadaKPancieraRMarlowDStintziAMajor role for FeoB in Campylobacter jejuni ferrous iron acquisition, gut colonization, and intracellular survivalInfect Immun200674543354441698821810.1128/IAI.00052-06 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>WuytsAProostPLenaertsJPBen-BaruchAVanDJWangJMDifferential usage of the CXC chemokine receptors 1 and 2 by interleukin-8, granulocyte chemotactic protein-2 and epithelial-cell-derived neutrophil attractant-78Eur J Biochem19982556773969290210.1046/j.1432-1327.1998.2550067.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>HickeyTEMcVeighALScottDAMichieluttiREBixbyACarrollSABourgeoisALGuerryPCampylobacter jejuni cytolethal distending toxin mediates release of interleukin-8 from intestinal epithelial cellsInfect Immun200068653565411108376210.1128/IAI.68.12.6535-6541.2000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Young KTDavisLMDiritaVJCampylobacter jejuni: molecular biology and pathogenesisNat Rev Microbiol200756656791770322510.1038/nrmicro1718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>DattaSNiwaHItohKPrevalence of 11 pathogenic genes of Campylobacter jejuni by PCR in strains isolated from humans, poultry meat and broiler and bovine faecesJ Med Microbiol2003523453481267687410.1099/jmm.0.05056-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>FoutsDEMongodinEFMandrellREMillerWGRaskoDARavelJBrinkacLMDeBoyRTParkerCTDaughertySCDodsonRJDurkinASMadupuRSullivanSAShettyJUAyodejiMAShvartsbeynASchatzMCBadgerJHFraserCMNelsonKEMajor structural differences and novel potential virulence mechanisms from the genomes of multiple campylobacter speciesPLoS Biol20053e151566015610.1371/journal.pbio.0030015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>KonkelMEKimBJKlenaJDYoungCRZiprinRCharacterization of the thermal stress response of Campylobacter jejuniInfect Immun199866366636729673247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>ZiprinRLYoungCRByrdJAStankerLHHumeMEGraySAKimBJKonkelMERole of Campylobacter jejuni potential virulence genes in cecal colonizationAvian Dis2001455495571156972610.2307/1592894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>BrasAMKetleyJMTranscellular translocation of Campylobacter jejuni across human polarised epithelial monolayersFEMS Microbiol Lett199917920921510518717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>KonkelMEKimBJRivera-AmillVGarvisSGBacterial secreted proteins are required for the internaliztion of Campylobacter jejuni into cultured mammalian cellsMol Microbiol1999326917011036127410.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01376.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Rivera-AmillVKonkelMESecretion of Campylobacter jejuni Cia proteins is contact dependentAdv Exp Med Biol199947322522910659362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Rivera-AmillVKimBJSeshuJKonkelMESecretion of the virulence-associated Campylobacter invasion antigens from Campylobacter jejuni requires a stimulatory signalJ Infect Dis2001183160716161134320910.1086/320704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>BangDDNielsenEMKnudsenKMadsenMA one-year study of campylobacter carriage by individual Danish broiler chickens as the basis for selection of Campylobacter spp. strains for a chicken infection modelEpidemiol Infect20031303233331272920110.1017/S095026880200821X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>GinzingerDGGene quantification using real-time quantitative PCR: an emerging technology hits the mainstreamExp Hematol2002305035121206301710.1016/S0301-472X(02)00806-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>LivakKJSchmittgenTDAnalysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) MethodMethods2001254024081184660910.1006/meth.2001.1262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
