<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3692464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825615</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-07122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Comparative Anatomy</subject><subject>Electrophysiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Sensory Systems</subject><subj-group><subject>Auditory System</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Physiology</subject><subject>Comparative Anatomy</subject><subject>Ichthyology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Otorhinolaryngology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="?"><plain>Does the Hearing Sensitivity in Thorny Catfishes Depend on Swim Bladder Morphology? </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Swim Bladders and Hearing in Thorny Catfishes</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zebedin</surname><given-names>Angelika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ladich</surname><given-names>Friedrich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Department of Behavioural Biology, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>Harold A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>National Institutes of Health/NICHD, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>friedrich.ladich@univie.ac.at</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: AZ FL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: AZ FL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AZ FL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e67049</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Zebedin, Ladich</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zebedin, Ladich</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Thorny catfishes exhibit large variations in swim bladder morphology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>These organs are of different sizes, forms and may have simple or branched diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder plays an important role in otophysans because it enhances their hearing sensitivity by transmitting sound pressure fluctuations via ossicles to the inner ear. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>To investigate if a form-function relationship exists, the swim bladder morphology and hearing ability were analyzed in six species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The morphology was quantified by measuring the length, width and height and calculating a standardized swim bladder length (sSBL), which was then used to calculate the relative swim bladder length (rSBL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Hearing was measured using the auditory evoked potential (AEP) recording technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Two species had simple apple-shaped and four species heart-shaped (cordiform) bladders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>One of the latter species had short unbranched diverticula on the terminal margin, two had a secondary bladder and two had many long, branched diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The rSBL differed significantly between most of the species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>All species were able to detect frequencies between 70 Hz and 6 kHz, with lowest thresholds found between 0.5 and 1 kHz (60 dB re 1 µPa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Hearing curves were U-shaped except in Hemidoras morrisi in which it was ramp-like. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Mean hearing thresholds of species possessing smaller rSBLs were slightly lower (maximum 8.5 dB) than those of species having larger rSBLs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Conclusions/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The current findings reveal a relationship between swim bladder form and its function among thorny catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Relatively smaller swim bladders resulted in relatively better hearing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This is in contrast to a prior inter-familial study on catfishes in which species with large unpaired bladders possessed higher sensitivity at higher frequencies than species having tiny paired and encapsulated bladders. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF grant 22319 to FL). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder in fishes plays an important role in buoyancy, in respiration, in the detection of sounds and in sound production [1]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Due to these different selection pressures the swim bladder morphology varies widely or this organ can be completely reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Modifications for sound detection typically involve large swim bladders which are variously connected to the inner ears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In non-otophysines such as clupeids (Clupeiformes), holocentrids (Beryciformes), sciaenids and cichlids (both Perciformes), some or all representatives possess rostral swim bladder extensions which contact the inner ears [6]–[11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In otophysines, in contrast, swim bladders are connected via a chain of bony ossicles to the inner ear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These Weberian ossicles are found in all representatives of Cypriniformes (carps and minnows), Siluriformes (catfishes), Characiformes (tetras) and Gymnotiformes (South American knifefishes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A complete loss of swim bladders or ossicles has not been reported in any representative of otophysines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Otophysines, which comprise more than 8000 species, evolved an impressive variation in swim bladder and Weberian ossicles morphology, in particular in Siluriformes and to a lesser extent in Cypriniformes [12]–[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In catfishes the form of the gas bladder can vary from unpaired apple- or heart-shaped (cordiform) bladders to paired tiny and encapsulated ones to swim bladders with diverticula at the posterior end or over the entire length of the organ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Pseudopimelodids (bumblebee catfish) have large cordiform or tiny gas bladders, which are partly divided into two lateral sacs [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Similar modifications were found in ariids (sea catfishes) and auchenipterids (driftwood catfishes) [21]–[22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Free heart-shaped swim bladders were found in the families malapterurids (electric catfishes), heptapterids (three-barbeled catfishes) and mochokids (squeakers), whereas bony encapsulated ones were found in the families loricariids (armoured catfishes) and callichthyids (callichthyid armoured catfishes) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The swim bladders in doradids (thorny catfishes) are always unpaired and may possess a caudal sac, termed secondary bladder, and numerous diverticula [23]–[24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Elimination of swim bladders or Weberian ossicles demonstrated that ancillary hearing structures efficiently enhance the hearing sensitivity in otophysines [25]–[31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Among catfishes, hearing abilities were measured in representatives of 11 out of 36 families: in doradids, pimelodids (long-whiskered catfishes), callichthyids, ariids, pseudopimelodids, malapterurids, heptapterids, mochokids, auchenipterids, silurids (sheatfishes) and ictalurids (North American freshwater catfishes) [19], [32]–[38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Lechner and Ladich (2008) [19] showed in a comparative investigation on representatives of eight catfish families that species which have large unpaired swim bladders and 3–4 Weberian ossicles hear better above 1 kHz than species which have tiny and encapsulated bladders and only 1–2 ossicles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Relationships between the morphological variations in accessory hearing structures and hearing abilities were analysed in non-related holocentrids (squirrelfishes), sciaenids (drums or croakers) and in cichlids [6], [8]–[11], [39]–[40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In general a decrease in the distance between the swim bladder and the inner ear results in an increase in hearing sensitivity at higher frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Besides distance, the size of swim bladders seems to play a role in hearing enhancement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Data on cichlids indicate that species with a large bladder hear better than species with reduced swim bladders [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This intrafamilial study was designed to determine if larger swim bladders result in higher auditory sensitivity in thorny catfish (family Doradidae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Thorny catfishes are a potential model to investigate the role of the diversity in swim bladder morphology on hearing within one family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This is because, in contrast to non-otophysines such as cichlids, the factor distance is negligible: bladders are always directly connected to the inner ears via ossicles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Six doradid species were dissected, swim bladder dimensions determined and fish hearing abilities measured. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Six species of the catfish family Doradidae were used for this study: Acanthodoras spinosissimus (talking catfish) (standard length 55.1–113.2 mm, N = 3), Agamyxis pectinifrons (whitebarred catfish) (54.8–59.4 mm, N = 7), Amblydoras affinis (53–71.2 mm, N = 7), Hemidoras morrisi (71–87.3 mm, n = 9), Megalodoras uranoscopus (69.6–122.7 mm, N = 9) and Oxydoras niger (ripsaw catfish) (105–168 mm, N = 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Three specimens of each species were used for morphological investigations and three to nine for hearing measurements. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>All fish were purchased from a tropical fish supplier (Transfish, Munich, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Fish were kept in aquaria equipped with sand on the bottom, plants, roots, and various shelters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The tanks were between 70 × 35 × 40 cm (width × height × depth) and 100 × 50 × 50 cm in size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In order to reduce noise within aquaria, water was maintained by external filters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Temperature was kept at 25±1°C and a 12·h:12·h L:D cycle was provided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Fish were fed four to six times per week with frozen chironomid larvae or artificial food. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the Austrian Federal Ministry of Science and Research, permit number GZ 66.006/0023-II/10b/2008. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Material Examined </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Specimen of each species have been deposited in the Naturhistorisches Museum, Wien ( = Vienna) (NMW). Acanthodoras spinosissimus: NMW-98200 (2 alc, 62 mm, 112 mm SL), Aquarium purchase. Agamyxis pectinifrons: NMW-98201 (1 alc., 62 mm SL) Aquarium purchase. Amblydoras affinis: NMW-98202 (5 alc., 62–78 mm SL) Aquarium purchase. Hemidoras morrisi: NMW-98203 (1 alc., 128 mm SL) Aquarium purchase. Megalodoras uranoscopus: NMW-98204 (1 alc., 185 mm SL) Aquarium purchase. Oxydoras niger NMW-98205 (1 alc., 113 mm SL) Aquarium purchase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Morphological Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Fish were euthanized using an overdose of tricaine methanesulfonate (MS 222) and were directly fixed in alcohol (70%) for conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Dissections were performed under a dissecting microscope (Wild M7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Fish length and swim bladder measures were taken using digital callipers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All measures were taken including the secondary bladders but excluding the diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder form was classified following the terminology by [23] (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Terminology of shapes and morphological features of doradid swim bladders. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Standardized swim bladder length (sSBL) was calculated using the formula sSBL = (l+h+w)/3, where l is length, h is height and w is width according to [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The relative swim bladder length (rSBL) was calculated following the formula rSBL = sSBL/SL, where SL is the standard length. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Hearing Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Hearing sensitivity was measured using the auditory evoked potentials (AEP) recording technique developed by [41] and modified by Wysocki and Ladich [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The thorny catfish were mildly immobilized with Flaxedil (gallamine triethiodide; Sigma Aldrich Handels GmbH, Vienna, Austria). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The dosage used was 3.07–3.27 µg g−1 for Acanthodoras spinosissimus, 3.99–5.38 µg g−1 for Agamyxis pectinifrons, 0.86–3.26 µg g−1 for Amblydoras affinis, 1.73–2.82 µg g−1 for Hemidoras morrisi, 3.8–7.01 µg g−1 for Megalodoras uranoscopus, and 1.73–2.06 µg g−1 for Oxydoras niger. The lowest dosage that immobilized fish while enabling slight movement of the opercula during the experiments was applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>All auditory measurements were carried out in a bowl-shaped plastic tub (diameter 33 cm, water depth 13 cm, 1 cm layer of gravel) which was lined inside with acoustically absorbent material (air-filled packing wrap) to decrease resonances and reflections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The tub was positioned on an air table (TMC Micro-g 63–540, Technical Manufacturing Corporation, Peabody, MA, USA), which rested on a vibration-isolated plate of concrete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A sound proof chamber, constructed as a Faraday cage (interior dimensions: 3.2 m × 3.2 m × 2.4 m), enclosed the whole setup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Test subjects were positioned in the centre of the tub, so that the nape of the head was at the water surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For respiration a pipette was inserted into the fish’s mouth and respiration was effected by a simple, temperature-controlled (25±1°C), gravity-fed water system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The area of the head above the water surface was covered with a small piece of Kimwipes ® tissue paper to keep it moist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Silver wire electrodes (diameter 0.38 mm) were used for recording AEPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The recording electrode was placed in the midline of the skull over the region of the medulla, the reference electrode cranially between the nares. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Both electrodes were pressed firmly against the skin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Both presentation of sound stimuli and AEP waveform recording were achieved using a modular rack-mount system (Trucker-Davis Technologies (TDT) System 3, Gainesville, FL, USA) controlled by a PC containing a TDT digital signal processing board and running TDT BioSig RP software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Hearing thresholds were determined for the following frequencies: 0.07, 0.1, 0.3, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Sound stimuli waveforms were created using TDT SigGen RP software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For tone bursts, two speakers (Fostex PM-0.5 Sub and PM-0.5 MKII, Fostex Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) installed 0.5 m above the fish were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Tone bursts at different frequencies were presented in random order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A hydrophone (Brüel and Kjaer 8101, Naerum, Denmark; frequency range 1 Hz to 80 kHz±2 dB; voltage sensitivity −184 dB re 1 VµPa−1) was placed 2 cm from the right side of the animal to determine absolute sound pressure levels (SPLs) under water in the immediate vicinity of the test subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A second custom-built preamplifier was used to amplify the hydrophone signal (1000×). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Sound stimuli consisted of tone bursts played at a repetition rate of 21 s−1 and at opposite polarities (90° and 270°). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>One thousand stimuli of each polarity were presented and the corresponding AEPs averaged by BioSig RP software to eliminate stimulus artefacts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The SPL was reduced in 4 dB steps until the AEP waveform was no longer identifiable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>By overlaying replicate traces, the lowest SPL yielding a repeatable AEP trace was determined and regarded as threshold. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>All morphological and physiological data were normally distributed (Kolmogorov-Smirnov-Test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>For statistic analysis of the morphological data, a one-way ANOVA was calculated to determine whether rSBLs differ between the species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Differences between the hearing sensitivities of the six species were calculated using a two-way ANOVA followed by a Bonferroni post hoc test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In order to determine whether rSBL affects hearing sensitivities two calculations were carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>First, the mean thresholds of the three species having smaller rSBLs than 0.165 were calculated for each frequency and compared with those three species having large rSBLs than 0.165 by calculating a two-way ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Second, Pearson’s correlation coefficient was calculated to correlate the mean hearing thresholds of each specimen at each frequency to rSBL of this species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>All statistical tests were run using PASW 18.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Swim Bladder Morphology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The swim bladders of all six species were unpaired and free (not encapsulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>They were classified as being apple-shaped, heart-shaped (cordiform) or abbreviated cordiform (Fig. 1). Acanthodoras spinosissimus and Amblydoras affinis had apple-shaped swim bladders without any diverticula (Fig. 2). Agamyxis pectinifrons possessed abbreviated heart-shaped swim bladders with small, simply formed diverticula on the caudal end of the bladder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>These organs were cordiform in Megalodoras uranoscopus, Oxydoras niger and Hemidoras morrisi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In Megalodoras uranoscopus and Hemidoras morrisi they had many long, branched diverticula anteriorly, laterally and caudally. Megalodoras uranoscopus and Oxydoras niger had a small secondary swim bladder (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Lateral (left) and ventral (right) view of the six investigated thorny catfish species. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Swim bladders are given in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Scale bar 3 cm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The rSBL varied between 0.129 in Hemidoras morrisi and 0.201 in Acanthodoras spinosissimus and differed significantly between species (one-way ANOVA; F5,17 = 31.351; p&lt;0.001) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Bonferroni post hoc test revealed significant differences in 9 cases (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0067049-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Swim bladder morphology and measures of species and of swim bladders. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0067049-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0067049.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>SB morphology </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>SL (mm) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>sSBL (mm) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>rSBL </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>1) Acanthodoras spinosissimus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>apple-shaped </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>83.02±15.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>16.64±2.89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>0.201±0.003 3) 4) 5) 6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>2) Agamyxis pectinifrons </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>abbreviated cordiform, diverticula </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>58.15±0.62 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>11.48±0.28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>0.197±0.003 3) 4) 6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>3) Amblydoras affinis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>apple-shaped </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>64.83±5.26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>10.36±1.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>0.159±0.005 4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>4) Hemidoras morrisi </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>cordiform, diverticula </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>81.94±2.72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>10.50±0.15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>0.129±0.006 5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>5) Megalodoras uranoscopus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>cordiform, secondary bladder, diverticula </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>112.40±6.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>19.44±0.62 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>0.174±0.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>6) Oxydoras niger </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>cordiform, secondary bladder </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>119.06±7.10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>17.96±1.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>0.150±0.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Values: means ± s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: SB, swim bladder; rSBL, relative swim bladder length; SL, standard length; sSBL, standardized swim bladder length. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Superscripts in the last column indicate significant differences in rSBL between the given species and other species calculated by a Bonferroni Post Hoc test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Auditory Sensitivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>All species detected tone bursts between 70 Hz and 6 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Hearing curves were typically U-shaped (five out of six species) with best hearing sensitivity located at 0.5 or 1 kHz (Fig. 3, Table 2). Oxydoras niger and Amblydoras affinis showed lowest thresholds at 0.5 kHz, whereas Acanthodoras spinosissimus, Agamyxis pectinifrons and Megalodoras uranoscopus had best hearing sensitivity at 1 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Hearing thresholds decreased by approximately 15–20 dB from 70 Hz to 0.5/1 kHz and increased at higher frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the hearing thresholds of Hemidoras morrisi showed an almost constant increase in sensitivity up to 6 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Thus, Hemidoras morrisi had better hearing abilities at low and high frequencies compared to the other five species and a lower sensitivity in the mid-frequency range from 0.5–1 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The lowest threshold was found in Amblydoras affinis (59.6 dB re 1 µPa at 0.5 kHz) (Fig. 3, Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Mean auditory sensitivities of the investigated doradid species. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0067049-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Hearing thresholds (dB re 1 µPa) of thorny catfish species investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0067049-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0067049.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>F kHz </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Acanthodoras spinosissimus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Agamyxis pectinifrons </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Amblydoras affinis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Hemidoras morrisi </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Megalodoras uranoscopus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Oxydoras niger </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>81.33±0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>82.57±0.81 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>81.00±1.45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>71.89±1.21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>81.33±0.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>77.00±0.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>0.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>78.33±0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>82.00±0.58 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>75.43±0.90 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>72.00±1.29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>80.33±1.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>73.67±0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>71.00±2.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>70.43±0.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>64.71±1.11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>70.44±0.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>71.89±0.72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>65.00±1.53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>0.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>64.67±1.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>65.14±1.28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>59.57±0.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>69.89±0.61 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>67.22±1.12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>63.67±1.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>63.33±0.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>63.43±0.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>59.86±0.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>66.22±1.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>61.22±0.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>64.67±2.73 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>66.33±1.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>65.29±0.68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>65.43±1.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>64.78±0.85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>67.00±0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>69.00±1.53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>71.00±1.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>67.71±1.19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>70.71±1.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>66.56±0.69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>68.33±0.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>69.00±1.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>79.67±1.76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>70.71±0.18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>73.14±1.98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>65.56±0.84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>73.11±0.99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>69.00±1.53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>82.00±2.65 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>75.14±0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>75.29±1.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>64.33±0.82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>79.00±0.94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>70.67±2.60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>85.33±1.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>80.86±0.94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>78.00±1.22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>62.78±1.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>83.11±0.70. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>81.00±1.53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Values: means ± s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>F – frequency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Comparison of hearing curves revealed a significant difference between most of the species (two-way ANOVA: F5, 320 = 50.913, p&lt;0.001) and a significant interaction between species and frequency (F45, 320 = 12.476, p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>This indicates that auditory sensitivities showed different trends at different frequencies. Hemidoras morrisi differed from all other species in sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Swim bladders were relatively smaller in Hemidoras morrisi, Oxydoras niger and Amblydoras affinis than in Acanthodoras spinosissimus, Agamyxis pectinifrons and Megalodoras uranoscopus (see rSBL in Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Averaged hearing sensitivity of the three species with smaller swim bladders was significantly higher than in the three species with larger swim bladders (two-way ANOVA: F 1,40 = 16.245, p&lt;0.001) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Differences between both groups were not frequency-dependent, indicating a similar trend at all frequencies (two-way ANOVA: F1,40 = 0.854, p&gt;0.05) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Averaged hearing thresholds of thorny catfish species with large (Acanthodoras spinosissimus, Agamyxis pectinifrons, Megalodoras uranoscopus) and small (Amblydoras affinis, Hemidoras morrisi, Oxydoras niger) swim bladders. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Standard errors were only drawn in one direction to avoid overlap. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Correlations between Morphological Structures and Hearing Sensitivities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The rSBL was positively correlated to the hearing thresholds at 70 and 100 Hz (Pearson’s correlation: 70 Hz: r = 0.75, p&lt;0.001; 100 Hz: r = 0.69, p&lt;0.001, N = 38) (Fig. 5A, B) and at 4, 5 and 6 kHz (Pearson’s correlation: 4 kHz: r = 0.60, p&lt;0.001; 5 kHz: r = 0.76, p&lt;0.001; 6 kHz: r = 0.81, p&lt;0.001, N = 38) (Fig. 6 A, B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Species with larger swim bladders had higher thresholds in five out of ten frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>No significant relationship between relative swim bladder size and hearing were found between 0.3 and 3 kHz. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Correlation between mean relative swim bladder length (rSBL) and hearing thresholds at different frequencies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Correlations at A) 70 Hz and B) 100 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Color and symbol code see figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Regression equations: 70 Hz: threshold = 144.7; * rSBL +55.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>100 Hz: threshold = 136.4 * rSBL +54.5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0067049-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067049.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Correlation between mean relative swim bladder length (rSBL) and hearing thresholds at different frequencies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Correlations at A) 4 kHz, B) 5 kHz and C) 6 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Color and symbol code see figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Regression equations: 4 kHz: threshold = 114.3 * rSBL +52.2; 5 kHz: threshold = 193.3 * rSBL +41.9; 6 kHz: threshold = 270.4 * rSBL +32.3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0067049.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Swim Bladder Morphology in Catfishes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Thorny catfish comprise 92 species in 31 genera [43], [44] and exhibit the largest variety of swim bladder modifications among catfishes [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder morphology described in the present study mostly resembles that described by [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder of Amblydoras affinis is similar to that of Amblydoras bolivarensis (apple-shaped with completely smooth walls) [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Another apple-shaped bladder was found in Acanthodoras spinosissimus, which is comparable to the organ of Acanthodoras cataphractus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The swim bladder of Megalodoras uranoscopus from the current study resembles that of M. uranoscopus and Megalodoras guayoenis, i.e. cordiform with a secondary bladder and many well-developed and often branched diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Birindelli et al. (2009) [23] showed that small specimens of Megalodoras uranoscopus possess diverticula all over the swim bladder, whereas diverticula are lacking anteriorly in larger specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The size of the secondary chamber and the number of diverticula increase with growth. Hemidoras morrisi exhibited a cordiform swim bladder with many branched diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Birindelli et al. (2009) [23] mentioned that these diverticula became thinner and more branched in larger specimens of Hemidoras species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>In Agamyxis pectinifrons there were three to five small posterolateral diverticula, whereas in Agamyxis albomaculatus there was only a single posterolateral diverticulum on either side of the terminal diverticulum according to [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Kaatz and Stewart (2012) [24] described the swim bladder morphology in this family similar to [23], except that all extensions including secondary bladders were termed diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Kaatz and Stewart (2012) [24] provided absolute swim bladder measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Swim bladders varied from 0.4 to 4.5 cm in length, from 0.5 to 3.3 cm in width and from 0.2 to 2.0 cm in depth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The number and lengths of diverticula were species-specific and varied from shorter diverticula less than a few mm in length (e.g. Agamyxis pectinifrons) to longer diverticula about 1/3 of the swim bladder length (e.g. Oxydoras niger) [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Recent studies on swim bladder morphology in other catfish families revealed further differences in gross morphology, but these intrafamilial differences were smaller than in thorny catfishes [21]–[22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Gas bladders in auchenipterids, which are closely related to doradids [45]–[46], varied to a lesser extent than in doradids, but more than in other catfish families such as pseudopimelodids and ariids [20]–[22], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Auchenipterids possessed either cordiform swim bladders with smooth walls (Glanidium, Pseudauchenipterus), almost apple-shaped bladders (Centromochlus spp.) or bladders reduced in size and partially or completely ossified (Ageneiosus inermis). Tocantinsia piresi and Asterophysus batrachus had distinctive-looking bladders with either two or many diverticula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Variations were also found within genera: Trachycorystes menezesi had a simple cordiform organ, whereas Trachycorystes trachycorystes had a pair of lateral diverticula and a well-developed terminal diverticulum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The bladder of the genus Auchenipterichthys was characterized by having a secondary bladder [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Birindelli et al. (2012) [22] discussed that such morphological variation may be related to the elastic spring apparatus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The diversity of swim bladder shapes in ariids is moderate compared to the high diversity in doradids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>In ariids most species have a cordiform bladder with smooth external walls (Bagre); a few species have well-developed secondary bladders (Sciades spp.) and some have apple-shaped bladders (Galeichthys ater, G. feliceps and G. peruvianus) [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Gas bladders either completely lack diverticula or possess rounded bulges or blister-like swellings (e. g. Aspistor quadriscutis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the diversity in the swim bladder form in thorny catfishes, these organs in pseudopimelodids varied only minimally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The organ in pseudopimelodids is large and cordiform (Cephalosilurus albomarginatus, Batrochoglanis) or moderately sized and apple-shaped (Lophiosilurus alexandri). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Representatives of the genera Pseudopimelodus and Cruciglanis have diminutive organs partially divided into two lateral sacs, where the parapophyses of the fourth vertebra partially cover the bladder anteroventrally [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The relative size of swim bladders varied between different species of thorny catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The largest rSBl was found in Acanthodoras spinosissimus (0.201), the smallest in Hemidoras morrisi. (0.129). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Quantitative data on relative swim bladder lengths are found only in [19]: Kaatz and Stewart (2012) [24] did not calculate ratios between swim bladder measures and the (standard) length of fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Lechner and Ladich (2008) [19] reported that the rSBL of free unpaired swim bladders varied from 0.084 in Malapterurus beninensis (Malapteruridae) to 0.152 in Synodontis schoutedeni (Mochokidae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>In catfish species with tiny paired and encapsulated bladders, the rSBL was much smaller and varied between 0.016 in Hemiodontichthys acipenserinus and 0.057 in Ancistrus ranunculus (Loricariidae) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>This comparison reveals that free unpaired bladders (Ariidae, Pseudopimelodidae, Malapteruridae, Heptapteridae, Mochokidae, Auchenipteridae and Doradidae) are larger than paired bladders (Loricariidae and Callichthyidae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Intrafamilial variation among doradids in rSBL (1∶1.6) is much smaller than the interfamilial variation (1∶9.5) described by [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Siluriformes comprise numerous buttom-dwelling fishes; thus, most species do not require large swim bladders for buoyancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, catfishes and all other otophysines never completely lose their swim bladders, in contrast to other fish taxa (e.g. gobiids, bleniids, cottids), most likely because of their auditory function [14], [46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Hearing Sensitivity in Catfishes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Overall hearing abilities of the investigated doradids differed between most species, but showed similar general characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The hearing curves where U-shaped with best sensitivities between 0.5 and 1 kHz in five out of six species The hearing curve of Hemidoras morrisi differed from all other species because of its ramp-like shape with an almost constant decline towards higher frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The U-shaped hearing curves of Acanthodoras spinosissimus, Agamyxis pectinifrons, Amblydoras affinis, Megalodoras uranoscopus and Oxydoras niger resemble the audiogram previously gained in the striped Raphael catfish Platydoras armatulus (formerly P. costatus), another representative of thorny catfishes [34], [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the hearing threshold of Agamyxis pectinifrons was 10–30 dB higher in the previous than in the current study [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Because the AEP protocols utilized in both studies were similar, we assume that fish size is responsible for this difference in sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The fish in the prior study covered a smaller size range (2.1–7.9 g) than in the present one (6.9–9.0 g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, sensitivity probably improved during growth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Differences in hearing sensitivities were also found in other catfish families such as callichthyids and loricariids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Lechner and Ladich [19] showed that within callichthyids Corydoras sodalis had higher hearing thresholds (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>7 dB at all frequencies tested) than Dianema urostriatum, which resembles difference between Acanthodoras spinossisimus and Amblydoras affinis in the current study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Similar differences were found among loricariids, where Ancistrus ranunculus had higher thresholds than Hemiodontichthys acipenserinus and Hypoptopoma thoracatum [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>No significant difference was found among pimelodids [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>This may be due to the fact that Pimelodus pictus and P. blochii belong to the same genus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Comparing different families with regard to hearing abilities reveals a general trend, namely that relative swim bladder size affects hearing sensitivities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Ladich (1999) [34] determined that callichthyids had lower auditory sensitivities than pimelodids (Pimelodus blochii and P. pictus) and doradids (Platydoras armatulus), whereas there was no difference between the latter two families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Lechner and Ladich (2008) [19] observed that loricariids and callichthyids had lower sensitivities above 1 kHz than ariids, pseudopimelodids, malapterurids, heptapterids, mochokids and auchenipterids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Relationship between Swim Bladder Morphology and Hearing Sensitivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The present study investigated whether the variation in swim bladder morphology affects hearing sensitivity in thorny catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Regarding their rSBLs the doradids were divided into two groups: fish with larger (Acanthodoras spinosissimus, Agamyxis pectinifrons and Megalodoras uranoscopus) and fish with smaller swim bladders (Hemidoras morrisi, Oxydoras niger, Amblydoras affinis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, fish with smaller swim bladders had slightly better hearing abilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>This finding is in contrast to former studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Lechner and Ladich (2008) [19] described pronounced differences in rSBL between catfishes possessing large unpaired (mean rSBL of 0.121) and those having small paired bladders (mean rSBL of 0.037). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>These differences resulted in significantly better hearing abilities at frequencies above 1 kHz, with mean differences of about 5 dB at 1 kHz until up to more than 20 dB at 5 kHz [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>We expected smaller differences in hearing sensitivities because differences in rSBLs between thorny catfishes having larger and smaller rSBLs was smaller (mean rSBLs: 0.191 versus 0.146) than between different catfish families (0.015 versus 0.152). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, a comparison of hearing sensitivities of the thorny catfish species with smaller and larger rSBLs yielded unexpected results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Clearly, factors other than swim bladder size affected hearing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="?"><plain>Did swim bladder diverticula improve hearing sensitivities? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>This was not the case: Amblydoras affinis, with its simple apple-shaped swim bladder without any diverticula had the lowest auditory threshold, whereas species with a cordiform gas bladder and diverticula had poorer sensitivities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>None of the swim bladders in this study were covered by bones, enabling them to vibrate freely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>The differences in hearing abilities may be explainable by differences in accessory hearing structures (swim bladder, Weberian ossicles), by inner ear morphology or by ontogenetic development [19], [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The effects of different swim bladder size on hearing have not been studied in fishes except in catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Typically, investigators concentrated on the distance between swim bladder (including anterior extensions) and inner ear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Smaller distances positively affect the hearing sensitivities in holocentrids and to some degree in sciaenids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The Hawaiian squirrelfish Myripristis kuntee showed lower auditory thresholds and detected a wider frequency range than Adioryx xantherythrus [6], [8]. Myripristis kuntee possesses anterior swim bladder horns, which directly contact the ear, whereas the distance between bladder and inner ear in Adioryx xantherythrus is significant larger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The situation is more complicated in sciaenids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>No clear differences in absolute hearing threshold were observed in sciaenid fishes in subsequent studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The weakfish Cynoscion regalis detects frequencies up to 2000 Hz, the spot Leiostomus xanthurus frequencies only up to 700 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The hearing differences were explained by different swim bladder-inner ear configurations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>In weakfish the bladder has a pair of anterior horns and terminates close to the ear, while in the spot it terminates farther away from the ear [9], [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Horodysky et al. (2008) [50] showed that among sciaenids, Menticirrhus saxatilis – which lacks swim bladders as adults – exhibits best hearing sensitivities below 600 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>They also showed that thresholds of species with anterior extensions of their swim bladders (e.g. Atlantic croaker, spotted seatrout) were not significantly lower than those of fishes lacking these projections (e.g. northern kingfish, red drum) [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>In cichlids, anterior swim bladder extensions improve hearing sensitivities above 300 Hz in the orange chromide Etroplus maculatus and in Paratilapia polleni [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Swim bladder size seems to be important (besides distance to the inner ear). Hemichromis guttatus, which lacks anterior extensions but possesses a large swim bladder, has an auditory sensitivity similar to Etroplus maculatus and Paratilapia polleni up to 3 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Steatocranus tinanti, which has a tiny swim bladder, detects sounds frequencies only up to 700 Hz. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The present investigation showed that thorny catfish with smaller swim bladders had slightly better hearing abilities than species with larger ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Although this result is unexpected underlines that the relationship between swim bladder morphology and auditory sensitivity is not always straightforward: larger swim bladders and shorter distances between swim bladders and inners ear result in improved hearing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Horodysky et al. (2008) [50] showed that, among sciaenids, swim bladder reduction and the presence or absence of anterior extensions do not affect hearing sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Other factors such as the surrounding of the bladder (bony encapsulation) and thus its vibrations patterns, the fine structure of the swim bladder wall, morphological differences in the Weberian ossicles, or the inner ear morphology might influence hearing sensitivity in fishes in general and in thorny catfishes in particular. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>We want to thank Walter Lechner for his help with dissections, Sandra Papes for her help with hearing measurements, Tanja Schulz-Mirbach for help with anatomical drawings and Michael Stachowitsch for professional scientific English proofreading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we wish to thank Mark Sabaj Perez and Jose Birindelli for species identification as well as Jose Birindelli and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments which improved the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0067049-HardenJones1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>1 Harden JonesFR, MarshallNB (1952) The structure and function of the teleostean swimbladder. Biol Rev 28: 16–83. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Bone1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>2Bone Q, Marshall NB, Blaxter JHS (1995) Biology of Fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Glasgow: Blackie Academic &amp; Professional. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>3 LadichF (2001) Sound-generating and -detecting motor system in catfish: Design of swimbladder muscles in doradids and pimelodids. Anat Rec 263: 297–306.11455539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich2"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>4Ladich F, Popper AN (2004) Parallel evolution in fish hearing organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>In: Manley G, Fay RR, Popper AN, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Evolution of the Vertebrate Auditory System. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>New York: Springer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>95–127. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich3"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>5Ladich F, Fine ML (2006) Sound-generating mechanisms in fishes: a unique diversity in vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>In: Communication in Fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Ladich F, Collin SP, Moller P, Kapoor BG, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Enfield, NH: Science Publishers Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>3–43. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Coombs1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>6 CoombsS, PopperAN (1979) Hearing differences among Hawaiian squirrelfish (family Holocentridae) related to differences in the peripheral auditory system. J Comp Physiol 132: 203–207. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Blaxter1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>7Blaxter JHS, Denton EJ, Gray JAB (1981) Acousticolateralis system in clupeid fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>In: Hearing and Sound Communication in Fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Tavolga WN, Popper AN, Fay RR, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>New York: Springer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>39–56. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Hawkins1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>8Hawkins AD (1993) Underwater sound and fish behaviour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>In: Behaviour of Teleost Fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Pitcher TJ, editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>London: Chapman and Hall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>129–169. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ramcharitar1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>9 RamcharitarJU, HiggsDM, PopperAN (2006a) Audition in sciaenid fishes with different swim bladder-inner ear configurations. J Acoust Soc Am 119: 439–443.16454298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Braun1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>10Braun CB, Grande T (2008) Evolution of peripheral mechanisms for the enhancement of sound reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>In: Fish Bioacoustics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Springer Handbook of Auditory Research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Webb JE, Fay RR, Popper AN, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>New York: Springer-Verlag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>99–144. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-SchulzMirbach1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>11 Schulz-MirbachT, MetscherB, LadichF (2012) Relationship between swim bladder morphology and hearing abilities – A case study on Asian and African cichlids. PLOS ONE 7: e42292.22879934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Chranilov1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>12 ChranilovNS (1927) Beiträge zur Kenntnis des Weber'schen Apparates der Ostariophysi 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Vergleichend-anatomische Übersicht der Knochenelemente des Weber'schen Apparates bei Cypriniformes. Zool Jahrb Anat 49: 501–597. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Chranilov2"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>13 ChranilovNS (1929) Beiträge zur Kenntnis des Weber'schen Apparates der Ostariophysi: 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Der Weber'sche Apparat bei Siluoidea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Zool Jahrb. Abt Anat Ontog Tiere 51: 323–462. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Alexander1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>14 AlexanderRM (1964) The structure of the Weberian apparatus in the cyprini. Proc Zool Soc London 142: 419–440. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Chardon1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>15 ChardonM (1968) Anatomie comparee de l'appareil de Weber et des structures connexes chez les Siluriformes. Musee Royal de l'Afrique Centrale - Tervuren, Belgique Annales, Serie in 8, Sciences Zoologiques 169: 1–273. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Chardon2"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>16 ChardonM, VandewalleP (1997) Evolutionary trends and and possible origin of the Weberian apparatus. Netherlands J Zool 47: 383–403. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Chardon3"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>17Chardon M, Parmentier E, Vandewalle P (2003) Morphology, development and evolution of the Weberian apparatus in catfish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>In: Catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Arratia G, Kapoor BG, Diogo R, Chardon, M, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Enfield, NH: Science Publishers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>71–120. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Bird1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>18 BirdNC, HernandezLP (2007) Morphological variation in the Weberian apparatus of cypriniformes. J Morphol 268: 739–757.17591731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Lechner1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>19 LechnerW, LadichF (2008) Size matters: diversity in swimbladders and Weberian ossicles affects hearing in catfishes. J Exp Biol 211: 1681–1689.18456895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Birindelli1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>20 BirindelliJL, ShibattaOA (2011) Morphology of the gas bladder in bumblebee catfishes (Siluriformes, Pseudopimelodidae). J Morphol 72: 890–896. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Marceniuk1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>21 MarceniukAP, BirindelliJL (2010) Morphology of the gas bladder in sea catfishes (Siluriformes: Ariidae). Zootaxa 2579: 59–68. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Birindelli2"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>22 BirindelliJL, AkamaA, BritskiHA (2012) Comparative morphology of the gas bladder in driftwood catfishes (Siluriformes: Auchenipteridae). J Morphol 273: 651–660.22290561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Birindelli3"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>23 BirindelliJL, SousaLM, Sabaj PérezMH (2009) Morphology of gas bladder in thorny catfishes (Siluriformes: Doradidae). Proc Acad Nat Sci Philadelphia 158: 261–296. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Kaatz1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>24 KaatzIM, StewartDJ (2012) Bioacoustic variation of swimbladder disturbance sounds in Neotropical doradoid catfishes (Siluriformes: Doradidae, Auchenipteridae): Potential morphological correlations. Curr Zool 58: 171–188. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Frisch1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>25 FrischKv, StetterH (1932) Untersuchungen über den Sitz des Gehörsinnes bei der Elritze. Z vergl Physiol 17: 687–801. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Poggendorf1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>26 PoggendorfD (1952) Die absolute Hörschwelle des Zwergwelses (Amiurus nebulosus) und Beiträge zur Physik des Weberschen Apparates der Ostariophysen. Z vergl Physiol 34: 222–257. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Kleerekoper1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>27 KleerekoperH, RoggenkampPA (1959) An experimental study on the effect of the swimbladder on hearing sensitivity in Ameiurus nebulosus (Lesueur). Can J Zool 37: 1–8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Fay1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>28 FayRR, PopperAN (1974) Acoustic stimulation of the ear of the goldfish, (Carassius auratus). J Exp Biol 61: 243–260.4411820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Fay2"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>29 FayRR, PopperAN (1975) Modes of stimulation of the teleost ear. J Exp Biol 62: 379–387.1206339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Yan1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>30 YanHY, FineML, HornNS, ColonWE (2000) Variability in the role of the gasbladder in fish audition. J Comp Physiol A 186: 435–445.10879947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich4"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>31 LadichF, WysockiLE (2003) How does tripus extirpation affect auditory sensitivity in goldfish? Hear Res 182: 119–129.12948607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Weiss1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>32 WeissBA, StrotherWF, HartigGH (1969) Auditory sensitivity in the bullhead catfish (Ictalurus nebulosus). Proc Nat Acad Sci 64: 552–556.5261032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Popper1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>33 PopperAN, TavolgaWN (1981) Structure and function of the ear in the marine catfish, Arius felis . J Comp Physiol 144: 27–34. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich5"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>34 LadichF (1999) Did auditory sensitivity and vocalization evolve independently in otophysan fishes? Brain, Behav Evol 53: 288–304.10473905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Wysocki1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>35 WysockiLE, MonteyK, PopperAN (2009) The inﬂuence of ambient temperature and thermal acclimation on hearing in a eurythermal and a stenothermal otophysan fish. J Exp Biol 212: 3091–3099.19749101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Lechner2"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>36 LechnerW (2011) Ladich (2011) How do albino fish hear? J Zool 283: 186–192. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich6"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>37Ladich F, Bass AH (2003) Audition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>In: Catfishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Arratia G, Kapoor BG, Chardon M, Diogo R, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Enfield, NH: Science Publishers Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>701–730. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ladich7"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>38Ladich F, Fay RR (2013) Auditory evoked potential audiometry in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Rev Fish Biol Fisher. DOI: ––<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s111600129297-z">10.1007/s11160–012–9297-z</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ramcharitar2"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>39 RamcharitarJU, DengX, KettenD, PopperAN (2004) Form and function in the unique inner erar of the teleost: silver perch (Bairdiella chrysoura). J Comp Neurol 475: 571–539. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ramcharitar3"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>40 RamcharitarJ, PopperAN (2004) Masked auditory thresholds in sciaenid fishes: a comparative study J Acoust Soc Am. 116: 1687–1691. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Kenyon1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>41 KenyonTN, LadichF, YanHY (1998) A comparative study of hearing ability in fishes: the auditory brainstem response approach. J Comp Physiol A 182: 307–318.9528109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Wysocki2"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>42 WysockiLE, LadichF (2005) Effects of noise exposure on click detection and the temperal resolution ability of the goldfish auditory system. Hear Res 201: 27–36.15721558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ferraris1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>43 FerrarisCJ (2007) Checklist of catfishes, recent and fossil (Osteichthyes: Siluriformes), and catalogue of siluriform primary types. Zootaxa 1418: 1–628. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Birindelli4"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>44 BirindelliJLO, Sabaj-PérezMH (2011)  Ossancora, new genus of thorny catfish (Teleostei: Siluriformes: Doradidae) with description of one new species. Proc Acad Nat Sci Philadelphia 161: 117–152. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Diogo1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>45 DiogoR, ChardonM, VandewalleP (2004) On the osteology and myologie of the cephalic region and pectoral girdle of Franciscodoras marmoratus (Lütken 1874), comparison with other doradids, and comments on the synapomorphies and phylogenetic relationsphips of the Doradidae (Teleostei: Siluriformes). Anim Biol 54: 175–193. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Sullivan1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>46 SullivanJP, LundbergJG, HardmannM (2006) A phylogenetic analysis of the major groups of catfishes (Teleostei: Siluriformes) using rag1 and rag2 nuclear gene sequences. Mol Phylog Evol 41: 636–662. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Papes1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>47 PapesS, LadichF (2011) Effects of temperature on sound production and auditory abilities in the Striped Raphael catfish Platydoras armatulus . PLOS ONE 6(10): e26479.22022618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Lechner3"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>48 LechnerW, WysockiLE, LadichF (2010) Ontogenetic developement of auditory sensitivity and sound production in the squeaker catfish Synodontis schoutedeni . BMC Biology 8: 10.20113466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Ramcharitar4"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>49 RamcharitarJ, GannonDP, PopperAN (2006b) Bioacoustics of fishes of the family Sciaenidae (croakers and drums). Trans Am Fish Soc 135: 1409–1431. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0067049-Horodysky1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>50 HorodyskyAZ, BrillRW, FineML, MusickJA, LatourRJ (2008) Acoustic pressure and particle thresholds in six sciaenid fishes. J Exp Biol 211: 1504–1511.18424685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
