<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3365900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22675509</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-02287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Epigenetics</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA modification</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics of Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Germ Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA transcription</subject><subject>Chromatin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Demethylation of the Coding Region Triggers the Activation of the Human Testis-Specific PDHA2 Gene in Somatic Tissues </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Somatic Activation of Testis-Specific <italic>PDHA2</italic> Gene</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>Maria João</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milagre</surname><given-names>Inês</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>Elsa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Maria João</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>Isabel Tavares</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>Isabel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Research Institute for Medicines and Pharmaceutical Sciences (iMed.UL), Lisbon, Portugal</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biochemistry and Human Biology, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Lisbon, Lisbon, Portugal</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Wei-Guo</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Peking University Health Science Center, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>iarivera@ff.ul.pt</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: IR ER. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AP MJN IM MJS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: IR ER ITA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MJS ITA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: IR ER AP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e38076</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Pinheiro et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Human PDHA2 is a testis-specific gene that codes for the E1α subunit of Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex (PDC), a crucial enzyme system in cell energy metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Since activation of the PDHA2 gene in somatic cells could be a new therapeutic approach for PDC deficiency, we aimed to identify the regulatory mechanisms underlying the human PDHA2 gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Functional deletion studies revealed that the −122 to −6 promoter region is indispensable for basal expression of this TATA-less promoter, and suggested a role of an epigenetic program in the control of PDHA2 gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Indeed, treatment of SH-SY5Y cells with the hypomethylating agent 5-Aza-2′-deoxycytidine (DAC) promoted the reactivation of the PDHA2 gene, by inducing the recruitment of the RNA polymerase II to the proximal promoter region and the consequent increase in PDHA2 mRNA levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Bisulfite sequencing analysis revealed that DAC treatment induced a significant demethylation of the CpG island II (nucleotides +197 to +460) in PDHA2 coding region, while the promoter region remained highly methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Taken together with our previous results that show an in vivo correlation between PDHA2 expression and the demethylation of the CpG island II in testis germ cells, the present results show that internal methylation of the PDHA2 gene plays a part in its repression in somatic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our data support the novel finding that methylation of the PDHA2 coding region can inhibit gene transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This represents a key mechanism for absence of PDHA2 expression in somatic cells and a target for PDC therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDC) is a mitochondrial matrix enzyme system that catalyses the oxidative decarboxylation of pyruvate to acetyl-CoA, a key metabolite for energy metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The rate-limiting component is the E1 enzyme, which is a heterotetramer (α2β2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The α subunit, besides forming with the β subunit the active and the cofactor binding sites, is also the target for regulatory mechanisms governing global activity of PDC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The E1α subunit can be encoded by two different genes: PDHA1 located on X chromosome and expressed in somatic tissues; and PDHA2 an intronless gene located on chromosome 4 (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>This autosomal gene is repressed in all somatic tissues but actively transcribed in post-meiotic germ cells where the X chromosome is absent or inactive [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It was suggested that the translocation of PDHA to the eutherian X chromosome, which is inactivated during spermatogenesis, led to the evolution of this second testis-specific locus by retroposition to an autosome [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Schematic representation of the PDHA2 gene showing the localization of the 2 CpG islands (CpG I and CpG II), the transcriptional start site and the putative Sp1 binding site. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Besides the potential of PDHA2 as a model for unraveling the mechanisms that govern gene expression during spermatogenesis [4], some authors also postulated that PDHA2 gene activation in somatic cells could be an effective therapy for PDC deficiency [5], an inborn error of metabolism mainly caused by mutations in PDHA1 gene [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The amount of published work on PDHA2 gene regulation is scarce and the studies performed relied on the mouse orthologue, Pdha2 [4], [7], [8], [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, it is believed that the regulatory mechanisms that control these orthologous genes are different, once there is no gross homology between their promoters, which seem to have evolved from different retroposons [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Datta and collaborators publish the first and, to our knowledge, unique study on human PDHA2 gene regulation [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>They isolated and characterized approximately 800 nucleotides of the PDHA2 promoter region, identified the location of the transcription start site and performed functional studies that suggested the existence of multiple regulatory elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>More importantly, these authors proposed that the PDHA2 tissue-specific expression could be modulated by mechanisms, such as DNA methylation, that would limit PDHA2 expression to spermatogenic cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Indeed, DNA methylation is a widely known epigenetic mechanism that plays a central role in the selective expression of particular genes in different tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The methylation of cytosine residues acts as a negative regulator of transcription by three potential mechanisms: direct interference with the binding of specific transcription factors to promoters, direct binding of specific transcriptional repressors and alteration of the chromatin structure [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>DNA methylation can be inhibited by 5-Aza-2′-deoxycytidine (DAC), a potent inhibitor of DNA methyltransferase (DNMT) activity, through the irreversible binding of DNMTs to DAC substituted DNA [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Recently, we have demonstrated an in vivo correlation between an increase in PDHA2 mRNA levels and the demethylation of a CpG island in its coding region [14], which is a strong evidence for a role of DNA methylation in the epigenetic control of the human PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this study we show that inhibition of DNMTs with DAC reactivates PDHA2 gene expression in SH-SY5Y cells, in a demethylation-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>PDHA2 promoter constructs display basal activity in human somatic cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Human PDHA2 gene expression is restricted to post-meiotic germ cells [2] suggesting the absence of positive modulating factors and/or the presence of repressors in somatic tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, the lack of suitable human spermatogenic germ cell lines makes it difficult to easily elucidate the regulatory mechanisms involved upon PDHA2 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the regions important for transcriptional modulation and, more precisely, to define the regions putatively involved in the repression of PDHA2 gene in somatic cells, several deletion promoter constructs were generated (Fig. 2), and their ability to direct expression of the reporter luciferase gene was analyzed after transient transfection in different somatic cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the various PDHA2 reporter plasmids and the parental pGL2-Basic vector were transfected into HeLa (cervix adenocarcinoma), NT2 (human teratocarcinoma) and SH-SY5Y (human neuroblastoma) cells, which do not normally express PDHA2 mRNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Functional deletion analysis of the human PDHA2 gene promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Progressive 5′ deletion constructs were transiently transfected into HeLa, NT2 and SH-SY5Y cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Transfections were carried out using 0.5 µg of the PDHA2 reporter constructs or the empty pGL2 vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Normalized luciferase activities were expressed as mean values ± SEM of duplicates for a minimum of three experiments (*p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, PDHA2 reporter constructs displayed high luciferase activities in all three somatic cell lines (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were found between the luciferase activities of the several constructs, in HeLa (ANOVA one-way test: F = 20.29, df = 10, p&lt;0.001), NT2 (ANOVA one-way test: F = 26.01, df = 10, p&lt;0.001), and SH-SY5Y (ANOVA one-way test: F = 48.89, df = 10, p&lt;0.001) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>However, post hoc comparisons only revealed significant differences between the luciferase activities of the empty pGL2-Basic and all the other reporter constructs (Tukey HSD p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These results firstly show that the region between nucleotides −122 and −6 seems to contain all the sequences necessary to drive transcription initiation, and thus most probably corresponding to the basal proximal promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Secondly, the fact that PDHA2 promoter reporter constructs present high luciferase activity in somatic cell lines where the PDHA2 mRNA cannot be detected, and that there are no significant differences between the luciferase activities of the different deletion constructs, suggest an important role of epigenetic modifications in the regulation PDHA2 tissue-specific expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In vitro methylation prevents PDHA2 promoter constructs activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the role of DNA methylation on the activity of the PDHA2 proximal promoter, we performed an in vitro methylation assay using SssI methylase (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that the PDHA2 proximal promoter activity was completely abolished after in vitro methylation (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Moreover, since we had previously demonstrated an in vivo inverted correlation between methylation of a CpG island localized in the coding region (see CpG II in Fig. 1) and the PDHA2 mRNA levels [14], we wanted to assess if the presence of a methylated CpG island II region could further decrease PDHA2 construct's luciferase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, since there were already no significant differences between the luciferase activity of the 296.pGL2 construct and of the empty pGL2.Basic vector (Fig. 3B and 3C), the inclusion of the CpG II region did not result in a further decrease in promoter activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In vitro methylation with SssI methylase abrogates PDHA2 promoter constructs activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Constructs, either methylated or mock-methylated, were transiently transfected into SH-SY5Y cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Transfections were carried out using 0.5 µg of the PDHA2 reporter constructs or the empty pGL2 vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Normalized luciferase activities were expressed as mean values ± SEM of duplicates for a minimum of three experiments (*p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(A) Control of the methylation reaction by digestion with the methylation-sensitive endonuclease HpaII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>(B) Methylation of PDHA2 constructs prevents proximal promoter activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(C) No significant decrease in the luciferase activity was observed in the PDHA2 construct including the CpG II region (CpGs.pGL2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>These results indeed show that methylation plays an important repressive role upon PDHA2 gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Activation of PDHA2 expression in somatic cells after treatment with epigenetic drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the role of epigenetic mechanisms upon PDHA2 gene regulation, we treated SH-SY5Y cells, where this gene is not normally expressed, with a potent inhibitor of the de novo methylation (DAC) and with a pharmacological inhibitor of histone deacetylases (TSA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>PDHA2 expression was quantified by real-time PCR (qPCR) and the results revealed that after treatment with 5 µM DAC for 96 h or 120 h, there is a significant increase of PDHA2 mRNA, when compared with untreated cells (ANOVA one-way test: F = 27.84, df = 3, p&lt;0.001; Tukey HSD for unequal N p&lt;0.001) (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>DAC increases PDHA2 mRNA levels in SH-SY5Y cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR analysis of PDHA2 steady-state mRNA transcript levels in SH-SY5Y cells treated with 5 µM DAC for the indicated time points (A), and with 5 µM DAC for 96 h and/or 0.25 µM TSA for 24 h (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Values were normalized to the internal standard β-actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Data represent means ± SEM of at least three independent experiments and was expressed as pg of PDHA2 mRNA per ng of β-actin mRNA (* p&lt;0.001; § p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Since it is generally accepted that DAC and TSA synergistically affect gene expression, by a mechanism that depends on promoter demethylation induced by DAC and subsequent reinforcement by histone acetylation induced by TSA, we also treated SH-SY5Y with TSA for 24 h, and with DAC for 96 h prior to a 24 h treatment with TSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Incubation with 0.25 µM TSA for 24 h did not significantly affect PDHA2 mRNA levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Moreover, pretreatment with DAC for 96 h, prior to the 24 h TSA treatment, did not further increase the observed PDHA2 mRNA accumulation with DAC treatment only (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In order to corroborate the fact that DAC treatment induces a derepression of PDHA2 gene transcription, we analyzed the recruitment of RNA polymerase II (RNA pol II) to this gene by chromatin immunoprecipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>We have designed three sets of primers, one targeting the promoter region (+1 bp), another targeting a distal upstream region (−10 kb) and a third one targeting the CpG island II (+385 pb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that we could only detect RNA pol II binding to the +1 bp region after DAC treatment (Student's t-test, p&lt;0.001), which most likely triggers the observed increase in PDHA2 gene transcription (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we could not detect the occupancy of the putative Sp binding site, by the Sp1 transcription factor (Fig. 5), as previously suggested by Datta and co-workers [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we investigated the possible recruitment of the elongation marker H3K36me3 to the gene body, but the results showed no occupancy of the targeted region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Recruitment of RNA pol II to the human PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Chromatin from SH-SY5Y was prepared at 72 hours after treatment with 5 µM DAC and precipitated with antibodies directed against IgG, Sp1 and RNA pol II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After DNA recovery, the precipitates were evaluated by real-time PCR as described in Experimental Procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as fold change over IgG and represent means of at least three independent experiments ± SEM (* p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrate that PDHA2 gene transcription was reactivated by DAC treatment in SH-SY5Y cells, suggesting that DNA demethylation may play a pivotal role in PDHA2 tissue-specific expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>DAC induces demethylation of PDHA2 coding region </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In order to confirm that DAC can induce the reactivation of PDHA2 expression in SH-SY5Y cells, in a demethylation dependent manner, we analyzed the methylation status of PDHA2 gene body by sodium bisulfite sequencing analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Since we have previously shown that the PDHA2 gene contains two CpG islands, one located in the promoter region (nucleotides −128 to +73) and the other located in the coding region (nucleotides +197 to + 460) [14], we have analyzed the methylation patterns of both CpG islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In accordance with our previous results, we observed that the CpG island I, located in the promoter region, is fully methylated in untreated SH-SY5Y cells, and seems to be insensitive to DAC, since it remains methylated after treatment with this drug (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Effectively, its CpG sites remained fully methylated not only after DAC treatment, but after TSA and DAC plus TSA treatment, as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the analysis of the CpG island II, located in the coding region, showed significant demethylation after treatment with DAC (Table S1) (Fig. 6A and 6B); TSA alone had no effect, but after pre-treatment with DAC, the demethylation level of this exonic CpG island seems to be slightly increased, which is particularly significant in the CpG sites +410 and +492 (Tukey for unequal N, p&lt;0.01) (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>DNA methylation status of the human PDHA2 gene after sodium bisulfite PCR sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A) Sample chromatograms obtained for both PDHA2 CpG Islands, before and after treatment with 5 µM DAC; B) DNA methylation status of CpG sites in the CpG island II located in the coding region of PDHA2 gene, before and after treatment with 5 µM DAC for 96 h and/or 0.25 µM TSA for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Results represent means of at least three independent experiments ± SEM (* p&lt;0.05; † p&lt;0.01; § p&lt;0.001 by Tukey HSD for unequal N test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Recently, several potential alternative transcription start sites were identified in PDHA2 gene [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>These are located in the coding region encompassing the CpG island II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Therefore, one could hypothesize that demethylation of the PDHA2 CpG island II corresponds to the demethylation of alternative promoters that control transcription of truncated PDHA2 transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Indeed, as the qPCR assay used a TaqMan probe hybridizing to the 3′UTR of the PDHA2 mRNA, the presence of eventual shorter truncated transcripts could not be discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, we further analyzed PDHA2 expression by conventional RT-PCR with a set of specific primers designed to amplify the 5′ region of the full-length transcript (nucleotides −27 to +432). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We detected the expected amplification product with 459 bp only in DAC-treated cells, which proves that DAC promotes the transcription of a full-length PDHA2 transcript (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038076-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>DAC activates a full-length PDHA2 transcript. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Conventional RT-PCR analysis, using primers hybridizing to the 5′ region, was used for detection of PDHA2 transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>(1) SH-SY5Y cells before treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(2) SH-SY5Y cells after treatment with 5 µM DAC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(3) Negative control – no biological sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(4) Positive control – mature spermatozoa sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(M) HyperLadder II (Bioline, London, UK). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038076.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with our previous work [14], and strongly suggest that PDHA2 reactivation in somatic cells proceeds via a mechanism independent of promoter demethylation, most probably dependent on demethylation of the coding region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>PDHA2 gene activation in somatic tissues has been postulated as a conceptual therapy for PDC deficiencies caused by PDHA1 gene mutations [5], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, it is crucial to understand the mechanisms controlling human PDHA2 tissue-specific expression, namely what factors are responsible for the silencing of this gene in somatic tissues, and its activation in spermatogenic ones (diploid and haploid germ cells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>However, the lack of a suitable cell line to study the regulatory mechanisms underlying PDHA2 gene expression has hampered this elucidation for a long time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The first step towards understanding the regulation of a particular gene is the identification of regulatory elements and factors involved in basal expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, our studies began by the functional analysis of human PDHA2 promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The results showed that PDHA2 promoter-directed transcription of the luciferase reporter gene occurred in cultured somatic cells (HeLa, NT2 and SH-SY5Y), where PDHA2 mRNA is undetectable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Deletion analysis further revealed that the region spanning from −122 to −6 is indispensable for basal expression of this TATA-less promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Moreover, and in each cell line, no significant differences were found among the reporter gene activities driven by all the other PDHA2 deletion promoter constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Additionally, each construct displayed comparable reporter activities in the three different somatic cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>These observations suggested that the mechanisms involved in the repression of PDHA2 expression in somatic cells are not operative when the core promoter or the 5′ flanking region are transiently transfected into somatic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these results corroborated the previous transactivation experiments described by Datta and colleagues [5], who also observed PDHA2 promoter-directed transcription in human hepatocellular carcinoma cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>However, we could not replicate their results concerning the detection of several enhancer and repressor elements, because no significant differences in luciferase reporter activities were detected between the various deletion constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the same authors suggested the existence of a putative Sp responsive element that would be important for Sp1-dependent transcription initiation [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>However, our chromatin immunoprecipitation assays did not demonstrate any binding of Sp1 transcription factors to the proximal promoter of the PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Additionally, and more importantly, our observation that PDHA2 promoter reporter constructs presented high luciferase activity in all somatic cell lines, where the PDHA2 mRNA cannot be detected, reinforces the idea that PDHA2 tissue-specific expression may be under strict control of epigenetic mechanisms of regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in vitro methylation of PDHA2 promoter constructs with SssI methylase resulted in a complete abrogation of luciferase activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Our next approach was to further explore the involvement of epigenetics, namely DNA methylation and/or histone modifications, on the regulation of PDHA2 gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The results showed that treatment of SH-SY5Y cell cultures with DAC induced PDHA2 derepression with a concomitant accumulation of PDHA2 transcript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, inhibition of histone deacetylation did not elicit any induction of PDHA2 expression, nor did it potentiate the DAC effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the accumulation of the PDHA2 mRNA after DAC treatment was correlated with an enrichment of RNA pol II at the PDHA2 proximal promoter (+1 bp region), which likely triggers the observed increase in PDHA2 mRNA levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The fact that treatment with DAC alone elicited a significant effect upon PDHA2 gene expression suggests that changes associated with methylation are sufficient to drive transcription initiation of this testis-specific gene in somatic cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Once proved that DAC was able to induce PDHA2 gene expression in cultured somatic cells, it would be important to investigate the methylation status of this gene, before and after treatment with the demethylating drug, in order to assure that demethylation was underlying PDHA2 transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Our results demonstrated that DAC promoted a relevant demethylation of PDHA2 coding region, which was fully methylated before treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, the promoter CpG island I remained fully methylated, suggesting its insensibility to demethylation, at least by DAC treatment in the tested conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>These findings corroborate our previous reported results, where we observed that PDHA2 expressing tissues (i.e spermatogenic cells) presented the coding region completely demethylated, while non-expressing tissues displayed it fully methylated [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these results also correlate with our recent finding concerning a family displaying PDHA2 gene expression in somatic tissues [17], an interesting case that may configure the previously referred long dreamed therapy for PDC deficiency, i.e. the somatic activation of PDHA2 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The results obtained either then by in-vivo or now by ex-vivo experiments are overlapping; actually, both methylation analyses revealed a correlation between demethylation of the coding region and PDHA2 derepression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Moreover, and interestingly, the level of demethylation in the coding region is very similar in samples derived from the cultured cells treated with DAC and from the family individuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, Yamashita and colleagues [15] recently identified multiple transcriptional start sites downstream of the canonical one (+248, +253 and +269), which are located precisely within the CpG island II region (nucleotides +197 to +460). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, this region could eventually harbor alternative promoter that would trigger the transcription of truncated PDHA2 mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, our RT-PCR results clearly show that DAC induces transcription of full-length transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>These data are corroborated by the significant enrichment of RNA pol II at the proximal promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our results confirm that methylation of the coding region is a key point in somatic cell silencing of PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Actually, DNA methylation appears to be particularly suitable for the regulation of germ line-specific genes, and this is probably related to the global demethylation process that occurs during the development of spermatogenic cells, which may provide the mechanism by which these germ line-specific genes are demethylated [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>And, despite the fact that DNA methylation does not seem to be the primary control mechanism regulating the programmed expression of most tissue-specific genes resulting in tissue differentiation, there are several examples that indicate that DNA methylation can serve as the primary control mechanism for the expression of a number of germ line-specific genes [20], [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Although the expression of previously referred genes proceeds via a promoter methylation-dependent mechanism, we also can find in the literature some references to human genes that are regulated by methylation of the coding region, namely monocarboxylate transporter MCT3 [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Another particular interesting example is the mouse Tact1/Actl7 gene [24], which is also intronless and testis-specific, like the PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Indeed, it has already been described that methylation of the coding region, per se, can control gene expression by preventing promoter activity at the level of the chromatin structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Indeed, CpG methylation induces a local repressive chromatin structure, mediated by the binding of methyl-CpG binding domain (MBD) proteins which recruit other proteins including sin3A and histone deacetylase; when a sufficient amount of CpGs is methylated, this repression is transmissible in cis, spreading for several hundred base pairs [25], [26], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, more or less distant methylated sequences, like the PDHA2 coding region, can promote gene repression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, and as stated by Nan and co-workers, this type of repression is greater if the promoter itself is methylated [28], which is the case of PDHA2 promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it has also been postulated that methylation of the coding region can inhibit gene expression by interfering with the elongation step rather than with transcription initiation, by causing RNA pol II to pause or to prematurely terminate [29], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the inhibitory effect upon elongation is prominent when methylation occurs near the start codon [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Based on this hypothesis, we attempted to explore elongation of PDHA2 transcription by chromatin immunoprecipitation assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The results did not show any particular differences in the chromatin recovered before and after DAC treatment, namely when using the elongation marker H3K36me3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A recent report has shown a clear correlation between H3K36me3 marking and transcriptional activity in intron-containing genes; however, in intronless genes H3K36me3 is detected at much lower levels irrespective of expression levels [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Indeed, there are other examples showing that transcriptional elongation is differently controlled in intronless genes when compared to longer intron-containing genes [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, because PDHA2 gene lacks introns, different approaches need to be designed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In summary, we hypothesize that PDHA2 gene belongs not only to a restricted group of germ line-specific genes that use DNA methylation as a primary silencing mechanism, but to a unique subset of those genes whose expression is regulated by the methylation status of the coding region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these new insights on the regulatory mechanism underlying PDHA2 tissue-specific expression may open potential therapeutic avenues for PDC deficiency caused by PDHA1 mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Cloning the human PDHA2 gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Two different fragments of the human PDHA2 gene (GenBank ID: M86808) were cloned in pCR®4Blunt-TOPO® vector (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA, USA) after PCR amplification with Platinum® Pfx Polymerase (Invitrogen) of genomic DNA isolated from circulating lymphocytes of a healthy individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The first fragment harboring the PDHA2 promoter region (nucleotides −980 to −6) was amplified using the primers pPDHA2-975 bp and pPDHA2-R listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The second fragment designed to harbor both CpG islands of PDHA2 gene (−274 to +487) was amplified with pPDHA2-269 bp and PDHA2.CpGs-R primers (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The recombinant plasmids were sequenced by primer walking and named pPDHA2-TOPO and PDHA2.CpGs-TOPO, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For sequence numbering, nucleotide +1 was assigned to the adenosine of the initiation translation codon ATG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0038076-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038076.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Sequence of oligonucleotides used in the human PDHA2 gene cloning. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038076-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0038076.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotides </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Sequence (5′→3′) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – R </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>TCACGGAGTGCTGTAGATGGCTCGAGCCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 975 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>TGGAAACCTGCTGAAGACATT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 833 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>AAGGAAAAGTGGAATGTCACAAA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 695 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>ATACATTTTCCCTCCCCACT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 591 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>GTTAACGTGCGTGTGCTTGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 506 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>GGCACATTATGGAGCAGGAT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 436 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>TGGTAGGAAGAAATACCTTTGGA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 349 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>TTGTCGGGAAAGCTTGAGAT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 269 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>GCGATTAGGATGCCCTGTAG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>pPDHA2 – 196 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>GGCAGGCACTGTACAAATCA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>PDHA2.CpGs – R </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>CGGCTCGAGCCATTGCCCCCATAGAAGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>PDHA2 promoter reporter constructs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Several different fragments derived from the human PDHA2 promoter region were subcloned into the luciferase expression vector pGL2-Basic vector (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>We used the pPDHA2-TOPO plasmid as a template to amplify fragments of different lengths, using different forward primers and a reverse primer, which contains a XhoI overhang site, listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The PCR products, amplified with the Platinum® Pfx Polymerase (Invitrogen), were subcloned in the pGL2 reporter plasmid into SmaI/XhoI sites generating plasmids 975.pGL2 (−980 to −6), 833.pGL2 (−838 to −6), 695.pGL2 (−700 to −6), 591.pGL2 (−596 to −6), 506.pGL2 (−511 to −6), 436.pGL2 (−441 to −6), 349.pGL2 (−354 to −6), 269.pGL2 (−274 to −6), and 196.pGL2 (−201 to −6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The pPDHA2-TOPO recombinant was also digested with enzymes MslI/XhoI and the 117 bp fragment was subcloned in the pGL2 reporter plasmid generating the 117.pGL2 recombinant (−122 to −6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>An ultimate PDHA2 reporter construct was subcloned into the pGL2-Basic vector, using as template the PDHA2.CpGs-TOPO plasmid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This reporter construct was named CpGs.pGL2 and harbored both CpGs islands present in PDHA2 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In vitro methylation of PDHA2 constructs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>M.SssI was used to methylate the CpG dinucleotides of the PDHA2 gene/luciferase reporter constructs or the pGL2 basic vector, based on the protocol of the manufacturer (New England Biolabs, Beverly, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Mock reactions were carried out in parallel without adding the methylase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The samples were then incubated with methylation-sensitive restriction enzyme HpaII, followed by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Complete methylation of the CpG sites of the constructs was verified by protection of the methylated DNA from digestion by this enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Methylated and mock-treated plasmids were purified with a QIAquick gel extraction kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and used for reporter gene analyses after transient transfection in somatic cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Transactivation studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The basal promoter activity of the different reporter plasmids was assayed by measuring the luciferase activity after transient transfection in HeLa, SH-SY5Y and Ntera2/clone D1 (NT2) cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>To minimize variations in transfection efficiency, replicates were transfected in single batch suspension with FuGENE® HD (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Penzberg, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Plates containing 200,000 cells were co-transfected with 0.5 µg of the reporter plasmid together with an expression plasmid containing the β-galactosidase gene-coding region (pSV40-βGAL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Cells were inoculated in 24-well plates and maintained for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>These cells were harvested and lysed in reporter lysis buffer (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Cell extracts were assayed for luciferase and β-galactosidase activity (β-Gal Reporter Gene Assay, Roche), which was used to normalize the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed at least three times in duplicate well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Cell cultures and treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>SH-SY5Y (human neuroblastoma, ATCC CRL-2266) cell line was maintained in low glucose Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (Sigma-Aldrich Inc., St. Louis, MO, USA), while HeLa (human cervix adenocarcinoma, ATCC CCL-2) and NT2 (human teratocarcinoma, ATCC CRL-1973) cell lines were cultured in high glucose Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>All media were supplemented with 10% heat inactivated fetal bovine serum (Biochrom AG, Berlin, Germany), 2 mM L-glutamine (Sigma), 100 units/mL penicillin and 100 mg/mL streptomycin (Sigma), with the exception of NT2 culture medium that was supplemented with 4 mM L-glutamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>All cell cultures were carried out at 37°C in humidified 5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Dose response assays of 5-Aza-2′-deoxycytidine (DAC) and Trichostatin A (TSA) were performed as stated in Milagre and collaborators (2008) [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, cells were treated with 5 µM DAC and 0.25 µM TSA for the indicated periods (or vehicle as control) and every 24 hours the medium was changed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation and qPCR for PDHA2 expression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was prepared from all cells, treated and untreated, using the RNeasy® Mini Kit (Qiagen) and contamination by genomic DNA was eliminated from each RNA sample by pre-treatment with DNase I using RNase-free DNase Set (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was reverse transcribed using the Reverse Transcription System A3500 Kit (Promega) with random primers following the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>First strand DNA (1 µg) was used as template for quantitative real-time PCR with an ABI PRISM 7300 sequence detection system (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The cycling conditions were 95°C/10 min followed by 40 cycles of 95°C/15 sec and 60°C/1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>It was used the TaqMan® Gene Expression Assay - ID: Hs01043024_s1 (Applied Biosystems) for specific detection of PDHA2 mRNA, and the TaqMan® β-actin Control Reagents as endogenous control (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>In every reaction we used the TaqMan® Gene Expression Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) following enclosed instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Each sample was assayed in triplicate and results show a minimum of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Transcript levels were normalized to β-actin and expressed in pg PDHA2 mRNA per ng of β-actin mRNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we analyzed PDHA2 mRNA by conventional RT-PCR analysis with a gene specific set of primers, designed to amplify the 5′ region of the transcript: the forward primer 5′-TGCCATCTACAGCACTCCGT-3′ hybridizing to nucleotides −27 to −8 and the reverse primer 5′-AGCACAACCTCCTCTTCTTCC-3′ hybridizing to nucleotides +412 to +432. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The 459 pb product was amplified with SYBR green Master Mix in an ABI 7300 sequence detection system (Applied Biosystems) and visualized by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA isolation and bisulfite sequencing for PDHA2 methylation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was isolated from treated and untreated cells using a salting-out method (Citogene® DNA Blood Kit – Citomed, Lisbon, Portugal). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The number and distribution of scattered CpG sites and CpG islands of PDHA2 gene has been previously analyzed [14] using the online program MethPrimer, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.urogene.org/methprimer">www.urogene.org/methprimer</ext-link>, which defines CpG islands as sequences longer than 200 bp, with a calculated CG composition &gt;50% and an observed to expected CpG ratio of &gt;0.6 [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Bisulfite PCR sequencing was carried out using the EpiTect® Bisulfite Kit (Qiagen) and CpG islands were amplified by PCR using the specific primers and the conditions previously described [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The reaction products were purified by MinElute® PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen) and sequenced in both directions by primer walking with ABI Prism BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kits, in an ABI PRISM 310 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation assays were performed as described previously [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Briefly, chromatin isolated from cell cultures was immunoprecipitated using the following antibodies: anti RNA pol II clone CTD4H8 (#05-623, Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA), H3K36me3 (#ab9050, Abcam, Cambridge, UK), Sp1 (PEP 2) X (#SC-59X, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA) and normal rabbit immunoglobulin (#X0903, DakoCytomation, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The recovered DNA was analyzed by quantitative real-time PCR with SYBR green Master Mix in an ABI 7300 sequence detection system (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The qPCRs were performed using primers designed to cover three different regions of the PDHA2 gene: the proximal promoter region (+1 bp) 5′-GGCAGGCACTGTACAAATCA-3′ (forward) and 5′-CAGTGCACACGGGTGATAGA-3′ (reverse); the CpG island II region (+385 bp) 5′-GGGCTCATGGTGTGTGCTAT-3′ (forward) and 5′-AGCACAACCTCCTCTTCTTCC-3′(reverse); and a distal upstream region (−10 Kb) 5′-GCATGGCAGGACTTCTCTC-3′ (forward) and 5′-TTACAGGCAATGCTTG ACCA-3′ (reverse). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was performed using the Student's t-test and the ANOVA one-way test with the Tukey Honestly Significant Differences (HSD) post-hoc test, the Tukey HSD for unequal N (Spjotvoll/Stoline test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>All analyses were performed using the STATISTICA (data analysis software system), version 7.1 StatSoft, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>(Tulsa, OK, USA; 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>A value of p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038076.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis of  PDHA2  gene methylation results by the ANOVA one-way test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038076.s001.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Funding: This study was supported by the PhD grant SFRH/BD/31264/2006, from the Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT), Lisboa, Portugal, awarded to Ana Pinheiro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0038076-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>1 BrownRMDahlHHBrownGK 1989 X-chromosome localization of the functional gene for the E1 alpha subunit of the human pyruvate dehydrogenase complex. Genomics 4 174 181 2737678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Dahl1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>2 DahlHHBrownRMHutchisonWMMaragosCBrownGK 1990 A testis-specific form of the human pyruvate dehydrogenase E1 alpha subunit is coded for by an intronless gene on chromosome 4. Genomics 8 225 232 2249846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Fitzgerald1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>3 FitzgeraldJWilcoxSAGravesJADahlHH 1993 A eutherian X-linked gene, PDHA1, is autosomal in marsupials: a model for the evolution of a second, testis-specific variant in eutherian mammals. Genomics 18 636 642 8307573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Iannello1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>4 IannelloRCYoungJSumarsonoSTymmsMKolaI 1995 A model for understanding gene regulation during spermatogenesis: the mouse testis Pdha-2 promoter. Reprod Fertil Dev 7 705 712 8711207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Datta1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>5 DattaUWexlerIDKerrDSRazIPatelMS 1999 Characterization of the regulatory region of the human testis-specific form of the pyruvate dehydrogenase alpha-subunit (PDHA-2) gene. Biochim Biophys Acta 1447 236 243 10542321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Brown2"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>6 BrownGKBrownRMScholemRDKirbyDMDahlHH 1989 The clinical and biochemical spectrum of human pyruvate dehydrogenase complex deficiency. Ann N Y Acad Sci 573 360 368 2517465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Iannello2"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>7 IannelloRCDahlHH 1992 Transcriptional expression of a testis-specific variant of the mouse pyruvate dehydrogenase E1 alpha subunit. Biol Reprod 47 48 58 1637947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Iannello3"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>8 IannelloRCGouldJAYoungJCGiudiceAMedcalfR 2000 Methylation-dependent silencing of the testis-specific Pdha-2 basal promoter occurs through selective targeting of an activating transcription factor/cAMP-responsive element-binding site. J Biol Chem 275 19603 19608 10766751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Iannello4"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>9 IannelloRCYoungJSumarsonoSTymmsMJDahlHH 1997 Regulation of Pdha-2 expression is mediated by proximal promoter sequences and CpG methylation. Mol Cell Biol 17 612 619 9001214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-RC1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>10 RCIannelloJCYoungSSumarsonoMJTymmsKolaI 1994 Mouse testis Pdha-2 promoter upstream sequences confer tissue-and temporal-specific activity in transgenic mice. Reprod Fertil Dev 6 599 604 7569039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Fitzgerald2"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>11 FitzgeraldJDahlHHJakobsenIBEastealS 1996 Evolution of mammalian X-linked and autosomal Pgk and Pdh E1 alpha subunit genes. Mol Biol Evol 13 1023 1031 8752009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Miranda1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>12 MirandaTBJonesPA 2007 DNA methylation: the nuts and bolts of repression. J Cell Physiol 213 384 390 17708532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Christman1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>13 ChristmanJK 2002 5-Azacytidine and 5-aza-2′-deoxycytidine as inhibitors of DNA methylation: mechanistic studies and their implications for cancer therapy. Oncogene 21 5483 5495 12154409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Pinheiro1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>14 PinheiroAFaustinoISilvaMJSilvaJSaR 2010 Human testis-specific PDHA2 gene: methylation status of a CpG island in the open reading frame correlates with transcriptional activity. Mol Genet Metab 99 425 430 20005141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Yamashita1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>15 YamashitaRSathiraNPKanaiATanimotoKArauchiT 2011 Genome-wide characterization of transcriptional start sites in humans by integrative transcriptome analysis. Genome Res 21 775 789 21372179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Robinson1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>16 RobinsonBHMacKayNChunKLingM 1996 Disorders of pyruvate carboxylase and the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex. J Inherit Metab Dis 19 452 462 8884569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Pinheiro2"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>17 PinheiroASilvaMJFlorindoCBarrosoMAfonsoA 2012 The unique case of a family expressing the testis-specific PDHA2 gene in somatic tissues. Manuscript under submission  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-delMazo1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>18 del MazoJPranteraGTorresMFerraroM 1994 DNA methylation changes during mouse spermatogenesis. Chromosome Res 2 147 152 8032673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Rocamora1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>19 RocamoraNMezquitaC 1989 Chicken spermatogenesis is accompanied by a genomic-wide loss of DNA methylation. FEBS Lett 247 415 418 2714442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Choi1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>20 ChoiYCChaeCB 1991 DNA hypomethylation and germ cell-specific expression of testis-specific H2B histone gene. J Biol Chem 266 20504 20511 1718964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-DeSmet1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>21 De SmetCLurquinCLetheBMartelangeVBoonT 1999 DNA methylation is the primary silencing mechanism for a set of germ line- and tumor-specific genes with a CpG-rich promoter. Mol Cell Biol 19 7327 7335 10523621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Kroft1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>22 KroftTLJethanandaniPMcLeanDJGoldbergE 2001 Methylation of CpG dinucleotides alters binding and silences testis-specific transcription directed by the mouse lactate dehydrogenase C promoter. Biol Reprod 65 1522 1527 11673270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Zhu1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>23 ZhuSGoldschmidt-ClermontPJDongC 2005 Inactivation of monocarboxylate transporter MCT3 by DNA methylation in atherosclerosis. Circulation 112 1353 1361 16116050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Hisano1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>24 HisanoMOhtaHNishimuneYNozakiM 2003 Methylation of CpG dinucleotides in the open reading frame of a testicular germ cell-specific intronless gene, Tact1/Actl7b, represses its expression in somatic cells. Nucleic Acids Res 31 4797 4804 12907721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Bird1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>25 BirdAPWolffeAP 1999 Methylation-induced repression–belts, braces, and chromatin. Cell 99 451 454 10589672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Kass1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>26 KassSUPrussDWolffeAP 1997 How does DNA methylation repress transcription?. Trends Genet 13 444 449 9385841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Keshet1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>27 KeshetIYisraeliJCedarH 1985 Effect of regional DNA methylation on gene expression. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 82 2560 2564 3857599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Nan1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>28 NanXCampoyFJBirdA 1997 MeCP2 is a transcriptional repressor with abundant binding sites in genomic chromatin. Cell 88 471 481 9038338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Choi2"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>29 ChoiJKBaeJBLyuJKimTYKimYJ 2009 Nucleosome deposition and DNA methylation at coding region boundaries. Genome Biol 10 R89 19723310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Graessmann1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>30 GraessmannASandbergGGuhlEGraessmannM 1994 Methylation of single sites within the herpes simplex virus tk coding region and the simian virus 40 T-antigen intron causes gene inactivation. Mol Cell Biol 14 2004 2010 7509450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Hohn1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>31 HohnTCorstenSRiekeSMullerMRothnieH 1996 Methylation of coding region alone inhibits gene expression in plant protoplasts. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 8334 8339 8710871 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-deAlmeida1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>32 de AlmeidaSFGrossoARKochFFenouilRCarvalhoS 2011 Splicing enhances recruitment of methyltransferase HYPB/Setd2 and methylation of histone H3 Lys36. Nat Struct Mol Biol 18 977 983 21792193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Medlin1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>33 MedlinJScurryATaylorAZhangFPeterlinBM 2005 P-TEFb is not an essential elongation factor for the intronless human U2 snRNA and histone H2b genes, EMBO J 24 4154 4165  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Milagre1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>34 MilagreINunesMJGamaMJSilvaRFPascussiJM 2008 Transcriptional regulation of the human CYP46A1 brain-specific expression by Sp transcription factors. J Neurochem 106 835 849 18445135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Li1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>35 LiLCDahiyaR 2002 MethPrimer: designing primers for methylation PCRs. Bioinformatics 18 1427 1431 12424112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038076-Nunes1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>36 NunesMJMilagreISchnekenburgerMGamaMJDiederichM 2010 Sp proteins play a critical role in histone deacetylase inhibitor-mediated derepression of CYP46A1 gene transcription. J Neurochem 113 418 431 20096088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
