<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sann</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0785-3890</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1365-2060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Informa Healthcare</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3231843</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07853890.2011.582137</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Trends in Clinical Practice</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Overcoming limitations of current antiplatelet drugs: A concerted effort for more profitable strategies of intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Minno</surname><given-names>Matteo Nicola Dario</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guida</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Camera</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Colli</surname><given-names>Susanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Minno</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tremoli</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, Regional Reference Centre for Coagulation Disorders, ‘Federico II’ University, Naples, Italy</aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacological Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label>Centro Cardiologico Monzino IRCCS, Milan, Italy</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Professor Elena Tremoli, Department of Pharmacological Sciences, Universita degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy; Centro Cardiologico Monzino IRCCS, Milan, Italy. E-mail: <email>elena.tremoli@unimi.it</email>, <email>elena.tremoli@ccfm.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>43</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2011 Informa UK, Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/mpp/uploads/iopenaccess_tcs.pdf">Supplemental Terms and Conditions for iOpenAccess articles published in Informa Healthcare journals</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Platelets play a central role in the pathophysiology of atherothrombosis, an inappropriate platelet activation leading to acute ischemic complications (acute myocardial infarction, ischemic stroke). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In view of this, platelets are a major target for pharmacotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Presently, the main classes of antiplatelet agents approved for the use in such complications are aspirin and fhienopyridines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Although antiplatelet treatment with these two types of drugs, alone or in combination, leads to a significant reduction of non-fatal myocardial infarction (−32%), non-fatal stroke (−25%), and of cardiovascular death (−17%), a residual risk persists. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Newer antiplatelet agents have addressed some, but not all, these limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Vis-à-vis their net clinical benefit, the higher potency of some of them is associated with a rise in bleeding complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Moreover, newer fhienopyridines do not show advantages over and above the older ones as to reduction of stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A concerted effort that takes into consideration clinical, genetic, and laboratory information is increasingly recognized as a major direction to be pursued in the area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The well-established road signs of clinical epidemiology will provide major information to define newer potentially useful targets for platelet pharmacology. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Aspirin failure</kwd><kwd>cardiovascular prevention</kwd><kwd>clopidogrel failure</kwd><kwd>new antiplatelet drugs</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Thrombotic (ischemic) complications of atherosclerosis (acute coronary syndrome (ACS), acute myocardial infarction (AMI), ischemic stroke) are the leading causes of morbidity and mortality in Western countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Following atherosclerotic plaque disruption/endothelial cell detachment, circulating platelets, exposed to a highly thrombogenic environment, become activated (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table I, a series of soluble agonists (ADP, thromboxane A2 (T×A2), serotonin (5-HT), and thrombin) recruit and activate additional platelets (2,3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Upon activation, glycoprotein (Gp) IIb/IIIa (αIIbβ3 integrin) mediates platelet aggregation and spreading by means of fibrinogen bridges, which, once converted to fibrin, ultimately contribute to thrombus stabilization (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This leads to the formation of platelet-rich thrombi that, occluding the arterial lumen and impairing blood-flow and oxygen supply, cause acute ischemia (5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table I</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Platelet activation: agonists and signal transduction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Agonist </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Receptor(s) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Effect(s) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Comments </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>ADP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Gaq-coupled P2Y1; Gai-coupled P2Y12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>P2Y1: shape change; P2Y12: aggregation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>P2Y12 amplifies aggregation induced by 5-HT, T×A2, and thrombin </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>T×A2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>TPa;TPb (secondary) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Shape change; platelet recruitment; platelet aggregation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In endothelial cells, COX-1-derived PGH2 is converted into PGI2, a strong antiaggregating and vasodilating agent </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Thrombin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>PAR-1; PAR-4 (secondary); GpIbα </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Shape change; ADP and T×A2 secretion; P-selectin expression; αIIbβ3 integrin receptor; platelet activation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>PAR-1 and P2Y12 cross-reaction (via Gαq and Gai-coupled receptors) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Serotonin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>5HT-2A receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Shape change; platelet recruitment; retention of fibrinogen and thrombospondin on the platelet surface </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Implicated in shear-induced platelet aggregation and thrombus propagation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The transduction of the ADP signal involves its interaction with two platelet receptors belonging to the P2 purinergic family, the Gαq-coupled receptor P2Y1 and the Gαi-coupled receptor P2Y12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The concomitant activation of both the Gαq and Gαi pathways by ADP is needed for platelet aggregation to occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Signaling from the P2Y1 receptor causes platelet shape change and rapid transient aggregation, whereas the signaling from the P2Y12 receptor facilitates sustained irreversible aggregation and stimulates surface expression of the pro-inflammatory P-selectin (6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, the P2Y12 receptor plays a critical role in the amplification of platelet aggregation induced by agents other than ADP, including 5-HT,T×A2, and thrombin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Together, these contribute to thrombus growth and stability (5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><boxed-text position="float"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Key messages </plain></SENT>
</text></title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Platelets are a major target for pharmacotherapy in cardiovascular disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In spite of a significant antithrombotic effect, current antiplatelet drugs have major limitations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Newer antiplatelet agents have addressed some but not all the limitations of the current antiplatelet drugs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>T×A2, generated from arachidonic acid by cyclooxygenase 1 (COX-1) and T× synthase, further amplifies platelet activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>COX-1 converts arachidonic acid into prostaglandin endoperoxides PGG2 and PGH2, the latter being, in turn, transformed by T× synthase into T×A2, a potent amplifier of platelet aggregation with vasoconstrictive properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>At the site of the atheroma rupture, platelet-released T×A2 leads to downstream micro-vessel contraction and thrombus propagation (7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In addition to its role in coagulation, thrombin at extremely low concentrations is one of the major platelet activators (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Human platelets express two cell surface G-protein-coupled protease-activated receptors (PARs) for thrombin: PAR-1 and PAR-4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>By binding the hirudin-like extracellular amino terminal domain (the so-called thrombin receptor), thrombin activates platelets and smooth muscle cells, thus promoting platelet pro-coagulant activity, shape change, secretion and release of agonists (ADP and T×A2), expression of P-selectin, activation of the αIIbβ3 integrin receptor, and aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Thrombin also binds to GpIbα on the surface of platelets, thought to act as a co-factor that localizes the enzyme on the platelet surface and accelerates the hydrolysis of PAR-1 (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>PAR-1 and P2Y12 cross-react in platelet activation, and Gαq and Gαi-coupled receptors are involved in this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Thrombin-dependent platelet aggregation is mediated in part by secreted ADP, acting on the Gαi-linked ADP receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>By blocking Gαq via PAR-1 and Gβi via P2Y12, combined inhibition of thrombin and P2Y12 receptors leads to a synergistic inhibitory effect on thrombin-induced platelet aggregation (10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>5-HT is a vasoconstrictor agent that binds to 5HT-2A receptors and amplifies the platelet response by stimulating shape change and enhancing platelet recruitment at sites of injury (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>It may also play a pro-coagulant role by promoting the retention of fibrinogen and thrombospondin on the platelet surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Intraplatelet 5-HT stores are implicated in shear-induced platelet aggregation and thrombus propagation (3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Antiplatelet agents in clinical practice: efficacy, safety, limitations (Figure 1) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Three main classes of antiplatelet agents are licensed for treatment of atherothrombosis: acetyl salicylic acid (aspirin), P2Y12 inhibitors (ticlopidine, clopidogrel, prasugrel, cangrelor, ticagrelor), and GpIIb/ Ilia receptor antagonists (abciximab, eptifibatide, and tirofiban) (11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>While the last-mentioned are only employed intravenously in ACS in combination with other antithrombotic agents (their effect being rather unpredictable when administered orally), the former two classes are widely used chronically. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Platelet activation pathways and drug molecular targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Thrombin binds to PAR-1 receptor, which leads to shape change, phospholipase C (PLC) activation, thromboxane A2 (T×A2) generation, and activation of the glycoprotein (GP) IIb/IIIa receptor, resulting in sustained platelet aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Cyclooxygenase (COX)-l catalyzes the production of T×A2, a potent platelet aggregator, generated by platelets activated by thrombin and other agonists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Adenosine 5'-diphosphate (ADP) binds to its 7-transmembrane domain receptors, P2Y1 and P2Y12, to activate platelets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>P2Y1 is coupled to Gαq and G12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Gαq is linked to a signaling pathway involving PLC activation, resulting in a rise in the intracellular calcium concentration ([Ca+2]i) and protein kinase C (PKC) activation, leading to GP IIb/IIIa activation and transient platelet aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>G12 mediates platelet shape change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>P2Y12 is linked to Gai-coupled signaling cascades associated with adenylcyclase (Ac) down-regulation and decreased cyclic-3',5'-monophosphate (cAMP) production, which mediates GP IIb/IIIa receptor activation, leading to sustained platelet aggregation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sann43-531-f1"/></fig></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Aspirin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Owing to its efficacy and favorable cost-effectiveness, aspirin is the mainstay treatment for all atherothrombotic conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of aspirin lies in its ability to inhibit irreversibly platelet COX-1 (by acetylating a serine located near the active site of the enzyme) and, in turn, T×A2 formation (12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A recent meta-analysis by the Antithrombotic Trialists’ Collaboration (13) assessed the role of aspirin in primary (95,000 subjects at low cardiovascular risk) and secondary prevention (17,000 patients at medium/high risk) and showed that, while in high-risk conditions the advantages of aspirin outweigh the inherent bleeding hazard, in primary prevention aspirin is associated with an absolute benefit of 0.06%/year, too exiguous as compared to the 0.03% increase in major bleedings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Ticlopidine </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Ticlopidine was the first agent of the thienopyridine class shown both to prevent the interaction of ADP with its platelet purinergic receptor and to determine the inhibition of the binding of fibrinogen to the αIIbβ3 integrin (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In subjects with a history of cerebrovascular events, ticlopidine was superior to placebo and to aspirin in the reduction of stroke, AMI, or vascular death (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In addition, the combination of ticlopidine with aspirin was successful in ACS patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) with stent implantation (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Diarrhea, neutropenia, aplastic anemia, and thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura are the main limitations for a wide-spread use of ticlopidine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Clopidogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The thienopyridine prodrug clopidogrel irreversibly binds the P2Y12 platelet receptor after a two-step activation by cytochrome P450 (CYP) liver isoenzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>While the CAPRIE trial (about 20,000 subjects) (17) and a Cochrane systematic review (18) showed that in patients with a history of AMI, stroke, or symptomatic peripheral arterial disease (PAD), clopidogrel administered alone was only marginally superior to aspirin (RRR 8.7; P= 0.043) in preventing vascular events, a significantly higher efficacy has been shown for the ‘dual antiplatelet therapy'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The CURE (19) and the CREDO (20) studies established the superiority of clopidogrel in combination with aspirin versus aspirin alone in ACS and in ACS with PCI, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Low response to aspirin or clopidogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Although antiplatelet treatment in high-risk patients significantly lowers non-fatal AMI (32%), non-fatal stroke (25%), and cardiovascular death (17%), a residual vascular risk persists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>After an AMI or a stroke, in a long-term follow-up, 10%-20% of patients with a history of an ischemic event develop recurrent events in spite of their antiplatelet treatment (21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Compared to aspirin-sensitive patients, the residual platelet reactivity in subjects on antiplatelet therapy correlates with a higher cardiovascular risk and predicts recurrent thrombotic events (22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In the HOPE study, aspirin-treated patients in the highest quartile of the urinary excretion of T×A2 metabolite had a 1.8-fold higher vascular risk than those in the lowest quartiles (23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysis (24) evaluated the relation between a low laboratory response to clopidogrel and the clinical outcome in ≈4,500 patients with coronary artery disease (CAD) and PCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Several methods were used to assess platelet response to therapy, and 26.4% of patients showed as low responders to clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>These patients showed a higher risk of death/ischemic events as compared to that of patients in whom a normal response was documented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Although often secondary to a poor compliance (25), a low treatment response ('failure') may be due, at least in part, to an incomplete inhibition of platelet function (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Concomitant clinical conditions (diabetes mellitus, inflammation, hypercoagulable states, low fibrinolytic potential), high pretreatment platelet reactivity (observed in ACS or in subjects with high BMI), an increased platelet turn-over, and the simultaneous administration of some drugs (drug interaction and/or inadequate drug absorption) are common, major determinants of a low response to clopidogrel or to aspirin (21,27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The possibility that, in addition to such conditions, genetic variations play a role in a low response to aspirin or to clopidogrel has also been documented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Different haplotypes of COX-1 significantly correlate with the response to aspirin and with T×A2 generation in patients with stable coronary artery disease (28). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>A variety of polymorphisms in the CYP2C19 gene (most often the CYP2C19*2), associated with a 20%-25% production of inactive metabolite, diminish the response to clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Among subjects under treatment with clopidogrel for a previous vascular event, carriers of these polymorphisms have a 50% higher risk of cardiovascular death, AMI, or stroke (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Among clopidogrel-treated patients, carriers of at least one allele associated with the loss of or a reduced function in the CYP2C19 gene had a higher than normal occurrence of fatal and non-fatal coronary thrombotic events, as well as of stent thrombosis (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In the same study population, polymorphic alleles of a gene modulating clopidogrel absorption (ABCB1) have been associated with a higher rate of cardiovascular events at 1-year follow-up as compared to wild-type subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Overcoming limitations of aspirin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Changing doses and schedules of aspirin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Because inhibition of platelet aggregation by aspirin is irreversible, the possibility of monitoring the entry of newly formed platelets into the circulation (i.e. the platelet turn-over) was documented by measuring the recovery of TxB2 biosynthesis after aspirin ingestion (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The data show that platelets with intact cyclo-oxygenase activity can be detected into the circulation as early as 4-6 h after aspirin ingestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A higher than normal rate of entry of platelets into the circulation has been documented in diabetic angiopathy or in patients with coronary artery bypass (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Indeed, schedules of aspirin which may suffice in normal subjects are not effective in patients with diabetic angiopathy, presumably because these patients have a high rate of entry of new platelets into the circulation (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A long-lasting suppression of thromboxane biosynthesis may be achieved by repeated low-dose administrations or by slow-release preparations of aspirin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The relevance of an accelerated platelet turn-over as to ‘aspirin resistance’ has been confirmed in a series of clinical settings (32,33). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Attempts to improve the efficacy of aspirin by using larger doses have been associated with contrasting results (34). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a significant higher bleeding risk (mainly gastrointestinal) may occur with higher aspirin doses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Thus, increasing the dose of aspirin would expose the patient to a doubtful clinical advantage (35). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Overcoming limitations of clopidogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Changing doses of clopidogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In spite of the greater antithrombotic efficacy of higher doses of clopidogrel, thrombotic events still occur in 4.2% of patients (36). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Whereas a vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein (VASP)-tailored clopidogrel loading dose has been found to improve the clinical outcome (37) and to reduce the rate of early stent thrombosis after PCI (38), the GRAVITAS trial has been designed to evaluate only the efficacy and safety of VASP-tailored clopidogrel-maintaining regimens (39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Early results of the study indicate that, compared with standard-dose, high-dose clopidogrel only achieved a modest pharmacodynamic effect in PCI patients with high residual platelet activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Moreover, 6-month higher-dose clopidogrel did not reduce the rate of cardiovascular death, non-fatal MI, or stent thrombosis, nor did it increase severe or moderate bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Thus the GRAVITAS study does not support a treatment strategy of high clopidogrel dose in PCI patients with high residual activity, identified by a single platelet function test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Further strategies have been evaluated to overcome clopidogrel limitations. Ω-3 Ethyl esters (1 g/day for 1 month) added to standard dual antiplatelet therapy significantly lowered maximal platelet aggregation in response to ADP and VASP phosphorylation as well (40). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Cilostazol, selectively targeting phosphodiesterase type 3 (PDE3) and, then, determining intracellular cAMP accumulation, inhibits platelet aggregation (41). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In diabetic patients on standard dual antiplatelet therapy, adjunctive treatment with cilostazol enhances inhibition of platelet P2Y12 signaling (42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A Cochrane review (43), in which two randomized studies on stroke prevention were summarized, documented that, compared with aspirin, cilostazol was associated with a significantly lower risk of vascular events (6.77% versus 9.39%; RR 0.72; 95% CI 0.57-0.91, composite outcome), and with a lower risk of hemorrhagic stroke (0.53% versus 2.01%; RR 0.26; 95% CI 0.13-0.55). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In terms of outcome of safety, cilostazol was associated with significantly fewer adverse events (8.22% versus 4.95%; RR 1.66; 95% CI 1.51-1.83) than aspirin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In the SILOAM phase IV study (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov">Clini-calTrials.gov</ext-link> Identifier: NCT01261832), a triple antiplatelet therapy (cilostazol plus aspirin and clopidogrel) is compared (at 1 month and at 6 months) with the standard dual antiplatelet treatment (ASA and clopidogrel) in 951 ACS subjects (expected number) undergoing PCI and drug eluting-stent implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The primary efficacy end-point is the occurrence of major cardiovascular and cerebrovascular events (total death, non-fatal myocardial infarction, repeat revascularization, stroke). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The end of the study is expected by January 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Exploring newer antiplatelet strategies (Table II) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Prasugrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Prasugrel, a prodrug of the thienopyridine family, after a rapid one-step conversion into a highly bioavailable metabolite, causes an irreversible block of the P2Y12 ADP receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Because of a distinct chemical structure, the conversion to its active metabolite is less dependent on specific cytochrome P450 enzymes than that of other thienopyridines (44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>A phase I study (45) evaluated the inhibition of ADP-induced platelet aggregation by prasugrel (60 mg loading and 10 mg repeated doses) as compared to clopidogrel (300 mg loading dose and 75 mg repeated doses). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In platelets exposed to ADP, inhibition of the aggregation and the onset of the antiplatelet effect were higher for prasugrel than for clopidogrel (maximal inhibition achieved 30-60 min and 4-6 hours after prasugrel and clopidogrel, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Of interest, the number of ‘non-responders’ was significantly lower with a 60-mg loading dose of prasugrel than with a 300-mg loading dose of clopidogrel (0% versus 42%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table II</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Molecular targets of newer and emerging antiplatelet therapies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Drug </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Mechanism </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Comment </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Prasugrel </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>P2Y12 receptor inhibition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Irreversible inhibition; orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Cangrelor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Adenosine triphosphate analog with a high affinity for the P2Y12 receptor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Reversible inhibition; intravenous </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Ticagrelor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>P2Y12 and (partly) P2Y1 receptor inhibition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Reversible inhibition; orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Elinogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>P2Y12 receptor inhibition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Reversible; oral and intravenous </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Vorapaxar (E530348) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>PAR-1 inhibitor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>No effect on thrombin-induced fibrin production, orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Atopaxar (E5555) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Low-molecular-weight PAR-1 inhibitor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of expression of the inflammatory markers (sCD40L and interleukin 6 and the expression of P-selectin), orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Sarpogrelate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Selective inhibitor of serotonin (5HT-2A) platelet receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>DZ-697b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Inhibits collagen and ristocetin-mediated platelet adhesion and aggregation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Orally active </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Gas6 (growth arrest-specific gene 6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Vitamin K-dependent protein; a polyclonal anti-Gas6 antibody lowers platelet thromboembolism induced by the intravenous injection of collagen plus epinephrine and aggregation by ADP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Stored in platelet a granules, released upon activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Through its carboxy-terminal domains it interacts with the membrane receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) of the TAM family (Tyro3, Axl, MerTK); through its vitamin K-dependent Gla module it interacts with phosphatidylserine-containing membranes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>By potentiating PI3K activation, MMP-2 amplifies platelet aggregation regardless of the presence of aspirin and of P2Y12 receptor antagonists </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Involved in tissue remodeling and in the progression of atherosclerosis, MMP-2 is present in platelet cytosol and released upon aggregation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>CD40 ligand (CD40L; CD 154) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>On activated platelets an exodomain (soluble CD40 ligand, sCD40L) is released and binds to αIIbβ3 integrin, thus promoting thrombus stabilization and blunting platelet reactivity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane protein expressed on the surface of activated platelets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Shedding of sCD40L from the surface of activated platelets can be prevented by an anti-CD40L antibody (G28-5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>A phase II dose-ranging trial, the JUMBO-TIMI 26 (46), compared clopidogrel and prasugrel regimens in 900 patients undergoing elective or urgent PCI plus stenting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Patients were randomized to one of three combinations of prasugrel loading and maintenance doses: 40 mg and 7.5 mg/d, 60 mg and 10 mg/d, and 60 mg and 15 mg/d, or to the standard clopidogrel regimen (300 mg and 75 mg/d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>While the thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) major bleeding was similar between prasugrel and clopidogrel groups, subjects receiving prasugrel showed a lower incidence of the composite end-point of 30-day major adverse cardiac events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Likewise, significantly lower rates of coronary target vessel thrombosis were seen in prasugrel-treated patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The PRINCIPLE-TIMI 44 (47) was a randomized, double-blind, two-phase cross-over trial of prasugrel compared with high-dose clopidogrel in 201 patients undergoing a planned PCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In the first phase, a 60-mg prasugrel loading dose was compared with a 600-mg loading dose of clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>After the loading dose, the subjects received prasugrel 10 mg or clopidogrel 150 mg for 14 days, and then they were crossed over to the alternative treatment for an additional 14 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The primary end-point was the inhibition of platelet aggregation at 6 hours following 20 μmol/L ADP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>After the loading dose, the inhibition of platelet aggregation at 6 hours was significantly greater in the patients receiving prasugrel than in those on clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In addition, patients on prasugrel showed more consistent levels of platelet inhibition, a lower interindividual variability, and a reduced incidence of low response as compared to those on clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The same figures were confirmed after 14 days of maintenance therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Thus, both the 60 mg loading dose and the maintenance dose of 10 mg of prasugrel were superior to clopidogrel regimen in inhibiting P2Y12-dependent platelet aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>As to safety findings, no TIMI major bleeding event occurred after the loading dose in either group, whereas two subjects (2.0%) in the prasugrel group and no subject in the clopidogrel group experienced a TIMI minor bleeding episode before the cross-over. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The TRITON-TIMI 38 (48) was a randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, multinational phase III trial comparing the efficacy and safety of prasugrel and clopidogrel in 13,608 subjects with ACS undergoing PCI and coronary stenting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Patients were randomized to receive prasugrel (60-mg loading dose followed by a 10-mg/day maintenance dose) or clopidogrel (300-mg loading dose followed by a 75-mg/day maintenance dose) for a mean of 14.5 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The primary efficacy end-point (death from CV causes, non-fatal MI, non-fatal stroke) occurred in 643 patients (9.9%) receiving prasugrel and in 781 patients (12.1%) receiving clopidogrel (hazard ratio (HR) 0.81; 95% CI 0.73-0.90; P= 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>An early significant difference in the primary end-point was also documented at the 3-day pre-specified time point, a finding consistent with a more rapid onset of the antiplatelet activity of prasugrel (43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Such difference was maintained from the third day to the end of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The difference in the primary end-point was found both among patients with unstable angina and non-STEMI and STEMI subjects, the reduction in AMI being the major determinant of such difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In addition, regardless of the type of stent, a significant 52% reduction of stent thrombosis was found in the prasugrel group (49). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table III</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Efficacy and safety of newer antiplatelet drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Results from phase III studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Study (ref) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>TRITON-TIMI 38 (48), 13,608 subjects: </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain> Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Prasugrel (60-mg loading dose (LD) 10-mg maintenance dose (MD) versus Clopidogrel (300 mg LD 75 mg MD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain> Efficacy end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>9.9% versus 12.1%; P = 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain> Safety end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>2.4% versus 1.8%; P = 0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>CHAMPION-PCI (52), 8,887 subjects: </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain> Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Cangrelor (bolus 30 μg/kg + infusion 4 μg/kg/min) + Clopidogrel (600 mg LD) versus Placebo + Clopidogrel (600 mg LD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain> Efficacy end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>7.5% versus 7.9%; P= 0.59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain> Safety end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>0.4% versus 0.3%; P= 0.39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>CHAMPION-PLATFORM (53), 2,654 subjects: </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain> Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Cangrelor (bolus 30 μg/kg or 4 μg/kg/min infusion for a 2 h) + Clopidogrel (600 mg LD) versus Placebo + Clopidogrel (600 mg LD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain> Efficacy end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>7.0% versus 8.0%; P= 0.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain> Safety end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>3.5% versus 5.5%; P&lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The PLATO trial (53), 18,624 subjects: </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain> Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Ticagrelor (180 mg LD + 90 mg twice a day MD) or Clopidogrel (300-600 mg LD + 75 mg MD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain> Efficacy end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>9.8% versus 11.7%; P= 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain> Safety end-point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>11.6% versus 11.2%; P= 0.46 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Efficacy end-point: CV death/non-fatal Ml/non-fatal stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Safety end-point: major bleeding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Vis-à-vis a 2.2% reduction in fatal and non-fatal ischemic events, both TIMI major and minor bleeding episodes were 1.2% more frequent with prasugrel than with clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The TIMI major bleeding was observed in 2.4% of subjects in the prasugrel group and in 1.8% in the clopidogrel group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The rate of life-threatening bleeding (1.4% versus 0.9%; P=0.01) and of fatal bleeding (0.4% versus 0.1%; P = 0.002) was greater in the prasugrel group than in the clopidogrel group, with maximal bleeding risk in patients with a history of stroke/TIA (in whom this drug should be avoided, being associated with increased intracranial hemorrhage), in elderly patients (aged ≥ 75 years) and in those with a body-weight &lt; 60 kg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, based on TIMI major bleedings (key safety end-point of the trial), prasugrel should also be used with caution in candidates to Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG), &gt; 50% of total bleedings being reported in this setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Together, in a risk/benefit analysis, prasugrel was 13% better than clopidogrel (HR 0.87; 95% CI 0.79-0.95; P = 0.004), maximal clinical benefit being found in patients with diabetes, with coronary stents, or with recurrent events (RRR 30%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Whether prasugrel is safer and better than clopidogrel in reducing the risk of cardiovascular death, MI, or stroke, in patients with ACS who are medically managed, and in whom no revascularization is planned, will be evaluated in the TRILOGY ACS study, a phase III multicenter, double-blind, randomized, controlled trial including approximately 10,000 patients (50). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Cangrelor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Cangrelor, an adenosine triphosphate (ATP) analog with a high affinity for the P2Y12 receptor (35), does not need conversion, being immediately active following infusion (half-life of 3-6 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In the STEP-AMI trial, 92 ACS patients (51) treated with aspirin and heparin were randomized to receive cangrelor (280 μg/kg/min) alone, full-dose tissue plasminogen activator (t-PA) alone, or cangrelor (35, 140, or 280 μg/kg/min) in combination with half-dose t-PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>A 60-min coronary patency similar to that of full-dose t-PA alone and a greater patency than with cangrelor alone was found in patients receiving the combination of cangrelor and half-dose t-PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Although in two randomized controlled clinical phase III trials on ACS patients requiring PCI (CHAMPION PCI, CHAMPION PLATFORM) (52,53), cangrelor did not show superiority over clopidogrel, this drug is currently investigated as a bridge to CABG surgery (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> Identifier: NCT00767507). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Ticagrelor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Ticagrelor, an orally active cyclopentyl-triazolo-pyrimidine, binds to domains of the P2Y12 receptor other than those recognized by ADP (the 1, 2, and 7 transmembrane domains, the extracellular loop 2, and the N-terminal domain), determining a potent and rapid non-persistent receptor conformational change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>After the occupancy of P2Y12, ADP-catalyzed conversion of cAMP from ATP, dephosphorylation of phosphorylated VASP, and activation of phosphoinositide 3-kinase are blocked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The net result is a reduced exposure of fibrinogen-binding sites on the αIIbβ3 integrin receptor and, in turn, the inhibition of platelet aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of ADP-mediated constriction of vascular smooth muscle and enhancement of adenosine-induced coronary blood-flow are also reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>After oral administration, ticagrelor is rapidly absorbed and does not require hepatic biotransformation to be pharmacologically active. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>However, ticagrelor is also metabolized to an equipotent, active metabolite (AR-C124910XX) by CYP3A4 enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Being both ticagrelor and AR-C124910XX-excreted by the intestinal route, no dose adjustment is needed in kidney failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors/inducers as well as a significant liver dysfunction may be of concern for its use (54). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>After pharmacodynamic evaluations (55,56), a 90-mg twice daily dose of ticagrelor has been chosen to optimize its efficacy, safety, and tolerability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>A loading dose of 180-270 mg may minimize intersubject variability as to initial inhibition in platelet aggregation and may be appropriate in ticagrelor-naive patients with ACS or in preparation for PCI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In 174 subjects with a recent coronary artery disease receiving 75-100 mg/day aspirin (92 also under ticagrelor 180-mg load and 90 mg/twice daily maintenance dose, and 82 also under clopidogrel 600-mg load and 75 mg/d maintenance dose) the genotyping of the cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2C19 (*1,*2,*3,*4,*5,*6,*7,*8,*17) was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In addition, platelet function was measured by aggregometry, VerifyNow P2Y12 assay, and VASP assay at pre-dose, 8 hours post-loading, and during maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>There was no significant effect of the genotype on platelet function during aspirin therapy alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, irrespective of the 2C19 genotype, of the metabolizer status, and of the assays employed, subjects on ticagrelor showed a lower platelet reactivity than did those on clopidogrel (P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with a genotype-independent better pharmacodynamic effect of ticagrelor as compared to clopidogrel (57). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The DISPERSE trial (200 subjects with stable atherosclerotic disease) (54) showed ticagrelor (100 mg/b.i.d., 200 mg/b.i.d., or 400 mg/d) to inhibit platelet aggregation more rapidly and effectively and with less variability than clopidogrel (75 mg/d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The DISPERSE-2 trial (58) (990 NSTEMI patients) showed that ticagrelor, added to standard medical treatment, has a safety profile similar to clopidogrel with a better profile as to the incidence of AMI, silent AMI, severe recurrent ischemia, stroke, and death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>However, the study was not powered to detect differences in efficacy end-points (size), nor was the duration of the drug exposure appropriate (52). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The PLATO trial was a phase III, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, double-dummy study that evaluated the efficacy and safety of ticagrelor and of clopidogrel in lowering the risk of vascular events in more than 18,000 NSTEMI or STEMI patients (59). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Within 24 hours after a diagnosis of ACS, the patients were randomized to receive ticagrelor 90 mg/twice daily or clopidogrel 75 mg once daily for 6-12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Before starting the maintenance dose, each subject received a loading dose of 180 mg ticagrelor or 300 mg clopidogrel, depending on the group of randomization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>All subjects received concomitant treatment with aspirin 75-100 mg/day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome of the study was the time to the first occurrence of cardiovascular or cerebrovascular death, non-fatal MI, or non-fatal stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The primary safety outcome was the time to the first occurrence of any major bleeding event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>At 12 months, the primary end-point occurred in 9.8% of patients receiving ticagrelor as compared with 11.7% of those receiving clopidogrel (HR 0.84; 95% CI 0.77-0.92; P&lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Similar figures were achieved by evaluating the rate of the primary outcome at 30 days (4.8% for ticagrelor group versus 5.4% for clopidogrel group; P= 0.045). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The rate of death from any cause was also reduced with ticagrelor (4.5% versus 5.9% with clopidogrel; P&lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Major, life-threatening, or fatal bleedings did not differ between those on ticagrelor and on clopidogrel (11.6% and 11.2%, respectively; P=0.43), nor did CABG-related major bleeding, although ticagrelor patients were allowed to undergo CABG earlier (24-72 hours), after withdrawing from the study drug, as compared to those on clopidogrel (5 days). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>However, Vis-à-vis fewer fatal bleeding episodes of other types, a higher rate of higher major bleeding not related to coronary artery bypass grafting (4.5% versus 3.8%; P=0.03), including fatal intracranial bleedings, were detected in subjects on ticagrelor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Secondary end-point evaluation showed significant differences in the rates of myocardial infarction (5.8% in the ticagrelor group versus 6.9% in the clopidogrel group; P= 0.005) and of death from vascular causes (4.0% versus 5.1%; P= 0.001), but not of stroke (1.5% versus 1.3%; P= 0.22). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>More patients in the ticagrelor group discontinued the study drug due to adverse events compared to the clopidogrel group (7.4% versus 6.0%; P&lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>A significantly higher reversible increase in serum uric acid and creatinine was found in subjects receiving ticagrelor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Dyspnea, nausea, hypotension, and asymptomatic ventricular pauses were more frequent in the ticagrelor group, maybe because of an adenosine-mediated response (60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Thus, the use of ticagrelor should be evaluated with caution in patients with hyperuricemia, bradyar-rhythmias without pacemakers, and syncope and in those at high risk of bleeding (e.g. elderly, low body-weight, renal dysfunction) and avoided in patients with history of stroke (61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Of interest, in the ONSET/ OFFSET study, 123 patients with stable coronary artery disease receiving aspirin (75-100 mg/d) received on top ticagrelor (180-mg load, 90-mg b.i.d. maintenance dose (n = 57)), clopidogrel (600-mg load, 75-mg/d maintenance dose (n = 54)), or placebo (n = 12) for 6 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Ticagrelor achieved a more rapid and greater platelet inhibition (evaluated with 20 μmol/L ADP) than did high-loading-dose clopidogrel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>In addition, a faster offset occurred with ticagrelor than with clopidogrel (4-72-hour slope (% inhibition of platelet aggregation/h) -1.04 versus -0.48; P&lt; 0.0001) (62). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>To evaluate further the safety and efficacy parameters, in a phase III study (NCT01294462) 90 mg/twice daily ticagrelor (on top of 100 mg aspirin) will be compared to 75 mg clopidogrel (on top of 100 mg aspirin as well) in ACS subjects with a planned PCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The safety outcome will be evaluated by measuring the time to first occurrence of any major bleeding event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The time to first occurrence of the composite of death from any vascular cause (myocardial infarction and stroke) will also be measured. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The study is expected to enroll 800 subjects, and the estimated study completion date is August 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In addition, a randomized phase III PEGASUS trial (NCT01225562), on an expected number of 21,000 subjects with a history of myocardial infarction, will evaluate the efficacy of ticagrelor (90 or 60 mg/twice daily) compared to placebo on top of aspirin (100 mg) in the prevention of the composite end-point of cardiovascular death, non-fatal MI, or non-fatal stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The end of the study is expected by February 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Elinogrel </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Elinogrel (PRT128) is a direct, reversible P2Y12 inhibitor available in both oral and intravenous formulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial (63) in which single intravenous doses (1–40 mg) were administered, elinogrel yielded a dose-dependent, complete inhibition of ADP-induced aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>All doses of elinogrel were well tolerated, with no serious adverse events observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Sarpogrelate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Sarpogrelate is a selective inhibitor of 5-HT platelet receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In the S-ACCESS trial (64), 1,510 patients with recent cerebral infarction were randomly assigned to receive either sarpogrelate (100 mg t.i.d.) or aspirin (81 mg/day). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Mean follow-up was 1.59 years, with the recurrence of a cerebral infarction as primary efficacy end-point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Clusters of serious vascular events (stroke, acute coronary syndrome, or vascular death) were secondary end-points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The aim of the primary efficacy analysis was the non-inferiority of sarpogrelate with respect to aspirin, the upper limit of the 95% CI of the hazard ratio for the recurrence of cerebral infarction not exceeding 1.33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Cerebral infarction recurred in 72 patients in the sarpogrelate group and in 58 in the aspirin group (HR 1.25; 95% CI 0.89-1.77; P=0.19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>A serious vascular event occurred in 90 and in 85 patients, respectively (HR 1.07; 95% CI 0.80-1.44; P= 0.65). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The overall incidence of bleeding events was 89 (11.9%) and 131 (17.3%), respectively </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>DZ-697b </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>DZ-697b inhibits collagen and ristocetin-mediated platelet adhesion and aggregation and does not require metabolization to generate its active compound (65). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The antithrombotic effect and the bleeding time prolongation of three DZ-697b doses were compared with 300 mg clopidogrel in 20 healthy subjects randomized to a single oral dose of DZ-697b (60, 120, and 360 mg) or clopidogrel (300 mg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>DZ-697b (120 mg) showed antithrombotic effects comparable to 300 mg clopidogrel, with significantly reduced bleeding time prolongations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Atopaxar (E5555) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Atopaxar (E5555) is a small molecule, 1-(3-tert-butyl-4-methoxy-5-morpholinophenyl) -2- (5,6-diethoxy-7-fluoro-1 -intino-1,3-dihydro-2H-isoindol-2yl) ethanone hydrobromide that acts as PAR-1 antagonist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>In healthy volunteers, E5555 showed antiplatelet effects without increasing bleeding times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Two randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase II clinical trials (J-LANCELOT) (66) have assessed the safety and tolerability of atopaxar in addition to standard therapy in patients with ACS or high-risk coronary artery disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>In addition to aspirin, patients received atopaxar (50 mg, 100 mg, or 200 mg) or placebo once daily for 12 or 24 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>All atopaxar doses tested achieved a significant level of platelet inhibition with no increase in severe bleeding episodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The rate of major cardiovascular adverse events in the atopaxar group was similar to placebo (ACS 6.6% and 5.0% in placebo or E5555, respectively, P=0.73; CAD 4.5% placebo versus 1.0% E5555, P= 0.066). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Vorapaxar </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Vorapaxar (SCH 530348) is an orally active and reversible agent belonging to the class of thrombin receptor antagonists (TRAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Vorapaxar blocks the platelet PAR-1 receptor, inhibiting thrombin-induced activation and aggregation of platelets without affecting thrombin-induced fibrin production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Phase I study data showed a significant dose-related inhibition of platelet aggregation with &gt; 90% inhibition at 1 h, lasting at least 72 h in the absence of significant adverse events (67). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The TRA-PCI (68), a randomized, double-blind, multicenter phase II study, was designed to assess tolerability and safety of an oral loading dose of vorapaxar (10 mg, 20 mg, or 40 mg) in patients undergoing coronary angiography with planned PCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>In addition to the standard of care (aspirin ± clopidogrel), those who subsequently underwent PCI received an oral maintenance dose (0.5 mg, 1.0 mg, or 2.5 mg/day) of vorapaxar or placebo for 60 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>The primary end-point was the incidence of clinically significant major or minor bleeding according to theTIMI scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>In spite of the limited time of observation (60 days) versus the very long half-life (100-360 h) of vorapaxar, no difference in the primary end-point of major or minor bleeding has been found (2%, 3%, 4% in the three loading dose groups versus 3.3% in placebo group;P= 0.57). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Nor were significant differences in major cardiovascular events observed in the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Platelet function testing showed a very potent and sustained effect with the 40-mg loading dose and the 2.5-mg maintenance dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>In a subgroup of subjects undergoing coronary bypass surgery while under vorapaxar, there was no evidence of increased bleeding, suggesting that PAR-1 blockade during cardiopulmonary bypass may ‘preserve’ normal hemostasis (69). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>In a phase II study (70), 117 NSTEMI patients undergoing non-urgent PCI have been randomized to receive, on top of standard dual antiplatelet therapy (aspirin + ticlopidine) and heparin, two different dosages of vorapaxar (20 mg or 40 mg loading dose, followed by 1 mg/d or 2.5 mg/d maintenance dose) or placebo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>While TIMI major and minor bleedings were similar between the different treatment arms (14% versus 10%), peri-procedural AMI was significantly lower in treated patients (16.9% versus 42.9 in the placebo group %; P= 0.013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Two large multicenter, international, prospective, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III clinical trials were designed to establish the potential role of vorapaxar in treatment of CAD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>TRA* CER (71) is a prospective, randomized, double-blind, multicenter phase III trial designed to determine whether vorapaxar (40-mg loading dose, followed by 2.5 mg daily for at least 1 year) can lead to further reduction in ischemic events when added to standard medical treatment in NSTEMI patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>As an estimate, 19,000 subjects are required to achieve adequate power. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Primary composite end-point is the effect on cardiovascular death, AMI, stroke, recurrent ischemia with hospitalization, urgent PCI, and bleeding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>TRA 2°P-TIMI 50 (72) will evaluate the efficacy and safety of vorapaxar during long-term treatment of patients with established atherosclerotic disease receiving standard therapy (up to 27,000 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The study targeted patients with a documented history of AMI or stroke within 2 weeks to 12 months before the time of inclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Patients with peripheral artery disease (PAD) are eligible for inclusion if they have intermittent claudication in conjunction with an ankle-brachial index &lt; 0.85 or previous revascularization for limb ischemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Participants are randomized to receive vorapaxar (2.5 mg daily) or placebo in addition to standard therapy for at least 1 year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The primary composite end-point is cardiovascular death, AMI, stroke, or urgent coronary revascularization, whereas the evaluation of long-term safety includes bleeding events defined by the GUSTO and TIMI criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Future antiplatelet drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>In addition to the antiplatelet drugs reported above, there is a continuous effort to identify newer targets toward which to direct pharmacological strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Gas6 (growth arrest-specific gene 6), a member of the family of vitamin K-dependent proteins, is stored in platelet α granules and is released upon activation (73). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Although it has a 44% sequence homology with protein S, it does not show any anticoagulant activity (74). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Being a growth factor-like molecule, as it interacts with receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) of the Tyro3, Axl, and MerTK (TAM) family, Gas6 employs a unique mechanism of action, interacting through its vitamin K-dependent Gla module with phosphatidylserine-containing membranes and through its carboxy-terminal LG domains with the TAM membrane receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Studies indicate an association between Gas6 and stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of Gas6 function can be achieved by Gas6-neutralizing antibodies, by proteases cleaving the extracellular domain of Gas6 receptors, or by inactivation of RNA for Gas6 or Gas6 receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Antibodies to the carboxy-terminal part of Gas6, responsible for the binding to its receptors, inhibit the aggregation of human platelets induced by ADP (75). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) are involved in tissue remodeling and in the progression of atherosclerosis (76). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Human platelets contain MMP-2 in their cytosol and release them upon aggregation (77). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Active MMP-2, potentiating phosphoinositide-3 kinase activation, amplifies platelet aggregation induced by a variety of agonists in an aspirin- or ADP-receptor antagonist-independent fashion (78). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>MMP-2-neutralizing antibodies have shown protective effects in hearts exposed to ischemia-reperfusion injury (79). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>MMP-2 gene-silencing techniques (80) may be exploited to gain cell-selective MMP-2 inhibition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The CD40 ligand (CD40L; CD 154) is a trans-membrane protein expressed on the surface of activated platelets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Following its exposure, an exodomain (soluble CD40 ligand, sCD40L) is released and binds to integrin αIIbβ3 on activated platelets, thus promoting thrombus stabilization (81). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Therapeutic targeting of the CD40-CD40L axis using humanized anti-CD40L antibodies has already been attempted (82). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Shedding of sCD40L from the surface of activated platelets can be prevented by an anti-CD40L antibody (G28-5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>This may reduce plasma concentrations of sCD40L and, in turn, blunt platelet reactivity (83). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In addition to the production by platelets, PGE2 is also produced by other cells in blood, including monocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Low concentrations of PGE2 potentiate platelet aggregation by priming protein kinase C activation and by inhibiting ade-nylylcyclase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The facilitating effects of PGE2 on platelets are mediated by EP3 (84,85). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>In animal studies, DG041, a novel first-in-class antagonist of EP3, effectively inhibits platelet aggregation without increasing the bleeding time (86). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>In a phase II trial in patients with peripheral arterial disease, DG041 was found to reduce platelet activation (87). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Major limitations of current antiplatelet drugs include risk of bleeding, significant interindividual variability in the response, and extended duration of action that cannot be reversed if the need for hemostasis or emergency surgery arises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Newer anti-platelet drugs have addressed some but not all these limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Dual antiplatelet treatment has only been efficacious in acute coronary syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>In addition, newer thienopyridines did not show advantages over and above those of ticlopidine or clopidogrel as to reduction of stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Because of its pharmacodynamic characteristics, prasugrel is more efficacious in preventing ischemic events in patients with ACS undergoing PCI, but with increased bleeding complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>The same concept is true for ticagrelor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Platelet activation by thrombin is distinct and appears to be less important for hemostasis than fibrin generation (preclinical data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, inhibition of PAR-1 function rather than inhibition of fibrin generation or activity may provide a newer strategy for treatment of thrombotic disorders in humans (88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Individual bleeding risk, however, has to be further defined, as this would be the first antiplatelet drug in which a greater efficacy is not associated with a worse safety (greater bleeding tendency). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>A concerted effort that takes into consideration clinical, genetic, and laboratory information represents a major direction to be pursued in order to tailor the therapeutic approach for individual patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>The results of on-going clinical trials and the identification of further potentially useful targets for antiplatelet treatment (87) will hopefully help address this issue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Supported by a grant of the Italian Government: Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Università e della Ricerca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>PRIN 2008: ‘Farmacogenetica degli antiag-greganti: identificazione di varianti geniche comuni quali alleli di suscettibilità per una farmacoterapia su base individuale'. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Declaration of interest</title><p>All the authors have revised and approved the present manuscript. Professor Giovanni Di Minno, Professor Elena Tremoli, Professor Marina Camera, and Professor Susanna Colli did not receive specific funding for the preparation of this manuscript. During the last 5 years they served on advisory boards and received honoraria and grants for research unrelated to this study. The other authors have nothing to declare.</p></sec></SecTag><sec><title>Note</title><p>While this manuscript was under revision, results from LANCELOT-CAD were published (Circulation. 2011;123:1854-1863). In this study patients with a history of high-risk CAD were randomized to receive 50, 100, or 200 mg daily atopaxar or matching placebo for 24 weeks and followed up for an additional 4 weeks. Although no difference was found as to major bleeding events, overall bleeding incidence (key safety end point) showed a dose-dependent trend in the atopaxar arm as compared with placebo by CURE criteria (p for trend=0.01) but not by TIMI criteria (p for trend=0.07). As to the major adverse cardiac events occurrence (secondary end points), no significant difference was found between the atopaxar treatment arms and placebo (2.6% vs 4.6%; p=0.20). In addition, a transient elevation in liver transaminases and dose-dependent QTc prolongation without apparent complications were observed in higher-dose atopaxar treatment groups.</p></sec><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>1WassermanEJShipleyNMAtherothrombosis in acute coronary syndromes: mechanisms, markers, and mediators of vulnerabilityMt Sinai J Med200673431916470323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>2BrassLFThrombin and platelet activationChest20031243suppl18S25S12970120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>3OffermannsSActivation of platelet function through G protein coupled receptorsCirc Res200699129330417158345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>4Varga-SzaboDPleinesINieswandtBCell adhesion mechanisms in plateletsArterioscler Thromb Vase Biol20082840312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>5MontalescotGPlatelet biology and implications for antiplatelet therapy in atherothrombotic diseaseClin Appl Thromb Hemost2010Jun 21 (Epub ahead of print) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>6CattaneoMNew P2Y12 blockersJ Thromb Haemost20097Suppl 1262519630813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>7RaymenantsEYangBNicoliniFBehrensPLawsonDMehtaJLVerapamil and aspirin modulate platelet-mediated vasomotion in arterial segments with intact or disrupted endotheliumJ Am Coll Cardiol19932268498354799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>8CoughlinSRProtease-activated receptors in hemostasis, thrombosis and vascular biologyJ Thromb Haemost2005318001416102047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>9De CandiaEHallSWRutellaSLandolfiRAndrewsRKDe CristofaroRBinding of thrombin to glycoprotein Ib accelerates the hydrolysis of Par-1 on intact plateletsJ Biol Chem20012764692811084032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>10ShahRProtease-activated receptors in cardiovascular health and diseasesAm Heart J20091572536219185631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>11JenningsLKRole of platelets in atherothrombosisAm J Cardiol20091033suppl4A10A </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>12DaviGPatronoCPlatelet activation and atherothrombosisN Engl J Med200735724829418077812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>13BaigentCBlackwellLCollinsREmbersonJGodwinJPetoRAntithrombotic Trialists’ (ATT) CollaborationAspirin in the primary and secondary prevention of vascular disease: collaborative meta-analysis of individual participant data from randomised trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Antithrombotic Trialists’ (ATT) CollaborationLancet200937318496019482214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>14DiMinno GCerboneAMMattioliPLTurcoSIovineCManciniMFunctionally thrombasthenic state in normal platelets following the administration of ticlopidineJ Clin Invest198575328383156146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>15HassWKEastonJDAdamsHPJrPryse-PhillipsWMolonyBAAndersonSA randomized trial comparing ticlopidine hydrochloride with aspirin for the prevention of stroke in high-risk patients: Ticlopidine Aspirin Stroke Study GroupN Engl J Med198932150172761587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>16UrbanPMacayaCRupprechtHJKiemeneijFEmanuelssonHFontanelliARandomized evaluation of anticoagulation versus antiplatelet therapy after coronary stent implantation in high-risk patients: the multicenter aspirin and ticlopidine trial after intracoronary stenting (MATTIS)Circulation1998982126329815866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>17A randomized, blinded trial of clopidogrel versus aspirin in patients at risk of ischaemic events (CAPRIE)CAPRIE Steering CommitteeLancet19963481329398918275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>18HankeyGJSudlowCLDunbabinDWThienopyridine derivatives (ticlopidine, clopidogrel) versus aspirin for preventing stroke and other serious vascular events in high vascular risk patientsCochrane Database Syst Rev2000CD001246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>19PetersRJMehtaSRFoxKAZhaoFLewisBSKopeckySLEffects of aspirin dose when used alone or in combination with clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromes: observations from the Clopidogrel in Unstable angina to prevent Recurrent Events (CURE) studyCirculation20031081682714504182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>20AronowHDSteinhublSRBrennanDMBergerPBTopolEJCREDO InvestigatorsBleeding risk associated with 1 year of dual antiplatelet therapy after percutaneous coronary intervention: insights from the Clopidogrel for the Reduction of Events During Observation (CREDO) trialAm Heart J20091573697419185647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>21AngiolilloDJVariability in responsiveness to oral antiplatelet therapyAm J Cardiol2009103Suppl27A34A </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>22KrasopoulosGBristerSJBeattieWSBuchananMRAspirin ‘resistance’ and risk of cardiovascular morbidity: a systematic review and meta-analysisBMJ2008336195818202034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>23EikelboomJWHirshJWeitzJIJohnstonMYiQYusufSAspirin resistant thromboxane B biosynthesis and risk of myocardial infarction or cardiovascular death in patients at high risk of for cardiovascular eventsCirculation20021051650511940542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>24SofiFMarcucciRGoriAMGiustiBAbbateRGensiniGFClopidogrel non-responsiveness and risk of cardio vascular morbidity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>An updated meta-analysisThromb Haemost2010103841820135063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>25HerasMBuenoHBardajíAFernández-OrtizAMartíHMarrugatJMagnitude and consequences of undertreatment of high-risk patients with non-ST segment elevation acute coronary syndromes: insights from the DESCARTES RegistryHeart2006921571616644860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>26KuliczkowskiWWitkowskiAPolonskiLWatalaCFilipiakKBudajAInterindividual variability in the response to oral antiplatelet drugs: a position paper of the Working Group on antiplatelet drugs resistance appointed by the Section of Cardiovascular Interventions of the Polish Cardiac Society, endorsed by the Working Group on Thrombosis of the European Society of CardiologyEur Heart J2009304263519174428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>27DiMinno GSilverMJCerboneAMMurphySTrial of repeated low-dose aspirin in diabetic angiopathyBlood198668886913092890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>28MareeAOCurtinRJChubbADolanCCoxDO'BrienJCycloxygenase-1 haplotype modulates platelet response to aspirinJ Thromb Haemost200532340516150050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>29SimonTVerstuyftCMary-KrauseMQuteinehLDrouetEMéneveauNGenetic determinants of response to clopidogrel and cardiovascular eventsN Engl J Med20093603637519106083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>30Di MinnoGSilverMJMurphySMonitoring the entry of new platelets into the circulation after ingestion of aspirinBlood198361108156404326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>31ZimmermannNGamsEHohlfeldTAspirin in coronary artery bypass surgery: new aspects of and alternatives for an old antithrombotic agentEur J Cardiothorac Surg2008349310818448350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>32GroveELHvasAMMortensenSBLarsenSBKristensenSDEffect of platelet turnover on whole blood platelet aggregation in patients with coronary artery diseaseJ Thromb Haemost201191859120955349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>33DiMinno GVioliFAspirin resistance and diabetic angiopathy: back to the futureThromb Res200411397915115664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>34FarréAJTamargoJMateos-CaceresPJAzconaLMacayaCOld and new molecular mechanisms associated with platelet resistance to antithromboticsPharm Res20102723657320628791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="?"><plain>35CoccheriSAntiplatelet drugs—do we need new options? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>With a reappraisal of direct thromboxane inhibitorsDrugs20107088790820426498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>36MehtaSRBassandJPChrolaviciusSDiazRFoxKAGrangerCBDesign and rationale of CURRENT-OASIS 7: a randomized, 2x2 factorial trial evaluating optimal dosing strategies for clopidogrel and aspirin in patients with ST and non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndromes managed with an early invasive strategyAm Heart J20081561080819033002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>37BonelloLCamoin-JauLArmeroSComOArquesSBurignat-BonelloCTailored clopidogrel loading dose according to platelet reactivity monitoring to prevent acute and subacute stent thrombosisAm J Cardiol2009110351019101221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>38BonelloLCamoin-JauLArquesSBoyerCPanagidesDWittenbergOAdjusted clopidogrel loading doses according to vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein phosphorylation index decrease rate of major adverse cardiovascular events in patients with clopidogrel resistance: a multicenter randomized prospective studyJ Am Coll Cardiol20085114041118387444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>39PriceMJBergerPBAngiolilloDJTeirsteinPSTanguayJFKandzariDEEvaluation of individualized clopidogrel therapy after drug-eluting stent implantation in patients with high residual platelet reactivity: design and rationale of the GRAVITAS trialAm Heart J20091578182419376306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>40GajosGRostoffPUndasAPiwowarskaWEffects of polyunsaturated omega-3 fatty acids on responsiveness to dual antiplatelet therapy in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention: the OMEGA-PCI (OMEGA-3 fatty acids after pci to modify responsiveness to dual antiplatelet therapy) studyJ Am Coll Cardiol2010551671820394870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>41GotoSCilostazol: potential mechanism of action for antithrombotic effects accompanied by a low rate of bleedingAtheroscler Suppl200563ll16275169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>42AngiolilloDJCapranzanoPGotoSAslamMDesaiBCharltonRKA randomized study assessing the impact of cilostazol on platelet function profiles in patients with diabetes mellitus and coronary artery disease on dual antiplatelet therapy: results of the OPTIMUS-2 studyEur Heart J20082922021118567918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>43KamalAKNaqviIHusainMRKhealaniBACilostazol versus aspirin for secondary prevention of vascular events after stroke of arterial originCochrane Database Syst Rev2011CD008076. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/14651858.CD008076.pub2">10.1002/14651858.CD008076.pub2</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>44AngiolilloDJBhattDLGurbelPAJenningsLKAdvances in antiplatelet therapy: agents in clinical developmentAm J Cardiol2009103Suppl40A51A </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>45BrandtJTPayneCDWiviottSDWeerakkodyGFaridNASmallDSA comparison of prasugrel and clopidogrel loading doses on platelet function: magnitude of platelet inhibition is related to active metabolite formationAm Heart J200715366e9-el617174640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>46WiviottSDAmmanEMWintersKJWeerakkodyGMurphySABehounekBDRandomized comparison of prasugrel (CS-747, LY640315), a novel thienopyridine P2Y12 antagonist, with clopidogrel in percutaneous coronary intervention: results of the Joint Utilization of Medications to Block Platelets Optimally (JUMBO)-TIMI 26 trialCirculation200511133667315967851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>47WiviottSDTrenkDFrelingerALO'DonoghueMNeumannFJMichelsonAPrasugrel compared with high loading- and maintenance-dose clopidogrel in patients with planned percutaneous coronary intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>The prasugrel in comparison to clopidogrel for inhibition of platelet activation and aggregation thrombolysis in myocardial infarction 44 trialCirculation200711629233218056526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>48WiviottSDBraunwaldEMcCabeCHMontalescotGRuzylloWGottliebSPrasugrel versus clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromesN Engl J Med200735720011517982182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>49WiviottSDBraunwaldEMcCabeCHHorvathIKeltaiMHerrmanJPIntensive oral antiplatelet therapy for reduction of ischaemic events including stem thrombosis in patients with acute coronary syndromes treated with percutaneous coronary intervention and stenting in the TRITON-TIMI 38 trial: a subanalysis of a randomised trialLancet200837113536318377975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>50ChinCTRoeMTFoxKAPrabhakaranDMarshallDAPetitjeanHStudy design and rationale of a comparison of prasugrel and clopidogrel in medically managed patients with unstable angina/non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction: the TaRgeted platelet Inhibition to cLarify the Optimal strateGy to medicallY manage Acute Coronary Syndromes (TRILOGY ACS) trialAm Heart J2010160162220598967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>51GreenbaumABOhmanEMGibsonCMBorzakSStebbinsATLuMPreliminary experience with intravenous P2Y12 platelet receptor inhibition as an adjunct to reduced-dose alteplase during acute myocardial infarction: results of the Safety, Tolerability and Effect on Patency in Acute Myocardial Infarction (STEP-AMI) angiographic trialAm Heart J2007154702917892995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>52HarringtonRAStoneGWMcNultySWhiteHDLincoffAMGibsonCMPlatelet inhibition with cangrelor in patients undergoing PCIN Engl J Med200936123182919915221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>53BhattDLLincoffAMGibsonCMStoneGWMcNultySMontalescotGIntravenous platelet blockade with cangrelor during PCIN Engl J Med200936123304119915222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>54AndersonSDShahNKYimJEpsteinBJEfficacy and safety of ticagrelor: a reversible P2Y12 receptor antagonistAnn Pharmacother2010445243720124464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>55StoreyRFHustedSHarringtonRAHeptinstallSWilcoxRGPetersGInhibition of platelet aggregation by AZD6140, a reversible oral P2Y12 receptor antagonist, compared with clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromesJ Am Coll Cardiol2007501852617980251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>56HustedSEmanuelssonHHeptinstallSSandsetPMWickensMPetersGPharmacodynamics, pharmacokinetics, and safety of the oral reversible P2Y12 antagonist AZD6140 with aspirin in patients with atherosclerosis: a double-blind comparison to clopidogrel with aspirinEur Heart J2006271038716476694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>57TantryUSBlidenKPWeiCStoreyRFArmstrongMButlerKFirst analysis of the relation between CYP2C19 genotype and pharmacodynamics in patients treated with ticagrelor versus clopidogrel: The ONSET/ OFFSET and RESPOND genotype studiesCirc Cardiovasc Genet201035566621079055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>58CannonCPHustedSHarringtonRASciricaBMEmanuelssonHPetersGSafety, tolerability, and initial efficacy of AZD6140, the first reversible oral adenosine diphosphate receptor antagonist, compared with clopidogrel, in patients with non-ST segment elevation acute coronary syndrome: primary results of the DISPERSE-2 trialJ Am Coll Cardiol20075018445117980250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>59WallentinLBeckerRCBudajACannonCPEmanuelssonHHeldCTicagrelor versus clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromesN Engl J Med200936110455719717846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>60SerebruanyVLStebbingJAtarDDyspnoea after antiplatelet agents: the AZD6140 controversyInt J Clin Pract2007615293317313629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>61BhattDLIntensifying platelet inhibition—navigating between Scylla and CharybdisN Engl J Med200735720788117982183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>62GurbelPABlidenKPButlerKTantryUSGesheffTWeiCRandomized double-blind assessment of the ONSET and OFFSET of the antiplatelet effects of ticagrelor versus clopidogrel in patients with stable coronary artery disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>The ONSET/OFFSET StudyCirculation200912025778519923168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>63LeonardiSRaoSVHarringtonRABhattDLGibsonCMRoeMTRationale and design of the randomized, double-blind trial testing INtraveNous and Oral administration of elinogrel, a selective and reversible P2Y(12)-receptor inhibitor, versus clopidogrel to eVAluate Tolerability and Efficacy in nonurgent Percutaneous Coronary Interventions patients (INNOVATE-PCI)Am Heart J2010160657220598974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>64ShinoharaYNishimaruKSawadaTTerashiAHandaSHiraiSS-ACCESS Study GroupSarpogrelate-SarpoAspirin comparative clinical study for efficacy and safety in secondary prevention of cerebral infarction (S-ACCESS): a randomized, double-blind, aspirin controlled trialStroke20083918273318388340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>65ZafarMUIbáñezBChoiBGVorchheimerDAPiñeroAJinXA new oral antiplatelet agent with potent antithrombotic properties: comparison of DZ-697b with clopidogrel in a randomized phase I studyThromb Haemost20101032051220062928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>66GotoSOgawaHTakeuchiMFlatherMDBhattDLJ-LANCELOT (Japanese-Lesson from Antagonizing the Cellular Effect of Thrombin) InvestigatorsDouble-blind, placebo-controlled phase II studies of the protease-activated receptor 1 antagonist E5555 (atopaxar) in Japanese patients with acute coronary syndrome or high-risk coronary artery diseaseEur Heart J20103126011320805115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>67AngiolilloDJCapranzanoPPharmacology of emerging novel platelet inhibitorsAm Heart J20081562SupplS10518657681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>68BeckerRCMoliternoDJJenningsLKPieperKSPeiJNiedermanASafety and tolerability of SCH 530348 in patients undergoing non-urgent percutaneous coronary intervention: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase II studyLancet20093739192819286091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>69DayJRPunjabiPPRandiAMHaskardDOLandisRCTaylorKMClinical inhibition of the seven-transmembrane thrombin receptor (PAR1) by intravenous aprotinin during cardiothoracic surgeryCirculation2004110259760015262827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>70GotoSYamaguchiTIkedaYKatoKYamaguchiHJensenPSafety and exploratory efficacy of the novel thrombin receptor (PAR-1) antagonist SCH530348 for non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndromeJ Ateroscler Thromb20101715664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>71TRA*CERExecutiveSteeringCommitteesThe thrombin receptor antagonists for clinical event reduction in acute coronary syndrome (TRA*CER) trial: study design end rationaleAm Heart J20091583273419699853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>72MorrowDASciricaBMFoxKABermanGStronyJVeltriEEvaluation of a novel antiplatelet agent for secondary prevention in patients with a history of atherosclerotic disease: Design and rationale for the Thrombin-Receptor Antagonist in Secondary Prevention of Atherothrombotic Ischemic Events (TRA 2°P)-TIMI 50 trialAm Heart J20091583354119699854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>73IshimotoYNakanoTRelease of a product of growth arrestspecific gene 6 from rat plateletsFEBS Lett2000466197910648841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>74ManfiolettiGBrancoliniCAvanziGSchneiderCThe protein encoded by a growth arrestspecific gene (gas6) is a new member of the vitamin K-dependent proteins related to protein S, a negative coregulator in the blood coagulation cascadeMol Cell Biol1993134976858336730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>75ChenCLiQDarrowALWangYDerianCKYangJMer receptor tyrosine kinase signaling participates in platelet functionArterioscler Thromb Vase Biol200424111823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>76NagaseHVisseRMurphyGStructure and function of matrix metalloproteinases and TIMPsCardiovasc Res2006695627316405877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>77SawickiGSandersEJSalasEWozniakMRodrigoJRadomskiMWLocalization and translocation of MMP-2 during aggregation of human plateletsThromb Haemost19988083699843180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>78FalcinelliEGuglielminiGTortiMGreselePIntraplatelet signaling mechanisms of the priming effect of matrix metalloproteinase-2 on platelet aggregationJ Thromb Haemost2005325263516241951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>79CheungPYSawickiGWozniakMWangWRadomskiMWSchulzRMatrix metalloproteinase-2 contributes to ischemia reperfusion injury in the heartCirculation20001011833910769285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>80HuYBLiDGLuHMModified synthetic siRNA targeting tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-2 inhibits hepatic fibrogenesis in ratsJ Gene Med200792172917351970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>81AndrePPrasadKSDenisCVHeMPapaliaJMHynesROCD40L stabilizes arterial thrombi by a b3 integrin-dependent mechanismNat Med200282475211875495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>82KuwanaMNomuraSFujimuraKNagasawaTMutoYKurataYEffect of a single injection of humanized anti-CD 154 monoclonal antibody on the platelet-specific autoimmune response in patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpuraBlood200410312293614551140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>83OtterdalKPedersenTMSolumNORelease of soluble CD40 ligand after platelet activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Studies on the solubilization phaseThromb Res20041141677715342213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>84MaHHaraAXiaoCYOkadaYTakahataONakayaKIncreased bleeding tendency and decreased susceptibility to thromboembolism in mice lacking the prostaglandin E2 receptor subtype EP3Circulation200110411768011535576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b85"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>85FabreJENguyenMAthirakulKCogginsKMcNeishJDAustinSActivation of the murine EP3 receptor for PGE2 inhibits cAMP production and promotes platelet aggregationJ Clin Invest20011076031011238561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b86"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>86SinghJZellerWZhouNHategenGMishraRPolozovAAntagonists of the EP3 receptor for prostaglandin E2 are novel antiplatelet agents that do not prolong bleedingACS Chem Biol200941152619193156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b87"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>87GreselePFalcinelliEMomiSPotentiation and priming of platelet activation: a potential target for antiplatelet therapyTrends Pharmacol Sci2008293526018539343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b88"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>88AngiolilloDJCapodannoDGotoSPlatelet thrombin receptor antagonism and atherothrombosisEur Heart J201031172819948715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
