<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3613406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23560048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-33147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059442</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Kinetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA-binding proteins</subject><subject>Growth factors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Differentiation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Mechanisms of Signal Transduction</subject><subject>Membrane Receptor Signaling</subject><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject><subject>Signaling in Cellular Processes</subject><subject>Signaling Pathways</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Bursted BMP Triggered Receptor Kinase Activity Drives Smad1 Mediated Long-Term Target Gene Oscillation in c2c12 Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">BMP Signaling Activates Pulsatile Gene Expression</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schul</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Regneri</surname><given-names>Janine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Toni Ulrich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Physiological Chemistry I, University of Wuerzburg, Wuerzburg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>Prasun</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Temple University, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>toni.wagner@viserion.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: DS TUW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: DS AS JR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: DS MS TUW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MS TUW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: DS MS TUW. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e59442</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Schul et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Schul et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Bone Morphogenetic Proteins (BMPs) are important growth factors that regulate many cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>During embryogenesis they act as morphogens and play a critical role during organ development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>They influence cell fates via concentration-gradients in the embryos where cells transduce this extracellular information into gene expression profiles and cell fate decisions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>How receiving cells decode and quantify BMP2/4 signals is hardly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>There is little data on the quantitative relationships between signal input, transducing molecules, their states and location, and ultimately their ability to integrate graded systemic inputs and generate qualitative responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Understanding this signaling network on a quantitative level should be considered a prerequisite for efficient pathway modulation, as the BMP pathway is a prime target for therapeutic invention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Hence, we quantified the spatial distribution of the main signal transducer of the BMP2/4 pathway in response to different types and levels of stimuli in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>We found that the subcellular localization of Smad1 is independent of ligand concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Smad1 phosphorylation levels relate proportionally to BMP2 ligand concentrations and they are entirely located in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found that BMP2 stimulates target gene expression in non-linear, wave-like forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Amplitudes showed a clear concentration-dependency, for sustained and transient stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>We found that even burst-stimulation triggers gene-expression wave-like modulations that are detectable for at least 30 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Finally, we show here that target gene expression oscillations depend on receptor kinase activity, as the kinase drives further expression pulses without receptor reactivation and the target gene expression breaks off after inhibitor treatment in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding was provided by the German Research Foundation (DFG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dfg.de">www.dfg.de</ext-link>), and GK 1048 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gk-1048.uni-wuerzburg.de">www.gk-1048.uni-wuerzburg.de</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Tightly controlled quantitative integration of ligand levels is very important for multicellular organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This is best illustrated by embryonic development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Bone Morphogenetic Proteins (BMPs) act as graded morphogens and are responsible for the dorsal-to-ventral cell type specification in a dose-dependent manner [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Clearly, there must exist a machinery that translates these morphogen gradients into so far unknown cell fate mechanisms by thresholding them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>BMPs are secreted proteins that belong to the TGF-ß superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>They are involved in the regulation of many cellular processes like proliferation, differentiation, adhesion as well as apoptosis [2]–[4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The ligands signal through a family of transmembrane serine/threonine kinase receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Signaling occurs through the heterotetramerization of two receptor subtypes [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The constitutively active type II receptor activates the type I receptor by trans-phosphorylation, and the activated type I receptor then in turn activates the key signal transducers, the Smad proteins [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Distinct Smad family members have been identified and classified into three different subgroups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The receptor-regulated Smads (R-Smads) include Smad1, 2, 3, 5 and 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>They become phosphorylated by the type I receptor kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Smad2 and Smad3 are activated by TGF-ß proteins, while Smad1, 5 and 8 are activated by BMP ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The R-Smads form complexes with Smad4, which is the only member of the common mediator Smads (Co-Smads) [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The Smad complexes translocate into the nucleus and activate expression of target genes in association with other transcription factors [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, even without ligand the cellular distribution of Smad2 and Smad3 is not static, but the proteins are constantly shuttling between the nucleus and the cytoplasm [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In the case of BMP signaling, Smad-complexes bind to short GC-rich DNA regions in target gene promoters that were identified as BMP-responsive elements (BRE) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The inhibitory Smad proteins, Smad6 and Smad7, stably bind to the intracellular domain of the type I receptor and thereby prevent the phosphorylation of R-Smads [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Smad6 also exhibits other inhibitory functions like competing with Smad4 for binding to phosphorylated Smad1 [13] and interacting with transcriptional co-repressors in the nucleus [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The BMP signaling pathway is implicated in severe human diseases like cancer, fibrosis, multiple hereditary conditions and wound-healing disorders [15]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This elucidates that its regulation needs to be tightly controlled and is often subject to disregulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Consequently, it is reasonable to expect a strict fine tuning of each individual step of signal transduction when looking at the large number of modulatory factors that regulate the pathway (reviewed in [19]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In order to successfully develop new therapeutics, it is thus pivotal to quantify the BMP signal transduction dynamics, their modulation and coupled transcriptional outcomes with high resolution and accuracy over an extended period of time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In this context a large number of studies have been published on the TGFß-Smad2/3 pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>First, indirect immunostaining had shown that Smad2 and Smad3 almost completely translocate into the nucleus after 30 minutes of stimulation with TGF-ß [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Later, the kinetics of the Smad2 nucleocytoplasmic shuttling have been investigated with and without stimulation using GFP-fusions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>It revealed, that the nuclear export rate for non-induced cells is more rapid than the import rate and that the nuclear accumulation of Smad2 upon stimulation is caused by a pronounced drop in the export rate [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Recently, a study on quantification of TGF-ß signaling showed that both dose as well as time course of stimulation have significant effects on Smad2 signaling dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this study also demonstrated that cells do respond to short time stimulation pulses [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In principle, there are several ways to modulate signaling output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Besides ligand concentration, stimulation time obviously is an important signal modulator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Studies on ERK revealed that duration of its activation controls cell fate by proliferative or anti-proliferative responses [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained for the TGFß-Smad2/3 pathway, where variation in the cellular behavior was evoked by different signaling durations [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Investigating the quantitative integration of BMP signaling, we present long-term measurements of cellular responses to both sustained and transient BMP2 stimulation under varying concentrations in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Spatio-temporal analyses of Smad1 distribution revealed a basal shuttling mechanism that is unaffected by ligand stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the transcriptional responses were evaluated by two independent approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The gene expression induced by BMP results in oscillating curve patterns over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Mathematical Fourier analysis of our measurements revealed two oscillation components that clearly responded to modulation of stimulation parameters and also verified that basal oscillation is fully dependent on receptor kinase activity in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Smad1 shuttles constantly between nucleus and cytoplasm while the amount of pSmad increases in relation to the stimulation concentration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In order to measure the subcellular localization of Smad1 under non-stimulated and stimulated conditions, we performed indirect immunofluorescence staining using anti-Smad1 in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For quantification of Smad1 amounts in the nucleus and the cytoplasm, respectively, we further stained cell membranes and nuclei with specific dyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Confocal analysis revealed, that there is no significant difference in Smad1 subcellular localization upon ligand stimulation with 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2 over 2 h (Fig. 1A; Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Instead both, the non-stimulated as well as the stimulated cells, showed a nucleocytoplasmic oscillatory translocation behavior of Smad1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0059442-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059442.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Nucleo/cytoplasmic shuttling of Smad1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(A) 3D-Analysis of immunofluorescent stainings using an anti-Smad1 primary antibody, secondary Alexa488 antibody, specific membrane- and nuclear staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Confocal stacks were processed using the Volocity 3D image analysis software; the nuclear/cytoplasmic ratio was calculated and illustrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The black line depicts the time course of the ratio for the unstimulated control, the green line shows the subcellular distribution after stimulation with 0.1 nM BMP2 and the red line after 1 nM BMP2 stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The depicted values are the average of eleven cells for every time point and concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>(B) Analysis of the Smad1-live shuttling using a GFP-Smad1 fusion protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Cells were transiently cotransfected with the Smad1-GFP fusion construct and a H2B-mCherry vector and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>On the next day, cells were stimulated with either 0 nM BMP2 or 1 nM BMP alone or while adding Leptomycin B and imaged at the indicated time points after stimulation using a confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The figure shows two independent cells for each treatment over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence intensity of Smad1-GFP is indicated in pseudocolors ranging from dark blue (lowest signal) to red (strongest signal). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059442.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We next used a GFP-Smad1 fusion construct and transiently cotransfected this with a H2B-mCherry vector into c2c12 wildtype cells to verify this finding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Transfected cells were either non-stimulated or stimulated with 1 nM BMP2, but again did not find nuclear accumulation of the GFP-Smad1 fusion protein in either treatment up to 1 h after stimulation start. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>To ensure that the fusion protein was able to visualize nuclear accumulation of Smad1, we added the nuclear-export-inhibitor Leptomycin B (LMB) to the previously treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Under this condition, GFP-Smad1 fusion proteins clearly accumulated in the nuclei of LMB treated cells independent of previous BMP stimulation (Fig. 1B; Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The quite different cell morphology is typical for this cell type (Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that Smad1 shuttles constantly between the nucleus and the cytoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the distribution of Smad1 protein due to this basal nucleocytoplasmic shuttling is not significantly altered by stimulation with either 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, we found that the amount of nuclear phospho-Smad1 increases in a BMP2 stimulation time- and concentration-dependent manner (Figure S3A–D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Sustained and oscillating gene expression upon continuous stimulation with BMP2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We next investigated the time course of target gene expression of cells continuously stimulated with BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>We therefore generated a clonal cell line stably expressing the secreted Gaussia Luciferase under control of a BRE minimal promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Using secreted Luciferase allowed us to record a true time course of BMP induced promoter transcriptional regulation, as only a small volume of supernatant was taken from each cell culture well at each time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We analyzed Luciferase activity over a time course of 4 h before to 30 h after stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Total Luciferase activity was concentration dependent, which is clear evidence for a functional read-out system as well as the lag-phase at the beginning (Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, as expected, Luciferase activity decreased to baseline levels when incubated at 37°C for 1 h (Figure S6, [25]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We found that BMP-induced reporter gene expression is concentration- and time-dependent (figure 2A), and oscillating progressions suggest gene expression pulses during continuous stimulation with BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the frequencies of the activity bursts are similar for all tested ligand concentrations, however, the wave-peak amplitudes show clear positive correlation with the respective BMP2-concentration used for stimulation (Fig. 2A, Figure S8A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To further prove the reliability of the reporter system, we performed transient experiments with a NFkb-binding site upon stimulation with TNFα (Figure S7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0059442-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059442.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analysis of continuously stimulated cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>(A) 30 h experiment using cells that stably express the Gaussia Luciferase under control of a BRE minimal promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The cells were stimulated with either 0.1 nM (green), 1 nM (red) or 10 nM (blue) BMP2 or non-stimulated (black) as control, 50 µl medium were removed every hour and the Luciferase activity was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the unstimulated control was calculated and assigned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>(B) Quantitative real-time PCR was performed on the BMP target genes id1 and smad6. The cells were stimulated with 0.1 nM (green), 1 nM (red) BMP2 or non-stimulated (black) and every hour one sample was lysed and frozen at −80°C until the further processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059442.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In order to verify this finding in an independent experimental setup, we performed qRT-PCR on the well-described BMP target genes id1 and smad6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Both genes showed an oscillating expression profile with a mRNA maximum after 1 h or 2 h, for 0.1 nM and 1 nM BMP2 respectively (Fig. 2B; Figure S9, Figure S10 and Figure S11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>At later time points, the mRNA expression pulses decreased gradually to a low level of oscillations that were detectable until 30 h after stimulation (Figure S12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>We could show that these transcript level oscillations do directly reflect changes of the target gene mRNA levels, but not changes of the housekeeping gene levels used for RNA level calibrations (Figure S13A and B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>However, the results from these experiments differ in the oscillatory pattern as the Luciferase activity increases over time whereas the mRNA levels decrease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This could be attributed to many reasons including different translation dynamics, different promoters (optimized BRE-promoter element in contrast to endogenous promoters), measurement of protein activity in contrast to mRNA level, half-life times of mRNAs and proteins as well as the delay of the protein due to export, synthesis and folding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>But intracellular Gaussia Luciferase mRNA levels show a similar pattern to endogenous target genes (Figure S14). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Short-time receptor stimulation shows similar gene expression profile as continuous stimulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A recent study revealed that the duration of stimulation is critical for the cellular response [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To better understand the signaling dynamics and the critical parameters, we analyzed how cells respond to a short time receptor stimulus of only 15 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We measured Luciferase activity over 30 h as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Instead of keeping the stimulation medium on the cells until the end of the experiment we, however, replaced it with basal DMEM medium after 15 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The relative Luciferase activity of 0.1 nM, 1 nM and 10 nM BMP2 in case of the wash-away treatment displayed an activity pattern similar to that seen during continuous treatment (Fig. 3A, Figure S15A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Hallmarks of the measured responses were concentration- and time-dependency as well as the oscillating progression with significant activity increases and decreases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Certainly, relative Luciferase activities (fold changes) were lower for 15 minutes stimulation than for continuous treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0059442-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059442.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analysis of short-time receptor stimulus and short-time Smad-phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>(A) 30 h experiment using the stable reporter cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The cells were stimulated with 0.1 nM (green), 1 nM (red) 10 nM (blue) BMP2 or non-stimulated (black) and after 15 minutes the stimulation medium was removed and fresh starvation medium were given to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Then every hour 50 µl medium was withdrawn and the Luciferase activity was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the unstimulated control is depicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(B) Quantitative real-time PCR on id1 and smad6. The cells were stimulated with 0.1 nM (green), 1 nM (red) BMP2 or non-stimulated (black) for 15 minutes and then cultivated in starvation medium until cell lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(C) 30 h experiment using the stable reporter cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The cells were stimulated with the indicated ligand concentrations and after 15 minutes Dorsomorphin was added to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>50 µl medium were withdrawn every hour and the Luciferase activity was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the unstimulated control was calculated and assigned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>(D) qRT-PCR analysis of id1 and smad6. The cells were stimulated with the indicated concentrations for 15 minutes and Dorsomorphin was given to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Every hour one sample was lysed and frozen at −80°C until the further processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059442.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>As before, we verified the reporter gene expression data by qRT-PCR analysis (Fig. 3B) of endogenous target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>15 minutes post receptor activation both target genes showed increased expression and sustained it over 8 h, again displaying oscillations for both 0.1 nM and 1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This fact becomes even more obvious when looking at the single experiment data (Figure S16). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Short-time Smad-phosphorylation leads to decreased and downregulated gene expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Short-time receptor stimulation was sufficient to activate target gene expression for as long as continuous stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>To examine the influence of the receptor kinase on this mechanism, we next wanted to examine how the gene expression profile changes when the receptor kinase is inhibited and no further Smad-proteins can be activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We therefore stimulated the cells with BMP2 as before, but administered Dorsomorphin (BMP receptor type I kinase inhibitor) to the cells 15 minutes later (Fig. 3C, Figure S17A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Compared to the other treatments, the Luciferase assays again show an oscillatory curve shape, but decreased activity fold changes as well as a complete termination after 12 h stimulation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR experiments confirmed this observation. id1 was upregulated after 1 h stimulation-time with 1 nM BMP2, but later downregulated to a level below the basal level (Fig. 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Cells that were stimulated with 0.1 nM BMP and the non-stimulated control cells showed an immediate downregulation of id1 after 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In the case of smad6, Dorsomorphin treatment resulted in an immediate downregulation for all tested ligand concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>These data show that the half-life time of the receptor-kinase activity is 0.5 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Different pathway components contribute to the oscillatory response </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The gene expression experiments revealed that continuous as well as short-term receptor stimulation result in sustainable and oscillating cellular responses, whereas short-term Smad activation leads to abbreviated and decreased responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>We next studied the results of the Luciferase experiments with mathematical methods to compare components of the detected oscillation patterns of the three treatments. Figure 4 shows Fast Fourier Transformations (FFT) of the absolute Luciferase activities of the different cell treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the plots of the continuous and the short-term receptor stimulus treatments show the same prominent oscillation components (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Both show one slow oscillation on a 31 h frequency which appears to be concentration dependent, as the amplitudes rise with higher ligand concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Moreover, at about 16 h/cycle there is an oscillation that increases in proportion to the ligand amount in the case of the continuous stimulation, but it is inversely proportional to the short-time treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Two more at about 10.5 and 2.8 h/cycle are proportional to the BMP2 concentration in both cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Finally, another interesting oscillation was found at 2.5 h/cycle, which is proportional to the ligand concentration for the continuous stimulation and for the short receptor stimulus treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In contrast to that is the treatment with the receptor kinase inhibitor (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Here only one distinctive oscillation at 31 h/cycle was identified, suggesting that different components of the signaling pathway contribute to the overall oscillatory behaviour. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0059442-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059442.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Fast Fourier Transformation (FFT) of the Luciferase data. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The absolute values of one Gaussia Luciferase experiment triplet were entered to the MATLAB software and transformed using the “fft” comand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The blue crosses illustrate the stimulation with 10 nM BMP, the red crosses the stimulation with 1 nM BMP, the green crosses with 0.1 nM BMP and the black crosses show the non-stimulated control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(A) FFT of the continuous stimulation experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(B) FFT of the short-time receptor stimulus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>(C) FFT of the short-time Smad-phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059442.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In recent years, the analysis of signaling modulation and networking responsible for the regulation of target gene expression has gained increasing attention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A great deal of work has been done on modeling a series of different signaling pathways including the TGF-ß signaling pathway [21], [26]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Since BMP and TGF-ß signaling share the co-Smad, the inhibitory Smads as well as one receptor subtype, one could assume that the models of the TGF-ß pathway are conferrable to the BMP-pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In this study we examined the dynamics of the BMP signaling pathway and could show profound differences to the TGF-ß signaling dynamics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>For the TFGß-Smad2/3 pathway, it is well known that Smad2/3 strongly accumulate in the nucleus upon stimulation with very low TGF-ß concentrations in the picomolar range [20], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that this cannot be attributed to Smad1 in c2c12 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Instead we found that only the phospho-Smad1 level in the nuclei increases in proportion to the ligand-concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>A similar effect has been described for Smad1 in a B-cell lymphoma cell line after stimulation with TGF-ß [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, studies in Xenopus embryos also suggest that the pathway activity has little effect on the localization of Smad1 [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Reasons for this difference within the Smad family are unknown, yet two studies indicate that differences in nuclear export signals might play a role [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Our results strongly suggest a constant, basal nucleocytoplasmic shuttling of Smad1, which is not significantly modulated by stimulation up to 1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, it has been shown that stimulation with 10 nM BMP2 leads to a clear nuclear accumulation of Smad1 [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>As a conclusion, Smad1-shuttling dynamics are dose-dependent with a threshold-concentration in the range between 1 nM and 10 nM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The Smad1 import-rate exceeds the export-rate and the proteins accumulate in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Reasons for that might be lacking dephosphorylation, more phospho-Smad1 proteins per complex meaning longer resting time on DNA or that export-proteins have poorer binding efficiency for phospho-Smad1 proteins; many possibilities for this phenomenon, but the real cause remains unexplored. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Concerning the TGF-ß/Smad pathway, it is known that upon sustained stimulation the amount of phospho-Smad2 increases to a maximum and then decreases to a constant level over 8 h [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>This fact points to a correlating gene expression profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our data also show a maximum of smad6 expression after 2 h with subsequent relative peaks at two-hourly intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We conclude that there is a basal oscillation mechanism of the BMP-induced expression of id1 and smad6. Oscillating target gene transcription is supported by the fact that hes1 expression, which is controlled by BMP2 in embryonic stem cells, has been found to oscillate and a hes1-promoter driven Luciferase mimics this oscillatory expression [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>We further conclude that the oscillatory frequency is not influenced by stimulation intensity (BMP concentration). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Instead, the amplitudes are clearly dose-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The discriminated signaling response in the case of Dorsomorphin treatment might be attributed to the input strength in combination with the inhibitor potency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Shortly after continuous stimulation with 1 nM BMP2 nuclear phospho-Smad1 level is considerably higher than the level with 0.1 nM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Thus after stimulation with BMP2 and subsequent kinase-inhibitor treatment, the phospho-Smad1 level is sufficient to exclusively trigger expression of very early target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Since phospho-Smad1 proteins are rapidly degraded by E3 ubiquitin ligases [36] expression of later target genes expires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Mouse models for lung cancer associate elevated BMP2 levels with increased malignancy [37], promoted lung tumor growth [38] and stimulated angiogenesis in developing tumors [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Our study shows, that the BMP target gene transcription is dose-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>As BMP2 has been found to induce cell cycle regulators [40], this might be a reason for pathological proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Consequently, disease conditions might trigger Smad1 accumulation and thus break physiological regulatory pathway mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Comparison of continuous exposure with kinase-inhibitory and wash-away treatment demonstrated that target gene oscillation is directly dependent on the receptor kinase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, once ligand-bound, thus activated, receptor complexes keep up target-gene stimulation for at least 8 h and in wave-like forms without receptor reactivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>It is known that Smad6 is an inhibitor of BMP signaling and continuous expression of Smad6 leads to the inhibition of phospho-Smad1 formation [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>As our results show that smad6 oscillates with 1 h delay to id1, Smad6 is a negative feedback regulator and may be an important regulator for the wave-like response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Possible advantages of oscillating responses are minimized exposure to high levels of ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, transforming stimuli into oscillatory signals is more robust against noise in the input signal and signal propagation [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>However, the real causes for these oscillations remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>During embryogenesis, body patterning and axis formation are determined by morphogen gradients and different cell fates result from distinct gene expression profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, BMPs are used as therapeutics in the clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Our data on signal half-life, the influence of BMP2 concentration, exposure time and receptor inhibition on the temporal course of target-gene-expression create a basis for a novel mathematical model for the BMP signaling pathway that could be used to improve drug compositions, amounts and administration for the compensation of developmental defects and the patients benefit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Cell Culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The mouse myoblast cell line c2c12 (purchased from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lgcstandards-atcc.org/">http://lgcstandards-atcc.org/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2013 March 3.) was cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS (PAA) and penicillin/streptomycin at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>To examine the cellular response of the cells to BMP2 stimulation, cells were starved over night in basal DMEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Transfections were performed using the Fugene HD transfection reagent (Roche) following the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Generation of reporter construct and cell line </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The BRE-Luciferase reporter construct contains a dimer of a published BMP responsive element [43] in front of a MLP minimal promoter and the Gaussia Luciferase gene; furthermore it comprises an independent mCherry-Zeocin fusion under control of a CMV-promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The genes are flanked by a tol2 recognition site for generation of a stable cell line including both reporters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>For generation of the c2c12-BRE_Luc cell line, the tol2 transposase system [44] was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Cells were cotransfected with a construct containing the coding sequence of the tol2 transposase under control of the CMV-promoter and the BRE_Luc construct at a ratio of 2∶1, and subsequently selected with Zeocin for two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Single colonies were picked, expanded and then checked for correct function of the BRE_Luc construct. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Luciferase Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The stable c2c12-BRE_Luc cells were seeded out at a density of 15000cells/cm2 in 6 well plates in the morning in complete medium and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>On the next day, 50 µl medium of all wells was withdrawn hourly for 4 hours to generate the baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>After that cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM, 1 nM or 10 nM BMP2 (kind gift of Walter Sebald, Würzburg) in starvation medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Three different cell treatments were performed: (1) cells were permanently stimulated with BMP2 (continuous stimulation), (2) cells were stimulated for 15 minutes, then the pathway was inhibited by the administration of 10 mM Dorsomorphin (Sigma-Aldrich) or (3) cells were stimulated for 15 minutes, then the stimulation medium was removed and fresh starvation medium was given to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Then every hour 50 µl of the culture medium was removed and stored at 4°C untill measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>An equal volume of fresh starvation medium was administrated to the cells, to keep a constant medium volume over the whole time of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>After 30 h stimulation time, the Luciferase activity was measured with the Promega GloMax 96 Microplate Luminometer and a final concentration of 20 µM Coelenterazine (Synchem OHG) for the enzyme reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Data were evaluated using Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescent stainings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>c2c12 wildtype cells were seeded out on glass coverslips and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Then cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2 for indicated time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescent staining was performed as previously described [45] using anti-Smad1 antibody (Santa Cruz, sc-9765), Alexa Fluor 488 secondary antibody (Invitrogen), Hoechst 33258 (Molecular probes) for DNA staining and CellMask Orange (Invitrogen) for cell membrane staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Confocal stacks were taken at room temperature using a Nikon Eclipse Ti confocal microscope and data were processed using Volocity 3D Image Analysis Software (Improvision). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Live Smad1 shuttling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>A meGFP-Smad1 fusion protein was cloned in front of a CMV-promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>This vector was cotransfected with a H2B-mCherry fusion construct in a 2∶1 ratio into c2c12 wildtype cells and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>On the next day, cells were treated with 0 nM BMP2, 0 nM BMP2 with 10 ng/ml Leptomycin B, 1 nM BMP2 or 1 nM BMP2 with 10 ng/ml Leptomycin B (Sigma-Aldrich) in starvation medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Then the cells were incubated at 37°C and imaged for 1 h with the Nikon Eclipse Ti confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The resulting data were processed using Volocity 3D Image Analysis Software (Improvision). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Real-Time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from cell cultures using the Total RNA Isolation Reagent (AB Gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Samples were digested with DNAseI (Fermentas) to exclude gDNA contamination followed by cDNA synthesis (Fermentas). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed on 25 ng cDNA using SYBR Green reagent and the following primer pairs in single reactions: EF1a forward 5′- TCAGGAGGAGACCACACCTT-3′ and reverse 5′- ATATCCACAGGCAGCAAACA-3′; ID1 forward 5′- AGAACCGCAAAGTGAGCAAG-3′ and reverse 5′- GTGGTCCCGACTTCAGACTC-3′; Smad6 forward 5′- CAAGATCGGTTTTGGCATACTG -3′ and reverse 5′- GTCGGGGAGTTGACGAAGAT -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>PCRs were run at the following conditions: 5 minutes denaturation at 95°C; 40 amplification cycles, each including denaturation at 95°C for 15 seconds, annealing for 20 seconds at 55°C and 20 seconds extension at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The products of the primers pairs were of approximately the same size and had similar melting points, enabeling direct comparison of the transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The results are averages from four independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Data were evaluated using Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Mathematical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The results from the Luciferase experiments were entered to the MATLAB software and transformed using the fft algorithm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Nucleocytoplasmic shuttling of Smad1. c2c12 wt cells were seeded out on glass coverslips and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>On the next day, the cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2 for 0 min, 30 min, 1 h, 1.5 h or 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Then the cells were fixed, sampled with anti-Smad1 primary antibody and Alexa 488-secondary antibody and confocal images were acquired. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Real-color images according to the pseudocolor images of   Fig. 1B . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>These pictures show the real green fluorescence of the Smad1-GFP fusion protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Nuclear pSmad/total Smad1 ratio after stimulation with BMP2. c2c12 wt cells were seeded out on coverslips and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>On the next day, the cells were stimulated with (A) 0 nM, (B) 0.1 nM or (C) 1 nM BMP2 for 0 min, 20 min, 40 min or 60 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>After fixation with PFA and methanol-permeabilization, the cells were sampled with a primary phospho-Smad1/5/8 and secondary Alexa594-secondary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Further immunostaining was performed using anti-Smad1 primary antibody and Alexa 488-secondary antibody and a following incubation with Hoechst was executed for nuclear staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Then confocal stacks were taken and processed using Volocity 3D software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>(D)The fluorescence intensities of the two Alexa-antibodies were taken to calculate the phospho-Smad/Smad ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The bar graphs in the lower panel describe significant increases/decreases between two treatment groups for the respective time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>For example, is the nuclear pSmad/Smad ratio after 40 min stimulation time with 1 nM BMP significantly increased compared to the 40 min non-stimulated situation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Phase contrast images of c2c12 cells. The pictures show the typical variable morphology of the c2c12 cell line. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Progression of the absolute Gaussia Luciferase activity upon sustained stimulation with BMP2. c2c12_BRE-Luc cells was seeded out in 6-well plates and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>On the next day, cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM, 1 nM or 10 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>50 µl medium from every well were removed hourly and stored at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>All samples were measured on the same day with the same Coelenterazine-solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The assigned values represent averages from independent triplets out of one experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Decrease of Gaussia Luciferase activity after incubation at 37°C for 1 h. c2c12_BRE-Luc cells were seeded out and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>On the next day they were stimulated with 0 nM or 10 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>After 12 h stimulation time, 50 µl from every well were removed twice every hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>One sample was stored at 4°C until the measurement and the other sample was incubated for one additional hour at 37°C and then stored at 4°C until the measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>All samples were measured on the same day with the same Coelenterazine-solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>All values represent averages from independently measured triplets of the same experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s006.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Progression of absolute Gaussia Luciferase activity upon sustained stimulation with TNFα. c2c12 cells were seeded out in 6-well plates, transiently transfected with a NFkb-binding site Luciferase reporter and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>On the next day, cells were stimulated with 0 ng/ml or 10 ng/ml TNFα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>50 µl medium from every well were removed hourly and stored at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>All samples were measured on the same day with the same Coelenterazine-solution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s007.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s008"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Two further independent 30 h Luciferase experiments (A) and (B) upon sustained stimulation with BMP2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s008.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s009"><label>Figure S9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Curve progressions of the four independent continuously stimulated qRT-PCR experiments of (A)  id1  after stimulation with 1 nM BMP2, (B)  id1  after stimulation with 0.1 nM BMP2, (C)  smad6  after 1 nM BMP2 and (D)  smad6  after 0.1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s009.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s010"><label>Figure S10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Higher temporal resolution of the target gene curve progression. c2c12_BRE-Luc cells were seeded out and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Then the cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2 and harvested at the indicated time points after stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR anaylsis of the BMP target genes id1 and smad6 as well as the housekeeping gene ef1a followed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the housekeeping gene was calculated and depicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>This figure represents the average of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s010.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s011"><label>Figure S11</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Higher temporal resolution of the target gene curve progression. c2c12_BRE-Luc cells were seeded out and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Then the cells were stimulated with 0 nM or 1 nM BMP2 and harvested at the indicated time points after stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR anaylsis of the BMP target genes id1 and smad6 as well as the housekeeping gene ef1a followed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the housekeeping gene was calculated and depicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>This figure represents the average of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s011.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s012"><label>Figure S12</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Analysis of BMP target gene transcription after long time stimulation. c2c12_BRE-Luc cells were seeded out and starved over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Then the cells were stimulated with 0 nM, 0.1 nM or 1 nM BMP2 and harvested at the indicated time points after stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR anaylsis of the BMP target genes id1 and smad6 as well as the housekeeping gene ef1a followed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The relative fold change to the housekeeping gene was calculated and depicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>This figure represents the average of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s012.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s013"><label>Figure S13</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Raw data from two single qRT-PCR experiments. (A) Triplet of ct-values from one experiment analyzing ef1a and id1 after stimulation with 1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>(B) Triplet of ct-values from one experiment analyzing ef1a and smad6 after stimulation with 0.1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s013.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s014"><label>Figure S14</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR was performed on the Gaussia Luciferase gene of the stably transgenic cell line. The cells were stimulated with 0 nM (black) or 1 nM (red) BMP2 and every hour one sample was lysed and frozen at −80°C until the further processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s014.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s015"><label>Figure S15</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Two further independent 30 h Luciferase experiments (A) and (B) upon removal of the stimulation medium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s015.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s016"><label>Figure S16</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Curve progressions of the four independent short-time stimulation qRT-PCR experiments of (A) id1 after stimulation with 1 nM BMP2, (B) id1 after stimulation with 0.1 nM BMP2, (C) smad6 after 1 nM BMP2 and (D) smad6 after 0.1 nM BMP2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s016.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059442.s017"><label>Figure S17</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Two further independent 30 h Luciferase experiments (A) and (B) with additional Dorsomorphin treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059442.s017.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>We thank W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Sebald for providing the BMP2 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>We further thank G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Harms and Q. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Gan for providing access to the SP5 confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we thank Rudolf Sailer for the help with using the MATLAB software. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0059442-Ferguson1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>1Ferguson EL, Anderson KV (1992) Decapentaplegic acts as a morphogen to organize dorsal-ventral pattern in the Drosophila embryo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Cell 71: 451–461. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1423606">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1423606</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Accessed 28 May 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Patterson1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>2Patterson GI, Padgett RW (2000) TGF beta-related pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Roles in Caenorhabditis elegans development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Trends in genetics 16: 27–33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10637628">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10637628</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Accessed 14 July 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-TenDijke1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>3Ten Dijke P, Miyazono K, Heldin CH (2000) Signaling inputs converge on nuclear effectors in TGF-beta signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Trends in biochemical sciences 25: 64–70. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10664585">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10664585</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Accessed 21.November 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Massagu1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>4Massagué J (2008) TGF-ß in Cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Cell 134: 215–230. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18662538">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18662538</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Accessed 7 July 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Massagu2"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>5 MassaguéJ (1998) TGF-β Signal Transduction. Annu Rev Biochem 67: 753–791.9759503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Shi1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>6Shi Y, Massagué J (2003) Mechanisms of TGF-beta signaling from cell membrane to the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Cell 113: 685–700. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12809600">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12809600</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2012 Feb 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>7Zhang Y, Musci T, Derynck R (1997) The tumor suppressor Smad4/DPC 4 as a central mediator of Smad function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Current biology 7: 270–276. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9094310">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9094310</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 May 19. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Feng1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>8Feng X-H, Derynck R (2005) Specificity and versatility in tgf-beta signaling through Smads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Annual review of cell and developmental biology 21: 659–693. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16212511">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16212511</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 June 14. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Schmierer1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>9 SchmiererB, HillCS (2005) Kinetic Analysis of Smad Nucleocytoplasmic Shuttling Reveals a Mechanism for Transforming Growth Factor ß-Dependent Nuclear Accumulation of Smads. Molecular and cellular biology 25: 9845–9858 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/MCB.25.22.9845">10.1128/MCB.25.22.9845</ext-link>.16260601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Korchynskyi1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>10Korchynskyi O, Ten Dijke P (2002) Identification and functional characterization of distinct critically important bone morphogenetic protein-specific response elements in the Id1 promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>The Journal of biological chemistry 277: 4883–4891. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11729207">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11729207</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 July 18. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Imamura1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>11Imamura T, Takase M, Nishihara a, Oeda E, Hanai J, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>(1997) Smad6 inhibits signalling by the TGF-beta superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Nature 389: 622–626. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9335505">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9335505</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2010 Nov 21. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Inoue1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>12Inoue H, Imamura T, Ishidou Y, Takase M, Udagawa Y, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>(1998) Interplay of signal mediators of decapentaplegic (Dpp): molecular characterization of mothers against dpp, Medea, and daughters against dpp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Molecular biology of the cell 9: 2145–2156. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=25468&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=25468&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 April 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Hata1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>13Hata A, Lagna G, Spring C (1998) Smad6 inhibits BMP/Smad1 signaling by specifically competing with the Smad4 tumor suppressor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Genes &amp; Development 12: 186–197. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genesdev.org/cgi/doi/10.1101/gad.12.2.186">http://www.genesdev.org/cgi/doi/10.1101/gad.12.2.186</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2012 March 26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Murakami1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>14Murakami G, Watabe T, Takaoka K, Miyazono K, Imamura T (2003) Cooperative Inhibition of Bone Morphogenetic Protein Signaling by Smurf1 and Inhibitory Smads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Molecular Biology of the Cell 14: 2809 –2817. doi:10.1091/mbc.E02. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Gautschi1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>15Gautschi OP, Frey SP, Zellweger R (2007) Bone Morphogenetic Proteins in Clinical Applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>ANZ Journal of Surgery 77: 626–631. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1445-2197.2007.04175.x">http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1445-2197.2007.04175.x</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Accessed 26 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Alarmo1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="?"><plain>16Alarmo E-L, Kallioniemi A (2010) Bone morphogenetic proteins in breast cancer: dual role in tumourigenesis? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Endocrine-related cancer 17: R123–39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20335308">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20335308</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2012 March 26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Shore1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>17Shore EM, Xu M, Feldman GJ, Fenstermacher D a, Cho T-J, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>(2006) A recurrent mutation in the BMP type I receptor ACVR1 causes inherited and sporadic fibrodysplasia ossificans progressiva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Nature genetics 38: 525–527. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16642017">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16642017</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 Sept 11. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Connor1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>18Connor JM, Evans D a (1982) Genetic aspects of fibrodysplasia ossificans progressiva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Journal of medical genetics 19: 35–39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3253727&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3253727&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 March 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Sieber1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>19Sieber C, Kopf J, Hiepen C, Knaus P (2009) Recent advances in BMP receptor signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Cytokine &amp; growth factor reviews 20: 343–355. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19897402">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19897402</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Accessed 21 June 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Inman1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>20Inman GJ, Nicolás FJ, Hill CS (2002) Nucleocytoplasmic shuttling of Smads 2, 3, and 4 permits sensing of TGF-beta receptor activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Molecular cell 10: 283–294. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12191474">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12191474</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Accessed 26 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Zi1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>21Zi Z, Feng Z, Chapnick D a, Dahl M, Deng D, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>(2011) Quantitative analysis of transient and sustained transforming growth factor-β signaling dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Molecular systems biology 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3130555&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3130555&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Accessed 22 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Santos1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>22Santos SDM, Verveer PJ, Bastiaens PIH (2007) Growth factor-induced MAPK network topology shapes Erk response determining PC-12 cell fate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Nature cell biology 9: 324–330. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17310240">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17310240</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Accessed 4 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Marshall1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>23Marshall CJ (1995) Specificity of receptor tyrosine kinase signaling: transient versus sustained extracellular signal-regulated kinase activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Cell 80: 179–185. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7834738">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7834738</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Accessed 21 June 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Nicols1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>24Nicolás FJ, Hill CS (2003) Attenuation of the TGF-beta-Smad signaling pathway in pancreatic tumor cells confers resistance to TGF-beta-induced growth arrest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Oncogene 22: 3698–3711. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12802277">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12802277</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Accessed 29 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Ruecker1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>25Ruecker O, Zillner K, Groebner-Ferreira R, Heitzer M (2008) Gaussia-luciferase as a sensitive reporter gene for monitoring promoter activity in the nucleus of the green alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Molecular genetics and genomics 280: 153–162. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18516621">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18516621</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Accessed 23 September 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Clarke1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>26Clarke DC, Liu X (2008) Decoding the quantitative nature of TGF-beta/Smad signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Trends in cell biology 18: 430–442. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2774497&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2774497&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Accessed 27 July 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Bachmann1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>27Bachmann J, Raue a, Schilling M, Becker V, Timmer J, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(2012) Predictive mathematical models of cancer signalling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Journal of internal medicine 271: 155–165. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22142263">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22142263</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Accessed 5 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Batchelor1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>28Batchelor E, Loewer A, Mock C, Lahav G (2011) Stimulus-dependent dynamics of p53 in single cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Molecular systems biology 7: 488. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3130553&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3130553&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Accessed 1 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Xu1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>29Xu L, Kang Y, Cöl S, Massagué J (2002) Smad2 nucleocytoplasmic shuttling by nucleoporins CAN/Nup214 and Nup153 feeds TGFbeta signaling complexes in the cytoplasm and nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Molecular cell 10: 271–282. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12191473">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12191473</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Accessed 23 September 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Munoz1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>30Munoz O, Fend F, De Beaumont R, Husson H, Astier A, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>(2004) TGFbeta-mediated activation of Smad1 in B-cell non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and effect on cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Leukemia 18: 2015–2025. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15470494">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15470494</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Accessed 5 April 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Warmflash1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>31Warmflash A, Zhang Q, Sorre B, Vonica A, Siggia ED, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>(2012) Dynamics of TGF-β signaling reveal adaptive and pulsatile behaviors reflected in the nuclear localization of transcription factor Smad4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America: 1–10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22689943">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22689943</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Accessed 13 June 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Xiao1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>32Xiao Z, Brownawell AM, Macara IG, Lodish HF (2003) A novel nuclear export signal in Smad1 is essential for its signaling activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>The Journal of biological chemistry 278: 34245–34252. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12821673">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12821673</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Accessed 26 Dec 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Kurisaki1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>33 KurisakiA, KurisakiK, KowanetzM, YonedaY, HeldinC, et al (2006) The Mechanism of Nuclear Export of Smad3 Involves Exportin 4 and Ran. Molecular and cellular biology 26: 1318–1332 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/MCB.26.4.1318">10.1128/MCB.26.4.1318</ext-link>.16449645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Schwappacher1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>34 SchwappacherR, WeiskeJ, HeiningE, EzerskiV, MaromB, et al (2009) Novel crosstalk to BMP signalling: cGMP-dependent kinase I modulates BMP receptor and Smad activity. The EMBO journal 28: 1537–1550 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/emboj.2009.103">10.1038/emboj.2009.103</ext-link>.19424179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Kobayashi1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>35 KobayashiT, MizunoH, ImayoshiI, FurusawaC, ShirahigeK, et al (2009) The cyclic gene Hes1 contributes to diverse differentiation responses of embryonic stem cells. Genes &amp; Development 23: 1870–1875 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.1823109.1870">10.1101/gad.1823109.1870</ext-link>.19684110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Fuentealba1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>36Fuentealba LC, Eivers E, Ikeda A, Hurtado C, Kuroda H, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>(2007) Integrating patterning signals: Wnt/GSK3 regulates the duration of the BMP/Smad1 signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Cell 131: 980–993. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2200633&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2200633&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Accessed 17 March 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Jiang1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>37Jiang S, Fritz DT, Rogers MB (2010) A conserved post-transcriptional BMP2 switch in lung cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Journal of cellular biochemistry 110: 509–521. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20432245">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20432245</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2 June 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Langenfeld1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>38Langenfeld EM, Kong Y, Langenfeld J (2006) Bone morphogenetic protein 2 stimulation of tumor growth involves the activation of Smad-1/5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Oncogene 25: 685–692. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16247476">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16247476</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Accessed 28 May 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Langenfeld2"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>39Langenfeld EM, Langenfeld J (2004) Bone Morphogenetic Protein-2 Stimulates Angiogenesis in Developing Tumors 1 1 NIH K22 grant CA91919-01A1 and UMDNJ Foundation to J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Langenfeld. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Bone Morphogenetic Protein-2 Stimulates Angiogenesis in Developing Tumors: 141–149. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Peiffer1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>40Peiffer DA, Bubnoff A Von, Shin Y, Kitayama A, Mochii M, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>(2005) A Xenopus DNA Microarray Approach to Identify Novel Direct BMP Target Genes Involved in Early Embryonic Development: 445–456. doi:10.1002/dvdy.20230. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Yoshiura1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>41 YoshiuraS, OhtsukaT, TakenakaY, NagaharaH, YoshikawaK, et al (2007) Ultradian oscillations of Stat, Smad and Hes1 expression in response to serum. PNAS 104: 11292–11297.17592117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Rapp1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>42Rapp PE, Mees a I, Sparrow CT (1981) Frequency encoded biochemical regulation is more accurate than amplitude dependent control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Journal of theoretical biology 90: 531–544. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6272030">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6272030</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2 June 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Monteiro1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>43Monteiro RM, De Sousa Lopes SMC, Korchynskyi O, Ten Dijke P, Mummery CL (2004) Spatio-temporal activation of Smad1 and Smad5 in vivo: monitoring transcriptional activity of Smad proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Journal of cell science 117: 4653–4663. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15331632">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15331632</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Accessed 28 Sept 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Kawakami1"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>44 KawakamiK, NodaT (2004) Transposition of the Tol2 Element, an Ac-Like Element From the Japanese Medaka Fish Oryzias latipes, in Mouse Embryonic Stem Cells. Genetics 166: 895–899.15020474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0059442-Wagner1"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>45 WagnerTU, KräusslingM, SchartlM (2009) STAT3 and SMAD1 signalling in Medaka embryonic stem-like cells and blastula embryos. Stem cells and development 18: 151–160.18554090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
