<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3260253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22272308</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-09789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Protozoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parastic Protozoans</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitic Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Malaria</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Tropical Diseases (Non-Neglected)</subject><subj-group><subject>Malaria</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Diversity of Plasmodium falciparum Chloroquine Resistance Transporter (pfcrt) Exon 2 Haplotypes in the Pacific from 1959 to 1979 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Malaria and Chloroquine Resistance in Pacific</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Chim W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spathis</surname><given-names>Rita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reiff</surname><given-names>Dana M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>Stacy E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garruto</surname><given-names>Ralph M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>J. Koji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Evolutionary Anthropology and Health, Binghamton University, Binghamton, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Biomedical Anthropology and Neurosciences, Binghamton University, Binghamton, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Anthropology, Binghamton University, Binghamton, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Binghamton University, Binghamton, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Templeton</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Weill Cornell Medical College, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>aramidus44@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RMG JKL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: CWC RS DMR SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: CWC JKL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RMG JKL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: CWC RMG JKL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e30213</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Chan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Nearly one million deaths are attributed to malaria every year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Recent reports of multi-drug treatment failure of falciparum malaria underscore the need to understand the molecular basis of drug resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Multiple mutations in the Plasmodium falciparum chloroquine resistance transporter (pfcrt) are involved in chloroquine resistance, but the evolution of complex haplotypes is not yet well understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Using over 4,500 archival human serum specimens collected from 19 Pacific populations between 1959 and 1979, the period including and just prior to the appearance of chloroquine treatment failure in the Pacific, we PCR-amplified and sequenced a portion of the pfcrt exon 2 from 771 P. falciparum-infected individuals to explore the spatial and temporal variation in falciparum malaria prevalence and the evolution of chloroquine resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the Pacific, the prevalence of P. falciparum varied considerably across ecological zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>On the island of New Guinea, the decreases in prevalence of P. falciparum in coastal, high-transmission areas over time were contrasted by the increase in prevalence during the same period in the highlands, where transmission was intermittent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We found 78 unique pfcrt haplotypes consisting of 34 amino acid substitutions and 28 synonymous mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>More importantly, two pfcrt mutations (N75D and K76T) implicated in chloroquine resistance were present in parasites from New Hebrides (now Vanuatu) eight years before the first report of treatment failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Our results also revealed unexpectedly high levels of genetic diversity in pfcrt exon 2 prior to the historical chloroquine resistance selective sweep, particularly in areas where disease burden was relatively low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In the Pacific, parasite genetic isolation, as well as host acquired immune status and genetic resistance to malaria, were important contributors to the evolution of chloroquine resistance in P. falciparum. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Malaria caused approximately 243 million clinical cases and 863,000 deaths in 2008 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The development of resistance to chloroquine (CQ), once the mainstay of malaria treatment worldwide, has exacerbated malaria morbidity and mortality over the last few decades, especially in sub-Saharan Africa [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>An understanding of the evolution of CQ resistance in the malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum is crucial to providing important insights into the mechanisms by which parasites respond to other aminoquinolines such as amodiaquine, which are currently used as partner drugs with artesunate in artemisinin-based combination therapies (ACTs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Such insights are urgently needed, given recent evidence of diminished efficacies of ACTs in Southeast Asia [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>CQ resistant (CQR) P. falciparum show diminished accumulation of CQ in the digestive vacuole (DV), and this phenotype is correlated with amino acid substitutions in the DV membrane transporter, P. falciparum chloroquine resistance transporter (pfCRT) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In pfCRT, the lysine to threonine substitution at codon position 76 (K76T) shows the most consistent correlation with CQ resistance, but as many as eight other amino acid substitutions are also involved in distinguishing CQR from CQ sensitive (CQS) parasites [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Together with K76T, substitutions at positions 72, 74, and 75 form complex CQR pfcrt exon 2 haplotypes that correspond to the geographical origins of CQ resistance [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, it is unclear how these CQR pfcrt haplotypes arose due to the lack of previous genetic characterization of parasites during the periods of CQ resistance emergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Multiple origins of CQ resistance in P. falciparum have been suggested based on epidemiological data [7] and genetic analyses [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>CQ treatment failures first appeared simultaneously near the Thai-Cambodian border and in Colombia in the late 1950s, and CQR parasites spread from these original foci to neighboring areas [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Characterization of pfcrt haplotypes from laboratory-adapted P. falciparum clones provided strong support for these two independent origins of CQ resistance, and the invasion of CQR parasites from Southeast Asia to Africa [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In Papua New Guinea (PNG), CQ treatment failure was first reported in 1976, and was initially assumed to indicate the expansion of CQR P. falciparum from Southeast Asia into the Pacific [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Examination of pfcrt polymorphisms showed that despite the geographic proximity to the Southeast Asian focus of resistance, CQR parasites from PNG harbored a pfcrt exon 2 haplotype similar to one from South America [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Since these pfcrt substitutions were associated with a different genetic background [6], [10], it was argued that PNG represented another independent focus of CQ resistance [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In other malarious regions of the Pacific, the evolution of CQ resistance in P. falciparum might have been more complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Nagesha et al. [11] identified four pfcrt haplotypes associated with CQ resistance in field isolates from Indonesian Papua (West New Guinea or WNG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These haplotypes were representative of both the Southeast Asian/African (codon 72–76: CVIET) and the PNG/South American (codon 72–76: SVMNT) CQR haplotypes, and a third composite (codon 72–76: SVIET) haplotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>This region of the Pacific is also characterized by very diverse ecologies which affect parasite population dynamics that in turn play a crucial role in the evolution of CQR parasites and their dispersals [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In this regard, it is important to include parasites from multiple locales and examine their interactions at a population level over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Archival biological specimens have been shown to be useful in studying past evolutionary events such as CQ resistance in P. falciparum [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We reasoned that blood samples collected prior to (and slightly after) the mid-1970s from populations residing in the malarious Pacific might contain DNA from P. falciparum that was under increasing CQ selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of pfcrt might therefore provide important insights into the evolution of the complex CQR haplotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Additionally, by including samples from multiple locations collected at various time periods, we sought to examine the spatial and temporal dynamics of the evolution and spread of CQR P. falciparum across the diverse environments in the Pacific [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Results from our study indicated that pfcrt exon 2 was highly diverse prior to the CQ selective sweep, and suggested that CQ resistance in the Pacific evolved in situ and arose first in low transmission areas, where host populations had minimal genetic resistance and acquired immunity against malaria infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Overall, 771 of 4598 (16.8%) specimens from 19 populations were positive for P. falciparum (Figure 1, Table S1), as determined by successful PCR amplification and DNA sequencing of a 195-bp segment of pfcrt exon 2 corresponding to codon positions 36 to 99. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Rates of P. falciparum infection ranged from 0% in the Papua New Guinea (PNG) eastern highlands sample of BAR62 and the West New Guinea (WNG) coastal sample of MRK61 to 55.4% in the WNG coastal sample of SWC60 (Figure 1, Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>When analyzed by ecological zones, coastal populations from both WNG and PNG showed the highest average rates of P. falciparum infection at 26.9% and 20.3%, respectively, followed by those from Island Melanesia at 17.4% and PNG Papuan Plateau at 13.6%, with those from the PNG eastern highlands showing the lowest rate at 3.14% (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Our results from PNG were consistent with the observation that malaria prevalence decreases with increasing altitude [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Approximate locations of populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Populations are denoted by their sample codes (Table S1) and assigned to one of five ecological zones as indicated by colors as followed: WNG coast (purple), PNG coasts (green), PNG Papuan Plateau (blue), PNG eastern highlands (red), and Island Melanesia (orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Samples collected from the same locations in different years (e.g. SWC60, SWC62, and SWC69) did not represent repeated samplings from the same populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For three of the five ecological zones, longitudinal samples allowed for crude estimates of temporal variation in P. falciparum prevalences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>On the WNG coast, the infection rates remained high from 1960 to 1969, while on the PNG coasts, there was a steady decrease in prevalence from 1960 to 1979. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In contrast, P. falciparum prevalence increased slightly over the same period in the PNG eastern highlands (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Temporal variation in P. falciparum infection rates (bar) and pfcrt haplotype diversities (line). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Ecological zones are indicated by colors as followed: PNG eastern highlands (red), WNG coast (purple), and PNG coasts (green). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Approximately 8.95% (69/771) of P. falciparum-positive specimens showed two distinct pfcrt exon 2 genotypes, yielding a total of 840 sequences (GenBank accession numbers HM019533–HM020128, HM020130–HM020332, and HM202334–HM020374). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Samples from the PNG eastern highlands and Island Melanesia showed the highest frequencies of individuals with multiple infections (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Seventy eight unique pfcrt haplotypes were identified, of which the wildtype pfcrt sequence accounted for 83.8% (704/840) of sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We calculated pfcrt haplotye diversities to compare the amounts of genetic variation among populations and ecological zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Haplotype diversity indices range between 0 and 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>A measure of 0 indicates that all haplotypes within a population or ecological zone are identical to one another, whereas a measure of 1 indicates that all haplotypes within a population or ecological zone are unique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>When analyzed by individual populations, pfcrt haplotype diversity ranged from 0 in EHP60, WSP65, and ONB69, to 0.722 in EHP79 (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>When grouped into ecological zones, populations from the PNG eastern highlands and Island Melanesia had higher haplotype diversities than those from the other ecological zones, although the difference was not statistically significant (ANOVA; p = 0.106) (Table S1). Pfcrt haplotype diversities did not vary substantially over time along the WNG coast, but in both PNG coasts and eastern highlands the levels of diversity showed substantial fluctuations, with an appreciable increase over time in the PNG eastern highlands (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Among the 77 mutant pfcrt haplotypes, non-synonymous substitutions were more abundant (34 vs. 28) and occurred more frequently (94 vs. 75) than synonymous substitutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>During the two early periods (1959–61 and 1962–65), no differences were found in the distribution of mutant pfcrt haplotypes among populations (Figures 3, 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Between 1969 and 1972, significantly more (p&lt;0.001) mutant pfcrt haplotypes were found in populations from Island Melanesia than those from the PNG Papuan Plateau and the WNG coast (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In 1979, the PNG eastern highlands have significantly more (p = 0.018) mutant pfcrt haplotypes than the PNG coast (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Fifty two (67.5%) mutant pfcrt haplotypes contained at least one non-synonymous substitution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Most mutations observed were either private or present at very low frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Only five mutant haplotypes (6, 14, 24, 26, and 39) were found in five or more individuals (Figures 3–  6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Three amino acid substitutions previously implicated in CQ resistance were detected in our samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In NNH72, the N75D (codon 72–76: CVMDK) and the K76T (codon 72–76: CVMNT) substitutions were found individually in two specimens (Figure 5), while the K76N (codon 72–76: CVMNN) substitution was found in one specimen from EHP79 (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Median-joining network of pfcrt haplotypes (A) and alignment of translated sequences (B) from 1959–61. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In the network diagram, each unique pfcrt haplotype is represented by a node, and the size of each node is proportional to the frequency of the haplotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Substitutions are represented by branches, with the branch length proportional to the number of substitutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Non-synonymous substitutions are represented by branches in bold. Pfcrt haplotypes that appeared in more than one time period are noted by their haplotype numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In the amino acid sequence alignment, the shaded region represents transmembrane domain 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Synonymous substitutions are represented by dashes (-) and synonymous substitutions by asterisks (*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Populations are denoted by their sample codes (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Median-joining network of pfcrt haplotypes (A) and alignment of translated sequences (B) from 1962–5. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Median-joining network of pfcrt haplotypes (A) and alignment of translated sequences (B) from 1969–72. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Hypothetical nodes are indicated by arrows. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Median-joining network of pfcrt haplotypes (A) and alignment of translated sequences (B) from 1979. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The relationship among pfcrt exon 2 haplotypes from each time period is shown by a median-joining network diagram (Figures 3–6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The wildtype pfcrt haplotype was shared by all populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Nine mutant pfcrt haplotypes (3, 6, 10, 11, 12, 14, 24, 25, and 26) were found in samples from at least two time periods (Figures 3–  6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Four of these haplotypes (6, 11, 24, and 26) harbored non-synonymous substitutions while the remaining five had only synonymous mutations (Figures 3–6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Overall, 83.3% (65/78) of haplotypes were population specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Of the 12 mutant pfcrt haplotypes shared between two or more populations, 10 were shared between populations from different ecological zones. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We also calculated pairwise FST genetic distances to infer gene flow among parasite populations across ecological zones and persistence of parasite populations within ecological zones over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Gene flow among populations from the same time period, as defined by non-statistically significant (p&gt;0.05) pairwise FST values, is illustrated in Figure 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>During the two early periods (1959–61 and 1962–65), parasite populations from different ecological zones were not significantly differentiated from one another (Figures 7A and 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Between 1969 and 1972, parasite populations in Island Melanesia were significantly differentiated from those in the PNG Papuan Plateau and the WNG coast (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In 1979, parasites in the PNG eastern highlands were significantly differentiated from those in the PNG coast (Figure 7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>No statistically significant (p&lt;0.05) FST values were found among temporally distinct samples within the same ecological region, suggesting that parasite populations within a particular region generally persisted through time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The spatial and temporal patterns of gene flow as inferred from pairwise FST distances suggested that P. falciparum CQ resistance in the Pacific likely arose locally and evolved in situ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0030213-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030213.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Gene flow among P. falciparum populations from different ecological zones. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Gene flow among parasite populations from (A) 1959–61, (B) 1962–5, (C) 1969–72, and (D) 1979, is represented by solid lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Gene flow is inferred from pairwise FST distances determined to be non-statistically significant (p&gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0030213.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Malaria endemicity in the Pacific is inversely correlated with latitude and altitude [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In PNG, malaria transmission is most intense in coastal lowlands where both temperature and rainfall remain high throughout the year, whereas in the highlands, transmission is epidemic and coincides with the conclusion of the rainy season [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In Vanuatu, a Y-shaped archipelago that extends along the north-south axis in the southern hemisphere, malaria transmission in the northern islands is in general more intense than in the southern islands, with the southernmost island of Aneityum being free of malaria since 1991 [16], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In our archival samples, the pattern of P. falciparum prevalences as determined by our PCR and sequencing assays was consistent with that obtained by current malariometric surveys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Since all four commonly recognized human malaria species are present in the southwest Pacific [15], and our molecular techniques specifically targeted template DNA from P. falciparum, it is likely that the rates of malaria infections in these archival samples were higher than reported here, especially in the PNG highlands, where unstable malaria transmission has historically favored the predominance of P. vivax [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of P. falciparum infections in coastal and highland samples of New Guinea showed opposite longitudinal trends, which are consistent with changing social factors of the times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In the coastal lowlands of both PNG and WNG, the decreasing prevalence over time coincided with the initiation of malaria eradication programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Malaria control measures began in both PNG and WNG in 1952, consisting of residual insecticide spraying, introduction of Gambusia spp. to swampy areas, and in some places mass drug administration of CQ and/or pyrimethamine [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Although complete eradication proved elusive, notable reduction in malaria prevalence was accomplished in many lowland areas despite technical and logistical difficulties [20]–[23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the overall decrease in P. falciparum prevalence in the lowlands, we observed a slight increase in infection rate in the PNG eastern highlands over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Radford et al. [24] argued that social factors were important in changing malaria epidemiology in the highlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Increased contact and the opening of the Highland Highways facilitated the movement of people and malaria parasites from the highly malarious coastal areas to the highlands, while many highlanders recruited as wage laborers in lowland plantations served as parasite reservoirs when they returned to the highlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Establishment of plantations and adoption of western-style housing in the highlands also created additional mosquito breeding sites that led to increased malaria transmission [19], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The increase in P. falciparum prevalence in our PNG eastern highland samples might also represent a gradual shift in species predominance from P. vivax to P. falciparum, as recently noted by Mueller et al. [19], although this will require molecular surveys of P. vivax to confirm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In the Pacific, CQ treatment failure was first reported in WNG (Irian Jaya) in 1974 [25] and by 1980 resistance had been confirmed in all malaria endemic countries in the region [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Two CQ resistance-implicated amino acid substitutions, N75D and K76T were observed individually in two specimens from NNH72, resulting in the haplotypes CVMDK and CVMNT, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The pfcrt K76T substitution has consistently been shown to correlate with CQ resistance [5], [16], [26], and the CVMNT haplotype has previously been described in CQR parasites from South America [5] and Papua [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The N75D substitution was associated with the K76T substitution in parasites from Cambodia [27], Thailand and Laos [28], although in the absence of the diagnostic K76T substitution, it is unclear if this CVMDK-bearing parasite had an altered response to CQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The presence of these substitutions in parasites from northern New Hebrides in 1972 agrees with the long held suspicion that CQ resistance had been present in New Hebrides many years before it was clinically and experimentally confirmed in 1980 [29], [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We also detected the replacement of lysine by asparagine at pfcrt codon 76 in EHP79. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This K76N substitution was previously experimentally induced when the CQS laboratory clone 106/1, which already had six of the seven pfcrt mutations found in CQR parasites from Asia and Africa, was exposed to high levels of CQ [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>However, it is unclear whether the 76N bearing parasite we identified in this study was CQR, since it was associated with a different pfcrt genetic background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Whereas the mutant 106/1 parasite carried the CVIEN haplotype [31], our parasite carried the CVMNN haplotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>This rare haplotype has been reported twice in parasite isolates from Indonesia, although in both studies the in vitro response to CQ was not evaluated [28], [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Archival biological samples from PNG provide crucial insights into the evolution and spread of CQR parasites [13], [14], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Using samples collected from 12 locations in PNG during the early 1980s, Mehlotra et al. [13] found a high frequency (97%; 33/34) of the CQR SVMNT pfcrt haplotype, which was consistent with a nation-wide epidemiological survey reporting widespread CQ resistance conducted during that period [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the CQS CVMNK haplotype predominated (97%; 34/35) in our PNG samples collected in 1979 (EHP79 and WSP79), indicating that strong CQ selection resulted in the nearly complete replacement of CQS parasites by their resistant counterparts in as few as three years, and the latter's persistence to the present [9], [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>It is unclear whether the CVMNN haplotype observed in our sample represented a transitional strain that ultimately gave rise to parasites carrying the more ubiquitous SVMNT haplotype seen today, or was replaced by invading parasites carrying the latter haplotype, nonetheless our data are consistent with previous interpretation that CQ resistance in the Pacific evolved in situ [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Analyses of additional samples from this critical period are currently underway and will hopefully shed light on the relationships among these haplotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Of the 34 amino acid substitutions observed in our samples, 20 are considered to be non-conservative, involving a side-chain property change in either polarity and/or charge that might affect the function of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Two such substitutions, I59T and I63T were observed in 14 and 19 samples respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In particular, mutant pfcrt haplotypes harboring the I63T substitution persisted through time and later dispersed into multiple regions, suggesting that these haplotypes may reflect a drug tolerant if not resistant phenotype (Figures 3–6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Transfections of CQS P. falciparum clones with I63T and other novel substitutions identified in this study are currently underway to evaluate their effects on CQ response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It remains unclear how the historical use of other antimalarials prior to our earliest samples (1959) might have contributed to the selection of pfcrt alleles observed in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>During WWII, malaria was a major cause of casualties for both the Japanese and the Allied troops stationed in the Southwest Pacific [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Quinine and quinacrine, also known as mepacrine or Atabrine, were used extensively to prevent and treat malaria infections, especially among Allied soldiers [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The mode of action for quinine is thought to be similar to that of CQ [38], and cross resistance with CQ has been suggested [39], [40], although the association between quinine resistance in P. falciparum and specific substitutions in pfcrt has been inconclusive [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Quinacrine resistance was first noted in P. falciparum from the Wewak-Aitape region along the north coast of New Guinea in 1944 [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>We did observe in our earliest sample from the same region (ESP61) a non-synonymous substitution (F48L) at relatively high frequency (6.1%; 3/49) (Figure 3), which might reflect previous selection by quinacrine and warrants further studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>However, it should be noted that the genetic basis for quinacrine resistance is unknown, and the use of quinacrine was largely abandoned after WWII in favor of CQ [42], such that little selective pressure was maintained during the intervening years between the end of the war and the collection of our samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Four factors may have contributed to the unexpectedly higher levels of pfcrt exon 2 genetic diversity in parasites from the PNG eastern highlands and Island Melanesia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>First, in Island Melanesia the high level of parasite genetic diversity might have resulted from population structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Samples from NNH72 and SSI72 were collected from populations on 13 and three different islands, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>While variable levels of travel among islands within each archipelago were noted [43], more recently extensive human contact has been essential for gene flow between parasites on different islands [44], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>When subdivided into individual islands, parasites on some islands were found to be genetically distinct from those on neighboring islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>For example, parasites from Gaua in northern New Hebrides were significantly distinct from those on nearby Mota Lava (FST = 0.04155; p = 0.03604) and Vanua Lava (FST = 0.01819; p = 0.03604). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>This implies that isolation and genetic drift on individual islands, although reducing diversity locally, have increased the genetic diversity of the archipelago as a whole. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Second, in these areas of relatively low transmission, the use of antimalarials was often reserved for treatments only [43], such that intermittent CQ pressure might have selected for a suite of different non-synonymous substitutions that only slightly altered the parasites' response to CQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In contrast to high transmission areas where competition among different genetic strains is intense [46], even in the absence of continuous CQ selection, genetic drift may have maintained these non-synonymous substitutions in small parasite populations as suggested by low rates of infection in these low transmission areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Third, host immune status played an important role in the occurrence of multiple infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In high transmission areas the host acquired immunity to malaria is constantly maintained by recurrent infections, whereas in low transmission areas malaria infections by multiple genetic strains might be more common since parasite clearance in semi-immune individuals is less effective [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In this study, the frequencies of multiple infections were significantly correlated with pfcrt haplotype diversities (R2 = 0.9361, p = 0.007), suggesting that lowered host acquired immunity in the PNG Eastern Highlands and Island Melanesia might have contributed to the high level of parasite genetic diversities in these low transmission areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Lastly, differences in host genetics may have affected the degree to which populations living in different ecological regions were susceptible to infection by multiple genetic strains of P. falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Strong selection in the coastal lowland populations of PNG results in the maintenance of a number of red cell polymorphisms conferring resistance to malaria, including Southeast Asian ovalocytosis [48]–[50], alpha-thalassemia [51], beta-thalassemia [52], and Gerbich negativity [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>It is possible that in high transmission areas, individuals with one or more of these malaria resistant alleles present a less hospitable environment to parasites, such that only those that are most adapted, i.e. either wildtype (with no pfcrt mutations) or fully CQR (with a complete suite of CQR pfcrt mutations), can survive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Conversely in low transmission areas, host selection against parasites might be less severe, thus allowing slightly less fit parasite strains, i.e. those with only one or two pfcrt mutations, to evolve and persist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Genetic characterization of P. falciparum in the Pacific from the period of CQ resistance emergence revealed that prior to complete CQ selective sweep, pfcrt exon 2 was highly diverse, highlighted by a number of previously undescribed substitutions including several implicated in CQ resistance, consistent with in situ evolution of resistance within the Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In addition to CQ selection, isolation among parasite populations and reduced strain competition in small parasite populations, combined with lowered acquired immunity and genetic resistance to malaria among hosts in low transmission areas, might have been crucial to the evolution and initial establishment of CQR P. falciparum in the Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that populations at the peripheries of malaria endemic areas may be the most crucial to monitor for parasites evolving tolerance and resistance to currently used antimalarials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This study was submitted to the Human Subjects Research Review Committee of Binghamton University, where it was reviewed and determined exempt because no human DNA was examined (Protocol # 787-08). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Archival Human Serum Collections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Samples used in this study were provided by the Binghamton University Serum Archive Facility at Binghamton, NY, USA, and their use in this study was approved by the institutional review board of Binghamton University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Samples were collected under the ethical and legal guidelines of the United States National Institutes of Health and all existing international standards of the time, and their continued use for biomedical research has recently been reaffirmed by the Papua New Guinea Medical Research Advisory Committee (documentation available upon request). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A total of 4598 specimens from 19 Pacific populations sampled between 1959 and 1979 was included in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The locations of sample collections and brief descriptions are given in figure 1 and table S1, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Samples collected from the same locations in different years did not represent repeated samplings of the same populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acid Extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from 200 µl of human serum using either the QIAamp Blood Mini Kit (QIAgen Biosciences, Germantown, MD) or the automated Maxwell-16 system (Promega, Madison, WI) according to the respective manufacturers' instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Eluted DNA was frozen at −20°C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Molecular Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>A segment of the pfcrt exon 2 was PCR-amplified in a 12.5 µl reaction containing 4 µl of DNA, 0.2 mM of dNTP, 2 mM of MgCl2, 0.5 µM of each primer (CRT76-sense 5′-GGTGGAGGTTCTTGTCTTGG-3′ and CRT76-antisense 5′-ATAAAGTTGTGAGTTTCGGATG-3′) [54], and 0.25 unit of HotStar Taq DNA polymerase (QIAgen Biosciences, Germantown, MD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The cycling conditions consisted of 15 minutes at 95°C, 90 seconds at 61°C, 60 seconds at 72°C for 1 cycle; 10 seconds at 95°C, 90 seconds at 61°C, and 2 minutes at 72°C for 50 cycles, and a final extension for 10 minutes at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>PCR amplicons were purified using the Millipore Manu03050 Filter Plate (Millipore, Billerica, MA), and were sequenced in both directions using internal primers, CRTD1 5′-TGTGCTCATGTGTTTAAACTT-3′ and CRTD2 5′-CAAAACTATAGTTACCAATTTTG-3′ [55], with the BigDye Terminator Kit v.3.1 on an ABI 3730xl DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Electropherograms were visually checked using Sequencing Analysis 2.1 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Infection by genetically distinct P. falciparum strains was inferred when heterologous peaks were present in a single specimen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In cases where heterologous peaks were observed at more than one nucleotide position in a single specimen, pfcrt haplotypes were constructed based on the relative peak heights at each nucleotide position in question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Assuming that multiple substitutions in a lineage arose in a stepwise manner, we examined the position of the constructed halpotypes in the network diagrams (Figures 3–6) [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Only two branches directly stemming from the wildtype pfcrt haplotype contained hypothetical internal nodes (Figure 5), indicating that most of these constructed haplotypes were derived from simpler haplotypes that were also present in our data set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of P. falciparum infection was determined at two hierarchical levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Since malaria endemicity in the Pacific varies by altitude and latitude [15], [16], in addition to comparisons among all samples, individual samples were assigned to one of five ecological zones: (1) PNG eastern highlands, (2) WNG coast, (3) PNG coasts, (4) PNG Papuan Plateau, and (5) Island Melanesia, consisting of New Hebrides (now Vanuatu) and Solomon Islands (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Samples used in this study were collected over a span of 20 years (1959–79), and were therefore divided into the following periods, (A) 1959–61, (B) 1962–5, (C) 1969–72, and (D) 1979, to account for temporal variation and assess the persistence of genotypes over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Pfcrt haplotype diversity was calculated for each population and each ecological zone using the equation: H = n(1−∑Xi 2)/(n−1), where n is the number of pfcrt sequences, and Xi is the frequency of the i-th haplotype [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Mean pfcrt haplotype diversities among ecological zones were compared using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>For each time period, G-test for homogeneity was used to compare the distribution of mutant pfcrt haplotypes among populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Median-joining network diagrams were constructed using the software Network 4.600 to illustrate the phylogenetic relationships among all pfcrt sequences for each period [56], [58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>To infer gene flow among populations, two sets of pairwise FST genetic distances were calculated using Arlequin 3.1 [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The first set consisted of comparisons of samples from the same time period to examine gene flow across ecological zones, while the second consisted of samples from the same ecological zone but were collected in different periods to infer replacement (or persistence) over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The statistical significance (p&lt;0.05) of the observed values was evaluated by randomly permuting sequences among populations approximately 10,000 times to generate a null distribution against which the observed values were compared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0030213.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The approximate geographic locations of these samples are shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Samples collected from the same locations in different years did not represent repeated samplings of the same population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Ages of donors for the sample EHP79 were not available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0030213.s001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The authors acknowledge the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) for contributing the samples to Binghamton University through a material transfer agreement to the University's Serum Archive Facility, and the Graduate Program in Biomedical Anthropology for the archiving and preparation of the samples used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The authors would also like to thank the Papua New Guinea Institute of Medical Research (PNG-IMR) which helped to make the research collection possible through its many years of collaboration with the NINDS former Laboratory of Central Nervous System Studies (LCNSS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Preparation of figures and tables in this paper by Krithivasan Sankaranarayanan is gratefully appreciated. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Funding: Financial support for the study was provided by the United States National Institutes of Health (R01GM080593). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0030213-World1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>1 World Health Organization 2009 World malaria report 2009 Geneva WHO Press. 66  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Trape1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>2 TrapeJF 2001 The public health impact of chloroquine resistance in Africa. Am J Trop Med Hyg 64 1–2 Suppl 12 7  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Wongsrichanalai1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>3 WongsrichanalaiCPickardALWernsdorferWHMeshnickSR 2002 Epidemiology of drug-resistant malaria. Lancet Infect Dis 2 209 218 11937421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Noedl1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>4 NoedlHSeYSchaecherKSmithBLSocheatD 2008 Evidence of artemisinin-resistant malaria in western Cambodia. N Engl J Med 359 2619 2620 19064625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Fidock1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>5 FidockDANomuraTTalleyAKCooperRADzekunovSM 2000 Mutations in the P. falciparum digestive vacuole transmembrane protein PfCRT and evidence for their role in chloroquine resistance. Mol Cell 6 861 871 11090624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Wootton1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>6 WoottonJCFengXFerdigMTCooperRAMuJ 2002 Genetic diversity and chloroquine selective sweeps in Plasmodium falciparum. Nature 418 320 323 12124623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mita1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>7 MitaTKanekoAHombhanjeFHwaihwanjeITakahashiN 2006 Role of pfmdr1 mutations on chloroquine resistance in Plasmodium falciparum isolates with pfcrt K76T from Papua New Guinea. Acta Trop 98 137 144 16620743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Yung1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>8 YungAPBennettNM 1976 Chloroquine-resistant falciparum malaria acquired in Papua New Guinea. Med J Aust 2 845  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mehlotra1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>9 MehlotraRKFujiokaHRoepePDJannehOUrsosLM 2001 Evolution of a unique Plasmodium falciparum chloroquine-resistance phenotype in association with pfcrt polymorphism in Papua New Guinea and South America. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 98 12689 12694 11675500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Anderson1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>10 AndersonTJHauboldBWilliamsJTEstrada-FrancoJGRichardsonL 2000 Microsatellite markers reveal a spectrum of population structures in the malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum. Mol Biol Evol 17 1467 1482 11018154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Nagesha1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>11 NageshaHSCaseyGJRieckmannKHFryauffDJLaksanaBS 2003 New haplotypes of the Plasmodium falciparum chloroquine resistance transporter (pfcrt) gene among chloroquine-resistant parasite isolates. Am J Trop Med Hyg 68 398 402 12875286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Hastings1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>12 HastingsIMWatkinsWM 2005 Intensity of malaria transmission and the evolution of drug resistance. Acta Trop 94 218 229 15847846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mehlotra2"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>13 MehlotraRKMatteraGBhatiaKReederJCStonekingM 2005 Insight into the early spread of chloroquine-resistant Plasmodium falciparum infections in Papua New Guinea. J Infect Dis 192 2174 2179 16288385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Chan1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>14 ChanCWLynchDSpathisRHombhanjeFWKanekoA 2006 Flashback to the 1960s: utility of archived sera to explore the origin and evolution of Plasmodium falciparum chloroquine resistance in the Pacific. Acta Trop 99 15 22 16890903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mller1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>15 MüllerIBockarieMAlpersMSmithT 2003 The epidemiology of malaria in Papua New Guinea. Trends Parasitol 19 253 259 12798082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Kaneko1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>16 KanekoATaleoGKalkoaMYaviongJReevePA 1998 Malaria epidemiology, glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency and human settlement in the Vanuatu Archipelago. Acta Trop 70 285 302 9777715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Kaneko2"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>17 KanekoATaleoGKalkoaMYamarSKobayakawaT 2000 Malaria eradication on islands. Lancet 356 1560 1564 11075770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mueller1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>18 MuellerIBjorgeSPoigenoGKundiJTandrapahT 2003 The epidemiology of malaria in the Papua New Guinea highlands: 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Eastern Highlands Province. P N G Med J 3–4 166 179  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mueller2"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>19 MuellerINamuigiPKundiJIviviRTandrapahT 2005 Epidemic malaria in the highlands of Papua New Guinea. Am J Trop Med Hyg 72 554 560 15891129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Spencer1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>20 SpencerM 1992 The history of malaria control in the southwest Pacific region, with particular reference to Papua New Guinea and the Solomon Islands. P N G Med J 35 33 66 1566607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Metselaar1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>21 MetselaarD 1961 Seven years' malaria research and residual house spraying in Netherlands New Guinea. Am J Trop Med Hyg 10 327 334 13769879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Peters1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>22 PetersW 1962 A critical survey of the results of malaria-eradication and control programmes in the Southwest Pacific. Ann Trop Med Parasitol 56 20 32  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Smithurst1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>23 SmithurstBA 1970 A malaria survey on Bougainville Island (Kieta Subdistrict) January–February 1967. Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health 1 117 122  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Radford1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>24 RadfordAJVan LeeuwenHChristianSH 1976 Social aspects in the changing epidemiology of malaria in the highlands of New Guinea. Ann Trop Med Parasitol 70 11 23 1267506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Clyde1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>25 ClydeDFMcCarthyVCMillerRMHornickRB 1976 Chloroquine-resistant falciparum malaria from Irian Jaya (Indonesian New Guinea). J Trop Med Hyg 79 38 41 775119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Durand1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>26 DurandRJafariSVauzelleJDelabreJFJesicZ 2001 Analysis of pfcrt point mutations and chloroquine susceptibility in isolates of Plasmodium falciparum. Mol Biochem Parasitol 114 95 102 11356518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Lim1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>27 LimPChySArieyFIncardonaSChimP 2003  pfcrt polymorphism and chloroquine resistance in Plasmodium falciparum strains isolated in Cambodia. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 47 87 94 12499174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-SaitoNakano1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>28 Saito-NakanoYTanabeKKameiKIwagamiMKomaki-YasudaK 2008 Genetic evidence for Plasmodium falciparum resistance to chloroquine and pyrimethamine in Indochina and the Western Pacific between 1984 and 1998. Am J Trop Med Hyg 79 613 619 18840753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Bowden1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>29 BowdenDKBastienPDouglasFPMuirJWTambisariE 1982 Chloroquine-reistant Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Vanuatu. Med J Aust 2 561 562 6761561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Parkinson1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>30 ParkinsonADBowdenDK 1980 Chloroquine resistance in the south-west Pacific. Med J Aust 2 637 638 7007842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Cooper1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>31 CooperRAFerdigMTSuXZUrsosLMMuJ 2002 Alternative mutations at position 76 of the vacuolar transmembrane protein PfCRT are associated with chloroquine resistance and unique stereospecific quinine and quinidine responses in Plasmodium falciparum. Mol Pharmacol 61 35 42 11752204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Huaman1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>32 HuamanMCYoshinagaKSuryanathaASuarsanaNKanbaraH 2004 Short report: polymorphisms in the chloroquine resistance transporter gene in Plasmodium falcipaum isolates from Lombok, Indonesia. Am J Trop Med Hyg 71 40 42 15238686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Dulay1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>33 DulayISGibsonFDEyeson-AnnanMBNararaA 1987 Chloroquine resistance in Plasmodium falciparum and its geographical distribution in Papua New Guinea. P N G Med J 30 281 290 3321751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mita2"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>34 MitaTKanekoAHombhanjeFHwaihwanjeITakahashiN 2006 Role of pfmdr1 mutations on chloroquine resistance in Plasmodium falciparum isolates with pfcrt K76T from Papua New Guinea. Acta Trop 98 137 144 16620743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Sweeney1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>35 SweeneyAW 2000 Wartime research on malaria chemotherapy. Parassitologia 42 33 45 11234330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Joy1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>36 JoyRJ 1999 Malaria in American troops in the South and Southwest Pacific in World War II. Med Hist 43 192 207 10885139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Sweeney2"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>37 SweeneyAW 1996 The possibiligy of an “X” factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The first documented drug resistance of human malaria. Int J Parasitol 26 1035 1061 8982785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Warhurst1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>38 WarhurstDC 1981 The quinine-haemin interaction and its relationship to antimalarial activity. Biochem Pharmacol 30 3323 7 7326041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Simon1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>39 SimonFLe BrasJCharmotGGirardPMFaucherC 1986 Severe chloroquine-resistant falciparum malaria in Gabon with decreased sensitivity to quinine. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 80 996 997  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Warsame1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>40 WarsameMWernsdorferWHPayneDBjörkmanA 1991 Susceptibility of Plasmodium falciparum in vitro to chloroquine, mefloquine, quinine and sulfadoxine/pyrimethamine in Somalia: relationships between the responses to the different drugs. Trans R Soc Tom Med Hyg 85 565 569  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Okombo1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>41 OkomboJOhumaEPicotSNzilaA 2011 Update on genetic markers of quinine resistance in Plasmodium falciparum. Mol Biochem Parasitol 177 77 82 21295079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Peters2"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>42 PetersW 1984 History and current status of drug resistance. PetersWRichardsWHG Antimalarial Durgs: Biological Background, Experimental Methods, and Drug Resistance Berlin Springer-Verlag 423 445  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>43 BrownPCollinsWEGajdusekDCMillerLH 1976 An evaluation of malaria fluorescent antibody patterns in several remote island populations of the New Hebrides, Solomons, Western Carolines, and New Guinea. Am J Trop Med Hyg 25 775 783 795310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Lum1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>44 LumJKKanekoATanabeKTakahashiNBjörkmanA 2004 Malaria dispersal among islands: human mediated Plasmodium falciparum gene flow in Vanuatu, Melanesia. Acta Trop 90 181 185 15177144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Lum2"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>45 LumJKKanekoATaleoGAmosMReiffDM 2007 Genetic diversity and gene flow of humans, Plasmodium falciparum, and Anopheles farauti s.s. of Vanuatu; inferred malaria dispersal and implications for malaria control. Acta Trop 103 102 107 17662681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mita3"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>46 MitaTKanekoALumJKZunguILTsukaharaT 2004 Expansion of wild type allele rather than back mutation in pfcrt explains the recent recovery of chloroquine sensitivity of Plasmodium falciparum in Malawi. Mol Biochem Parasitol 135 159 163 15287598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Langhorne1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>47 LanghorneJNdunguFMSponaasAMMarshK 2008 Immunity to malaria: more questions than answers. Nat Immunol 9 725 732 18563083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Allen1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>48 AllenSJO'DonnellAAlexanderNDMgoneCSPetoTE 1999 Prevention of cerebral malaria in children in Papua New Guinea by Southeast Asian ovalocytosis band 3. Am J Trop Med Hyg 60 1056 1060 10403343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Genton1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>49 GentonBal-YamanFMgoneCSAlexanderNPaniuMM 1995 Ovalocytosis and cerebral malaria. Nature 378 564 565 8524388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Mgone1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>50 MgoneCSKokiGPaniuMMKonoJBhatiaKK 1996 Occurrence of the erythrocyte band 3 (AE1) gene deletion in relation to malaria endemicity in Papua New Guinea. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 90 228 231 8758056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Flint1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>51 FlintJHillAVBowdenDKOppenheimerSJSillPR 1986 High frequencies of alpha-thalassaemia are the result of natural selection by malaria. Nature 321 744 750 3713863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Hill1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>52 HillAVSBowdenDKO'ShaughnessyDFWeatherallDJCleggJB 1988 Beta thalassemia in Melanesia: association with malaria and characterization of a common variant (IVS-1 nt 5 G—C). Blood 72 9 14 2898955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Serjeantson1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>53 SerjeantsonSW 1989 A selective advantage for the Gerbich-negative phenotype in malarious areas of Papua New Guinea. PNG Med J 32 5 9  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Ariey1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>54 ArieyFFandeurTDurandRRandrianarivelojosiaMJambouR 2006 Invasion of Africa by a single pfcrt allele of South East Asian type. Malar J 5 34 16638153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Djimd1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>55 DjimdéADoumboOKCorteseJFKayentaoKDoumboS 2001 A molecular marker for chloroquine-resistant falciparum malaria. N Engl J Med 344 257 263 11172152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Network1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>56 Network 4.516. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fluxus-engineering.com">www.fluxus-engineering.com</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Nei1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>57 NeiM 1987 Molecular Evolutionary Genetics New York Columbia University Press. 512  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Bandelt1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>58 BandeltHJForsterPRöhlA 1999 Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol 16 37 48 10331250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0030213-Excoffier1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>59 ExcoffierLLavalGSchneiderS 2005 Arlequin (version 3.0): An integrated software package for population genetics data analysis. Evol Bioinform Online 1 47 50  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
