<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3792120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24116009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-09281</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Clinical Effectiveness of Patient Initiated Clinics for Patients with Chronic or Recurrent Conditions Managed in Secondary Care: A Systematic Review </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Patient Initiated Clinics in Secondary Care</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Whear</surname><given-names>Rebecca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdul-Rahman</surname><given-names>Abdul-Kareem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>Kate</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson-Coon</surname><given-names>Jo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Peninsula Collaboration for Leadership in Applied Health Research and Care, Institute of Health Research, University of Exeter, Exeter, Devon, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Rheumatlogy Department, Plymouth Healthcare National Health Service Trust, Plymouth, Devon, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>Johanna I.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>r.s.whear@exeter.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: MGP is currently involved with implementing and evaluating a patient initiated clinic for people with Rheumatoid Arthritis at Plymouth Healthcare National Health Service Trust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RW AA JTC MP KS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: RW AA KB JTC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: RW AA JTC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: N/A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: RW AA JTC KB MP KS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e74774</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Whear et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Whear et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Missed or inappropriate hospital appointments cost the UK National Health Service millions of pounds each year and delay treatment for other patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Innovative methods of appointment scheduling that are more flexible to patient needs, may improve service quality and preserve resources. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>A systematic review of the evidence for the clinical effectiveness of patient initiated clinics in managing long term care for people with chronic or recurrent conditions in secondary care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Seven databases were searched including MEDLINE, Embase and PsycINFO (using the OVID interface), the Cochrane Library of Systematic Reviews and CENTRAL, Science Citation Index Expanded, Social Sciences Citation Index, and Conference Proceedings Citation Index (via the Web of Science interface) from inception to June 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Studies comparing patient initiated clinics with traditional consultant-led clinics in secondary care for people with long term chronic or recurrent diseases were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Included studies had to provide data on clinical or resource use outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Data were extracted and checked by two reviewers using a piloted, standardised data extraction form. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Eight studies (n = 1927 individuals) were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>All were conducted in the UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>There were few significant differences in clinical outcomes between the intervention and control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In some instances, using the patient initiated clinics model was associated with savings in time and resource use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The risk of harm from using the patient initiated clinic model of organising outpatient care is low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Studies with longer follow-up periods are needed to assess the long term costs and the ongoing risk of potential harms. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The UK policy context is ripe for evidence-based, patient-centred services to be implemented, especially where the use of health care resources can be optimised without reducing the quality of care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Implementation of patient initiated clinics should remain cautious, with importance placed on ongoing evaluation of long term outcomes and costs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This systematic review was funded by the National Institute of Health Research (NIHR) Collaboration for Leadership in Applied Health Research and Care for the South West. The views expressed in this publication are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the National Health Service, the NIHR or the Department of Health. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Around 17.5 million people in the UK have a chronic condition [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Usually these people attend regular hospital appointments initiated by a physician (usually every six, nine or 12 months). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The appointments commonly occur at a time when a person is feeling relatively well with little action taken as result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Conversely, when symptoms recur or worsen it may be difficult to obtain urgent appointments [2] as outpatient capacity is committed to routine follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Missed hospital appointments are reported to cost the UK National Health Service millions of pounds every year [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Traditionally many lifelong secondary care appointments for people with chronic diseases are arranged weeks or months in advance, clinician driven, and often happen at times when the patient is well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Alternative methods of appointment scheduling with improved flexibility have been developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Some examples of this are the Choose and Book service implemented in 2004 [4] and the Expert Patient Programme courses implemented in 2006 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The Expert Patient Programme aimed to help people with long term conditions develop skills and confidence to self-manage their condition and make more effective use of healthcare services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Other strategies commonly used to improve appointment attendance include: over-booking, fines for missed appointments and appointment reminder systems; these strategies are less responsive to patient need. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In 2002 the World Health Organisation published a report which highlighted the need for a model of care that more readily meets the needs of people with chronic conditions [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The authors of the report suggested that innovations that build on evidence-based decision-making, have a population and quality focus and are flexible to the needs and demands of the patient population should do well in improving the management of chronic conditions for the healthcare system and the people that use it. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In contrast to a traditional appointment system, a patient-initiated clinic (PIC) system aims to be responsive to patient need. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Routine appointments are not regularly scheduled by the physician. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>An example of how this might work in practice is, if a patient is experiencing an exacerbation of their condition, they can phone an advice line manned by a specialist nurse, and where necessary a consultant appointment is arranged as soon as possible. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Several studies have assessed the effectiveness of the PIC system (otherwise known as open or advanced access) in primary care [6]–[8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The results suggest that this method of scheduling outpatient appointments results in improvements in satisfaction with, and a reduced cost of, care delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>With the increasing focus on NHS efficiencies highlighted by the Government's Health and Social Care Bill [9], determining the benefits and harms of alternative methods of appointment scheduling in the secondary care setting is crucial to understanding their worth for both the health system and the people who use it. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study was to systematically review the evidence for the PIC system in secondary care for patients with chronic or recurrent conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In particular we were interested in whether these clinics can effectively manage conditions without causing clinical harm to patients and whether resource use can be reduced in comparison to usual care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The systematic review was conducted according to the principles published by the NHS Centre for Reviews and Dissemination [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>A protocol was developed in consultation with experts and is available on the PenCLAHRC website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clahrc-peninsula.nihr.ac.uk/systematic-review-of-patient-initiated-clinics.php">http://clahrc-peninsula.nihr.ac.uk/systematic-review-of-patient-initiated-clinics.php</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Literature search and eligibility criteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>An information specialist (IS) developed the search strategy in collaboration with clinical consultants and other IS experts to ensure all appropriate terms were captured (KB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>No methods filter was applied to the search strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The search was conducted in the following databases: MEDLINE, Embase and PsycINFO (using the OVID interface), the Cochrane Library of Systematic Reviews and CENTRAL, Science Citation Index Expanded, Social Sciences Citation Index, Conference Proceedings Citation Index (via the Web of Science interface) from inception to December 2010 (see Figure 1 for the full strategy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Update searches were conducted in October 2011 and June 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We also checked the references of included studies, hand searched the BMJ from 1990 to October 2011 for additional studies, searched for ongoing research studies and contacted authors and other experts to identify relevant literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All searches were recorded and Endnote X4 was used to manage the references (KB). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Master search strategy. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Studies were included if they reported a comparison of the effectiveness of PICs (the intervention) against routine, clinician-led, follow-up procedures in secondary care for people with chronic or recurrent conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We defined chronic or recurrent conditions as those diseases that are of a long duration and have fluctuating symptoms, although no ‘condition’ filter was used in the search strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Included studies had to report at least one relevant outcome such as health status, frequency of visits, cost to patient or NHS, or other measures of disease control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Studies where there was insufficient information to allow appraisal of study quality were excluded as were studies set in primary care, those that dealt with diagnosis (as opposed to management) of conditions, and those that included short term acute conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>No date or language restrictions were applied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Titles and abstracts were independently screened by two reviewers (JTC, AA or RW) using the inclusion and exclusion criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Full texts were retrieved for articles that required more in depth application of the inclusion and exclusion criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>All full texts were independently reviewed by two reviewers and discrepancies were resolved by a third (JTC) and fourth (KS) reviewer where necessary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Data extraction was conducted by two reviewers (RW and AA) and checked by a third reviewer (JTC) using a standardised data extraction form (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The data extracted included information on the quality of the study (based on the guidelines from the Centre for Reviews and Dissemination) and information on the participants, intervention and control descriptions, outcomes and outcome measures as well as the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Studies were not excluded on the basis of quality. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Data synthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Narrative synthesis was used to summarise and discuss the results of the included studies following the principles described in Economic and Social Research Council guidelines [11] and the Centre for Reviews and Dissemination guidelines [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Meta-analysis was inappropriate due to the clear heterogeneity in participants, conditions and outcomes across studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The identification and selection of studies is summarised in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Eight studies met the inclusion criteria [12]–[21], six were identified by electronic searches and two were identified by searching citations in identified studies [13], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Seven included studies were randomised controlled trials (RCT) and one was a retrospective audit [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>One study was reported in three articles at different stages of follow up [19]–[21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In total 2,642 articles were excluded (including 368 duplicates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Reasons for exclusion after retrieval of the full text articles are presented in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Identification and selection of studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The included studies reported the clinical effectiveness of a PIC system in three disease areas – breast cancer (BC) [12], [13], [22], inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) [15]–[17] and rheumatoid arthritis (RA) [18]–[21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>All of these studies were conducted in the UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A total of 1,927 patients over the age of 16 years were included (562 with breast cancer, 1,083 with IBD, and 382 with RA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Participants were followed up for between 12 and 72 months. Figure 3 details the characteristics of the included studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of included studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The structure of PICs was broadly similar across the studies with the main access point being a telephone number, through which patients could request clinical advice and, if necessary, arrange an appointment to see a clinician. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In four studies [12], [13], [15], [16] patients in the intervention group were also given written guidance to help them self-manage their condition and to make them aware of what symptoms or events should initiate the need for a consultation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of the PIC system in each study are presented in Table S2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The quality of included studies varied (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Despite the majority being RCTs, the quality of reporting was inconsistent and important information was lacking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>For example, very few studies reported the method of randomisation; in all studies it was unclear whether the personnel measuring outcomes were blinded to the participants' allocation; information on the reliability and variability of outcome measures was not provided; very few studies reported an intention-to-treat analysis and only half reported having more than 80% of the participants remaining at follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The lack of information limits the interpretation and extrapolation of the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>However details of power calculations to understand the sample size, baseline characteristics of all the participants; eligibility criteria of participants involved; and reporting of data ensuring all participants had been accounted for were well reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The methods used and reported by Sheppard and colleagues [22], Robinson and colleagues [16], Kennedy and colleagues [15] and Hewlett and colleagues [19], [20] suggested lower potential for bias in their results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Quality of studies in included. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A proposed logic model for the theory behind both the traditional and PIC appointment systems is illustrated in Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The results of individual studies are presented in Figures 6 and 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Each figure lists the studies that reported on the appropriate outcome data across disease area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Studies that did not report on those outcomes are not included in the tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Results as published in the original articles can be seen in Table S3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Logic model of traditional and Patient Initiated Clinic appointment systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcomes chart. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0074774-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>a Health service resource use and cost chart. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Health service resource use and cost chart. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0074774.g007"/></fig></SecTag><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A large number of clinical outcomes were reported across studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, there were few common outcomes and direct comparison between studies is limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a1"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Relapse </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The results from Sheppard and colleagues [22] suggest that for BC patients there was no difference in the relapse rate reported between the two groups over their 18 month study (both were low at 4% recurrence). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Results from one IBD study [15] suggested that at 12 months, patients in the intervention group (PIC) had a significantly reduced mean relapse rate (m = 1.8±2.2) compared with the control group (m = 2.2±2.5; 95% CI -0.63 to −0.09). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In another IBD study (16), the duration of the relapse was longer (though not significantly so) for the patients in the intervention group compared to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Relapse was not reported in the RA studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3a2"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Medical intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Results from one of the studies in RA [18] implied that patients in the intervention (PIC) group received significantly more interventions in their care as a proportion of total clinic appointments than those in the control group (96.7% vs 52.2% respectively, p&lt;0.00001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The intervention group were also more likely than the control group to receive a meaningful intervention, for example, a change of medication or further investigations (66.7% vs 30.1%, p&lt;0.00001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3a3"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcomes over time (RA only) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>For the remaining RA studies [19]–[21] that reported on clinical outcomes it is possible to follow the same groups of participants throughout their six year follow-up, during which time no clear and consistent pattern favouring either approach to follow up was shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Hewlett and colleagues [19] reported that at 24 months the intervention (PIC) group had statistically significant and clinically improved mean pain scores (on a 10 point scale) than the control group (m = 3.9; 95%CI 3.2 to 4.4 vs m = 4.8; 95%CI 4.2 to 5.4 respectively; p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>However, by 48 months Kirwan and colleagues' [21] results indicated that the overall change in pain scores from 0–48 months was only marginally better for the intervention than the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The decline in pain continued in both groups up to 72 months with Hewlett and colleagues [20] reporting worse (but non-significant) change in pain scores for the intervention group (median change  = 1.25, range −0.40 to 3.25 vs 1.1, −1.00 to 3.60 respectively, p = 0.91). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Disease activity fluctuated over time, with results across the three studies [19]–[21] indicating that at 24 months, disease activity was better in the intervention group than in the control group [19], and at 48 months, disease activity was worse in the intervention group [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>By 72 months, although both groups outcomes were worse, there was almost no difference in their disease activity [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>These results showed no clinically significant impacts for the patients in either group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Change in disability scores held a more stable pattern, the results were better for the intervention group than the control group, although over time they both became worse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Results for other bodily functions such as hand grip strength, elbow mobility and knee mobility also presented fairly consistent results across time with the intervention group generally doing better than the control group (details can be seen in Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Health service resource use </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3b1"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Breast Cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>One study on BC [13] reported a reduction in the number of consultant visits for the intervention group but an increase in the number of nurse visits and medical investigations, though these were not statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>There were also increased numbers of investigations and no difference in the number of booked appointments between the intervention and control groups [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b2"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory Bowel Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>For patients with IBD, in the intervention group the number of patients making appointments for themselves (43% vs 22%, 95%CI 1.63, 4.46) was significantly lower than those recorded in the control group [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The number of clinic appointments not kept, visits to outpatient clinics, day visits and visits to the GP were reduced in the intervention group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Robinson and colleagues [16] reported that the time between symptom flares and treatment was significantly reduced for patients in the intervention group in comparison to the control group (m = 14.8 hrs vs m = 49.6hrs respectively; p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In a third study, there was a reduction in the mean number of visits to accident and emergency wards (m = 0.03 vs m = 0.05) [15], a reduction in the number of missed appointments (n = 1 vs n = 47) [16], and a reduced number of investigations e.g. blood tests in the intervention group (p = 0.09–0.81) [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Williams and colleagues [17] reported that on average patients in the intervention group spent more days as inpatients than the control group (m = 0.83±3.53 vs m = 0.43±1.74 respectively; p = 0.71). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b3"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Rheumatoid Arthritis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Hewlett and colleagues [19], [20] reported a significant reduction in the number of consultant visits in the intervention group at 24 and 72 months in comparison to the control group (PIC median 8 (5–13) vs 13 (11–17) appointments; p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>There was also a greater time between appointments (fewer appointments being made) [18], a reduction in safety net failure and fewer complications in the intervention group [19] (Figures 7a and b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Health service costs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The overall cost to the NHS per patient was reported to be less in the intervention group than the control group in the four studies that measured this outcome [13], [15], [17], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The annual NHS cost difference between the intervention and control groups was estimated to be an average of £89 per patient/per year (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0074774-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074774.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>NHS summary costs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0074774-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0074774.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Study </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Control (£) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>PIC (£) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Difference </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Annualised cost difference (£) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Koinberg (2009) 48mths NHS – BC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>1869 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>1266 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>603 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>−150.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Hewlett (2000) 12mths NHS – RA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>313 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>208 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>105* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>−105 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Kennedy (2003) 12mths NHS – IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>1070 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>922 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>148 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>−148 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Williams (2000) 24mths NHS – IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>951 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>1046 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>+47.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Williams (2000) 24mths patients-IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>122 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>−3.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Robinson (2001) 14mths patients-IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>8.92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>0.86 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>8.06* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>−6.91 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>NB: Summary of mean total NHS financial cost per patient (in time specified) and mean total financial cost to patient (in time specified). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Average difference in NHS cost per patient per year is £89.06 range £+47.50 to −150.75 in favour of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Average difference in Patient cost per year is £5.21 range £3.50–6.91 in favour of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>NB. Koinberg (2009) costs originally published in Euros, converted to Sterling using Jan 2006 exchange rates (0.688 Euros to the pound) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.x-rates.com/cgi-bin/hlookup.cgi">http://www.x-rates.com/cgi-bin/hlookup.cgi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>There was no perceived difference between measured costs in the intervention and control groups at 12 months, in the study of people with BC [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Kennedy and colleagues [15] reported reduced costs in the intervention group for all outcomes at 12 months in comparison to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>These results included reduced costs from GP visits, IBD outpatient visits, IBD inpatient stays and medication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The results from Williams and colleagues' [17] study were more mixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The findings reported significantly reduced mean costs for investigations made in secondary care (m = £198 vs m = £257; p = 0.032) and for total cost to secondary care (£582 vs £611, p = 0.012) at 24 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, the total drug, primary care, NHS and societal costs per patient were all reported to be marginally higher in the intervention group than in the control group at 24 months; these differences are not significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>One study on RA reported about costs [19] and found that the PIC intervention significantly reduced costs to the NHS over one year (£208 per patient per year) in comparison to usual follow up (£313 per patient per year, p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Robinson and colleagues [16] reported a reduced cost in terms of patient's time (including travelling to and from appointments) at 14 months (PIC m = 1 hr ±2.95 vs m = 6.2 hr ±7.1; p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Robinson and colleagues' [16] study also reported a significant difference in mean cost for patients between the groups at 14 months (m = £0.86±3.41 vs 8.92±18.30 respectively; p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Williams and colleagues [17] also found cost savings for patients in the intervention group (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Exploration of relationships </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Figure 5 portrays one theory about how the PIC system could lead to a more effective and satisfactory service without harming patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Additional boxes (with an interrupted border) are where the studies included in this review may inform the future implementation of the PIC system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Establishing definitive links between the characteristics of the intervention and the reported outcomes was not possible from the small amount of variable literature that was available for inclusion in this review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>However, below are some observations regarding possible links which should be considered in any further research in this area. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Four studies [12], [13], [15], [16] described a similar PIC system with each involving written information to support the patient, a telephone helpline, an annual check-up and an initial consultation (Brown and colleagues report no initial consultation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>From the results across outcomes it could be argued that those studies tended to produce better results for the PIC system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, the Hewlett and Kirwan [19]–[21] studies also reported positive results for the PIC system without the use of written information or an initial consultation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The methods suggest that a large amount of verbal information was supplied by the consultant to individuals in the intervention group in these studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, there was some suggestion that studies in which written information was provided in addition to a telephone helpline and an annual check-up were associated with greater long-term cost savings to the NHS and the patient. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Another feature of some of the PIC interventions was that much of the care responsibility was handed back to the primary care physician [17], [19]–[22], though this was primarily the case in those that did not have any written information for the patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This would have meant that the patient could contact their primary care physician with any concerns about their condition in the first instance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The primary care physician was then guaranteed speedy access to a specialist consultant when needed or the patient was allowed to contact the hospital directly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>However, it is possible that whilst support from the primary care physician may replace written information adequately in terms of clinical outcomes, the impact on resources and costs was less clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In some instances, the number of visits to the GP and the cost of the intervention to primary care could have increased whilst appointments and costs in secondary care decreased. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We identified eight studies of the impact of a PIC system on the clinical outcomes of patients with BC, IBD and RA in secondary care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Although there were limitations in the quality of reporting, which indicates that a number of the studies may have been affected by bias, and the level of heterogeneity in populations and outcomes were considerable, there was some evidence that the PIC system of appointment scheduling was not harmful to patients with BC, IBD and RA, and may be associated with savings in health service resources, costs and clinician time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>In the included studies there were minimal differences in clinical outcomes between traditional appointment scheduling and the PIC system, suggesting that PIC follow up was as good as traditional models at delivering care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The differences observed could be due to the nature of the disease areas, i.e. the relapsing and remitting nature of IBD and RA, compared to the “remission or recurrence” in malignancies like BC (e.g. people can learn to manage their own symptoms with appropriate guidance better in the former than the latter). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>It might not be expected that a change in service would necessarily lead to an improvement in the way symptoms are experienced by the patient but no further data was available to inform this observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to note if symptoms become significantly worse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>There was evidence that the PIC system could be associated with a reduced number of booked appointments which allows clinician and patient time to be used more efficiently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>This would allow for more autonomy within the service to treat those who need immediate care quickly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Several studies reported financial cost savings to the NHS and to patients, however, whether the PIC system is cost effective in the long term is unclear and may be dependent on the condition being considered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Though the results of this review imply benefits in the use of the PIC system without harming patients they must be taken in the context of the various limitations and potential biases within the included studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The most obvious harm risk in terms of clinical outcomes is believed to result from situations where the patient fails to request an appointment at the time of relapse or escalation of their condition and therefore symptoms become worse and possibly critical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>This may increasingly be the case where PIC interventions do not include a ‘safety-net’ appointment system or where clinicians are unable to select ‘appropriate’ patients for the PIC pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>A less apparent harm risk may occur if during a “routine” traditional appointment there are elements of preventative healthcare or patient education that occur, which are not covered during an “urgent” PIC appointment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This risk can probably be circumvented by incorporating an appropriate check list into a safety net appointment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>There are no statistically significant harms reported by any study in terms of clinical outcomes, however, some of the studies (n = 4) excluded participants who had not completed all the questionnaires or diaries from the final analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>From these studies it is clear that approximately 18 patients withdrew from the studies due to recurrence of illness, 34 refused to complete the final questionnaires or were otherwise lost to follow-up and in one study approximately 19 patients died during participation [21] so the potential for harms to have been recorded may have limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In addition to the bias within the studies, publication bias may also have influenced the results of the review, reflecting the bias towards pursuing ideas and publishing studies with positive outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>All of the included studies were conducted within the UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>There are a number of possible explanations for this: 1) other terms for this approach may be used in different health care systems; 2) PICs are implemented in secondary care without evaluation of their impact and hence no primary research is available; 3) evaluation of PICs may be hidden within health departments with limited access to and awareness of the final report documents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We are confident that our search terms are likely to have identified all appropriate studies published in English. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Our search strategy did not include grey literature (i.e. literature informally published, such as technical reports from government agencies or scientific research groups, working papers from research groups or committees, white papers, and preprints that may be difficult to trace via published journals and monographs because it is not widely accessible) from outside the UK and this is a limitation, although it seems unlikely that grey literature would contain randomised evaluations of PICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Contact with professionals identified an ongoing trial investigating the use of outpatient on-demand clinics for people with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease in the Netherlands (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00556816">http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00556816</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>It is perhaps surprising that, despite the promising nature of the PIC system and the direction of national guidelines for RA and IBD, such limited research has been conducted to establish the barriers to or even the key components of implementing this system of care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Recent guidelines for the management of RA [23], [24] and IBD [25] in adults have all suggested that patients with these conditions should be able to access a specialist as soon as possible if the state of their condition worsens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Recent qualitative research in people with IBD has also reported that patients want flexibility and choice, they do not want to be discharged from secondary care and desire the specialist to still be involved in overall management [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The PIC approach to outpatient care is clearly in line with these guidelines and would also fall in line with guidelines for other chronic diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>For example, the UK Department of Health National Service Framework for long term [4] conditions states, in relation to care for people with Parkinson's Disease, that there should be enough flexibility to allow for both planned reviews and unplanned reviews when a person's condition suddenly deteriorates or their circumstances change [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the British Thoracic Society guidelines also discuss outpatient clinic management in this way and a recent study has used similar processes of minimising clinic time for well patients and giving them fast access to clinician care should they deteriorate [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>If it is true, as suggested by our review, that patients are not likely to come to harm as a result of follow-up initiated by themselves, then there may be substantial gains in efficiency for health care systems to adopt this approach in suitable conditions and with appropriately selected patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Giving patients the option of either form of follow-up may be important in avoiding harm and ensuring the most appropriate patients use the service. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Importantly, five out of eight identified studies retained an annual or biennial consultation as a safety-net in the intervention groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>There is a clear need for long term randomised controlled trials of this type of appointment system using comparable outcome data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Quantitative and qualitative evaluations of PIC implementations to enable a better understanding of clinical and efficiency outcomes and investigation of context-dependent influences including the professional and organisational barriers to implementing PICs should also be conducted, as suggested by Whear and colleagues [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Patient initiated clinic systems should include some form of ‘safety-net’ and allow for how clinicians and patients would like to use the system e.g. allowing patient choice and/or clinician selection into specific care pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The UK policy context is ripe for evidence-based, patient-centred services to be implemented and evaluated, especially where health professionals' and patients' wasted time and costs can be minimised without reducing the quality of health care or patient outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Present research on the PIC system has presented some positive findings but implementation should remain cautious with ongoing evaluation of its long term outcomes and costs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074774.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Data Extraction and Quality Appraisal form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0074774.s001.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074774.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of patient initiated clinics in included studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0074774.s002.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074774.s003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Outcome data from original articles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0074774.s003.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074774.s004"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Key for   Figure 3  . </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0074774.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074774.s005"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Prisma checklist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0074774.s005.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>We would like to give our thanks for the IS support of Morwenna Rogers and Alison Bethel who conducted the updated searches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Also to Will Stahl-Timmins for the use of the Graphical Overview for Evidence Reviews (GOfER) programme. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0074774-DoH1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>1DoH (2001) The Expert Patient: A New Approach to Chronic Disease Management for the 21st Century. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>London: Department of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>35. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Hehir1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2 HehirM, HewlettS, MitchellK, KirwanJ, MemelD, et al (2001) What happens in RA outpatient clinics? Rheumatology 40: s146. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-HES1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>3HES (2010) Outpatient data: SHA and provider level analysis 2008–09 and 2009–10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>ONS: NHS Information Centre for Health and Social Care. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hscic.gov.uk/searchcatalogue?productid=2805&amp;q=%2822hospitaloutpatientactivity%2822&amp;topics=2800%2802fHospitalcare&amp;sort=Relevance&amp;size=2810&amp;page=2801#top">http://www.hscic.gov.uk/searchcatalogue?productid=2805&amp;q=%2822hospitaloutpatientactivity%2822&amp;topics=2800%2802fHospitalcare&amp;sort=Relevance&amp;size=2810&amp;page=2801#top</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-DoH2"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>4DoH (2004) Choose &amp; Book – Patient's Choice of Hospital and Booked Appointment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>London: Department of Health. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>16. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-WHO1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>5WHO (2002) Innovative Care for Chronic Conditions: Building Blocks for Action. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Geneva: World Health Organisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>103 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Rose1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>6 RoseKD, RossJS, HorwitzLI (2011) Advanced access scheduling outcomes a systematic review. Archives of internal medicine 171: 1150–1159.21518935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Robinson1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>7 RobinsonL, ChenR (2010) A comparison of traditional and open-access policies for appointment scheduling. Manufacturing and Service Operations Management 12: 330–346. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>8 LiuN, ZiyaS, KulkarniVG (2010) Dynamic scheduling of outpatient appointments under patient no-shows and cancellations. M&amp;Som-Manufacturing &amp; Service Operations Management 12: 347–364. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Nuffield1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>9Nuffield (2011) Health and Social Care Bill: Second reading, House of Lords. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>London: Nuffield Trust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>16 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-CRD1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>10CRD (2009) Systematic Reviews: CRD's guidance for undertaking reviews in healthcare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>York: Centre for Reviews and Dissemination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>294 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Popay1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>11Popay J, Roberts H, Sowden A, Petticrew M, Arai L, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>(2006) Guidance on the conduct of systematic reviews. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>London: Economic and Social Research Council. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>12 BrownL, PayneS, RoyleG (2002) Patient-initiated follow-up of breast cancer. Psycho-Oncology 11: 346–355.12203747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Koinberg1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>13 KoinbergI, EngholmG, GenellA, HolmbergL (2009) A heath economic evaluation of follow-up after breast cancer surgery. Acta Oncologica 48: 99–104.18766474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Sands1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>14 SandsA, AdamsN (2009) A comparison of patient-initiated versus conventional follow-up for rheumatoid arthritis. Journal of Pain Management 1: 391–400. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Kennedy1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>15Kennedy A, Nelson E, Reeves D, Richardson G, Roberts C, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>(2003) A randomised controlled trial to assess the impact of a package comprising a patient-orientated, evidence-based self-help guidebook and patient-centered consultations on disease management and satisfaction in inflammatory bowel disease Health Technology Assessment 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Robinson2"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>16 RobinsonA, ThompsonDG, WilkinD, RobertsC, GrpNWGR (2001) Guided self-management and patient-directed follow-up of ulcerative colitis: a randomised trial. Lancet 358: 976–981.11583752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Williams1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>17 WilliamsJG, CheungWY, RussellIT, CohenDR, LongoM, et al (2000) Open access follow up for inflammatory bowel disease: Pragmatic randomised trial and cost effectiveness study. British Medical Journal 320 (7234): 544–548. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Chattopadhyay1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="?"><plain>18 ChattopadhyayC, HickeyPM (2008) Are routine appointments cost-effective in modern rheumatology practice? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>A comparative outcome audit of routine follow-ups and patient initiated consultations. Arthritis and Rheumatism 58: S885–S885. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Hewlett1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>19Hewlett S, Mitchell K, Haynes J, Paine T, Korendowych E, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>(2000) Patient-initiated hospital follow-up for rheumatoid arthritis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SO: Rheumatology (Oxford, England): 990–997. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Hewlett2"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>20 HewlettS, KirwanJ, PollockJ, MitchellK, HehirM, et al (2005) Patient initiated outpatient follow up in rheumatoid arthritis: six year randomised controlled trial. BMJ 330: 171.15546895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Kirwan1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>21 KirwanJR, MitchellK, HewlettS, HehirM, PollockJ, et al (2003) Clinical and psychological outcome from a randomized controlled trial of patient-initiated direct-access hospital follow-up for rheumatoid arthritis extended to 4 years. Rheumatology 42 (3): 422–426. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Sheppard1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>22 SheppardC, HigginsB, WiseM, YiangouC, DuboisD, et al (2009) Breast cancer follow-up: a randomised controlled trial comparing point of need access versus routine 6-monthly clinical review. European Journal of Oncology Nursing 13: 2–8.19119079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-NICE1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>23NICE (2009) Rheumatoid arthritis: The management of rheumatoid arthritis in adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>London: National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>35 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Luqmani1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>24 LuqmaniR, HennellS, EstrachC, BasherD, BirrellF, et al (2009) British Society for Rheumatology and British Health Professionals in Rheumatology guideline for the management of rheumatoid arthritis (after the first 2 years). Rheumatology 48: 436–439.19174570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Mowat1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>25 MowatC, ColeA, WindsorA, AhmadT, ArnottI, et al (2011) Guidelines for the management of inflammatory bowel disease in adults. Gut 60: 571–607.21464096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Kemp1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>26 KempK, GriffithsJ, CampbellS, LovellK (2013) A qualitative exploration of the follow up needs of patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Journal of Crohn's and Colitis 7: S246–S247. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-DoH3"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>27DoH (2005) The National Service Framework for long term conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>London: Crown Copyright. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>106. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Turner1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>28 TurnerAM, DalaySK, TalwarA, SnelsonC, MukherjeeR (2013) Reforming respiratory outpatient services: a before-and-after observational study assessing the impact of a quality improvement project applying British Thoracic Society criteria to the discharge of patients to primary care. Primary Care Respiratory Journal 22: 72–78. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0074774-Whear1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>29Whear R, Abdul-Rahman A, Thompson-Coon J, Boddy K, Perry M, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Patient initiated clinics for patients with chronic or recurrent conditions managed in secondary care: a systematic review of patient reported outcomes and patient and clinician satisfaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>BMC Health Services Research (under review): personal communication. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
