<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3836741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24278378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-26135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Novel In Vitro Model for Microvasculature Reveals Regulation of Circumferential ECM Organization by Curvature </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Curvature Regulates ECM Organization</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto-Ortiz</surname><given-names>Sebastian F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shuming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fradkin</surname><given-names>Jamie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Hai-Quan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gerecht</surname><given-names>Sharon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, Johns Hopkins Physical Sciences-Oncology Center and Institute for NanoBioTechnology, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Materials Science and Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Translational Tissue Engineering Center, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Engler</surname><given-names>Adam J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of California, San Diego, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>gerecht@jhu.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: SFBO SG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: SFBO JF MD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: SFBO SZ JF MD BG H-QM SG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SZ BG H-QM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: SFBO SG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Edited the paper: H-QM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e81061</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Barreto-Ortiz et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Barreto-Ortiz et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In microvascular vessels, endothelial cells are aligned longitudinally whereas several components of the extracellular matrix (ECM) are organized circumferentially. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>While current three-dimensional (3D) in vitro models for microvasculature have allowed the study of ECM-regulated tubulogenesis, they have limited control over topographical cues presented by the ECM and impart a barrier for the high-resolution and dynamic study of multicellular and extracellular organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Here we exploit a 3D fibrin microfiber scaffold to develop a novel in vitro model of the microvasculature that recapitulates endothelial alignment and ECM deposition in a setting that also allows the sequential co-culture of mural cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We show that the microfibers' nanotopography induces longitudinal adhesion and alignment of endothelial colony-forming cells (ECFCs), and that these deposit circumferentially organized ECM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We found that ECM wrapping on the microfibers is independent of ECFCs' actin and microtubule organization, but it is dependent on the curvature of the microfiber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Microfibers with smaller diameters (100–400 µm) guided circumferential ECM deposition, whereas microfibers with larger diameters (450 µm) failed to support wrapping ECM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Finally, we demonstrate that vascular smooth muscle cells attached on ECFC-seeded microfibers, depositing collagen I and elastin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Collectively, we establish a novel in vitro model for the sequential control and study of microvasculature development and reveal the unprecedented role of the endothelium in organized ECM deposition regulated by the microfiber curvature. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>SFBO acknowledges the support from the Cancer and Nanotechnology Training Center at Johns Hopkins University – Institute of NanoBioTechnology under the grant number R25CA153952; This research was partially funded by National Institute of Health grants R01HL107938 and U54CA143868, and an American Heart Association Scientist Development grant (to SG) and National Science Foundation Career Award grant number DMR-0748340 (to H-Q M). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The development of functional microvascular vessels requires complex interactions between endothelial cells (ECs), perivascular cells, and the extracellular matrix (ECM) [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The ECM is comprised of an abundance of nanometer sized macromolecular ECM proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>As such, many of the physical interactions between vascular cells and macromolecular components of the ECM occur at the sub-micron scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>EC adhesion to the ECM initiates the angiogenic cascade [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Cells detect and respond to the nanoarchitecture of their microenvironment by cytoskeletal reorganization and activated signaling cascades to regulate fundamental cell behaviors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Indeed, it has been shown that surfaces with nano-scale line-grating features affect EC adhesion, alignment, and elongation [4]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>ECs, sitting on their basal lamina, comprise the innermost lining of the vessels, followed by a layer of subendothelial connective tissue and an internal elastic lamina composed of different ECM proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>These layers together make the tunica intima of blood vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Mural cells, along with their ECM, make up the tunica media or middle layer and provide the contractility necessary for vasoreactivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>On top of this layer lays the tunica adventitia, though it is only present in larger blood vessels. [2], [8]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The specific composition as well as the organization and arrangement of both cellular and ECM components in each layer are necessary for proper microvasculature development, maturation, stability, and function [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that in microvasculature EC nuclei and cytoskeleton are aligned in the direction of blood flow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, studies on microvasculature have not analyzed the organization of different ECM components in detail [15]–[17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>By large, the literature that has studied the particular organization of the ECM in native blood vessels is focused on analyzing the elastin and collagen structures in the aorta and other large arteries [10]–[14], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These studies have shown that the structural organization of collagen varies not only between the three layers of the vasculature, but also varies with vessel size and specific location in the body [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Overall, the studies agree that each tunica possesses at least two different families of collagen fibrils, with distinctly different organizations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The general arrangement has been found to be close to axial in the adventitia, outer layers having a more pronounced axial orientation transitioning to a circumferential alignment in inner layers [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the medial layer has been shown to have a nearly perfect circumferential order [11]–[14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Studies also agree both the internal and external elastic lamina are fenestrated, though both axial and circumferential organization of these layers has been reported [15], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the subendothelium has been found to have a more varied composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>It has been described as a multilayered fabric of collagen, containing distinct layers of both longitudinally and circumferentially aligned fibers [10], [13], [14], [20]; some studies suggesting a layer of longitudinally aligned ECM directly under the media layer, followed by a helically arranged region of connective tissue beneath, and a thin circumferentially aligned layer next to the lumen [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to note that these findings were all made on large arteries with diameters in the millimeter range. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To date, only a few studies have attempted to model or recreate microvasculature in a full 3D setting in vitro [21]–[23], as the majority of models have either focused on the development of capillary beds in natural or synthetic hydrogels [24]–[35], decellularized matrices [36], [37], and electrospun polymer scaffolds [38], [39], or have instead aimed to create vascular grafts typically &gt;3 mm in diameter [40]–[45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>While these models enabled us to study the ECM-driven molecular mechanisms that regulate EC tubulogenesis, they typically support spontaneous and random tubulogenesis (size, shape, organization, etc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Recent works employ micro-patterning and demonstrate an organized vascular network structure within hydrogels, some of which are able to recruit vascular smooth muscle cells (vSMCs) [46]–[48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, these systems have limited control over topographical cues presented by the ECM and impart a barrier for the high-resolution, dynamic, and detailed study of vascular organization and specific cell-ECM and multi-cellular interactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Tubular polymeric scaffolds have the potential to provide a better and more sophisticated platform to study the microvasculature, but currently are obtainable with diameters in the millimeter range [49]–[51] and are utilized to study graft's mechanical strength [52]–[54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>To recapitulate the microvasculature in vitro, the tubular scaffolds must exhibit a physiologically-relevant diameter and sub-micron topography with sufficient mechanical properties, be biocompatible, mediate specific cell adhesion, allow tubular vessel formation, and support multi-cellular interactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Endothelial colony forming cells (ECFCs), a subpopulation of endothelial progenitor cells, are known for their proliferative capacity and contribution to functional vessels [55]–[57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Recently, we revealed that ECFCs deposit ECM proteins, namely collagen IV, fibronectin and laminin, and also assemble it into web-like structures when cultured on Petri dishes [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests an important role for ECM production by ECFCs in the process of vascular assembly that has not yet been identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Here we exploit a three-dimensional (3D) fibrin microfiber scaffold to develop a novel in vitro model of the microvasculature that recapitulates ECFC alignment and ECM deposition in a setting that also allows the sequential co-culture of vSMCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Using this model, we determine that the microfiber curvature affects the circumferential deposition of ECM from ECFCs independently of cellular organization, demonstrating unique opportunities to study microvasculature development and regeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Cell Culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Human ECFCs (Lonza, Walkersville, MD) were used for experiments between passages 5 and 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were expanded in flasks coated with type I collagen (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ) in Endothelial Basal Medium-2 (EBM-2; Lonza) supplemented with EGM-2 Bulletkit (Lonza) and 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Hyclone, Logan, UT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were fed every other day, passaged every 5 to 7 days with 0.05% trypsin/0.1% ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Human vSMCs (ATCC, Manassas, VA) were used between passages 4 and 9 and cultured in F-12K medium (ATCC) supplemented with 0.01 mg/ml insulin (Akron Biotech, Boca Raton, FL), 10% FBS (Hyclone), 0.05 mg/ml ascorbic acid, 0.01 mg/ml transferrin, 10 ng/ml sodium selenite, 0.03 mg/ml endothelial cell growth supplement, 10 mM HEPES, and 10 mM TES (all from Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Preparation of 3D fibrin hydrogel microfiber </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Fibrin hydrogel microfibers were generated by a new electrostretching method ( Fig. 1A ) [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>An aqueous solution of 1.5 wt% alginate (Sigma-Aldrich) was in-line mixed with 2 wt% fibrinogen (Sigma-Aldrich) at feeding rates of 2 ml/h and 1 ml/h, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The mixed solution was then charged with 4 kV electric potential and extruded through a 25-gauge needle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The fibrinogen-alginate solution jet was collected at a distance of 3–5 cm from the needle tip, in a grounded, rotating bath (20 cm diameter, 20–40 rotation/min) containing 50 mM CaCl2 solution with 5 units/ml thrombin (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>To generate microfibers with different diameters, collection times were varied from 7–75 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>After spinning, the resulting ring of nanofibers was left in the collection solution for 15 min before being cut once to obtain nanofiber strands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The crosslinked fibrin-alginate nanofibers were then soaked in 0.2 M sodium citrate overnight to remove calcium ions and dissolve alginate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Nanofibers were soaked in water for 30 min to remove sodium citrate, collected as an aligned bundle, stretched to 150% of their initial length, and air-dried for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Resulting microfibers ( Fig. 1A ) were wrapped around a custom-made plastic frame, then sterilized by soaking in 75% ethanol for 2 min followed by rinsing twice with sterile water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Microfiber diameter was measured from confocal z-stack projections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>ECFCs attached and aligned on fibrin hydrogel microfibers. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic of experimental procedure including electrospinning, ECFC seeding, and tumbling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Drawing not to scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>SEM of critical-point dried fibrin microfiber showing aligned topography on the microfiber surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Scale bar is 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>(B–D) Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs seeded on fibrin hydrogel microfibers horizontally aligned after 5 days in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>F-actin (phalloidin staining) is shown in green, EC-specific markers (VECad, CD31, or vWF) in red, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of stretching and nanotopography on microfiber surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. n≥2 per stain with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Cell seeding and culture on fibrin hydrogel microfibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were seeded on microfibers of 15 cm length total at a density of 4×105 cells/ml in 5 ml of ECFC media supplemented with 50 ng/mL of VEGF (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The seeding tube was left on a tumbler (Labquake, Dubuque, IA) for 24 h at 37°C to facilitate cell attachment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Frames with ECFC seeded microfibers were then transferred to 35 mm Petri dishes using tweezers, and cultured in the same media in a CO2 incubator at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Media was refreshed every other day thereafter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>vSMCs were seeded on 5–7 day ECFC-seeded fibrin microfibers at 1–4×105 cells/ml in 5 ml of 0.5% serum or regular ECFC media, tumbled for 24 hours, and then transferred to 35 mm Petri dishes to continue culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Media was changed every other day thereafter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Preparation of 2D fibrin nanofiber sheets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Fibrin-alginate hydrogel nanofibers were prepared according to the same electrostretching protocol as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The collected fibrin-alginate hydrogel nanofibers were wrapped around a modified plastic frame to form a sheet of nanofibers while slightly stretching the nanofibers to ensure proper alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The fibrin sheets were placed in a 0.2-M sodium citrate solution overnight to remove alginate, followed by a 30 min wash in water to remove excess sodium citrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Fibrin sheets were then sterilized with 75% ethanol and rinsed twice with sterile water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Cell seeding and culture on 2D fibrin sheets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Cells were seeded by placing 5×105 ECFCs in a concentrated solution of cells (about 2×106 cells/ml) directly on top of the fibrin sheet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>After 5 min the cell solution that had filtered through the sheets was collected and reseeded on top of the fibrin sheets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>This process was repeated 3 times, after which the same culture media as used for 3D fibers was added to the samples before being placed in a humidified incubator at 37°C in a 5% CO2 atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Media was refreshed every other day up to 5 days of culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Preparation of 3D polyethersulfone (PES) fibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Solid polymer fibers were prepared as a control according to a modified electrostretching protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In brief, PES (Goodfellow Cambridge Limited, UK, Mw 55,000) was dissolved in 30 wt% DMSO and electrospun under an electric potential of 5 kV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The feed rate of PES solution was 12 ml/h to initiate a polymer jet, which was collected in a grounded, rotating ethanol bath (20–40 rotations/min) to extract the solvent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The collection distance was set to 5 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>After 10 min in ethanol, PES strings were removed from the bath and air dried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>After electrospinning, PES fibers were wrapped around a seeding frame similarly to the fibrin hydrogel microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Samples were then plasma-treated for 5 min before soaking for 5 min in a 10 units/ml thrombin in 15 mM CaCl2 solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Thrombin-coated PES fibers were then immersed in a 0.2% fibrinogen solution diluted in 0.9% NaCl for fibrinogen polymerization into fibrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Excess fibrin coating on the frame and outside of the fibers was removed before sterilization with 75% ethanol for 1–2 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Samples were rinsed twice with sterile water, after which cell seeding was performed similarly to the fibrin microfibers as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Actin and microtubule disruption studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Cytochalasin D or nocodazole were dissolved in DMSO (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were cultured on Petri dishes or fibrin microfibers in the same media described above supplemented with either 1 µg/mL cytochalasin D or 3.3 µM nocodazole from either day 0 or day 1 after seeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>F-actin or α-tubulin organization and ECM deposition was analyzed after 1, 2, or 3 days of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Final concentration of DMSO in cell culture medium was kept at 0.1% (v/v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Controls were treated with DMSO alone at the same concentration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence staining and confocal microscopy imaging </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Cell-microfiber constructs were fixed with 3.7% formaldehyde (Fisher Chemical, Fairlawn, NJ) for 15 min, permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 solution (Sigma-Aldrich) in 3.7% formaldehyde for 10 min, washed three times with PBS, and incubated for 1 h at room temperature with the indicated primary antibodies (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>After rinsing with PBS three times, samples were then incubated with the appropriate secondary antibodies or conjugated phalloidin (Table S1) at room temperature for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Samples were then rinsed with PBS three times, and counterstained with DAPI for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Z-stack and cross-sectional images were obtained and processed using confocal microscopy (LSM 510 Meta, Carl Zeiss Inc., Thornwood, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Epifluorescence images were obtained using an Olympus BX60 microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Samples were prepared for transmission electron microscopy (TEM) analysis as described previously [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Briefly, samples were fixed with 3.7% formaldehyde, 1.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate, 5 mM CaCl2, and 2.5% sucrose at room temperature for 1 h and washed 3 times in 0.1 M cacodylate/2.5% sucrose (pH 7.4) for 15 min each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The cells were post-fixed with Palade's OsO4 on ice for 1 h, en bloc stained with Kellenberger uranyl acetate overnight, dehydrated through a graded series of ethanol, and then embedded in EPON. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Sections of 80-nm were cut, mounted onto copper grids, post-stained in 2% uranyl acetate and Reynolds lead citrate, and viewed using a Phillips EM 420 transmission electron microscope (FEI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Images were captured with an Olympic Soft Imaging Systems Megaview III CCD digital camera. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Hydrogel microfiber samples were first serially dehydrated in 50%, 60%, 70%, 80%, 90%, 95% and 100% ethanol for 15 min in each solution, critical point dried, and then sputter-coated with 8-nm thick Au/Pd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Samples were imaged on a field-emission SEM (JEOL 6700F, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Image and statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>All image analyses were performed on at least 60 measurements per condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Cytoskeletal alignment angle was calculated by fitting an ellipse to each cell using the LSM 510 software and measuring the angle between the long axis of each ellipse and the longitudinal axis of the microfiber, found by drawing a line at the edges of the microfiber in its image projection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>ECM angle of orientation was measured by drawing a line following the ECM deposition and finding the angle between the line and the longitudinal axis of the microfiber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Graphs were plotted with 5–95% confidence intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Unpaired two-tailed Welch-corrected t-tests were performed where appropriate (GraphPad Prism 5.01, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Significance levels were determined between samples examined and were set at *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, and ***p&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>ECFC attachment and alignment on fibrin microfibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>We have recently developed a new approach to create aligned hydrogel microfibers using an electrostretching process from various polymer materials [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Unique characteristics of the electrostretched hydrogel microfibers are the internal and topographical alignment of the fibrous structure, generated as a result of both electrical field and mechanical shear-induced polymer chain alignment [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the microfibers' diameter is controllable and uniform as a result of the bundling and processing of the individual nanofibers composing the microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>As fibrin gels have been extensively utilized to study microvasculature assembly [61]–[65], vSMC responses [66], [67] and multicellular organization [68], we chose to use fibrin as the matrix material to prepare hydrogel microfibers as a template for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Using the electrostretching approach, fibrin hydrogel microfibers were prepared and exhibited longitudinally aligned nanotopography ( Fig. 1A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This is an important feature as sub-micron (&lt;1 µm, but greater than 100 nm) scale topographic features have been shown to increase EC adhesion, migration, and orientation [4]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The seeding of ECFCs was facilitated by continuous rotation ( Fig. 1A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>After 24 hrs, ECFCs attached to the microfibers throughout the surface (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Within 5 days in culture, ECFCs were found to be elongated and aligned longitudinally with the microfibers as indicated by F-actin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>ECFCs covered the microfiber surface continuously, and exhibited typical membrane expression of endothelial markers VEcad and CD31, and cytoplasmic expression of von Willebrand factor (vWF,  Fig. 1B–D ), demonstrating that fibrin microfibers support the adhesion and culture of ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>ECM deposition from ECFCs on fibrin microfibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>While the importance of ECM deposition in vascular development has been recognized, few studies have looked at ECM production by the endothelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Previously we demonstrated that ECFCs deposit collagen IV, fibronectin and laminin in an organized web-like structure when cultured on Petri dishes [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>We therefore sought to characterize the ECM protein deposition by the endothelium on hydrogel microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>We found that ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers deposited laminin, collagen IV, and fibronectin after one day in culture ( Fig. 2A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>On Day 5, ECFCs completely covered the fibrin microfiber, and abundant ECM deposition was observed ( Fig. 2B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In contrast to what we observed previously on Petri-dishes [58], the ECM proteins deposited by ECFCs on hydrogel microfibers were organized; laminin, collagen IV, and fibronectin wrapped around the microfibers, perpendicular to the EC orientation, along the microfiber's circumference ( Fig. 2C  ; Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>S2; Video S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these ECM structures appeared to be distributed either below or among the ECFCs ( Fig. 2D–E , resembling the basal lamina found in native microvessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that similarly to what we observed on Petri-dishes [58], ECFCs did not express or deposit collagen I (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>ECFCs deposit ECM circumferentially on fibrin hydrogel microfibers. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs on fibrin microfibers after (A) 1 and (B) 5 days in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 200 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(C) High magnification confocal images of laminin, fibronectin and collagen IV wrapping around the fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>(D) TEM images of cross-sectional slices of a cell-fibrin microfiber construct after 5 days in culture (i–ii) with cells and (iii) without cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>(ii) is a higher magnification image for the boxed area in (i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>F  =  Fibrin; E  =  ECM; C  =  Cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>(E) Cross-sectional projections of confocal z-stack images of ECFCs on fibrin microfibers after 5 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>F-actin (phalloidin) is shown in green, ECM proteins (collagen IV, laminin, fibronectin) in red or magenta, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of nanotopography on microfiber surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A n≥2, B–E n≥5 per stain with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>ECM deposition from ECFCs on fibrin sheets and PES fibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It was previously demonstrated that line-grating topography influences EC adhesion, alignment, and elongation [4]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>To probe if the aligned nanotopography of the fibrin microfibers is responsible for ECFC alignment and coordinated deposition of laminin, collagen IV, and fibronectin, we first examined their deposition on flat (2D) fibrin sheets with a similar aligned nanotopography (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>S3A) as our hydrogel microfibers, but varying the dimensionality and cylindrical shape of our scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>As expected, ECFCs seeded on fibrin sheets were effectively aligned with the nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>However, the collagen IV, fibronectin and laminin produced by ECFCs exhibited a random organization, as opposed to the perpendicular orientation with respect to cell alignment observed in the 3D microfibers ( Fig. 3A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that the microfiber geometry may be crucial to the specific organization of ECM molecules secreted by ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Nanotopography and geometry differently effect ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of (A) ECFCs on 2D fibrin sheets after 5 days in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. n = 2 with duplicates (B) ECFCs on PES 3D fibrin-coated fibers with random non-aligned topography after 5 days in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. n≥4 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Actin filaments (phalloidin) are shown in green, ECM proteins (collagen IV, laminin, fibronectin) in red, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Box-and-whisker plots showing ECFC (C) and ECM (D) angle of orientation on PES and fibrin hydrogel microfibers after 5 days in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>(E) Standard deviation of ECM angle of orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 5–95% confidence intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Significance levels in the mean represented by ***p&lt;0.001. n≥2 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We next utilized electrospun PES fibers coated with fibrin to generate fibers that maintain the dimensionality and geometry of our fibrin microfibers but with a random nanotopography (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>S3Bi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Note that before coating the PES fibers with fibrin, the surface of PES fibers is smooth (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>S3Bii), however, an uncoated PES fiber is not bioadhesive, and we could not detect any ECFC attachment after seeding (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it does no present the same bioactive substrate to the ECFCs as the fibrin fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we coated the PES fibers with fibrin, resulting in the random, non-aligned nano-topography of coating presented in Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>S3Bi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Such PES fibers have a similar diameter (240±45 µm; data not shown) as fibrin microfibers and thus enable us to investigate whether the uniaxial alignment topography contributes to the unique cellular activity and ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were seeded according to the same protocol used for fibrin hydrogel fiber seeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Similarly as observed in  Fig. 2B , ECFCs completely covered the PES microfibers and deposited ECM molecules after 5 days of culture ( Fig. 3B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>While ECFCs grown on the PES fibers did not necessarily have a random orientation on the PES fibers, and in fact often exhibited a partial diagonal orientation ( Fig. 3C ), the ECFC-deposited ECM proteins were still found to wrap around the PES fiber in a similar manner to ECFC-deposited ECM on fibrin microfibers, as evidenced by measuring the angles between ECM ribbons and the fiber's longitudinal axis ( Fig. 3D ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Note that the average angle in both cases is close to 90°, demonstrating perpendicular alignment, and that the distribution (represented by the height of the boxes and also shown as standard deviation in  Fig. 3E ) is small, signifying most ECM ribbons had an orientation close to 90°. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>ECM organization: dependence on ECFC alignment and microtubule organization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We next sought to determine whether ECFC actin filament alignment and microtubule organization direct ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Towards this, ECFCs were seeded on fibrin microfibers and after 24 hrs an actin destabilization agent, cytochalasin D, was added to the culture media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>We found that the unique wrapping arrangement of the deposited ECM molecules around the fibrin microfibers was still present after 24 and 48 hrs of treatment ( Fig. 4A  and Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>S4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>No difference was found in the average angle of ECM orientation or in the variance of all angles measured ( Fig. 4D–E ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that ECM deposition was observed also in control treatments of ECFCs in Petri dishes (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>S4B) and that similar organization of wrapping ECM was observed when cytochalasin D was applied through the entire 3 days of culture (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>S4C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Disrupting actin and microtubule organization does not affect ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers for 24 hrs followed by treatment with (A) cytochalasin D or (B) nocodazole for 24 hrs and 48 hrs in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>(C) Low (left) and high (right) magnification of ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers for 72 hrs without drug treatment, serving as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>F-actin (phalloidin) is shown in green, microtubules (α-tubulin) in red, ECM proteins (collagen IV or fibronectin) in red or magenta, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm except of high magnification in C that is 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>(D) Box-and-whisker plots and (E) standard deviation of ECM angle of orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 5–95% confidence intervals. n = 2 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Likewise, when nocodazole, a microtubule polymerization disturbing agent, was added to the culture media at 24 hrs after ECFC seeding on microfibers, a similar ECM wrapping pattern was observed ( Fig. 4B  ; Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>S5A) even though microtubule formation was disrupted compared to samples with no drug treatment ( Fig. 4C ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Similarly, no difference was found in the average angle of ECM orientation or in the variance of all angles measured ( Fig. 4D–E ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>In addition, ECM deposition was also observed in the 2D control group with the same treatment (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>S5B), and similar organization of wrapping ECM was observed when Nocodazole D was applied through the entire 3 days of culture (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>S5C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Overall, while treatment of ECFCs seeded on the nanopatterned microfibers with either cytochalasin D or nocodazole effectively altered actin and microtubule organization, respectively, it did not alter the wrapping organization of the deposited ECM molecules as compared to control cultures ( Fig. 4 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Also, even after only 3 days of culture when the endothelium layer was not always confluent and therefore the cell density was lower, ECM organization was still found to be circumferential ( Fig. 4C–E , Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>S6), suggesting there is no effect of cell density on ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>ECM organization: dependence on microfiber curvature </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>As our data indicated that the ECM organization is independent of the cytoskeleton organization of the ECFCs, but is influenced by the geometry of the microtubular structure, we next tested the hypothesis that the diameter of the tubular structure modulates the ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We prepared hydrogel microfibers of different sizes by varying the collection time of the electrostretching process, thus changing the number of nanofibers in each microfiber bundle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Fibrin microfibers with an average diameter of 107.1±11.7 µm, 136.1±12.1 µm, 372.0±27.3 µm, and 443.4±30.6 µm were prepared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>These microfibers were processed similarly and thus exhibited similar nanotopographical alignment [59], inducing alignment of ECFCs with the longitudinal axis of the microfibers on all sizes (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>However, we noticed that decreasing organization of the ECM molecules was apparent on microfiber's with large diameters ( Fig. 5A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Measuring the angles between ECM ribbons and the microfiber's longitudinal axis revealed that microfibers with diameters smaller than ∼400 µm had average angles close to 90° with a small distribution, signifying perpendicular orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>On the largest diameter tested (443.4±30.6 µm), we observed a non-circumferential ECM organization as evidenced by a significant increase in the distribution of the angles between ECM ribbons and the microfiber's longitudinal axis ( Fig. 5B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Since values measured range from 0° to 180°, a perfectly random distribution of angles would average to the mean of 90° as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, a sample with ECM wrapping would have most of these values close to 90°, having a small variance compared to a sample presenting random ECM orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the largest microfibers resulted in ECM angles with a markedly higher standard deviation compared to the smaller microfibers ( Fig. 5C ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Microfiber curvature influences ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>(A) Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of collagen IV deposition on fibrin microfibers with different diameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 200 µm (B) Scatter plot and (C) standard deviation of ECM angle of orientation on microfibers with different diameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 5–95% confidence intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Significance levels in the distribution represented by ***p&lt;0.001. n = 2 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>We also observed that when collagen IV has a wrapping organization, the individual collagen nano-fibrils also seem to follow this macroscopic circumferential alignment at the nano-scale ( Fig. 2C, S2B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Further analysis revealed this was also true for microfibers of ∼105 to ∼370 µm, and that the largest microfibers tested (∼445 µm) did not have a distinguishable collagen nano-fibril orientation (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>S7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>vSMCs attachment and new ECM deposition on ECFC-seeded microfibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>One of the advantages of our fibrin microfiber system is the opportunity to co-culture vSMCs towards the study of their interactions with the endothelial layer as well as the deposition of ECM components that compose the tunica media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>vSMCs seeded on ECFC-coated fibrin microfibers attached and grew on the ECFC layer, forming a bilayer cellular construct ( Fig. 6A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Occasionally, vSMCs were found to have a random orientation on the structures ( Fig. 6A ), and in some instances they wrapped around the microfibers ( Fig. 6B . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>However, more often they aligned with the longitudinal axis of the microfibers ( Fig. 6C ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>More importantly, vSMCs cultured for 3 and 5 days deposited collagen type I and elastin ( Fig. 6D–G ), located beneath the vSMC layer and above SM22 negative cells, the ECFCs ( Fig. 6E, G ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081061-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081061.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Co-cultured vSMCs deposit new ECM. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of fibrin microfibers seeded with ECFCs followed by (A) co-culture of vSMCs for 2 days. n = 2 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 200 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Co-cultured vSMCs for 3 days showing (B) wrapping and (C) aligned arrangement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>(D) Collagen I deposited by co-cultured vSMCs after 3 days in co-culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(E) Cross-sectional projection of confocal z-stack images of vSMCs after 5 days in co-culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Arrowheads indicate SM22− cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>B–E n≥3 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>(F) Confocal z-stack image reconstruction and (G) cross-sectional projection of co-cultured vSMCs after 5 days in co-culture. n = 2 with quadruplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>SM22 is shown in green, CD31 in red, collagen I and elastin in red, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081061.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The cellular and ECM composition, as well as their specific structural organization, varies greatly in blood vessels of different type, size, and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>While postcapillary venules (10–30 µm) are formed by ECs and their basal lamina, along with scattered pericytes, and are semipermeable like capillaries [69], larger venules (larger than 50 µm in diameter) have a muscle layer and a thin adventitia [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Both arterioles of 100 µm to 300 µm in diameter and muscular arteries (300 µm to 1 cm) have an aligned endothelium sitting on its basal lamina, surrounded by a layer of connective tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>This layer is followed by a well-defined fenestrated internal elastic membrane (with ECM occupying void spaces in the fenestrae) and a developed tunica media composed of several layers of circumferentially oriented vSMCs and ECM (mainly collagenous and elastic fibrils). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>These arteries are the main vessels in charge of restricting blood flow to capillary beds via vSMC constriction in response to neural or chemical stimuli [69], [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Even though the ECM is known to be circumferentially oriented in the media, the specific alignment of each layer in the tunica intima remains unclear; several studies report a mix of circumferential orientation close to the lumen and axial orientation close to the media [10]–[12], [15], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>However, it is known that circumferentially aligned ECM is necessary for vessels to be able to withstand the circumferential stress resulting from the distending pressure of blood flow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>These facts highlight the importance of having both circumferential alignment of ECM and several layers of vSMCs, an aspect not found in current microvasculature models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the organization of other ECM components, such as fibronectin and laminin, remains widely uninvestigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Most current approaches for the in vitro study of the microvasculature in a 3D setting use hydrogels and scaffolds embedded with vascular cells, which are subject to spontaneous capillary bed formation [35]–[38], [60], [71]–[81], or use micropatterned hydrogels to generate organized microvasculature structures [46]–[48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>While these approaches are instrumental for studying angiogenic processes, they provide only partial control over the topographical cues presented to the cells by the ECM and possess limited opportunities to create and investigate multi-cellular vascular structures with proper ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Our goal in this study was to create a model of the microvasculature that recapitulated both cellular and ECM organization, towards the understanding of microvasculature development and utilization of the model for regenerative medicine applications in the future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Towards this, we utilized electrostretched microfibers designed to generate a micro-cylindrical mold with a line-grating nanotopography to enable both endothelial layer organization and co-culture of supporting mural cells such as vSMCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>We utilize microfibers with diameters ranging from 100 to 450 µm, corresponding to a poorly studied range of vasculature in the body, namely venules and arterioles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the existing models of microvasculature, the deposition and organization of ECM proteins by endothelial cells has not been studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the full investment of mural cells on the endothelium of microvascular models has been challenging, due in part to the use of endothelial-lined void spaces in most models [21], [22], which introduces a cell migration barrier for mural cell investment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In contrast, our model allows not only high resolution studies of both cell and ECM organization; it allows introduction of mural cells after endothelial layer formation and enables full investment of these mural cells, recreating the media layer of microvasculature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>We first demonstrate that the aligned microfiber bundles can be utilized as a cylindrical platform to control the organized adhesion of ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>ECFCs cultured on fibrin microfibers with diameter of 100–450 µm attached throughout the microfibers, creating a continuous monolayer over the entire microfiber with a distinctive elongated and mature morphology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The fibrin microfibers thus offer an innovative approach in which ECFCs are seeded on the surface of an electrostretched microfiber, as opposed to in the body of a nanofiber mesh, as conventional electrospun scaffolds have been used [38], [39], [82], [83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>This unique approach allows detailed control of the cellular assembly of microvasculature, as the fibrin microfibers present a blueprint with a unique aligned nanotopography around which ECFCs can adhere to. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Examining the ECFC-deposited ECM organization on the fibrin microfiber, we found that after 5 days in culture ECFCs deposit collagen IV, fibronectin and laminin wrapping in discrete circumferentially aligned segments on the microfibers, perpendicular to their macroscopic cellular alignment and intracellular cytoskeletal organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>This characteristic of ECFCs of depositing abundant ECM [58] that is assembled circumferentially on a micro-cylindrical mold recognizes an active role of the endothelium in the construction of the extracellular components of the microvasculature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that in longer period cultures of ECFCs on fibrin microfibers (i.e. &gt;10days) we observed full coverage of the structures by ECM (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>However, at this time point the initial circumferential organization of the ECM became impossible to analyze due to several layers of ECM being deposited on top of each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>For quantification purposes, we analyzed cultures of ECFC when ECM organization was evident, before full coverage was achieved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>As this is the first time that circumferential wrapping of ECM is reported by ECFCs, we proceeded to elucidate whether the ECFC alignment or the cylindrical structure and 3D aspect of the scaffold had a direct effect on ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Towards this, we designed two different systems that varied these parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The first scaffold used was a flat fibrin sheet with the same nanotopography as our original microfibers, varying therefore only the shape and geometry of the scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>ECFCs were found to align with the nanotopography of the fibrin sheets, but the ECM was deposited with no distinguishable organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The second scaffold used was a polymer fiber coated with fibrin, which maintains the microfiber's spatial geometry, but has a random surface topography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Here, while ECFCs were not induced to align with the fiber's longitudinal axis, they still deposited ECM wrapping circumferentially around the polymer fiber, similarly to ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Together, these results suggest that the cylindrical shape of the fibers, and not the cellular organization induced by the scaffold's nanotopography, is necessary for ECM circumferential deposition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The cytoskeleton is known to regulate endothelial alignment [4], [7] and drive angiogenic responses through ECM-interactions [27], [84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Thus, to further verify whether the ECFC alignment on the microfibers through actin and tubulin configuration is instrumental for their circumferential ECM deposition, we examined the effect of cytoskeleton re-arrangement of ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>We found that inhibition of neither actin filament nor microtubule polymerization affected ECM circumferential organization around the fibrin microfiber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>These results signify that ECM organized deposition from ECFCs is independent of their cellular organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, shorter culture time periods (day 3) which did not always have a confluent endothelium still resulted in wrapping ECM, suggesting an independence of cell density on ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Overall, even though we demonstrate that the aligned topography of the fibrin microfibers induces ECFC alignment, the findings that either ECFCs seeded on PES fibers or ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers with disrupted actin and microtubule organization still produce wrapping ECM suggest that ECM organization is regulated by 3D geometric sensing of curvature, rather than by the scaffold's nano-topography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Further studies are required to elucidate the underlying mechanism that modulates ECM expression and deposition by ECFCs and whether this is specific for progenitors or similar for mature ECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>We next set to elucidate whether the circumferential wrapping of the ECM depended on the curvature of the microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>While curvature of nano-scale features of ECM has been suggested to regulate cellular responses [85], its effect on cellular responses at the micronscale and during microvascular formation and organization has not been investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>As mentioned above, the electrostretching approach allowed us to generate microfibers with uniform and tunable diameters while preserving the aligned nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>As our focus is on the microvasculature, microfibers with diameter ranging from 100–500 µm were examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>We found that microfibers of up to ∼400 µm in diameter guide the organized wrapping of deposited ECM, while large microfibers resulted in a more random ECM organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>This observation is the first to suggest an effect of curvature on ECM organization, and opens the door to further studies to determine the underlying mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>These results further highlight the novelty of our system, which enables us to study the role of curvature at the microscale in contrast to studies using larger diameter templates to study ECM deposition of perivascular cells [86]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Thus, this work presents the unprecedented role of endothelium in producing circumferentially aligned ECM, and the first-time discovery of the effect of micron-scale curvature on ECM organization as deposited by vascular cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>These studies exemplify the potential of the newly developed model to date in the study of processes of microvascular development, and highlight the importance of correct ECM organization in the microvasculature, a characteristic often not analyzed in current models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge that ECFCs will initially have an inverted polarity due to the presence of the fiber where the luminal surface would be and an absence of a tunica media on top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The first step towards correcting this inverted polarity was obtaining full investment of vSMCs on top of the endothelium, which has been achieved, demonstrating the versatility of our system in allowing sequential and controlled introduction of mural cells and their deposited ECM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>For this, vSMCs were introduced into the model after 5 days of ECFC culture on the fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>First, vSMCs were found to attach to the ECFC-seeded microfibers with organizations that varied from the random, sporadic attachment typical of muscular venules to the circumferential wrapping observed in arterioles under physiological conditions [15]–[17], [19], [69], [70], but always in a multilayer configuration as opposed to the monolayer formed by the ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The different morphologies observed are most likely a result of lack of pulsatile flow, which has been shown to induce circumferential wrapping of SMCs in different studies [87], [88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the lack of internal pressure in our system is more conducive to the generation of muscular venules, which have much lower blood pressures compared to arterioles and contain randomly oriented vSMCs [69]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The next step in correcting the polarity of the ECFCs in our model is obtaining a defined lumen to create a hollow microvascular vessel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Still, another unique advantage of our fibrin microfiber scaffold is its biodegradability; fibrin can be easily degraded in a controlled manner using plasmin in conditions that do not affect cell viability [89]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Ongoing studies explore the degradation of the fibrin microfibers to generate a hollow microstructure with a defined lumen towards their use for applications in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Thus, our system further offers future opportunities to fully correct the initial ECFC polarity and to study flow-induced vSMC organization post fibrin core degradation </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Finally, vSMCs deposited collagen I and elastin on the ECFC-seeded microfibers, below the vSMC layer, and above the ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>These results signify that co-cultured vSMCs deposited ECM components that organize the subendothelial connective tissue and internal elastic lamina in between the endothelium and the tunica media, which is in accordance to native microvascular organization (endothelium/basal lamina – subendothelial connective tissue – internal elastic lamina – tunica media) [15]–[17], [19], [69], [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Overall, we demonstrate investment of vSMCs with ECFCs in our system and distinctive vSMC-ECM deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that we performed co-culture experiments in ECFC media, which was found to best support both ECFC and vSMC viability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>However, this medium is not optimized for vSMC culture and may reduce their deposition of ECM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>In fact, current studies in our lab focus on optimizing this phenomena and delineating the organization of vSMCs through their interaction with the endothelial layer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Collectively, we establish a novel in vitro model that recapitulates key aspects in the cellular and ECM organization of the microvasculature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Using this model we are able to guide organized microvascular structure formation, inducing endothelial cell alignment and elongation, and demonstrating circumferential deposition of ECM proteins by ECFCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Our system enabled the discovery of the role of vessel diameter on ECM organization during human microvascular growth, a biophysical phenomenon not studied to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we demonstrate the ability of our system to support a step-wise vascular formation process via introduction of perivascular cells at varying time points, a current challenge in microvascular tissue engineering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>This approach can be used towards the mechanistic understanding of human microvasculature assembly and stabilization in health and disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>ECFC attachment on fibrin microfibers. Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers after one day in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Actin filaments (phalloidin staining) are shown in green, CD31 in red, and nuclei are counterstained in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>ECM deposition by ECFCs on fibrin microfibers. High magnification confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs-seeded fibrin microfibers after 5 days in culture showing (A) wrapping ribbon-like organization of Collagen IV, laminin and fibronectin (in red; Scale bars are 50 µm) and (B) horizontal orientation of ECFCs with circumferential organization of the deposited Collagen IV (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrow indicates the direction of nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Topography of fibrin microfibers sheet and PES microfibers. (A) SEM of critical-point dried fibrin fiber sheets showing aligned topography on the surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Scale bar is 2 µm (B) SEM of critical-point dried PES microfibers (i) coated with fibrin showing random topography and (ii) uncoated showing smooth topography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Cytochalasin D treatment of ECFC-seeded on fibrin microfibers. Confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs seeded on (A) fibrin microfibers or (B) on Petri dishes for 24 hrs followed by treatment with cytochalasin D for 48 hrs in culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>(C) ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers and treated immediately with cytochalasin D for 72 hrs of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>F-Actin filaments (phalloidin) are shown in green, collagen IV in red, fibronectin or laminin in magenta, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of nanotopography on fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm in A–B and 100 µm in C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Nocodazole treatment of ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers. Confocal z-stack high-magnification image reconstructions of ECFCs seeded on (A) fibrin microfibers or (B) Petri-dishes for 24 h followed by treatment with nocodazole for 48 h of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>(C) ECFCs seeded on fibrin microfibers and treated immediately with nocodazole for 72 hrs of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>F-Actin filaments (phalloidin) in green, microtubules (α-tubulin) in red, Collagen IV in magenta, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrows indicate the direction of nanotopography on fibrin microfibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm in A (left), B, and C (right); 20 µm in A (right); and 100 µm in C (left). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>ECM deposition by ECFCs on fibrin microfibers after 3 days. Confocal z-stack image reconstructions at different magnifications of ECFCs-seeded fibrin microfibers after 3 days in culture showing non-confluent ECFCs with circumferential organization of the deposited Collagen IV (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrow indicates the direction of nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are (A) 200 (B) 100 (C) 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s006.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>ECM deposition by ECFCs on fibrin microfibers of different sizes. High magnification confocal z-stack image reconstructions of ECFCs-seeded fibrin microfibers with different diameter after 5 days in culture showing Collagen IV in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Yellow arrow indicates the direction of nanotopography. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s007.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s008"><label>Video S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>3D z-stack image sequence of a microfiber with ECFCs cultured for 5 days exhibiting wrapping collagen IV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>(AVI) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s008.avi"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081061.s009"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Reagents and Antibodies used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081061.s009.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Michael McCaffery from the Integrated Imaging Center at JHU for TEM processing and imaging; Joon Eoh from JHU for assisting with cell culture and sample preparation. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0081061-Jain1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>1 JainRK (2003) Molecular regulation of vessel maturation. Nat Med 9: 685–693.12778167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Carmeliet1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>2 CarmelietP, JainRK (2000) Angiogenesis in cancer and other diseases. Nature 407: 249–257.11001068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Hynes1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>3 HynesRO (2007) Cell–matrix adhesion in vascular development. JThromb Haemost 5: 32–40.17635706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Ranjan1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>4 RanjanA, WebsterT (2009) Increased endothelial cell adhesion and elongation on micron-patterned nano-rough poly(dimethylsiloxane) films. Nanotechnology 20: 305102.19581692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Liliensiek1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>5 LiliensiekS, WoodJ, YongJ, AuerbachR, NealeyP, et al (2010) Modulation of human vascular endothelial cell behaviors by nanotopographic cues. Biomaterials 31: 5418–5426.20400175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Bettinger1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>6 BettingerCJ, ZhangZ, GerechtS, BorensteinJT, LangerR (2008) Enhancement of In Vitro Capillary Tube Formation by Substrate Nanotopography. Adv Mater 20: 99–103.19440248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lu1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>7 LuJ, RaoMP, MacDonaldNC, KhangD, WebsterTJ (2008) Improved endothelial cell adhesion and proliferation on patterned titanium surfaces with rationally designed, micrometer to nanometer features. Acta Biomater 4: 192–201.17851147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-BruceAlberts1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>8Bruce Alberts AJ, Julian Lewis, Martin Raff, Keith Roberts, and Peter Walter (2002) Molecular Biology of the Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>New York: Garland Science. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Jain2"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>9 JainRK (2003) Molecular regulation of vessel maturation. Nature medicine 9: 685–693. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Schwartz1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>10 SchwartzSM, BendittEP (1972) Studies on aortic intima: I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Structure and permeability of rat thoracic aortic intima. The American journal of pathology 66: 241.5009972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Schriefl1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>11 SchrieflAJ, ZeindlingerG, PierceDM, RegitnigP, HolzapfelGA (2012) Determination of the layer-specific distributed collagen fibre orientations in human thoracic and abdominal aortas and common iliac arteries. Journal of The Royal Society Interface 9: 1275–1286. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Tsamis1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>12Tsamis A, Krawiec JT, Vorp DA (2013) Elastin and collagen fibre microstructure of the human aorta in ageing and disease: a review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Journal of The Royal Society Interface 10.. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Canham1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>13 CanhamPB, FinlayHM, DixonJG, BoughnerDR, ChenA (1989) Measurements from light and polarised light microscopy of human coronary arteries fixed at distending pressure. Cardiovascular research 23: 973–982.2611805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Finlay1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>14 FinlayH, McCulloughL, CanhamP (1995) Three-dimensional collagen organization of human brain arteries at different transmural pressures. Journal of vascular research 32: 301–312.7578798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Movat1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>15 MovatHZ, FernandoNVP (1963) The fine structure of the terminal vascular bed I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Small arteries with an internal elastic lamina. Experimental and Molecular Pathology 2: 549–563.14104191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Hibbs1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>16 HibbsRG, BurchGE, PhillipsJH (1958) The fine structure of the small blood vessels of normal human dermis and subcutis. American Heart Journal 56: 662–670.13582838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Fernando1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>17 FernandoNV, MovatHZ (1964) The fine structure of the terminal vascular bed: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>The smallest arterial vessels: Terminal arterioles and metarterioles. Experimental and Molecular Pathology 3: 1–9.14117849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Halloran1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>18 HalloranBG, DavisVA, McManusBM, LynchTG, BaxterBT (1995) Localization of Aortic Disease Is Associated with Intrinsic Differences in Aortic Structure. Journal of Surgical Research 59: 17–22.7630123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Moore1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>19 MooreDH, RuskaH (1957) The fine structure of capillaries and small arteries. The Journal of biophysical and biochemical cytology 3: 457–462.13438930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Gasser1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>20 GasserTC, OgdenRW, HolzapfelGA (2006) Hyperelastic modelling of arterial layers with distributed collagen fibre orientations. Journal of the royal society interface 3: 15–35. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Miller1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>21 MillerJS, StevensKR, YangMT, BakerBM, NguyenD-HT, et al (2012) Rapid casting of patterned vascular networks for perfusable engineered three-dimensional tissues. Nat Mater 11: 768–774.22751181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Zheng1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>22 ZhengY, ChenJ, CravenM, ChoiNW, TotoricaS, et al (2012) In vitro microvessels for the study of angiogenesis and thrombosis. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 109: 9342–9347. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Neumann1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>23 NeumannT, NicholsonBS, SandersJE (2003) Tissue engineering of perfused microvessels. Microvascular Research 66: 59–67.12826075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Yee1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>24Yee D, Hanjaya-Putra D, Bose V, Luong E, Gerecht S (2011) Hyaluronic Acid Hydrogels Support Cord-Like Structures from Endothelial Colony-Forming Cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Tissue Engineering Part A: Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>1351–1361. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-HanjayaPutra1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>25 Hanjaya-PutraD, YeeJ, CeciD, TruittR, YeeD, et al (2010) Vascular endothelial growth factor and substrate mechanics regulate in vitro tubulogenesis of endothelial progenitor cells. Journal of cellular and molecular medicine 14: 2436–2447.19968735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Meyer1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>26 MeyerGT, MatthiasLJ, NoackL, VadasMA, GambleJR (1997) Lumen formation during angiogenesis in vitro involves phagocytic activity, formation and secretion of vacuoles, cell death, and capillary tube remodelling by different populations of endothelial cells. 249: 327–340. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Bayless1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>27 BaylessKJ, DavisGE (2002) The Cdc42 and Rac1 GTPases are required for capillary lumen formation in three-dimensional extracellular matrices. Journal of Cell Science 115: 1123–1136.11884513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Bayless2"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>28 BaylessKJ, SalazarR, DavisGE (2000) RGD-Dependent Vacuolation and Lumen Formation Observed during Endothelial Cell Morphogenesis in Three-Dimensional Fibrin Matrices Involves the α&lt; sub&gt; v&lt;/sub&gt; β&lt; sub&gt; 3&lt;/sub&gt; and α&lt; sub&gt; 5&lt;/sub&gt; β&lt; sub&gt; 1&lt;/sub&gt; Integrins. The American journal of pathology 156: 1673–1683.10793078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Grant1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>29Grant DS, Tashiro K-I, Segui-Real B, Yamada Y, Martin GR, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Two different laminin domains mediate the differentiation of human endothelial cells into capillary-like structures in vitro; 1989 Feb 08. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Cell Press.pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>933–943. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Sacharidou1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>30 SacharidouA, StratmanAN, DavisGE (2011) Molecular mechanisms controlling vascular lumen formation in three-dimensional extracellular matrices. Cells Tissues Organs 195: 122–143.21997121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Davis1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>31 DavisGE, CamarilloCW (1996) An alpha 2 beta 1 integrin-dependent pinocytic mechanism involving intracellular vacuole formation and coalescence regulates capillary lumen and tube formation in three-dimensional collagen matrix. 224: 39–51. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>32Kim DJ, Martinez-Lemus L, Davis GE (2013) EB1, p150Glued and Clasp1 control endothelial tubulogenesis through microtubule assembly, acetylation and apical polarization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Blood. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-HanjayaPutra2"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>33 Hanjaya-PutraD, BoseV, ShenY-I, YeeJ, KhetanS, et al (2011) Controlled activation of morphogenesis to generate a functional human microvasculature in a synthetic matrix. Blood 118: 804–815.21527523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lutolf1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>34 LutolfM, HubbellJ (2005) Synthetic biomaterials as instructive extracellular microenvironments for morphogenesis in tissue engineering. Nature biotechnology 23: 47–55. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Moon1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>35 MoonJJ, SaikJE, PochéRA, Leslie-BarbickJE, LeeS-H, et al (2010) Biomimetic hydrogels with pro-angiogenic properties. Biomaterials 31: 3840–3847.20185173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Hielscher1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>36 HielscherAC, QiuC, GerechtS (2012) Breast cancer cell-derived matrix supports vascular morphogenesis. American Journal of Physiology - Cell Physiology 302: C1243–C1256.22277754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Soucy1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>37 SoucyPA, RomerLH (2009) Endothelial cell adhesion, signaling, and morphogenesis in fibroblast-derived matrix. Matrix Biology 28: 273–283.19375504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Pham1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>38 PhamQP, SharmaU, MikosAG (2006) Electrospinning of polymeric nanofibers for tissue engineering applications: a review. Tissue Eng 12: 1197–1211.16771634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Kumbar1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>39 KumbarSG, JamesR, NukavarapuSP, LaurencinCT (2008) Electrospun nanofiber scaffolds: engineering soft tissues. Biomed Mater 3: 034002.18689924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Aper1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>40 AperT, SchmidtA, DuchrowM, BruchHP (2007) Autologous Blood Vessels Engineered from Peripheral Blood Sample. European Journal of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery 33: 33–39.17070080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Gui1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>41 GuiL, MutoA, ChanSA, BreuerCK, NiklasonLE (2009) Development of decellularized human umbilical arteries as small-diameter vascular grafts. Tissue engineeringPart A 15: 2665–2676. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Swartz1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>42 SwartzDD, RussellJA, AndreadisST (2005) Engineering of fibrin-based functional and implantable small-diameter blood vessels. American Journal of Physiology-Heart and Circulatory Physiology 288: H1451–H1460.15486037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Kaushal1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>43 KaushalS, AmielGE, GuleserianKJ, ShapiraOM, PerryT, et al (2001) Functional small-diameter neovessels created using endothelial progenitor cells expanded ex vivo. Nature medicine 7: 1035–1040. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Cho1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>44 ChoS-W, LimSH, KimI-K, HongYS, KimS-S, et al (2005) Small-Diameter Blood Vessels Engineered With Bone Marrow–Derived Cells. Annals of surgery 241: 506.15729075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lheureux1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>45 L'heureuxN, PâquetS, LabbéR, GermainL, AugerFA (1998) A completely biological tissue-engineered human blood vessel. The FASEB Journal 12: 47–56.9438410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Baranski1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>46Baranski JD, Chaturvedi RR, Stevens KR, Eyckmans J, Carvalho B, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>(2013) Geometric control of vascular networks to enhance engineered tissue integration and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Miller2"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>47 MillerJS, StevensKR, YangMT, BakerBM, NguyenDH, et al (2012) Rapid casting of patterned vascular networks for perfusable engineered three-dimensional tissues. Nat Mater 11: 768–774.22751181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Zheng2"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>48 ZhengY, ChenJ, CravenM, ChoiNW, TotoricaS, et al (2012) In vitro microvessels for the study of angiogenesis and thrombosis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 109: 9342–9347.22645376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Melchiorri1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>49Melchiorri AJ, Hibino N, Fisher JP (2012) Strategies and Techniques to Enhance the In Situ Endothelialization of Small-Diameter Biodegradable Polymeric Vascular Grafts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Tissue Eng Part B Rev. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Fioretta1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>50 FiorettaES, FledderusJO, Burakowska-MeiseEA, BaaijensFP, VerhaarMC, et al (2012) Polymer-based scaffold designs for in situ vascular tissue engineering: controlling recruitment and differentiation behavior of endothelial colony forming cells. Macromol Biosci 12: 577–590.22566363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Gui2"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>51 GuiL, MutoA, ChanSA, BreuerCK, NiklasonLE (2009) Development of decellularized human umbilical arteries as small-diameter vascular grafts. Tissue Eng Part A 15: 2665–2676.19207043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>52 WuW, AllenRA, WangY (2012) Fast-degrading elastomer enables rapid remodeling of a cell-free synthetic graft into a neoartery. Nat Med 18: 1148–1153.22729285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Huynh1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>53 HuynhT, TranquilloR (2010) Fusion of Concentrically Layered Tubular Tissue Constructs Increases Burst Strength. Annals of Biomedical Engineering 38: 2226–2236.20431952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>54 LeeK-W, StolzDB, WangY (2011) Substantial expression of mature elastin in arterial constructs. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 108: 2705–2710. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Critser1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>55 CritserPJ, YoderMC (2010) Endothelial colony-forming cell role in neoangiogenesis and tissue repair. Curr Opin Organ Transplant 15: 68–72.19898235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Yoder1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>56 YoderMC (2009) Defining human endothelial progenitor cells. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis 7: 49–52. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Yoder2"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>57 YoderMC, MeadLE, PraterD, KrierTR, MrouehKN, et al (2007) Redefining endothelial progenitor cells via clonal analysis and hematopoietic stem/progenitor cell principals. Blood 109: 1801–1809.17053059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Kusuma1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>58 KusumaS, ZhaoS, GerechtS (2012) The extracellular matrix is a novel attribute of endothelial progenitors and of hypoxic mature endothelial cells. FASEB J 26: 4925–4936.22919069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>59Zhang SL, Barreto-Ortiz FS, Yu Y, Ginn B, DeSantis N, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>(2013) Creating Polymer Hydrogel Microfibers with Internal Alignment via Electrical and Mechanical Stretching. in submission </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-HanjayaPutra3"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>60 Hanjaya-PutraD, BoseV, ShenYI, YeeJ, KhetanS, et al (2011) Controlled activation of morphogenesis to generate a functional human microvasculature in a synthetic matrix. Blood 118: 804–815.21527523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Dickinson1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>61 DickinsonLE, MouraME, GerechtS (2010) Guiding endothelial progenitor cell tube formation using patterned fibronectin surfaces. Soft Matter 6: 5109–5119. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Bayless3"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>62 BaylessKJ, DavisGE (2003) Sphingosine-1-phosphate markedly induces matrix metalloproteinase and integrin-dependent human endothelial cell invasion and lumen formation in three-dimensional collagen and fibrin matrices. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications 312: 903–913.14651957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Davis2"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>63 DavisGE, BaylessKJ (2003) An Integrin and Rho GTPase-Dependent Pinocytic Vacuole Mechanism Controls Capillary Lumen Formation in Collagen and Fibrin Matrices. Microcirculation 10: 27–44.12610662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Bayless4"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>64 BaylessKJ, SalazarR, DavisGE (2000) RGD-Dependent Vacuolation and Lumen Formation Observed during Endothelial Cell Morphogenesis in Three-Dimensional Fibrin Matrices Involves the αvβ3 and α5β1 Integrins. The American Journal of Pathology 156: 1673–1683.10793078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Dickinson2"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>65 DickinsonLE, LutgebaucksC, LewisDM, GerechtS (2012) Patterning microscale extracellular matrices to study endothelial and cancer cell interactions in vitro. Lab Chip 12: 4244–4248.22992844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Ahmann1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>66 AhmannKA, WeinbaumJS, JohnsonSL, TranquilloRT (2010) Fibrin degradation enhances vascular smooth muscle cell proliferation and matrix deposition in fibrin-based tissue constructs fabricated in vitro. Tissue Eng Part A 16: 3261–3270.20536358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Long1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>67 LongJL, TranquilloRT (2003) Elastic fiber production in cardiovascular tissue-equivalents. Matrix Biol 22: 339–350.12935818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lesman1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>68 LesmanA, KofflerJ, AtlasR, BlinderYJ, KamZ, et al (2011) Engineering vessel-like networks within multicellular fibrin-based constructs. Biomaterials 32: 7856–7869.21816465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Standring1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>69Standring S (2008) Gray's anatomy. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Marieb1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>70Marieb E, Hoehn K (2010) Human Anatomy &amp; Physiology (8e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Boston, Massachusetts: Pearson Benjamin Cummings. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Benjamin1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>71 BenjaminLE, HemoI, KeshetE (1998) A plasticity window for blood vessel remodelling is defined by pericyte coverage of the preformed endothelial network and is regulated by PDGF-B and VEGF. Development 125: 1591–1598.9521897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Gerhardt1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>72 GerhardtH, BetsholtzC (2003) Endothelial-pericyte interactions in angiogenesis. Cell and Tissue Research 314: 15–23.12883993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Stratman1"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>73 StratmanAN, MalotteKM, MahanRD, DavisMJ, DavisGE (2009) Pericyte recruitment during vasculogenic tube assembly stimulates endothelial basement membrane matrix formation. Blood 114: 5091–5101.19822899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>74 WangZZ, AuP, ChenT, ShaoY, DaheronLM, et al (2007) Endothelial cells derived from human embryonic stem cells form durable blood vessels in vivo. Nat Biotech 25: 317–318. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Koike1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>75 KoikeN, FukumuraD, GrallaO, AuP, SchechnerJS, et al (2004) Creation of long-lasting blood vessels. Nature 428: 138–139.15014486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-MeleroMartin1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>76 Melero-MartinJM, De ObaldiaME, KangSY, KhanZA, YuanL, et al (2008) Engineering robust and functional vascular networks in vivo with human adult and cord blood-derived progenitor cells. Circulation Research 103: 194–202.18556575 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Levenberg1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>77 LevenbergS, RouwkemaJ, MacdonaldM, GarfeinES, KohaneDS, et al (2005) Engineering vascularized skeletal muscle tissue. Nature Biotechnology 23: 879–884. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Hielscher2"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>78 HielscherAC, GerechtS (2012) Engineering approaches for investigating tumor angiogenesis: Exploiting the role of the extracellular matrix. Cancer Research 72: 6089–6096.23172313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Soucy2"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>79 SoucyPA, WerbinJ, HeinzW, HohJH, RomerLH (2011) Microelastic properties of lung cell-derived extracellular matrix. Acta Biomaterialia 7: 96–105.20656080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-HanjayaPutra4"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>80 Hanjaya-PutraD, WongKT, HirotsuK, KhetanS, BurdickJA, et al (2012) Spatial control of cell-mediated degradation to regulate vasculogenesis and angiogenesis in hyaluronan hydrogels. Biomaterials 33: 6123–6131.22672833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-LeslieBarbick1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>81 Leslie-BarbickJE, SaikJE, GouldDJ, DickinsonME, WestJL (2011) The promotion of microvasculature formation in poly(ethylene glycol) diacrylate hydrogels by an immobilized VEGF-mimetic peptide. Biomaterials 32: 5782–5789.21612821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Christopherson1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>82 ChristophersonGT, SongH, MaoHQ (2009) The influence of fiber diameter of electrospun substrates on neural stem cell differentiation and proliferation. Biomaterials 30: 556–564.18977025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Chua1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>83 ChuaKN, ChaiC, LeePC, TangYN, RamakrishnaS, et al (2006) Surface-aminated electrospun nanofibers enhance adhesion and expansion of human umbilical cord blood hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells. Biomaterials 27: 6043–6051.16854459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-HanjayaPutra5"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>84Hanjaya-Putra D, Yee J, Ceci D, Truitt R, Yee D, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>(2009) Vascular endothelial growth factor and substrate mechanics regulate in vitro tubulogenesis of endothelial progenitor cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>J Cell Mol Med. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Vogel1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>85 VogelV, SheetzM (2006) Local force and geometry sensing regulate cell functions. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 7: 265–275.16607289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Grassl1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>86 GrasslE, OegemaT, TranquilloR (2003) A fibrin-based arterial media equivalent. Journal of Biomedical Materials Research Part A 66: 550–561.12918038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Lee2"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>87 LeeAA, GrahamDA, Dela CruzS, RatcliffeA, KarlonWJ (2002) Fluid shear stress-induced alignment of cultured vascular smooth muscle cells. J Biomech Eng 124: 37–43.11871603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>88 LiuB, QuM-J, QinK-R, LiH, LiZ-K, et al (2008) Role of Cyclic Strain Frequency in Regulating the Alignment of Vascular Smooth Muscle Cells In Vitro. Biophysical Journal 94: 1497–1507.17993501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0081061-Neidert1"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>89 NeidertMR, LeeES, OegemaTR, TranquilloRT (2002) Enhanced fibrin remodeling in vitro with TGF-beta1, insulin and plasmin for improved tissue-equivalents. Biomaterials 23: 3717–3731.12109697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
