<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3899050</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465697</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-37504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Response</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Fructooligosacharides Reduce Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 Pathogenicity through Distinct Mechanisms </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Effects of FOS on <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ortega-González</surname><given-names>Mercedes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez de Medina</surname><given-names>Fermín</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Molina-Santiago</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>López-Posadas</surname><given-names>Rocío</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>Tino</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martínez-Augustin</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelali</surname><given-names>Daddaoua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology II, Centre of networked Biomedical Research about Hepatic and Digestive Diseases, School of Pharmacy, University of Granada, Granada, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Environmental Protection, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas, C/Profesor Albareda 1, Granada, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Departments of Pharmacology, Centre of networked Biomedical Research about Hepatic and Digestive Diseases, School of Pharmacy, University of Granada, Granada, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Cascales</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Aix-Marseille Université, France</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>abdelali.daddaoua@eez.csic.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MG OMA DA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: OMA FSM TK DA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: DA OMA TK FSM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CM RP DP DA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: FSM OMA TK DA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e85772</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Ortega-González et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ortega-González et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Pseudomonas aeruginosa is ubiquitously present in the environment and acts as an opportunistic pathogen on humans, animals and plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We report here the effects of the prebiotic polysaccharide inulin and its hydrolysed form FOS on this bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>FOS was found to inhibit bacterial growth of strain PAO1, while inulin did not affect growth rate or yield in a significant manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Inulin stimulated biofilm formation, whereas a dramatic reduction of the biofilm formation was observed in the presence of FOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Similar opposing effects were observed for bacterial motility, where FOS inhibited the swarming and twitching behaviour whereas inulin caused its stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In co-cultures with eukaryotic cells (macrophages) FOS and, to a lesser extent, inulin reduced the secretion of the inflammatory cytokines IL-6, IL-10 and TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Western blot experiments indicated that the effects mediated by FOS in macrophages are associated with a decreased activation of the NF-κB pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Since FOS and inulin stimulate pathway activation in the absence of bacteria, the FOS mediated effect is likely to be of indirect nature, such as via a reduction of bacterial virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Further, this modulatory effect is observed also with the highly virulent ptxS mutated strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Co-culture experiments of P. aeruginosa with IEC18 eukaryotic cells showed that FOS reduces the concentration of the major virulence factor, exotoxin A, suggesting that this is a possible mechanism for the reduction of pathogenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The potential of these compounds as components of antibacterial and anti-inflammatory cocktails is discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors acknowledge financial support from FEDER funds and Fondo Social Europeo through grants from the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (grants SAF2011-22922, SAF2011-22812) the Andalusian regional government Junta de Andalucía (grant CVI-7335) and the Centre of Networked Biomedical Research on Hepatic and Digestive Diseases (CIBERehd) which is funded by the Carlos III Health Institute and the Ramón Areces Foundation, Spain. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Strains of P. aeruginosa are ubiquitously present in the environment [1], which is due to their capacity to colonize different ecological niches [2], [3] and metabolic versatility [4]. P. aeruginosa is an opportunistic pathogen able to infect different animals and plants [5], [6], being a frequent cause of hospital-acquired infections including ventilator associated pneumonia [7] and catheter infections in immuno-compromised patients. P. aeruginosa lung infections are the main cause of morbidity and mortality in cystic fibrosis (CF) patients [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The bacterium is highly resistant to antibiotic treatment and difficult to eradicate once established in the host [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>One of the important antibiotic resistance mechanisms is the formation of biofilms [10], hence a great deal of attention has been given to the study of the molecular mechanisms involved in its generation, maturation and dispersal [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that flagella and type IV pili-mediated motility are required for efficient biofilm formation [13]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Bacteria use different secretion systems to inject virulence factors into the cytoplasm of eukaryotic cells, leading to bacterial replication within macrophages and, consequently, evasion from the immune system [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In Gram-negative bacteria several secretion systems have been characterized, referred to as type I to type VI systems [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The type II (T2SS) and type III secretion system (T3SS) secrete the majority of known toxins [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>They differ in their molecular mechanisms and operate on several substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The secretion system type I is an ABC transporter composed of an ABC protein, a membrane fusion protein and an outer membrane protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This system transports various molecules of diverse nature such as ions, drugs, and proteins [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Similarly, type II and V secretion systems generally transport proteins to the surface of the host cell and are involved in the extracellular release of various toxins and hydrolytic enzymes such as exotoxin A, Las A, Las B, protease and elastase [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the type III secretion system (T3SS) injects proteins, small molecular weight compounds and hydrolytic enzymes into the cytosol of eukaryotic cells [23], which corresponds to a potent virulence mechanism shared by many pathogenic Gram-negative bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This protein injection in turn triggers a cytoskeletal reorganization of the host cell as shown by the inhibition of P. aeruginosa internalization upon incubation with cytochalasin D [24], which destroys microfilaments, thereby preventing further uptake of bacteria [16], [23], [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A significant number of natural compounds have been found to inhibit bacterial growth, although their mechanism of action remains unclear in most cases [26], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Here we report a study on the activity of the fructo-oligosaccharides (FOS) and inulin on P. aeruginosa proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Inulin is a linear polymer formed by 20 to over 60 β-2,1-linked fructose monomers with a terminal glucose residue, whereas FOS are short-chain oligosaccharides with the same structure but a maximal chain length of 2 to 20 monomeric units which are generated by hydrolysis of inulin [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Inulin is found in different nutrients such as wheat, onion, garlic and banana [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Inulin and FOS are considered prebiotics, based on the observation that they promote the growth of certain beneficial gut bacteria such as bifidobacteria [30], [31], but they have been also found to inhibit the growth of pathogenic bacteria such as Salmonella typhimurium [32], S. enteritidis [33] Listeria monocytogenes or the fungus Candida albicans [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In addition inulin and FOS have been found to have a beneficial impact on human health, including the stimulation of calcium, iron and zinc absorption [35] and the modulation of local and systemic immune responses [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Here we show that the addition of FOS to P. aeruginosa PAO1 cultures decreases growth and biofilm formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This effect appears to be specific for FOS since it was not observed following inulin treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, FOS reduces the cytokine response of rat primary monocytes to P. aeruginosa infection, an effect considered indirect since this oligosaccharide was found to activate the NF-κB pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Attenuated responses are observed also with the virulent ptxS mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Exotoxin A production is lowered by FOS treatment, suggesting that FOS may interfere with exotoxin synthesis and/or secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data suggest that FOS may be a useful component of drug cocktails for the treatment of P. aeruginosa infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Differential effect of FOS and inulin on the growth of P. aeruginosa PAO1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>As stated in the introduction, a number of natural compounds can either promote or slow down the growth of microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>To assess the effect of inulin and FOS on P. aeruginosa, growth curves were recorded in minimal medium M9 supplemented with citrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions only minor changes in the bacterial growth rate and yield were observed in the presence of 5–20 mg/ml inulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Namely, 5 and 15 mg/ml of inulin resulted in a slight to moderate stimulation of growth, whereas at the concentration of 20 mg/ml a slight reduction was noted (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Effect of inulin and FOS on the growth of P. aeruginosa PAO1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Growth curves in minimal medium M9 supplemented with 50(A) and FOS (B) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>As a control, growth in the minimal medium M9 supplemented with 20 mg/ml of goat milk oligosaccharides (OS) is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Growth curves were recorded at 37°C for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Representative data from one of three independent experiments with similar results are shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in the presence of 5–15 mg/ml of FOS a minor stimulation of bacterial growth was noted (Fig. 1B); however, at the concentration of 20 mg/ml a marked inhibition was observed (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Since inulin and FOS differ only in the carbohydrate chain length, this parameter appears to be central for antibacterial activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In comparison, a growth curve was recorded in the presence of 20 mg/ml of control goat milk oligosaccharides (OS), showing promotion of bacterial growth at the same concentration at which FOS inhibits growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In fact, both FOS and inulin (at 15–20 mg/ml) are able to support bacterial growth when M9 minimal medium is used (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Reduction of biofilm formation in the presence of FOS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>To assess the influence of FOS and inulin on biofilm formation, P. aeruginosa PAO1 was cultured in 24-well plates in the absence or presence of different concentrations of both compounds for 6 hours (Fig. 2A), followed by a quantification of biofilm formation. Fig. 2 B and Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>S1 show the relative amount of biofilm formation as a function of the inulin/FOS concentration (logarithmic scale). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>It became apparent that both compounds have opposite effects; whereas inulin stimulated biofilm formation, FOS had a concentration dependent inhibitory effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Fitting of data (Fig. 2B) resulted in an EC50 value of 2.1 mg/ml for FOS (inhibition) and 5.8 mg/ml for inulin (stimulation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Biofilm formation was almost completely inhibited at a FOS concentration of 4–8 mg/ml, which is in sharp contrast with inulin that produced a ∼10-fold enhancement at concentrations up to approximately 10 mg/ml. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Formation of P. aeruginosa biofilm. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A) Biofilm formation in the absence and presence of different concentrations of FOS and inulin in 24-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Biofilm formation was monitored in M9 minimal medium supplemented with 0.2% (w/v) glucose and casamino acids and quantified after 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>B) The relative amounts of biofilm formation in the experiments shown in Fig. 2A are plotted against the logarithm of inulin/FOS concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Data were fitted with the sigmoidal model of the ORIGIN software package to determine EC50 values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Data are the average of three independent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>C) Microscopic inspection of biofilm formation in the absence and in the presence of 20 mg/ml inulin or FOS at 2, 4 and 6 hours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, biofilms formed in the presence or absence of both compounds (at 20 mg/ml) were observed under the microscope (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To this end bacteria were grown in M9 minimal medium supplemented with 0.2% (w/v) glucose, 0.4% (wt/v) casamino acids and with inulin or FOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In control conditions clear biofilm formation was observed after 4 and 6 hours of culture, as expected (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained with 20 mg/ml of inulin, but the biofilm was more prominent after 6 h as compared to the control sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In contrast, while biofilm formation in the presence of FOS was comparable to that in control conditions after 4 hours, it was virtually absent at 6 h (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>FOS and inulin have opposite effects on bacterial motility </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>P. aeruginosa has been shown to exhibit three different types of motility, namely swimming, swarming and twitching [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Twitching motility across solid surfaces [39] has been found to be required for biofilm development [13], [40], as well as for a persistent colonization of lungs, and it is associated with virulence in corneal infection models [39], [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We have studied the effect of inulin and FOS at 5 mg/ml on P. aeruginosa bacterial motility on agar plates and in bacterial suspension (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Neither FOS nor inulin affected swimming behaviour (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, FOS inhibited both swarming and twitching motility, whereas inulin treatment resulted in the opposite effect, i.e. stimulation (Fig. 3B and C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Effects of FOS and inulin on the motility of P. aeruginosa. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Motility assays were carried out as described in materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Inulin or FOS at 5 mg/ml was present in the agar plates and in the bacterial suspensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A) Swimming assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>B) Swarming assays and C) Twitching assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Average values of the distances of bacterial migration are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Data are the average of three independent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± s.e.m., n = 6; *P&lt;0.05 vs without effectors (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Inulin and FOS reduce cytokine secretion in P. aeruginosa infected macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Tissue injury or infection results in the recruitment and activation of host immune cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Macrophages are the first immune cells likely to encounter P. aeruginosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The activation of macrophages is based largely on the recognition of pathogens by molecular pattern receptors, including Toll-like receptors (TLRs), such as TLR4 [16], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Macrophages can internalize and kill bacterial pathogens; however, during P. aeruginosa infections their role in pathogen sensing is of primary importance [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This in turn causes significant changes in gene expression and the secretion of proinflammatory cytokines IL-6 and TNF-α that recruit inflammatory cells in response to bacterial virulence factors, while IL-10 tends to mitigate this response [44]–[47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>These are among the main signalling mediators released by monocyte/macrophages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Initial experiments were carried out to establish the experimental conditions for the assessment of the effect of FOS and inulin on cytokine secretion (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were incubated with P. aeruginosa PAO1 and interleukin 6 secretion was measured at different time intervals (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Maximal secretion was observed after 4 hours of incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Therefore, these experimental conditions were used to quantify the effect of FOS/inulin on the secretion of IL-6, IL-10 and TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In the absence of bacteria (Fig. 4, column –PAO1), inulin and FOS had no significant effect on cytokine secretion, although a slight increase was noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>PAO-1 infection caused the expected significant increase in cytokine secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>This response was markedly attenuated for the three cytokines in the presence of FOS, while inulin caused exclusively a reduction in IL-6 levels (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>These data therefore show that the presence of inulin and particularly FOS reduced the inflammatory response of macrophages to bacterial infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Since FOS/inulin did not reduce the cytokine release in the absence of bacteria, our results suggest that the inhibitory effect of FOS is probably due to a direct interaction with P. aeruginosa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Effect of inulin and FOS on inflammatory response of macrophages against P. aeruginosa (WT). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were incubated with WT P. aeruginosa cells (ratio 1/5) for 4 hours in either the absence or the presence of 5 mg/ml FOS and inulin prior to the determination of IL-6 (A), IL-10 (B) and TNF-α secretion (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± s.e.m., n = 6–8; *P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage without bacteria and &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs WT in the absence of inulin or FOS (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Activation of the NF-κB signal transduction pathway is downregulated by FOS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) and the NF-κB signalling pathways are implicated in the production of TNF-α and IL-6 in macrophages [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In addition, it has been reported that P. aeruginosa infection is associated to stimulation of TLR4 receptors, leading to an activation of the NF-κB pathway [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To assess the impact of inulin and FOS on the inflammatory response, the role of the NF-κB and MAPK signalling pathways in the FOS-mediated modulation of macrophages was assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>One of the ways to activate NF-κB by extracellular stimuli involves the rapid degradation of IκB-α as a consequence of IκB-α phosphorylation at Ser32 by IκB kinase, which corresponds to IKK in the so-called canonical pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We studied the effect of inulin and FOS on the activation (phosphorylation) of IκB-α and MAPK, ERK, JNK and p38 by Western blot analysis in macrophages infected with P. aeruginosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 5A, neither FOS nor inulin affected the phosphospecific signal of the three MAPK, suggesting that they are not involved in the observed changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In contrast, FOS but not inulin reduced IκB-α phosphorylation, pointing to a modulation of the NFκ-B canonical pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>FOS but not inulin reduces the amount of phosphorylated IkB-α. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A) Macrophages were infected with P. aeruginosa in the absence or presence of either 5 mg/ml FOS or inulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>After 4 h growth Western blots were performed using cell extracts and the corresponding antibodies against ERK (Extracellular Regulated Kinase), p-ERK (the phosphorylated form of Extracellular Regulated Kinase), p-P38 (activated and phosphorylated form of P38 mitogen-activated protein kinases), p-JNK (Jun N-terminal kinases) and after 1 h for p-IκB-α (activated form in the NF-κB canonical pathway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As control, actin was quantified in all samples using an anti-α-actin antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Duplicate samples in the absence of added effectors and triplicate samples in the presence of FOS and inulin are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>B) NF-κB activation was determined by measuring the nuclear translocation of the p65 component, expressed as the OD450 nm. *P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage without bacteria and &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs WT in the absence of inulin or FOS (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the activation of the NF-κB transcription factor is associated with the nuclear translocation of the p65 component of the complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>To confirm the effect of inulin or FOS on nuclear NF-κB/p65 translocation, p65 was quantified by ELISA in cell nuclei following 1 h activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In contrast to inulin, FOS (5 mg/ml) effectively reduced NF-κB/p65 translocation (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the effect of FOS is associated with a minor activation of the NF-κB signalling pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The effect of FOS is observed in P. aeruginosa mutant strains with different degrees of virulence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Since the FOS-mediated inhibition of bacterial growth and biofilm formation may reduce virulence, we hypothesized that the response of eukaryotic cells to infection may be modulated by the presence of this oligosaccharide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Subsequent experiments were aimed at assessing the effect of FOS and inulin in two strains of P. aeruginosa showing different levels of virulence compared as compared to wild type strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We used mutants deficient in PtxS and PtxR, two transcriptional regulators that control the expression of the toxA gene, encoding the exotoxin A virulence factor [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Both, PtxR and PtxS play a role in regulating the activity from the PtoxA promoter [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Mutation of ptxS increases toxA expression by a factor of ∼4, whereas deletion of ptxR causes a ∼2-fold reduction [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The increase in toxicity of the ptxS mutant (Fig. 6A) is reflected in the colour of bacterial cultures due to the increased production of the bright blue-green siderophore pyocyanin, an important virulence factor of fluorescent Pseudomonads [52]–[54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In contrast the colour of the ptxR mutant is similar to that of the wild type strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Further, anti-exotoxin A western blot showed that ptxS mutant produces significantly more exotoxin A than the ptxR mutant (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the cytotoxic activity of P. aeruginosa on macrophages was analysed 4 hours after infection, using the Cytotox 96® non-radioactive cytotoxicity assay kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>As expected, cytotoxicity was highest for the ptxS mutant (Fig. 6C) where approximately 25% of cells died, followed by the wild type strain (10% of cell death) and the ptxR mutant for which no toxicity was detected (Figure 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The lactase dehydrogenase (LDH) is a marker for cytotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We have determined the LDH levels of 0.1–0.2 mU/µl in the absence of bacteria but in the presence of FOS or inulin (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Both compounds did not induce any significant changes in the LDH levels, indicating that they are not cytotoxic to macrophages under the conditions used (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Effect of wild type and mutant P. aeruginosa PAO1 on macrophages. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>A) Cultures of P. aeruginosa PAO1 and its mutants deficient in ptxS and ptxR were grown in M9 Minimum medium supplemented with 50 mM citrate for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The blue-green colour is indicative of an increased pyocyanin secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>B) Western blot determination of exotoxin A concentration secreted by P. aeruginosa WT and its isogenic mutants ptxS and ptxR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>C) The macrophage mortality induced by WT P. aeruginosa and its ptxS and ptxR mutants was measured by the total release of cytoplasmic lactate dehydrogenase (LDH). *P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage without bacteria and &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage with WT (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>As expected, the cytokine secretory response followed the same pattern, being higher with the ptxS mutant, followed by the wild type and lower for the ptxR mutant (Fig. 7) (Data from Fig. 4 are included for comparison) [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>For all three bacterial strains analysed, FOS caused a very pronounced reduction (Fig. 7), while inulin caused a more moderate reduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the FOS/inulin mediated reduction was more pronounced in the ptxS mutant than in WT strain, suggesting that virulent strains may be more sensitive to the effect of fructose oligosaccharides. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Effect of inulin and FOS on inflammatory response of macrophages against WT P. aeruginosa and its isogenic mutants ptxS and ptxR. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were incubated with WT and mutant P. aeruginosa cells (ratio 1/5) for 4 hours in either the absence or the presence of 5 mg/ml FOS and inulin prior to the determination of IL-6 (A), IL-10 (B) and TNF-α secretion (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± s.e.m., n = 6–8; *P&lt;0.05 vs WT in the absence of inulin or FOS; &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs ptxS mutant without effectors (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>P. aeruginosa employs a number of systems to secrete proteins which play different roles during infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>To analyse the role of FOS or inulin on P. aeruginosa virulence, exotoxin A was quantified in supernatants of bacterial co-cultures with eukaryotic cells as well as within eukaryotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>To achieve a good separation of eukaryotic cells from bacteria, we used the rat small intestinal cell line IEC18 that grows on surfaces and exhibits inflammatory responses [55], [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Bacteria are removed by a washing step with fresh PBS solution, leaving an intact IEC18 cell monolayer containing infecting Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Anti-exotoxin A western blot analysis showed that the addition of FOS and inulin to eukaryotic cells did not alter exotoxin A levels present in the culture medium (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In contrast, FOS was found to reduce intracellular exotoxin A levels in IEC18 cells co-cultured with P. aeruginosa, whereas no significant change was observed in the presence of inulin (Fig. 8A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that the type II-dependent exotoxin A secretion from P. aeruginosa to the cell cytosol is inhibited by FOS, presumably limiting its virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Because we cannot rule out the presence of extracellular, cell adherent bacteria in the sample, it may be possible that FOS also downregulates exotoxin A in extracellular Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085772-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085772.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>FOS reduces exotoxin A expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A) Western blot determination of the cellular concentration of exotoxin A in IEC18 cells following co-culture with P. aeruginosa in the presence and absence of FOS and inulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>B) Densitometric analysis of above data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Exotoxin A densities were corrected with those obtained for α-actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± s.e.m., n = 3; &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage/WT without inulin or FOS (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085772.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Prebiotics are defined as compounds that have beneficial effects on humans by altering the intestinal microbiota in a manner that is beneficial to health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of their action is not clear, but it is thought to involve preferential utilization of oligosaccharides by host-friendly bacterial species such as bifidobacteria or lactobacilli, indicating that prebiotic substances might have the capacity to protect against infections and reduce the presence of clinically relevant pathogens in the faecal flora [57], [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Another proposed mechanism involves enhanced bacteriocin secretion by lactobacilli [59], which in turn facilitates the incorporation of bacteria into a niche and inhibits the invasion of competing strains or pathogens, leading ultimately to a modulation of the microbiota and of the host immune system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the inhibition of pathogens by prebiotics is thought to be largely due to indirect effects [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>However, antimicrobial properties have been described for a number of oligosaccharides [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge this is the first report showing that FOS, one of the most studied and used prebiotics, has specific effects on P. aeruginosa PAO1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We were able to show that FOS (1) inhibits P. aeruginosa growth, biofilm formation and motility; (2) limits the P. aeruginosa evoked NF-κB dependent cytokine secretion in macrophages; and (3) decreases exotoxin A levels in P. aeruginosa infected IEC18 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These effects have also been observed for inulin, but in general the magnitude of the changes induced by FOS was superior to that of inulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the length of the oligosaccharide chains is an essential determinant for the magnitude of the biological activities observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This is exemplified by growth inhibition: both FOS and inulin can be used as carbon and energy source by P. aeruginosa and it is therefore not surprising to see a growth stimulation in the presence of up to 10 mg/ml of both compounds (Fig. 1 and data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>However, at a concentration of 20 mg/ml inulin had a very modest effect on growth which contrasts with FOS that caused a very significant growth inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with a biphasic response of P. aeruginosa to FOS/inulin: growth is stimulated at low concentrations of inulin and then inhibited to a certain extent; the same response is observed with FOS, but growth inhibition is clearly more pronounced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The control goat milk oligosaccharides did not produce any inhibition at similar concentrations, underlining the specificity of action of FOS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The variety of cellular processes modulated by FOS was a surprising finding and it is tempting to speculate that glycoside receptors may be involved in the recognition of FOS and that these receptors signal via different cascades modulating different cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Such a mechanism would be comparable to that for the sensing of other antimicrobial glycosides [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, biofilm formation is a major mechanism that confers bacterial resistance and biofilm induced antibiotics tolerance is of major clinical importance [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Currently significant research efforts are being made to identify compounds that interfere with biofilm formation, maturation and dispersion and to explore their effect in infection models [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Here we show that FOS and inulin have opposite effects on biofilm formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>While inulin caused a stimulation, a dramatic reduction was observed in the presence of FOS (Fig. 2 and Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, FOS did not appear to affect the early stages of biofilm formation since no significant changes were observed after 4 hours growth (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In turn, a dramatic reduction was seen after 6 hours (Fig. 2C), suggesting that FOS interferes with later stages of biofilm formation or triggers its dispersal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Further experiments to elucidate this point are underway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that these effects may alter P. aeruginosa virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In order to test this hypothesis, we infected rat primary monocyte cultures with PAO1 and measured cytokine release in the presence and absence of oligosaccharides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Monocytes display an enhanced release of cytokines in response to infection, which was shown to be chiefly dependent on NF-κB activation and p65 nuclear translocation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>These are early changes associated with modest cytotoxicity due to the short incubation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, treatment with FOS attenuated significantly all the steps of this response, i.e. secretion of IL-6, IL-10 and TNF-α, IκB-α phosphorylation and p65 nuclear translocation (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Inulin in contrast had a significantly more moderate effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In the absence of bacteria neither FOS nor inulin caused an effect on cytokine secretion and their long-term effect on macrophages (and intestinal epithelial cells) is an activation of the NF-κB pathway [65] and thus contrary to the oligosaccharide reduction of pathway activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Thus it follows that the inhibited NF-κB response in this case is likely to be of indirect nature, i.e. borne out of a reduced stimulation by P. aeruginosa infection, confirming our hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This may also explain why inulin failed to inhibit IκB-α phosphorylation, since it is also capable of activating this signalling pathway; however, it is unclear why inulin decreases IL-6 and IL-10 secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that MAPK is not involved in this process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We then investigated potential links between FOS and other determinants of P. aeruginosa virulence, such as the PtxS and PtxR regulators that modulate exotoxin A expression (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Mutation of the corresponding genes showed the expected alterations in cytokine release and cytotoxicity in infected monocytes, respectively, confirming previous observations [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>These changes correlated with toxA expression, since the highest cytokine secretion/toxA transcription was observed in the ptxS mutant, followed by the WT strain and the ptxR mutant [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>It is therefore likely that exotoxin A plays a role in stimulating cytokine secretion in the host cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The main finding of this series of experiments is that FOS exerts its modulatory effects also on the more virulent ptxS mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Of note, the effect of inulin was somewhat increased compared to that on the wild type, although always lower than that of FOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Our results therefore suggest that FOS effectively reduces the virulence of 3 different strains of P. aeruginosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Modulation of exotoxin A expression or transport can probably be associated with this effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>P. aeruginosa is an opportunistic pathogen and can infect immunocompromised individuals at different sites such as the respiratory tract, intestine, skin, urinary tract, and wounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The severity of the opportunistic infection depends to a great extent on the virulence factors expressed by the bacterium, which in turn influence cytotoxicity and antibiotic resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>As a result P. aeruginosa infections are notoriously difficult to treat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Several classes of antibiotics including cephalosporins, penicillins, carbapenems, quinolones and aminoglycosides are currently been used to combat P. aeruginosa clinically, but specific sensitivity testing is mandatory [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that FOS may be a useful component of a drug cocktail to combat P. aeruginosa infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, it appears also plausible to use FOS in a prophylactic context to prevent gastrointestinal infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Oral FOS supplements are currently been used to prevent gastrointestinal infections [67], which implies that the oral route may be also valid to administer FOS to fight Pseudomonas infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>However, any clinical application will require an extensive study of the potential effects of FOS on the human body which are issues that are to be addressed in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Wistar rats (200–250 g) obtained from the Animal Service Laboratory of the University of Granada (Spain) were used, housed in macrolon cages, and maintained in air-conditioned animal quarters with a 12-h light-dark cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Rats were given free access to tap water and food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>This study was carried out in accordance with the Directive for the Protection of Vertebrate Animals used for Experimental and other Scientific Purposes of the European Union (86/609/EEC) and the animal protocol used has been approved by the ethics committee of the Granada University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Bacterial strains used in this study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>P. aeruginosa PAO1 and its mutants deficient in ptxS and ptxR obtained through insertion of streptomycin and tetracycline cassettes, respectively [51], were grown in LB medium or M9 minimal medium (Na2HPO4: 6 g/l; KH2PO4: 3 g/l; NaCl: 0.5 g/l; NH4Cl: 1 g/l, 1 mM MgSO4, 0.3 mM CaCl2 and 0.2 ml/l of 1% ferric ammonium citrate) [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>When required, antibiotics were added to the culture medium to reach a final concentration of 50 µg/ml ampicillin, 50 µg/ml streptomycin and 30 µg/ml tetracycline. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Chemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Inulin and FOS were provided by BENEO-Orafti (Tienen, Belgium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>FOS and inulin were kindly provided by BENEO Orafti® (Tienen, Belgium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Orafti® GR (inulin) is a food ingredient consisting mainly of chicory root inulin, a mixture of oligo- and polysaccharides which are composed of fructose units linked together by β(2-1) linkages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Almost every molecule is terminated by a glucose unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The total number of fructose or glucose units ( = Degree of Polymerization or DP) of chicory inulin ranges mainly between 2 and 60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Orafti® P95 oligofructose (FOS) is produced by the partial enzymatic hydrolysis of chicory-derived inulin, consisting mainly of molecules with DP between 2 and 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Solutions were made at 200 g/l in M9 minimal medium and, in the case of eukaryotic cell cultures, in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) containing fetal bovine serum (10%), 2 mM L-glutamine, and 2.5 mg/mL amphotericin B, all provided by Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Solutions were filtered using 0.22 µm cut-off filters and aliquots were stored at −20°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The goat milk oligosaccharides (OS) were obtained according to the method described in [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>A product containing &gt;80% of the original oligosaccharide content, only 5% (w/w) of lactose and virtually salt free, was obtained and used to carry out all the experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Effects of inulin and FOS on P. aeruginosa growth </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Individual colonies of P. aeruginosa PAO1 were picked from the surface of freshly grown LB plates and grown overnight in M9 minimum medium (supplemented with 5 mM of citrate) at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The overnight culture was diluted with fresh M9 minimum medium to an OD660 nm of 0.05 and 96 well flat-bottomed polystyrene microtiter plates were filled with 180 µl of this cellular suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Then, 20 µl of either inulin or FOS were added to reach final concentrations of 5, 15 and 20 mg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Plates were incubated at 37°C under continuous agitation in a Bioscreen C MBR analyser FP-1100-C (OY Growth Curves Ab Ltd., Raisio, Finland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The turbidity was measured using a wideband filter at 420–660 nm every 60 minutes over a 24 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The measurements at 580 nm were used to generate growth curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Some cultures were carried out with the same medium without citrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Semiquantitative determination of biofilm formation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Semiquantitative determination of biofilm formation was performed as described [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Experiments were conducted in 24 well flat-bottomed polystyrene microtiter plates in M9 minimal medium supplemented with 0.2% (w/v) of glucose and 0.4% (w/v) casamino acids in the absence and in the presence of different concentrations (up to 20 mg/ml) of inulin or FOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Biofilm formation was quantified after 6 h by staining with crystal violet following the method described in [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The structure of biofilms was observed under contrast-phase microscopy using a Zeiss Axioscope fluorescence microscope coupled to a Nikon DSS-Mc CCD camera and a 100-fold magnifier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Data reported are means from two independent experiments each conducted in quadruplet repeats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Motility assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Assays were carried out to determine the effect of inulin and FOS (each at a concentration of 5 mg/ml) on swimming, twitching and swarming. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In all assays these compounds were added at identical concentrations to the bacterial suspension in the plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>For swimming assays bacteria were placed with the help of a sterile tooth-pick at the centre of plates containing a 5 mm layer of LB medium with 0.3% (w/v) Bacto agar, 0.2% casamino acids (w/v) and 30 mM glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 h and the radial diffusion of bacteria, due to swimming, was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>To monitor twitching motility bacteria were placed with a toothpick into a 2 mm thick layer containing 1.5% (w/v) Bacto agar, 0.2% (w/v) casamino acids and 30 mM glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>After incubation for 24 h at 37°C, the expansion of bacteria on the plate was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>For swarming assays 5 µl of an overnight culture of bacteria were placed into the centre of swarm plates, which are made of 0.5% (w/v) Bacto agar supplement with 0.2% (w/v) casamino acids and 30 mM glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 h, followed by an inspection of the bacterial surface movement [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>All the motility assays were performed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Macrophage cell isolation by magnetic activated cell sorting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Female Wistar rats were sacrificed by cervical dislocation and the spleen was extracted aseptically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Cell suspensions were obtained by disrupting the tissues between dissecting forceps in medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation (1500×rpm/5 min), cells were cleared of erythrocytes by resuspension in hypotonic lysis buffer (15 mM NH4Cl, 10 mM KHCO3, 0.1 mM Na2EDTA, pH 7.3) for 30 min on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Mononuclear cells were washed and resuspended in MACs buffer (PBS containing 0.5% (w/v) BSA, 2 mM EDTA, pH 7.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>To obtain a monocellular suspension, cells were passed through 70 µm nylon mesh prior to magnetic labelling and subsequently isolated by negative selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>To remove lymphocytes, CD161.1-biotin (1∶200), CD45RA-PE (1∶200) and CD3 (1∶150) (Biosciences), were added and incubated at 4°C for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed and sedimented by centrifugation at 1500×rpm for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>After resuspension in MACs buffer, 25 µl of each antibiotin Microbeads and anti-PE-microbeads (Miltenyi Biotec), were added and the resulting suspension incubated at 4°C during 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed, centrifuged and dissolved in DMEM medium (Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>CD161.1+, CD45RA+ and CD3+ cells were discarded using an LD column (Miltenyi Biotec). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Macrophages in the flow-through were centrifuged at 1500×rpm for 5 min and resuspended in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM Sigma ®) supplemented with 10% FBS (sigma), 2.5 mg/L amphotericin B and 2 mM L-glutamine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Measurement of inulin- and FOS-induced changes in cytokine secretion from macrophages following infection by P. aeruginosa PAO1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>For the determination of cytokine levels the macrophage suspensions (106 cells/ml DMEM medium) were co-cultured with P. aeruginosa and incubated with 5 mg/ml FOS or inulin for 4 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Following centrifugation at 4°C and 10.000×rpm for 5 min, the resulting supernatants were frozen at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Aliquots were thawed and cytokine levels determined using ELISA-based kits (BD Biosciences, Erembodegem, Belgium) following the protocol provided by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>In addition, macrophage cells were used for the quantification of phosphorylated IκB-α and MAP kinases by Western blot determination as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Western blot </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>For the detection of ERK, p-ERK, p-P38, p-JNK and phosphorylated IκB-P, cells were homogenized in lysis buffer (PBS containing 0.1% (w/v) SDS, 0.1% (w/v) sodium deoxycholate, 1% (v/v) Triton X-100) with protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma) 1∶100 (v/v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, homogenates were sonicated and centrifuged 7000× g for 5 min at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Protein concentrations were determined using the Bicinchoninic acid assay [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Samples were boiled in 5× Laemmli buffer (220 mM Tris, 312 µM SDS, 50% (v/v) glycerol, 1% (v/v) 2-mercaptoethanol, 22.5 mM EDTA, pH 6.8, containing traces of bromphenol blue) for 5 min, separated by SDS-PAGE, electroblotted to PVDF membranes (Millipore, Madrid, Spain), and exposed to the primary antibodies against ERK, p-ERK (both from Sigma), p-P38, p-JNK and phosphorylated IkB-P, respectively (all three from Cell signalling, Danvers, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Prior to exposure to the secondary IgG Peroxidase antibody (anti-mouse IgG for ERK and p-ERK, anti-rabit IgG for p-P38, p-JNK and p-IkB, (Sigma) the bands were visualized by enhanced chemiluminescence (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA) and quantified with the NIH software (Scion Image). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Determination of the NF-κB p65 subunit in macrophages nuclear extracts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were co-cultured with P. aeruginosa with a 1∶5 ratio and incubated with FOS (5 mg/ml) or inulin (5 mg/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>After 1 h, nuclear extracts were obtained using a nuclear extract kit (Active Motif, Belgium) and NF-κB activation was determined by quantifying the p65 component using a TransAM kit following the protocols recommended by the manufacturers (Active Motif, Belgium). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxicity Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Measurement of P. aeruginosa induced cytotoxicity in macrophages: Macrophages were incubated with P. aeruginosa with a ratio of 1∶5 for 4 hours and the percentage of cytotoxicity was determinate using cytotox 96 non-radioactive cytotoxicity assay kit following the protocols recommended by the manufacturers (Promega) which evaluates cytotoxicity by assessing the total release of cytoplasmic lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), by the calorimetric detection, into culture medium as a consequence of damaged cell membranes [74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Determination of exotoxin A concentration in rat IEC18 cells infected by P. aeruginosa PAO1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>IEC18 cells were cultured in 6 well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>At confluence IEC18 cells were infected with P. aeruginosa at a ratio of 5 bacterial cells per eukaryotic cell in the absence and in the presence of 5 mg/ml FOS or inulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Plates containing cells were washed 3 times with PBS and incubated with gentamicin at 100 µg/ml for 1 h to eliminate bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, plates were washed 3 times with PBS prior to cell collection using RIPA buffer [25 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.2, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% sodium deoxycholate and 0.1% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)] containing a protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Proteins were extracted for Western blot analysis, as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Western blot were carried out as outlined above using the Exotoxin A antibody (Sigma) at a 1∶2.000 dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Following overnight incubation with the primary antibody the membrane was incubated with the secondary IgG Peroxidase anti-rabbit antibody (Sigma) at a 1∶3.000 dilution for two hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The bands were detected by enhanced chemiluminescence (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA) and quantified with NIH software (Scion Image). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>All results are expressed as means with the corresponding standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Differences among means were analysed for statistical significance by a one-way ANOVA analysis and a posteriori least significance test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>All analyses were carried out using the SigmaStat 2.03 program (Jandel Corporation, San Rafael, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Concentration-response curves were fitted to a logarithmic curve when possible with Origin 7.0 (OriginLab Corporation, Northampton, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered significant at P&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0085772.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The OD at 560 nm of crystal violet (CV) stained and resuspended bacteria from biofilm are given. Shown are means and standard deviations with n = 3–6; *P&lt;0.05 vs WT in the absence of inulin or FOS (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The densitometric analysis of experiments is shown in Fig. 2A. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0085772.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0085772.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Measurement of interleukin-6 secretion of macrophages in the presence of WT  P. aeruginosa  PAO1 and its  ptxS  and  ptxR  mutants. The macrophage/bacteria ratio was of 1∶5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Experimental conditions involving incubation for 4 hours were subsequently used to assess the effect of FOS and inulin on interleukin secretion as reported in Fig. 4 and 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± s.e.m., n = 3; *P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage without bacteria and &amp;P&lt;0.05 vs macrophage with WT (ANOVA followed by least significance tests). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0085772.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>We thank Juan Luis Ramos for critical reading of this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0085772-Green1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>1 GreenSK, SchrothMN, ChoJJ, KominosSK, Vitanza-jackVB (1974) Agricultural plants and soil as a reservoir for Pseudomonas aeruginosa . Appl Microbiol 28: 987–991.4217591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Perkins1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>2 PerkinsSD, WoeltjeKF, AngenentLT (2010) Endotracheal tube biofilm inoculation of oral flora and subsequent colonization of opportunistic pathogens. Int J Med Microbiol 300: 503–511.20510651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Walker1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>3 WalkerTS, BaisHP, DezielE, SchweizerHP, RahmeLG, et al (2004)  Pseudomonas aeruginosa-plant root interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Pathogenicity, biofilm formation, and root exudation. Plant Physiol 134: 320–331.14701912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Oberhardt1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>4 OberhardtMA, PuchalkaJ, FryerKE, Martins dos SantosVA, PapinJA (2008) Genome-scale metabolic network analysis of the opportunistic pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1. J Bacteriol 190: 2790–2803.18192387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Cao1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>5 CaoH, BaldiniRL, RahmeLG (2001) Common mechanisms for pathogens of plants and animals. Annu Rev Phytopathol 39: 259–284.11701866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Rahme1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>6 RahmeLG, StevensEJ, WolfortSF, ShaoJ, TompkinsRG, et al (1995) Common virulence factors for bacterial pathogenicity in plants and animals. Science 268: 1899–1902.7604262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Chastre1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>7 ChastreJ, FagonJY (2002) Ventilator-associated pneumonia. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 165: 867–903.11934711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hoiby1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>8 HoibyN (2005) Bacterial meningitis. Ugeskr Laeger 167: 2429–2430. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hoiby2"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>9 HoibyN, CiofuO, BjarnsholtT (2010)  Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms in cystic fibrosis. Future Microbiol 5: 1663–1674.21133688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hoiby3"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>10 HoibyN, Krogh JohansenH, MoserC, SongZ, CiofuO, et al (2001)  Pseudomonas aeruginosa and the in vitro and in vivo biofilm mode of growth. Microbes Infect 3: 23–35.11226851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Stoodley1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>11 StoodleyP, SauerK, DaviesDG, CostertonJW (2002) Biofilms as complex differentiated communities. Annu Rev Microbiol 56: 187–209.12142477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Flemming1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>12 FlemmingHC, NeuTR, WozniakDJ (2007) The EPS matrix: the “house of biofilm cells”. J Bacteriol 189: 7945–7947.17675377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Klausen1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>13 KlausenM, HeydornA, RagasP, LambertsenL, Aaes-JorgensenA, et al (2003) Biofilm formation by Pseudomonas aeruginosa wild type, flagella and type IV pili mutants. Mol Microbiol 48: 1511–1524.12791135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Giltner1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>14 GiltnerCL, van SchaikEJ, AudetteGF, KaoD, HodgesRS, et al (2006) The Pseudomonas aeruginosa type IV pilin receptor binding domain functions as an adhesin for both biotic and abiotic surfaces. Mol Microbiol 59: 1083–1096.16430686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-OToole1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>15 O'TooleGA, KolterR (1998) Initiation of biofilm formation in Pseudomonas fluorescens WCS365 proceeds via multiple, convergent signalling pathways: a genetic analysis. Mol Microbiol 28: 449–461.9632250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Coburn1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>16 CoburnB, SekirovI, FinlayBB (2007) Type III secretion systems and disease. Clin Microbiol Rev 20: 535–549.17934073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Durand1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>17 DurandE, VergerD, RegoAT, ChandranV, MengG, et al (2009) Structural biology of bacterial secretion systems in gram-negative pathogens–potential for new drug targets. Infect Disord Drug Targets 9: 518–547.19594425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Bleves1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>18 BlevesS, ViarreV, SalachaR, MichelGP, FillouxA, et al (2010) Protein secretion systems in Pseudomonas aeruginosa: A wealth of pathogenic weapons. Int J Med Microbiol 300: 534–543.20947426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Jyot1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>19 JyotJ, BalloyV, JouvionG, VermaA, TouquiL, et al (2011) Type II secretion system of Pseudomonas aeruginosa: in vivo evidence of a significant role in death due to lung infection. J Infect Dis 203: 1369–1377.21502078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Durand2"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>20 DurandE, BernadacA, BallG, LazdunskiA, SturgisJN, et al (2003) Type II protein secretion in Pseudomonas aeruginosa: the pseudopilus is a multifibrillar and adhesive structure. J Bacteriol 185: 2749–2758.12700254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Sandkvist1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>21 SandkvistM (2001) Type II secretion and pathogenesis. Infect Immun 69: 3523–3535.11349009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Cianciotto1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>22 CianciottoNP (2005) Type II secretion: a protein secretion system for all seasons. Trends Microbiol 13: 581–588.16216510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hauser1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>23 HauserAR (2009) The type III secretion system of Pseudomonas aeruginosa: infection by injection. Nat Rev Microbiol 7: 654–665.19680249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Fleiszig1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>24 FleiszigSM, ZaidiTS, PierGB (1995)  Pseudomonas aeruginosa invasion of and multiplication within corneal epithelial cells in vitro . Infect Immun 63: 4072–4077.7558321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Parsot1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>25 ParsotC (2009)  Shigella type III secretion effectors: how, where, when, for what purposes? Curr Opin Microbiol 12: 110–116.19157960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Amer1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>26 AmerLS, BishopBM, van HoekML (2010) Antimicrobial and antibiofilm activity of cathelicidins and short, synthetic peptides against Francisella . Biochem Biophys Res Commun 396: 246–251.20399752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Periti1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>27 PeritiP, MazzeiT, MiniE, NovelliA (1992) Pharmacokinetic drug interactions of macrolides. Clin Pharmacokinet 23: 106–131.1511528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Scott1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>28 ScottKP, MartinJC, ChassardC, ClergetM, PotrykusJ, et al (2011) Protective response to subunit vaccination against intranasal Burkholderia enzymes in the utilization of inulin and starch. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 108: 4672–4679.20679207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Lattimer1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>29 LattimerJM, HaubMD (2010) Effects of dietary fiber and its components on metabolic health. Nutrients 2: 1266–1289.22254008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Gibson1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>30 GibsonGR, BeattyER, WangX, CummingsJH (1995) Selective stimulation of bifidobacteria in the human colon by oligofructose and inulin. Gastroenterology 108: 975–982.7698613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Bosscher1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>31 BosscherD, Van LooJ, FranckA (2006) Inulin and oligofructose as prebiotics in the prevention of intestinal infections and diseases. Nutr Res Rev 19: 216–226.19079887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Velez1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>32 VelezE, CastilloN, MesonO, GrauA, Bibas BonetME, et al (2013) Study of the effect exerted by fructo-oligosaccharides from yacon (Smallanthus sonchifolius) root flour in an intestinal infection model with Salmonella Typhimurium . Br J Nutr 109: 1971–1979.23137694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Babu1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>33 BabuUS, SommersK, HarrisonLM, BalanKV (2012) Effects of fructooligosaccharide-inulin on Salmonella-killing and inflammatory gene expression in chicken macrophages. Vet Immunol Immunopathol 149: 92–96.22627194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Buddington1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>34 BuddingtonKK, DonahooJB, BuddingtonRK (2002) Dietary oligofructose and inulin protect mice from enteric and systemic pathogens and tumor inducers. J Nutr 132: 472–477.11880573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Bosscher2"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>35 BosscherD, Van Caillie-BertrandM, Van CauwenberghR, DeelstraH (2003) Availabilities of calcium, iron, and zinc from dairy infant formulas is affected by soluble dietary fibers and modified starch fractions. Nutrition 19: 641–645.12831951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hosono1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>36 HosonoA, OzawaA, KatoR, OhnishiY, NakanishiY, et al (2003) Dietary fructooligosaccharides induce immunoregulation of intestinal IgA secretion by murine Peyer's patch cells. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 67: 758–764.12784615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Verstraeten1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>37 VerstraetenN, BraekenK, DebkumariB, FauvartM, FransaerJ, et al (2008) Living on a surface: swarming and biofilm formation. Trends Microbiol 16: 496–506.18775660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Bradley1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>38 BradleyDE (1980) A function of Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 polar pili: twitching motility. Can J Microbiol 26: 146–154.6105908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Mattick1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>39 MattickJS (2002) Type IV pili and twitching motility. Annu Rev Microbiol 56: 289–314.12142488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Chiang1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>40 ChiangP, BurrowsLL (2003) Biofilm formation by hyperpiliated mutants of Pseudomonas aeruginosa . J Bacteriol 185: 2374–2378.12644510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-OToole2"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>41 O'TooleGA, KolterR (1998) Flagellar and twitching motility are necessary for Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm development. Mol Microbiol 30: 295–304.9791175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Huang1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>42 HuangX, DuW, McClellanSA, BarrettRP, HazlettLD (2006) TLR4 is required for host resistance in Pseudomonas aeruginosa keratitis. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 47: 4910–4916.17065506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Lavoie1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>43 LavoieEG, WangdiT, KazmierczakBI (2011) Innate immune responses to Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection. Microbes Infect 13: 1133–1145.21839853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Yu1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>44 YuFS, HazlettLD (2006) Toll-like receptors and the eye. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 47: 1255–1263.16565355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Chang1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>45 ChangJH, McCluskeyPJ, WakefieldD (2006) Toll-like receptors in ocular immunity and the immunopathogenesis of inflammatory eye disease. Br J Ophthalmol 90: 103–108.16361678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Schultz1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>46 SchultzMJ, SpeelmanP, ZaatSA, HackCE, van DeventerSJ, et al (2000) The effect of pseudomonas exotoxin A on cytokine production in whole blood exposed to Pseudomonas aeruginosa . FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol 29: 227–232.11064270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-DiMango1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>47 DiMangoE, ZarHJ, BryanR, PrinceA (1995) Diverse Pseudomonas aeruginosa gene products stimulate respiratory epithelial cells to produce interleukin-8. J Clin Invest 96: 2204–2210.7593606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Beinke1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>48 BeinkeS, LeySC (2004) Functions of NF-kappaB1 and NF-kappaB2 in immune cell biology. Biochem J 382: 393–409.15214841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Paolillo1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>49 PaolilloR, Romano CarratelliC, SorrentinoS, MazzolaN, MitaL, et al (2011) Expression of IL-23, VEGF and TLR2/TLR4 on mononuclear cells after exposure to Pseudomonas aeruginosa . Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol 24: 961–973.22230402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Colmer1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>50 ColmerJA, HamoodAN (1998) Characterization of ptxS, a Pseudomonas aeruginosa gene which interferes with the effect of the exotoxin A positive regulatory gene, ptxR . Mol Gen Genet 258: 250–259.9645431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Daddaoua1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>51 DaddaouaA, FilletS, FernandezM, UdaondoZ, KrellT, et al (2012) Genes for carbon metabolism and the ToxA virulence factor in Pseudomonas aeruginosa are regulated through molecular interactions of PtxR and PtxS. PLoS One 7: e39390.22844393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Meyer1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>52 MeyerJM, NeelyA, StintziA, GeorgesC, HolderIA (1996) Pyoverdin is essential for virulence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa . Infect Immun 64: 518–523.8550201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Lau1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>53 LauGW, HassettDJ, RanH, KongF (2004) The role of pyocyanin in Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection. Trends Mol Med 10: 599–606.15567330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Lau2"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>54 LauGW, RanH, KongF, HassettDJ, MavrodiD (2004)  Pseudomonas aeruginosa pyocyanin is critical for lung infection in mice. Infect Immun 72: 4275–4278.15213173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Rak1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>55 RakJ, MitsuhashiY, ErdosV, HuangSN, FilmusJ, et al (1995) Massive programmed cell death in intestinal epithelial cells induced by three-dimensional growth conditions: suppression by mutant c-H-ras oncogene expression. J Cell Biol 131: 1587–1598.8522614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Olivas1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>56 OlivasAD, ShoganBD, ValuckaiteV, ZaborinA, BelogortsevaN, et al (2012) Intestinal tissues induce an SNP mutation in Pseudomonas aeruginosa that enhances its virulence: possible role in anastomotic leak. PLoS One 7: e44326.22952955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Garrido1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>57 GarridoD, BarileD, MillsDA (2012) A molecular basis for bifidobacterial enrichment in the infant gastrointestinal tract. Adv Nutr 3: 415S–421S.22585920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Kondepudi1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>58 KondepudiKK, AmbalamP, NilssonI, WadstromT, LjunghA (2012) Prebiotic-non-digestible oligosaccharides preference of probiotic bifidobacteria and antimicrobial activity against Clostridium difficile . Anaerobe 18: 489–497.22940065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Munoz1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>59 MunozM, MosqueraA, Almeciga-DiazCJ, MelendezAP, SanchezOF (2012) Fructooligosaccharides metabolism and effect on bacteriocin production in Lactobacillus strains isolated from ensiled corn and molasses. Anaerobe 18: 321–330.22342961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Knol1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>60 KnolJ, BoehmG, LidestriM, NegrettiF, JelinekJ, et al (2005) Increase of faecal bifidobacteria due to dietary oligosaccharides induces a reduction of clinically relevant pathogen germs in the faeces of formula-fed preterm infants. Acta Paediatr Suppl 94: 31–33. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Daddaoua2"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>61 DaddaouaA, PuertaV, RequenaP, Martinez-FerezA, GuadixE, et al (2006) Goat milk oligosaccharides are anti-inflammatory in rats with hapten-induced colitis. J Nutr 136: 672–676.16484541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Nenaah1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>62 NenaahG (2013) Antimicrobial activity of Calotropis procera Ait. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>(Asclepiadaceae) and isolation of four flavonoid glycosides as the active constituents. World J Microbiol Biotechnol 29: 1255–1262.23417281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Ciofu1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>63 CiofuO, MandsbergLF, WangH, HoibyN (2012) Phenotypes selected during chronic lung infection in cystic fibrosis patients: implications for the treatment of Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm infections. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol 65: 215–225.22540844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Worthington1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>64 WorthingtonRJ, RichardsJJ, MelanderC (2012) Small molecule control of bacterial biofilms. Org Biomol Chem 10: 7457–7474.22733439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Thomas1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>65 ThomasCM, VersalovicJ (2010) Probiotics-host communication: Modulation of signaling pathways in the intestine. Gut Microbes 1: 148–163.20672012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Livermore1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>66 LivermoreDM (2002) Multiple mechanisms of antimicrobial resistance in Pseudomonas aeruginosa: our worst nightmare? Clin Infect Dis 34: 634–640.11823954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Yasuda1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>67 YasudaA, InoueK, SanbongiC, YanagisawaR, IchinoseT, et al (2012) Dietary supplementation with fructooligosaccharides attenuates allergic peritonitis in mice. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 422: 546–550.22580001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Abril1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>68 AbrilMA, MichanC, TimmisKN, RamosJL (1989) Regulator and enzyme specificities of the TOL plasmid-encoded upper pathway for degradation of aromatic hydrocarbons and expansion of the substrate range of the pathway. J Bacteriol 171: 6782–6790.2687253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-MartnezFrezA1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>69 Martínez-Férez ARS, GuadixA, HenkelGA, PohlentzG, BozaJJ, GuadixEM, KunzC (2005) Goat's milk is a natural source of lactose-derived oligosaccharides: isolation by membrane technology. Int Dairy J 16: 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Christensen1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>70 ChristensenGD, SimpsonWA, YoungerJJ, BaddourLM, BarrettFF, et al (1985) Adherence of coagulase-negative staphylococci to plastic tissue culture plates: a quantitative model for the adherence of staphylococci to medical devices. J Clin Microbiol 22: 996–1006.3905855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Fredheim1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>71 FredheimEG, KlingenbergC, RohdeH, FrankenbergerS, GaustadP, et al (2009) Biofilm formation by Staphylococcus haemolyticus . J Clin Microbiol 47: 1172–1180.19144798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Hay1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>72 HayID, RemminghorstU, RehmBH (2009) MucR, a novel membrane-associated regulator of alginate biosynthesis in Pseudomonas aeruginosa . Appl Environ Microbiol 75: 1110–1120.19088322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Smith1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>73 SmithAJ, CawstonTE, HazlemanBL (1985) A rapid and reproducible method for the analysis of immune complexes using affinity chromatography and Western blotting. J Immunol Methods 84: 125–134.3877768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0085772-Halprin1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>74 HalprinKM, OhkawaraA (1966) Lactate production and lactate dehydrogenase in the human epidermis. J Invest Dermatol 47: 222–229.5922980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
