<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3836913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24278403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-29251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081250</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Caco-2 Cell Acquisition of Dietary Iron(III) Invokes a Nanoparticulate Endocytic Pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Dietary Iron(III) Uptake Invokes Endocytosis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>Dora I. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mergler</surname><given-names>Bianca I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>Nuno</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bruggraber</surname><given-names>Sylvaine F. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>Mohamad F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poots</surname><given-names>Lynsey K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prassmayer</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lönnerdal</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Andy P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>Jonathan J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Medical Research Council Human Nutrition Research (MRC HNR), Elsie Widdowson Laboratory, Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Nutrition, University of California Davis, Davis, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Institute for Materials Research, School of Process, Environmental and Materials Engineering, University of Leeds, Leeds, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hotchin</surname><given-names>Neil A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Birmingham, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jonathan.powell@mrc-hnr.cam.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors declare no conflict of interest but D.I.A.P., N.F., S.F.A.B. and J.J.P. wish to note that they are inventors on a patent detailing novel Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide structures that may have potential as dietary supplements [Powell, J., S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Bruggraber, et al. (2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Ligand modified poly oxo-hydroxy metal ion materials, their uses and processes for their preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Organization, U.K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>WO/2008/096130]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This patent does not alter adherence to all PLOS ONE policies on sharing data or materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: DIAP BIM JJP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: DIAP BIM LKP LP MFA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: DIAP BIM MFA APB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BL NF SFAB APB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Wrote the manuscript: DIAP APB JJP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Developed the hypothesis behind this research: JJP DIAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Provided input on development of the hypothesis behind this research: SFAB NF APB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Had primary responsibility for final content: DIAP JJP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Read, provided input to and approved the manuscript: DIAP BIM NF SFAB MFA LKP LP BL APB JJP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn1"><label>☯</label><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These authors contribute equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e81250</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Pereira et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pereira et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Dietary non-heme iron contains ferrous [Fe(II)] and ferric [Fe(III)] iron fractions and the latter should hydrolyze, forming Fe(III) oxo-hydroxide particles, on passing from the acidic stomach to less acidic duodenum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Using conditions to mimic the in vivo hydrolytic environment we confirmed the formation of nanodisperse fine ferrihydrite-like particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Synthetic analogues of these (~ 10 nm hydrodynamic diameter) were readily adherent to the cell membrane of differentiated Caco-2 cells and internalization was visualized using transmission electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Caco-2 exposure to these nanoparticles led to ferritin formation (i.e., iron utilization) by the cells, which, unlike for soluble forms of iron, was reduced (p=0.02) by inhibition of clathrin-mediated endocytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Simulated lysosomal digestion indicated that the nanoparticles are readily dissolved under mildly acidic conditions with the lysosomal ligand, citrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed in cell culture as monensin inhibited Caco-2 utilization of iron from this source in a dose dependent fashion (p&lt;0.05) whilet soluble iron was again unaffected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Our findings reveal the possibility of an endocytic pathway for acquisition of dietary Fe(III) by the small intestinal epithelium, which would complement the established DMT-1 pathway for soluble Fe(II). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the UK Medical Research Council (MRC) (U105960399), MRC Technology Development Gap Fund (DGF), Action Medical Research (SP4528) and WellChild. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Dietary non-heme iron (Fe) contains ferrous [Fe(II)] and ferric [Fe(III)] fractions in a number of chemical forms: for example Fe in ferritin and in Fe-sulphur cluster proteins [1–3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Redox changes to dietary Fe between the points of ingestion and cellular uptake from the intestinal lumen are complex and may favour oxidation to Fe(III) due to intestinal pH and endogenous ligands, or reduction to Fe(II) due to the presence of ascorbate and low luminal oxygen levels [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Overall, however, both Fe(II) and Fe(III) appear to reach the intestinal epithelial surface to some extent [4,6–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Fe(II) is transported by the divalent metal transporter-1 (DMT-1) and Fe(III) is proposed to undergo enzymatic reduction to Fe(II), perhaps by duodenal cytochrome B (DcytB), prior to transport by DMT-1 [9–13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Chemically, however, there is an uncomfortable paradox with respect to this latter pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Fe(III) is remarkably insoluble at duodenal pH, immediately precipitating out of solution as Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>[logKeq Fe3+  +  3  H2O  ↔  Fe(OH)3  +  3H+ =  -11.7 [14]]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To obviate iron precipitation several authors have suggested the presence of endogenous Fe binding agents (i.e. proteins, organic acids etc.) in gastrointestinal secretions that retain Fe(III) in a soluble form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The aluminium ion (Al(III)) can be viewed as a kinetically less labile, non-paramagnetic metal ion (M) ‘probe’ for Fe(III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Work on the chemical speciation of Al(III) in the intestinal lumen did not identify any endogenous ligands that could prevent its precipitation as an oxo-hydroxide at peri-neutral pH [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Instead, Powell et al. proposed that a range of endogenous, low molecular weight ligands could slow the rate of hydrolysis to allow M(III) binding to gastrointestinal mucins [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Indeed, luminal Fe binding to gastrointestinal mucins has been identified by a number of authors [8,16,17] and so effective is this binding that gastric mucin has been previously referred to as ‘gastroferrin’: the endogenous gastro(intestinal) molecule that can keep dietary Fe(III) in ‘solution’ [18–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Rudzki et al. detailed the nature of the binding between Fe(III) and the Fe-binding glycoprotein of gastric juice (mucin) and showed that at pH values of the proximal bowel (typical pH range 5.8-6.7 [25]), Fe(III) is not quite kept in ‘solution’ [26].Instead, it appears that Fe(III) commences hydrolysis but further growth and agglomeration of the Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles are prevented by mucin binding [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>They visualized the nanoparticles formed in the Fe-glycoprotein complex, noting that they were ~10-20 nm in diameter and appeared to be amorphous aggregates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The Fe(III) oxo-hydroxide phase expected to first precipitate from an Fe(III)-bearing solution at proximal small bowel pH is ferrihydrite [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This is a cross-linked polymeric (i.e. poorly (nano)crystalline) phase with primary platelets of 2-5 nm in size depending on the degree of crystallinity and is prone to agglomeration and aggregation [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Rudzki et al. produced a synthetic version, referring to this phase as colloidal Fe and, importantly, showed that direct instillation of this ferrihydrite–mucin solution into the duodenum of rats, led to Fe absorption nearly equivalent to that of the gold standard, Fe(II) ascorbate [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>How nanoparticulate Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide, which is insoluble at duodenal pH, would be acquired by enterocytes and processed for absorption and utilization is not clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Current understanding of dietary Fe(III) absorption suggests synergistic association between an intestinal ferrireductase (e.g. DcytB) and the apical Fe(II) transporter ( DMT-1) such that the enzyme reduces Fe(III) allowing its transport and absorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>However, our current in vivo studies reasonably preclude the requirement for reduction and dissolution of Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide prior to uptake by the enterocyte (Pereira, Latunde-Dada and Powell; unpublished observations). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>To investigate the above paradox in more detail we first built on the model of Rudzki et al. [26,29] using mucin plus typical low molecular weight ligands of the gastrointestinal lumen to better mimic in vivo Fe(III) hydrolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We confirmed the formation of a fine ferrihydrite-like phase in ‘luminally hydrolysed’ dietary Fe(III) and then we probed cellular uptake and utilization of synthetic ligand-modified ferrihydrite, as an analogue for this nanoparticulate phase, demonstrating the requirement of endocytic uptake mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Synthesis of iron materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Soluble Fe(II) material was prepared by mixing an acidified stock solution of Fe(II) sulphate heptahydrate (40 mM) with a stock solution of ascorbic acid (0.5 M) to achieve a molar ratio of 1:100 (Fe:ascorbic acid). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Soluble Fe(III) maltol chelate (Fe(III) maltol) was produced by mixing a stock solution of Fe(III) chloride (8 mM) with a maltol (3-hydroxy-2-methyl-4H-pyran-4-one) solution (40 mM) to achieve a molar ratio of Fe:maltol of 1:5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Soluble Fe(III) nitrilotriacetate chelate (Fe(III) NTA) was produced by mixing a solution of Fe(III) chloride (8 mM) with a NTA solution to achieve a molar ratio of Fe:NTA of 1:5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The pH of the above mixtures was adjusted to 7.4 with NaOH prior to use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Ligand-modified (LM) Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide material was produced following the protocol described by Powell et al. [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Briefly, an acidic concentrated stock solution of Fe(III) chloride (40 mM) was added to a solution containing tartaric acid and adipic acid or, in the case of un-modified Fe(III) oxo-hydroxide, to 0.9 %(w/v) of electrolyte (potassium chloride). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The initial pH of the mixture was always below 2.0 and the iron was fully solubilized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The pH was then slowly increased by drop-wise addition of a concentrated solution of NaOH with constant agitation until the desired final pH (ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>7.4 for LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide and 7.4-8.2 for un-modified Fe(III) oxo-hydroxide) were attained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In the case of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide the ratio of Fe:tartaric acid:adipic acid in the final suspension was 2:1:1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Chemical characterisation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Detailed methods of the below are provided in the Supplementary Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Fe(III) structures were characterised by transmission electron microscopy (TEM) after hydrolysis of Fe(III) in simulated digestion medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The solubility of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide and un-modified Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (i.e. standard synthetic ferrihydrite) was determined at pH 5.0 ± 0.1 in a 10 mM citric acid, 0.15 M NaCl solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The Fe material was added to the assay solution at an Fe concentration of ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>1 mM and incubated for 360 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Soluble iron was determined following ultrafiltration (3,000 Da MWCO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The hydrodynamic particle size of the nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide material was determined by Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS) and the non-aquated primary particle size by Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Cellular uptake studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To avoid aggregation/agglomeration of the nanoparticulate iron, the medium for cellular uptake consisted of a balanced salt solution (BSS) containing 130 mM NaCl, 10 mM KCl, 1 mM MgSO4, 5 mM Glucose and 1 mM CaCl2 in 10 mM PIPES buffer (pH 7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Immediately before the cellular uptake experiments, fresh solutions of the Fe materials were prepared in BSS at an Fe concentration of 200 μM and the partition of the Fe into the soluble, nanoparticulate and microparticulate fractions was assessed to assure that most of the Fe (i.e. &gt;90%) was present in the nanoparticulate fraction and had not agglomerated/aggregated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>DLS measurements were also taken of the nanoparticulate fraction to assure a mono-disperse distribution of the intended size (i.e. ~10nm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Detailed methodology is shown in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Iron uptake in undifferentiated Caco-2 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Human adenocarcinoma (Caco-2) cells were obtained from ATCC (LGC standards, Middlesex, United Kingdom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cells were seeded at 1.13 x 106 cells/mL onto 6-well cell culture plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Plates were centrifuged at 680 xg for 5 min to remove the growth medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The different Fe preparations in uptake medium were carefully added to the cells and incubated for 1 h at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Uptake medium with no supplemented Fe was also incubated with cells as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Each condition was tested in triplicate wells for each experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>After the Fe incubation period, the uptake medium was removed by centrifugation and aspiration, and the cells were washed with phosphate buffered saline (PBS)-EDTA (2 mM) to remove any loosely bound Fe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The cells were then resuspended in fresh MEM (with no supplemental Fe) and returned to the incubator for an additional 23 h to allow for ferritin-protein formation to plateau [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>At the end of the incubation period, the cells were washed with Dulbecco's Phosphate-Buffered Saline (DPBS; PAA Laboratories) and lysed with Mammalian Protein Extraction Reagent (MPER®, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Cramlington, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>After lysis, cell debris was removed by centrifugation (5 min, 16,000 xg) and the supernatant used for analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Iron uptake in differentiated Caco-2 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Cells (Caco-2 ATCC as above) were seeded at ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>1.8 x 105 cells/mL onto 6-well cell culture plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The Caco-2 cells were maintained under the culture conditions described in Methods S1 and used for the Fe uptake experiments at 11 or 12 days post-seeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Cell differentiation and formation of a cell monolayer were confirmed for this timepoint as described in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Approximately 16 h prior to the experiments the growth medium was replaced by non-supplemented MEM, i.e. without FBS or antibiotics, and cells were returned to the incubator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This was carried out to ‘starve’ cells of Fe prior to the experiments and did not induce any changes in the cell monolayer integrity as confirmed by TEER measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The Caco-2 cell monolayer was then washed once with pre-warmed DPBS and incubated with the different Fe materials or control uptake medium for 1 h at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>For each experiment every condition was investigated in triplicate wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Following the Fe incubation period the uptake medium was removed, the cell monolayer was washed three times with PBS-EDTA (2 mM) to remove any Fe loosely adherent to the cell membrane and fresh non-supplemented MEM was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The cells were then returned to the incubator for an additional 23 h to allow for ferritin-protein formation [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At the end of the incubation period, the cells were washed and lysed as before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The cell lysate supernatant was used for analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The Caco-2 cells requirement of energy for Fe uptake from Fe(III) maltol or the nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide was investigated by low temperature incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The cells were kept on ice for 10 min prior to the experiment and during the 1 h incubation period with the two Fe materials suspended in uptake medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The cells were then washed 3 times with ice-cold PBS-EDTA (2 mM) and fresh non-supplemented MEM was added and the cells incubated for the remaining 23 h at 37° C and treated as above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To study the effect of endocytosis-related-pathway-inhibitors on Fe uptake from the different materials, Caco-2 cells were co-incubated for 1 h at 37° C with the Fe materials in BSS supplemented with the following inhibitors (each inhibitor tested in triplicate wells): chlorpromazine (100 µM), filipin (5 mg/L), methyl-β-cyclodextrin (5 mM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Additionally, cells were incubated with Fe in K+-free BSS consisting of 130 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgSO4, 5 mM glucose and 1 mM CaCl2 in 10 mM PIPES buffer (pH 7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>For this experimental condition cells were pre-incubated for 5 min with a 1:1 mixture of Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM):water prior to incubation in K+-free medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>For the cellular lysosomal dissolution experiments, cells were co-incubated for 1 h at 37° C with the Fe materials in BSS supplemented with monensin (5-30 µM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>As before ferritin-formation was assessed at 23h following the removal of the inhibitors and Fe materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Controls were performed for each inhibitor by incubating the cells with uptake medium (BSS) supplemented with the inhibitor but not containing Fe. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Chlorpromazine [32,33] and K+ free BSS [33,34] were used to inhibit clathrin-mediated uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Filipin [35] and methyl-β-cyclodextrin [34,36] were used to inhibit caveolin-mediated uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Monensin was used to inhibit acidification of endosomes/lysosomes [37–39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Cell lysate supernatants were analysed for cellular ferritin-protein content using the commercial enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kit “Spectro Ferritin” (ATI Atlas, Chichester, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The uptake data were normalized to total cell protein content determined with the non-interfering protein assay™ (NIPA™, Calbiochem/Merck, Nottingham, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>TEER measurements were carried out to determine if the chemical inhibitors used in the uptake studies had a negative impact on the integrity of the cell monolayer (an early indication of toxicity) as detailed in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy was used to visualize nanoparticulate Fe uptake by the Caco-2 cells as detailed in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>All statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism version 6 for Windows (GraphPad Software, San Diego, California, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Unless stated otherwise, results are presented as means with standard deviations (s.d.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The unpaired t-test was used to statistically compare ferritin-protein formation for the different Fe compounds in differentiated and undifferentiated cells and ferritin-protein formation with and without chemical inhibitors of endocytosis-related pathways (level of significance set to p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The repeated measures 2-way ANOVA with Sidak correction for multiple comparisons was used to statistically compare TEER at different time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Regular 2-way ANOVA (no matching) was used to statistically compare ferritin formation for different monensin doses between the nano Fe and the soluble Fe materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Ferritin-protein concentration in the presence of monensin was fitted with a non-linear dose-response inhibition curve (i.e. Log10(inhibitor) versus response). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Formation and cellular uptake of ligand-modified Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>First, as a mimetic of gastrointestinal hydrolysis conditions, Fe(III) chloride was dissolved at pH 1.2 in a solution of relevant, low molecular weight ligands and gastric porcine mucin and then adjusted to pH 6.5-7.1 using sodium bicarbonate (final Fe concentration 1 mM) (detailed methodology is available in Methods S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>A drop of the resultant ‘solution’ (colloidal suspension) was placed on a thin amorphous carbon film for TEM and imaged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Agglomerates of fine (~5 nm) poorly crystalline particles in an amorphous gel were noted (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Whole area energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDX) showed these to be Fe-containing (Figure 1B), and electron diffraction (not shown) indicated a mixture of two phases – ferrihydrite-like (two broad diffraction rings characteristic of 2-line ferrihydrite [40]) and a second phase which was not uniquely identified (two broad diffraction rings at 0.20 and 0.13 nm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Under prolonged exposure to the electron beam the particles agglomerated further, developed in crystallinity and the diffraction pattern became dominated by this second phase: it was still not possible to confirm the identity of this alteration product but an Fe phosphate hydroxide provides the closest match to the observed lattice spacings (International Centre for Diffraction Data powder diffraction file 00-047-0413). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Irradiation damage to poorly crystalline fine particles such as ferrihydrite [41] is well recognized, especially in the absence of supporting resin or tissue structure, so we considered this second phase to be artifactual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Hence the larger particles (10-20 nm) observed in the earlier work of Rudzki et al. [26] are, likely, an artifact of beam damage but the smaller particles are not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the hydrolysis of the Fe(III) and the formation of these fine, disperse, ferrihydrite-like particles was not prevented by the presence of typical gastrointestinal low-molecular weight ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>As a simplified and practical analogue to the above ferrihydrite-like particles we have developed ligand-modified (LM) Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxides of similar size and structure [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This ligand-modified analogue remains well-dispersed upon aqueous suspension in the uptake medium used for cellular experiments (balanced salt solution: BSS) taking on an average hydrodynamic particle diameter of 10 nm (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081250-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081250.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Characterisation of hydrolysed Fe(III) with simulated digestion and of aquated LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>A, Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) images collected from a drop of suspension after simulated digestion of 1 mM Fe(III) chloride in the presence of 2 g/L mucin and low molecular weight ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The boxed regions are shown magnified below and highlight the presence of fine, poorly crystalline nanoparticles dispersed in an amorphous gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Crystallinity is indicated by the spots in the inset diffractograms (fast Fourier transforms) in the boxed regions and lattice spacings are discussed in the main text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Scale bar represents 5 nm. B, Whole area EDX analysis of a particle agglomerate similar to those in ‘A’ shows elemental compositions (the specimen support film and grid produce the background C and Cu signals respectively). C, Hydrodynamic size distribution of nanoparticulate 500 µM LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide in balanced salt solution (BSS) measured by Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Values are expressed as mean diameter ± s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>(3 independent measurements) on a log10 scale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081250.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Here, ferritin-protein formation of epithelial cell cultures, as a measure of cellular iron utilisation, was assessed following a 24 h total incubation period that involved 1 h Fe exposure of cells in BSS followed by washing, change of medium, and a 23 h incubation in non-supplemented minimum essential medium (MEM) (i.e. with very low Fe content). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>We used soluble Fe, either as Fe(III) maltol [42] or Fe(II) sulphate-ascorbate as positive controls [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Initially, we used both differentiated and undifferentiated cells and iron utilization varied greatly for the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide structures (undifferentiated &gt; differentiated; p=0.0003) but not at all for the soluble Fe(III) (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Alkaline phosphatase levels were used as a marker for Caco-2 cell differentiation and the integrity of the cell monolayer was assured prior to the experiments (see Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The solid phase distribution, i.e. the partition of the Fe in the soluble, nanoparticulate (aquated) or microparticulate (agglomerated) fractions, largely confirmed the nanoparticulate nature of the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide and the solubility of the Fe(III) maltol and Fe(II) sulphate-ascorbate (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Cellular uptake and utilization of the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide required nano dispersion because purposeful agglomeration to microparticles (first hour in MEM, rather than in BSS, leading to 97 ± 2% microparticulate iron at 30 min) prevented iron utilization (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>We confirmed that BSS did not affect monolayer integrity for the duration of the exposure (Figure 2D) although Fe(II) sulphate-ascorbate did [31], so further cellular work used Fe(III) maltol as the soluble control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081250-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081250.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Ferritin-protein levels in Caco-2 cells following exposure to LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (nano Fe), Fe(III) maltol (FeM) or Fe(II) sulphate-ascorbate (FeSO4 + AA). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A, Ferritin-protein regulation in differentiated and undifferentiated cells. ***, p=0.0003. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated for 1 h with 200 μM Fe plus a further 23 h in fresh, non-supplemented MEM to allow for ferritin formation. B, Phase distribution of Fe in the BSS uptake medium: i.e. fractional percentage of microparticulate (black bars), nanoparticulate (red bars) and soluble Fe (open bars) for each Fe material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Values are mean ± s.d. of 3 independent experiments. C, Effect of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide particle dispersion (in BSS medium, closed bars) or agglomeration (in MEM medium, open bars) on ferritin-protein levels in differentiated cells: the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide was dispersed in its nano-form (99 ± 2% nano) using BSS or agglomerated (97 ± 2% microparticulate) using MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Data are mean of 3 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicate wells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>FeM: soluble iron control, Fe(III) maltol. ***, p=0.0002 for the comparison between BSS and MEM. D, TEER changes in differentiated Caco-2 cell monolayer at different time points during incubation with BSS supplemented with LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (open circles) or non-supplemented BSS control (closed inverted triangles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Incubations were for 3 h with 200 μM Fe (measurements at 1, 2 &amp; 3 h) plus a further 21 h in fresh, non-supplemented MEM (24-h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Values are expressed as a percentage of the initial measurement and are shown as mean ± s.d. of 3 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicate wells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Experimental points are connected with a solid line to aid visualization and not because a linear relationship is assumed between time and TEER measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Detailed methodology is available in the Methods Section and in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081250.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Hence, the uptake and utilization of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide required its dispersion in nanoparticulate form (Figure 2C) and the mechanism of acquisition appeared different to that of soluble Fe (Figure 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Next we investigated energy requirements for Fe uptake by comparing data at 37° C with those at low temperature (i.e. on ice). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Fe utilization from Fe(III) maltol at low temperature was decreased by 95 % (95 ± 1; n=3) as expected, but from nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide the reduction was only ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>20 % (19 ± 13; n=3) (Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Apparent low temperature uptake of nanoparticles has been observed before [43,44] and is attributed to particle adhesion to the cell membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Adherent particles, that withstand washing, may be subsequently taken up by cells (and in this case utilized to form ferritin-protein, indicating that cells remained healthy) upon re-incubation in fresh medium at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy indicated cell surface adhesion of the nanoparticles and also showed that, generally, the cell membrane tended to induce loose agglomeration or aggregation of the particles into clusters up to 200 nm in diameter (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Thus we considered that Fe from the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles was utilized following acquisition by endocytic uptake, as this is superior in undifferentiated versus differentiated Caco-2 cells [45], and cell surface adhesion is a requirement prior to uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Indeed further electron microscopy work revealed evidence of cell surface invagination (Figure 3B) with respect to the surface clusters of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide and showed loose agglomerates of ≤ 200 nm in diameter within vesicles that we suggest are endosomes or lysosomes (Figure 3C, D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>TEM images were also collected for control Caco-2 cells: i.e. cells incubated with non-supplemented BSS and cells incubated with BSS supplemented with the soluble Fe(III) maltol chelate and no discernible particulate Fe was observed (Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>To determine whether nanoparticulate uptake contributed to cellular Fe utilization of the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide we used an inhibitor of clathrin-mediated endocytosis, namely chlorpromazine, at a dose of 100 μM consistent with previous studies [32,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>We confirmed that this significantly reduced (p=0.02) ferritin-protein formation in the cells exposed to LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (Figure 3E), without significantly affecting monolayer integrity (Figure 3F), whilst no difference was observed for soluble iron uptake (Figure 3E, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Further endocytic-inhibition studies with K+ depletion, filipin and methyl-β-cyclodextrin suggested the same picture: namely that Fe utilization appeared reduced albeit so only for LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide exposure and not for soluble Fe (Figure 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, filipin and methyl-β-cyclodextrin inhibit caveolae-related rather than clathrin-mediated endocytosis so, consistent with previous nanoparticulate uptake work, there either appears to be a degree of redundancy/overlap between the uptake pathways [43] or precise uptake may be related to the size range of the nanoparticulate clusters formed on the cell membrane [46–49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>All cell monolayers appeared healthy under the microscope, and also without significant changes in TEER measurements, under the assay conditions used with K+-free BSS and methyl-β-cyclodextrin (Figure 3F), although no TEER assessment was made with filipin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081250-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081250.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Cellular uptake of nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide by Caco-2 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>A, B, C, D TEM images showing differentiated Caco-2 cells incubated with LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide. A, arrows show particle clusters adhering to the cell membrane microvilli (scale bar, 500 nm). B, arrows indicate invagination on the cell membrane (scale bar, 100 nm). C and D, arrows indicate Fe accumulation inside the cell (scale bars: panel C, 500 nm and panel D, 100 nm). E, Effect of chemical inhibitors of endocytosis-related pathways on Fe utilization by differentiated Caco-2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Data are shown as a percentage of the controls (without inhibitor) after a 1 h exposure to LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (black bars) or Fe(III) maltol (open bars) co-incubated with either chlorpromazine (CPZ), potassium-free BSS (K+ depletion), filipin or methyl-β-cyclodextrin (M-β-c), plus 23 h in fresh non-supplemented MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Results are mean ± s.d. of 3 independent experiments with 3 replicate wells per experiment for chlorpromazine (*, p=0.02 relative to control) or triplicate wells of the same experiment for the remaining inhibitors. F, Change in TEER in the Caco-2 cell monolayer following a 1 h exposure to chlorpromazine (closed diamonds), K+-free BSS (open triangles), M-β-c (open squares) or non-supplemented BSS (closed inverted triangles) and with 23 h further incubation in fresh MEM (24 h total). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Values are a percentage of the initial measurement (0 h) and are shown as mean ± s.d. as above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Experimental points are connected with a solid line to aid visualization and not because a linear relationship is assumed between time and TEER measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Detailed methodology is available in the Methods Section and in Methods S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081250.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Lysosomal dissolution of ligand-modified Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles enables cellular utilization of iron </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Overall, direct endocytosis of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles by differentiated Caco-2 cells appears, chiefly, to explain uptake of Fe under these conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>However, this Fe still needs to be released for cellular utilization (i.e. ferritin-protein synthesis in the current cell assay) and there would be insufficient intracellular (lysosomal) acidification for this alone to drive the release and cytosolic iron transit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Skotland et al. [50] developed a simplified endosomal/lysosomal solution that included 10 mM citrate and this chelator might, when aided by endosomal/lysosomal acidification, enable the breakdown and release of Fe from these fine, ligand-destabilized ferrihydrite-like particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>We showed that under these simplified endosomal/lysosomal conditions soluble Fe could be released within hours from the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (ferrihydrite) structures at pH 5.0 (Figure 4A) whereas, in the absence of ligand modification, the native Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide was poorly broken down and little soluble Fe was released (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This ‘destabilization’ role of low molecular weight ligands in the nano-structured Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide indicates a more likely physiological role for them in the gut lumen rather than, as originally proposed [19], as donors of Fe(III) to mucin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Next, using cell studies and monensin to inhibit endosomal/lysosomal acidification [39], we showed a monensin-dose-dependent reduction (i.e. Log10 [monensin] versus [ferritin-protein], r2=0.935, p&lt;0.05) in Fe utilization by differentiated Caco-2 cells when exposed to LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (Figure 4B), with statistically significant inhibition of ferritin formation at monensin doses ≥ 7.5 µM (p=0.002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Again, soluble Fe was unaffected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The monensin doses used here were equivalent to those reported previously in inhibition studies of endosomal/lysosomal acidification in Caco-2 cells [51,52] or other cell types [53,54], even though by 24 h some disruption of the monolayer was visible by TEER measurements particularly at the highest monensin dose (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, the monolayer was intact during the 1 hour cell exposure to Fe (Figure 4C) and, when examined microscopically, the cell monolayers appeared integral and healthy at doses of monensin up to 10 µM which still greatly inhibited ferritin-protein formation (Figure 4B), and there were similar protein levels in the presence and absence of the inhibitor (Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0081250-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081250.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Lysososmal dissolution of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>A, Solubility in simulated lysosomal conditions at pH 5.0 with 10 mM citric acid and 0.15 M NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Soluble Fe was measured by ICP-OES following 5 min ultrafiltration (3000 Da MWCO) for the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (black) and for un-modified Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (solid blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Nanoparticulate Fe was obtained from the Fe in the supernatant following centrifugation excluding the soluble (ultrafilterable) Fe, and is shown for LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (red) and for un-modified Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (dotted blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Values are plotted as mean ± s.d. of 3 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicates). B, Effect of inhibition of lysosomal acidification using monensin on Fe utilization by differentiated Caco-2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Data are shown as a percentage of the control (without monensin) at 24 h: i.e. 1 h exposure to 200 µM nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (open circles) or Fe(III) maltol (closed squares) ± 5-30 µM monensin followed by 23 h in non-supplemented MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Results are means ± s.d. of 3 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicate wells). **, p&lt;0.005; ***, p&lt;0.001 in relation to the soluble Fe control (Fe(III)maltol). C, Change in TEER in the Caco-2 cell monolayer following 1 h exposure to 10 μM monensin (closed squares), 30 μM monensin (open diamonds) or non-supplemented BSS control (closed inverted triangles) and with 23 h further incubation in fresh MEM (24 h in total). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Values are expressed as a percentage of the initial measurement at the start of the exposure time (corresponding to 0 h) and are shown as mean ± s.d. of 2 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicate wells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Experimental points are connected with a solid line to aid visualization and not because a linear relationship is assumed between time and TEER measurement. ***, p=0.0003; ****, p&lt;0.0001 in relation to the non-supplemented BSS control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0081250.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Finally, we confirmed that none of the inhibitors caused significant agglomeration of the nanoparticles in the supplemented uptake medium (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Overall Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The Caco-2 cell line has been extensively used for iron uptake studies [55–59] as following confluence it differentiates into a polarised cell monolayer that exhibits a phenotype similar to human small intestinal enterocytes [60,61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that an endocytic, apical uptake mechanism exists in these differentiated Caco-2 cells for uptake of luminally hydrolysed (poly oxo-hydroxide) dietary Fe(III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This route apparently relies on endocytic uptake of small clusters of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles which agglomerate at the cell membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Many cellular studies on nanoparticulate uptake and processing are challenged with issues of agglomeration and aggregation meaning that, finally, cells are exposed to micron-sized clusters which will be acquired and processed differently compared to genuinely disperse nanostructures [46,62,63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Thus we paid considerable attention to developing a cell culture medium that mitigated against such pitfalls and retained appropriate dispersion of the particles prior to cell delivery [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The finding that these fine LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles then tend to agglomerate at the cell membrane must be interpreted with caution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>It could be that the processing required to produce thin sections for electron microscopy induced clustering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>However, small agglomerates of nanoparticles were observed in endosomal/lysosomal compartments within the cell and, so, the particles must have been taken up either as individual particles or clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Moreover, and importantly, we observed loose clusters almost always smaller than 200 nm diameter and it is at around this size that uptake mechanisms may switch between classical endocytosis and macropinocytosis [46,64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>There appears to be no mechanism of macropinocytosis in intestinal enterocytes, including differentiated Caco-2 cells, and phagocytosis has been rarely demonstrated [65,66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The inhibitors used here were classical endocytic inhibitors and our findings suggest endocytosis of individual particles or membrane-induced small clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We accept that the specificity of K+-depletion to clathrin-mediated endocytosis and methyl-β-cyclodextrin to caveolin-dependent endocytosis in HuTu cells has been previously questioned [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>However, chlorpromazine has been consistently shown to be highly specific for clathrin-mediated endocytosis in both HuTu and Caco-2 cells, providing comparable inhibition rates to siRNA approaches [34,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Filipin also appears specific to caveolin-dependent endocytosis [35,68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, we do not, here, suggest dominance of one specific form of endocytosis for the uptake of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles as further work may be required to conclude on this. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Our observations on Fe utilization by Caco-2 cells, through endocytic uptake and lysosomal dissolution of nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide, are still consistent with the established fact that DMT-1 is indispensable for mammalian Fe absorption and, therefore, survival [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>DMT-1, as well as being the enterocyte Fe(II) apical transporter is probably also the export transporter of the lysosomal membrane [70–72]: i.e. the point from where endocytosed and then solubilized nanoparticulate Fe would join the common Fe pool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The elegant study of Gunshin et al. [69], utilizing an intestinal-specific DMT-1 knock-out model termed Slc11a2int/int (which is a cross of Slc11a2flox/flox mice with mice carrying a Villin-Cre transgene), proved essentiality of this transporter for intestinal non-haem iron absorption after birth [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, the Slc11a2int/int model has DMT1 knocked-out in the entire enterocyte and not solely from the apical membrane [69] and, therefore, this study did not eliminate DMT-1 functionality in both apical uptake and cytosolic processing of intracellular iron.A further point is that laboratory rodent diets poorly represent the human diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Invariably the laboratory diet is rich in fibrous carbohydrate that is poorly digestible in the upper gastrointestinal tract and will bind Fe(III) thereby preventing mucosal access. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Thus, Fe(II) sulphate is commonly supplemented into rodent laboratory chow, as for example in the RMH 3000 LabDiet (PMI Nutrition International) used by Gunshin et al. in the study referred to above [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>In this case, the essentiality of an Fe(II) transporter would be favoured. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Future in vivo rodent experiments could use a diet representing the more varied human diet for non-heme Fe (e.g., mixed Fe(II)-Fe(III) salts that undergo gastric dissolution, plus ferritin-protein) and then establish, in the Slc11a2int/int mouse, whether or not there is enterocyte lysosomal accumulation of Fe (i.e. initial apical uptake due to a non DMT-1 pathway for the hydrolysed Fe(III) and possibly ferritin-protein fractions, but accumulation due to export failure with lack of lysosomal DMT-1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Such a diet fed to Slc11a2int/int mice will delineate the essential role of DMT-1 for apical iron uptake versus lysosomal iron efflux. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Indeed, Kalgaonkar and Lonnerdal [3] have speculated that dietary ferritin Fe, which contains subunits of ferrihydrite similar in structure to the LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide nanoparticles used herein [73], may not all be dissolved under post-prandial gastric conditions, and could be absorbed whole by duodenal enterocytes and subsequently broken down intra-lysosomally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Moreover, elsewhere in mammalian Fe physiology, the lysosome is a safe reservoir for catabolism of Fe-rich species, whether it be ferritin-protein, red blood cells or transferrin turnover [71,74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Free Fe is potentially redox active and thus toxic to cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>So the concept that cells lining the gut are protected from redox damage (Fe(III) ↔ Fe(II) + e-) due to luminal nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide formation, which is only available for breakdown in the safest compartment of the cell, i.e. the endosome/lysosome, is consistent with other aspects of Fe metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Finally, of particular note, is a paper by Theil and colleagues [75], published during preparation of this manuscript, where they show that the Fe derived from dietary ferritin-protein (i.e. protein-encapsulated ferrihydrite-like nanostructures) is absorbed differently in rats and humans to that of DMT-1-dependent Fe(II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Moreover, their findings invoke an epithelial endocytic process, which we believe we detail here: i.e. the fraction of dietary iron derived from ferritin-protein ingestion could lose its protein shell but maintain its ferrihydrite-like structure following gastrointestinal digestion and ‘ride’ the endocytic mechanisms that exists for endogenously formed LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, the two forms may look very similar, being 2-5 nm diameter, destabilized ferrihydrite [73] and thus, readily solubilized by the enterocyte endosome/lysosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Our preliminary data in duodenal epithelial cells (HuTu-80 cell line) using siRNA targeting DMT1 further supports a pathway independent of DMT1 and Dcyt B for the intestinal uptake of LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide and, thus, not involving reduction of Fe(III) to Fe(II) (Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated the existence of a nanoparticulate ferrihydrite-like phase in a model of luminally hydrolysed Fe(III) and, using a synthetic nanoparticulate ligand-modified ferrihydrite as an analogue, we have shown the existence of an endocytic pathway of Fe uptake by Caco-2 cells, a gut epithelial cell model, followed by lysosomal dissolution of nanoparticulate LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide which is consistent with in vivo observations elsewhere [75]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>These in vitro mechanistic findings now need to be replicated by in vivo data for physiological relevance, and, it is noteworthy that, when supplemented into the diet of iron deficient rats, these LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide structures improved haemoglobin levels in line with Fe(II) sulphate supplementation [Pereira, Latunde-Dada and Powell unpublished observations]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s001"><label>Methods S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s001.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Iron solid-phase distribution of 200 µM Fe as LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (nano Fe) and Fe(III) maltol (FeM) co-incubated with different chemical inhibitors in the BSS uptake medium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s002.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s003"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Caco-2 cell growth and differentiation parameters in monolayers grown for 21 days. A, cell protein (open circles) and transepithelial electrical resistance (TEER, closed squares). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Data shown are mean ± s.d. of n=3 independent experiments (each experiment with 12 replicate wells). B, alkaline phosphatase activity (closed triangles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Data shown are mean ± s.d. of n=3 independent experiments (each experiment with 3 replicate wells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Under these culture conditions the cell monolayer is fully confluent at day 5 post-seeding and differentiated at day 10 post-seeding in accordance with reference values reported in the literature [76,77]. . </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s004"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Effect of low temperature incubation on ferritin-protein levels in Caco-2 cells following exposure to LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (nano Fe) or Fe(III) maltol (FeM). Cells were incubated for 1 h in BSS at 37°C (closed bars) or 4°C (open bars) supplemented with 200 µM Fe plus a further 23 h in fresh, non-supplemented MEM to allow for ferritin formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Data are mean (± s.d.) of 3 replicate wells within one experiment. **, p=0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s005"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>TEM image showing differentiated Caco-2 cells incubated at 37° C for 3 h with (A) non-supplemented control media (i.e. balanced salt solution, BSS), (B) control BSS supplemented with maltol alone and (C) BSS supplemented with 500 µM Fe as the soluble Fe(III) maltol chelate. Scale bar, 500 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s006"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Effect of monensin on cellular protein levels in Caco-2 monolayers. Cells were incubated for 1 h in BSS supplemented with different concentrations of monensin plus a further 23 h in fresh, non-supplemented MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Box and whisker plots show median, minimum and maximum for n=6 independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The red solid line represents the mean cellular protein for all experiments and the dotted red lines represent the corresponding 95% confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>No statistical differences were found for any monensin concentration in relation to control cells incubated without monensin (0 µM). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s006.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081250.s007"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Effect of siRNA targeting of DMT1 (closed bars) and Dcyt B (open bars) on iron uptake in HuTu cells. HuTu cells were transfected with siRNAs and, after 3 days, the cells were incubated for 1 h in BSS supplemented with 10 µM Fe as soluble Fe(II) (ferrous sulphate) or LM Fe(III) poly oxo-hydroxide (nano Fe) plus a further 23 h in fresh, non-supplemented MEM to allow for ferritin formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Pattern bars indicate scrambled-transfected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Data are mean (± s.d.) of 3 replicate wells within one experiment. ****, p&lt;0.0001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0081250.s007.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>This work is a publication of the UK Medical Research Council (U105960399). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>B.I.M thanks the MRC and Rank Prize Funds for her PhD studentship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>We thank Emma Thomas-McKay for kindly collecting the TEM images of the cells and Ewgenia Roth for kindly collecting some of the TEER measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge Dr G Latunde-Dada for her guidance and expertise with the cell transfection and siRNA experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>A.P.B. holds an Engineering and Physical Science Research Council (UK) Advanced Research fellowship (EP/E059678/1). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>1 TheilEC (2004) Iron, ferritin, and nutrition. Annu Rev Nutr 24: 327-343. doi:10.1146/annurev.nutr.24.012003.132212. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15189124">15189124</ext-link>.15189124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>2 SharpPA (2010) Intestinal iron absorption: regulation by dietary &amp; systemic factors. Int J Vitam Nutr Res 80: 231-242. doi:10.1024/0300-9831/a000029. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21462105">21462105</ext-link>.21462105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>3 KalgaonkarS, LönnerdalB (2009) Receptor-mediated uptake of ferritin-bound iron by human intestinal Caco-2 cells. J Nutr Biochem 20: 304-311. doi:10.1016/j.jnutbio.2008.04.003. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18602806">18602806</ext-link>.18602806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>4 SimpsonRJ, PetersTJ (1990) Forms of soluble iron in mouse stomach and duodenal lumen: significance for mucosal uptake. Br J Nutr 63: 79-89. doi:10.1079/BJN19900093. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2317479">2317479</ext-link>.2317479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>5 DoreyC, CooperC, DicksonDP, GibsonJF, SimpsonRJ et al. (1993) Iron speciation at physiological pH in media containing ascorbate and oxygen. Br J Nutr 70: 157-169. doi:10.1079/BJN19930113. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8399098">8399098</ext-link>.8399098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>6 HopplerM, SchönbächlerA, MeileL, HurrellRF, WalczykT (2008) Ferritin-iron is released during boiling and in vitro gastric digestion. J Nutr 138: 878-884. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18424595">18424595</ext-link>.18424595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>7 Latunde-DadaGO, NealeRJ (1986) Availability of iron from foods- review. Food Technology 21: 255-268. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>8 CarpenterCE, UmmadiM (1995) Iron Status Alters the Adsorption, Uptake, and Absorption Capacities of Rat Duodenum for Ferrous and Ferric Iron. Nutrition Research 15: 1129-1138. doi:10.1016/0271-5317(95)00072-Q. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>9 AndersonGJ, FrazerDM, McKieAT, VulpeCD, SmithA (2005) Mechanisms of haem and non-haem iron absorption: lessons from inherited disorders of iron metabolism. Biometals 18: 339-348. doi:10.1007/s10534-005-3708-8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16158226">16158226</ext-link>.16158226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>10 McKieAT, BarrowD, Latunde-DadaGO, RolfsA, SagerG et al. (2001) An iron-regulated ferric reductase associated with the absorption of dietary iron. Science 291: 1755-1759. doi:10.1126/science.1057206. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11230685">11230685</ext-link>.11230685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>11 MackenzieB, GarrickMD (2005) Iron Imports. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Iron uptake at the apical membrane in the intestine. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol 289: G981-G986. doi:10.1152/ajpgi.00363.2005. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16286504">16286504</ext-link>.16286504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>12 GunshinH, MackenzieB, BergerUV, GunshinY, RomeroMF et al. (1997) Cloning and characterization of a mammalian proton-coupled metal-ion transporter. Nature 388: 482-488. doi:10.1038/41343. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9242408">9242408</ext-link>.9242408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>13 McKieAT (2008) The role of Dcytb in iron metabolism: an update. Biochem Soc Trans 36: 1239-1241. doi:10.1042/BST0361239. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19021532">19021532</ext-link>.19021532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>14 FlynnCM (1984) Hydrolysis of Inorganic Iron(III) Salts. Chem Rev 84: 31-41. doi:10.1021/cr00059a003. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>15 PowellJJ, WhiteheadMW, AinleyCC, KendallMD, NicholsonJK et al. (1999) Dietary minerals in the gastrointestinal tract: hydroxypolymerisation of aluminium is regulated by luminal mucins. J Inorg Biochem 75: 167-180. doi:10.1016/S0162-0134(99)00094-X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10474202">10474202</ext-link>.10474202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>16 ConradME, UmbreitJN, MooreEG (1991) A role for mucin in the absorption of inorganic iron and other metal cations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>A study in rats. Gastroenterology 100: 129-136. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1983814">1983814</ext-link>.1983814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>17 BernerLA, MillerDD, Van CampenD (1986) Absorption of iron from ferric hydroxide polymers introduced into ligated rat duodenal segments. J Nutr 116: 259-264. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3944661">3944661</ext-link>.3944661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>18 SimovichM, HainsworthLN, FieldsPA, UmbreitJN, ConradME (2003) Localization of the iron transport proteins Mobilferrin and DMT-1 in the duodenum: the surprising role of mucin. Am J Hematol 74: 32-45. doi:10.1002/ajh.10383. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12949888">12949888</ext-link>.12949888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>19 PowellJJ, JugdaohsinghR, ThompsonRP (1999) The regulation of mineral absorption in the gastrointestinal tract. Proc Nutr Soc 58: 147-153. doi:10.1079/PNS19990020. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10343352">10343352</ext-link>.10343352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>20 WebbJ, MultaniJS, SaltmanP, GrayHB (1973) Spectroscopic and magnetic studies of iron(3) gastroferrin. Biochemistry 12: 265-267. doi:10.1021/bi00726a014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4683000">4683000</ext-link>.4683000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>21 MultaniJS, CepurneekCP, DavisPS, SaltmanP (1970) Biochemical characterization of gastroferrin. Biochemistry 9: 3970-3976. doi:10.1021/bi00822a015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/5501652">5501652</ext-link>.5501652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>22 DavisPS, MultaniJS, CepurneekCP, SaltmanP (1969) Isolation of gastroferrin from human gastric juice. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 37: 532-537. doi:10.1016/0006-291X(69)90948-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/5356534">5356534</ext-link>.5356534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>23 DellerDJ, EdwardsRG, DartG, LukeCG, DavisPS (1969) Gastric iron binding substance (gastroferrin) in a family with haemochromatosis. Australas Ann Med 18: 36-42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/5776898">5776898</ext-link>.5776898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>24 LukeCG, DavisPS, DellerDJ (1967) Change in gastric iron-binding protein (gastroferrin) during iron-deficiency anaemia. Lancet 1: 926-927. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4164401">4164401</ext-link>.4164401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>25 DressmanJB, BerardiRR, DermentzoglouLC, RussellTL, SchmaltzSP et al. (1990) Upper gastrointestinal (GI) pH in young, healthy men and women. Pharm Res 7: 756-761. doi:10.1023/A:1015827908309. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2395805">2395805</ext-link>.2395805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>26 RudzkiZ, BakerRJ, DellerDJ (1973) The iron-binding glycoprotein of human gastric juice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Nature of the interaction of the glycoprotein with iron. Digestion 8: 53-67. doi:10.1159/000197300. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4776489">4776489</ext-link>.4776489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>27 JamborJL, DutrizacJE (1998) Occurrence and Constitution of Natural and Synthetic Ferrihydrite, a Widespread Iron Oxyhydroxide. Chem Rev 98: 2549-2586. doi:10.1021/cr970105t. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11848971">11848971</ext-link>.11848971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>28 CornellRL, SchwertmannU (2003) The iron oxides: structure, preparation, reactions, occurrences and uses Weinham. Wiley-VCH. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>29 RudzkiZ, DellerDJ (1973) The iron-binding glycoprotein of human gastric juice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Isolation and characterization. Digestion 8: 35-52. doi:10.1159/000197299. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4776488">4776488</ext-link>.4776488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>30 PowellJ, BruggraberS, FariaN, PereiraD (2008) Ligand modified poly oxo-hydroxy metal ion materials, their uses and processes for their preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>In: Organization WIP, editor. U.K.  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>31 MerglerBI (2012) Enterocyte uptake of nanoparticulate iron(III) oxo-hydroxide [PhD Thesis]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>U.K.: University of Cambridge. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>32 Vanden BroeckD, De WolfMJ (2006) Selective blocking of clathrin-mediated endocytosis by RNA interference: epsin as target protein. BioTechniques 41: 475-484. doi:10.2144/000112265. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17068964">17068964</ext-link>.17068964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>33 IvanovAI (2008) Pharmacological inhibition of endocytic pathways: is it specific enough to be useful? Methods Mol Biol 440: 15-33. doi:10.1007/978-1-59745-178-9_2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18369934">18369934</ext-link>.18369934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>34 VercauterenD, VandenbrouckeRE, JonesAT, RejmanJ, DemeesterJ et al. (2010) The use of inhibitors to study endocytic pathways of gene carriers: optimization and pitfalls. Mol Ther 18: 561-569. doi:10.1038/mt.2009.281. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20010917">20010917</ext-link>.20010917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>35 San MartinCD, GarriC, PizarroF, WalterT, TheilEC et al. (2008) Caco-2 intestinal epithelial cells absorb soybean ferritin by mu2 (AP2)-dependent endocytosis. J Nutr 138: 659-666. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18356317">18356317</ext-link>.18356317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>36 GrattonSE, RoppPA, PohlhausPD, LuftJC, MaddenVJ et al. (2008) The effect of particle design on cellular internalization pathways. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105: 11613-11618. doi:10.1073/pnas.0801763105. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18697944">18697944</ext-link>.18697944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>37 ConteMP, PetroneG, LonghiC, ValentiP, MorelliR et al. (1996) The effects of inhibitors of vacuolar acidification on the release of Listeria monocytogenes from phagosomes of Caco-2 cells. J Med Microbiol 44: 418-424. doi:10.1099/00222615-44-6-418. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8636958">8636958</ext-link>.8636958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>38 PohlmannR, KrügerS, HasilikA, von FiguraK (1984) Effect of monensin on intracellular transport and receptor-mediated endocytosis of lysosomal enzymes. Biochem J 217: 649-658. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6231917">6231917</ext-link>.6231917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>39 MollenhauerHH, MorréDJ, RoweLD (1990) Alteration of intracellular traffic by monensin; mechanism, specificity and relationship to toxicity. Biochim Biophys Acta 1031: 225-246. doi:10.1016/0304-4157(90)90008-Z. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2160275">2160275</ext-link>.2160275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>40 JanneyDE, CowleyJM, BuseckPR (2000) Structure of synthetic 2-line ferrihydrite by electron nanodiffraction. American Mineralogist 85: 1180-1187. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>41 PanYH, VaughanG, BrydsonR, BlelochA, GassM et al. (2010) Electron-beam-induced reduction of Fe(3+) in iron phosphate dihydrate, ferrihydrite, haemosiderin and ferritin as revealed by electron energy-loss spectroscopy. Ultramicroscopy 110: 1020-1032. doi:10.1016/j.ultramic.2010.01.008. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>42 HarveyRS, ReffittDM, DoigLA, MeenanJ, EllisRD et al. (1998) Ferric trimaltol corrects iron deficiency anaemia in patients intolerant of iron. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 12: 845-848. doi:10.1046/j.1365-2036.1998.00380.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9768526">9768526</ext-link>.9768526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>43 KempSJ, ThorleyAJ, GorelikJ, SecklMJ, O'HareMJ et al. (2008) Immortalization of human alveolar epithelial cells to investigate nanoparticle uptake. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol 39: 591-597. doi:10.1165/rcmb.2007-0334OC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18539954">18539954</ext-link>.18539954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>44 SmithPJ, GiroudM, WigginsHL, GowerF, ThorleyJA et al. (2012) Cellular entry of nanoparticles via serum sensitive clathrin-mediated endocytosis, and plasma membrane permeabilization. Int J Nanomedicine 7: 2045-2055. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22619541">22619541</ext-link>.22619541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>45 GuignotJ, Bernet-CamardMF, PoüsC, PlançonL, Le BouguenecC et al. (2001) Polarized entry of uropathogenic Afa/Dr diffusely adhering Escherichia coli strain IH11128 into human epithelial cells: evidence for alpha5beta1 integrin recognition and subsequent internalization through a pathway involving caveolae and dynamic unstable microtubules. Infect Immun 69: 1856-1868. doi:10.1128/IAI.69.3.1856-1868.2001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11179364">11179364</ext-link>.11179364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>46 RejmanJ, OberleV, ZuhornIS, HoekstraD (2004) Size-dependent internalization of particles via the pathways of clathrin- and caveolae-mediated endocytosis. Biochem J 377: 159-169. doi:10.1042/BJ20031253. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14505488">14505488</ext-link>.14505488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>47 YangH, WangY, LaiS, AnH, LiY et al. (2007) Application of atomic force microscopy as a nanotechnology tool in food science. J Food Sci 72: R65-R75. doi:10.1111/j.1750-3841.2006.00218.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17995783">17995783</ext-link>.17995783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>48 ZhangSL, LiJ, LykotrafitisG, BaoG, SureshS (2009) Size-Dependent Endocytosis of Nanoparticles. Advanced Materials 21: 419-424. doi:10.1002/adma.200801393. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19606281">19606281</ext-link>.19606281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>49 OhJM, ChoiSJ, LeeGE, KimJE, ChoyJH (2009) Inorganic Metal Hydroxide Nanoparticles for Targeted Cellular Uptake Through Clathrin-Mediated Endocytosis. Chem Asian J 4: 67-73. doi:10.1002/asia.200800290. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18988236">18988236</ext-link>.18988236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>50 SkotlandT, SontumPC, OulieI (2002) In vitro stability analyses as a model for metabolism of ferromagnetic particles (Clariscan), a contrast agent for magnetic resonance imaging. J Pharm Biomed Anal 28: 323-329. doi:10.1016/S0731-7085(01)00592-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11929675">11929675</ext-link>.11929675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>51 AnwarK, KaydenHJ, HussainMM (2006) Transport of vitamin E by differentiated Caco-2 cells. J Lipid Res 47: 1261-1273. doi:10.1194/jlr.M500523-JLR200. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16569910">16569910</ext-link>.16569910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>52 FieldFJ, BornE, MurthyS, MathurSN (1998) Transport of cholesterol from the endoplasmic reticulum to the plasma membrane is constitutive in CaCo-2 cells and differs from the transport of plasma membrane cholesterol to the endoplasmic reticulum. J Lipid Res 39: 333-343. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9507994">9507994</ext-link>.9507994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>53 SaermarkT, GratzlM (1986) Na+/Ca2+ exchange in coated microvesicles. Biochem J 233: 643-648. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2939825">2939825</ext-link>.2939825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>54 SubramanianVS, MarchantJS, BoulwareMJ, MaTY, SaidHM (2009) Membrane targeting and intracellular trafficking of the human sodium-dependent multivitamin transporter in polarized epithelial cells. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol 296: C663-C671. doi:10.1152/ajpcell.00396.2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19211916">19211916</ext-link>.19211916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>55 GarciaMN, FlowersC, CookJD (1996) The Caco-2 cell culture system can be used as a model to study food iron availability. J Nutr 126: 251-258. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8558308">8558308</ext-link>.8558308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>56 GlahnRP, JinF, RutzkeM, WelchRM (2006) Iron bioavailability from ferritin as measured via an in vitro digestion/Caco-2 cell culture model. FASEB Journal 20: A130-A131. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>57 GlahnRP, LeeOA, YeungA, GoldmanMI, MillerDD (1998) Caco-2 cell ferritin formation predicts nonradiolabeled food iron availability in an in vitro digestion/Caco-2 cell culture model. J Nutr 128: 1555-1561. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9732319">9732319</ext-link>.9732319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>58 GlahnRP, WienEM, Van CampenDR, MillerDD (1996) Caco-2 cell iron uptake from meat and casein digests parallels in vivo studies: use of a novel in vitro method for rapid estimation of iron bioavailability. J Nutr 126: 332-339. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8558319">8558319</ext-link>.8558319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>59 KalgaonkarS, LönnerdalB (2008) Effects of dietary factors on iron uptake from ferritin by Caco-2 cells. J Nutr Biochem 19: 33-39. doi:10.1016/j.jnutbio.2007.02.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17509858">17509858</ext-link>.17509858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>60 Alvarez-HernandezX, NicholsGM, GlassJ (1991) Caco-2 cell line: a system for studying intestinal iron transport across epithelial cell monolayers. Biochim Biophys Acta 1070: 205-208. doi:10.1016/0005-2736(91)90165-5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1751528">1751528</ext-link>.1751528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>61 ArturssonP (1990) Epithelial transport of drugs in cell culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>I: A model for studying the passive diffusion of drugs over intestinal absorptive (Caco-2) cells. J Pharm Sci 79: 476-482. doi:10.1002/jps.2600790604. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1975619">1975619</ext-link>.1975619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>62 WangSH, LeeCW, ChiouA, WeiPK (2010) Size-dependent endocytosis of gold nanoparticles studied by three-dimensional mapping of plasmonic scattering images. J Nanobiotechnology 8: 33. doi:10.1186/1477-3155-8-33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21167077">21167077</ext-link>.21167077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>63 AwaadA, NakamuraM, IshimuraK (2011) Imaging of size-dependent uptake and identification of novel pathways in mouse Peyer's patches using fluorescent organosilica particles. Nanomedicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>64 ConnerSD, SchmidSL (2003) Regulated portals of entry into the cell. Nature 422: 37-44. doi:10.1038/nature01451. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12621426">12621426</ext-link>.12621426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>65 LeitchGJ, WardTL, ShawAP, NewmanG (2005) Apical spore phagocytosis is not a significant route of infection of differentiated enterocytes by Encephalitozoon intestinalis. Infect Immun 73: 7697-7704. doi:10.1128/IAI.73.11.7697-7704.2005. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16239574">16239574</ext-link>.16239574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>66 YamauchiKE, SnelJ (2000) Transmission electron microscopic demonstration of phagocytosis and intracellular processing of segmented filamentous bacteria by intestinal epithelial cells of the chick ileum. Infect Immun 68: 6496-6504. doi:10.1128/IAI.68.11.6496-6504.2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11035767">11035767</ext-link>.11035767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>67 Vanden BroeckD, De WolfMJ (2006) Selective blocking of clathrin-mediated endocytosis by RNA interference: epsin as target protein. BioTechniques 41: 475-484. doi:10.2144/000112265. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17068964">17068964</ext-link>.17068964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>68 RothbergKG, HeuserJE, DonzellWC, YingYS, GlenneyJR et al. (1992) Caveolin, a protein component of caveolae membrane coats. Cell 68: 673-682. doi:10.1016/0092-8674(92)90143-Z. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1739974">1739974</ext-link>.1739974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>69 GunshinH, FujiwaraY, CustodioAO, DirenzoC, RobineS et al. (2005) Slc11a2 is required for intestinal iron absorption and erythropoiesis but dispensable in placenta and liver. J Clin Invest 115: 1258-1266. doi:10.1172/JCI24356. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15849611">15849611</ext-link>.15849611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>70 AbouhamedM, GburekJ, LiuW, TorchalskiB, WilhelmA et al. (2006) Divalent metal transporter 1 in the kidney proximal tubule is expressed in late endosomes/lysosomal membranes: implications for renal handling of protein-metal complexes. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol 290: F1525-F1533. doi:10.1152/ajprenal.00359.2005. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16449358">16449358</ext-link>.16449358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>71 AndrewsNC (2000) Iron homeostasis: insights from genetics and animal models. Nat Rev Genet 1: 208-217. doi:10.1038/35043032. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11252750">11252750</ext-link>.11252750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>72 TabuchiM, YoshimoriT, YamaguchiK, YoshidaT, KishiF (2000) Human NRAMP2/DMT1, which mediates iron transport across endosomal membranes, is localized to late endosomes and lysosomes in HEp-2 cells. J Biol Chem 275: 22220-22228. doi:10.1074/jbc.M001478200. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10751401">10751401</ext-link>.10751401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>73 PanYH, SaderK, PowellJJ, BlelochA, GassM et al. (2009) 3D morphology of the human hepatic ferritin mineral core: new evidence for a subunit structure revealed by single particle analysis of HAADF-STEM images. J Struct Biol 166: 22-31. doi:10.1016/j.jsb.2008.12.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19116170">19116170</ext-link>.19116170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>74 ZhangY, MikhaelM, XuD, LiY, Soe-LinS et al. (2010) Lysosomal proteolysis is the primary degradation pathway for cytosolic ferritin and cytosolic ferritin degradation is necessary for iron exit. Antioxid Redox Signal 13: 999-1009. doi:10.1089/ars.2010.3129. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20406137">20406137</ext-link>.20406137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>75 TheilEC, ChenH, MirandaC, JanserH, ElsenhansB et al. (2012) Absorption of iron from ferritin is independent of heme iron and ferrous salts in women and rat intestinal segments. J Nutr 142: 478-483. doi:10.3945/jn.111.145854. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22259191">22259191</ext-link>.22259191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>76 EkmekciogluC, MarktlW (1998) The effect of differentiation on the brush border membrane ferric reductase activity in Caco-2 cells. In Vitro Cell Dev Biol Anim 34: 674-676. doi:10.1007/s11626-998-0061-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9794217">9794217</ext-link>.9794217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>77 BravoSA, NielsenCU, AmstrupJ, FrokjaerS, BrodinB (2004) In-depth evaluation of Gly-Sar transport parameters as a function of culture time in the Caco-2 cell model. Eur J Pharm Sci 21: 77-86. doi:10.1016/S0928-0987(03)00205-7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14706814">14706814</ext-link>.14706814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
