<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3938772</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24587392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-43710</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune System Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject><subject>Immune Response</subject><subject>Immunoglobulins</subject><subject>Immunopathology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject><subject>Immune Response</subject><subject>Immunoglobulins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nephrology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chronic Kidney Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nutrition</subject><subj-group><subject>Micronutrient Deficiencies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Dietary Zinc Is a Key Environmental Modifier in the Progression of IgA Nephropathy </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Dietary Effect on IgA Nephropathy</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maiguma</surname><given-names>Masayuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Yusuke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Hitoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>Keiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>Masashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>Masahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomino</surname><given-names>Yasuhiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Division of Nephrology, Department of Internal Medicine, Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>Jörg Hermann</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>McGill University, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yasu@juntendo.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: YT YS M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Maiguma HS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Maiguma YS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Maiguma YS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Maiguma YS M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Muto KO MI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Maiguma YS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e90558</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Maiguma et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Maiguma et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>IgA nephropathy (IgAN) shows diverse epidemiological characteristics, resulting from both genetic and acquired (e.g., environmental) causes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Environmental factors, such as diet or exposure to exogenous antigens, may prescribe the progression or prognosis of IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>It remains unclear as to how diet and infection influence susceptibility to IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A relationship, such as Toll-like receptors (TLRs), especially TLR9 and TLR4, was demonstrated between IgAN and pathogen-recognition molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Recently, zinc (Zn) was discovered to be involved in various immune-related diseases, affecting B, T, and dendritic cells (DCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This study investigates the relationship between dietary Zn and IgAN development in IgAN-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Seven-week-old IgAN-prone mice were divided into low, normal, and high Zn diet groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>To assess exogenous pathogen-mediated immune responses, lipopolysaccharide (LPS) was nasally administered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The activity of IgAN was biochemically and pathologically evaluated during the disease course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>We also examined in vitro IgA production in spleen cells or in combinations of cocultured B, T, and DCs under various Zn conditions with or without LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Dietary conditioning with Zn affected serum immunoglobulins and urinary albumin levels, and mesangial deposition of IgA and IgG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Zn deficiency is associated with IgAN progression through the activation of the TLR4/TIR-domain-containing adapter-inducing interferon-β (TRIF), but not the TLR9, in DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Zn supplementation prevented disease aggravation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Our findings indicate that immune conditioning with dietary Zn alters nephritogenic IgA production after mucosal infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported in part by a Grant-in-Aid for Progressive Renal Diseases Research, Research on Intractable Disease, from the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare of Japan, by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number 23790957, by Strategic International Research Cooperative Program, Japan Science and Technology Agency (JST), and by a research grant from the Study Group on IgAN in Japan. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>First described by Berger et al. in 1968 [1], IgA nephropathy (IgAN) is the most common primary chronic glomerulonephritis worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Many factors, including mucosal infection [2], [3], genetic predisposition [4], diet [5], and hygiene [6], have been implicated in IgAN progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Johnson et al. [7] suggested that environmental factors, such as exposure to antigens, affect the immune system and explain the difference in IgAN prevalence between developing and industrial countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, despite long-term research, the precise mechanism by which environmental factors affect IgAN severity is poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The pathological impact of mucosal infection in IgAN has been established, as the disease is frequently exacerbated by upper respiratory or gastrointestinal infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A series of studies are underway focusing on Toll-like receptors (TLRs), which are evolutionarily conserved regulators of the innate immune response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>TLR activation may represent the final common pathway for exogenous antigens, which have a negative effect on the mucosa of patients with IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We have reported that IgAN severity correlates with splenic TLR9 expression in IgAN-prone mice [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In addition, nasal challenge with CpG DNA (a ligand of TLR9) exacerbated glomerular damage and was accompanied by increases in serum IgA concentration and mesangial IgA deposition in these mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>This suggested that mucosal stimulation of TLR may be linked, in part, to production of nephritogenic IgA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In patients with IgAN, the expression of tonsillar TLR9 and TLR9 single nucleotide polymorphisms was correlated with the efficacy of tonsillectomy and steroid pulse therapy [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Coppo et al. [10] reported a significant correlation between TLR4 expression on circulating mononuclear (CD14+) cells and the levels of proteinuria and the phases of clinical activity in patients with IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, TLR-mediated innate immunity may be significantly involved in IgAN progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the prevalence of IgAN markedly differs depending on geographic location, suggesting the importance of diet and socioeconomic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Donadio et al. [11] proposed that dietary supplementation with fish oils could benefit patients with immune-related renal diseases, including IgAN, lupus nephritis, and cyclosporine-induced nephrotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Coppo et al. [5] reported the influence of dietary gluten on primary IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>However, the alimentary effects on IgAN progression remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>An alimentary zinc (Zn) plays an important role in the functioning of the immune system [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Zn is a non-redox active ion essential for cell growth, development, and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In addition to its involvement with liver disease [13], growth retardation, and cognitive impairment, a Zn deficiency has many other negative effects [14], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Emerging data [16]–[18] revealed that Zn deficiency in humans was correlated with an increased susceptibility to bacterial and/or viral infections, suggesting that Zn is the one of the most important alimentary factors for immune responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Indeed, patients with Zn deficiency show defective cellular immunity, lymphopenia, and abnormalities in hematopoietic cells, including T cells [19], natural killer cells [20], and monocytes [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Stimulation with the TLR4 agonist LPS altered the expression of Zn transporters in the dendritic cells (DCs), thereby decreasing free intracellular Zn levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A Zn chelator mimicked the effects of LPS, whereas Zn supplementation or overexpression of the gene encoding Zip6, a Zn transporter whose expression is reduced by LPS, inhibited LPS-induced upregulation of the Class II major histocompatibility complex and costimulatory molecules [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These results suggest a functional linkage between TLR signaling and Zn homeostasis in DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, Zn deficiency may be involved in the pathogenesis of immune diseases via inappropriate immunological responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In fact, Zn deficiency is often observed in patients with autoimmune diseases [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, we hypothesized that dietary Zn levels are associated with susceptibility to IgAN via the modulation of the innate immune response in the mucosa, involving nephritogenic IgA production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we assessed this hypothesis in IgAN-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The “grouped ddY” (gddY) mice were established by selective mating of early-onset ddY mice for more than 20 generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>This resulted in a 100% incidence of severe disease at a young age [8], [23]–[25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The mice were maintained in an SPF room at the animal facility of Juntendo University, Tokyo, Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The experimental protocol of this study was approved by the Ethics Review Committee for Animal Experimentation of Juntendo University Faculty of Medicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Experimental Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The basal mouse diet included the original formulation (AIN-93G) recommended by the American Institute of Nutrition for rodent feeding studies [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Basal diets were amended to yield three experimental diets containing the following (per kg): </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>low Zn diet: 0 mg Zn; </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>normal Zn diet: 67 mg Zn; and </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>high Zn diet: 1000 mg Zn. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>All diets were obtained from Oriental Yeast, Tokyo, Japan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Female gddY mice at 7 weeks were randomly divided into three groups: low, normal, and high Zn diet groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To assess the exogenous pathogen-mediated immune response, 100 ng LPS (055:B5; Sigma, USA) or saline as a vehicle control was nasally administered to mice from each group four times every 12 h before sacrifice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A histological examination was performed on each of the 10 gddY mice at 13 weeks of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were obtained from the buccal vein at 7, 9, and 11 weeks of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Serum IgA, IgG, IgM, and IgA–IgG IC concentrations were measured using a sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kit (Bethyl Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Urinary samples were obtained once a week from 7 weeks of age and stored at −80°C until analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Urinary albumin and creatinine levels were measured by immunoassay (DCA 2000 system; Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics, Tokyo, Japan) [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Kidneys were obtained after perfusion with normal saline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Renal specimens were mounted in an optimal cutting temperature (OCT) compound (Sakura Finetek, Tokyo, Japan) and stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Specimens embedded in the OCT compound were cut into 3-µm sections and fixed with acetone at −20°C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>IgA and IgG were stained by immunofluorescent staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In brief, the sections were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), blocked with a blocking agent (DS Pharma Biomedical, Osaka, Japan) at room temperature for 30 min, and incubated with DyLight 488-conjugated goat anti-murine IgA (Bethyl laboratories, Texas, USA) and Alexa 555-conjugated goat anti-murine IgG (Invitrogen AG, Basel, Switzerland) antibodies at room temperature for 120 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>After three washing with PBS, the slides were mounted with a mounting medium (Dako, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Samples were analyzed and imaged using confocal laser microscopy (Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For the semi-quantitative analysis of the glomerular deposition of IgA or IgG, more than 10 glomeruli/cross section were observed and the following scores were assigned: 1 point, no glomerular deposition; 2 points, trivial glomerular deposition; 3 points, mild glomerular deposition; 4 points, moderate glomerular deposition; 5 points, severe glomerular deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The deposition score was calculated as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Culture of Spleen Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The spleen was enucleated under aseptic conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Spleen cell suspensions were prepared by compression with the handle of a syringe in a Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 1640 medium, followed by passage through a 100-µm nylon mesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Red blood cells were removed by incubation with a Red Blood Cell Lysing Buffer (R7757; Sigma, USA) at room temperature for 1 min, followed by washing in a RPMI-1640 medium [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>B cells, T cells, and DCs were isolated from the spleens of gddY mice using CD19 MicroBeads, a Pan T Cell Isolation Kit, and Pan DC MicroBeads (MACS; Milteny Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We used N,N,N′,N′-tetrakis (2-pyridylmethyl) ethylenediamine (TPEN) [22], a Zn chelator, to create low Zn conditions, and ZnSO4 with pyrithione to create high Zn conditions [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>LPS (055:B5) and TPEN,2,2′-dithiodipyridine (D-5767) were obtained from Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Pyrithione (2-mercaptopyridine N-oxide; P-24193) was obtained from Invitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>An RPMI 1640 medium with 5 µM TPEN was used for the spleen cell culture under low Zn conditions [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>An RPMI 1640 medium with 5 µM ZnSO4 and 3 µM pyrithione was used for spleen cell culture under high Zn conditions [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>IgA production by individual combinations of spleen cells was measured by ELISA after 48 h incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the viability of B cells in each Zn condition, we cultured splenic B cells with anti-CD40 antibody (553721; BD Pharmingen, Tokyo, Japan) and anti-IgM antibody (115-006-020; Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Pennsylvania, USA) and then used the Cell Counting Kit-8 (Dojindo Laboratories, Tokyo, Japan) to quantify the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Real-time Reverse Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>RNA from spleen cells was purified with an RNeasy Mini Kit (74106; Qiagen, USA) after Zn conditioning or LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) and a 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems) were used for the quantitative polymerase chain reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Transcript levels were normalized to those of the glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (Gapdh) gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences used were as follows: mouse TLR4, TGGCACTGTTCTTCTCCTGCCT and GGAATGTCATCAGGGACTTTGCTGA; mouse TLR9, TCTCCCAACATGGTTCTCCGTCG and TGCAGTCCAGGCCATGA; mouse MyD88, GCACCTGTGTCTGGTCCATT and CTGTTGGACACCTGGAGACA; mouse TRIF, TCTCTCCTCCTCCTCCAGCA and CGTCCCCTGCTGCAAAGAT; mouse interferon-β, GTCCTCAACTGCTCTCCACT and CCAGGCGTAGCTGTTGTACT; and mouse GAPDH, CATTGTGGAAGGGCTCATGA and TCTTCTGGGTGGCAGTGATG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The correlation between different parameters was analyzed using analysis of variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as the mean ± standard deviation or median values. p values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism version 6.0 for Windows (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Effect of Dietary Zinc in the IgAN Model Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We divided IgAN-prone gddY mice into three dietary groups (low, normal, and high Zn diet groups) and assessed IgAN progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Serum Zn concentrations significantly differed between the groups from the fourth week after dietary intervention (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>As expected, body weight gain was suppressed in the low Zn diet group because of growth retardation caused by the Zn deficiency (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Symptoms such as diarrhea were not caused by the high Zn diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Liver dysfunction was not observed in any dietary group at the 6th week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To avoid various redundant negative effects of a long-term Zn deficiency, such as growth retardation or severe immunodeficiency, we evaluated IgAN activity in the sixth week after intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Physiological effect of dietary zinc intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(A) Changes in serum zinc (Zn) concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Serum Zn concentrations were significantly different in each group from the fourth week after dietary intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(B) Changes in body weights. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Significant body weight gain was suppressed in the low Zn diet group. *p&lt;0.05; ***p&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Dietary Zinc Affects the Severity of Murine IgAN </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The number of splenic B cells was not different among each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>However, the serum concentrations of IgG, IgA, IgM, and IgA–IgG ICs in the low and normal Zn diet groups increased during the course of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, a significant suppression of serum IgA (p&lt;0.05) and IgA–IgG ICs (p&lt;0.05) was observed in the high Zn diet group in the sixth week (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Serum concentration of immunoglobulins for each dietary zinc condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Dietary zinc intervention altered the serum concentrations of IgA and IgA–IgG immune complexes but not of IgG and IgM. *p&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Urinary albumin levels in the low Zn diet group were significantly higher than that in the normal and high Zn diet groups (vs. normal Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; vs. high Zn diet group: p&lt;0.01) in the sixth week (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The intensity of glomerular IgA deposition in the high Zn diet group in the sixth week was significantly lower than that in the other groups (vs. normal Zn diet group: p&lt;0.01; vs. low Zn diet group: p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the low Zn diet group exhibited significantly higher IgG deposition in the glomeruli than the other groups (vs. normal Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; vs. high Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Urinary albumin levels for each dietary zinc condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Urinary levels of albumin were significantly higher in the low zinc (Zn) diet group and lower in the high Zn diet group on the sixth week. *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Intensity of mesangial IgA and IgG deposition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The intensity of IgA and IgG deposition was scored on a 1–5 scale based on an average of more than 10 glomeruli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>IgA deposition was significantly attenuated in the high zinc (Zn) diet group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>IgG deposition in the low Zn diet group was significantly higher than that in the normal and high Zn diet groups. *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Toll-like Receptor 4 Stimulation Accelerates Murine IgAN Progression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>To investigate whether dietary Zn levels influenced the mucosal TLR-mediated aggravation of IgAN, we performed nasal challenges with CpG DNA and LPS in each dietary group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The effect of the nasal challenge with CpG DNA against serum immunoglobulins (IgG, IgA, IgM, and IgA–IgG ICs) and urinary albumin were not different in each dietary group (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Although all mice in each dietary group showed an aggravation of IgAN after nasal LPS stimulation, increased albuminuria was more pronounced in the low Zn diet group (p&lt;0.05), with a greater increase in serum concentrations of IgA (p&lt;0.07) and IgA–IgG ICs (p&lt;0.05; Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the changes in the serum concentrations of IgA and IgA–IgG ICs after LPS stimulation was clearly suppressed in the high Zn diet group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that dietary Zn levels influence the TLR4-mediated progression of murine IgAN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Reactivity against lipopolysaccharide. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Lipopolysaccharide (LPS) was nasally administered to some mice in each dietary group, while others received saline as a vehicle control; samples were collected during the sixth week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We calculated the ratio (sixth:fourth week) of each parameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Although ACR in all groups increased after LPS stimulation, the elevation in the low zinc (Zn) diet group was very high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Serum concentrations of IgA and IgA–IgG immune complexes (ICs) in the low and normal Zn diet groups tended to be higher after LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, the high Zn diet group maintained low concentrations of serum IgA and IgA–IgG ICs despite LPS stimulation. *p&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Zinc Regulation Affects IgA Production by Spleen Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>To further assess the association between dietary Zn levels and IgA production, we examined IgA production by spleen cells for each Zn level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In the absence of LPS, IgA production by spleen cells in low Zn conditions was significantly higher than those under normal (p&lt;0.001) and high (p&lt;0.001) Zn conditions (Figure 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these different levels of IgA production in each Zn condition were independent of the viability of B cells (Figure 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Under normal and low Zn conditions, IgA production tended to be higher in the presence of LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, under high Zn conditions, serum IgA concentration remained at a low level despite the presence of LPS (Figure 6C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>IgA production by whole spleen cells for each zinc condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>(A) Production of IgA was significantly higher in the low zinc (Zn) diet group and lower in the high Zn diet group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>(B) The viability of splenic B cells in each Zn condition was not significantly different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(C) Reactivity against lipopolysaccharide (LPS) in each Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In the normal and low Zn diet groups, IgA production tended to be higher in the presence of LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>However, in the high Zn diet group, serum IgA concentration remained at a low level despite of the presence of LPS. *p&lt;0.05; ***p&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>B cells, T cells, and DCs were isolated from spleen cells to further investigate the influence of Zn on each cell type and their interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>As expected, IgA production by B cells increased when cocultured with T cells and/or DCs (Figure 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Under low Zn conditions, IgA production was significantly increased in the presence of DCs, suggesting that elevated IgA production under low Zn conditions is mainly mediated by B cell – DC interaction (Figure 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In contrast, under high Zn conditions, IgA production was suppressed in all cell combinations (Figure 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Similar results were evident when we cultured untreated B cells with T cells and/or DCs from low Zn conditions (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In addition, LPS significantly enhanced IgA production when cocultured with DCs (p&lt;0.001), confirming that DCs activated by LPS directly increase IgA production in a T cell-independent manner (Figure 7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, when we cocultured B cells and DCs from gddY or BALB/c mice, a combination of both B cells and DCs from gddY mice showed the highest levels of IgA production (Figure 7E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the production of nephritogenic IgA by gddY mice is due to a functional abnormality of both B cells and DCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>IgA production by various spleen cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>(A) IgA production by B cells increased when cocultured with T cells and/or dendritic cells (DCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(B) Under low zinc (Zn) conditions, IgA production was significantly increased in the presence of DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Under high Zn conditions, IgA production by all cell combinations was suppressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(C) Coculture of untreated B cells with low Zn-treated T cells and/or DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>IgA production increased in the presence of DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(D) Coculture of B cells and DCs with or without lipopolysaccharide (LPS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>LPS significantly enhanced IgA production despite the absence of T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>(E) Coculture of B cells and DCs from gddY or BALB/c mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A combination of both B cells and DCs from gddY mice yielded the highest production of IgA. **p&lt;0.01; ***p&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Expression levels of TLR4 and TLR9 in DCs for each Zn level were checked with or without LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The expression of TLR9 was unaffected by Zn or LPS stimulation (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the expression of TLR4 significantly increased under LPS stimulation under low (p&lt;0.05) and normal (p&lt;0.01) Zn conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>However, TLR4 expression under high Zn conditions was attenuated, even in the presence of LPS (vs. normal Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; vs. low Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; Figure 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>We also examined the expression of MyD88 and TIR-domain-containing adapter-inducing interferon-β (TRIF), which are key signaling molecules of TLR4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Although the expression of MyD88 was unaffected by Zn (Figure 8B), the expression of TRIF under low Zn conditions was significantly upregulated (vs. normal Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; vs. high Zn diet group: p&lt;0.05; Figure 8C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>To confirm the functional alteration of the TLR4/TRIF pathway caused by Zn, we examined the expression of interferon-β, which is specifically induced by the activation of the TRIF-dependent pathway following TLR4 activation [28], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The expression of interferon-β was higher in low Zn condition and lower in high Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(Figure 8D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0090558-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090558.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Expression of Toll-like receptor 4, MyD88, TRIF, and interferon-β in each zinc condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(A) Expression of Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) for each zinc (Zn) condition with/without lipopolysaccharide (LPS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Expression of TLR4 was significantly increased when stimulated by LPS under low and normal Zn conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, TLR4 expression under high Zn conditions was low despite LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(B) Expression of MyD88 at each Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Expression of MyD88 remained constant at each Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(C) Expression of TRIF for each Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Expression of TRIF under low Zn conditions was significantly higher than that in other groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>(D) Expression of interferon-β in each Zn condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Expression of interferon-β was higher in low Zn condition and lower in high Zn condition. *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0090558.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Environmental factors are considered to have an impact on susceptibility to IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Johnson et al. [7] assessed the geographic bias in the prevalence, from the perspective of the immunological effects of exposure to exogenous antigens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Moreover, diet may be involved in the pathogenesis of IgAN, as well as in other atopic diseases [30] considered to be associated with hygiene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>As dietary intervention is easy and has few adverse effects, clarifying the association between diet and such diseases through dietary intervention may represent an important step toward new potential treatments for IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, few reports, except for a small number on fish oil [11] and gluten [5], discuss the connection of diet and renal diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>It is difficult to identify one key factor among the vast number of nutritive components involved in diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focused on the immunological functions of Zn, an important component of the immune system, and investigated the relationship between dietary Zn levels and IgAN development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We discovered that the dietary Zn levels are critically involved in the immune process of nephritogenic IgA production by affecting the activity of DCs, especially through the TLR4/TRIF pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>We used IgAN-prone gddY mice, which exhibit the same renal phenotype and dysregulation of the systemic immune system as patients with IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We recently demonstrated that the renal prognosis of gddY mice may be linked to differences in sugar content or the O-glycosylation acceptor site of the IgA hinge region [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that the progression of this murine IgAN also may be dependent on the aberrantly glycosylated IgA, similar to that seen in human IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We previously reported that, in ddY mice under conventional conditions the serum concentrations of IgA, but not those of IgG and IgM, were significantly elevated relative to mice maintained under specific pathogen-free (SPF) conditions [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This study showed that Zn supplementation suppressed urinary albumin levels in association with a decrease in the serum concentrations of IgA and IgA–IgG ICs, but not those of IgG and IgM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>These findings led us to conclude that Zn-mediated mechanisms are specifically involved in the increased nephritogenic IgA production in response to mucosal exogenous antigens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In fact, the dietary Zn supplementation reduced mesangial IgA deposition, in association with decreasing concentrations of IgA and IgA–IgG ICs, even after mucosal LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>In contrast, low Zn levels worsened the course of the disease with or without LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the dietary Zn levels influence the mucosal immune response, including nephritogenic IgA production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The in vitro study confirmed the in vivo results: IgA production by splenocytes was increased at low Zn levels and decreased at high Zn levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the influence of Zn on IgA production was abrogated in the absence of DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>To avoid a direct effect of Zn on B cells, we cocultured untreated B cells with Zn-treated T cells and/or DCs and obtained similar results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that Zn regulation is associated with an immune reaction mediated by DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, DCs from gddY mice played a critical role in IgA production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The concentration of IgA production by B cells was higher when cocultured with DCs, irrespective of the presence of T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in a T cell-independent manner, DCs stimulated by LPS directly altered the IgA production by B cells (Figure 7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>It was also evident that DCs from gddY mice were capable of inducing higher levels of IgA production by B cells than the same number of DCs from BALB/c mice, even when cultured under the same conditions (Figure 7E), suggesting that DCs from gddY mice have an increased capacity to induce IgA production than those from BALB/c mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Next, we analyzed the effect of Zn and exogenous antigens on DCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We previously reported that the activation of the TLR9/MyD88 pathway on B cells or DCs is a critical determinant of IgAN severity [8], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>However, this study revealed that Zn affects the reactivity of TLR4, but not that of TLR9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assessed the expression of TLR4 in splenic DCs under various Zn and LPS conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Although LPS stimulation increased TLR4 expression by DCs under normal and low Zn conditions, there was little change in TLR4 expression by DCs under high Zn conditions, irrespective of LPS stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>This result is consistent with a previous report demonstrating that Zn homeostasis is involved in some DC maturation events and affects the magnitude of immune responses via the activation of TLR4 [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Each TLR triggers a specific biological response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>MyD88 is universally used by all TLRs except TLR3, and induces inflammatory cytokines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In contrast, TRIF is used by TLR3 and TLR4 only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>TLR4 is therefore the only TLR that activates both the MyD88 and TRIF signaling pathways [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>We investigated the expression of these two signaling molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Although MyD88 expression was unaltered at each Zn level, TRIF expression was significantly higher at low Zn levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>MyD88 induces inflammatory responses by activating NF-κB and MAPK, whereas TRIF recruits TRADD, TRAF6, and TRAF3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>TRADD and TRAF6 also lead to activation of MAPK and NF-κB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, TRAF3 activates some kinases, such as TBK1 and IKKi, and subsequently, IRF3, which is a key transcriptional factor for interferon-β [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Therefore, during TLR4 activation, interferon-β is specifically induced by the TRIF signaling pathway and not by the MyD88 signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The present study showed that expression levels of interferon-β and TRIF were both enhanced in low Zn conditions, indicating the involvement of Zn in the TRIF pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, although expression levels of TRIF were not significantly different, expression levels of interferon-β in high Zn conditions were lower than those in normal Zn conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that a high Zn condition may directly attenuate the activation of the downstream TRIF signaling pathway rather than TRIF expression itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>These findings are consistent with the in vivo and other in vitro experiments, and therefore, provide further support for the Zn effect on IgA production via the TLR4/TRIF pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In summary, we demonstrated that Zn alters nephritogenic IgA production and, thus, is critically involved in disease activity in murine IgAN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that diet, as a major environmental factor, plays an important role in the pathogenesis of IgAN, as well as in other immune-related diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Zn modulates IgA production by altering the activity of DCs, especially via TLR4/TRIF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In other words, dietary Zn levels may determine the susceptibility to environmental factors, such as exogenous antigens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>As a recent study demonstrated the clinical application of Zn supplements combined with other supplementation in immune-related diseases, including asthma, Zn supplementation represents a therapeutic strategy for preventing the progression or aggravation of IgAN [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>We thank Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Terumi Shibata for her excellent technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>We also thank Takako Ikegami and Tomomi Ikeda, Laboratory of Molecular and Biochemical Research, Research Support Center, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan, for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0090558-Berger1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>1 BergerJ, HinglaisN (1968) Intercapillary deposits of IgA-IgG. J Urol Nephrol (Paris) 74: 694–695.4180586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-DAmico1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>2 D’AmicoG (1987) The commonest glomerulonephritis in the world: IgA nephropathy. Q J Med 64: 709–727.3329736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Endo1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>3 EndoY, KanbayashiH (1994) Etiology of IgA nephropathy syndrome. Pathol Int 44: 1–13.8025643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Schena1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>4 SchenaFP, D’AltriC, CerulloG, MannoC, GesualdoL (2001) ACE gene polymorphism and IgA nephropathy: An ethnically homogeneous study and a meta-analysis. Kidney Int 60: 732–740.11473656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Coppo1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>5 CoppoR, BasoloB, RollinoC, RoccatelloD, MartinaG, et al (1986) Dietary gluten and primary IgA nephropathy. N Engl J Med 315: 1167–1168. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Coppo2"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>6 CoppoR (1988) The pathogenetic potential of environmental antigens in IgA nephropathy. Am J Kidney Dis 12: 420–424.3055968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Johnson1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>7 JohnsonRJ, HurtadoA, MerszeiJ, Rodriguez-IturbeB, FengL (2003) Hypothesis: Dysregulation of immunologic balance resulting from hygiene and socioeconomic factors may influence the epidemiology and cause of glomerulonephritis worldwide. Am J Kidney Dis 42: 575–581.12955687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Suzuki1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>8 SuzukiH, SuzukiY, NaritaI, AizawaM, KiharaM, et al (2008) Toll-like receptor 9 affects severity of IgA nephropathy. J Am Soc Nephrol 19: 2384–2395.18776126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Sato1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>9 SatoD, SuzukiY, KanoT, SuzukiH, MatsuokaJ, et al (2012) Tonsillar TLR9 expression and efficacy of tonsillectomy with steroid pulse therapy in IgA nephropathy patients. Nephrol Dial Transplant 27: 1090–1097.21778277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Coppo3"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>10 CoppoR, CamillaR, AmoreA, PeruzziL, DapraV, et al (2010) Toll-like receptor 4 expression is increased in circulating mononuclear cells of patients with immunoglobulin A nephropathy. Clin Exp Immunol 159: 73–81.19891659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Donadio1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>11 DonadioJVJr, GrandeJP, BergstralhEJ, DartRA, LarsonTS, et al (1999) The long-term outcome of patients with IgA nephropathy treated with fish oil in a controlled trial. mayo nephrology collaborative group. J Am Soc Nephrol 10: 1772–1777.10446945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Prasad1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>12 PrasadAS (1995) Zinc: An overview. Nutrition 11: 93–99.7749260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Mohammad1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>13 MohammadMK, ZhouZ, CaveM, BarveA, McClainCJ (2012) Zinc and liver disease. Nutr Clin Pract 27: 8–20.22307488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Siklar1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>14 SiklarZ, TunaC, DallarY, TanyerG (2003) Zinc deficiency: A contributing factor of short stature in growth hormone deficient children. J Trop Pediatr 49: 187–188.12848213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Ganss1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>15 GanssB, JheonA (2004) Zinc finger transcription factors in skeletal development. Crit Rev Oral Biol Med 15: 282–297.15470266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Prasad2"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>16 PrasadAS (1998) Zinc and immunity. Mol Cell Biochem 188: 63–69.9823012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Fraker1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>17 FrakerPJ, KingLE (2004) Reprogramming of the immune system during zinc deficiency. Annu Rev Nutr 24: 277–298.15189122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-FischerWalker1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>18 Fischer WalkerC, BlackRE (2004) Zinc and the risk for infectious disease. Annu Rev Nutr 24: 255–275.15189121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Hosea1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>19 HoseaHJ, RectorES, TaylorCG (2003) Zinc-deficient rats have fewer recent thymic emigrant (CD90+) T lymphocytes in spleen and blood. J Nutr 133: 4239–4242.14652378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Prasad3"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>20 PrasadAS (2000) Effects of zinc deficiency on Th1 and Th2 cytokine shifts. J Infect Dis 182 Suppl 1S62–8.10944485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Ibs1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>21 IbsKH, RinkL (2003) Zinc-altered immune function. J Nutr 133: 1452S–6S.12730441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Kitamura1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>22 KitamuraH, MorikawaH, KamonH, IguchiM, HojyoS, et al (2006) Toll-like receptor-mediated regulation of zinc homeostasis influences dendritic cell function. Nat Immunol 7: 971–977.16892068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Tomino1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>23 TominoY, ShimizuM, KoideH, AbeM, ShiraiT (1993) Effect of monoclonal antibody CD4 on glomerulonephritis of ddY mice, a spontaneous animal model of IgA nephropathy. Am J Kidney Dis 21: 427–432.8096678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Suzuki2"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>24 SuzukiH, SuzukiY, YamanakaT, HiroseS, NishimuraH, et al (2005) Genome-wide scan in a novel IgA nephropathy model identifies a susceptibility locus on murine chromosome 10, in a region syntenic to human IGAN1 on chromosome 6q22–23. J Am Soc Nephrol 16: 1289–1299.15772254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Okazaki1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>25 OkazakiK, SuzukiY, OtsujiM, SuzukiH, KiharaM, et al (2012) Development of a model of early-onset IgA nephropathy. J Am Soc Nephrol 23: 1364–1374.22797187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Reeves1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>26 ReevesPG, NielsenFH, FaheyGCJr (1993) AIN-93 purified diets for laboratory rodents: Final report of the american institute of nutrition ad hoc writing committee on the reformulation of the AIN-76A rodent diet. J Nutr 123: 1939–1951.8229312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Suzuki3"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>27 SuzukiH, SuzukiY, AizawaM, YamanakaT, KiharaM, et al (2007) Th1 polarization in murine IgA nephropathy directed by bone marrow-derived cells. Kidney Int 72: 319–327.17495863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Takeda1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>28 TakedaK, KaishoT, AkiraS (2003) Toll-like receptors. Annu Rev Immunol 21: 335–376.12524386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Kawai1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>29 KawaiT, AkiraS (2010) The role of pattern-recognition receptors in innate immunity: Update on toll-like receptors. Nat Immunol 11: 373–384.20404851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Hensel1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>30 HenselP (2010) Nutrition and skin diseases in veterinary medicine. Clin Dermatol 28: 686–693.21034992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Kajiyama1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>31 KajiyamaT, SuzukiY, KiharaM, SuzukiH, HorikoshiS, et al (2011) Different pathological roles of toll-like receptor 9 on mucosal B cells and dendritic cells in murine IgA nephropathy. Clin Dev Immunol 2011: 819646.21765852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0090558-Biltagi1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>32 BiltagiMA, BasetAA, BassiounyM, KasrawiMA, AttiaM (2009) Omega-3 fatty acids, vitamin C and zn supplementation in asthmatic children: A randomized self-controlled study. Acta Paediatr 98: 737–742.19154523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
