<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3316545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-10042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Classes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Protein Phosphatase 1 Dephosphorylates Profilin-1 at Ser-137 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Dephosphorylation of Profilin-1 by PP1</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Jieya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>Marc I.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Department of Neurology, School of Medicine, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>El-Rifai</surname><given-names>Wael</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Vanderbilt University Medical Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>shaoj@neuro.wustl.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: JS MID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: JS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: JS MID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JS MID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: JS MID. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e32802</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Shao, Diamond.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Profilin-1 (PFN1) plays an important role in the control of actin dynamics, and could represent an important therapeutic target in several diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We previously identified PFN1 as a huntingtin aggregation inhibitor, and others have implicated it as a tumor-suppressor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Rho-associated kinase (ROCK) directly phosphorylates PFN1 at Ser-137 to prevent its binding to polyproline sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This negatively regulates its anti-aggregation activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>However, the phosphatase that dephosphorylates PFN1 at Ser-137, and thus activates it, is unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Using a phospho-specific antibody against Ser-137 of PFN1, we characterized PFN1 dephosphorylation in cultured cells based on immunocytochemistry and a quantitative plate reader-based assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Both okadaic acid and endothall increased pS137-PFN1 levels at concentrations more consistent with their known IC50s for protein phosphatase 1 (PP1) than protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Knockdown of the catalytic subunit of PP1 (PP1Cα), but not PP2A (PP2ACα), increased pS137-PFN1 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>PP1Cα binds PFN1 in cultured cells, and this interaction was increased by a phosphomimetic mutation of PFN1 at Ser-137 (S137D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Together, these data define PP1 as the principal phosphatase for Ser-137 of PFN1, and provide mechanistic insights into PFN1 regulation by phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Profilins are small actin-binding proteins that are essential for all eukaryotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>They play a role in many cellular processes including cell motility, cytokinesis, gene transcription, endocytosis and neuronal plasticity [1], [2], [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These activities depend on their interactions with three major cellular ligands: globular actin (G-actin), polyproline-containing proteins, and phosphatidylinositols (e.g. phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate, PIP2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In mammals, four profilin isoforms have been identified, each encoded by a distinct gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Profilin-1 (PFN1) and profilin-2a (PFN2a), the classic “somatic” isoforms, are 65% identical in amino acid sequence, and highly conserved in 3D structure [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>PFN1 is ubiquitously expressed, while PFN2a, the major splice isoform of PFN2, is preferentially enriched in the brain [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Two testis-specific profilins, PFN3 and PFN4, are recently described, and differ substantially from PFN1 and PFN2a in their primary sequences [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Both PFN3 and PFN4 bind G-actin with lower affinity than PFN1 and PFN2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>PFN3 binds polyproline-ligands poorly, and PFN4 completely lacks this activity [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have linked profilins, in particular PFN1, to several human diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Our prior work identified PFN1 as an inhibitor of huntingtin aggregation, suggesting a role in the pathogenesis of Huntington Disease (HD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The anti-aggregation activity of PFN1 depends on its binding to both G-actin and a polyproline tract within huntingtin [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>PFN1 is also a putative tumor suppressor, and has been shown to inhibit tumor cell growth and metastasis in several cancer models [7], [8], [9], [10], [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Despite our detailed knowledge of profilin's structure and functions, we know little about how its cellular activities are regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>PFN1 is a phospho-protein in vivo [13], [14], suggesting that its activities could be regulated by phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We have previously determined that Ser-137 of PFN1 is a bona fide phosphorylation site for the Rho-associated kinase ROCK [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Ser-137 lies within the polyproline-binding site of PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Mimicking phosphorylation at this site abolishes PFN1's binding to huntingtin, and inhibits its activity as an aggregation suppressor [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this was the first study to link a specific phosphorylation event to defined cellular functions of PFN1, and to demonstrate that PFN1 activity is regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>While our prior work identified ROCK as an upstream kinase for Ser-137, it left uncertain which phosphatase mediates dephosphorylation of this site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>By exploiting a highly sensitive and specific PFN1 antibody against pSer-137, we now provide pharmacological, genetic and biochemical evidence that protein phosphatase-1 (PP1) exists in the same protein complex with PFN1 and dephosphorylates Ser-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>P3490 specifically recognizes pS137-PFN1 in situ </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We previously generated a polyclonal phospho-specific antibody against pSer-137 of PFN1 (P3490). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Using this antibody, we previously determined by Western blot (WB) that pS137-PFN1 levels in cultured cells are regulated by RhoA/ROCK signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The RhoA activator lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) mildly increased pS137-PFN1 levels in cultured cells, which was blocked by the ROCK inhibitor Y-27632 [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>To directly characterize the phospho-specificity of this antibody, we pre-incubated P3490 with antigenic peptides containing (pS137) or lacking a phosphate on Ser-137 (S137), followed by WB to determine if its reactivity with cellular PFN1 was affected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The pS137-peptide completely blocked P3490 binding to PFN1 (Fig. 1A) as expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>However, the non-phospho S137-peptide effectively blocked 90% of the PFN1 signal versus the no peptide control (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus, P3490 contains pan-antibodies that react with unphosphorylated PFN1, and the bulk of the observed PFN1 signal likely represents cross-reactivity with unphosphorylated PFN1 molecules that outnumber those of phospho-PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This limits the fidelity of P3490 to accurately report pS137-PFN1 levels via WB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0032802-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In situ staining of mammalian cells by pSer-137-PFN1 antibody P3490 is responsive to RhoA/ROCK signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A, Equal amounts of HEK293 cell lysate were separated on SDS-PAGE, and individual lanes were blotted with P3490 that was pre-incubated with no peptide (Lane 1), or PFN1 peptides containing unphosphorylated (Lane 2) or phosphorylated Ser-137 (Lane 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>PFN1-pS137 peptide completely blocked the binding of P3490 to PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Unphosphorylated PFN1-S137 peptide blocked ∼90% binding vs. the no peptide control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Total PFN1 (on a separate and identically loaded gel) and actin levels were confirmed as being equal across all lanes. B, P3490 stains the cytoplasm of multiple cell lines in a heterogeneous fashion, including HEK293, HeLa and NIH 3T3 (in green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>DAPI was used as counterstain (in blue). C, Immunostaining of HEK293 cells with P3490 (green) was unaffected by pre-incubation with the unphosphorylated PFN1-S137 peptide, but was completely inhibited by the phosphorylated PFN1-pS137 peptide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>DAPI staining is shown in blue. D, NIH 3T3 cells were serum-starved for 16 hr in the absence or presence of 50 µM Y-27632, followed by treatment with 10 µM Lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) for 60 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Cells were immunostained with P3490 (green) and counterstained with DAPI (blue) (a–c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>LPA increased P3490 staining, which was blocked by the pretreatment with Y-27632. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Total PFN1 levels were unaffected by these treatments as indicated by immunostaining with a generic PFN1 antibody (PFN1 in green and DAPI in blue) (d–l). E, HEK293 cells were treated with or without 50 µM hydroxyfasudil (OH-fasudil) for 2 hr, followed by immunostaining with P3490 (a–b) or the generic PFN1 antibody (c–d) (both in green) and counterstaining with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Nearly all cells treated with OH-fasudil became P3490-negative without changes in their total PFN1 levels. F, HEK293 cells grown in a 96-well plate were treated for 24 hr with increasing concentrations of OH-fasudil (1, 3, 10, 50 µM), immunostained with P3490 and Alexa Fluor®488-labeled secondary antibody, and counterstained with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence intensity was quantified on a fluorescence plate reader. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>P3490 staining was normalized vs. DAPI to control for cell numbers, and the effects of OH-fasudil were calculated as relative values as compared to the untreated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>OH-fasudil reduced P3490 staining dose-dependently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032802.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Due to the limitation of P3490 associated with WB, we tested if it can detect pS137-PFN1 in situ by immunocytochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>P3490 heterogeneously stained several cell lines (predominantly the cytoplasm), i.e. not all cells were positive at the same time (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The cause for this staining pattern of P3490 is unclear, but could either reflect individual variation among cells, or cell cycle dependence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Cell staining by P3490 was completely inhibited by its pre-incubation with the pS137-peptide, but was unaffected by the unphosphorylated S137-peptide (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>This contrasted the results on WB, and suggested that P3490 is highly phospho-specific when used for in situ cell staining, in which the pan-antibodies are nonreactive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In serum-starved NIH 3T3 cells, the RhoA activator lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) markedly increased the number of P3490-positive cells, and this was blocked by ROCK inhibition with Y-27632 (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Hydroxyfasudil (OH-fasudil), a ROCK inhibitor structurally distinct from Y-27632, also dose-dependently reduced P3490 staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>These effects were visible microscopically (Fig. 1E), and easily quantified using a fluorescence plate reader following incubation with a fluorescently-labeled (Alexa Fluor®488) secondary antibody (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>At 50 µM, OH-fasudil eliminated P3490 staining in nearly all cells without affecting their total PFN1 levels (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We further confirmed the specificity of P3490 for pS137-PFN1 using RNAi knockdown of endogenous PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>HEK293 cells were transduced with lentiviral shRNAs targeting PFN1 (Fig. 2A), which reduced P3490 staining (Fig. 2B–C), consistent with PFN1 being the cellular target of the antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>This effect was evident microscopically (Fig. 2B), and was quantified using the fluorescence plate reader (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The relative decrease in total PFN1 level (60%) as a result of shRNA knockdown was larger than that of P3490 staining (40%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>This implies that Ser-137 phosphorylation of PFN1 may need to be kept at a certain level in the cell, and could be regulated in a fashion partially independent of total PFN1 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In addition, P3490 stained ectopically expressed phosphomimetic PFN1(S137D) in cultured cells, but not PFN1(wt) or PFN1(S137A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This was most evident when phosphorylation of endogenous PFN1 at Ser-137 was inhibited by OH-fasudil (Fig. 2D), and was also quantified by the fluorescence plate reader (Fig. 2E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results confirmed the specificity of P3490 for pS137-PFN1 for in situ staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0032802-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>P3490 specifically detects pS137-PFN1 via immunofluorescence staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A, HEK293 cells were infected for three days with lentiviral shRNA particles encoding either a scrambled nucleotide sequence (Ctrl shRNA), or a target-specific sequence for human PFN1 (PFN1 shRNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Efficient PFN1 knockdown was confirmed by Western blot. B, virus-mediated PFN1 knockdown reduced P3490 staining (green, a–b), as visualized by confocal fluorescence microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Total PFN1 decrease was also confirmed by immunofluorescence staining (green, c–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>DAPI (blue) was used to counterstain cells either as merged (a–b) or unmerged images (e–f). C, staining of virus-infected cells with P3490 and PFN1 antibodies (as in A and B) was quantified by fluorescence plate reader, and normalized vs. DAPI to control for cell numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The decrease of P3490 (∼40%; *, p&lt;0.05, unpaired t-test) and total PFN1(60%; p&lt;0.001, unpaired t-test) staining caused by PFN1 knockdown was calculated relative to cells infected with the control shRNA (arbitrarily set as 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. D, HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with Myc-tagged PFN1(wt, S137A or S137D), treated with 50 µM hydroxyfasudil for 16 hr, and double stained with an anti-Myc (red) and P3490 (green) antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Only cells expressing the phosphomimetic Myc-PFN1(S137D) stained positive with P3490 (g–i), but not Myc-PFN1(wt) (a–c) or Myc-PFN1(S137A) (d–f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Arrowheads indicate two cells that expressed Myc-PFN1(S137D) and stained positive with P3490. E, Western blot confirmed comparable levels of Myc-PFN1 over-expression (wt, S137A and S137D) in transiently transfected HEK293 cells, as compared to cells transfected with an empty vector (pcDNA3). F, cells transfected (as in E) with pcDNA3 or various PFN1 constructs were immunostained with P3490, and quantified on a fluorescence plate reader with normalization vs. DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The effects of PFN1 over-expression on P3490 staining are represented as relative change compared to cells transfected with pcDNA3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Only PFN1(S137D) increased P3490 staining (***, p&lt;0.001, unpaired t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Cells were not treated with hydroxyfasudil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032802.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Phosphatase inhibitors increase pS137-PFN1 levels in cultured cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>To identify candidate phosphatases for pSer-137 of PFN1, we employed pharmacologic inhibitors of serine/threonine phosphatases in cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Okadaic acid (OA) inhibits the serine/threonine-specific phosphoprotein phosphatase (PPP) family, in particular its two most abundant members, PP1 and PP2A [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Differential potencies of OA towards its target phosphatases have enabled its use to implicate candidates, particularly PP1 (IC50∼15–50 nM) and PP2A (IC50∼0.1–0.3 nM) [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Thus, we treated HEK293 cells with increasing concentrations of OA, and tested the effects on pS137-PFN1 levels by immunostaining with P3490. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>16 hr of OA treatment markedly increased the number of P3490-positive cells at mid-nanomolar concentrations (≥10 nM), which was evident both microscopically (Fig. 3A) and after quantification using a fluorescence plate reader (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The effective concentration of OA to increase pS137-PFN1 levels was much higher than its IC50 for PP2A (0.1–0.3 nM), and more consistent with its known IC50 for PP1 (15–50 nM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>We also used endothall, a structurally distinct phosphatase inhibitor that is also much more potent against PP2A (IC50 = 90 nM) than PP1 (IC50 = 5 µM) [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Like OA, endothall increased P3490 staining at concentrations (mid-micromolar) that are substantially higher than its IC50 for PP2A, but similar to that for PP1 (Fig. 3A and 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Due to cytotoxic effects at high concentrations, we were unable to carry out complete dose-responses of OA and endothall with regard to pS137-PFN1 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>At their effective concentrations, neither drug affected the total PFN1 levels within cells (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Fostriecin, a highly specific and potent inhibitor of PP2A (IC50 for PP2A = 1.5–5.5 nM; IC50 for PP1 = 45–58 µM), had no effect on P3490 staining, even at 1 µM (data not shown), a concentration expected to fully inhibit PP2A in a living cell [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggested that PP1, rather than PP2A, might be responsible for dephosphorylation of PFN1 at Ser-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0032802-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Pharmacologic inhibition of serine/threonine phosphatases increases pS137-PFN1 in cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A, HEK293 cells were treated with okadaic acid (OA) (a–d) or endothall (e–h) for 16 hr at increasing concentrations (1, 3 and 10 nM for OA; 1, 3 and 10 µM for endothall), followed by immunostaining with P3490 (green) and counterstaining with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The number of P3490-positive cells and overall P3490 staining intensity increased notably at 10 nM of OA and 10 µM of endothall treatment. B, effects of OA and endothall on P3490 staining were quantified using a fluorescence plate reader. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>P3490 levels were normalized vs. DAPI, and the effects of the drugs were represented as relative change vs. the vehicle controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>OA and endothall increased P3490 staining dose-dependently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. C, HEK293 cells treated with 10 nM OA (a–b) or 10 µM endothall (c–d) were immunostained for total PFN1 (green) and counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Merged images showed no changes in total PFN1 levels as a result of the drugs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032802.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Genetic modulation of PP1 activity controls pS137-PFN1 levels in cultured cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The above effects of phosphatase inhibitors indicated a role of PP1 in pS137-PFN1 dephosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To test this more definitively, we knocked down the alpha isoform of the PP1 catalytic subunit, PP1Cα, by transfecting HEK293 cells with siRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In parallel, we also knocked down the alpha isoform of the PP2A catalytic subunit, PP2ACα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Based on Western blot analysis, endogenous PP1Cα and PP2ACα were both knocked down by 90% with no effect on cellular PFN1 levels (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>This was also confirmed via immunofluorescence staining of the transfected cells (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>We detected a three-fold increase of P3490 staining in cells transfected with the PP1Cα-specific siRNA in comparison to those transfected with the control siRNA (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In contrast, silencing PP2ACα had no effect on P3490 staining (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>As an additional test, in HeLa cells we over-expressed wild-type PP1Cα, a catalytically inactive PP1Cα(H125A) mutant, or wild-type PP2ACα, and stained with P3490. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Nearly all cells expressing wild type PP1Cα stained negative for pS137-PFN1, while many cells expressing the inactive PP1Cα(H125A) mutant or wild type PP2ACα stained positive for pS137-PFN1 (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>These data strongly suggested that PP1 dephosphorylates PFN1 at Ser-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0032802-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Protein phosphatase-1 (PP1) dephosphorylates PFN1 at Ser-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>A, HEK293 cells were transfected with control, or sequence-specific siRNAs targeting human PP1Cα or PP2ACα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>They were immunostained with P3490 (a–c) or the antibody against total PFN1 (d–f) (both in green) and counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Silencing PP1Cα, but not PP2ACα, increased the number of P3490-positive cells and their staining intensities, while having no effect on total PFN1 levels. B, effects of PP1Cα and PP2ACα knockdown on P3490 staining were quantified using the fluorescence plate reader, normalized vs. DAPI, and represented as change relative to control siRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>PP1Cα knockdown increased P3490 staining three-fold (***, p&lt;0.001, unpaired t-test), while PP2ACα knockdown had no effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± S.E.M. of three independent experiments. C, Western blot confirmed &gt;90% knockdown of both PP1Cα and PP2ACα in HEK293 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Neither affected PFN1 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Arrowhead indicates PP1Cα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The identity of the protein band above PP1Cα, which cross-reacts with PP1Cα antibody, is unknown. D, HeLa cells were transfected with Myc-PP1Cα(wt) (a–c), Myc-PP1Cα(H125A) (catalytically inactive) (d–f) or Myc-PP2ACα (g–i), double immunolabeled with an anti-Myc antibody (red) and P3490 (green), and counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Neither Myc-PP1Cα(H125A) nor Myc-PP2ACα over-expression affected P3490 staining of the transfected cells (as indicated by the presence of cells that were both red and green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>However, PP1Cα(wt) over-expression inhibited P3490 staining (as indicated by the mutual exclusivity of red and green cells). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032802.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>PP1 interacts with PFN1 in a pS137-dependent manner </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The preceding experiments correlated PP1 activity with pS137-PFN1 dephosphorylation, but left uncertain whether the dephosphorylation is carried out directly by PP1, or by an unknown phosphatase whose activity is regulated by PP1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>To test this, we transiently expressed Myc-PP1Cα and PFN1 in HEK293 cells, immunoprecipitated Myc-PP1Cα via an anti-Myc antibody, and tested for co-precipitation of PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Myc-PP2ACα was separately co-expressed with PFN1 and immunoprecipitated as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We readily detected PFN1 in a complex with PP1Cα, but not PP2ACα (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We next tested for preferential binding of PP1Cα to pS137-PFN1 vs. unphosphorylated PFN1 by using the phosphomimetic PFN1(S137D) vs. phospho-resistant PFN1(S137A) mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We transiently expressed HA-tagged PFN1(wt), PFN1(S137A) or PFN1(S137D) in HEK293 cells along with Myc-PP1Cα, followed by immunoprecipitation of Myc-PP1Cα and Western blot for co-precipitation of HA-PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>PP1Cα bound more phosphomimetic PFN1(S137D) and less phospho-resistant PFN1(S137A) in comparison to PFN1(wt), with all PFN1 variants expressed at a similar level (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>These data suggested that Ser-137 phosphorylation promotes PFN1 interaction with PP1, which subsequently dephosphorylates pSer-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0032802-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032802.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>PP1 and PFN1 interact in cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A, HEK293 cells were co-transfected with an untagged PFN1 along with either an empty vector (pcDNA3) (Lane 1), or Myc-tagged PP1Cα (Lane 2), or PP2ACα (Lane 3), followed by immunoprecipitation with an anti-Myc antibody and Western blot for PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>PFN1 co-immunoprecipitated specifically with PP1Cα, but not PP2ACα. B, HA-PFN1 constructs (wt, S137A or S137D) were co-transfected into HEK293 cells with pcDNA3 (Lanes 1–3) or Myc-PP1Cα (Lanes 4–6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Myc-PP1Cα was immunoprecipitated with an anti-Myc antibody, and co-immunoprecipitated HA-PFN1 was detected by an anti-HA antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Relative to PFN1(wt), more PFN1(S137D) and less PFN1(S137A) bound to PP1Cα. C, Purified 6His-PFN1 (wt, S137A or S137D) proteins were bound to Ni-NTA beads, and subsequently mixed with recombinant PP1Cα (Lanes 2–4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Beads without His-PFN1 were mixed with the same amount of PP1Cα to control for nonspecific binding (Lane 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Beads were washed, and analyzed for binding of PP1Cα to 6His-PFN1 by Western blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>6His-PFN1 proteins were visualized by Coomassie blue staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>No specific binding was observed between purified PP1Cα and 6His-PFN1 (wt, S137A or S137D), despite that they were abundantly present. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032802.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>PP1 is known to interact directly with a small number of substrates [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To determine if PP1 directly binds PFN1, we tested for their binding in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>We immobilized recombinant 6His-PFN1 (wt, S137A or S137D) proteins on nickel beads, mixed them with bacterially expressed recombinant PP1Cα, and subsequently tested for their interaction via Western blot against PP1Cα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>We did not detect any specific binding of PP1Cα to all three forms of 6His-PFN1(wt, S137A and S137D), despite that all proteins were abundantly present (Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Thus, our data suggest that PP1 indirectly associates with PFN1 through an unknown linker protein, and dephosphorylates pSer-137. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Our prior studies were the first to demonstrate how PFN1's biological activities are regulated, at least in part, through phosphorylation at Ser-137 by the Rho-associated kinase ROCK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Ser-137 phosphorylation abolishes PFN1's binding to polyproline-containing ligands, e.g. huntingtin, which reduces its ability to inhibit polyglutamine-dependent huntingtin aggregation [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Our current work identifies PP1 as the principal phosphatase to dephosphorylate PFN1 at Ser-137. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>By using a phospho-antibody against pSer-137 of PFN1, we found that pharmacologic inhibition and genetic knockdown of the catalytic subunit of PP1 (PP1Cα), but not PP2A (PP2ACα), increased pS137-PFN1 levels in cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>PP1Cα binds PFN1 in cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This interaction increases when Ser-137 is mutated to aspartate, mimicking phosphorylation, and decreases when it is mutated to alanine, blocking phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The simplest interpretation of our data is that PP1 directly dephosphorylates pSer-137 of PFN1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>PP1 is a major eukaryotic serine/threonine phosphatase, and is thought to catalyze the majority of cellular protein dephosphorylation events [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>There are four different catalytic subunits of PP1 in mammals (α, β, γ1,γ2), which are associated with a large number of regulatory subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This allows for hundreds of dimeric holoenzymes that are highly substrate-specific [19], [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Our finding that PFN1 co-immunoprecipitates with PP1 from cultured cells in a phosphorylation-dependent manner suggests that they co-exist in a complex to dephosphorylate pSer-137. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>However, a lack of direct binding between these two proteins in vitro suggests that they are likely linked in vivo by an unknown PP1-interacting protein (PIP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the fact that PFN1 lacks a typical PP1-docking motif (RVxF, SILK or MyPhoNE (myosin phosphatase N-terminal element with the consensus sequence of RxxQV/I/LK/RxY/W)) that is found in most PIPs [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Given the vast number of PIPs estimated to be encoded by the human genome (∼650, 180 of which are known) [19], identifying the one specifically targeting PP1 to PFN1 could be a daunting task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>However, screening PFN1-binding proteins for this PIP might be a more feasible approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Our finding that mimicking Ser-137 phosphorylation (which should disrupt PFN1's binding to all polyproline-containing proteins) increases PFN1's interaction with PP1 argues against this PIP being a polyproline-containing ligand of PFN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>This effectively rules out the vast majority of PFN1-interacting proteins as the candidate, and focuses our future efforts on the limited number of non-polyproline ligands of PFN1 (e.g. actin and gephyrin) [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>At a minimum, this will reveal the additional linker protein, if existent, between PFN1 and the unknown PIP, and take us one step closer to identifying it. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>As an essential protein for all eukaryotic cells, PFN1 has now been linked to several human diseases such as Huntington disease [6] and cancer [7], [8], [9], [10], [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It will thus be of great interest to identify therapeutic approaches to regulate its activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Our prior and current identification of ROCK and PP1 as direct regulators of Ser-137 phosphorylation and dephosphorylation raises the possibility of targeting these two enzymes to manipulate PFN1 activity and treat these diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>For example, ROCK inhibitors (e.g. fasudil), which are expected to up-regulate PFN1 activity, are already in clinical use to reduce vasospasm in the setting of subarachnoid hemorrhage [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Importantly, they ameliorate behavioral deficits of HD transgenic mice [24] and have been validated as being anti-metastatic in several cancer models [25], [26], [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Our work thus represents an early step in defining the mechanisms by which it may be possible to specifically control PFN1's activity to benefit patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Plasmids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Mammalian expression vectors encoding Myc-PP1Cα (wt or H125A) and Myc-PP2ACα were kindly provided by Dr. Hiroshi Shima (Miyagi Cancer Center Research Institute, Japan) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Mammalian expression vectors encoding untagged or Myc-tagged PFN1 (wt, S137A and S137D) were cloned in pcDNA3 as described previously [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>HA-tagged human PFN1 (wt, S137A and S137D) was PCR amplified and cloned into the EcoRI (5′) and XhoI (3′) sites of pcDNA3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences are as follows: 5′-CCGGAATTCGCCGCCATGGCCTACCCATATGATGTTCCAGATTACGCTTCTTTGGGTGCCGGGTGGAACGCCTACATCGACAACCTCATG-3′ (upper primer containing an HA-tag); 5′-CCGCCGCTCGAGTCAGTACTGGGAACGCCGAAGGTGG-3′ (lower primer). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>siRNAs and shRNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Negative control siRNA (SI03650325) and human PP1Cα-specific siRNA (SI02225748) were purchased from Qiagen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>A pool of three siRNAs targeting different regions of human PP2ACα were purchased from Santa Cruz (sc-43509). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>To silence PFN1, a 21nt sequence (5′-GGAATTTAGCATGGATCTTCG-3′) was custom-designed to target 246-267nt of human PFN1 mRNA, and cloned as short hairpin RNA (shRNA) downstream of the U6 promoter in a lentiviral vector, pFLRu-FH (kind gift of Dr. Greg Longmore) [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A control shRNA was similarly constructed using a non-targeting sequence (5′-CAACAAGATGAAGAGCACCAA-3′) adapted from the MISSION Non-Target shRNA control vector from Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Lentiviral particles were purified by the Hope Center Viral Vectors Core at Washington University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Commercially available primary antibodies were as follows: rabbit anti-PFN1 (Cell Signaling, #3237), mouse anti-Myc tag (Santa Cruz, sc-40), rabbit anti-actin (Santa Cruz, sc-1616-R), rabbit anti-PP1Cα (Cell Signaling, #2582), rabbit anti-PP2ACα (Cell Signaling, #2038), mouse anti-HA tag (Covance, MMS-101P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Custom-made antibodies include rabbit polyclonal antibody against the C-terminus of PFN1 (KCYEMASHLRRSQY, gift of Dr. Nicholas A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>DiProspero) and affinity purified rabbit polyclonal anti-pS137-PFN1 (New England Peptides, Ac-CMASHLRR(pS)QY-OH) [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies used for Western blotting include alkaline phosphatase-conjugated secondary antibodies (Sigma, A3562) and horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies (Amersham Biosciences, NA9340V for anti-rabbit and NA931V for anti-mouse antibodies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies for immunofluorescence staining include Alexa Fluor® 488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (Invitrogen, A-11034) and Alexa Fluor® 546-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Invitrogen, A-11030). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Agarose conjugated with secondary anti-mouse IgG (A6531) and EZview Red affinity gel conjugated with rabbit anti-c-Myc antibody (E6654) were purchased from Sigma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Alpha isoform of bacterially expressed recombinant PP1 catalytic subunit was purchase from Sigma (P7937). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Nickel-NTA beads were purchased from Qiagen (30410). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Protease inhibitor cocktail (11-836-170-001) was purchased from Roche Diagnostics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>ECL Plus Western blotting detection kit (RPN2132) was purchased from GE Healthcare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Lysophosphatidic acid (L7260) was purchased from Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Okadaic acid (495609), Endothall (324760), Fostriecin (344280) and Hydroxyfasudil (390602) were purchased from Calbiochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Fetal bovine serum (SH3007103) was purchased from Hyclone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Gold anti-fade mounting media was purchased from Invitrogen (P36934). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Cell culture and transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>HEK293, HeLa and NIH 3T3 cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum and penicillin/streptomycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) was used for transfecting both DNAs and siRNAs using the protocol recommended by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>HEK293 cells over-expressing Myc-PP1Cα(wt or H125A) or Myc-PP2ACα were lysed with buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Triton X-100, and protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Cleared lysate was mixed with agarose beads bound with anti-Myc antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>After 2 hr of mixing at 4°C, beads were washed 4 times with lysis buffer, and analyzed by Western blot for co-immunoprecitation of untagged or HA-tagged PFN1 via antibodies against PFN1 (1∶1000) or the HA tag (1∶1000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>For in vitro pull-down experiment, 20 µl nickel NTA beads were pre-blocked with 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) for 30 min at room temperature, and subsequently mixed with 10 µg 6His-tagged PFN1(wt, S137A and S137D) proteins previously purified from bacteria [6] for 30 min at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>After washing, 2 µg of recombinant PP1Cα was added to the beads in 100 µl binding buffer containing 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% BSA, 0.1% Triton X-100 and protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Following 1 hr incubation at 4°C, beads were washed 4 times with binding buffer without BSA, and analyzed by Western blot for PP1Cα or Coomassie blue staining for 6His-PFN1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Cultured cells were fixed for 30 min with 4% paraformaldehyde, washed 3 times with PBS, followed by blocking with 2% BSA in PBS/0.1% Triton X-100 for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>P3490 antibody was diluted at 1∶5000 (v/v) with blocking buffer and incubated with cells for 2 hr at room temperature or overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed 4 times with PBS/0.1% Triton X-100, incubated with 1∶500 dilution of Alexa Fluor® 488 goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody in blocking buffer for 2 hr at room temperature, washed 4 times with PBS/0.1% Triton X-100, and mounted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>For total PFN1 staining, custom-made rabbit polyclonal antibody against the C-terminus of PFN1 (KCYEMASHLRRSQY) was used at 1∶100 and followed by secondary antibody incubation as for P3490. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>For double labeling, cells were simultaneously incubated with P3490 (1∶5000) and anti-Myc antibody (1∶1000) overnight at 4°C, followed by 2 hr incubation with 1∶500 dilution of Alexa Fluor® 488 goat anti-rabbit antibody and Alexa Fluor® 546 goat anti-mouse antibodies at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In all cases, DAPI was included in the secondary antibody solution at a concentration of 1 µg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Images were acquired using the Zeiss LSM 5 PASCAL system equipped with the following lasers: 405 nm, 488 nm, 543 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>For quantitative immunostaining within 96-well plates, HEK293 cells were grown to approximately 90% confluence, fixed, blocked, stained with P3490 (1∶5000) or anti-PFN1 antibody (1∶100) and Alexa Fluor® 488 goat anti-rabbit antibody (1∶500), and counterstained with DAPI as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed 4 times with PBS/0.1% Triton X-100, left in 150 µl PBS, and quantified for fluorescence intensity (490/519 nm for Alexa Fluor® 488 and 365/439 nm for DAPI) using a fluorescence plate reader (INFINITE M1000, Tecan, Inc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Background fluorescence was acquired using cells stained only with the secondary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Background subtracted fluorescence intensity for Alexa Fluor® 488, which represented P3490 reactivity, was then normalized against DAPI level to control for total cell number. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>For all experiments, at least 4 replicate wells were quantified for a given condition, and each experiment was repeated at least three times independently. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Antigen competition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>P3490 was first diluted 1∶5000 in the blocking buffers for immunofluorescence (PBS/0.1% Triton X-100/2% BSA) or Western blot (TBS/0.05% Tween 20/5% skim milk), and then mixed at 1∶200 molar ratio (antibody/peptide) with PFN1 peptides containing (Ac-CMASHLRR(pS)QY-OH) or lacking a phosphate on Ser-137 (Ac-CMASHLRRSQY-OH) for 30 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>A control antibody solution was set up by mixing an equivalent volume of water (instead of peptides) with P3490. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>All antibody solutions (no peptide, S137-peptide and pS137-peptide) were subsequently used to immunostain or immunoblot HEK293 cells as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Hiroshi Shima and Dr. Nobuhiro Tanuma (Miyagi Cancer Center Research Institute, Japan) for generously providing PP1 and PP2A constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Greg Longmore and Dr. Yunfeng Feng (Washington University in St. Louis) for sharing the lentiviral shRNA vector pFLRu-FH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>We also thank Dr. Nicholas A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>DiProspero (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) for generously providing the anti-profilin-1 antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the American Cancer Society Institutional Research Grant (Dr. Shao, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.org">www.cancer.org</ext-link>), the Muscular Dystrophy Association (Dr. Shao and Dr. Diamond, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mdausa.org">www.mdausa.org</ext-link>), National Institutes of Health/National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NIH/NINDS) R01 NS50284 (Dr. Diamond). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The Hope Center Viral Vectors Core is supported by a Neuroscience Blueprint Core grant (P30 NS057105) from NIH to Washington University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0032802-Birbach1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>1 BirbachA 2008 Profilin, a multi-modal regulator of neuronal plasticity. Bioessays 30 994 1002 18798527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Schluter1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>2 SchluterKJockuschBMRothkegelM 1997 Profilins as regulators of actin dynamics. Biochim Biophys Acta 1359 97 109 9409807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Witke1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>3 WitkeW 2004 The role of profilin complexes in cell motility and other cellular processes. Trends Cell Biol 14 461 469 15308213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Bottcher1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>4 BottcherRTWiesnerSBraunAWimmerRBernaA 2009 Profilin 1 is required for abscission during late cytokinesis of chondrocytes. Embo J 28 1157 1169 19262563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Behnen1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>5 BehnenMMurkKKursulaPCappallo-ObermannHRothkegelM 2009 Testis-expressed profilins 3 and 4 show distinct functional characteristics and localize in the acroplaxome-manchette complex in spermatids. BMC Cell Biol 10 34 19419568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Shao1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>6 ShaoJWelchWJDiprosperoNADiamondMI 2008 Phosphorylation of profilin by ROCK1 regulates polyglutamine aggregation. Mol Cell Biol 28 5196 5208 18573880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Janke1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>7 JankeJSchluterKJandrigBTheileMKolbleK 2000 Suppression of tumorigenicity in breast cancer cells by the microfilament protein profilin 1. J Exp Med 191 1675 1686 10811861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Wittenmayer1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>8 WittenmayerNJandrigBRothkegelMSchluterKArnoldW 2004 Tumor suppressor activity of profilin requires a functional actin binding site. Mol Biol Cell 15 1600 1608 14767055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Zou1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>9 ZouLJaramilloMWhaleyDWellsAPanchapakesaV 2007 Profilin-1 is a negative regulator of mammary carcinoma aggressiveness. Br J Cancer 97 1361 1371 17940506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Zou2"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>10 ZouLDingZRoyP 2010 Profilin-1 overexpression inhibits proliferation of MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells partly through p27kip1 upregulation. J Cell Physiol 223 623 629 20143334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Roy1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>11 RoyPJacobsonK 2004 Overexpression of profilin reduces the migration of invasive breast cancer cells. Cell Motil Cytoskeleton 57 84 95 14691948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Bae1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>12 BaeYHDingZZouLWellsAGertlerF 2009 Loss of profilin-1 expression enhances breast cancer cell motility by Ena/VASP proteins. J Cell Physiol 219 354 364 19115233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-DaSilva1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>13 Da SilvaJSMedinaMZulianiCDi NardoAWitkeW 2003 RhoA/ROCK regulation of neuritogenesis via profilin IIa-mediated control of actin stability. J Cell Biol 162 1267 1279 14517206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Sathish1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>14 SathishKPadmaBMunugalavadlaVBhargaviVRadhikaKV 2004 Phosphorylation of profilin regulates its interaction with actin and poly (L-proline). Cell Signal 16 589 596 14751544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Bialojan1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>15 BialojanCTakaiA 1988 Inhibitory effect of a marine-sponge toxin, okadaic acid, on protein phosphatases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Specificity and kinetics. Biochem J 256 283 290 2851982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Swingle1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>16 SwingleMNiLHonkanenRE 2007 Small-molecule inhibitors of ser/thr protein phosphatases: specificity, use and common forms of abuse. Methods Mol Biol 365 23 38 17200551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Li1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>17 LiYMCasidaJE 1992 Cantharidin-binding protein: identification as protein phosphatase 2A. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89 11867 11870 1334551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Yi1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>18 YiKDSimpkinsJW 2008 Protein phosphatase 1, protein phosphatase 2A, and calcineurin play a role in estrogen-mediated neuroprotection. Endocrinology 149 5235 5243 18566123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Bollen1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>19 BollenMPetiWRagusaMJBeullensM 2010 The extended PP1 toolkit: designed to create specificity. Trends Biochem Sci 35 450 458 20399103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Cohen1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>20 CohenPT 2002 Protein phosphatase 1–targeted in many directions. J Cell Sci 115 241 256 11839776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Bollen2"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>21 BollenM 2001 Combinatorial control of protein phosphatase-1. Trends Biochem Sci 26 426 431 11440854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Takanashi1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>22 TakanashiYIshidaTMeguroTKiwadaHZhangJH 2001 Efficacy of intrathecal liposomal fasudil for experimental cerebral vasospasm after subarachnoid hemorrhage. Neurosurgery 48 894 900; discussion 900–891 11322450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Tachibana1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>23 TachibanaEHaradaTShibuyaMSaitoKTakayasuM 1999 Intra-arterial infusion of fasudil hydrochloride for treating vasospasm following subarachnoid haemorrhage. Acta Neurochir (Wien) 141 13 19 10071681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Li2"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>24 LiMHuangYMaAALinEDiamondMI 2009 Y-27632 improves rotarod performance and reduces huntingtin levels in R6/2 mice. Neurobiol Dis 36 413 420 19591939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Burthem1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>25 BurthemJRees-UnwinKMottramRAdamsJLucasGS 2007 The rho-kinase inhibitors Y-27632 and fasudil act synergistically with imatinib to inhibit the expansion of ex vivo CD34(+) CML progenitor cells. Leukemia 21 1708 1714 17554385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Ying1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>26 YingHBirocSLLiWWAlickeBXuanJA 2006 The Rho kinase inhibitor fasudil inhibits tumor progression in human and rat tumor models. Mol Cancer Ther 5 2158 2164 16985048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Itoh1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>27 ItohKYoshiokaKAkedoHUehataMIshizakiT 1999 An essential part for Rho-associated kinase in the transcellular invasion of tumor cells. Nat Med 5 221 225 9930872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Sahai1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>28 SahaiEIshizakiTNarumiyaSTreismanR 1999 Transformation mediated by RhoA requires activity of ROCK kinases. Curr Biol 9 136 145 10021386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Mitsuhashi1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>29 MitsuhashiSShimaHTanumaNMatsuuraNTakekawaM 2003 Usage of tautomycetin, a novel inhibitor of protein phosphatase 1 (PP1), reveals that PP1 is a positive regulator of Raf-1 in vivo. J Biol Chem 278 82 88 12374792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0032802-Feng1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>30 FengYNieLThakurMDSuQChiZ 2010 A multifunctional lentiviral-based gene knockdown with concurrent rescue that controls for off-target effects of RNAi. Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics 8 238 245 21382592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
