<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3031208</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1746-4269-7-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21235814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-7-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Knowledge and practice of traditional healers in oral health in the Bui Division, Cameroon </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Agbor</surname><given-names>Ashu M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>agborasm@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>Sudeshni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>suenaidoo@uwc.ac.za</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Community Dentistry, University of the Western Cape, Tygerberg, South Africa</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2011 Agbor and Naidoo; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Agbor and Naidoo; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.ethnobiomed.com/content/7/1/6"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The majority of Cameroonians depend on traditional medicines for their health care needs and about seven per cent of the average household health budget is spent on traditional medicines irrespective of their incomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to determine the oral care knowledge and practices of Traditional Healers (TH) on oral health delivery in the urban and rural areas of Bui Division of Cameroon and the objectives to determine the cost of treatment and reasons why people visit TH. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The present study was cross sectional and utilized semi-structured questionnaires to collect data. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The sample consisted of 21 TH and 52 clients of TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Sixty two percent of the TH's were above 40 years and 90% male. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The mean age was 46 years (range 20-77 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Twenty four percent of the TH practiced as herbalists and the remainder both divination and herbalism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Sixty seven percent of people in the Bui Division, who patronize TH for their oral health needs, fall within the 20-40 year age group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>There is little collaboration between the oral health workers and TH and only 6% of all patients seen by TH are referred to the dentist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Socio-cultural and economic factors affect the oral health care seeking behavior of patients in this area and only 6.5% of patients visit dental clinics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Reasons for not attending dental clinics included high cost, poor accessibility, superstition and fear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>TH's are not experienced in the treatment of pulpitis - the majority of patients who presented with toothache had temporary or no relief, but despite this 67% reported being satisfied with their treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Sixty nine percent of the patients visited TH because of low cost - the average cost of treatment with TH (approximately $5) is very low, as compared to conventional treatment ($50). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Traditional healers are willing to co-operate with oral health workers in improving oral health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Since they have a vital role to play in health care seeking attitudes in this community and barriers affecting the oral health seeking behaviours should be removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Mutual cooperation, collaboration and by integrating TH into primary oral health care services needs to be increased. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A traditional healer is a person who has no formal medical training, but is recognized by the community in which he/she lives as being competent to provide health care by using plant, animal and mineral substances and certain other methods based on social, cultural and religious background as well as the knowledge, attitudes and beliefs that are prevalent in the community regarding physical, mental and social well-being and the causation of the disease and disability [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>According to the World Heath Organization (WHO), more than 80 percent of Africans rely on traditional medicine and indigenous knowledge to meet their health needs [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This is due to the fact that traditional medicine is accessible, affordable, culturally and socially acceptable and most people prefer it to the 'exorbitantly priced' conventional Western medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>With the legalization of traditional medicine as a complimentary health care service to primary health care in Cameroon, the role of the traditional healer will be vital in the promotion of health especially in resource poor settings and rural areas where they may be the only source of health care [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Since colonial times, Western medicine was the only formally accepted medicine in Cameroon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Traditional medicinal practices were condemned as witchcraft or sorcery and discouraged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Despite this, the practice of traditional medicine has survived clandestinely in Cameroon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>One of the main reasons Cameroonians still favor traditional medicines is financial - they resort to traditional medicine because they cannot afford pharmaceutical medicaments or conventional medical care [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The oral health care work force in Cameroon consists of 220 dentists all trained abroad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Nearly all are located in the two big cities of Douala and Yaoundé serving just 20% of the country's population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, it is estimated that there are more than 20 000 traditional healers (TH) in the country serving both the rural and urban population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Rural populations do not have access to the services of trained oral health personnel due to cost constraints and poor accessibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Today, seven per cent of the average household health budget is spent on traditional medicines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Nearly twice as many people from poor households rely on traditional medicine as do people from rich households [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The recognition and integration of traditional medicine into the health system of Cameroon was officially proposed in 1981. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Since then, traditional medicine has been recognized, but not regulated by the Ministry of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In 1995, a presidential decree no. 95-040 of July 3, 1995 gave TH in Cameroon, the authorization to create associations at both provincial and national levels to manage their activities [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In recognition of the fact that traditional medicine is "the most affordable and accessible system of health care for the majority of the African rural population," the Organization for African Unity (now the African Union) declared the years 2001-2010 to be the 'Decade for African Traditional Medicine'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The aim of this declaration was to bring together all the stakeholders in health care in an effort to make traditional medicine "safe, efficacious, affordable and available to the vast majority of African people" [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>One of the tasks of the WHO (Africa Region) is to assist countries in ensuring that the African population enjoys improved levels of oral health and function through a significant reduction of all oral diseases and conditions that are prevalent in the region, with equitable access to cost-effective quality oral health care and adoption of healthy lifestyles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Despite much research in recent times regarding health (medical) sector collaboration with TH, there is paucity of literature with regard to the role of TH in the provision of oral health care and in the diagnosis and management of the common oral problems including the oral manifestations of HIV/AIDS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Given shrinking health budgets, economic constraints and the diminishing capacity for oral health personnel to handle the burden of oral diseases throughout much of Sub-Saharan Africa, it would seem logical to develop and enhance co-operation and collaboration between the formal oral health services and TH to bring available resources in the health sector to serve the population for better oral health and HIV/AIDS prevention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Traditional healers are considered to be effective agents of change as they command authority in their communities, function as psychologists, marriage and family counselors, physicians and legal and political advisors [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>They are also the legitimate interpreters of customary rules of conduct, morality and values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>TH provide client-centered, personalized health care that is culturally appropriate and tailored to meet the needs and expectations of the client paying special respect to social and spiritual matters [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Lewis et al. [9] reported on the oral health care knowledge and practices of African TH from two communities: Zonkizizwe and Dube in the Gauteng Province, South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>According to their findings, more than 90% of TH from both areas correctly identified photographs of gingival inflammation, dental caries and oral candidiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>More than half reported patients presented with mouth problems such as toothache, swollen gums and oral candidiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Considering that oral candidiasis has been reported as the most prevalent oral manifestation of HIV/AIDS and the fact that almost all TH can recognize oral candidiasis suggests that TH could play an essential role in the efforts to address early diagnosis of the oral manifestations of HIV/AIDS [7,9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A study carried out in Nigeria [10] found that TH were providing dental care, but their work was not integrated with that of a dentist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>He reported that while TH were open to collaborating with dental professionals, the reverse was not true. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>TH are more numerous than dental and medical practitioners and are widely accepted by a large proportion of the population, therefore it is logical that their work be integrated with that of dental and medical practitioners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In Africa and some parts of Asia chewing sticks are used for plaque removal [11,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Most plants used as chewing sticks contain fluoride and/or have antimicrobial, anti-cariogenic or anti-inflammatory properties [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Ngilisho et al. [14] reported that sixty per cent of the villagers in Tanga region, Tanzania who suffered from toothache sought treatment from TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>They were treated with local herbs and obtained pain relief for more than six months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The authors concluded that the presence of modern health facilities did not influence the villagers' use of TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Hence, it could be surmised that TH play an important role in the relief of acute pain, in underserved rural areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Therapeutic methods used by African TH include psychosocial counseling, simple surgical procedures, rituals and symbolism [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The types of medications used by TH can be classified as preventive and prophylactic medications [16], treatment for ailments [17] and medications used to "destroy the power in others" [18-22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The need to identify and recognize the beneficial effects of traditionally used plants and medicaments has been recognized [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Hamza et al. [18] investigated the antifungal activity of traditionally used Tanzanian plants and found good correlation between traditional therapeutic use and in vitro antifungal activity and corroborated the importance of ethnobotanical surveys for screening plants as a potential source for bioactive components that may have preventive, prophylactic or treatment properties for oral and other diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Sarita and Tuominen [23] investigating the pattern of utilization of medical and dental health care services in rural Tanzania reported that indigenous home remedies were the only treatments used for managing dental problems, while for medical problems a TH was the most commonly used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Since the pattern of utilization of health care services differed for medical and dental problems, it should be taken into account when planning comprehensive health care services for rural African societies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>However, one needs to be aware that some traditional practices may be harmful for example, the practice of extracting tooth buds and of rubbing herbs on to the gingivae of children to treat fevers and diarrhea, as has been documented in countries such as Tanzania and Uganda [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>There is a need for health education programmes [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Discouraging the adoption of deeply rooted traditional practices that are potentially hazardous to health and oral health needs to be made a public health priority [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>This could be achieved by educating not only the general public, but also the TH and community leaders that convey the knowledge to their people. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>There have been many instances where TH have collaborated with the health sector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Wilkinson et al. [24] investigated the potential for TH to act as tuberculosis (TB) treatment supervisors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Although only four per cent of the study population believed that TH could cure TB, 84% stated that they would consider choosing a healer as a treatment supervisor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Eighty eight per cent of healers reported having referred patients with suspected TB to hospitals for treatment and all the healers were keen to collaborate with health services and to act as treatment supervisors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In an earlier report investigating the relationship between traditional and modern medicine Edwards [25] found that while traditional and modern practitioners worked from different theoretical orientations, they were in significant agreement as to both diagnosis and treatment of patients when faced with the same limited choice of options. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, patients perceived both the traditional and modern practitioners as being more or less equally helpful. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In Uganda, THETA (Traditional and modern health practitioners together against AIDS and other diseases), is promoting collaboration between traditional and biomedical health workers in the prevention and care of sexually transmitted infections (STIs) including HIV/AIDS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Projects involve collaboration in clinical trials to study the effectiveness of herbal treatments for opportunistic infections and to empower traditional medicine practitioners to offer counseling and education on STIs/AIDS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A study by Homsy and King [26] concluded that traditional healers could be trained as counselors and educators to disseminate HIV/AIDS information and prevention practices between their peers and communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Case studies indicate that TH are capable of performing at least as well as their biomedical counterparts as AIDS educators and counselors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Of concern to Homsy and King [26] however, was the failure of many projects to provide systematic follow-up to healers after their initial training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Such follow-up is essential to support healers in dealing with unfamiliar issues such as condom use and death and dying. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Masauso Nzima et al. [27] carried out a similar study in four Copperbelt towns in Zambia whereby TH received AIDS training and how to counsel clients on safe sex behaviors, together with follow-up monthly meetings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A qualitative investigation by Abdool Karim [28] exploring potential preventative health roles that TH could play with regard to HIV prevention, recommended that TH be incorporated into AIDS prevention programmes where they can play a role in community-based AIDS education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>There is increasing recognition on the role of TH in preventing and controlling HIV/AIDS and other sexually transmitted infections (STIs) [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Green [29] made some important recommendations for one to consider when planning collaborative work with TH: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>• Be fair and democratic in selecting healers for training </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>• Try to identify and train motivated healers who are respected in their communities </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>• Do not make membership of a TH's association a requirement for participation in HIV/AIDS training </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>• Encourage healers to promote sexual abstinence among youth, and fidelity within marriage among adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The World Health Organization (WHO) and other official groups have acknowledge the potential effectiveness of TH as primary caregivers and the potential efficacy of their treatments in the fight against HIV and AIDS, sexually transmitted disease, and other infectious diseases [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The WHO also supports the integration of Western medicine and traditional healing and encourages referrals between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In South Africa, TH have their own organization (Board of TH) that is recognized by the Department of Health and by the Ministry of Health respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Among the Zulu population, TH serve many functions in the community, such as the role of a minister of religion, legal advisor, healer, custodian of history and tradition and community organizer [17,31,32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Traditional healing has always been a component of health care in Cameroon but the actual contribution of TH to oral health care in the Bui Division of Cameroon is not known. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to assess the knowledge and practices of TH and determine the extent to which TH can diagnose oral conditions and how they can be incorporated into oral health care and prevention of oral diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This is a cross-sectional study design in rural and urban populations of Bui Division, in the North West Region of Cameroon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In Bui Division, general and oral care health delivery is carried out by 9 medical doctors and 1 dentist serving a population of 133 000 people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>There are more than 500 TH registered with the TH's association and treat common problems like diarrohea and malaria to more complex cases involving bone setting and serving as traditional birth attendants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Inhabitants residing in rural and urban areas of Bui division who sought treatment in hospital or from TH's for oral problems and individuals practicing as TH in the Bui divisions were interviewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>TH were randomly chosen from each of the sub-clans in the 3 towns located in Bui division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Bui division is one of the five divisions in the North West Region of Cameroon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Kumbo, it's headquarters is the second largest town in the region and is located 110 km from the regional capital, Bamenda. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The area is mountainous with poor road networks and basic infrastructure and the majority of inhabitants are subsistent farmers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The subclans division is based on 3 linguistic communities - the Nso, Oku and Noni whose headquarters are based at the towns of Kumbo, Oku and Nkor Noni respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A workshop was held to determine the knowledge and practices of TH on oral diseases and oral health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The objectives were to determine their knowledge of the common oral diseases, the type of treatments administered to treat oral problems and the cost of TH's care as compared to conventional dental treatment provided in local dental clinics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Colour photographs of common oral diseases and oral lesions were used for pre-testing of the knowledge of TH, a short training workshop was carried out followed by post-testing 3 months after the initial training workshop. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Questionnaires were administered to a convenience sample of inhabitants who used the services of THs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>TH questionnaires elicited data regarding their oral health knowledge and willingness to screen and educate their clients about oral health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Closed and open ended questionnaires were used for both groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all the participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Data were categorized, coded and then entered into the computer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The data was captured in Excel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Basic descriptive analysis was done using the Excel environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The database was imported into SPSS® to perform complex statistical analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistics were used to describe the demographic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The independent t-test was used to determine correlation between the scale variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The Chi-square test was used to determine the association between the nominal and the ordinal variables. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A total of 21 TH and 52 clients participated in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The ages of the TH ranged from 20 to 77 years with the average age of 46.09 years and a standard deviation of 14.29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Sixty two percent of the TH was over 40 years and 90% were male. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>More than a fifth (23.8%) of the TH were herbalists and the remainder practiced both divination and herbal medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Of the 52 clients, slightly more than half were males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The age distributions can be seen in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Age distribution of TH and their clients </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Age range (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>TH N(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Clients N(%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>&lt; 20 yrs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>1 (4.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>8 (15.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>21-30 yrs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>1 (4.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>22 (42.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>31-40 yrs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>6 (28.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>13 (25.0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>&gt;40 years </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>13 (61.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>9 (17.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Total </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>21(100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>52(100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>(a) Traditional healers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Seventy one percent of the TH had a primary and high school education, but had no formal training for their profession. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>More than two thirds (76.2%) were registered with the TH's association and the average duration of training of TH was 7.5 years (range 4 to 10 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The average duration of practice of TH was 21 years (range 2 to 41 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Three quarter of the TH were about half an hour away from the nearest health facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>All TH reported that if necessary, they referred patients to other health care workers (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Referral by TH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-4269-7-6-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Seventy one percent of TH reported that they knew the cause of HIV/AIDS and 67% stated that they could treat oral HIV lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Some of the causes of AIDS/HIV reported by TH included unprotected sex, contaminated needles and contact with blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>All TH were able to accurately detect candidiasis, dental caries and gum diseases from photographs after a training workshop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>There was a significant increase in knowledge in the diagnosis of aphthous ulcers, tongue cancer, and Kaposi sarcoma (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Identification of common oral conditions from photographs </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Lesion/Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Pre-test correct </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Post-test correct </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Percentage difference </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>p value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Caries </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>21 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>21 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>0.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Gum Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>11 (53.33) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>21 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>46.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>&lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Tongue Cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>2 (9.52) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>18 (85.68) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>76.16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>0.015 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Kaposi Sarcoma </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>4 (19) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>17 (80.92) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>61.92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>0.003 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>E </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Aphthous Ulcers </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>2 (9.52) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>19 (90.44) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>80.92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>0.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>F </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Candida </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>17 (80.92) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>21 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>19.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>0.036 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>MEAN </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>10(45.38) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>20(92.84) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>79.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>0.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>There was a statistical significant increase (p = 0.004) in knowledge from pre-test to post-test for all the six diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Tables 3 shows the treatment and materials used for oral lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The barks of trees, herbs and roots are used to make mouth washes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Their reported benefits include pain relieve and softening tooth before extractions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Type of treatment given by TH </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Type of treatment provided </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Percentage </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Mouth wash from bark of tree extracts </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>67.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Pain relieving herbs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>11.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Fume inhalations(from burnt spices in palm oil) that remove worms from infected tooth </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>11.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Softens tooth before extractions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Application of powder from bark of tree to stop pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>(b) Clients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Fifty two participants who reported having oral problems and had dental treatment were interviewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The age of participants ranged from 9 to 70 years; SD = 0.503(Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>More than half live below $100 per month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Most patients reported visiting the TH because of the low cost (69%), TH understand their problems better (12%), fear of death from tooth extractions (8%), and hospital or clinics were too far away (5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>More than two thirds (67.3%) were satisfied with the treatment the TH provided and those who were dissatisfied reported that there was no significant change in their presented complaint and pain persisted even after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Table 4 shows the proximity of TH and health facilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>For 76% it takes about 30 minutes to get to a TH and for more than half an average of 4 hours to get to the nearest oral health care facility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Proximity of patients to TH and health facilities </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Time </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Distance of patient from TH N (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Distance from oral health facility N (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>&lt; 30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>38(76) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>2(3.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>30 min - 1 hr </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>7(14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>17(33.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>1 hr - 4 hrs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>4(8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>5(9.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>&gt;4 hrs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>1(2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>27(52.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>(a) Traditional healers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The fact that more than two thirds of TH in the present study were older than 40 years implies that if speedy interventions to incorporate them into oral health education and promotion efforts are not made, the legacy of the use of traditional medicines in the treatment of oral lesions may be lost [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The most senior TH were illiterate, but form the majority of the trainers and are respected community leaders; therefore there is the existence of knowledge transfer from the elderly to younger healers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The higher preponderance of males in the TH sample is because traditional medicine is a male-dominated profession in the Bui division concurring with the findings of Gessler et al. [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Less than half of the TH had formal training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the training was not standardized, as most were trained by fathers, uncles and other senior TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The average duration of training for an herbalist was 7.5 years with training ranging from 4 to 10 years depending on the ability of the apprentice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>It can be concluded that because of their longer training, herbalists have good knowledge and skills to treat patients, unlike diviners who do not undergo any form of apprenticeship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Most of the TH in the Bui division diagnose and treat problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This finding is similar to studies carried out in the Tanzania and Zambia [2,35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Of the 21 TH in this study, only 76% of them are registered with the Traditional Healer's Association of Cameroon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Increasing the number of registered TH may be a way of regulating the profession and controlling bad practices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Despite the fact that more than two thirds of TH are close to basic primary health facilities, most of their referral for oral problems are to medical doctors and other TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Only few patients were referred to the dental clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Most patients visit TH first, before a medical or dental practitioner [36-39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Some encourage the use of self medication including herbs and common analgesics because of the perception that referral to a dental clinic will be very expensive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Seventy one percent of TH reported that they were aware of the causes of HIV/AIDS and this is comparable to the findings of Pelzer and colleagues [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>TH need to be educated on other practices that can transmit the virus and should also be trained in HIV counseling, condom distribution, community HIV/AIDS and STI education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Sixty seven percent of TH reported that they treat patients for mouth problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>With regard to HIV infections, many TH report that their treatments help patients to regain their appetite, cure the opportunistic lesions and increase the "red blood cell count". </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Their perceived impression is, that if you can increase the red blood cells, the patient feels better [2,3,33,35,36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Pre-testing the TH for knowledge of oral lesions revealed that they could diagnose candidiasis, dental caries and gum diseases from photographs of 6 oral lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Similar findings had been found by Lewis et al. [6] and Rudolph et al. [8] in South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>All the TH reported that they would be willing to learn more about common mouth problems in adult and children and were willing to screen patients for oral manifestations of HIV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, they were also interested in educating their clients about oral health care if given adequate training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A study carried out in Yaoundé, Cameroon has long-established that although the education level varies widely, traditional practitioners have a deep thirst for knowledge and yearn for greater inclusion into the public health sector [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>This is supported by other studies from Africa [2,33,35,36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>In the present study, treatment for oral disease by TH included the use of mouth washes, pain relieving herbs, fumes from burnt food spices used to remove "worms" from infected teeth and the application of powder made from bark of trees to stop pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The use of natural products for the treatment of other oral disease like herpes zoster, tuberculosis, candidiasis and toothache have also been reported by Kisangau [33] and Tapsoba and Deschamps [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>However, one of the problems associated with the use of herbal treatments is that some of them have never been rigorously evaluated or standardized (in terms of a standard pharmacopeia) [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>They are often poorly packed and preserved, limiting their usefulness, accessibility and shelf life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Hillenbrand [3] reported that all healers interviewed acknowledged that the plants that they use can be toxic as some of their ingredients can have profound effects on the mouth, stomach, and the entire gastro-intestinal tract with severe consequences like "iatrogenic gastritis and colitis". </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>A common complaint about traditional medicine is that healers claim they can treat everything whether they have a sound knowledge of the aetiology or patho-physiology of the disease or not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>This calls for caution about the efficacy of their treatment modalities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>(b) Clients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Two thirds of clients in the present study were aged between 21-40 years and this could be due not only to the small sample size, but also the demographic composition of the area since in Cameroon a larger proportion of the population is younger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Maclean and Bannerman [36] found that a higher number of older people visited TH than the younger age groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Kayombo and colleagues [2] have reported that the involvement of oral health into the primary health care system is still minimal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The average cost of treatment from TH is very low (approximately $5) as compared to conventional treatment ($50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Pelzer et al. [36] suggested that patients visit TH because they provide client-centered and personalized health care that is tailored to meet their needs and expectations, paying special respect to social and spiritual matters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless 32% were not satisfied by the treatment provided by the TH, mainly because the pain persisted despite the traditional remedies provided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Treatment for pulpitis was often short-lived. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Reasons for not taking up oral health services included poor accessibility to oral health facilities and unaffordable private dental care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, people were afraid of dental clinics and preferred cheap palliative treatments instead [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>There was also a lack of knowledge of the role of the dental team as efficient oral health care providers as there is an acute shortage of oral health care workers (only one dentist, 2 dental therapists and 4 other dental auxiliaries serve this population of about 800 000 people). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>More than a third reported only visiting the hospital or clinic when their situation got worse (e.g. development of dento-alveolar abscesses, Ludwig's angina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Some TH do refer patients because they are aware of their limitations [41,42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Proximity of the health care professional is a determinant in oral care delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>In the Bui Division, primary oral health care is underdeveloped with poor access to basic oral health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Poor access to oral health facilities limits patient's choices and hence patients prefer to patronize a TH rather than having to travel for more than 4 hours to see an oral health care worker. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The majority of Cameroonians depend on traditional medicines for their health needs with about 7% of the average household health budget is spent on traditional medicines irrespective of the earning of its inhabitants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>All TH operate full-time and greatly out-number the oral health care providers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Most people still rely on TH because their treatment is affordable and TH share their patient's culture, beliefs and values and understand their expectations of health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Hence they are generally more accessible and acceptable as health care providers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Their methods of treatment are effective and less invasive in certain cases, as they make use of local herbs and medicinal plants, though there are sometimes hazards associated with their treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>In view of the fact that factors affecting the oral health seeking behavior of patients in this region cannot be easily removed in a short term, a multisectorial-population based primary health care approach may be an option to break down some of these barriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>This should be based on an empowerment model which will integrate basic oral health care to all aspects of health care at PHC level equip TH with tools that that can assist them with the diagnosis and recording of oral disease, with appropriate referrals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Because TH have close contact with the community, simple basic dental practice applications like the Basic Package of Oral Care (BPOC) can be inculcated into their practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>They may also play a role in educating the community on the use of fluoride in the prevention of dental caries (AFT), restoring teeth using the atraumatic restorative (ART) and minimal invasive (MIT) techniques and carrying out emergency care by simple extractions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>From the findings of the present study, we can conclude that TH play a vital role in the health seeking behaviors of the community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Improving their knowledge and cooperation with oral health workers will serve to reduce inequalities and improve the standard of oral health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>TH can form a bridge linking the community to oral health care providers; can serve as a valuable tool for population-based health prevention and promotion approaches in achieving health for all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Oral health workers in this region have to increase cooperation and collaboration with TH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Therefore, traditional healers could be trained as counselors and educators to disseminate oral health information and carry out minor prevention practices within their communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>A follow-up study in collaboration with plant scientists to investigate the plants being used by TH for healing oral problems will be useful. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>MA contributed to the design of the study as well as acquisition of data, its analysis and interpretation and was involved in the drafting of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>SN made substantial contributions to the conception and design and in the drafting and revision of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>MA would like to thank with sincere gratitude his sponsor Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Aubrey Sheiham for making his dreams of postgraduate study a reality. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>World Health OrganizationTraditional medicine strategy 2002-2005World Health Organization2002Geneva: World Health OrganizationWHO/EDM/TRM/2002.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>KayomboEJUisoFCMbwamboZHMahunnahRLMoshiMJMgondaYHExperience of initiating collaboration of TH in managing HIV and Aids in TanzaniaJ Ethnobio Ethnomed20073610.1186/1746-4269-3-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>HillenbrandEImproving Traditional-Conventional Medicine Collaboration: Perspectives from Cameroonian Traditional PractitionersNordic J African Studies200615115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Ministère de la Sante PubliqueStratégie Sectorielle de Santé: Analyse Situationnelle du Secteur Sante au Cameroun2002Paper prepared by Ministry of Public Health, Yaounde, Cameroon </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Republic of Cameroon: Presidential decree no. 95-0401995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Kofi-TsekpoMInstitutionalization of African traditional medicine in health care systems in AfricaAfr J Health Sci20041-2iii </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>RudolphMJOgunbodedeEOMistryMManagement of the oral manifestations of HIV/AIDS by traditional healers and care giversCurationis20073056617515317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>KingRHomsyJInvolving traditional healers in AIDS education and counseling in sub-Saharan Africa: A reviewAIDS199711Suppl AS2172259451988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>LewisHARudolphMJMistryMMonyatsiVMarambanaTRamelaPOral health knowledge and original practices of African traditional healers in Zonkizizwe and Dube, South AfricaSADJ20045924324615457910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>OgunbodedeEDental care: the role of Traditional HealersWorld Health Forum199112444445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>AkpataESAkinrimsiEOAntibacterial activity of extracts from some African chewing sticksOral Surg, Oral Med, Oral Pathol19774471772210.1016/0030-4220(77)90381-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>EnwonwuCOAnyanwuRCThe chewing stick in oral health careWorld Health Forum19856232234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>SoteEOThe relative effectiveness of chewing sticks and toothbrush on plaque removalAfrican Dent J198724853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>NgilishoLAFMoshaHJPoulsenSThe role of traditional healers in the treatment of toothache in Tanga Region, TanzaniaCommunity Dent Health1994112402427850644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>KikwiluENHizaJFRTooth bud extraction and rubbing of herbs by TH in Tanzania: Prevalence, and sociological and environmental factors influencing the practicesInt J Paed Dent19977192410.1111/j.1365-263X.1997.tb00268.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>BabaSPKayEJThe mythology of killer deciduous canine tooth in southern SudanJ Paed1989144849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>BryantATZulu Medicine and Medicine-Men1970Cape Town, Struik </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>GumedeMVTraditional Healers1991Johannesburg: Skotaville Publishers </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>HamzaOJvan den Boutvan den BeukelCJMateeMIMoshiMJMikxFHSelemaniHOMbwamboZHVan der VenAJVerweijPEAntifungal activity of traditionally used Tanzanian plantIn the proceedings of the First African and Middle East IADR Federation Conference2005Kuwait </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>TapsobaHDeschampsJPUse of medicinal plants for the treatment of oral diseases in Burkina FasoJ Ethnopharmacol2005342347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>El-HilalyJHmammouchiMLyoussiBEthnobotanical studies and economic evaluation of medicinal plants in Taounate province (Northern MoroccoJ Ethnopharmacol2003861495810.1016/S0378-8741(03)00012-612738079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>KambiziLAfolayanAJAn ethnobotanical study of plants used for the treatment of sexually transmitted diseases (njovhera) in Guruve District, ZimbabweJ Ethnopharmacol2001775910.1016/S0378-8741(01)00251-311483371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>GesslerMCMsuyaDENkunyaMHMwasumbiLBScharAHeinrichMAnnerMTraditional healers in Tanzania: the treatment of malaria with plant remediesJ Ethnopharmacol1995481314410.1016/0378-8741(95)01293-M8719974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>SaritaPTTuominenRUse of health care services in two rural communities in TanzaniaCommunity Dent Oral Epidemiol19932113313510.1111/j.1600-0528.1993.tb00737.x8348785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>WilkinsonDGcabasheLLurieMTraditional healers as tuberculosis treatment supervisors: precedent and potentialInt J Tuberc Lung Dis200151072107411716345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>EdwardsSD:Traditional and modern medicine in South Africa: a research studySoc Sci Med1986221273610.1016/0277-9536(86)90194-23749954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>HomsyJKingRThe role of Traditional healers in HIV/AIDS counseling in Kampala, Uganda. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Key issues and debatesSoc Afr SIDA1996132312179372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Masauso NzimaMRomanoKAnyangweSWisemanJMacwan'giMKendallCGreenECA targeted intervention research on TH perspectives of sexually transmitted illnesses in urban Zambia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Current ResearchSoc Afr SIDA199613712179374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Abdool KarimSSTraditional healers and AIDS Prevention1998CERSA, South African Medical Research Council, Durban </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>GreenECInvolving healersAIDS Action199946312296172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>HewsonHGTraditional healers in Southern AfricaAnnals Int Med199812810291034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>NgubaneHBody and Mind in Zulu Medicine1977New York: Academic Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>ChoncoWZThe African Bantu traditional practice of medicine: some preliminary observationsSoc Sci Med1972628332210.1016/0037-7856(72)90104-75049311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>KisangauDPLyaruuHVMHoseaKMJosephCCUse of traditional medicines in the management of HIV/AIDS infections in Tanzania: a case in Bukoba rural districtJ Ethnobiol Ethnomed2007332910.1186/1746-4269-3-2917207273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>GesslerMCMsuyaDENkunyaMHMwasumbiLBScharAHeinrichMAnnerMTraditional Healers in Tanzania: socio-cultural profile and three short portraitsJ Ethnopharmacol19954814516010.1016/0378-8741(95)01295-O8719975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>BurnettABaggaleyRNdovi-MacMillanMSulweJHang'ombaBBennettJCaring for people with HIV in Zambia: Are Traditional Healers and formal health workers willing to work together?AIDS Care1999114819110.1080/0954012994787510533542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>PeltzerKMngqundanisoNPetrosGHIV/AIDS/STI/TB knowledge, beliefs and practices of traditional healers in KwaZulu-Natal, South AfricaAIDS Care2006186081310.1080/0954012050029420616831789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>MacleanUBannermanRHUtilization of indigenous healers in national health delivery systemsSoc Sci Med1982161815181610.1016/0277-9536(82)90441-57178926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>MorrisKTreating HIV in South Africa: a tale of two systemsThe Lancet2001357119010.1016/S0140-6736(00)04401-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>PuckreeTMkhizeMMgobhoziZLinJAfrican Traditional Healers: what health care professionals need to knowInt J Rehabil Res2002252475110.1097/00004356-200212000-0000112451299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>NationsMKNutoSAS"Tooth worms", poverty tattoo and dental care conflicts in Northeast BrazilSoc Sci Med20025422924410.1016/S0277-9536(01)00019-311824928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>SaubRJaafarNA dental anthropological study of health and illness behaviour among Orang Asli of the Semai tribe: the perspective of Traditional HealersMed J Malaysia200156401712014757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
