<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMRI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BioMed Research International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2314-6133</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2314-6141</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3581133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/734137</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX RFS: A Comprehensive Technical Approach for the In Vitro Exposure of Airway Epithelial Cells to the Particulate Matter at the Air-Liquid Interface </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aufderheide</surname><given-names>Michaela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">0000-0002-7924-7174</contrib-id><name><surname>Halter</surname><given-names>Beat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">0000-0001-7873-5646</contrib-id><name><surname>Möhle</surname><given-names>Niklas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hochrainer</surname><given-names>Dieter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Cultex Laboratories GmbH, Feodor-Lynen-Straße 21, 30625 Hannover, Germany</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Halter Engineering GmbH, Huebstraße 16, 9100 Herisau, Switzerland</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Von der Hardt 16, 57392 Oberkirchen, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Michaela Aufderheide: <email>m.aufderheide@cultex-laboratories.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Abderrahim Nemmar </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><elocation-id>734137</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Michaela Aufderheide et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The EU Regulation on Registration, Evaluation, Authorization and Restriction of Chemicals (REACH) demands the implementation of alternative methods for analyzing the hazardous effects of chemicals including particulate formulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In the field of inhalation toxicology, a variety of in vitro models have been developed for such studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To simulate the in vivo situation, an adequate exposure device is necessary for the direct exposure of cultivated lung cells at the air-liquid interface (ALI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX RFS fulfills these requirements and has been optimized for the exposure of cells to atomized suspensions, gases, and volatile compounds as well as micro- and nanosized particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This study provides information on the construction and functional aspects of the exposure device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>By using the Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) analysis, the technical design was optimized to realize a stable, reproducible, and homogeneous deposition of particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The efficiency of the exposure procedure is demonstrated by exposing A549 cells dose dependently to lactose monohydrate, copper(II) sulfate, copper(II) oxide, and micro- and nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>All copper compounds induced cytotoxic effects, most pronounced for soluble copper(II) sulfate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Micro- and nanosized copper(II) oxide also showed a dose-dependent decrease in the cell viability, whereby the nanosized particles decreased the metabolic activity of the cells more severely. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Provoked by public pressure and triggered by an increasing number of lethal lung diseases over the last few decades [1, 2], more and more studies in the field of inhalation toxicology now concentrate on the understanding of particle-lung interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Investigations of the toxicological effects of inhalable substances on the respiratory tract mainly focus on results from animal experiments based on the OECD guideline 403 on acute inhalation toxicology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>So far, only a few in vitro alternatives to animal inhalation tests for toxicology have been described [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>However, none of them is validated or officially accepted by the authorities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Recent changes in the EU chemical policy, namely, the new Registration, Evaluation, Authorization and Restriction of Chemicals directive (REACH; EC no. 1907/2006), and complaints about the immense number of animals needed to fulfill the requirements of REACH [6] demand the development and implementation of novel in vitro technologies—also in the field of inhalation toxicology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the effects of relevant particulate substances, only classic methodological approaches are available using either suspended or dissolved particles under submerged conditions in cell culture experiments [4, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The main concerns about these test methods are (1) the unrealistic behavior of suspended particles and (2) culture and exposure conditions which do not reflect the situation in the lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The fact of losing nanosized particles by agglomeration or the uncontrollable behavior of nanosized particles in suspensions may lead to uncertainties in the results [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Another major point of the discussion is the transferability of data from animal experiments to the human organism due to species-specific reactions and the generation of false positive or negative results [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>One of the “first” approaches for direct cell exposure came from Tarkington et al. [10] who conducted the atmosphere via a vertical stream directly over the cultivated test organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The system is also based on a biphasic cell culture exposed at an air-liquid interface [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The basic idea is to mimic the inhalation cycle in vitro by taking into consideration the most important biological and technical aspects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The selection of an appropriate cell model and its cultivation at the air-liquid interface are the basic prerequisites for such a system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the technical implementation should guarantee the direct contact of the test substances with the cells, as well as the homogeneous exposure of the entire cell layer without interfering with the cell viability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>These theoretical concepts led to the development of the CULTEX exposure module in 1999 by Aufderheide and Mohr [12] for the exposure of cultivated cells at the air-liquid interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The test aerosol is conducted directly over the cells through specially designed inlet nozzles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This setup guarantees a close contact between the test aerosol and the cells without any interference of the cell culture media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The first CULTEX exposure devices were used for the exposure to complex mixtures like cigarette smoke and gases, or in a modified version to analyze the mutagenic potency of airborne materials in the AMES assay [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, a large number of other air-liquid interface exposure systems are available, ranging from the exposure of two-cell culture plates (6-well), like the ALICE exposure device [14] or a flow-through system [15] to a radial multiwell module [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>All of these modules have certain advantages and disadvantages and may therefore only be used for a limited test assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The results obtained from exposure studies with the CULTEX RFS module have shown that the interactions between cells and particles are closely linked to the physical and chemical properties of these compounds and have advanced the redesign of the handmade CULTEX glass modules. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX Radial Flow System (RFS) presented here overcomes the limitations of its predecessor model and includes all features that are required to realize the exposure of cultivated cells to airborne particles under realistic conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Material and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Technical Description </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX RFS module was designed for exposing adherent growing cells at the air-liquid interface and is a precision instrument, characterized by a modular construction (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The basic CULTEX RFS consists of the following parts: (1) the inlet adapter which connects the aerosol generation and aerosol guiding module (Figure 1), (2) the aerosol guiding module to conduct and distribute the particles to be deposited on the cell culture inserts in the sampling module (Figures 2(a) and 2(b)), and (3) the sampling and socket module with three exposure chambers where the cell culture inserts or Petri dishes are located (Figures 1 and 2(c)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The aerosol guiding module as well as the sampling module can be heated to the appropriate temperature (e.g., 37°C) by the connection to an external water bath. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The socket module (4) guides the sampling module on the slide rails of the locking device (5) and serves as a spacer for integrating additional functions, like a control unit for electrostatic precipitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In addition to the above-mentioned modular components, the system can also be equipped with special adapters to enable the use of commercial inserts from different suppliers and of different sizes or for Petri dishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The aerosol emission ducts are adapted correspondingly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To increase the particle deposition efficiency, notably for nanosized particles, the electrical deposition device (Cultex EDD) can further be integrated into the technical setup (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Test Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Dry powder atmospheres were prepared from the substances listed in Tables 1 and 2 and used for the exposure studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The substances were pressed into powder cakes by the CULTEX HyP-Hydraulic Press (Cultex Laboratories GmbH, Germany), which allows electronically controlled compression of a high variety of powders by a pneumo-hydraulic cylinder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Aerosol Generation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The aerosol was generated from the prepared powder cakes with the CULTEX DG (Dust Generator) (Cultex Laboratories GmbH) according to Wright [5] (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The fully computerized generator is able to provide uniform airborne concentrations of dust over a long period of time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The highly compressed substances are scraped off by a rotating scraper under standardized controlled conditions (feed rate 0.24 to 20 mm/h, rotation 1 to 800 revs/h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The total exposure time is varied from 15, 30, to 60 minutes to generate different particle concentrations on the cell culture membranes without changing the aerosol generation or any other physical or chemical parameter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The generated particles were transported to the integrated elutriator by a constant air stream (8 L/min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The elutriator retains undesired large particles (&gt; approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>8 μm) and serves as a reservoir for a uniform aerosol which is finally drawn through the CULTEX RFS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The complete experimental setup is shown in Figure 5 consisting of the particle generation unit, two CULTEX RFS devices, and two pumps for the medium supply. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The cells are exposed to the test aerosol and clean air (process control) in parallel, in order to preclude process-related reactions which might interfere with the substance-specific effects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>CFD Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The aerosol flow within the experimental setup was simulated and optimized by means of Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) software (ANSYS CFX, ANSYS Incorporated). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Particle Number and Mass Distribution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The determination of the particle number and mass distribution was conducted with an Aerodynamic Particle Sizer APS (3321/TSI Incorporated) in the size range of 0.5 to 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>By accelerating particles through a nozzle and optical time-of-flight measurement of the particles, they are classified into 51 logarithmic size ranges between 0.523 and 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Particle Deposition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The deposition of the particles was analyzed by gravimetric methods, using the precision balance (SE2-F filter ultra-microbalance, Sartorius). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In preliminary tests, the particle mass concentration within the exposure system was analyzed at three sampling points (sampling point 1: 200 seconds, sampling point 2 + 3: 60 minutes) to determine appropriate exposure times for the corresponding test particles (Figure 6) and to check for uniform particle distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The first sampling point was located directly after the elutriator, the second at the outlet port of the aerosol emission duct to estimate the particle mass entering the exposure chamber, and the third at the insert membrane surface to measure the particle mass deposited on the cultivated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The particle mass was determined by collecting the particles on filter pads (glass fiber filter/GF-A/Macherey-Nagel), which were weighed before and after the exposure over a constant period (15 minutes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>This approach allows the analysis of the deposition efficiency of each test atmosphere within the exposure module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Under these experimental conditions, the deposited particle numbers on the cell cultures can only be calculated by taking into consideration the measurements of the Aerodynamic Particle Sizer APS (3321/TSI Incorporated) and the system-specific deposition capacities (Aufderheide et al. [17], Supplementary Material). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cell Cultivation and Exposure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>For particle exposure experiments, the human lung adenocarcinoma epithelial cell line A549 (ATCC number: CCL-185) was used [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The cells were grown in Dulbecco's MEM (Biochrom FG 0145, Germany) supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum and gentamicin (5 μg/mL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>A549 cells were seeded onto microporous membranes (growth area: 4.2 cm²) of cell culture inserts (0.4 μm pore size, BD Biosciences) with a density of 1∗105 cells/cm2 and cultivated submerged in a cell culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>After 24 hours, the apical medium was removed from the confluent cell layers and the direct exposure at the air-liquid interface with the CULTEX RFS was started. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The cells were exposed either to the test substances (deposition rate: 25 μg/cm²/15 min) or clean air (process control) for 15, 30, and 60 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The incubator control cultures were cultivated at the air-liquid interface in the incubator during the exposure period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>WST Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The aim of our study was the characterization of the exposure device, limited to the functional description of the system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, we used only one biological endpoint, the metabolic activity of the cells, to demonstrate dose-dependent cytotoxic reactions, not investigating further into the mechanisms behind these effects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>After a postincubation time of 24 hours (air-liquid interface; 37°C/5% CO2), the particle-exposed cells and the control cultures (incubator control: unexposed cells, process control: clean air-exposed cells) were analyzed for cell viability by using the WST-1 assay for the mitochondrial activity according to the manufacturer's instructions (Roche Diagnostics, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The data of the exposed cells were normalized to the values of the clean air control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The incubator controls were not considered, because they did not show significant differences to the clean air controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>2.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The results of three independent tests with three samples each is expressed as mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A Student's t-test was performed to analyze whether the differences between the mean values of the three exposure times are significant [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Deposition Efficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX RFS was designed for exposing adherent cells at the air-liquid interface to airborne materials like gases, complex mixtures, and particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>When dealing with particulate matter especially, questions arise concerning the deposition efficiency of such an exposure device. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The basic and theoretical considerations forming the basis of the efficiency of the system are already described by Aufderheide et al. ([17], Electronic Supplementary Material). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>CFD Analysis—Flow Conditions within the System </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>When developing the CULTEX RFS and its peripheral devices, a key to achieve uniform particle deposition on the cell cultures was the simulation and optimization of the particle flow within the system by means of CFD analysis (Figures 7 to 9). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Figure 7 shows a cross-section through the elutriator (a) and a streamline velocity plot (b) of the CFD analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The basic principle of an elutriator consists of separating small (light) from large (heavy) particles in a vertically upward directed stream. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The elutriator features an additional outlet at the bottom for discharging excess aerosol, as aerosol generation may require higher flow rates (e.g., 8 L/min) than those for the CULTEX RFS exposure module (e.g., 1.6 L/min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The streamline plot shows a curl in the lower zone of the device but a uniform upstream above, which is essential for a reliable particle separation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The results are based on flow rates of 8.0 L/min at the inlet, 1.09 L/min at the outlet, and 6.91 L/min at the aerosol excess outlet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Further calculations with the same flow rate at the inlet but 1.59 L/min at the aerosol outlet showed no substantial differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Figure 8 shows particle trajectory simulations with particle sizes of 2 μm (a) and 10 μm (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>While small particles are transported upwards to the aerosol outlet and the Cultex RFS module, large particles remain in the elutriator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The major portion of the particles is carried to the excess outlet, as a flow rate of only 1.09 L/min from totally 8 L/min was conducted to the module in this simulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>When testing prototypes of the Cultex RFS module, the distribution patterns between the three deposition chambers and within the individual chambers showed considerable differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>CFD calculations of the gas flow lines and particle trajectories resulted in the following essential findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Figure 9(a) shows the aerosol flow channels within the Cultex RFS module including a curved aerosol feeding tube with 6 mm diameter and 200 mm length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The flow lines represent an aerosol flow of 1590 mL/min in the feeding tube, which is divided into three minor flows of 30 mL/min leading to the deposition chambers and an excess flow of 1500 mL/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Backtracking a defined number of particles from the deposition chamber to the beginning of the curved aerosol feeding tube (which is equal to the elutriator outlet) showed that these particles originate from specific locations in the tube profile (Figure 9(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Further calculations showed that the specific locations are sensitive to changes in tube bending radius, tube length, or flow rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>As the particle concentration and particle size distribution at the beginning of the feeding tube is usually nonuniform across the tube profile, the distribution pattern in the deposition chambers are consequently also nonuniform. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>An optimal solution to completely avoid these undesired effects was the integration of a jet nozzle into the inlet adapter of the Cultex RFS module.  Figure 10(a) shows the deposition of copper(II) oxide micro on insert membranes without using a jet nozzle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The integration of a jet nozzle into the inlet adapter (Figure 10(b)) resulted in a homogenous distribution of the particles on the insert membranes (Figure 10(c), Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Dose-Response Relationship </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>After optimizing the deposition characteristics within the CULTEX RFS module, A549 cells were exposed to lactose monohydrate (process control), copper(II) sulfate (soluble substance), copper(II) oxide micro as well as copper(II) oxide nanoparticles (insoluble) for 15, 30, and 60 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The particle generation was adjusted for each substance to result in a particle deposition of 25 μg/cm² (low dose) during an exposure time of 15 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The concentration (low effect level, LOEL) is based on an interdisciplinary European project in which the cytotoxic potency of a variety of particles was analyzed with different cell types under submersed culture conditions [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The conditions for the particle generation had to be adjusted in preliminary experiments due to substance-specific variations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>24 hours after exposure, the cell viability was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The values obtained for the particle-exposed cultures were normalized to the clean air-exposed cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The results are shown in Figures 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, and 18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Generally the clean air-exposed cells (process control) showed no significant reduction in the cell viability in comparison with the incubator control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the exposure process itself had no influence on the metabolic activity of the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The exposure of the cell cultures to the test compounds showed, dependent on the chemical and physical properties of the particulate atmosphere, considerable differences in the cytotoxic response among the three exposure times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The comparison of the 15, 30, and 60 minutes exposures in a Student's t-test demonstrates significant differences with a 5% error probability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>No significant differences could be obtained for lactose monohydrate (30 minutes compared to 15 minutes) and copper(II) oxide micro-sized (60 minutes compared to 30 minutes) due to the low number of tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The exposure of A549 cells to lactose monohydrate (negative substance) led to a slight decrease in the cell viability of the cells after 15 minutes (94% of the clean air control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>By increasing the exposure time to 60 minutes, the metabolic activity of the cells was reduced by 30% in comparison to the clean air control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>At that point, the cultures were covered by a dense layer of the particulate matter thus pointing to an overload effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The particle number (black line) and mass distribution (red line) of the lactose monohydrate aerosol dependent on particle size are shown in Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The units number, respectively, mass per μm∗cm3 may be unfamiliar at first glance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>As the curves are based on particle counts, classified to 51 particle size intervals, the counts have to be divided not only through the volume but also through the interval width to get the required values for particle distribution curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The particle number distribution curve exhibits its peak value at a particle size of 0.7 μm while the particle mass distribution curve shows its peak value at a particle size of 4.2 μm due to the greater mass of larger particles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The exposure of the cell populations to copper(II) sulfate led to a pronounced decrease in the cell viability after 15 minutes 19% of the clean air control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>By increasing the time to 60 minutes, the metabolic activity was reduced by more than 91% compared to the clean air control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The peak for the particle number distribution was at 0.9 μm and the peak for the particle mass distribution was at 3.8 μm (Figure 14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Both particle number and particle mass were about five times higher than for lactose monohydrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The results after the exposure of A549 cells to copper(II) oxide micro also indicated a dose-dependent decrease of the metabolic activity over the exposure time (Figure 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The decrease of cell viability after 60 minutes exposure (61% reduction in comparison to the synthetic air control) is significantly higher than for lactose monohydrate but not as clear as for copper(II) sulfate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In comparison with copper(II) sulfate, the particle number distribution of copper(II) oxide micro also showed a peak at 0.9 μm, but with a more than four times lower number of particles (Figure 16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The values for the particle mass distribution were about 25% lower compared to copper(II) sulfate, indicating that the substances mostly differ in their content of small particles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The cell viability of the A549 cells was significantly reduced after the exposure to copper(II) oxide nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>After 15 minutes, the metabolic activity was reduced to less than 50% compared to the clean air and incubator control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A particle mass of 100 μg/cm2 (60 minutes) led to a reduction in the metabolic activity of 85%, indicating a higher cytotoxic effect by the nanopowder compared to the micro. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) oxide nano does not differ strongly from copper(II) oxide micro in numbers of sub-μm particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The nanopowder exhibits much lower mass distribution values, however, due to few particles in the size range over 1 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Due to changes in the EU regulations concerning the approval of chemical substances (Regulation (EU) no. 1907/2006) and the ongoing demand for alternative methods, new cell systems and exposure techniques were developed and characterized, also in the field of inhalation toxicology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The latter should meet special requirements with regard to the cell type and the type of exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The biological test systems include bronchial (Calu-3, 16HBE14o-, BEAS-2B) and alveolar epithelial (A549) cell lines, mostly from tumors as well as human primary cells isolated from different regions of the respiratory tract [22–25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>At the moment primary cell cultures are mostly studied under mechanistic aspects (differentiation, cellular interactions) [26] and are not used routinely for screening methods to address acute toxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the studies are mostly performed with cell lines like the alveolar epithelial cell line A549, which allows the generation of stable cultures (undifferentiated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The advantage of these cultures is the delivery of stable, reproducible, and significant data for the calculation of dose-response curves as well as the definition of key values (effective dose: EC50). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The exposure of cultivated cells from the respiratory tract for studying the effects of airborne substances represents a challenge with regard to the experimental design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The exposure of cells under conventional submerged conditions, mostly with soluble test substances, shows a variety of shortcomings like the interference of the test atmosphere with medium components, unrealistic exposure conditions including uncertain effective doses for gases and particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Therefore, several approaches have been made for the development of exposure systems (Table 4) at the air-liquid interface [3, 12, 14, 17, 27–35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Under such conditions, the cells are in direct contact with the test aerosol, which is conducted through the exposure device to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The exposure systems have to fulfill cell-specific requirements, meaning the maintenance of the cell cultures during the exposure process by medium supply and the establishment of a cell-specific environment (pH value, 37°C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>All described systems have taken into consideration those basic requirements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The inserts are located in medium-containing chambers, connected with a medium supply for intermittent or continuous medium exchange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In the system described by Adamson et al. [36], 4 culture vessels are placed together in a chamber filled up with medium to the bottom of the cell culture inserts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In the CULTEX RFS, and also the CULTEX glass modules [27, 28], the inserts are housed separately and are supplied individually with nutrients, as independent exposure chambers within one module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The medium level is adjusted via an overflow tube to establish comparable conditions in all three chambers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The basic principle of cellular exposure to airborne materials is based on the treatment of the cultivated cells at the air-liquid interface (ALI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The experimental setup to realize a direct contact between the cells and the test atmosphere differs considerably in the different systems, which are listed in Table 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A limited number of devices favor the exposure of the cultures to an aerosol passing through a box or exposure chamber [35, 36], but most of the exposure systems prefer a stream directed towards the cell culture to realize a close contact between the test atmosphere and the cell surface for depositing particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Gaseous compounds can be studied in all systems due to the homogeneous distribution of their test atmosphere, whereas the exposure of particulate materials is based mostly on a directed aerosol flow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>A comparative study of the different test systems is limited due to the limited availability of the modules and the absence of information. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX glass modules as well as the RFS are designed to establish an incoming flow which is directed immediately via emission ducts to the surface of the cells to guarantee a close contact with the test atmosphere, both qualitatively and quantitatively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In comparison with the glass modules, the aerosol guiding module of the RFS has been optimized concerning the uniform distribution of the incoming test atmosphere to the three exposure chambers, thus stabilizing the whole exposure process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In the glass modules, the aerosol is guided linearly above the module and the sampling points for the test atmosphere are arranged in succession. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In the case of gaseous compounds, the homogeneous distribution of the atmosphere is not limited, but airborne particles belong to another category, especially with regard to their aerosol physical properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>A linear flow path above the glass module leads to a concentration gradient, which may result, due to the sequentially arranged sampling points, at different exposure levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the CULTEX RFS module is characterized by a central inlet for the test atmosphere into the exposure device, wherefrom the aerosol is distributed into the chambers and the particles deposited on the cell cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The resulting data are characterized by a small standard deviation within a test or for multiple experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Another relevant advantage of the new system is the adjustment of the medium level, which ensures a comparable microenvironment for all cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The level in the Cultex RFS is controlled by special overflow tubes to stabilize the sensitive microclimate around the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>An autonomous medium supply for each cell culture insert offers the opportunity to test different medium additives without interaction between the three test chambers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The new modular design of the Cultex RFS guarantees a high flexibility in working with different types of cell culture inserts or even Petri dishes (for the AMES assay) by using special adapters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The efficiency of the exposure process depends on the deposition efficiency and represents, especially in the case of fine and ultrafine particles (nano particles), one of the main challenges [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The deposition efficiency of the particles in most air-liquid interface systems is based on sedimentation and diffusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, a characterization of the test aerosol with regard to the particle number and particle mass dependent on the particle size is one of the main requirements to judge the biological activity of the airborne material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Due to changes within the aerosol during the generation process and due to particle-particle interactions, the primary particle size should only be used as a basic indication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In this context, particle loss within the system and agglomeration of the particles has to be taken into account. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>In the literature, the deposition efficiency rate of in vitro exposure devices is described inconsistently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Theoretical considerations and experimental exposure data with ultrafine carbonaceous model particles with a CMD of 95 nm resulted in an efficiency of 2% [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The combination of such air-liquid interface exposure systems with an electrical charger and precipitator could improve particle deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Experimental data from Savi et al. [16] showed that the deposition efficiency can be increased to 30% with this type of setup without causing a cytotoxic effect on the exposed cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>First results obtained with the Cultex RFS in combination with an electrical deposition device (Cultex EDD) indicated that the efficiency for particles which are not deposited by sedimentation or diffusion can be increased up to 95% (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The outstanding importance of particle size and mass for the deposition efficiency highlights the importance of a controlled and stable generation of particulate atmospheres as well as the behavior of such particles in an exposure device. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>To obtain more insights into the flow conditions within our Cultex RFS module, CFD analysis was conducted by taking into consideration all components of the experimental setup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>CFD simulations included the particle distribution in the tubing system (connection between the elutriator and the exposure module) and the exposure module itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Here, we found that inhomogeneous particle distributions propagate over long distances due to laminar flow conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The integration of a jet nozzle into the inlet adapter enabled a homogeneous particle distribution and deposition on the insert membranes as shown in Figure 10 at the example of copper(II) oxide micro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The CFD analysis provides a good method to simulate the trajectories of the particles from generation to deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The consideration of different experimental conditions like the air flow rate or dimensions of the connecting tubes allows the selection of the appropriate experimental design to enhance the efficiency of the exposure system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Besides the experimental setup, the chemical and physical properties of the particles highly influence their deposition efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>To compare the biological activity of the different copper compounds, the particle mass concentration per area was adjusted for each substance to establish a comparable particle mass deposition (deposition rate: 25 μg/cm²/15 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>A549 cells were exposed for 15, 30, and 60 minutes at the air-liquid interface to the different test atmospheres and the metabolic activity of the cells was analyzed as an estimate for cytotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In comparison to the incubator control, the cells that were exposed to clean air showed no reduction in the cell viability, indicating that the exposure procedure itself had no effect on this analyzed endpoint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>As a negative substance control we used lactose, which induced no considerable cell damage (13% after an exposure time of 30 minutes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>At the end of the exposure period, the cultures were covered by a dense particle layer and a further reduction in cell viability (37% of the clean air control) was measured probably due to an overload effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In comparison with lactose monohydrate, all copper compounds induced significant dose-related effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The cytotoxic signal correlated strongly with the chemical and physical properties of the test compound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) sulfate, as soluble compound, induced a pronounced cytotoxic effect already after an exposure time of 15 minutes (reduction of cell viability of 80%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Comparable effects could also be observed for the insoluble copper(II) oxide compounds, but to a lesser extent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>As described by Karlsson and coworkers [38], the exposure of the cells to both substances resulted in a dose-dependent decrease in the cell viability by increasing the particle concentration, whereby the copper(II) oxide nanomaterial appeared to be more harmful to the cells than copper(II) oxide micro, based on the exposed particle mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>In the literature, nanoparticles are repeatedly described to be more potent in causing a cellular damage than microparticles [38–40], but there is also evidence that there is no difference in their biological activity [41–43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the above-mentioned studies, our direct exposure studies with nanosized copper(II) oxide exhibited a stronger cytotoxicity than the micro-sized particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Most of the studies on micro- or nanosized particles have been conducted under submersed conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Ahamed and coworkers also used A549 cells, which were treated with CuO nanoparticles (NP) suspended in medium (0, 10, 25, and 50 μg/mL for 24 hours) [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>CuO NPs significantly decreased cell viability in a dose-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The highest concentration (50 μg/mL) induced a reduction in viability of 52%, whereas the directly exposed A549 cells showed a decrease of more than 75%, pointing to a more efficient contact and interaction between deposited particles and the lung cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Investigations of Karlsson et al. support this assessment [38, 45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Concerning the number of particles per cm2 for each substance, A549 cells were exposed in the case of copper(II) oxide nano to more particles in comparison to copper(II) oxide micro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the higher cytotoxicity may also be a result of the higher number of smaller particles coming into contact with the surface of the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In summary, our results show that an efficient and stable cell exposure system like the Cultex RFS module allows a reproducible analysis of dose-dependent reactions to airborne materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The cell cultures can be exposed to the generated particulate atmospheres, characterized with regard to particle size and mass distribution, under controlled conditions thus favoring the generation of valid data for the calculation of key values (effective dose). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>These data can be compared with animal or clinical data and offer the possibility to verify the relevance and meaningfulness of these in vitro studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Disclosure</title><p>M. Aufderheide and N. Möhle are employees of Cultex Laboratories GmbH. B. Halter and D. Hochrainer are consultants.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>1BarnesPJNew therapies for chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseMedical Principles and Practice20101953303382-s2.0-7795479049520639653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>2LopezADMurrayCCJLThe global burden of disease, 1990–2020Nature Medicine1998411124112432-s2.0-0031789272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>3BérubéKAufderheideMBrehenyD In vitro models of inhalation toxicity and disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The report of a FRAME workshopAlternatives to Laboratory Animals2009371891412-s2.0-64849086385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>4MaySJensenBWolkenhauerMSchneiderMLehrCMDissolution techniques for in vitro testing of dry powders for inhalationPharmaceutical Research20122982157216622528980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>5WrightBMA new dust-feed mechanismJournal of Scientific Instruments19502711215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>6RovidaCHartungTRe-evaluation of animal numbers and costs for in vivo tests to accomplish REACH legislation requirements for chemicals—a report by the transatlantic think tank for toxicology (t(4))ALTEX20092631872082-s2.0-7394913261519907906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>7RaemyDOGrassRNStarkWJSchumacherCMCliftMJEffects of flame made zinc oxide particles in human lung cells—a comparison of aerosol and suspension exposuresParticle and Fibre Toxicology20129, article 33 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>8LimbachLKLiYGrassRNOxide nanoparticle uptake in human lung fibroblasts: effects of particle size, agglomeration, and diffusion at low concentrationsEnvironmental Science and Technology20053923937093762-s2.0-2844444264616382966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>9HartungTThoughts on limitations of animal modelsParkinsonism &amp; Related Disorders200814supplement 2S81S832-s2.0-4704910601318585949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>10TarkingtonBKWuRSunWMNikulaKJWilsonDWLastJA In vitro exposure of tracheobronchial epithelial cells and of tracheal explants to ozoneToxicology1994881–351682-s2.0-00282216928160205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>11VoisinCAertsCJakubczakEHoudretJLTonnelTBEffects of nitrogen dioxide on alveolar macrophages surviving in the gas phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>A new experimental model for the study of in vitro cytotoxicity of toxic gases (author's transl)Bulletin Européen de Physiopathologie Respiratoire1977131137144843644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>12AufderheideMMohrUCULTEX–a new system and technique for the cultivation and exposure of cells at the air/liquid interfaceExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology19995164894902-s2.0-003338175210661806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>13AufderheideMMohrUA modified CULTEX system for the direct exposure of bacteria to inhalable substancesExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology20045564514542-s2.0-414312467615384250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>14LenzAGKargELentnerBDittrichVBrandenbergerCA dose-controlled system for air-liquid interface cell exposure and application to zinc oxide nanoparticlesParticle and Fibre Toxicology20096, article 32 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>15de BruijneKEbersvillerSSextonKGDesign and testing of Electrostatic Aerosol In Vitro Exposure System (EAVES): an alternative exposure system for particlesInhalation Toxicology2009212911012-s2.0-6074909150718800273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>16SaviMKalbererMLangDA novel exposure system for the efficient and controlled deposition of aerosol particles onto cell culturesEnvironmental Science and Technology20084215566756742-s2.0-4874910033418754491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>17AufderheideMSchefflerSMohleNHalterBHochrainerDAnalytical in vitro approach for studying cyto- and genotoxic effects of particulate airborne materialAnalytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry2011401103213322021695378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>18GiardDJAaronsonSATodaroGJ In vitro cultivation of human tumors: establishment of cell lines derived from a series of solid tumorsJournal of the National Cancer Institute1973515141714232-s2.0-00157592324357758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>19LieberMSmithBSzakalAA continuous tumor-cell line from a human lung carcinoma with properties of type II alveolar epithelial cellsInternational Journal of Cancer197617162702-s2.0-0017275417175022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>20KohlrauschFPraktische Physik: zum Gebrauch für Unterricht, Forschung und Technik199624. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Aufl.Stuttgart, GermanyB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>TeubnerV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Kose, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Wagner, Ed. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>21NanoCareHealth related aspects of nanomaterialsProject Report2009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>22ForbesBShahAMartinGPLansleyABThe human bronchial epithelial cell line 16HBE14o- as a model system of the airways for studying drug transportInternational Journal of Pharmaceutics20032571-21611672-s2.0-003743381212711171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>23GraingerCIGreenwellLLLockleyDJMartinGPForbesBCulture of Calu-3 cells at the air interface provides a representative model of the airway epithelial barrierPharmaceutical Research2006237148214902-s2.0-3374563007216779708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>24PennAMurphyGBarkerSHenkWPennLCombustion-derived ultrafine particles transport organic toxicants to target respiratory cellsEnvironmental Health Perspectives200511389569632-s2.0-2384455239016079063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>25Rothen-RutishauserBBlankFMuhlfeldCGehrP In vitro models of the human epithelial airway barrier to study the toxic potential of particulate matterExpert Opinion on Drug Metabolism and Toxicology200848107510892-s2.0-5104910764718680442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>26GrayACMcLeodJDClothierRHA review of in vitro modelling approaches to the identification and modulation of squamous metaplasia in the human tracheobronchial epitheliumAlternatives to Laboratory Animals20073554935042-s2.0-3634897976218001171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>27AufderheideMDirect exposure methods for testing native atmospheresExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology200557supplement 12132262-s2.0-21244486183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>28AufderheideMAn efficient approach to study the toxicological effects of complex mixturesExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology2008602-31631802-s2.0-4474909381018479892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>29AufderheideMMohrUCULTEX—an alternative technique for cultivation and exposure of cells of the respiratory tract to airborne pollutants at the air/liquid interfaceExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology20005232652702-s2.0-003393866610930128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>30BitterleEKargESchroeppelADose-controlled exposure of A549 epithelial cells at the air-liquid interface to airborne ultrafine carbonaceous particlesChemosphere20066510178417902-s2.0-3375002937516762398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>31FukanoYOguraMEguchiKShibagakiMSuzukiMModified procedure of a direct in vitro exposure system for mammalian cells to whole cigarette smokeExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology20045553173232-s2.0-184242045315088633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>32MülhoptSPaurHRDiabateSKrugHFKimYJIn-vitro testing of inhalable fly ash at the air liquid interfaceEnvironmental Monitoring2008Dordrecht, The NetherlandsSpringer402414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>33Rothen-RutishauserBBlankFMühlfeldCGehrPGehrPMühlfeldCRothen-RutishauserBBlankFNanoparticle-cell membrane interactionsParticle-Lung Interactions2009New York, NY, USAInforma Healtscare226242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>34Rothen-RutishauserBGrassRNBlankFDirect combination of nanoparticle fabrication and exposure to lung cell cultures in a closed setup as a method to simulate accidental nanoparticle exposure of humansEnvironmental Science and Technology2009437263426402-s2.0-6434912428419452928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>35PhillipsJKlussBRichterAMasseyEDExposure of bronchial epithelial cells to whole cigarette smoke: assessment of cellular responsesAlternatives to Laboratory Animals20053332392482-s2.0-2184445117416180978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>36AdamsonJAzzopardiDErringtonGDickensCMcAugheyJAssessment of an in vitro whole cigarette smoke exposure system: the Borgwaldt RM20S 8-syringe smoking machineChemistry Central Journal20115, article 50 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>37TippeAHeinzmannURothCDeposition of fine and ultrafine aerosol particles during exposure at the air/cell interfaceJournal of Aerosol Science20023322072182-s2.0-0036132641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>38KarlssonHLGustafssonJCronholmPMöllerLSize-dependent toxicity of metal oxide particles—a comparison between nano- and micrometer sizeToxicology Letters200918821121182-s2.0-6734914466419446243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>39DonaldsonKTranCLInflammation caused by particles and fibersInhalation Toxicology20021415272-s2.0-003615378912122558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>40OberdörsterGPulmonary effects of inhaled ultrafine particlesInternational Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health2001741182-s2.0-003514047111196075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>41ParkSLeeYKJungMCellular toxicity of various inhalable metal nanoparticles on human alveolar epithelial cellsInhalation Toxicology200719supplement 159652-s2.0-3454883255917886052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>42VeranthJMKaserEGVeranthMMKochMYostGSCytokine responses of human lung cells (BEAS-2B) treated with micron-sized and nanoparticles of metal oxides compared to soil dustsParticle and Fibre Toxicology20074, article 22-s2.0-33947413465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>43WarheitDBWebbTRColvinVLReedKLSayesCMPulmonary bioassay studies with nanoscale and fine-quartz particles in rats: toxicity is not dependent upon particle size but on surface characteristicsToxicological Sciences20079512702802-s2.0-3384561321717030555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>44AhamedMSiddiquiMAAkhtarMJAhmadIPantABAlhadlaqHAGenotoxic potential of copper oxide nanoparticles in human lung epithelial cellsBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications201039625785832-s2.0-7795274298020447378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>45KarlssonHLCronholmPGustafssonJMöllerLCopper oxide nanoparticles are highly toxic: a comparison between metal oxide nanoparticles and carbon nanotubesChemical Research in Toxicology2008219172617322-s2.0-5354908640418710264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>46RitterDKnebelJWAufderheideM In vitro exposure of isolated cells to native gaseous compounds—development and validation of an optimized system for human lung cellsExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology20015353733862-s2.0-003515885011817107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>47KnebelJWRitterDAufderheideMExposure of human lung cells to native diesel motor exhaust—development of an optimized in vitro test strategyToxicology in Vitro20021621851922-s2.0-003618129011869881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>48DiabatéSMülhoptSPaurHRKrugHFThe response of a co-culture lung model to fine and ultrafine particles of incinerator fly ash at the air-liquid interfaceAlternatives to Laboratory Animals20083632852982-s2.0-4944908597618662093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>49PariselliFSaccoMGRembgesDAn optimized method for in vitro exposure of human derived lung cells to volatile chemicalsExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology200961133392-s2.0-5894909175218650076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>50DeschlUVogelJAufderheideMDevelopment of an in vitro exposure model for investigating the biological effects of therapeutic aerosols on human cells from the respiratory tractExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology201163659359820570119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>51SchmalzCWunderlichHGHeinzeRFrimmelFHZwienerCApplication of an optimized system for the well-defined exposure of human lung cells to trichloramine and indoor pool airJournal of Water and Health20119358659621976205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>52WijteDAlblasMJNoortDLangenbergJPvan HeldenHPToxic effects following phosgene exposure of human epithelial lung cells in vitro using a CULTEX systemToxicology in Vitro20112582080208721945045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>53NaraHFukanoYNishinoTAufderheideMDetection of the cytotoxicity of water-insoluble fraction of cigarette smoke by direct exposure to cultured cells at an air-liquid interfaceExperimental and Toxicologic Pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>In press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>54ElihnKCronholmPKarlssonHLMidanderKOdnevall WallinderICellular dose of partly soluble Cu particle aerosols at the air-liquid interface using an in vitro lung cell exposure systemJournal of Aerosol Medicine and Pulmonary Drug Delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>In press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>55GaschenALangDKalbererMCellular responses after exposure of lung cell cultures to secondary organic aerosol particlesEnvironmental Science and Technology2010444142414302-s2.0-7724914162520092303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>56TangTGminskiRKonczolMModestCArmbrusterBInvestigations on cytotoxic and genotoxic effects of laser printer emissions in human epithelial A549 lung cells using an air/liquid exposure systemEnvironmental and Molecular Mutagenesis201253212513522069140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>57FrohlichEBonstinglGHoflerAMeindlCLeitingerGComparison of two in vitro systems to assess cellular effects of nanoparticles-containing aerosolsToxicology in Vitro201227140941722906573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>58AndersonSEJacksonLGFrankoJWellsJREvaluation of dicarbonyls generated in a simulated indoor air environment using an in vitro exposure systemToxicological Sciences201011524534612-s2.0-7795407008420200221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>59GminskiRDeckerKHeinzCGenotoxic effects of three selected black toner powders and their dimethyl sulfoxide extracts in cultured human epithelial A549 lung cells in vitro Environmental and Molecular Mutagenesis20115242963092-s2.0-7995376333620872829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>60VolckensJDaileyLWaltersGDevlinRBDirect particle-to-cell deposition of coarse ambient particulate matter increases the production of inflammatory mediators from cultured human airway epithelial cellsEnvironmental Science and Technology20094312459545992-s2.0-6744913215519603682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Overview image of the modular CULTEX RFS exposure system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The device is composed of the following components: (1) inlet adapter, (2) aerosol guiding module, (3) sampling module and socket module, and (4) locking module with a hand wheel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Aerosol guiding module of the CULTEX RFS: (a) top view, (b) bottom view, and (c) sampling module. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX RFS exposure device extended with an electrical deposition device (Cultex EDD) for the increased particle deposition efficiency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The CULTEX DG (Dust Generator) (Cultex Laboratories GmbH, Germany) enables the generation of aerosols from a powder cake according to Wright [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Experimental setup for exposing cultivated cells at the air-liquid interface to particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The components of the exposure station are the particle generator according to Wright, the elutriator, two CULTEX RFS devices for exposure to particles and clean air and medium pumps for the automatic nutrient supply. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Schematic overview of the CULTEX system for exposing cultivated cells to particles at the air-liquid interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Components of the exposure station: (a) particle generator according to Wright (CULTEX Dust Generator); (b) elutriator: glass tube with vertical upward flow, where large particles are removed from the aerosol due to sedimentation; (c) CULTEX RFS modules for exposure to particles and synthetic air. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>The sampling points (1–3) for the test aerosols in the overall stream are marked. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Sectional view of the elutriator (a) and streamline plot calculated by CFD Analysis (b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Particle track simulation for 2 μm (a) and 10 μm (b) particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>8 L/min inlet flow rate (1) and 1.09 L/min outlet low rate (2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(a) Backtracking of flow lines from deposition chambers and excess outlet to the beginning of the aerosol feeding tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>(b) Flow lines running to the deposition chambers start at specific locations at the beginning of the feeding tube. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.009"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>(a) Unequal deposition of copper(II) oxide microparticles on filter membranes after a 60 min exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>(b) Inlet-adapter with an integrated jet nozzle to avoid unequal particle deposition within the CULTEX RFS module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(c) Uniform deposition of copper(II) oxide on filter membranes after a 60 min exposure with a jet nozzle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.010"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Relative cell viability of A549 cells after exposure to lactose monohydrate particles normalized to the clean air control dependent on time (15, 30, and 60 min). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.011"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig12" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Particle number (black line) and particle mass distribution (red line) of the generated lactose monohydrate aerosol entering the exposure module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The analysis was performed with an Aerodynamic Particle Sizer (TSI Inc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.012"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig13" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Relative cell viability of A549 cells after exposure to copper(II) sulfate particles normalized to the clean air control dependent on time (15, 30, and 60 min). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.013"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig14" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Particle number (black line) and particle mass distribution (red line) of the generated copper(II) sulfate aerosol entering the exposure module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>The analysis was performed with an Aerodynamic Particle Sizer (TSI Inc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.014"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig15" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Relative cell viability of A549 cells after exposure to copper(II) oxide microparticles normalized to the clean air control dependent on time (15, 30, and 60 min). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.015"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig16" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Particle number (black line) and particle mass distribution (red line) of the generated copper(II) oxide microaerosol entering the exposure module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The analysis was performed with an Aerodynamic Particle Sizer (TSI Inc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.016"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig17" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Relative cell viability of A549 cells after exposure to copper(II) oxide nanoparticles normalized to the clean air control dependent on time (15, 30, and 60 min). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.017"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig18" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Particle number (black line) and particle mass distribution (red line) of the generated copper(II) oxide nano aerosol entering the exposure module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The analysis was performed with an Aerodynamic Particle Sizer (TSI Inc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2013-734137.018"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Substances used for the generation of dry powder atmospheres. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Substance </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Producer/catalogue number </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Primary particle size </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Lactose monohydrat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Fluka/61341 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Not available </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) oxide nano </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Ionic Liquids Technologies GmbH/NO-0031-HP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>40–80 nm </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) oxide mikro </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Sigma Aldrich/20844-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>5 μm </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) sulfat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Sigma Aldrich/12852 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Not available </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Conditions for the generation of powder cakes and particulate atmospheres. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Substance </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Powder cake generation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Particle generation </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Pressure (bar) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Scraper (rev/h) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Feed rate (mm/h) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Lactose monohydrat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>110 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>10.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) oxide nano </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>2.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) oxide micro </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>2.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Copper(II) sulfate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>4.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Deposition of copper(II) oxide microparticles on filter membranes after an exposure time of 60 minutes with a jet nozzle in the inlet adapter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>60 minutes exposure of copper(II) oxide </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Chamber 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Chamber 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Chamber 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Weight gain of filter paper (μg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>530 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>529 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>549 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Weight gain of filter paper (μg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>529 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>537 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>521 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Weight gain of filter paper (μg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>548 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>553 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>548 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Exposure systems for exposing cultivated cells at the air-liquid interface. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Exposure system </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Electrostatic precipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Cell type </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Test atmosphere </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Literature </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Cultex CG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>LK004HFBE-21CHO-K1A549BEAS-2B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Cigarette smokeDiesel exhaust Ozone and nitrogene dioxidePhosgeneVolatile organic compoundsPharmaceuticalsTrichloramineFly ashParticles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Aufderheide and Mohr 1999 [12]Ritter et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>2001 [46]Knebel et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>2002 [47]Diabaté et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>2008 [48]Pariselli et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>2009 [49]Deschl et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>2011 [50]Schmalz et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>2011 [51] Wijte et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>2011 [52] Nara et al. [53]Elihn et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>2012 [54] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Cultex RFS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>A54916HBE14o- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Cigarette smoke </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Aufderheide et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>2011 [17] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>ALICE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>A549 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Carbon black nanoparticlesZinc oxide nanoparticlesGold nanoparticles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Lenz et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>2009 [14] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>NACIVT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>BEAS-2BPorcine lung macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Secondary organic aerosolsPolystyrene particles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Gaschen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>2010 [55]Savi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>2008 [16] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Vitrocell </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>A549 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Laser printer emissionsVolatile organic compoundsCarbon nanotubes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Tang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>2012 [56]Frohlich et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>2012 [57]Anderson et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>2010 [58]Gminski et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>2011 [59] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>BAT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>NCI-H292 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Cigarette smoke </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Phillips et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>2005 [35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>EAVES </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>A549 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Polystyrene particlesDiesel exhaustCoarse ambient particles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>de Bruijne et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>2009 [15]Volckens et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>2009 [60] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
