<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSWJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Scientific World Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2356-6140</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-744X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Scientific World Journal</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3322675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22545015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1100/2012/349842</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Early Healing Events around Titanium Implant Devices with Different Surface Microtopography: A Pilot Study in an In Vivo Rabbit Model </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orsini</surname><given-names>Ester</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salgarello</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>Désirée</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bacchelli</surname><given-names>Beatrice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quaranta</surname><given-names>Marilisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pisoni</surname><given-names>Luciano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bellei</surname><given-names>Emma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joechler</surname><given-names>Monika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ottani</surname><given-names>Vittoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Human Anatomical Sciences and Physiopathology of Locomotor Apparatus, Human Anatomy Section, University of Bologna, via Irnerio 48, 40126 Bologna, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Dental School, University of Brescia, Piazza Spedali Civili 1, 25123 Brescia, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Veterinary Medical Sciences, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Bologna, via Tolara di Sopra 50, 40064 Ozzano dell'Emilia, Bologna, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Ester Orsini: <email>ester.orsini@unibo.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Margaret Tzaphlidou </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>349842</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Ester Orsini et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In the present pilot study, the authors morphologically investigated sandblasted, acid-etched surfaces (SLA) at very early experimental times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The tested devices were titanium plate-like implants with flattened wide lateral sides and jagged narrow sides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Because of these implant shape and placement site, the device gained a firm mechanical stability but the largest portion of the implant surface lacked direct contact with host bone and faced a wide peri-implant space rich in marrow tissue, intentionally created in order to study the interfacial interaction between metal surface and biological microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The insertion of titanium devices into the proximal tibia elicited a sequence of healing events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Newly formed bone proceeded through an early distance osteogenesis, common to both surfaces, and a delayed contact osteogenesis which seemed to follow different patterns at the two surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In fact, SLA devices showed a more osteoconductive behavior retaining a less dense blood clot, which might be earlier and more easily replaced, and leading to a surface-conditioning layer which promotes osteogenic cell differentiation and appositional new bone deposition at the titanium surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This model system is expected to provide a starting point for further investigations which clarify the early cellular and biomolecular events occurring at the metal surface. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Osseointegration is regarded as a fundamental criterion for long-term success of endosseous dental implants [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>It is based on the establishment of a primary mechanical stability and subsequent biological fixation [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Numerous factors may influence the rate of osseointegration and among them, the original bone architecture/density and the surface topography are likely to play a major role [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Tooth replacement treatment, especially in the posterior region of the maxilla, generally implies placing implants into a bony bed characterized by a very thin cortical bone shell, an alveolar bone volume reduced in height, and an overall low bone density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The poor bone structural and architectural properties are accountable for a lower primary stability and the consequent higher failure rates claimed by clinical studies [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>To date, many approaches have been tried to improve these clinical results, shortening healing periods and reducing loading time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Implant topography modification treatments have provided surface microroughness in the range of 1–10 μm which has shown to result in greater bone-to-implant contact area, greater biomechanical interlocking of the implant with host bone (i.e., mechanical stability), and enhanced osteoconductive features (i.e., early biological fixation) compared to implants with smooth surfaces [7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Actually, bone healing around dental implants is considered a pathway similar to that occurring after injury, based on the following successive phases: inflammation and necrosis, blood clotting organization and replacement, chemotaxis of pluripotential mesenchymal cells into the peri-implant site and adhesion on implant surface, neoangiogenesis, as well as differentiation of these cells into osteoclasts and osteoblasts which collaborate within temporary anatomic structures, named basic multicellular units (BMUs), by coupling bone resorption and new formation, thus leading to regeneration and remodeling [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>It is well known that surface topography plays a role from the very beginning of these events; in particular, smooth surfaces integrate through appositional bone growth while microrough surfaces may show bone growth directly to the implant surface, according to a “contact osteogenesis” pattern [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>There are clear experimental evidences that these surfaces do provide favorable conditions for attaching and stabilizing the blood clot elements which in turn will constitute a conditioning layer for cell interactions [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The original surface conditioned by surrounded biological microenvironment can thus elicit subsequent events facilitating migrating osteogenetic cells to adhere to the implant surface, to differentiate, and to secrete biomolecules favoring earlier new bone formation [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Although many data have been published to date and despite the frequent clinical use of osseointegrated titanium implants, failures still occur, in many cases at early stages after insertion and apparently not related to surgical technique [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This decreased clinical predictability indicates that the bone healing around a titanium implant is a complex biological process not yet fully understood and underlines the necessity to clarify the initial responses of the surrounding tissue to implant surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge only a few in vivo studies have investigated the initial events taking place in the host tissues and at the interface with such implants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The aim of the current pilot study was therefore to investigate the early healing events that were triggered by microrough surface implants inserted in trabecular bone over the period 0–6 days, combining surface characterization techniques with morphological and histochemical approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The authors also intended to establish a titanium device implantation model in trabecular bone to be used for further in vivo analysis of the biological responses evoked by microroughness of implant surface. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Implant Design and Surface Characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Experimental implants consisted of custom-made, rectangular, titanium plate-like implants with flattened wide lateral sides, and jagged narrow sides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>They were made of commercially pure titanium (grade IV-ISO 5832-2, CpTi) by Or-Vit (Castelmaggiore, Bologna, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>They measured 5 mm in length, 4 mm in width, and 1 mm in thickness (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>This design offered some advantages: (1) two flat surfaces for interaction with the biological microenvironment establishing a geometrically regular compartment once inserted in the animal model; (2) two jagged narrow edges ensuring a firm mechanical stability in the surgically created osteotomy; (3) a quite wide gap between the titanium surfaces and the osteotomy walls preventing the risk of rubbing against the osteotomy wall and damaging the titanium-bone interface when extracting the device; (4) an overall shape allowing to analyze early in vivo bone-implant retention and peri-implant microenvironment attached to the extracted implants overlooking the parameter “implant design” which actually plays a key role in low-density bone [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Two kinds of surface textures were utilized: test and control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Test surfaces (SLA) were sandblasted, and acid-etched titanium plates resulting from a blasting treatment (with powders removing particles from the surface creating pits) followed by a chemical etching (with acids smoothing out some sharp peaks and removing chemical remnants), according to a registered process of Or-Vit, thus formed microroughened surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Such surface exhibited an irregular profile with moderately deep pits alternated with metal peaks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The microroughness was found to be perceived by in vitro cells which resulted positively influenced in growth and metabolic activity [16] and to increase peri-implant osteogenesis in vivo [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Machined surfaces (MSs) obtained by a machining process were used as control (Figures 1(a) and 1(b)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Implants were degreased in trichloroethylene, ultrasonically cleaned of contaminants in absolute ethanol, and supplied in individual gamma-sterilized surgical packs that were opened just before their surgical insertion in bone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Surface characterization was performed according to a standardized protocol previously presented [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the microtopography was qualitatively analyzed by means of scanning electron microscopy (SEM, Philips 515, Philips, Eindhoven, The Netherlands). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Surface characterization in terms of roughness profile was performed under a roughness tester (Surfcom130A, Tokio Seimitsu). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Animal Model and Surgical Procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>All surgical procedures were performed according to European and Italian legislation on animal experimentation and the ethical principles stated in the ‘‘Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12910">http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12910</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The experimental protocol was submitted and approved by the Scientific Technical Committee and Ethical Committee of Alma Mater Studiorum-Bologna University under the Prot.58897-X10 All.22-11/21/2008–Rif BQ/mc/af. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Twelve 8-month-old lop-eared New Zealand White female rabbits of 4.5 ± 0.5 kg in body weight (Farm Greci Agnese Bologna, Italy) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The proximal tibial epiphysis of rabbit was selected as the experimental animal model because of its anatomical heterogeneity which is regarded as a representative model for the jaw bony architecture [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The animals were housed in individual cages for a quarantine period of 7 days under the same environmental conditions (22°C ± 1; 55 RH ± 5%) and constant veterinary care, and they were fed with a standard diet and filtered tap water ad libitum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After a preoxygenation period in an Oxygen cage, general anesthesia was induced with an intramuscular injection of Medetomidine (0.2 mg/kg-Domitor), Ketamine (10 mg/kg-Imalgene 1000), and Butorphanol (0.5 mg/kg-Nargesic) and maintained by a facial mask and an open circuit (T-Ayre modified Jackson Rees), with Isofluorane (1.5–2%) in O2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>During the entire procedure, the rabbits were connected to a multiparametric monitor (Datex-Ohmeda S/5TM) and heated by means of a heated mat (AP 1137/FA, Dyaset S.r.l). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The rabbit proximal tibial region was shaved and disinfected with Betadine prior to surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The medial aspect of each epiphysis was surgically exposed via a skin incision and the muscles were dissected to allow sterile elevation of the periosteum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Tibial epiphysis was drilled at low speed and under a profuse irrigation with cold sterile 0.9% NaCl solution maintained throughout the process to prevent bone necrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In order to gain access to the deep trabecular bone compartment and ensure the device to the thin external cortical layer, two slightly undersized holes, 3.9 mm diameter and 1.2–1.5 cm distance apart, were drilled in each epiphysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Two implant devices, one for each surface type, were press-fit tightened into the surgically prepared holes in an alternating pattern (Figure 2(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>After the implants were seated, surgical sites were closed in layers by suturing muscles, fascia, internal dermal layer, and outer dermis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The implants were radiographically located (Figure 2(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>During the postoperative period, antibiotic (Enrofloxacin Baytril 10 mg/kg SC sid) and analgesic (Carprofen Rymadil 2 mg/kg SC SID) therapies were administered and the rabbits were housed in single boxes under the same environmental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Animals had water and were fed ad libitum while healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The animals were randomly divided into three groups of four animals each, according to the experimental times of 4 hours (representing the steady-state time or day 0), 3 and 6 days after implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>At the end of each experimental time, the animals were resubmitted to surgery under general anesthesia in order to extract some implant devices and then pharmacologically euthanized with an intracardiac injection of Tanax (Embutramide mebenzonium iodide-tetracaine hydrochloride; 0.2 mL/kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The proximal tibial regions were stripped of soft tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Each implant was surgically exposed via sharp dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The proximal tibial regions were excised with an oscillating saw and the block specimens including the implants were isolated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The entire blocks and the isolated titanium plates were processed for histological and ultrastructural evaluations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Histological, Ultrastructural, and Histochemical Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Most retrieved implant surrounded by nondecalcified cylindrical bone segments were immediately fixed by immersion in 10% buffered formalin solution (pH 7.2), dehydrated in an ascending series of ethanol concentrations, cleared in xylene and subsequently embedded in a methacrylate resin (Technovit 9100 New Heraeus Kulzer GmbH, Germany) which was polymerized at −10°C avoiding negative side effects of a heat-polymerizing resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The embedded samples were glued with acrylic resin (EXAKT Technovit 7210 VLC Adhesive, Heraus Kulzer, Wehrheim, Germany) to plexiglas slides and cut longitudinally, parallel to the long axis of the implant, resulting in 150 μm thick sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>These sections were grounded to a final thickness of about 50 μm (MT MICROMET, Saw and Grinding System, Remet, Bologna, Italy) and superficially stained with toluidine blue and acid fuchsin for general morphological analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Examination was performed under a Leitz Orthoplan light microscope (LM, Leica Microsystem Inc., Bannockburn, Ill, USA) equipped with a Leica camera image acquiring system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Some embedded sections were processed for histochemical demonstration of alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and TRAPase (tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase) activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>These methods involved deacrylation of the resin sections in 2-methoxyethylacetate and rehydration up to 0.1 M phosphate buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Briefly, for ALP activity, naphthol-AS-TR-phosphate was used as a substrate and the coupling salt reaction was carried out with Fast blue RR salt (code 30-30121LY, Bio-Optica S.p.A., Milan, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The incubation was carried out for 120 minutes at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>TRAPase activity was detected by the azodye method with slight modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The incubation medium comprised 0.06% fast red violet LB salt, 0.01% naphtol AS-MX phosphate (Sigma chemical Co., St. Luis, Mo), and 50 mM L-(+) sodium tartrate in 0.1 M acetate buffer pH 5.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The incubation was carried out for 60 minutes at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Some unstained methylmethacrylate-embedded sections were also processed for ultrastructural investigations, according to a standardized protocol which set a pretreatment step in order to remove the resin [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the sections were deacrylated using (2-methoxyethyl)-acetate (Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy), renewing the solution every 2 days and periodically checking on the deacrylation process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>They were then rinsed to remove (2-methoxyethyl)-acetate by immersion in 100% ethanol, immersed in hexamethyldisilazane (Sigma-Aldrich, Seelze, Germany), and dried under a hood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Dried sections were mounted on aluminum stubs using a carbon bioadhesive film and coated with gold/palladium for SEM observation using a secondary electron probe at a voltage of 15 kV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Some retrieved isolated titanium plates were processed for SEM investigations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The isolated plates were gently rinsed with PBS containing Ca2+ and Mg2+ to prevent detachment of interface from the surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Cells were fixed with Karnowsky solution (glutaraldehyde 1.5% paraformaldehyde 1% in cacodylate buffer) for 10 minutes then rinsed 3 times with 0.1% cacodylate buffer, postfixed for 20 minutes with 1% Os2O4 in cacodylate buffer, dehydrated with ethanol, and eventually treated with hexamethyldisilazane for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The samples were observed under a scanning electron microscope (Philips 515 Scanning Electron Microscope, Philips, Eindhoven, The Netherlands). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Surface Characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Roughness investigation underlined the differences between the two surfaces in terms of surface profile parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In particular, the MS sample exhibited the lowest values (R a 0.25 μm, R t 2.51 μm) of rugosity compared to the SLA surface (R a 1.11 μm, R t 9.01 μm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The parameter R q, which expressed the irregularities distribution, was slightly higher for the SLA surface compared to MS (1.63 μm versus 0.69 μm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrated that the treatment created pits and peaks the additional etching smoothens out some sharp peaks and the SLA surface exhibited a regular and quite homogeneous concave profile superimposed over the grooves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>SEM analysis confirmed the two substantially different types of topography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The MS surface exhibited a smooth appearance with oriented and parallel grooves in the l–10 um range as a turning manufacturing process feature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>SLA surfaces, on the other hand, showed a rough profile characterized by small irregular cavities homogeneously alternated with metal peaks (Figures 1(a) and 1(b)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Histological, Histochemical, and Ultrastructural Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>All experimental animals survived and recovered quickly after implant placement without any clinical or postoperative complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The healing was uneventful, with the initial postimplantation inflammation subsiding rapidly in 2 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>All implants were in situ when animals were euthanized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>At retrieval, a macroscopic evaluation of the implant site was performed, which confirmed that all the devices had been correctly inserted and no signs of infection were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Each histological ground section comprised the implant device and the surrounding host bone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Only the most proximal portion of the implant was held in position by the thin superficial cortical bone layer (ensuring a firm mechanical stability) while the remaining subcortical portion protruded into the deep trabecular bone network (Figure 2(c)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>3.2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Four Hours (Day 0, Steady State) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Four hours after implant placement (day 0), the ground section observed under light microscope showed a quite wide gap area (1.3 mm ± 0.2 mm SD) between the wall of the surgically created osteotomy and the titanium device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A coagulum of blood cells entrapped in a thin network of fibrin filled this gap reaching the implant surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A notable inflammatory cell infiltration, mainly neutrophilic granulocytes, along with primitive marrow cells and degenerating cellular elements was also observed throughout the interface of the bone and the implant cavity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Several chips of cortical and spongy host bone, shattered by drilling and placing procedures and surrounded by blood elements, could be seen not only adjacent to the implant surface but also quite far from the implant cavity (Figure 3(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Traumatized preexisting bone trabeculae near the implant cavity, as well as host bone chips, showed surface areas characterized by empty osteocytic lacunae, as documented by the lack of the typical deep blue staining of the osteocytic nuclei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The ultrastructural observation of extracted device surfaces under SEM confirmed the histological analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>These surfaces were covered by a network of fibrin entrapping a large number of cells identified through their morphology: biconcave erythrocytes, platelets, neutrophils, and macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This blood clot showed a different affinity for the two surfaces, being more thick and adherent on machined surfaces compared to SLA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Actually, on MS, a mesh of fibrin-like fiber bundles arranged on the superficial grooves and entrapping numerous cells could be seen (Figures 3(b) and 3(c)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>3.2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Three Days </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>After a three-day healing period, the general histological appearance was similar to the steady-state samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The original hole that was drilled to place the implant could still be recognized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The elements of the primitive blood clot were still present as well, especially in regions close to the device, but they were undergoing a wound-cleansing process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In particular, the inflammatory cell infiltration showed a tendency to disappear in the tissue around the implant, many multinucleated giant cells occurred, and portions of the coagulum were replaced with a healing tissue containing undifferentiated fibroblast-like mesenchymal cells and new vascular structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Observation of ground sections allowed the appreciation of a loose connective stroma, poorly vascolarized and organized, with elongated fibroblast-like cells at the MS interface (Figure 4(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, at SLA device, interface cells formed a more consistent layer along the surface of the implant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>These cells showed a polygonal shape and numerous blood vessels appeared near the implant and surrounded by cells (Figure 4(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Trabeculae showing areas with empty osteocytic lacunae were still visible after three days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>On the surface of these bony structures, signs of bone resorption were observed, as indicated by the presence of scalloped resorption areas located at the site facing the bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Histochemical TRAPase staining showed intense reactivity for these cells (Figure 4(c)) and SEM observation confirmed the histological data (Figure 4(d)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Initial osteoid deposition was detected next to these resorption regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The bony surface was lined by cuboidal osteoblast-like cells that were characterized by a pronounced deposition activity (extracellular matrix), as histologically shown by intense stainability (Figure 4(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Histochemical analysis of the enzyme activities supported the morphological data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A positivity for ALP (resulting in a dark stained osteoid rim) was detected at some bone areas facing the marrow cavity and at the incremental line in close connection to the old bone (Figure 4(e)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>3.2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Six Days </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Light microscopy of six day ground sections showed that the number of inflammatory and red blood cells reduced almost completely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The implant cavity along with the marrow spaces were filled by a loose connective matrix with sprouting blood vessels and fat cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>A large number of mesenchymal-like cellular elements with large rounded nuclei appeared to increase in density at the bone-implant interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In particular, flattened and elongated fibroblast-like cells were present on the perimeter of MS implant surfaces along with some blood vessels forming a continuous layer (Figure 5(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>By comparison, on SLA surfaces facing the marrow cavity, cuboidal osteoblast-like cells were arranged in parallel to the surface forming a layer next to a darkly stained thin line; these cells appeared more numerous than those on MS (Figure 5(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>They also appeared to be metabolically active in producing a high pink osteoid rim juxtaposed to the implant, as histologically demonstrated by Toluidine blue-acid fuchsin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The same ground sections were therefore deacrylated and the metal surface at the interface was investigated under SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Ultrastructural observations confirmed the features of the cells present on the surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In particular, on SLA surfaces, cells showed a cuboidal/polygonal shape and were widely spreaded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>They presented cytoplasmatic prolongations by which they came in contact with other cells and with the surface roughness peaks (Figure 5(c)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Some ultrastructural evidences of osteoclast-like cells, such as a ruffled border, could be detected on cells adjacent to the cuboidal ones (Figure 5(d)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Bone healing around a titanium dental implant is a complex biological process not yet fully understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>There is a growing interest especially in investigating the very early events taking place at the interface during the healing process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In particular, research focuses on the posterior region of the maxilla which is characterized by a very thin cortical bone shell, an alveolar bone volume reduced in height, and an overall low bone density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the clinical observation that tooth replacement treatments experience the lowest predictability and long-term success in trabecular bone tissue [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The proximal tibial epiphysis of rabbit was therefore selected as the experimental animal model because of its anatomical heterogeneity regarded as a representative model for the jaw bony architecture [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The aim of the current pilot study was to investigate the early healing events that were triggered by SLA implants inserted in rabbit tibial epiphysis over the period 0–6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>MS implants were used as control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Histological and ultrastructural investigations showed a different healing pattern for microrough and machined surfaces since the device insertion step. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>A few hours after implant placement, a coagulum of blood cells entrapped in a thin network of fibrin was detected at both implant surface types along with primitive marrow cells and inflammatory cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Many authors have suggested that this immediate interaction with biological microenvironment is governed by surface topography [12, 20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the blood clot appeared to be less dense on SLA and more abundant on MS surfaces where bundles of fibrin-like fibers were arranged in a tight network firmly adherent to the superficial grooves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The peri-implant gap area also contained several chips of host bone, as consequences of surgical drilling and placing procedures, surrounded by blood and marrow elements. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The following events at the bone-implant interface appeared according to a chronological sequence [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>At day 3, the sequence of morphological events which foreshadow newly peri-implant osteoid deposition occurred earlier at SLA surfaces compared to MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In particular, at the SLA interface, the presence of a more dense and mature connective stroma, more richly vascolarized and organized, was morphologically evident as long as signs of bone resorption by TRAP-positive osteoclasts present on the trabeculae surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Consequently, some ALP-positive osteoblasts starting the deposition of a new osteoid seam were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The new bone formation occurred very early in the first days of wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It started as resorption phenomena around preexisting bone at a distance from the implant, and it proceeded directed toward the implant surface, according to a model known as “distance osteogenesis” [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The present authors suggest that the conditioning superficial layer, which appeared less dense on SLA and therefore more easily replaced, could be accountable for this secondary surface cell recruitment pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This observation is consistent with data from other researchers [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>By day 6, the morphological differences between the two surfaces were clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>On SLA surface, it was possible to appreciate a cuboidal osteoblast seam depositing intense-stained osteoid matrix characterized by the presence of large osteocyte lacunae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In contrast, on the MS surface, only a few cuboidal cells could be detected and most of the cells appeared flat and elongated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These findings were consistent with literature which showed how attachment was higher and differentiation faster on microroughness surface in the scale dimension of cell adhesion structures [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The new bone formation phenomena, already remarkable at day 3 as distance osteogenesis, was visualized directly in tight contact with some SLA implant areas and raising the possibility of contact osteogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>It has been hypothesized that this contact osteogenesis at the implant surface is dependent on a surface-conditioning layer which in turn leads to a specific cell differentiation pattern [18, 27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>From day 6, samples osteoclast-like cells (exhibiting the typical “ruffled border”) were detected at the SLA implant surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>According to other authors [28, 29], osteclast-like cells might be present not only where bone remodeling starts, but in general where osteogenesis occurs as well as, since bone formation process results from osteoblast-osteoclast coupling activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We speculate that osteoclastic differentiation might be driven by surface topography, according to the geometric tropism of metal peaks and valleys which offer cell anchorage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the preliminary morphological data hereby described were achieved by means of an experimental in vivo model system consisting of a titanium plate-like device with different surfaces (microrough versus machined), inserted in rabbit proximal tibial epiphysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Because of these device shape and placement site, the most portion of the implant surface lacked direct contact with host bone but faced a wide peri-implant space rich in marrow tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This wide peri-implant space was intentionally created in order to dismiss a direct contact between host bone and metal implant and to better understand the role of the biological microenvironment at the interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the authors did not consider peri-implant gap area parameter which is known to play an important role in osseointegration process if not too wide [27, 30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The study confirmed that the insertion of titanium devices into the proximal tibia elicited a sequence of healing events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Newly formed bone proceeded through an early distance osteogenesis, common to both surfaces, and a delayed contact osteogenesis which seemed to follow different patterns at the two surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In fact, SLA devices showed a more osteoconductive behavior retaining a less dense blood clot, which might be earlier and easier replaced, and leading to a surface-conditioning layer promoting osteogenic cell differentiation and appositional new bone deposition at the titanium surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This model system is expected to provide a sequence of morphological events useful to clarify the early cellular and biomolecular events occurring at the metal surface. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by a grant of the Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Università e della Ricerca (PRIN, Progetti di rilevante interesse nazionale, ex quota 40%, 2007). The authors thank Or-Vit, Castelmaggiore, Bologna, Italy, for providing the implant devices and Mr. Cristian Mancini for the technical support. The authors Acknowledge to Professor Alessandro Ruggeri for his precious contribution to the revision of this manuscript.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1BrånemarkPIAdellRBreineUHanssonBOLindströmJOhlssonAIntra-osseous anchorage of dental prostheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Experimental studiesScandinavian Journal of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery196932811004924041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>2FranchiMOrsiniETrireAOsteogenesis and morphology of the peri-implant bone facing dental implantsThe Scientific World Journal200441083109515632988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>3FranchiMFiniMMartiniDBiological fixation of endosseous implantsMicron2005367-866567116233979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>4SennerbyLRoosJSurgical determinants of clinical success of osseointegrated oral implants: a review of the literatureInternational Journal of Prosthodontics19981154084209922733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>5SulYTKangBSJohanssonCUmHSParkCJAlbrektssonTThe roles of surface chemistry and topography in the strength and rate of osseointegration of titanium implants in boneJournal of Biomedical Materials Research200989494295018470920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>6Roos-JansåkerAMLindahlCRenvertHRenvertSNine- to fourteen-year follow-up of implant treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Part I: implant loss and associations to various factorsJournal of Clinical Periodontology200633428328916553637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>7Le GuéhennecLSoueidanALayrollePAmouriqYSurface treatments of titanium dental implants for rapid osseointegrationDental Materials200723784485416904738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>8HermidaJCBergulaADimaanoFHawkinsMColwellCWD’LimaDDAn in vivo evaluation of bone response to three implant surfaces using a rabbit intramedullary rod modelJournal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research201051, article 57 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>9MatsuoKIrieNOsteoclast-osteoblast communicationArchives of Biochemistry and Biophysics2008473220120918406338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>10DaviesJEUnderstanding peri-implant endosseous healingJournal of Dental Education200367893294912959168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>11MasakiCSchneiderGBZahariasRSeaboldDStanfordCEffects of implant surface microtopography on osteoblast gene expressionClinical Oral Implants Research200516665065616307571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>12LinderbäckPHarmankayaNAskendalAArevaSLausmaaJTengvallPThe effect of heat- or ultra violet ozone-treatment of titanium on complement deposition from human blood plasmaBiomaterials201031184795480120363497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>13WennerbergAAlbrektssonTEffects of titanium surface topography on bone integration: a systematic reviewClinical Oral Implants Research200920417218419663964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>14EspositoMHirschJMLekholmUThomsenPBiological factors contributing to failures of osseointegrated oral implants: (II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>EtiopathogenesisEuropean Journal of Oral Sciences199810637217649672097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>15OrsiniEGiavaresiGTrire’AOttaniVSalgarelloSDental implant thread pitch and its influence on osseointegration process: an in vivo comparison studyInternational Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Implants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>16GuizzardiSGalliCMartiniDDifferent titanium surface treatment influences human mandibular osteoblast responseJournal of Periodontology200475227328215068116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>17FranchiMBacchelliBGiavaresiGInfluence of different implant surfaces on peri-implant osteogenesis: histomorphometric analysis in sheepJournal of Periodontology200778587988817470022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>18SlaetsECarmelietGNaertIDuyckJEarly trabecular bone healing around titanium implants: a histologic study in rabbitsJournal of Periodontology200778351051717335375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>19TrirèAMartiniDOrsiniECorrelative microscopy of bone in implant osteointegration studiesThe Scientific World Journal2010102238224721103792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>20ParkJYGemmellCHDaviesJEPlatelet interactions with titanium: modulation of platelet activity by surface topographyBiomaterials200122192671268211519787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>21HongJAzensAEkdahlKNGranqvistCGNilssonBMaterial-specific thrombin generation following contact between metal surfaces and whole bloodBiomaterials200526121397140315482827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>22AbrahamssonIBerglundhTLinderELangNPLindheJEarly bone formation adjacent to rough and turned endosseous implant surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>An experimental study in the dogClinical Oral Implants Research200415438139215248872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>23OmarOSvenssonSZoricN In vivo gene expression in response to anodically oxidized versus machined titanium implantsJournal of Biomedical Materials Research20109241552156619431206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>24ThorARasmussonLWennerbergAThe role of whole blood in thrombin generation in contact with various titanium surfacesBiomaterials200728696697417095084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>25KellerJCSchneiderGBStanfordCMKelloggBEffects of implant microtopography on osteoblast cell attachmentImplant Dentistry200312217518112861887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>26GiordanoCSandriniEBusiniVA new chemical etching process to improve endosseous implant osseointegration: in vitro evaluation on human osteoblast-like cellsInternational Journal of Artificial Organs200629877278016969755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>27BerglundhTAbrahamssonILangNPLindheJDe novo alveolar bone formation adjacent to endosseous implants: a model study in the dogClinical Oral Implants Research200314325126212755774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>28LinderLCarlssonAMarsalLBjurstenLMBranemarkPIClinical aspects of osseointegration in joint replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A histological study of titanium implantsJournal of Bone and Joint Surgery19887045505553403596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>29SennerbyLThomsenPEricsonLEEarly tissue response to titanium implants inserted in rabbit cortical bone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Part I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Light microscopic observationsJournal of Materials Science199343240250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>30FutamiTFujiiNOhnishiHTissue response to titanium implants in the rat maxilla: ultra structural and histochemical observations of the bone-titanium interfaceJournal of Periodontology200071228729810711620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>31FranchiMBacchelliBMartiniDEarly detachment of titanium particles from various different surfaces of endosseous dental implantsBiomaterials200425122239224614741589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Technical drawing of the tested implant devices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Bottom. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>SEM images of MS (a) and SLA (b) surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Bar = 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2012-349842.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Clinical view of the device placement in rabbit proximal tibial epiphysis (a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>X-ray micrograph of the surgical site (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Histological ground section of an implant device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The implant is medially and laterally surrounded by cortical and trabecular host bone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>LM, toluidine blue, and acid fuchsin staining, 1x. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2012-349842.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Day 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Histology of longitudinal ground section (a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Empty osteocytic lacunae (*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>LM, toluidine blue, and acid fuchsin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Bar = 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>SEM images of MS (b) and SLA (c) surfaces extracted at 4 hours after insertion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Bar = 10 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2012-349842.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Day 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Histology of longitudinal ground sections of MS (a) and SLA (b) surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>LM, toluidine blue, and acid fuchsin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Bar = 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>TRAP staining of osteoclast at the trabecular bone surface (c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Bar = 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>SEM images of resorption lacunae at the trabecular bone surface (d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>ALP staining of osteoid rim at the trabecular bone surface (e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>ALP positivity for bone areas facing the marrow cavity (*); ALP positivity for the incremental line in close connection to the old bone (arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Bar = 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2012-349842.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Day 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Histology of longitudinal ground sections of MS (a) and SLA (b) surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Empty osteocytic lacunae (arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>LM, toluidine blue, and acid fuchsin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Bar = 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscopy of deacrylated ground sections of SLA implants: spreaded polygonal osteoblast-like cells (c) and osteoclast-like cell presenting a ruffled border (d) adherent to the metal surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Since the samples were initially processed for light microscopy (buffered formalin fixative) and afterwards deacrylated for SEM observation, the shrinked appearance of blood cells might be considered as an artifact due to the formalin fixation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2012-349842.005"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
