<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3478264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23110135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-23500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Decision Making</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Behavioral Neuroscience</subject><subject>Neurotransmitters</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Drugs and Devices</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral Pharmacology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nutrition</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Dopaminergic Modulation of Effort-Related Choice Behavior as Assessed by a Progressive Ratio Chow Feeding Choice Task: Pharmacological Studies and the Role of Individual Differences </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Dopamine Effort Progressive Ratio DARPP-32</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>Patrick A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>Eric J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>López Cruz</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vemuri</surname><given-names>V. Kiran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Makriyannis</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baqi</surname><given-names>Younis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>Christa E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>Mercè</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salamone</surname><given-names>John D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychology, University of Connecticut, Storrs, Connecticut, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Àrea de Psicobiologia, Campus de Riu Sec, Universitat Jaume I, Castelló, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Center for Drug Discovery, Northeastern University, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Pharma-Zentrum Bonn, Pharmazeutisches Institut, Pharmazeutische Chemie, Universität Bonn, Bonn, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Beeler</surname><given-names>Jeff A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Chicago, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>john.salamone@uconn.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Salamone's work was funded by the NIH(NIMH) and NIH(NIDA), and he has received compensation from Merck- Seronno, Pfizer and Roche. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Makriyannis was supported by NIH(NIDA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Müller received funding by UCB Pharma within the Biopharma collaborative project Neuroallianz funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Correa received funding by Fundació Bancaixa-UJI (P1.1B2010-43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Pardo was supported by Fundació Bancaixa-UJI (PREDOC-2007-43), and L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>López-Cruz was supported by Ministerio Educación, FPU (AP2010-3793). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>None of the other authors had financial interests to disclose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: PAR MP EN MC JDS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: PAR EJN MP LLC MC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: PAR MP LLC EJN MC JDS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: VKV AM YB CEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: PAR MP MC JDS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e47934</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Randall et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Randall et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Mesolimbic dopamine (DA) is involved in behavioral activation and effort-related processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Rats with impaired DA transmission reallocate their instrumental behavior away from food-reinforced tasks with high response requirements, and instead select less effortful food-seeking behaviors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the effects of several drug treatments were assessed using a progressive ratio (PROG)/chow feeding concurrent choice task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>With this task, rats can lever press on a PROG schedule reinforced by a preferred high-carbohydrate food pellet, or alternatively approach and consume the less-preferred but concurrently available laboratory chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Rats pass through each ratio level 15 times, after which the ratio requirement is incremented by one additional response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The DA D2 antagonist haloperidol (0.025–0.1 mg/kg) reduced number of lever presses and highest ratio achieved but did not reduce chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 increased lever presses and highest ratio achieved, but decreased chow consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The cannabinoid CB1 inverse agonist and putative appetite suppressant AM251 decreased lever presses, highest ratio achieved, and chow intake; this effect was similar to that produced by pre-feeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, DA-related signal transduction activity (pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression) was greater in nucleus accumbens core of high responders (rats with high lever pressing output) compared to low responders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Thus, the effects of DA antagonism differed greatly from those produced by pre-feeding or reduced CB1 transmission, and it appears unlikely that haloperidol reduces PROG responding because of a general reduction in primary food motivation or the unconditioned reinforcing properties of food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, accumbens core signal transduction activity is related to individual differences in work output. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants to J. Salamone from the National Institute of Mental Health (MH078023) and the National Institute of Drug Abuse (U01DA016194), and M. Correa has received funding from Fundació Bancaixa-UJI (P1.1B2010-43). M. Pardo was supported by Fundació Bancaixa-UJI (PREDOC-2007-43), and L. López-Cruz was supported by Ministerio Educación, FPU (AP2010-3793). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Brain dopamine (DA), particularly in nucleus accumbens, plays an important role in regulating aspects of instrumental behavior [1]–[4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Accumbens DA is involved in approach behavior, activational aspects of motivation (e.g. vigor, persistence), and enabling organisms to overcome work-related response costs to gain access to significant stimuli [1]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The increased activity induced by scheduled presentation of food pellets is accompanied by increases in accumbens DA release, and is reduced by DA antagonism and accumbens DA depletions [5], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Rats with accumbens DA depletions are very sensitive to ratio requirements in operant schedules [15]–[17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Moreover, DA antagonism or interference with accumbens DA transmission alters response allocation in tasks that measure effort-related choice behavior [1], [2], [6], [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Several behavioral tasks have been used to investigate the role of DA in effort-related choice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Some studies have used a T-maze barrier choice task, and reported that interference with DA transmission decreased barrier climbing to gain access to a high magnitude of reinforcement [12], [18]–[22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>T-maze and lever pressing versions of effort discounting procedures also have demonstrated that DA antagonism shifts choice behavior of rats towards low effort alternatives [23], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Another task that has been used is the concurrent fixed-ratio 5 (FR5)/chow feeding procedure, in which rats can either lever press on a FR5 schedule for preferred high-carbohydrate food pellets, or approach and consume less-preferred rodent chow that is freely available in the chamber [1], [6], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Under baseline conditions, rats tested with this procedure typically obtain most of their food by lever pressing while consuming very little of the chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Systemic or intra-accumbens administration of DA antagonists and accumbens DA depletions shift response allocation such that lever pressing is decreased but chow intake is substantially increased [6], [25]–[31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This effect is not due to drug-induced changes in food preference or consumption [6], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the effects induced by DA antagonism or depletion differ substantially from those seen following pre-feeding [6] or treatment with appetite suppressant drugs such as fenfluramine [25] or cannabinoid CB1 antagonism [30]; these appetite-related manipulations failed to increase chow intake at doses that suppress lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In addition to accumbens DA, there is a body of research implicating adenosine in behavioral activation and effort-related processes [32]-[34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Adenosine A2A receptors are primarily localized in striatal areas, including both neostriatum and accumbens [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, there is a functional interaction between DA D2 and adenosine A2A receptors [37]–[39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Intra-accumbens injections of the adenosine A2A agonist CGS 21680 decreased lever pressing on a ratio schedule [34], and also produced changes in effort-related choice behavior similar to the effects of DA antagonism [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In contrast, adenosine A2A antagonists have been shown to increase fixed interval response rate [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, several studies have shown that adenosine A2A antagonists can reverse the effects of DA D2 antagonists on tests of effort-related choice behavior [21], [22], [31], [32], [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The present studies employed a variant of the lever pressing/chow intake choice procedure, which utilized a progressive ratio (PROG) work requirement (see also refs. [13], [43]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Similar to the FR5/chow feeding choice task, rats tested with this PROG/chow feeding procedure have the choice of pressing the lever reinforced by presentation of the more preferred pellets vs. approaching and consuming the less preferred chow; the difference is that a PROG schedule, which gradually increases the ratio requirement, is used instead of an FR5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This variant of the choice procedure was used because the PROG schedule requires that the animal repeatedly make within-session choices between lever pressing and chow intake under conditions in which the ratio requirement was gradually incrementing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Moreover, preliminary data indicated that the PROG/chow feeding choice procedure generates much more variability in behavior between animals than the FR5 choice procedure, which could be particularly useful for studying neurochemical correlates of individual differences in behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To assess the effects of DA antagonism and compare these actions with other conditions, experiments were conducted to determine the effects of the DA D2 antagonist haloperidol, the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3, the cannabinoid CB1 antagonist/inverse agonist and putative appetite suppressant AM251, and the reinforcer devaluation provided by pre-feeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, to investigate signal transduction activity that is potentially related to task performance, expression of DARPP-32 that is phosphorylated at the threonine 34 residue (pDARPP-32-(Thr34) [44] was measured immunohistochemically in 4 specific regions of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>pDARPP-32(Thr34) immunoreactivity was used to provide a marker of DA-related signal transduction activity, because evidence indicates that DA acting through the D1 receptor and the G proteins Gs/Golf activates adenylate cyclase activity, thereby stimulating PKA-mediated phosphorylation of DARPP-32 at the Thr34 site [45], [46], [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>This experiment was conducted to determine if levels of pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression were higher in animals with high lever pressing output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Nucleus accumbens is implicated in effort-related processes, so both the core and shell divisions were analyzed for pDARPP-32(Thr34) activity following a PROG/Choice behavioral session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Because Schweimer and Hauber [43] demonstrated the importance of DA signaling in the anterior cingulate cortex in effort-related decision making, CG1 and CG2 divisions of the cingulate cortex also were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>It was hypothesized that haloperidol would affect PROG responding in a manner that was not dependent upon decreases in primary food motivation or appetite, and thus would decrease PROG lever pressing but leave chow intake intact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it was hypothesized that MSX-3 would produce behavioral effects that would be opposite to those produced by haloperidol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Due to the putative appetite suppressant effects of interfering with cannabinoid CB1 receptor transmission [1], [30], [49], [50], it was expected that AM251, as well as pre-feeding, would decrease both lever pressing and chow consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Finally, it was hypothesized that accumbens DARPP-32 immunoreactivity would be greater in animals with high baseline levels of lever pressing (i.e., “high responders”) than in rats with low levels of lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>48 adult male Sprague-Dawley rats (Harlan, Indianapolis, IN, USA) were housed in a colony at 23°C with 12-h light/dark cycles (lights on at 0∶700 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Rats weighed 300–350 g at the beginning of the study, and were initially food deprived to 85% of their free-feeding body weight for training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Rats were fed supplemental chow to maintain weight throughout the study, with water available ad libitum in the home cages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Despite food restriction, rats were allowed modest weight gain throughout the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>All animal protocols were approved by the University of Connecticut Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee, and followed NIH guidelines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Pharmacological Agents and Dose Selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Haloperidol was obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO) and was dissolved in 0.2% tartaric acid solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>MSX-3 ((E)-phosphoric acid mono-[3-[8-[2-(3-methoxyphenyl)vinyl]-7-methyl-2,6-dioxo-1-prop-2-ynyl-1,2,6,7-tetrahydropurin-3-yl] propyl] ester disodium salt) was synthesized in the laboratory of Christa Müller (University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>MSX-3 was dissolved in 0.9% saline and pH adjusted with 1.0 M NaOH to a final pH of 7.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>AM251 was synthesized in the laboratory of Alex Makriyannis (Center for Drug Discovery, Northeastern University, Boston, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>AM251 was dissolved in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO), Tween 80, and 0.9% saline at a ratio of 1∶1∶8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Doses were selected based on previous work [30], [40], [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Behavioral Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Preliminary studies were conducted to determine the optimal rate at which the schedule progressed (i.e., number of reinforcements per ratio level and by how much the ratio requirement increased with each level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>It was found that by having to complete 15 ratios at each ratio level, rats generally lever pressed at higher levels before switching to chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Behavioral sessions were conducted in operant conditioning chambers (28×23×23 cm3; Med Associates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Rats were initially trained to lever press on a continuous reinforcement schedule (30-min sessions; 45-mg high carbohydrate pellets, Bio-serv, Frenchtown, NJ, USA) for 1 week, and then were shifted to the PROG schedule (30-min sessions, 5 days/week) for several additional weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For PROG sessions, the ratio started at FR1 and was increased by one additional response every time 15 reinforcements were obtained (FR1×15, FR2×15, FR3×15,…). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Additionally, this schedule included a “time-out” feature that deactivated the response lever if 2 minutes elapsed without a ratio being completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Upon reaching stable baseline responding, chow was then introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Weighed amounts of laboratory chow (Laboratory Diet, 5P00 Prolab RMH 3000, Purina Mills, St. Louis, MO, USA; typically 15–20 g) were concurrently available on the floor of the chamber during the PROG sessions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>At the end of the session, rats were removed from the chamber, and food intake was determined by weighing the remaining food (including spillage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Rats were trained until they attained stable levels of baseline lever pressing and chow intake, after which drug testing began. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>For most baseline days rats did not receive supplemental feeding, however, over weekends and after drug tests, rats received supplemental chow in the home cage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>On baseline and drug treatment days, rats normally consumed all the operant pellets that were delivered during each session. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Experimental Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>For experiments 1–3a and 4, the same group of animals was used (n = 32), while a different group of animals was used for experiment 3b (n = 16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>For all experiments using drug manipulations (1, 2, 3b), all animals were given a single vehicle injection 1 week prior to the beginning of testing to habituate them to being injected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Experiments 1, 2, and 3b used a within-group design in which each rat received all drug or vehicle treatments (IP) in their particular experiment in a randomly varied order (one treatment per week). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Baseline training sessions (i.e., non-drug) were conducted 4 days per week. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2d1"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Experiment 1: Effects of the dopamine D2 antagonist haloperidol on PROG/chow feeding choice performance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>To assess the effects of haloperidol, rats were trained on the PROG/chow procedure described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>On test days, animals received injections of 0.025, 0.05, 0.1 mg/kg haloperidol or vehicle, 50 minutes prior to behavioral testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d2"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Experiment 2: Effects of the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 on PROG/chow feeding choice performance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>To assess the effects of the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3, the same group of animals was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The animals were first given 1 week off from any drug testing, but continued normal baseline training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>On test days, animals received injections of 0.5, 1.0, 2.0 mg/kg MSX-3 or vehicle, 20 minutes prior to behavioral testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d3"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Experiment 3a/b: Effects of appetite manipulations on PROG/chow performance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>3a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Effects of pre-feeding to reduce food motivation. To assess the effects of pre-feeding, the same group of animals was again given 1 week of additional baseline training after experiment 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The night before testing, animals were taken off of food restriction and given ad libitum access to lab chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>On the test day, several hours before behavioral testing, animals were given ad libitum access to Bio-serv pellets in the home cage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Performance on the test day was then compared to performance on the previous baseline day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>3b: Effects of the cannabinoid CB1 inverse agonist and putative appetite suppressant AM251. For assessment of the effect of AM251, a new group of animals (n = 16) were trained on the PROG/chow feeding choice procedure described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>On test days, animals received injections of 2.0, 4.0, 8.0 mg/kg AM251 or vehicle, 30 minutes prior to testing, once per week, in a randomly varied order. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d4"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Experiment 4: Effects of PROG/chow responding on pDARPP32-THR34 expression: high vs. low responders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Following the conclusion of experiment 3, animals (n = 32) were given 1 week to re-stabilize their baselines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>During the following week, 90 minutes after a baseline training session, animals were sacrificed and perfused to obtain tissue for pDARPP32-(Thr34) immunohistochemical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>For statistical analysis, these animals were divided into two groups (high performers and low performers, determined by a median split of lever pressing on the day of perfusion). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>pDARPP32(Thr34) visualization and quantification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Free floating coronal sections (50 µm) were serially cut using a cryostat (Weymouth, MA, USA) and rinsed in 0.01 M PBS (pH 7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>pDARPP32-(Thr34) immunohistochemistry was conducted according to the methods described previously by Segovia et al. (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The primary anti-pDARPP32-(Thr34) antibody was used at a concentration of 1∶1000 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, USA) for 48 h incubation, and the secondary antibody was anti-rabbit HRP conjugate, envision plus (DAKO, Carpinteria, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The immunohistochemical reaction was developed using diaminobenzidine (DAB) as the chromagen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The mounted and cover-slipped sections were examined and photographed using a Nikon Eclipse E600 (Melville, NY, USA) microscope equipped with an Insight Spot digital camera (Diagnostic Instruments, Inc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Images of the regions of interest were magnified at 20× and captured digitally using SPOT software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Cells that were positively labeled for pDARPP32-(Thr 34) were quantified with ImageJ software (v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>1.42, National Institutes of Health sponsored image analysis program) and a macro written to automate particle counting within regions of interest (1000×1000 µm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For each animal, cell counts were obtained bilaterally from at least three sections, and counts were averaged across sides and sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>All cell counting was done by someone who was blind to the experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>For the behavioral pharmacology experiments, number of lever presses, maximum ratio achieved, active lever time (in seconds) and chow intake (grams) were analyzed using repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Non-orthogonal planned comparisons using the ANOVA error term [51] were used to compare each treatment with the vehicle control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In addition, to provide another statistical measure of the reciprocal relationship between lever pressing and chow intake in each experiment, correlations were performed between number of lever presses and chow intake data collapsed across all conditions within the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>This measure has been used in previous studies [25], [27], and is potentially influenced by both between subject and treatment-related variability in lever pressing and chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Thus, in order to control for the effect of between-subject variability on this measure, partial correlations that controlled for the vehicle level of lever pressing also were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>For experiment 4, pDARPP32-(Thr34) cell counts were analyzed for differences in expression between high and low responders (after a median split of the lever pressing data) for each of 4 regions of interest, and t-tests were performed to determine significant differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Experiment 1: Effects of the DA D2 antagonist haloperidol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Haloperidol significantly decreased the number of lever presses (F(3,93) = 4.598, p&lt;0.01, see figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Planned comparisons revealed that there was a significant difference between 0.1 mg/kg haloperidol and vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Haloperidol also significantly decreased maximum ratio achieved (F(3,93) = 8.661, p&lt;0.01, figure 1B), and the amount of time the lever remained active (F(3,93) = 6.723, p&lt;0.01, figure 1C); for both measures, planned comparisons showed a significant difference between vehicle and 0.1 mg/kg haloperidol (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Haloperidol produced no significant effects on chow consumption in the dose range tested (figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>However, there was a tendency for animals that had high vehicle rates of responding, and correspondingly low vehicle levels of chow intake, to show increases in chow intake with haloperidol; this was marked by a significant correlation between vehicle number of lever presses and the difference in chow consumption between vehicle and the highest dose of haloperidol (r = 0.69, df = 30, p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Collapsed across all conditions, there was a significant negative correlation between number of lever presses and chow consumption (r = −0.765, df = 126, p&lt;0.001), which demonstrated the overall inverse relationship between lever pressing and chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the partial correlation between lever pressing and chow intake that controlled for between-subject variability also was statistically significant (−0.557, df = 125, p&lt;0.001), indicating that the inverse relation between lever pressing and chow intake was evident across treatments even if one controlled for the between-subject variability in lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Effects of the dopamine D2 antagonist haloperidol on PROG/chow performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>On measures of lever pressing, mean (±SEM) total lever presses (A), maximum ratio achieved (B), and active lever time (measured in seconds, C), haloperidol significantly decreased at the highest dose of 0.1 mg/kg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Chow consumption (mean±SEM, in grams) during test sessions was unaffected by any dose tested (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>(* p&lt;0.05, different from vehicle) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Experiment 2: Effects of the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>MSX-3 significantly increased number of lever presses (F(3,93) = 4.120, p&lt;0.01, figure 2A), and planned comparisons showed that both 1.0 and 2.0 mg/kg doses of MSX-3 increased number of lever presses compared to vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>There also was a significant increase in maximum ratio achieved (F(3,93) = 8.206, p&lt;0.01, see figure 2B), with the 1.0 and 2.0 mg/kg doses of MSX-3 differing significantly from vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, MSX-3 increased active lever time (F(3,93) = 3.784, p&lt;0.05, figure 2C), with the 2.0 mg/kg does of MSX-3 being significantly affected (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>MSX-3 decreased chow intake (F(3,93) = 8.017, p&lt;0.01; figure 2D), with a significant effect at 2.0 mg/kg MSX-3 compared to vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>As with experiment 1, there was a significant negative correlation between lever presses and chow intake when the data were collapsed across all conditions (r = −0.781, df = 126, p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In addition, the partial correlation between lever pressing and chow intake that controlled for between-subject variability also was statistically significant (−0.597, df = 125, p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Thus, as with the haloperidol experiment, the inverse relation between lever pressing and chow intake was evident across drug treatments even if one controlled for the between-subject variability in lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Effects of the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 on PROG/chow performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>On measures of lever pressing, mean (±SEM) total lever presses (A) and maximum ratio achieved (B) were both significantly increased at doses of 1.0 and 2.0 mg/kg while active lever time (measured in seconds, C) was only increased at a dose of 2.0 mg/kg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Chow consumption (mean±SEM, in grams) during test sessions was significantly decreased at the dose of 2.0 mg/kg (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(* p&lt;0.05, different from vehicle) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Experiment 3: Effects of appetite-related manipulations on PROG/chow performance: effects of pre-feeding and the putative appetite suppressant AM251 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Experiment 3a studied the effects of pre-feeding on PROG/chow intake choice performance (figures 3A–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Compared to the previous baseline day, pre-feeding the animals prior to the session produced marked decreases in number of lever presses (t = 2.96, df = 31, p&lt;0.05), and maximum ratio achieved (t = 3.94, df = 31, p&lt;0.05), but no significant effect on active lever time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Pre-feeding significantly decreased chow intake (t = 13.69, df = 31, p&lt;0.01) compared to previous day baseline performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>There was no significant overall correlation between number of lever presses and chow consumption (r = 0.12, df = 62, n.s.), and no significant partial correlation between lever pressing and chow intake when we controlled for the between-subject variability in lever pressing (r = 0.156, df = 61, n.s.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Experiment 3b studied the effects of the cannabinoid CB1 inverse agonist AM251. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>AM251 decreased the number of lever presses (F(3,45) = 3.891, p&lt;0.05, figure 4A), and the maximum ratio achieved (F(3,45) = 5.811, p&lt;0.05, see figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Planned comparisons showed that with both measures, only the highest dose of 8.0 mg/kg AM251 significantly differed from vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>AM251 did not produce any significant changes in active lever time (figure 4C), but it significantly decrease chow intake (F(3,45) = 45.634, p&lt;0.01, figure 4D), with all doses differing from vehicle (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>There was no significant overall correlation between number of lever presses and chow consumption (r = −0.05, df = 62, n.s.), and no significant partial correlation between lever pressing and chow intake when we controlled for the between-subject variability in lever pressing (r = 0.234, df = 61, n.s.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Effects of prefeeding on PROG/chow performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>On measures of lever pressing, mean (+SEM) total lever presses (A), maximum ratio achieved (B), and active lever time (measured in seconds, C) were all significantly decreased with prefeeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Chow consumption (mean+SEM, in grams) during test sessions was significantly decreased by prefeeding animals prior to the test session (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(* p&lt;0.05, different from vehicle) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Effects of the cannabinoid CB1 inverse agonist AM251 on PROG/chow performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>On measures of lever pressing, mean (±SEM) total lever presses (A) and maximum ratio achieved (B) were significantly decreased at 8.0 mg/kg while active lever time (measured in seconds, C) was unaffected at any dose tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Chow consumption (mean ±SEM, in grams) during test sessions was significantly decreased at 2.0, 4.0 and 8.0 mg/kg doses (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>(* p&lt;0.05, different from vehicle) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Experiment 4: pDARPP-32(Thr34) Immunohistochemistry in high and low responders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Performance on the PROG/chow feeding choice task was highly variable; some rats lever pressed fewer than 100 times and had high levels of chow intake, while others lever pressed more than 1000 times and consumed small amounts of chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This variability was seen across all the experiments described above, and in some cases was related to the drug effects seen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>For example, the effects of haloperidol were more marked in rats with higher control levels of lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>When a median split was done, and high and low lever pressing was used as a factor in a 2×4 factorial ANOVA, there was an overall effect of dose (F[3,90] = 5.071, p&lt;0.05) and importantly, a dose by group interaction (F[3,90] = 4.189, p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Although the repeated measures ANOVA demonstrated that both low and high responders showed significant decreases in number of lever presses (low responders: F(3,45) = 2.790, p&lt;0.05; high responders: F(3,45) = 4.638, p&lt;0.05), analysis of effect sizes showed that the suppressive effect of haloperidol on number of lever presses was greater in high responders (eta2 = 0.236) than low responders (eta2 = 0.157). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Similar analyses revealed differences between high and low responders in the AM251 experiment, with only the high responders showing a significant drug effect on number of lever presses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Because of this large variability, the final experiment investigated potential neurochemical differences between high and low responders, using pDARPP-32(Thr34) as a marker of signal transduction activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>To analyze the pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression data, a median split based upon behavioral performance during the final test day was performed, yielding two groups: high responders (n = 16, mean = 812.44, SEM = 201.68, range = 205–2852) and low responders (n = 16, mean = 116.31, SEM = 12.81, range = 54–190). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Four regions of interest were selected for analysis: cingulate cortex CG1/CG2 and accumbens core/shell (Figures 5–6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>There were no differences in pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression between high and low responders in CG1 (t = −0.066, df = 28, n.s.) or CG2 (t = 0.172, df = 25, n.s.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Nucleus accumbens shell showed no significant differences in pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression between high and low responders (t = 1.415, df = 30, n.s.), but nucleus accumbens core showed a significant difference in pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression between high and low responders (t = 2.703, df = 29, p&lt;0.05, figures 5–6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>pDARPP-32(Thr34) immunocytochemistry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>(A and B) Atlas plates (modified from Paxinos and Watson [68] with regions of interest denoted by squares. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>(C) High magnification photomicrograph of pDARPP-32(Thr34) immunoreactive cells at 40× magnification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Several pDARPP-32(Thr34) positive cells are shown, including a darkly staining cell, with clear soma and dendritic processes (arrow) (D) Mean (±SEM) number of pDARPP-32(Thr34) positive cells counted in each region of interest in high performers and low performers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>There were significantly more pDARPP-32(Thr34) positive cells counted in the nucleus accumbens core of high performers compared to low performers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(* p&lt;0.05) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0047934-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047934.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Photomicrographs of pDARPP-32(Thr34) staining in each region of interest, showing representative low performer (left column) and high performer (right column). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>All images were taken at 10× magnification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0047934.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The present studies investigated the effects of several manipulations using a concurrent PROG/chow feeding task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Experiment 1 demonstrated that the DA D2 antagonist haloperidol decreased number of lever presses, maximum ratio achieved, and active lever time (i.e., the time the PROG schedule was active). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>These findings are consistent with previous studies showing the ability of DA antagonists or accumbens DA depletions to reduce food-reinforced lever pressing in animals responding on the concurrent FR5/choice task [6], [25], [30], as well as conventional operant schedules, including various versions of the progressive ratio schedule [52], [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Moreover, they are consistent with recent research showing that the increased DA transmission resulting from DA transporter knockdown enhanced progressive ratio performance, including conditions in which a PROG schedule reinforced by sucrose was available in the home cage and non-deprived animals also had their homecage food available [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Despite producing clear reductions in measures of operant responding, haloperidol did not decrease chow intake, which indicates that primary food motivation was intact in haloperidol-treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Moreover, previous studies have shown that 0.1 mg/kg haloperidol does not change preference for these specific high carbohydrate food pellets relative to chow, or reduce total intake of either food type in free-feeding tests [6], [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In fact, there was a slight tendency for some rats to show increased chow intake after haloperidol treatment, which was marked by the significant correlation between vehicle lever pressing and the difference in chow intake between vehicle and the highest dose of haloperidol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In other words, animals that were high lever press responders under the vehicle condition, and therefore had correspondingly low levels of chow intake, showed greater increases in chow consumption on haloperidol than low responders did. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In fact, the 4 rats with the highest level of lever pressing showed very substantial increases in chow intake after haloperidol injection (i.e., increases of 3–6 grams relative to vehicle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, unlike the previous experiments using the FR5/chow choice task [6], [25], [30], haloperidol did not produce an overall significant increase in chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation for this pattern is the different levels of chow intake with the two procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>With the FR5/chow choice procedure, baseline or control levels of lever pressing are relatively high, while chow intake is relatively low (i.e., 1–2 grams), making it possible to observe an increase in chow intake with administration of a DA antagonist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In contrast, baseline or control levels of chow intake are much higher with the PROG/chow choice procedure (i.e., 7–8 grams), and are near ceiling levels of chow intake for a 30 minute period without water being available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>For example, Randall et al. [50] demonstrated that food-restricted rats in a free feeding study consume approximately 8 grams of chow in a 30-minute period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Thus, with the PROG/chow choice procedure, it is difficult to observe drug-induced increases in chow intake in animals that are already eating chow at maximal or near maximal levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, compared to the FR5/chow choice procedure, the PROG/chow choice task is better suited for observing large reductions in chow intake due to appetite-related manipulations such as pre-feeding or appetite suppressant drugs (see discussion below). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 produced effects that were opposite to those of haloperidol; MSX-3 increased number of lever presses and maximum ratio achieved, and also increased the amount of time that animals kept the lever active during the session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous work showing that adenosine A2A antagonists have stimulant-like properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>For example, the adenosine A2A antagonists MSX-3 and istradefylline increased lever pressing on a fixed interval 4-minute schedule, which generates a relatively low baseline rate of responding [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In addition, the PROG/chow feeding choice procedure allowed for parallel assessment of food intake, and MSX-3 decreased chow consumption at the highest dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, although MSX-3 and haloperidol produced opposite effects on measures of PROG lever pressing and chow intake, in both experiments, the reciprocal relation between lever pressing and chow intake was preserved, as indicated by the high negative correlations between lever pressing and chow intake across all treatments (−0.76 and −0.78). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Significant negative partial correlations also were observed in the haloperidol and MSX-3 experiments when partial correlations were used to control for between-subject variability in lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This inverse correlation between lever pressing and chow intake has been reported in previous experiments studying the effects of DA antagonists or depletions on FR5/chow feeding choice performance [25], [27], [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Experiment 3 was conducted to determine the effect of appetite-related manipulations on PROG/chow feeding choice performance, in order to provide a contrast with the effects of haloperidol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Two different appetite manipulations were employed: pre-feeding, and administration of a cannabinoid CB1 receptor antagonist/inverse agonist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Pre-feeding animals prior to their test session, which was used to reduce food motivation and thereby devalue the food reinforcement [15], [54], produced marked decreases in number of lever presses and highest ratio achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>But, unlike the effects of haloperidol, pre-feeding also substantially reduced chow consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>In experiment 3b, the CB1 receptor antagonist/inverse agonist AM251 was assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>CB1 antagonists/inverse agonists are putative appetite suppressant drugs that have been shown to decrease food intake in animals [30], [49], [50], [55] and humans [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Moreover, stimulation of CB1 receptors in nucleus accumbens shell increased hedonic taste reactivity for intraoral sucrose [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>On the PROG/chow feeding choice task, AM251 decreased number of lever presses, maximum ratio achieved, and chow consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Thus, the pattern of effects on lever pressing and chow intake produced by pre-feeding and AM251 differed markedly from those produced by haloperidol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Moreover, while there was a high inverse correlation between lever pressing and chow intake in the haloperidol experiment, there were no significant correlations or partial correlations between these measures in the pre-feeding and AM251 experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This analysis shows that the inverse relation between lever pressing and chow intake, which is evident under baseline conditions and also throughout the haloperidol experiment, is not shown when primary food motivation is reduced by pre-feeding or drugs, because appetite-suppressant manipulations decrease both food reinforced lever pressing and chow consumption [25], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>There are a number of factors that can influence progressive ratio performance [58], and rather than yielding a simple measure of “reward”, progressive ratio breakpoints represent the outcome of a cost/benefit analysis related partially to characteristics of the reinforcer itself, but also the work-related response costs and time constraints imposed by the ratio schedule [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Indeed, previous work has demonstrated that progressive ratio break points are sensitive to work-related factors such as the height of the lever [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Taken together, experiments 1–3 demonstrate that it is exceedingly unlikely that haloperidol is decreasing PROG lever pressing because of a reduction in primary food motivation, appetite, or the unconditioned reinforcing properties of food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Clearly, in the absence of parallel measures of food intake, or taste reactivity [57], [60], progressive ratio break points should not be used as markers of food “reward”, or “hedonic” reactivity to food [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Rather, they provide a measure of how much work the organism will do in order to gain access to a reinforcing stimulus [2], [61], [62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>An important aspect of the PROG/choice procedure is that performance is characterized by substantial individual variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>While some rats lever pressed relatively little and had high levels of chow intake, others lever pressed much more and ate relatively little chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Experiment 4 employed pDARPP-32-(Thr34) immunohistochemistry to determine if there were neurochemical differences between high responders and low responders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The entire group of animals was divided in two by a median split based upon numbers of lever presses, and pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression was determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>High responders did not differ from low responders in terms of pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression in CG1 or CG2 regions of anterior cingulate cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>In the accumbens shell, there was a slight tendency for high responders to show increased pDARPP-32 expression, but this was not statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>However, high responders did show significantly greater pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression in accumbens core than low responders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>pDARPP-32(Thr34) immunoreactivity was used to provide a marker of signal transduction activity, and evidence indicates that DA acting through the D1 receptor and related G proteins (Gs/Golf) activates adenylate cyclase activity, thereby stimulating PKA-mediated phosphorylation of DARPP-32 at the Thr34 site [45]–[48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>DARPP-32 expression has been used to study drug effects [47], [48], and a few studies have focused on changes in DARPP-32 immunoreactivity associated with behavioral manipulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Danielli et al. [63] demonstrated that pDARPP-32(Thr34) showed increased expression in nucleus accumbens shell after the first exposure to a novel food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Recently, Segovia et al. [44] reported that pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression in accumbens shell and core was increased in animals undergoing FR5 operant training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Although several neurochemical factors can influence pDARPP-32(Thr34) production [48], it is reasonable to suggest that the higher level of pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression in high responders relative to low responders could reflect greater DA release in the animals working harder on the lever pressing component of the task [44], [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>If so, this could indicate that individual differences in work output are related to individual differences in DA transmission in striatal areas, as recently shown in a human imaging study [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these observations of individual variability in exertion of physical effort are consistent with recent studies of individual variability in cognitive effort across subjects (i.e., “workers” vs. “slackers”) [66]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In summary, the DA antagonist haloperidol reduced the number of lever presses and highest ratio achieved but did not suppress chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 increased lever presses and highest ratio achieved, but decreased chow consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Pre-feeding and administration of the cannabinoid CB1 antagonist/inverse agonist AM251 decreased lever presses, highest ratio achieved, and chow intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Including the option of having chow concurrently available allows one to conclude that the effects of DA antagonism differed greatly from those produced by pre-feeding or decreases in CB1 transmission, despite the fact that all three manipulations decreased lever pressing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Thus, haloperidol is not reducing PROG responding because of a general reduction in primary food motivation or the valuation of food reinforcement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Instead, the present data are consistent with the hypothesis that haloperidol left aspects of food motivation intact, but reduced the tendency to work for food reinforcement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, DA-related signal transduction activity (pDARPP-32(Thr34) expression) was greater in high responders (i.e., rats with high lever pressing output) compared to low responders, indicating that accumbens core signal transduction activity is related to individual differences in work output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Future studies should compare the effects of DA D1 and D2 antagonists, and should determine if adenosine A2A antagonism is capable of reversing the effects of DA antagonism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Studies comparing cannabinoid CB1 inverse agonists with neutral antagonists (e.g. 50, 30) would be useful for further exploration of the role of CB1 receptor signaling in performance on this procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Finally, additional neurochemical measures should be investigated for their possible relation to lever pressing output on this task, including microdialysis studies of DA release [64], and other markers of signal transduction activity (e.g. c-Fos, pDARPP-32(Thr75)) in different striatal cell types (e.g. encephalin or substance P positive neurons; [44]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>These studies are important for understanding activational aspects of motivation, and may contribute to our understanding of the neural basis of effort-related motivational impairments (e.g. anergia, psychomotor retardation, fatigue) in depression and other disorders [1], [2], [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Many thanks to Simone Janniere, Michael Treadway and Hector Contreras for their help with conducting these experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>1 SalamoneJD, CorreaM, FarrarAM, MingoteSM (2007) Effort-related functions of nucleus accumbens dopamine and associated forebrain circuits. Psychopharmacology 191: 461–482.17225164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone2"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>2 SalamoneJD, CorreaM, NunesEJ, RandallPA, PardoM (2012) The behavioral pharmacology of effort-related choice behavior: dopamine, adenosine and beyond. J Exp Anal Behav 97: 125–146.22287808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Nicola1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>3 NicolaSM (2010) The flexible approach hypothesis: unification of effort and cue-responding hypotheses for the role of nucleus accumbens dopamine in the activation of reward-seeking behavior. J Neurosci 30: 16585–16600.21147998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Beeler1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>4 BeelerJ, FrazierCRM, ZhuangX (2012a) Putting desire on a budget: dopamine and energy expenditure, reconciling reward and resources. Front Integr Neurosci 6: 49.22833718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone3"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>5 SalamoneJD (1988) Dopaminergic involvement in activational aspects of motivation: effects of haloperidol on schedule induced activity, feeding and foraging in rats. Psychobiology 16: 196–206. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone4"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>6 SalamoneJD, SteinpreisRE, McCulloughLD, SmithP, GrebelD, et al (1991) Haloperidol and nucleus accumbens dopamine depletion suppress lever pressing for food but increase free food consumption in a novel food choice procedure. Psychopharmacology 104: 515–521.1780422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone5"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>7 SalamoneJD, CousinsMS, SnyderBJ (1997) Behavioral functions of nucleus accumbens dopamine: empirical and conceptual problems with the anhedonia hypothesis. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 21: 341–359.9168269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone6"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>8 SalamoneJD, CorreaM (2002) Motivational views of reinforcement: implications for understanding the behavioral functions of nucleus accumbens dopamine. Behav Brain Res 137: 3–25.12445713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Cagniard1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>9 CagniardB, BalsamPD, BrunnerD, ZhuangX (2006) Mice with chronically elevated dopamine exhibit enhanced motivation, but not learning, for a food reward. Neuropsychopharmacology 31: 1362–1370.16319913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Robbins1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>10 RobbinsTW, EverittBJ (2007) A role for mesencephalic dopamine in activation: commentary on Berridge (2006). Psychopharmacology 191: 433–437.16977476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Beeler2"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>11 BeelerJA, FrazierCR, ZhuangX (2012b) Dopaminergic enhancement of local food-seeking is under global homeostatic control. Eur J Neurosci 35: 146–159.22118191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Mai1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>12 MaiB, SommerS, HauberW (2012) Motivational states influence effort-based decision making in rats: the role of dopamine in the nucleus accumbens. Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci 12: 74–84.22012275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Beeler3"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>13 BeelerJA, McCutcheonJE, CaoZF, MurakamiM, AlexanderE, et al (2012) Taste uncoupled from nutrition fails to sustain the reinforcing properties of food. Eur J Neurosci 36: 2533–2546.22712685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-McCullough1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>14 McCulloughLD, SalamoneJD (1992) Involvement of nucleus accumbens dopamine in the motor activity induced by periodic food presentation: a microdialysis and behavioral study. Brain Res 592: 29–36.1450917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Aberman1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>15 AbermanJE, SalamoneJD (1999) Nucleus accumbens dopamine depletions make rats more sensitive to high ratio requirements but do not impair primary food reinforcement. Neuroscience 92: 545–552.10408603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Correa1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>16 CorreaM, CarlsonBB, WisnieckiA, SalamoneJD (2002) Nucleus accumbens dopamine and work requirements on interval schedules. Behav Brain Res 137: 179–187.12445723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Mingote1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>17 MingoteS, WeberSM, IshiwariK, CorreaM, SalamoneJD (2005) Ratio and time requirements on operant schedules: effort-related effects of nucleus accumbens dopamine depletions. Eur J Neurosci 21: 1749–1757.15845103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone7"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="?"><plain>18 SalamoneJD, CousinsMS, BucherS (1994) Anhedonia or anergia? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Effects of haloperidol and nucleus accumbens dopamine depletion on instrumental response selection in a T-maze cost/benefit procedure. Behav Brain Res 65: 221–229.7718155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Cousins1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>19 CousinsMS, AthertonA, TurnerL, SalamoneJD (1996) Nucleus accumbens dopamine depletions alter relative response allocation in a T-maze cost/benefit task. Behav Brain Res 74: 189–197.8851929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Denk1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>20 DenkF, WaltonME, JenningsKA, SharpT, RushworthMF, et al (2005) Differential involvement of serotonin and dopamine systems in cost- benefit decisions about delay or effort. Psychopharmacology 179: 587–596.15864561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Mott1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>21 MottAM, NunesEJ, CollinsLE, PortRG, SinkKS, et al (2009) The adenosine A2A antagonist MSX-3 reverses the effects of the dopamine antagonist haloperidol on effort-related decision making in a T-maze cost/benefi t procedure. Psychopharmacology 204: 103–112.19132351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Pardo1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>22 PardoM, Lopez-CruzL, ValverdeO, LedentC, BaqiY, et al (2012) Adenosine A2A receptor antagonism and genetic deletion attenuate the effects of dopamine D2 antagonism on effort-based decision making in mice. Neuropharmacology 62: 2068–2077.22261384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Floresco1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>23 FlorescoSB, TseMT, Ghods-SharifiS (2008) Dopaminergic and glutamatergic regulation of effort- and delay-based decision making. Neuropsychopharmacology 33: 1966–1979.17805307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Bardgett1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>24 BardgettME, DepenbrockM, DownsN, PointsM, GreenL (2009) Dopamine modulates effort based decision making in rats. Behav Neurosci 123: 242–251.19331447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone8"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>25 SalamoneJD, ArizziM, SandovalMD, CervoneKM, AbermanJE (2002) Dopamine antagonists alter response allocation but do not suppress appetite for food in rats: contrast between the effects of SKF 83566, raclopride and fenfl uramine on a concurrent choice task. Psychopharmacology 160: 371–380.11919664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone9"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>26 SalamoneJD, CousinsMS, MaioC, ChampionM, TurskiT, et al (1996) Different behavioral effects of haloperidol, clozapine and thioridazine in a concurrent lever pressing and feeding procedure. Psychopharmacology 125: 105–112.8783383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Cousins2"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>27 CousinsMS, SokolowskiJD, SalamoneJD (1993) Different effects of nucleus accumbens and ventrolateral striatal dopamine depletions on instrumental response selection in the rat. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 46: 943–951.8309975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Koch1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>28 KochM, SchmidA, SchnitzlerHU (2000) Role of nucleus accumbens dopamine D1 and D2 receptors in instrumental and Pavlovian paradigms of conditioned reward. Psychopharmacology 152: 67–73.11041317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Nowend1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>29 NowendKL, ArizziM, CarlsonBB, SalamoneJD (2001) D1 or D2 antagonism in nucleus accumbens core or dorsomedial shell suppresses lever pressing for food but leads to compensatory increases in chow consumption. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 69: 373–382.11509194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Sink1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>30 SinkKS, VemuriVK, OlszewskaT, MakriyannisA, SalamoneJD (2008) Cannabinoid CB1 antagonists and dopamine antagonists produce different effects on a task involving response allocation and effort-related choice in food-seeking behavior. Psychopharmacology 196: 565–574.18004546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Farrar1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>31 FarrarAM, SegoviaKN, RandallPA, NunesEJ, CollinsLE, et al (2010) Nucleus accumbens and effort-related functions: behavioral and neural markers of the interactions between adenosine A2A and dopamine D2 receptors. Neuroscience 166: 1056–1067.20096336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Farrar2"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>32 FarrarAM, PereiraM, VelascoF, HockemeyerJ, MullerCE, et al (2007) Adenosine A(2A) receptor antagonism reverses the effects of dopamine receptor antagonism on instrumental output and effort-related choice in the rat: implications for studies of psychomotor slowing. Psychopharmacology 191: 579–586.17072593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Font1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>33 FontL, MingoteS, FarrarAM, PereiraM, WordenL, et al (2008) Intra-accumbens injections of the adenosine A(2A) agonist CGS 21680 affect effort-related choice behavior in rats. Psychopharmacology 199: 515–526.18491078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Mingote2"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>34 MingoteS, FontL, FarrarAM, VontellR, WordenLT, et al (2008) Nucleus accumbens adenosine A2A receptors regulate exertion of effort by acting on the ventral striatopallidal pathway. J Neurosci 28: 9037–9046.18768698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Schiffmann1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>35 SchiffmannSN, JacobsO, VanderhaeghenJJ (1991) Striatal restricted adenosine A2A receptor (RDC8) is expressed by encephalin but not by substance P neurons: an in situ hybridization histochemistry study. J Neurochem 57: 1062–1071.1713612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Ferr1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>36 FerréS, CiruelaF, CanalsM, MarcellinoD, BurguenoJ, et al (2004) Adenosine A2A-dopamine D2 receptor–receptor heteromers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Targets for neuro-psychiatric disorders. Parkinsonism Relat Disord 10: 265–271.15196504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Ferr2"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>37 FerréS (1997) Adenosine–dopamine interactions in the ventral striatum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Implications for the treatment of schizophrenia. Psychopharmacology 133: 107–120.9342776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Hillion1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>38 HillionJ, CanalsM, TorvinenM, CasadoV, ScottR, et al (2002) Coaggregation, cointernalization, and codesensitization of adenosine A2A receptors and dopamine D2 receptors. J Biol Chem 277: 18091–18097.11872740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Fuxe1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>39 FuxeK, AgnatiLF, JacobsenK, HillionJ, CanalsM, et al (2003) Receptor heteromerization in adenosine A2A receptor signaling: relevance for striatal function and Parkinson's disease. Neurology 61: S19–S23.14663004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Randall1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>40 RandallPA, NunesEJ, JanniereSL, StopperCM, FarrarAM, et al (2011) Stimulant effects of adenosine antagonists on operant behavior: differential actions of selective A2A and A1 antagonists. Psychopharmacology 216: 173–186.21347642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone10"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>41 SalamoneJD, FarrarAM, FontL, PatelV, SchlarDE, et al (2009) Differential actions of adenosine A1 and A2A antagonists on the effort related effects of dopamine D2 antagonism. Behav Brain Res 201: 216–222.19428636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Nunes1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>42 NunesEJ, RandallPA, SanterreJL, GivenAB, SagerTN, et al (2010) Differential effects of selective adenosine antagonists on the effort-related impairments induced by dopamine D1 and D2 antagonism. Neuroscience 170: 268–280.20600675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Schweimer1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>43 SchweimerJ, HauberW (2005) Involvement of the rat anterior cingulate cortex in control of instrumental responses guided by reward expectancy. Learn Mem  12: . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Segovia1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>44 SegoviaKN, CorreaM, LenningtonJB, ConoverJC, SalamoneJD (2012) Changes in nucleus accumbens and neostriatal c-Fos and DARPP-32 immunoreactivity during different stages of food-reinforced instrumental training. Eur J Neurosci 35: 1354–1367.22462413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Nishi1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>45 NishiA, BibbJA, SnyderGL, HigashiH, NairnAC, et al (2000) Amplification of dopaminergic signaling by a positive feedback loop. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97: 12840–12845.11050161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Kuroiwa1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>46 KuroiwaM, BateupHS, ShutoT, HigashiH, TanakaM, et al (2008) Regulation of DARPP-32 phosphorylation by three distinct dopamine D1-like receptor signaling pathways in the neostriatum. J Neurochem 107: 1014–1026.18823371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Bateup1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>47 BateupHS, SvenningssonP, KuroiwaM, GongS, NishiA, et al (2008) Cell type-specific regulation of DARPP-32 phosphorylation by psychostimulant and antipsychotic drugs. Nat Neurosci 11: 932–939.18622401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Yger1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="?"><plain>48Yger M, Girault JA (2011) DARPP-32, jack of all trades… master of which? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Front Behav Neurosci 5: article 56. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-McLaughlin1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>49 McLaughlinPJ, WinstonK, SwezeyL, WisnieckiA, AbermanJ, et al (2003) The cannabinoid CB1 antagonists SR 141716A and AM 251 suppress food intake and food-reinforced behavior in a variety of tasks in rats. Behav Pharmacol 14: 583–588.14665975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Randall2"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>50 RandallPA, VemuriVK, SegoviaKN, TorresEF, HosmerS, et al (2010) The novel cannabinoid CB1 antagonist AM6545 suppresses food intake and food-reinforced behavior. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 97: 179–184.20713079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Keppel1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>51Keppel G (1991) Design and analysis: a researcher's handbook. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Aberman2"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>52 AbermanJE, WardSJ, SalamoneJD (1998) Effects of dopamine antagonists and accumbens dopamine depletions on time-constrained progressive-ratio performance. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 61: 341–348.9802826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Hamill1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>53 HamillS, TrevittJT, NowendKL, CarlsonBB, SalamoneJD (1999) Nucleus accumbens dopamine depletions and time-constrained progressive ratio performance: effects of different ratio requirements. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 64: 21–27.10494993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone11"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>54 SalamoneJD, ZigmondMJ, StrickerEM (1990) Characterization of the impaired feeding behavior in rats given haloperidol or dopamine-depleting brain lesions. Neuroscience 39: 17–24.2128534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Colombo1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>55 ColomboG, AgabioR, DiazG, LobinaC, RealiR, et al (1998) Appetite suppression and weight loss after the cannabinoid antagonist SR 141716. Life Sci 63: 113–117. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-PiSunyer1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>56 Pi-SunyerFX, AronneLJ, HeshmatiHM, DevinJ (2006) Effect of rimonabant, a cannabinoid-1 receptor blocker, on weight and cardiometabolic risk factors in overweight or obese patients: RIO-North America: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA 295: 761–775.16478899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Mahler1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>57 MahlerSV, SmithKS, BerridgeKC (2007) Endocannabinoid hedonic hotspot for sensory pleasure: anandamide in nucleus accumbens shell enhances ‘liking’ of a sweet reward. Neuropsychopharmacology 32: 2267–2278.17406653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Arnold1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>58 ArnoldJM, RobertsDC (2007) A critique of fixed and progressive ratio schedules used to examine the neural substrates of drug reinforcement. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 57: 441–447. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Skjoldager1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>59 SkjoldagerP, PierrePJ, MittlmanG (1993) Reinforcer magnitude and progressive ratio responding: Effects of increased effort, prefeeding and extinction. Learn Motiv 24: 303–343. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Smith1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>60 SmithKS, BerridgeKC, AldridgeJW (2011) Disentangling pleasure from incentive salience and learning signals in brain reward circuitry. Proc Natl Acad Sci 108: E255–264.21670308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone12"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="?"><plain>61 SalamoneJD (2006) Will the last person who uses the term ‘reward’ please turn out the lights? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Comments on processes related to reinforcement, learning, motivation, and effort. Addict Biol 11: 43–4.16759335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Stewart1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>62 StewartWJ (1975) Progressive reinforcement schedules: A review and evaluation. Aus J Psychol 27: 9–22. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Danielli1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>63 DanielliB, ScheggiS, GrappiS, MarcheseG, De MontisMG, et al (2010) Modifications in DARPP-32 phosphorylation pattern after repeated palatable food consumption undergo rapid habituation in the nucleus accumbens shell of non-food-deprived rats. J Neurochem 112: 531–541.19895662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Segovia2"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>64 SegoviaKN, CorreaM, SalamoneJD (2011) Slow phasic changes in nucleus accumbens dopamine release during fixed ratio acquisition: a microdialysis study. Neuroscience 196: 178–188.21884757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Treadway1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>65 TreadwayMT, BuckholtzJW, CowanRL, WoodwardND, LiR, et al (2012) Dopaminergic mechanisms of individual differences in human effort-based decision-making. J Neurosci 32: 6170–6176.22553023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Cocker1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>66 CockerPJ, HoskingJG, BenoitJ, WinstanleyCA (2012) Sensitivity to cognitive effort mediates psychostimulant effects on a novel rodent cost/benefit decision-making task. Neuropsychopharmacol 37: 1825–1837. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Salamone13"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>67 SalamoneJD, CorreaM, MingoteSM, WeberSM, FarrarAM (2006) Nucleus accumbens dopamine and the forebrain circuitry involved in behavioral activation and effort-related decision making: implications for understanding anergia and psychomotor slowing in depression. Curr Psychiatry Rev 2: 267–280. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0047934-Paxinos1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>68Paxinos G, Watson C (1998) The Rat Brian: In Stereotaxic Coordinates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Academic Press. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>San Diego, CA. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
