<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gastroenterol Res Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gastroenterol Res Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GRP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gastroenterology Research and Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1687-6121</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1687-630X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3388477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/106502</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Psychological Issues in Inflammatory Bowel Disease: An Overview </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sajadinejad</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Molavi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adibi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department Psychology, College of Educational Science and Psychology, University of Isfahan, Isfahan, Iran</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Integrative Functional Gastroenterology Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*P. Adibi: <email>adibi@med.mui.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Gionchetti </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>106502</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 M. S. Sajadinejad et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) including Crohn's disease (CD) and ulcerative colitis (UC) is a chronic and disabling disease with unknown etiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>There have been some controversies regarding the role of psychological factors in the course of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this paper is to review that role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>First the evidence on role of stress is reviewed focusing on perceived stress and patients' beliefs about it in triggering or exacerbating the course of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The possible mechanisms by which stress could be translated into IBD symptoms, including changes in motor, sensory and secretory gastrointestinal function, increase intestinal permeability, and changes in the immune system are, then reviewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The role of patients' concerns about psychological distress and their adjustment to disease, poor coping strategies, and some personality traits that are commonly associated with these diseases are introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The prevalence rate, the timing of onset, and the impact of anxiety and depression on health-related quality of life are then reviewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Finally issues about illness behavior and the necessity of integrating psychological interventions with conventional treatment protocols are explained. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) describes a group of chronic gastrointestinal tract diseases that are relapsing and remitting; the term primarily comprises Crohn's disease (CD) and Ulcerative Colitis (UC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of these diseases has increased in the past decades, up to 120–200/100000 and 50–200/100000 persons for UC and CD, respectively [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>To date, there is no certain cure for IBD, and treatment is aimed at managing the inflammatory response during flares and maintaining remission with a focus on adhering to therapy [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The etiology of IBD is unknown, but genetic, immune, and environmental factors are each thought to play a role in its causation [1, 3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>These factors interact together, so in a person who is predisposed genetically, environmental factors trigger immune dysfunction and bowel symptoms [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>One of these environmental triggers may be psychological factors particularly psychological stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Role of Psychological Stress in IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>A belief in the relevance of psychological factors to IBD is not new. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Historically, it was first in the 1930s that gastroenterologists and psychiatrists suggested that emotional life events and experiences are likely related to exacerbation of intestinal symptoms [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>At that time, IBD was considered as a psychosomatic disease, and its relation to stress and other psychological factors was thought so strong that researchers felt no need to use any control group in their studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A few decades later, this finding was questioned mostly due to methodological weaknesses and uncontrolled studies published in this area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For a while IBD was considered as an organic disease, and psychological influences were discounted as contributing to it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>But further anecdotal evidence and clinical observations indicated that stressful experiences could adversely affect the course of IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Indeed many review articles have now emphasized the relationship between stress and IBD [6–10], concluding that confusions and controversies in published reports were partly due to differences in definitions of stress (e.g., stressful life events or hassles, daily stress) and partly due to inclusion of mixed groups of patients (CD versus UC) and/or mixed status of disease (active versus inactive) [6, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the major trends in recent studies were to differentiate between CD and UC patients, and to utilize the notion of perceived stress, which emphasizes on individual's subjective perception of stress and his/her emotional response to it [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These trends have contributed to resolving controversies, and illuminating the role of psychological stress in IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Thus, while the role of stress in the onset of IBD has not been established, there is no doubt that stress is a triggering and exacerbating factor in relation to the course and symptoms of IBD [8, 10, 12, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Indeed it can be considered as one of the determinants of disease relapse [12, 14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, there are some discordant reports about a relation between stress and disease onset, like that of Li et al. [16] who, based on a follow-up study on the onset of IBD in parents who lost a child in Denmark, found a negative relationship between psychological stress and development of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These conclusions provide support for the beliefs of almost 75% of patients with IBD that stress, or their own personality is a major contributor to the development of their disease [10, 12], and of more than 90% that it influences their disease activity [13, 17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Possible Mechanisms of the Effects of Psychological Stress on Patients with IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="?"><plain>In the light of recent advances in psychobiological research, what are the mechanisms by which the course of IBD can be influenced by stress? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Nonspecific Effects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Many of the IBD symptoms experienced by patients may be due to stress-induced changes in gastrointestinal (GI) function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>There is a richly innervated nerve plexus between the enteric nervous system (ENS) and its spinal and autonomic connections to the central nervous system, known as the brain-gut axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>GI motor, sensory and secretory function as well as thresholds for the perception of pain [13], can be affected by psychological and emotional stress directly or indirectly through this axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These effects are mediated by substance P (SP), vasoactive intestinal protein (VIP) [18], several neuropeptides, neurotransmitters, and hormones [12, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Stress stimulates the secretion of corticotropin-releasing factor (CRF) either from central or peripheral parts of CNS (hypothalamus and adrenal cortex, resp.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>While central CRF regulates the ACTH-cortisol system, peripheral CRF directly influences gastrointestinal motility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Endogenous CRF mediates the stress-induced inhibition of the upper GI tract motility and stimulation of colonic motility [12, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus when symptoms such as abdominal pain and change in bowel function occur in IBD without significant disease activity, they may be attributed, at least in some instances, to alterations in motor and sensory function as a result of psychological stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Intestinal Permeability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Psychological stress can also increase intestinal permeability, probably as a result of alterations in the cholinergic nervous system and mucosal mast cell function [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Söderholm and Perdue [22] pointed out that various types of physical and psychological stress have an impact on several components of intestinal barrier function such as increasing intestinal permeability and stimulating secretion of ions, water, mucus, and even IgA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This increased permeability in turn reduces mucosal barrier function and alters bacteria-host interaction [12, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>However, based mainly on animal studies, these observations are likely to play a role in the pathophysiology of human IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Immunological Mechanisms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Finally, stress is also likely to mediate its effect on IBD through the immune system [15, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>On the one hand, it is believed that an inadequately controlled response within the intestinal mucosa leads to inflammation in patients who are genetically predisposed to IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Dysfunction of the intestinal immune system and cross-reactivity of its cells against host epithelial cells have been implicated as major mechanisms by which the inflammatory response occurs [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, it is increasingly recognized that the (hypothalamus-pituarity-adrenal) HPA axis, autonomic nervous system (ANS), and ENS can interact directly with the immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Cytokines are essential immune molecules in the pathogenesis of IBD [24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Many researchers [15, 20, 26, 27] reported that chronic or acute stress can alter profiles of cytokines (e.g., IL-1β, IL6, IL10, IL4, and TNFα) or of hormones such as cortisol, which may contribute to the pathophysiology of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>There is a bidirectional communication between neurons and mast cells within the gastrointestinal tract [28], and mucosal mast cells can be activated by stress [15, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Stress-induced activation of mast cells, through release of mediators such as eicosanoids, serotonin, and IL6 could contribute to the pathogenesis of IBD [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Indirect Effects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In addition to the above-mentioned direct pathways, stress can also indirectly affect clinical course of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>These indirect effects are exerted through behaviors known to promote relapse [14] and include poor medication adherence [30] and smoking [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Direct and indirect mechanisms by which the course of IBD can be influenced by stress are shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Coping with IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Once IBD develops, the unpredictability, uncertainty, and chronic course of the disease can cause a wide range of psychological and interpersonal concerns to patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>These include loss of control of the bowel, fatigue, impairment of body image, a fear of sexual inadequacy, social isolation of dependency, a concern about not reaching to one's full potential, and feeling dirty [13, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Indeed, symptoms, such as faecal incontinence or soiling and lack of bowel control, can lead to a loss of self-unworthiness or cause stigmatization in patients [33, 34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Dealing with these concerns needs appropriate coping strategies and good adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, however, a variety of studies suggest that IBD patients rely significantly on passive coping strategies [34, 35], utilizing fewer purposeful problem solving and positive reappraisal, and more escape-avoidance strategies [36, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Concerns such as those listed above on the one hand, and passive and/or avoidant coping on the other hand, lead to psychological distress [38] with maladaptation and poor adjustment to the disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Sewitch et al. [39] and Mikocka-Walus et al. [40] using Symptom Checklist-90-R (SCL-90) indicated that IBD patients had impaired psychological functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>When patients receive a new diagnosis of IBD, a series of psychological adaptive steps occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>For example, the patient may do an initial evaluation of the disease's likely impact on his/her life, subsequently showing emotional reactions such as distress, grief, and sometimes guilt, exhibiting a behavioral response involving taking new medications, seeking social support, and modifying their diet; various degrees of denial and or disease acceptance may occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This adaptive process is complex; it is likely to be influenced by a range of factors including severity of disease, age of onset of disease, its extent of interference in the patient's life and future plans [32], beliefs and thoughts about illness and health, illness attribution [37], emotional status [41], and previous experiences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Among these, factors such as social support and affective state (in the frame of personality trait) have been studied in detail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Sewitch et al. [39] revealed that the relationship between psychological distress and perceived stress changes according to the level of satisfaction with social support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>For patients who experienced moderate-to-high levels of perceived stress, high satisfaction with social support decreased the level of psychological distress and facilitated adjustment to the disease, a point which highlights the importance of social support in maintaining mental health in and adjustment to IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Pellissier et al. [41] suggested that negative effect was associated with poorer coping to IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Personality Traits </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Perhaps these factors can be integrated together and attributed to personality traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Indeed, some patients with IBD believe that their own personality is a major contributor to the development of their disease [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In this context, Thornton and Andersen [42] suggest that personality traits can modulate the relationship between stress and the immunological reaction to it. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec5.1"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>5.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Neuroticism and Perfectionism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In IBD patients, the commonest personality trait is reported to be neuroticism [17, 43, 44]; furthermore, high neuroticism scores appear to reduce psychological wellbeing, psychological adjustment, and quality of life in patients with IBD [44, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Another personality characteristic, emphasized in IBD patients, is perfectionism [46]; its negative impact in IBD is probably explained by its relationship with negative cognitive biases, heightened reactivity to stressors, and feeling pressured to be and look perfect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The latter may be particularly detrimental for IBD patients because these conditions are often accompanied by stigma, shame, feeling of dirty, and a burden [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The above investigators have shown a relationship between perfectionism and the psychological impact of IBD, so as the trait was associated with emotional preoccupation coping a maladaptive coping way with disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>5.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Alexithymia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Some studies have shown alexithymia to be another common personality characteristic in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Patients with alexithymia have difficulty in recognizing and verbalizing emotions, and their ability to regulate emotions and express them to others is usually reduced [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Numerous studies [36, 44, 45, 49] have shown that IBD patients have higher scores for alexithymia than controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In Jones, Wessinger, and Crowell's study [36], the scores of 74 IBS patients, 55 healthy control subjects, and 48 IBD patients compared on Toronto Alexithymia Scale and results showed that the IBS and IBD patients had higher scores on measures of alexithymia than controls but did not differ from one another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Porcelli et al. [49] in an epidemiological study compared 121 functional gastrointestinal disorders patients, 116 IBD patients, and a group of 112 healthy subjects using Toronto Alexithymia Scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Their results showed that the FGID group was significantly more alexithymic than the IBD group, and the scores of two gastrointestinal groups were higher than the normal healthy group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Even after controlling for the influence of education, gender, anxiety, depression and gastrointestinal symptoms, these differences remained significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Moreno-Jiménez et al. [44] did not use any control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In their sample comprised of 60 UC and 60 CD patients, they have tried to address this question that, which personality factors may predict HRQOL in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>They showed that difficulty in describing one's feelings was significant on predicting two dimensions of HRQOL, that is, systemic symptoms and social functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Difficulty in describing one's feelings negatively predicted systemic symptoms and social functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Patients experiencing more difficulty in describing their feelings reported lower HRQOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, Drossman and Ringel [13] reemphasized that while alexithymia is not specific to IBD, it may lead patients to communicate their psychological distress through somatic and behavioral symptoms rather than verbal communication; this might occur particularly when patients have limited perceived social support or personality traits such as introversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Whether alexithymia is specific to IBD or not, it has been reported that affected patients have greater difficulty in describing their feelings to others, have poorer disease outcome, lower psychological functioning, and worse health-related quality of life [44, 46, 50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Although discrete personality traits have been studied among IBD patients, no certain personality type matches this disease to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>It is recommended that future research considers discrete personality traits observed in these patients and integrates them in such a way that the traits will be addressed to new personality types such as type D [51, 52] and C [53], which are well matched with unregulated immune and hormonal systems that are characteristics of IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Anxiety and Depression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The numerous concerns and worries mentioned above, together with patients' awareness of its incurability and uncertain course and prognosis, and their fear of surgery or the development of cancer, are all likely to contribute to a risk of anxiety in people with IBD [54, 55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Once a patient develops IBD, he/she usually might form adaptive adjustment to it and accept the condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Sometimes when patient has weak coping skills or social support or he/she may be personally predisposed (some personality trait such as neuroticism), he/she may feel frustrated, sad, and avoid social events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>According to Seligman's theory [56], unpredictable and incurable course of disease impaired individual's belief about self-control [33] and self-efficacy [23, 32, 57] and thereby caused helplessness and predisposed the patient to depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>There are some controversies about the comorbidity of clinical anxiety and depression in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>While some researchers [38, 58, 59] found no evidence of any association between these psychiatric disorders and either UC or CD, others [60–63] confirmed that depression and anxiety are common in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of anxiety and/or depression has been estimated to be as high as 29–35% during remission [64] and 80% for anxiety and 60% for depression during relapse [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Robertson et al. [17] and Mikocka-Walus et al. [40] distinguished between these disorders and reported that anxiety is more prevalent than depression in IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="?"><plain>Another source of controversy lies in the question of whether psychological disorders precede and/or follow after onset of the IBD? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Some researchers have considered the psychological disorders as a consequence of a new diagnosis [6, 20] and emphasized that IBD is not caused by a psychological condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>However, Kurina et al. [66], using a database of linked hospital records abstracts, in a retrospective nested case-control study on 12499 patients (7268 UC and 5231 CD) and 800000 controls with minor medical conditions not related to the conditions of interest, found that both depression and anxiety preceded UC (but not CD) significantly more often than would be predicted by chance; the relationships were strongest when the mental conditions were diagnosed shortly before UC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, these disorders were significantly more common after the diagnosis of CD, and UC was followed by anxiety, not by depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Tarter et al. [67] reported that anxiety prior to diagnosis was common, in CD, but found no significant antecedent psychological disorder in UC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>These researchers studied 53 consecutive IBD patients including 26 CD and 27 UC patients and 28 healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In this study compared to normal controls, CD patients manifest an increased prevalence of anxiety, depression, and panic disorder occurring at any time in their life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Only panic disorder had an excess prevalence in CD relative to community dwelling normals prior to the time of disease onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Individuals with UC did not demonstrate an increased prevalence of psychiatric disorder before or after disease onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Mikocka-Walus et al. [7] suggested that it is difficult to reconcile these two divergent findings, as neither study was appropriately controlled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, the sample size of the Kurina et al.'s [66] group was substantially larger than of the Tarter et al. [67], and it is a methodological strength that partly facilitates the conclusion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Whether anxiety and depression appear before or after the onset of IBD, physiological data [68, 69], suggest that these mood disorders can stimulate production of proinflammatory cytokines and thereby adversely affect the course of IBD, a conclusion supported by clinical observations [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Drossman and Ringel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>[13] suggest that psychological disturbances as a component of the illness may modulate its clinical expression, rather than being etiologic or specific to IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It is, therefore, a priority to pay careful attention to the possibility of mood disorders in patients with IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Quality of Life (QOL) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>IBD generally begins in child- or young adulthood and lasts life-long. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Although the life expectancy of IBD patients approximates to that of healthy people, IBD substantially impairs patients' health-related quality of life (HRQOL) [70, 71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Relevant factors include those discussed above, the chronicity of IBD, its complications, associated physician visits and hospitalizations, and side effects of medical treatment or surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>It is not surprising, therefore, those patients with active IBD have poorer disease-specific quality of life relative than those with inactive disease [35, 72–74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Of course, poor HRQOL is not restricted to active episodes, and the negative impact of IBD on patients quality of life continues even when it is inactive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Considering disease type, Mikocka-Walus et al. [40] and Farmer et al. [75] pointed out that impairment in psychosocial dimensions of HRQOL is greater for CD than UC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Mikocka-Walus et al. [40] compared psychological problems such as anxiety and depression and impairment of quality of life in IBD, IBS and Hepatitis C, and general population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>These researchers found that each of three groups had significantly lower quality of life than the general population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In IBD group, 31 participants with CD had poorer physical quality of life in Physical Component Summary (PSC) subscales of SF-12 than 33 UC patients (P = 0.016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Farmer et al. [75], using an interview consisted of four categories: functional/economic, social/recreational, affect/life in general, and medical/symptoms, studied quality of life on 94 patients with ulcerative colitis and 70 patients with Crohn's disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>They found that Patients with ulcerative colitis had better scores on medical/symptoms' category in the interview than those with Crohn's disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These researchers believed that perhaps these findings could be attributable to experiencing more severe disease by CD patients than UC patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Drossman and Ringel [13] have pointed out to this conclusion, as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, others have suggested that after severity of disease was taken into account, there were no significant differences between CD and UC in terms of HRQOL [57, 70]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>However, the physical symptoms of IBD do not completely explain the reductions of HRQOL in affected patients because disease activity and the intensity of patients' symptoms do not significantly correlate with their subjective impairments [77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Indeed, sociodemographic variables influence quality of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>For example, Sainsbury and Heatley [35], Casellas et al. [70], and Haapamaki [71] listed the effects of gender (women had poorer QOL than men), level of education, socioeconomic status, and older age on HRQOL in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In addition to sociodemographic variables, others have noted that psychological factors can also affect HRQOL in these diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In this regard, more psychological disturbance and the presence of anxiety or depression contribute to poorer HRQOL, regardless of severity of the IBD [43, 59, 74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, Moreno-Jiménez et al. [44] and Boye et al. [45] suggest that factors such as personality traits may influence psychological well-being and HRQOL; in their studies, neuroticism and greater difficulty in describing feelings to others were related to poorer HRQOL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Overall, because of its influence on patients' psychological well-being, social adjustment to their IBD and health care utilization, integrating HRQOL into the routine clinical assessment of patients with IBD, and targeting it as a treatment aim is strongly recommended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The factors affecting QOL of patients with IBD summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Illness Behavior </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The personal meaning of the illness, the individual's attitudes and expectations, and illness attributions to internal or external factors may all affect disease-related concerns and consequently a patient's adjustment to an illness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Since patients differ in social context, cultural heritage, value systems, family structure, prior experiences with illness, and psychological status, each individual is likely to respond differently to the challenge of a chronic illness such as IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Levenstein et al. [78] suggested that because of the impact of sociocultural beliefs and values about the illness, the impact of a given disease may also vary significantly between one country and another, even if its biological behavior is uniform. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>For example, a patient with ulcerative colitis who suffers from abdominal pain may not go to the physician if he/she has previously experienced those symptoms without serious consequences, or if he/she has grown up in a family where attention to illness has been minimal, or if he/she believes that complaining might be regarded as weakness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Another patient with the same disease activity and symptoms may frequently utilize healthcare services if he/she perceives symptoms to have dangerous consequences and is seeking disability or comes from a family where greater attention has been paid to illness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In this context, Drossman et al. [79] found that the number of physician visits in IBD patients was related to both psychological and physical health factors, so that the presence of psychological distress such as depression may lead to more frequent physician visits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>For the above reasons, physicians need to establish a close and effective therapeutic relationship with their patients, be sensitive and responsive to their patients' concerns about IBD, provide information consistent with the patients' questions and needs, and educate their patients properly about their condition and planned treatment, thereby reducing patients' concerns and uncertainties and their dependency on the healthcare system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Management of Psychological Disordersin Patients with IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>As mentioned earlier, psychological disorders such as anxiety and depression are common among IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Even if the severity of these psychological problems does not reach the clinical definition of psychiatric disease, psychological distress, concerns, worries, fears, and poor coping strategies which may lead to reduced quality of life fully justify professional attention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Most current conventional medical treatments for IBD are associated with potential side effects, some of which are psychological (e.g., mood changes, mania, or depression induced by corticosteroids), and none of them pay attention to patient's psychological status or concerns or QOL [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Therefore, integrating psychological treatment with conventional medical therapy to improve psychological distress and coping strategies and when necessary to alleviate depression or anxiety is likely to be beneficial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec9.1"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>9.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Effect of Psychological Interventions on IBD Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that if psychological stress, for example, by worsening mucosal barrier and immune function, is a pathogenic factor in IBD (see above), then psychological intervention aimed at stress reduction and may potentially reduce disease activity [9, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Specifically, Niess et al. [19] and Thornton and Andersen [42] proposed that psychological interventions such as relaxation training influence stress-mediated alterations of the immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, psychological interventions can reportedly improve the course of some immune-mediated diseases such as cancer and HIV [93, 94]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>More work is needed to assess the proposal that psychological approaches could affect the course of IBD itself. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec9.2"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>9.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Improving Personal Control </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Another reason for incorporating these interventions as complementary options in the treatment protocol relates to establishing and highlighting for the patient a sense of personal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Compared to medical therapy that emphasizes patient's obedience to their doctor in relation, for example, to medication adherence, psychological interventions engage the patient in the treatment process and increase a sense of personal control of their illness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>These interventions do this by educating patients about cues for managing stress and relaxing them, assist the patients to solve their problems rather than avoiding them or surrendering them to others, and restructuring their cognitions rather than trying to alter their external environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Many researchers [95] in sociology and psychology have indicated that personal control is important to psychological functioning and can be regarded as a robust predictor of physical and mental well-being. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, psychological interventions may increase self-efficacy in patients and thereby improve their capacity for coping and managing their distress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec9.3"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>9.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Potential Psychological Therapies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Numerous psychological interventions have been developed and studied in IBD, with a range of outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Keller et al. [80] and Wietersheim et al. [81] reported that supportive-expressive and psychodynamic therapy may be ineffective in the treatment of psychological comorbidities and somatic course of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Some studies [43, 82–86] showed that although cognitive-behavioral therapy or stress management may lead to significant improvements in anxiety, depression, and quality of life, they have no effect on the course of patients' IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In contrast, others [87–89] suggested that stress management, relaxation training, and IBD-focused counseling have been useful both for psychological problems and the clinical symptoms of IBD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive lifestyle modification program [90] and mind-body therapy [91] have also been studied in IBD patients and revealed significant improvements in quality of life, anxiety, and psychological well-being. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec9.4"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>9.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Antidepressants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>High prevalence of psychological disorders, such as anxiety and depression in patients with IBD, may recommend psychopharmacological therapies specially antidepressants as an alternative treatment for these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Although a qualitative study [92], based on interviewing with gastroenterologists, showed that some gastroenterologists use antidepressants for treating pain, anxiety and/or depression, and insomnia in patients with IBD, to date application of these drugs is not straightforward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Mikocka-Walus et al. [96], based on their systematic review about antidepressants and IBD, reported that tricyclic antidepressants (e.g., Amitriptylin, dothiepin, prothiaden, doxepin, imipramin, and nortriptyline) not only alleviate psychological distress, but also have some positive effects on somatic status of IBD patients through reducing pain, gut irritability, and urgency of defecation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Newer antidepressants are not prescribed as much as TCAs by physicians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Recent systematic review by Mikocka-Walus et al. [97] even reported that antidepressants have positive effect on inflammation of the bowel in IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Since the most published data in this area have not been randomized and have methodological weaknesses, Hardt et al. [63] concluded that it is impossible to make a definitive statement of efficacy of antidepressants on mental and somatic status of IBD patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Overall, while there are contradictory reports on the effect of psychological interventions on clinical course of IBD, most show a positive effect on psychological and emotional status and HRQOL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Contradictory findings may be in part due to difference in trial design, the components of the tested treatment protocols, outcome measures assessed, and other confounding variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Undoubtedly, more rigorous better designed studies in this field are needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>With regard to recent findings about the effect of psychological interventions on immune modification [97, 98] and reducing the likelihood of relapse [57], the necessity of incorporating them to conventional treatment protocol of IBD is more illustrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Options for management of psychological disorders in patients with IBD are listed in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Current evidence indicates that psychological factors play a role both in the pathophysiology and course of IBD and in how patients deal with these chronic and disabling diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Over the two last decades, improvements in study design and methodology, along with advances in psychoneuroendocrinology and psychoneuroimmunology, have led to improved, if still incomplete, understanding of the relevant pathophysiological mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The contribution of some psychological factors such as predisposing personality remains uncertain and requires further study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, in view of the importance of psychological dysfunction in modifying illness behavior and its negative impact on symptoms and QOL, the integration of psychological interventions into conventional medical therapy, seems advisable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Where further study is most urgently needed, however, it lies in the analysis of the precise effects of these interventions on not only psychological state and quality of life, but also on the physiological parameters and the course of IBD itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Such research should investigate also which is the most effective component, or combination of components for the psychological management of IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Auther Contributions</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>All authers have contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Supportive Foundations</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Supported by Iran National Science Foundation: INSF, No. 89002451 </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The authers thank Professor David Rampton for his advice on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>1CosnesJGowerrousseauCSeksikPCortotAEpidemiology and natural history of inflammatory bowel diseasesGastroenterology20111406178517942-s2.0-7995556108321530745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>2NahonSLahmekPSaasCSocioeconomic and psychological factors associated with nonadherence to treatment in inflammatory bowel disease patients: results of the ISSEO surveyInflammatory Bowel Diseases2011176127012762-s2.0-7995579728521560190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>3HugotJPGenetic origin of IBDInflammatory Bowel Diseases200410supplement 1S11S152-s2.0-1542410513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>4ShanahanFInflammatory bowel disease: immunodiagnostics, immunotherapeutics, and ecotherapeuticsGastroenterology200112036226352-s2.0-003511609111179240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>5NeumanMGImmune dysfunction in inflammatory bowel diseaseTranslational Research2007149417318617383591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>6KeeferLKeshavarzianAMutluEReconsidering the methodology of “stress” research in inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Crohn’s and Colitis2008231932012-s2.0-48949086696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>7Mikocka-WalusAATurnbullDAMouldingNTWilsonIGAndrewsJMHoltmannGJControversies surrounding the comorbidity of depression and anxiety in inflammatory bowel disease patients: a literature reviewInflammatory Bowel Diseases20071322252342-s2.0-3424932544217206706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>8CámaraJAZieglerRBegréSSchoepferAMKänelRThe role of psychological stress in inflammatory bowel disease: quality assessment of methods of 18 prospective studies and suggestions for future researchDigestion200980212913919657191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>9LevensteinSStress and ulcerative colitis: convincing the doubting thomasesAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20039810211221152-s2.0-014224580314572553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>10MaunderRLevensteinSThe role of stress in the development and clinical course of inflammatory bowel disease: epidemiological evidenceCurrent Molecular Medicine20088424725218537632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>11FliegeHRoseMArckPThe perceived stress questionnaire (PSQ) reconsidered: validation and reference values from different clinical and healthy adult samplesPsychosomatic Medicine200567178882-s2.0-1274425999615673628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>12HisamatsuTInoueNYajimaTIzumiyaMIchikawaHHibiTPsychological aspects of inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Gastroenterology200742supplement 17344017238024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>13DrossmanDARingelYSartorRSandbornWPsychological factors in ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s diseaseKirsner’s Inflammatory Bowel Disease20046th editionPhiladelphia, Pa, USAWB Saunders340356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>14BittonASewitchMJPeppercomMAPsychosocial determinants of relapse in ulcerative colitis: a longitudinal studyAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20039810220322082-s2.0-014218368114572569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>15MawdsleyJERamptonDSPsychological stress in IBD: new insights into pathogenic and therapeutic implicationsGut20055410148114912-s2.0-2544447076216162953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>16LiJNørgardBPrechtDHOlsenJPsychological stress and inflammatory bowel disease: a follow-up study in parents who lost a child in DenmarkAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20049961129113315180736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>17RobertsonDAFRayJDiamondIEdwardsJGPersonality profile and affective state of patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseGut19893056236262-s2.0-00243338022731754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>18MaunderRMediators of stress effects in inflammatory bowel disease: not the usual suspectsJournal of Psychosomatic Research200048656957711033376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>19NiessJHMönnikesHDignassAUKlappBFArckPCReview on the influence of stress on immune mediators, neuropeptides and hormones with relevance for inflammatory bowel diseaseDigestion20026531311402-s2.0-003605723612138318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>20KiankCTachéYLaraucheMStress-related modulation of inflammation in experimental models of bowel disease and post-infectious irritable bowel syndrome: role of corticotropin-releasing factor receptorsBrain, Behavior, and Immunity201024141482-s2.0-71749085213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>21HollanderDInflammatory bowel diseases and brain-gut axisJournal of Physiology and Pharmacology200354supplement 4183190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>22SöderholmJDPerdueMHStress and the gastrointestinal tract II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Stress and intestinal barrier functionAmerican Journal of Physiology20012801G7G1311123192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>23KurokiTOhtaAAokiYStress maladjustment in the pathoetiology of ulcerative colitisJournal of Gastroenterology20074275225272-s2.0-3454760957617653646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>24RodaGMarocchiMSartiniARodaECytokine networke in ulcerative colitisUlcers201120115 pages391787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>25BamiasGKaltsaGLadasSDCytokines in the pathogenesis of ulcerative colitisDiscovery Medicine2011116045946721616044 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>26LanghorstJCobelensPMKavelaarsAStress-related peripheral neuroendocrine-immune interactions in women with ulcerative colitisPsychoneuroendocrinology2007328–10108610962-s2.0-3604904036017933470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>27BernsteinCNSinghSGraffLAWalkerJRMillerNCheangMA prospective population-based study of triggers of symptomatic flares in IBDAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20101059199420022-s2.0-7795634342020372115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>28NassauwLVAdriaensenDTimmermansJPThe bidirectional communication between neurons and mast cells within the gastrointestinal tractAutonomic Neuroscience20071331911032-s2.0-3394760592317169619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>29TheoharidesTCCochraneDECritical role of mest cells in inflammatory bowel diseases and the effect of acute stressJournal of Neuroimmunology20041461-211214698841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>30NahonSLahmekPSaasCSocioeconomic and psychological factors associated with nonadherence to treatment in inflammatory bowel disease patients: results of the ISSEO surveyInflammatory Bowel Diseases2011176127012762-s2.0-7995579728521560190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>31SinghSGraffLABernsteinCNDo NSAIDs, antibiotics, infections, or stress trigger flares in IBDAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20091045129813132-s2.0-6694916814719337242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>32KieblesJLDoerflerBKeeferLPreliminary evidence supporting a framework of psychological adjustment to inflammatory bowel diseaseInflammatory Bowel Diseases20101610168516952-s2.0-7864924930520155849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>33CooperJMCollierJJamesVHawkeyCJBeliefs about personal control and self-management in 30–40 year olds living with inflammatory bowel disease: a qualitative studyInternational Journal of Nursing Studies20104712150015092-s2.0-7804925777020646707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>34CasatiJTonerBBPsychosocial aspects of inflammatory bowel diseaseBiomedicine and Pharmacotherapy200054738839310989978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>35SainsburyAHeatleyRVReview article: psychosocial factors in the quality of life of patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseAlimentary Pharmacology and Therapeutics200521549950815740531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>36JonesMPWessingerSCrowellMDCoping strategies and interpersonal support in patients with irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel diseaseClinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology2006444744812-s2.0-3364582559116616353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>37GraffLAWalkerJRClaraIStress coping, distress, and health perceptions in inflammatory bowel disease and community controlsAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology200910412295929692-s2.0-7294910871219755973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>38CraneCMartinMSocial learning, affective state and passive coping in irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel diseaseGeneral Hospital Psychiatry200426150582-s2.0-094226811914757303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>39SewitchMJAbrahamowiczMBittonAPsychological distress, social support, and disease activity in patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology2001965147014792-s2.0-003500791111374685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>40Mikocka-WalusAATurnbullDAAndrewsJMPsychological problems in gastroenterology outpatients: a South Australian experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Psychological co-morbidity in IBD, IBS and hepatitis CClinical Practice and Epidemiology in Mental Health20084, article 152-s2.0-45949086448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>41PellissierSDantzerCCaniniFMathieuNBonazBPsychological adjustment and autonomic disturbances in inflammatory bowel diseases and irritable bowel syndromePsychoneuroendocrinology20103556536622-s2.0-7795255151119910123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>42ThorntonLMAndersenBLPsychoneuroimmunology examined: the role of subjective stressCellscience200624669118633462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>43PraskoJJelenovaDMihalVPsychological aspects and psychotherapy of inflammatory bowel diseases and irritable bowel syndrome in childrenBiomedical Papers of the Medical Faculty of the University Palacký, Olomouc, Czechoslovakia201015443073142-s2.0-78650804491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>44Moreno-JiménezBBlancoBLRodríguez-MuñozAHernándezEGThe influence of personality factors on health-related quality of life of patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Psychosomatic Research2007621394617188119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>45BoyeBLundinKEALegangerSThe INSPIRE study: do personality traits predict general quality of life (short form-36) in distressed patients with ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s disease?Scandinavian Journal of Gastroenterology200843121505151318777439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>46FlettGLBariczaCGuptaAHewittPLEndlerNSPerfectionism, psychosocial impact and coping with irritable bowel disease: a study of patients with Crohn’s disease and ulcerative colitisJournal of Health Psychology20111645615712-s2.0-7995460042421346015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>47HallNJRubinGPDougallAHunginAPNeelyJThe fight for health-related normality: a qualitative study of the experiences of individuals living with established inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Health Psychology20051034434552-s2.0-2324444127015857873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>48BagbyRMParkerJDATaylorGTThe twenty-item Toronto Alexithymia Scale—I: item selection and cross-validation of the factor structureJournal of Psychosomatic Research199438123328126686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>49PorcelliPTaylorGJBagbyRMde CarneMAlexithymia and functional gastrointestinal disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>A comparison with inflammatory bowel diseasePsychotherapy and Psychosomatics199968526326910516531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>50VaughnCLeffJSarnerMRelatives expressed emotion and the course of inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Psychosomatic Research19994754614692-s2.0-003340454810624844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>51SherLType D personality: the heart, stress and cortisolMonthly Journal of the Association of Physicians200598532332915820973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>52MolsFDenolletJType D personality in the general population: a systematic review of health status, mechanisms of disease, and work-related problemsHealth and Quality of Life Outcomes20108, article 91102-s2.0-7694909662420053296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>53TemoshokLRWaldsteinSRWaldRLType C coping, alexithymia, and heart rate reactivity are associated independently and differentially with specific immune mechanisms linked to HIV progressionBrain, Behavior, and Immunity20082257817922-s2.0-44749084721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>54GraffLAWalkerJRBernsteinCNIt’s not just about the gut: managing depression and anxiety in inflammatory bowel diseasePractical Gastroenterology201034711252-s2.0-78149269051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>55GraffLAWalkerJRBernsteinCNDepression and anxiety in iflammatory bowel disease: a review of comorbidity and managementInflammatory Bowel Diseases2009157110511182-s2.0-6644908837019161177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>56SeligmanMLearned Optimism2002New York, NY, USAVintage Books </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>57KeeferLKieblesJLMartinovichZCohenEVan DenburgABarrettTABehavioral interventions may prolong remission in patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseBehaviour Research and Therapy20114931451502-s2.0-7995167694421256475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>58GuthrieEJacksonJShafferJThompsonDTomensonBCreedFPsychological disorder and severity of inflammatory bowel disease predict health-related quality of life in ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s diseaseAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology2002978199419992-s2.0-003667735412190166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>59HelzerJEChammasSNorlandCCA study of the association between Crohn’s disease and psychiatric illnessGastroenterology19848623243302-s2.0-00213534486690360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>60FrochBZwolińska-WcisłoMBȩtkowska-KorpałaBMachTThe dynamics of emotional reactions in patients with inflammatory bowel diseasePrzeglad Gastroenterologiczny2009431411462-s2.0-70350763853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>61KovácsZKovácsFDepressive and anxiety symptoms, dysfunctional attitudes and social aspects in irritable bowel syndrome and inflammatory bowel diseaseInternational Journal of Psychiatry in Medicine20073732452552-s2.0-3754900248118314852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>62Mikocka-WalusAA Treatment of psychological comorbidities in common gastrointestinal and hepatologic disordersWorld Journal of Gastrointestinal Pharmacology and Therapeutics201012647121577298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>63HardtJConradSMuche-BorowskiCRaspeHEpidemiology of depression and distress in patients with inflammatory bowel disease and validation of an indicator scale of perceived stress for psychological impairmentsEuropean Psychiatry20112622172225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>64MittermaierCDejacoCWaldhoerTImpact of depressive mood on relapse in patients with inflammatory bowel disease: a prospective 18-month follow-up studyPsychosomatic Medicine200466179842-s2.0-074227056314747641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>65AddoloratoGCapristoEStefaniniGFGasbarriniGinflammatory bowel disease: a study of the association between anxiety and depression, physical morbidity, and nutritional statusScandinavian Journal of Gastroenterology19973210101310219361174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>66KurinaLMGoldacreMJYeatesDGillLEDepression and anxiety in people with inflammatory bowel diseaseJournal of Epidemiology and Community Health200155107167202-s2.0-003483573011553654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>67TarterRESwitalaJCarraJEdwardsKLVan ThielDHInflammatory bowel disease: psychiatric status of patients before and after disease onsetInternational Journal of Psychiatry in Medicine19871721731813610483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>68TachéYBernsteinCNEvidence for the role of the brain-gut axis in inflammatory bowel disease: depression as cause and effect?Gastroenterology20091367205820612-s2.0-6644909440419406133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>69Kiecolt-GlaserJKMcGuireLRoblesTFGlaserREmotions, morbidity and mortality: new perspectives from psychoneroimmunologyAnnual Review of Psychology20025383107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>70CasellasFLópez-VivancosJCasadoAMalageladaJRFactors affecting health related quality of life of patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseQuality of Life Research20021187757812-s2.0-003689169812482161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>71HaapamakiJHealth-Related Quality of Life, Symptoms and Comorbidity in Inflammatory Bowel Disease [Ph.D. dissertation]2011The Medical Faculty of the University of Helsinki </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>72AlbersnagelFDijkstraGinflammatory bowel disease: medical and psychological aspectsPsychologie &amp; Gezondheid20073528596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>73GraffLAWalkerJRLixLThe relationship of inflammatory bowel disease type and activity to psychological functioning and quality of lifeClinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology2006412149115012-s2.0-3384528491517162241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>74VidalAGomez-GilESansMHealth-related quality of life in inflammatory bowel disease patients: the role of psychopathology and personalityInflammatory Bowel Diseases20081479779832-s2.0-4794912054718275078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>75FarmerRGEasleyKAFarmerJMQuality of life assessment by patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseCleveland Clinic Journal of Medicine199259135422-s2.0-00264560851551212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B100"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>76MoradkhaniAInflammatory bowel disease: variables associated with health-related quality of life, stress, and health behaviors [Ph.D. thesis]2011Los Angeles, Calif, USAFaculty of the California School of Professional Psychology, Alliant International University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>77CuntzUWeltJRupertEZillessenEDetermination of subjective burden from chronic inflammatory bowel disease and its psychosocial consequencesPsychotherapy, Psychosomatics, Medical Psychology19994912494500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>78LevensteinSZhimingLIAlmerSCross-cultural variation in disease-related concerns among patients with inflammatory bowel diseaseAmerican Journal of Gastroenterology20019661822183011419836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B80"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>79DrossmanDALesemanJMitchellCMLiZZagamiEAPatrickDLHealth statuse and health care use in persons with inflammatory bowel disease: a national sampleDigestive Diseases and Sciences19913612174617551748045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B84"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>80KellerWPritschMWietersheimJEffect of psychotherapy and relaxation on the psychosocial and somatic course of Crohn’s disease: main results of the german prospective multicenter psychotherapy treatment study on Crohn’s diseaseJournal of Psychosomatic Research20045666876962-s2.0-454432416115193965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B85"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>81WietersheimJVScheibPKellerWThe effects of psychotherapy on Crohn’s disease patients—results of a randomized multicenter studyPsychotherapie Psychosomatik Medizinische Psychologie2001511292-s2.0-0035155153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B86"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>82BoyeBLundinKEAMoklebyKThe INSPIRE study stress-management psychotherapy improves disease specific quality of life in distressed patients with ulcerative colitis but not in distressed patients with Crohn’s diseaseBrain, Behavior, and Immunity20082241521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B87"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>83SibajaMADMorenoMIHessBMProtocolized cognitive-behavioural group therapy for inflammatory bowel diseaseRevista Espanola de Enfermedades Digestivas2007991059359818052663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B88"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>84SchwarzSPBlanchardEBEvaluation of a psychological treatment for inflammatory bowel diseaseBehaviour Research and Therapy19912921671772021379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B89"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>85MussellMBöckerUNagelNOlbrichRSingerMVReducing psychological distress in patients with inflammatory bowel disease by cognitive-behavioural treatment: exploratory study of effectivenessScandinavian Journal of Gastroenterology20033877557622-s2.0-004217039712889563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B90"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>86SzigethyEWhittonSWLevy-WarrenADemasoDRWeiszJBeardsleeWRCognitive-behavioral therapy for depression in adolescents with inflammatory bowel disease: a pilot studyJournal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry20044312146914772-s2.0-1284425023815564816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B91"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>87Garcia-VegaEFernandez-RodriguezCA stress management programme for Crohn’s diseaseBehaviour Research and Therapy200442436738314998732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B92"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>88ShawLEhrlichARelaxation training as a treatment for chronic pain caused by ulcerative colitisPain19872932872933302842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B93"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>89WahedMCorserMGoodhandJRRamptonDSDoes psychological counseling alter the natural history of inflammatory bowel disease?Inflammatory Bowel Diseases20101646646692-s2.0-7794952071019774642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B94"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>90LanghorstJMuellerTLuedtkeREffects of a comprehensive lifestyle modification program on quality-of-life in patients with ulcerative colitis: a twelve-month follow-upScandinavian Journal of Gastroenterology20074267347452-s2.0-3424851329517505996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B95"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>91ElsenbruchSLanghorstJPopkirowaKEffects of mind-body therapy on quality of life and neuroendocrine and cellular immune functions in patients with ulcerative colitisPsychotherapy and Psychosomatics20057452772872-s2.0-2384444163716088265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B96"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>92Mikocka-WalusAATurnbullDAMouldingNTWilsonIGAndrewsJMHoltmannGJ‘It doesn’t do any harm, but patients feel better’: a qualitative exploratory study on gastroenterologists’ perspectives on the role of antidepressants in inflammatory bowel diseaseBMC Gastroenterology20077, article 382-s2.0-35549013693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B81"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="?"><plain>93IronsonGHaywardHDo positive psychosocial factors predict disease progression in HIV-1? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>A review of the evidencePsychosomatic Medicine200870554655418541905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B82"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>94VedharaKIrwinMHuman Psychoneuroimmunology2005Oxford, UKOxford University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B83"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>95SkinnerEA guide to constructs of controlJournal of Personality and Social Psychology19967135495708831161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B97"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>96Mikocka-WalusAATurnbullDAMouldingNTWilsonIGAndrewsJMHoltmannGJAntidepressants and inflammatory bowel disease: a systematic reviewClinical Practice and Epidemiology in Mental Health20062, article 242-s2.0-33750160203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B98"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="?"><plain>97Mikocka-WalusAAClarkeDGibsonPCan antidepressants influence the course of inflammatory bowel disease? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>The current state of researchEuropean Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology200954853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B99"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>98BowerJESegerstromSCStress management, finding benefit, and immune function: positive mechanisms for intervention effects on physiologyJournal of Psychosomatic Research200456191114987958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Direct and indirect mechanisms by which the course of IBD can be influenced by stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="GRP2012-106502.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Factors affecting QOL in patients with IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Factor </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Study </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Result </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="13" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Disease-related factors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Disease activity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Vidal et al. [74] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Disease activity was one of strongest predictors of QOL impairments. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Albersnagel and Dijkstra [72] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Disease activity adversely affects QOL of the patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Haapamaki [71] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Disease activity was the most factors related to QOL impairment. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Graff et al. [73] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Patients with active disease had poorer QOL scores, but participants with either active or inactive disease had suboptimal general QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Disease severity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Guthrie et al. [58] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Disease severity was one of factors contributed to impaired QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Disease type </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Mikocka-Walus et al. [40] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>CD patients tended to have poorer physical QOL than UC patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Casellas et al. [70] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Disease type did not predict QOL scores. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Guthrie et al. [58] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>After controlling disease severity, there were no significant differences between CD and UC in QOL scores. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Graff et al. [73] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Disease type was not contributor to QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>History of surgery </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Haapamaki [71] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Lower QOL scores were seen in those patients with a history of surgery. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Disease chronicity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Haapamaki [71] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Lower QOL scores were seen in newly diagnosed patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Casellas et al. [70] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Longer disease duration and lower recurrence/year index predicted a better QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Need for hospitalization </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Casellas et al. [70] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Nonnecessity of hospitalization predicted a better QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Demographic factors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Gender </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Haapamaki [71] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Female had poorer QOL than men. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Casellas et al. [70] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Female gender predicted a better QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Age </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Haapamaki [71] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Older age patients had poorer QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Educational level </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Casellas et al. [70] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Higher level of education predicted a better QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Psychological factors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Personality </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Vidal et al. [74] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Personality traits did not play a significant role in QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Moreno-Jiménez et al. [44] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Neuroticism and greater difficulty in describing feelings to others were related to poorer QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Psychological distress </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Vidal et al. [74] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Psychological distress was one of strongest predictors of QOL impairments. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Guthrie et al. [58] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Psychological symptoms were one of factors contributed to impaired QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Social support </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Moradkhani [76] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Activity in online support groups was not related to QOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Options for management of psychological disorders in patients with IBD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Study </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Effectivity </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Psychological problems </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Course of IBD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Quality of life </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Supportive-expressive and psychodynamic therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Keller et al. [80] and Wietersheim et al. [81] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Ineffective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Ineffective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>CBT or stress management </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Boye et al. [45, 82], Sibaja et al. [83], Schwarz and Blanchard [84], Mussell et al. [85], Szigethy et al. [86] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Ineffective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Garcia-Vega and Fernandez-Rodriguez [87],and Shaw and Ehrlich [88] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>IBD-focused counseling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Wahed et al. [89] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Lifestyle modification program </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Langhorst et al. [26, 90] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Mind-body therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Elsenbruch et al. [91] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Antidepressants </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Mikocka-Walus et al. [7, 92] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Effective </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Controversial </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Not reported </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
