<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3787392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2013.00309</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Activation of the Interferon Pathway is Dependent Upon Autoantibodies in African-American SLE Patients, but Not in European-American SLE Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Kichul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koldobskaya</surname><given-names>Yelena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niewold</surname><given-names>Timothy B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Section of Rheumatology, Gwen Knapp Center for Lupus and Immunology Research, University of Chicago</institution>, <addr-line>Chicago IL</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Immunology, Division of Rheumatology, Mayo Clinic</institution>, <addr-line>Rochester, MN</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Fabrizio Mattei, Istituto Superiore di Sanità, Italy </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Dalil Hannani, Institut de Cancérologie Gustave Roussy – INSERM U1015, France; Kamil R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Kranc, University of Edinburgh, UK </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp content-type="corresp" id="cor1">*Correspondence: Timothy B. Niewold, Department of Immunology, Division of Rheumatology, Mayo Clinic, 200 1st Street SW, Guggenheim Building 3-42, Rochester, MN 55905, USA e-mail: <email>niewold.timothy@mayo.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Molecular Innate Immunity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Immunology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>309</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Ko, Koldobskaya, Rosenzweig and Niewold.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Background: In systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), antibodies directed at RNA-binding proteins (anti-RBP) are associated with high serum type I interferon (IFN), which plays an important role in SLE pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>African-Americans (AA) are more likely to develop SLE, and SLE is also more severe in this population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that peripheral blood gene expression patterns would differ between AA and European-American (EA) SLE patients, and between those with anti-RBP antibodies and those who lack these antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Methods: Whole blood RNA from 33 female SLE patients and 16 matched female controls from AA and EA ancestral backgrounds was analyzed on Affymetrix Gene 1.0 ST gene expression arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity Pathway Analysis was used to compare the top differentially expressed canonical pathways amongst the sample groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>An independent cohort of 116 SLE patients was used to replicate findings using quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Results: Both AA and EA patients with positive anti-RBP antibodies showed over-expression of similar IFN-related canonical pathways, such as IFN Signaling (P = 1.3 × 10−7 and 6.3 × 10−11 in AA vs. EA respectively), Antigen Presenting Pathway (P = 1.8 × 10−5 and 2.5 × 10−6), and a number of pattern recognition receptor pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In anti-RBP negative (RBP−) patients, EA subjects demonstrated similar IFN-related pathway activation, whereas no IFN-related pathways were detected in RBP−AA patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>qPCR validation confirmed similar results. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusion: Our data show that IFN-induced gene expression is completely dependent on the presence of autoantibodies in AA SLE patients but not in EA patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This molecular heterogeneity suggests differences in IFN-pathway activation between ancestral backgrounds in SLE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This heterogeneity may be clinically important, as therapeutics targeting this pathway are being developed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>systemic lupus erythematosus</kwd><kwd>interferon alpha</kwd><kwd>autoantibodies</kwd><kwd>ancestral background</kwd><kwd>interferon gamma</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="52"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6373"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a heterogeneous disease characterized by complex genetic contributions and activation of a number of immune system pathways (1–3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Recent advances in human genetic studies have helped us better understand the immunopathogenesis of the disorder (4, 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Multiple candidate gene association studies and genome wide association studies have led to discovery of more than 30 susceptibility loci throughout the whole genome, most of which are involved in three main pathways in lupus pathogenesis: abnormal clearance of nuclear debris and immune complexes, over-activation of innate immune system through Toll-like receptor (TLR) and type I interferon (IFN) signaling, and aberrant adaptive immune response through B and T cell signaling (6, 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Moreover, gene expression microarray studies have been instrumental in defining important aspects of the complex immunological pathogenesis in human subjects (8, 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Several gene expression analyses in SLE have found up-regulation of IFN-inducible genes (IFIGs) in more than 50% of patients (10–13), and others have shown differential expression of genes involved in several pathways including inflammation, apoptosis, DNA repair, and T cell activation (12, 14–17). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Interferon-α is a pleiotropic type I IFN which plays a key pathogenic role in lupus development (18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It is an anti-viral cytokine which is regulated by endosomal pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) such as TLRs or cytosolic PRRs like RIG-I like receptors (RLRs) (18, 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>It has the potential to break self-tolerance by inducing dendritic cell differentiation which in turn leads to activation of autoreactive T and B cells, thus linking innate and adaptive immune systems (20, 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>IFN-α is a heritable risk factor in SLE (22, 23) and some people who have received recombinant human IFN-α as a treatment for viral hepatitis C or malignancy have developed de novo SLE which resolves upon discontinuation of the IFN-α treatment (24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>These data strongly support a causal role for IFN-α in SLE pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Increased activity of IFN-α has been associated with presence of various SLE-associated autoantibodies, both anti-double-stranded DNA (anti-dsDNA) and anti-RNA-binding protein (anti-RBP) antibodies along with different organ involvement such as hematologic, renal, and central nervous systems (10, 25, 26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, longitudinal studies have not confirmed the association between increases in IFIG expression and disease flare (27, 28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It seems that patients with high IFN-α have more severe disease and a higher rate of flare on average, but the changes in IFN-α levels in circulation do not correlate closely or quantitatively with changes in measures of disease activity over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus is both more prevalent and more severe in African-American (AA) populations than in European-American (EA) populations, and disease manifestations are variable amongst different ancestral backgrounds (29–32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>AA and Hispanic-American (HA) patients are likely to have more active SLE, with an earlier age at onset, than EA patients (31, 32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Anti-ribonucleoprotein (anti-RNP) and anti-Smith (anti-Sm) antibodies are more prevalent in AA patients than in EA and HA (30, 32), and a number of genetic variants are associated with autoantibody profiles in different ancestral groups (33, 34). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Moreover, compared to EA patients, HA, and AA patients have a higher incidence of SLE-related renal disease, associated with anti-dsDNA and anti-RNP antibodies (31, 35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Additionally, some of the genetic factors associated with SLE are not shared between AA and EA patients (36–39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>These data all support the idea that molecular and biological differences should exist in SLE patients of different ancestral backgrounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We have shown that overall serum IFN-α activity is higher in SLE patients of non-European ancestry as compared to European ancestry, either directly or indirectly through an increased prevalence of anti-RBP antibodies (40, 41). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this study, we compare peripheral blood gene expression between AA and EA SLE patients taking into account the differences in autoantibody profile, and we find a striking difference in the activation of the IFN pathway between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Patients, samples, and data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were obtained from 149 female SLE patients from the University of Chicago Medical Center (UCMC) (n = 119) and NorthShore University Health System (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All cases fulfilled the American College of Rheumatology criteria for the diagnosis of SLE (1, 42), and the data regarding the presence or absence of these criteria as well as of SLE-associated autoantibodies [anti-nuclear antibodies (ANA), and anti-Ro, anti-La, anti-Sm, anti-RNP, and anti-dsDNA antibodies] were available for all patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Forty-nine unrelated females who were screened by medical record review for the absence of autoimmune disease were used as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>They were of similar age (P = 0.21) as the SLE cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>All subjects provided informed consent, and the study was approved by the institutional review boards at the Mayo Clinic and University of Chicago. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Detection of autoantibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Antibodies to Ro, La, Sm, and RNP for all samples were measured by ELISA methods (INOVA Diagnostics, San Diego, CA, USA) at UCMC at the time of serum and RNA sampling, and standard clinical laboratory cutoff points were used to categorize them as positive or negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Anti-dsDNA antibodies were measured using Crithidia luciliae immunofluorescence at UCMC, and detectable fluorescence was considered positive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Thirty-three SLE cases and 16 age-matched controls were selected for microarray gene expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The cases were subdivided into AA and EA patients, and those with positive anti-RBP antibodies and those without as described in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Whole blood from the subjects was collected in PAX gene tubes (Qiagen), and RNA was purified in spin columns per manufacture recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The RNA was analyzed on Affymetrix Gene 1.0 ST gene expression arrays, which were run in the University of Chicago Microarray Core facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>These intensity data were normalized through Affymetrix Expression Console software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Data from the microarray experiment have been deposited in the GEO database, accession number GSE50635. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Samples and data collection for microarray analysis*. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>SLE cases** </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Non-autoimmune controls </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>RBP+ </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>RBP− </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>European-American </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>African-American </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>*There was no difference in age amongst the groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>**All SLE cases fulfilled the ACR criteria for SLE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Anti-RBP (anti-Ro, anti-La, anti-Sm, and anti-RNP) antibodies were measured by ELISA, and anti-dsDNA antibody levels were measured using Crithidia luciliae immunofluorescence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>RBP+, anti-RNA-binding-protein (RBP) antibody positive; RBP−, RBP antibody negative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) was used to validate the hypotheses generated from the microarray data with an independent replication cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The RNA of whole blood from 60 AA SLE patients, 47 anti-RBP antibody positive (RBP+), and 13 anti-RBP antibody negative (RBP−), and 56 EA SLE patients, 21 RBP+ and 24 RBP− along with 25 AA and 8 EA controls was purified using Qiagen RNeasy kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>cDNA was synthesized from total mRNA, and qPCR was used to measure relative transcript expression using SYBR Green dye on an ABI 7900HT thermal cycler. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>For each ancestry, the anti-RBP antibody status was used as a dichotomous variable, and each subgroup was compared to respective controls from the same ancestral background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Following normalization, the mean microarray gene expression values along with standard deviations were calculated for each subgroup and used to calculate the fold changes between subjects and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Values were compared between the groups using the two-tailed Student’s unpaired t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Similar comparisons were made with the qPCR data, but this time, all group results were expressed in medians and compared using Mann–Whitney tests as they did not follow Gaussian distributions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For both microarray and qPCR analyses, P values less than 0.05 were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-5"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Canonical pathway analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>From the microarray data, the differentially expressed genes with a cutoff P value of 0.05 along with their respective fold changes were analyzed further through Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (IPA) (Ingenuity® Systems, www.ingenuity.com) to compare the top canonical pathways amongst the sample groups (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The IPA canonical pathway analysis identified the pathways from the IPA Knowledge Base that were most significant to the data set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The significance of the association between the data set and the canonical pathway was measured in two ways: (1) A ratio of the number of molecules from the data set that map to the pathway divided by the total number of molecules that map to the canonical pathway was displayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>(2) Fisher’s exact test was used to calculate a P value determining the probability that the association between the genes in the dataset and the canonical pathway was explained by chance alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3-6"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Demographics and presence of ANA and anti-dsDNA antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The average age of all subjects included in the microarray portion of the study was 43.5 ± 10.6 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>When the subjects and controls were divided into subgroups according to ancestry and the presence of anti-RBP antibodies (Table 1), there was no statistical difference in age amongst the subgroups including controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>There was lower prevalence in anti-dsDNA antibodies in RBP− AA patients (77% of RBP+ vs. 31% of RBP− had anti-dsDNA antibodies, P = 0.005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In EA subjects, this difference was much less pronounced, and was not statistically significant (66% of RBP+ vs. 54% of RBP− had anti-dsDNA antibodies, P = 0.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>This is in concordance with our previous large-scale analyses in SLE, in which we have also found that anti-RBP and anti-dsDNA antibodies are more correlated in AA as compared to EA SLE patients (40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>All subjects were female and all tested positive for ANA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-7"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>IFN-related canonical pathway activation in AA vs. EA SLE patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Top 10 canonical pathways from each subgroup are shown in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Many immune system associated pathways were associated with the cases, and similar to previous studies, type I IFN-related pathways were the most differentially expressed when comparing cases vs. controls except in RBP− AA group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>We examined in greater detail the six canonical pathways which were type I IFN-related across patients from the two different ancestral backgrounds studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 3, the microarray analysis of all SLE cases vs. controls demonstrated all six IFN-related canonical pathways significantly involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The same pattern was also observed for all EA cases vs. controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>However, to our surprise, the associations between the IFN-related canonical pathways and AA SLE cases were not as strong as only three out of six pathways were found to be significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This is despite that fact that high circulating levels of type I IFN are more common in AA SLE patients (40). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Top 10 canonical pathways from each subgroup vs. matching controls through IPA from microarray data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>All cases </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>All EA </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>All AA </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>EA RBP+ </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>EA RBP− </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>AA RBP+ </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>AA RBP− </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>EIF2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>EIF2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Antigen presentation pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>EIF2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Regulation of IL-2 expression in activated and anergic T lymphocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Antigen presentation pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>OX40 signaling pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Regulation of eIF4 and p70S6K signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Glucocorticoid receptor signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Antigen presentation pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Role of pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Angiopoietin signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Antigen presentation pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Autoimmune thyroid disease signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>mTOR signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>CD28 signaling in T helper cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Retinoic acid mediated apoptosis signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Regulation of eIF4 and p70S6K signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Role of pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Allograft rejection signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>T cell receptor signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>IL-12 signaling and production in macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Hypoxia signaling in the cardiovascular system </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>IL-15 production </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Glycosphingolipid biosynthesis - globoseries </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>mTOR signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Graft-vs.-host disease signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Role of RIG1-like receptors in antiviral innate immunity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Retinoic acid mediated apoptosis signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Graft-vs.-host disease signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Biosynthesis of steroids </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Role of pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Dendritic cell maturation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>mTOR signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Role of RIG1-like receptors in antiviral innate immunity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxic T lymphocyte-mediated apoptosis of target cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Colorectal cancer metastasis signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>April mediated signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>TNFR2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>IL-15 production </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Hereditary breast cancer signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Communication between innate and adaptive immune cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Crosstalk between dendritic cells and natural killer cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>TNFR2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Reelin signaling in neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Production of nitric oxide and reactive oxygen species in macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Autoimmune thyroid disease signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Role of PI3K/AKT signaling in the pathogenesis of influenza </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Dendritic Cell maturation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Type I diabetes mellitus signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>IL-8 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Glycosphingolipid biosynthesis – neolactoseries </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>IL-15 production </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Communication between innate and adaptive immune cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>TNFR2 signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Starch and sucrose metabolism </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Dendritic cell maturation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>P2Y purigenic receptor signaling pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Mitotic roles of polo-like kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>IPA, ingenuity pathway analysis; EA, European-American; AA, African-American; RBP+, anti-RNA-binding-protein (RBP) antibody positive; RBP−, RBP antibody negative; eIF2, eukaryotic initiation factor 2; IRF, interferon-regulatory factor; mTOR, mammalian target of rapamycin; TNFR2, tumor necrosis factor receptor 2; eIF4, eukaryotic initiation factor 4; RIG1, retinoic acid-inducible gene 1; PI3K, phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase; OX40 = CD134. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>P values for IPA IFN-related canonical pathways from microarray data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>All SLE cases (n = 33) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>EA SLE cases (n = 16) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>AA SLE cases (n = 17) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>1.53 × 10−10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>6.55 × 10−12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>0.29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>6.14 × 10−5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>2.74 × 10−5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>8.46 × 10−5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Role of RIG1-like receptors in antiviral innate immunity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>1.63 × 10−4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>5.85 × 10−7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>0.044 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Role of PKR in interferon induction and antiviral response </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>0.020 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>0.038 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>0.091 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Role of pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>0.0097 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>0.0064 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>0.0011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Communication between innate and adaptive immune cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>0.0098 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>0.0013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Not listed </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>IPA, ingenuity pathway analysis; IFN, interferon; SLE, systemic lupus erythematosus; EA, European-American; AA, African-American; IRF, interferon-regulatory factor; RIG1, retinoic acid-inducible gene 1; and PKR, protein kinase R. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="S3-8"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>IFN-related canonical pathway activation is not seen in RBP− AA patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>To explore this further, we looked at the associations between IFN-related canonical pathways within SLE patient subgroups stratified by both ancestry and the presence or absence of anti-RBP antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 4, all six type I IFN-related pathways were activated in both AA and EA RBP+ patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The key pathway difference was found between AA and EA patients who were RBP−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>RBP− EA patients demonstrated activation of all six IFN-related canonical pathways, whereas not a single type I IFN pathway was significantly involved in the RBP− AA patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>P values from IPA IFN-related canonical pathways from microarray data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>EA RBP+ </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>EA RBP− </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>AA RBP+ </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>AA RBP− </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Interferon signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>5.8 × 10−11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>10.6 × 10−5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>1.3 × 10−7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>0.063 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Activation of IRF by cytosolic pattern recognition receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>1.1 × 10−6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>0.016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>2.86 × 10−8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Role of RIG1-like receptors in antiviral innate immunity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2.0 × 10−5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>0.030 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>0.0014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Not listed </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Role of PKR in interferon induction and antiviral response </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>0.0073 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>0.042 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>9.0 × 10−4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Not listed </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Role of pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>1.8 × 10−4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>0.028 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>5.8 × 10−4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>0.31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Communication between innate and adaptive immune cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>0.0043 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>0.0064 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>0.023 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Not listed </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>IPA, ingenuity pathway analysis; IFN, interferon; EA, European–American; AA, African-American; RBP+, anti-RNA-binding-protein (RBP) antibody positive; RBP−, RBP antibody negative; IRF, interferon-regulatory factor; RIG1, retinoic acid-inducible gene 1; and PKR, protein kinase R. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="S3-9"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>IFN-induced gene expression pathway diagrams in AA vs. EA patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>In Figure 1, we show pathway diagrams generated in IPA software of the type I and type II IFN pathways, with genes that were up-regulated in cases vs. controls shaded red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>It is striking that none of the genes illustrated downstream of the type I and type II IFN receptors are up-regulated in the RBP− AA patients, while in the RBP− EA patients, many IFN-induced genes are over-expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>It is also interesting that STAT1 over-expression is observed in the RBP+ subjects regardless of ancestral background, and this is not observed in the RBP− patients from either ancestral background. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Pathway diagram illustrating the type I and type II IFN pathways in SLE patient subsets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Genes which are up-regulated are shaded red, with increasingly dark red shading indicating a greater degree of over-expression in cases as compared to controls of the same ancestral background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>AA, African-American; EA, European-American; RBP+, anti-RNA-binding-protein (RBP) antibody positive; and RBP−, RBP antibody negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Pictures generated using Ingenuity Pathway Analysis software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-04-00309-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="S3-10"><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Replication study confirms the dependence of IFN-induced gene expression upon presence of anti-RBP antibodies in AA patients, but not EA patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Three IFIGs (IFIT1, MX1, and PKR) were selected for qPCR analysis to replicate the microarray observation with regards to the association between anti-RBP antibodies and IFN-related gene expression across different ancestral backgrounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>These genes were quantified in whole blood mRNA from an independent cohort of 116 SLE patients and 33 controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 2, the pattern observed mirrors the microarray data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>All three genes were up-regulated in both EA and AA RBP+ patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>In the RBP− patients, there is essentially no increase in IFN-induced gene expression in AA patients, while the expression of these genes, in particular PKR, is increased in the RBP− EA SLE patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Because anti-dsDNA antibodies have been associated with high IFN-α (25, 26), it is important to determine whether anti-dsDNA antibodies are contributing to the induction of IFN-induced gene expression we observe in our RBP− EA patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>As noted above, the RBP− EA subjects were more likely to have anti-dsDNA antibodies than the RBP− AA subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>When we looked at the RBP negative patients in the qPCR replication cohorts with regard to presence or absence of anti-dsDNA antibodies, there was no significant difference in IFIT1, MX1, or PKR over-expression in the AA subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>In RBP− EA patients, however, over-expression of IFN-induced genes (IFIT1 and PKR) was observed in the anti-dsDNA antibody positive patients but not in the anti-dsDNA antibody negative group (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Thus, in RBP− EA subjects, the anti-dsDNA antibody status did have an effect on expression of IFIGs, and thus anti-dsDNA antibodies are contributing to the IFN-induced gene expression in this group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, anti-dsDNA antibodies had no impact upon IFN-induced gene expression in the RBP− AA group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>This was somewhat unexpected and reinforces the idea of RBP antibody dependence in the AA ancestral background. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Type I IFN-induced gene expression in SLE patient subgroups and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Expression of three genes (IFIT1, MX1, and PKR) are shown in both patients with anti-RNA-binding protein antibodies (RBP+), and those who lack those antibodies (RBP−). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Central tendency shown is a median, with error bars representing the interquartile range. P values generated by Mann–Whitney U test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-04-00309-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Type I IFN-induced gene expression in RBP–SLE patient subgroups and controls in regards to of anti-dsDNA antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Expression of three genes (IFIT1, MX1, and PKR) are shown in both patients with anti-dsDNA antibodies (DNA+), and those who lack those antibodies (DNA−). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Central tendency shown is a median, with error bars representing the interquartile range. P values generated by Mann–Whitney U test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-04-00309-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this was the first study to show differential gene expression patterns in various subgroups of SLE patients stratified by ancestral background and presence or absence of anti-RBP antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Through microarray whole genome expression with pathway analysis followed by independent qPCR validation, we demonstrated that activation of IFN-related pathways depended on presence of anti-RBP antibodies in AA patients, but not in EA patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The results also support the model suggested by our previous study in which African ancestry increases the likelihood of SLE-associated autoantibody formation, leading to higher IFN-α activity (41). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we observe a similar dependence of IFN-induced gene expression upon anti-RBP antibodies in AA patients, and this is not shared with the EA patients, and this novel observation should be confirmed in larger cohorts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Autoantibody immune complexes present in SLE patients have been implicated as major endogenous IFN-inducers, likely via the endosomal TLR and IFN regulatory factor pathways (43–45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Our data would suggest that the classical activation of IFN-related pathways observed in SLE patients is highly dependent upon anti-RBP antibodies in AA SLE patients, and this dependence is not shared by EA SLE patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The additional IFN-pathway activation observed in EA subjects is partly due to the presence of anti-dsDNA antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 3 there are a number of anti-dsDNA and anti-RBP negative EA patients that show over-expression of IFN-induced genes, while in AA SLE patients lacking RBP antibodies, IFN-induced gene expression resembles the AA control population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>This heterogeneity in the dependence of IFN-related pathways on autoantibody profile may reflect differential activation of the TLR pathway is SLE patients of different ancestral backgrounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Anti-RBP antibodies would be expected to activate the RNA-sensing TLRs, while anti-dsDNA antibody immune complexes would be expected to activate TLR 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Genetic variations in the TLR pathway genes such as IRF5 and IRF7 have been associated with risk of SLE, and with gain of function within the type I IFN pathway (46, 47). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>In our previous study looking at genetic variation at the IRF7/PHRF1 locus, we observed two different high IFN genetic effects in AA subjects, while we saw only one in EA subjects (46). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>This example demonstrates genetic diversity between world populations in the TLR/IRF system, and could support the idea that this pathway may more prominent in AA subjects and help to explain the findings we report here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Additionally, many of the genetic polymorphisms we have discovered that are associated with increased type I IFN in SLE patients differ between ancestral backgrounds (34, 48), and this would also support the idea that the pathway will be more or less prominent in different ancestral backgrounds. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>There were EA SLE patients that had increased expression of IFN-induced genes who did not have either anti-RBP or anti-dsDNA autoantibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that IFN-related pathways may be activated through different mechanisms in this ancestral background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>All patients in our study had ANA, and it may be that other nuclear antigen/autoantibody complexes could have triggered the TLR/RLR system leading to IFN-pathway activation in these subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that other molecules such as HMGB1, which can bind with immune complexes, may be activating an inflammatory cascade in plasmacytoid dendritic cells resulting in activation of IFN pathways (49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that there is an increased sensitivity to IFN signaling or a downstream activator of IFN-induced gene expression in these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>We have observed some SLE patients in previous studies that have high IFN-induced gene activity in their PBMC with essentially normal circulating type I IFN activity from the same sample (50, 51). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>This surprising diversity in IFN-pathway activation between different SLE patient subgroups is relevant to clinical care, as therapeutics directed at IFN or IFN-related pathways are being actively developed (52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>It seems likely that these IFN-pathway targeting therapeutics will be characterized by heterogeneity in treatment response, and our results may suggest some groups that are likely to be better responders that could be predicted without having to run a gene expression chip prior to therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The RBP− AA group is very interesting in this regard, as it seems that this patient group may represent a distinct subset of SLE patients which is not as IFN-dependent as other groups of SLE patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>This may represent a significant difference in disease pathogenesis, which could be important in planning targeted therapies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus is a heterogeneous disease with differences in disease incidence, clinical manifestations, serological findings, and genetic risk factors between ancestral backgrounds (7, 29–32, 36–39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Perhaps it is not very surprising to find heterogeneity in the activation of molecular pathways between ancestral groups, and it seems likely that different pathogenic factors will be relevant in RBP− AA patients as compared to the RBP+ SLE patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>SLE is a complex autoimmune disease, and understanding heterogeneity in the molecular pathogenesis in lupus will be crucial in informing therapeutic and diagnostic strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrates the relevance of careful patient characterization and including patients from more than one ancestral background in biological studies of SLE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Author’s Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Kichul Ko participated in the design of the study and its coordination, screened for cases and controls, lead the statistical analysis, and drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Yelena Koldobskaya helped screen for cases and controls, and collected microarray data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Elizabeth Rosenzweig helped generate qPCR data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Timothy B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Niewold was the senior scientist overseeing the study and helped with study design, statistical analysis, and manuscript drafting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Kichul Ko – Arthritis Foundation Clinical to Research Transition Award, Yelena Koldobskaya – none, Elizabeth Rosenzweig – none, Timothy B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Niewold – Research grants from the NIH (R01 AR060861, K08 AI083790, Clinical Research Loan Repayment AI071651, CTSA Core Subsidy Grant, and CTSA Pilot Grants from UL1 RR024999), and Lupus Research Institute Novel Research Grant. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec id="S8"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AA, African-American; ANA, antinuclear antibodies; Anti-dsDNA, anti-double-stranded DNA; Anti-RBP, anti-RNA-binding protein; Anti-RNP, anti-ribonucleoprotein; Anti-Sm, anti-smith; EA, European-American; HA, Hispanic-American; IFIGs, IFN-inducible genes; IFN, interferon; IPA, ingenuity pathway analysis; PRRs, pattern recognition receptors; qPCR, quantitative real-time PCR; RBP+, anti-RBP antibody positive; RBP−, anti-RBP antibody negative; RLRs, RIG-I like receptors; SLE, systemic lupus erythematosus; TLR, toll-like receptor; UCMC, University of Chicago Medical Center.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>1HochbergMCUpdating the American College of Rheumatology revised criteria for the classification of systemic lupus erythematosus. Arthritis Rheum (1997) 40:172510.1002/art.17804009289324032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>2Alarcon-SegoviaDAlarcon-RiquelmeMECardielMHCaeiroFMassardoLVillaAR Familial aggregation of systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, and other autoimmune diseases in 1,177 lupus patients from the GLADEL cohort. Arthritis Rheum (2005) 52:1138–4710.1002/art.20999<?supplied-pmid 15818688?>15818688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>3RhodesBVyseTJ The genetics of SLE: an update in the light of genome-wide association studies. Rheumatology (Oxford) (2008) 47:160310.1093/rheumatology/ken247<?supplied-pmid 18611920?>18611920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>4TsokosGC Systemic lupus erythematosus. N Engl J Med (2011) 365:2110–2110.1056/NEJMra110035922129255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>5WeckerleCENiewoldTB The unexplained female predominance of systemic lupus erythematosus: clues from genetic and cytokine studies. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol (2011) 40:42–910.1007/s12016-009-8192-4<?supplied-pmid 20063186?>20063186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>6LiuZDavidsonA Taming lupus-a new understanding of pathogenesis is leading to clinical advances. Nat Med (2012) 18:871–8210.1038/nm.2752<?supplied-pmid 22674006?>22674006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>7DengYTsaoBP Genetic susceptibility to systemic lupus erythematosus in the genomic era. Nat Rev Rheumatol (2010) 6:683–9210.1038/nrrheum.2010.176<?supplied-pmid 21060334?>21060334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>8MandelMAchironA Gene expression studies in systemic lupus erythematosus. Lupus (2006) 15:45110.1191/0961203306lu2332oa16898181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>9KoikeT The new era of autoimmune disease research. Arthritis Res Ther (2011) 13:11310.1186/ar3335<?supplied-pmid 21639950?>21639950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>10BaechlerECBatliwallaFMKarypisGGaffneyPMOrtmannWAEspeKJ Interferon-inducible gene expression signature in peripheral blood cells of patients with severe lupus. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (2003) 100:2610–510.1073/pnas.0337679100<?supplied-pmid 12604793?>12604793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>11BennettLPaluckaAKArceECantrellVBorvakJBanchereauJ Interferon and granulopoiesis signatures in systemic lupus erythematosus blood. J Exp Med (2003) 197:711–2310.1084/jem.20021553<?supplied-pmid 12642603?>12642603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>12HanGMChenSLShenNYeSBaoCDGuYY Analysis of gene expression profiles in human systemic lupus erythematosus using oligonucleotide microarray. Genes Immun (2003) 4:17710.1038/sj.gene.6363966<?supplied-pmid 12700592?>12700592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>13LiQZZhouJLianYZhangBBranchVKCarr-JohnsonF Interferon signature gene expression is correlated with autoantibody profiles in patients with incomplete lupus syndromes. Clin Exp Immunol (2010) 159:281–9110.1111/j.1365-2249.2009.04057.x<?supplied-pmid 19968664?>19968664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>14LeeHMSuginoHAokiCNishimotoN Underexpression of mitochondrial-DNA encoded ATP synthesis-related genes and DNA repair genes in systemic lupus erythematosus. Arthritis Res Ther (2011) 13:R6310.1186/ar3317<?supplied-pmid 21496236?>21496236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>15MaasKChanSParkerJSlaterAMooreJOlsenN Cutting edge: molecular portrait of human autoimmune disease. J Immunol (2002) 169:5<?supplied-pmid 12077221?>12077221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>16MandelMGurevichMPauznerRKaminskiNAchironA Autoimmunity gene expression portrait: specific signature that intersects or differentiates between multiple sclerosis and systemic lupus erythematosus. Clin Exp Immunol (2004) 138:16410.1111/j.1365-2249.2004.02587.x<?supplied-pmid 15373920?>15373920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>17RusVChenHZernetkinaVMagderLSMathaiSHochbergMC Gene expression profiling in peripheral blood mononuclear cells from lupus patients with active and inactive disease. Clin Immunol (2004) 112:23110.1016/j.clim.2004.06.005<?supplied-pmid 15308115?>15308115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>18NiewoldTB Interferon alpha as a primary pathogenic factor in human lupus. J Interferon Cytokine Res (2011) 31:887–9210.1089/jir.2011.0071<?supplied-pmid 21923413?>21923413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>19BronsonPGChaivorapolCOrtmannWBehrensTWGrahamRR The genetics of type I interferon in systemic lupus erythematosus. Curr Opin Immunol (2012) 24:530–710.1016/j.coi.2012.07.008<?supplied-pmid 22889593?>22889593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>20BlancoPPaluckaAKGillMPascualVBanchereauJ Induction of dendritic cell differentiation by IFN-alpha in systemic lupus erythematosus. Science (2001) 294:1540–310.1126/science.1064890<?supplied-pmid 11711679?>11711679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>21NiewoldTBClarkDNSalloumRPooleBD Interferon alpha in systemic lupus erythematosus. J Biomed Biotechnol (2010) 2010:94836410.1155/2010/948364<?supplied-pmid 20652065?>20652065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>22NiewoldTBHuaJLehmanTJHarleyJBCrowMK High serum IFN-alpha activity is a heritable risk factor for systemic lupus erythematosus. Genes Immun (2007) 8:49210.1038/sj.gene.6364408<?supplied-pmid 17581626?>17581626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>23NiewoldTBAdlerJEGlennSBLehmanTJHarleyJBCrowMK Age- and sex-related patterns of serum interferon-alpha activity in lupus families. Arthritis Rheum (2008) 58:2113–910.1002/art.23619<?supplied-pmid 18576315?>18576315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>24NiewoldTB Interferon alpha-induced lupus: proof of principle. J Clin Rheumatol (2008) 14:131–210.1097/RHU.0b013e318177627d18525429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>25NikpourMDempseyAAUrowitzMBGladmanDDBarnesDA Association of a gene expression profile from whole blood with disease activity in systemic lupus erythaematosus. Ann Rheum Dis (2008) 67:106910.1136/ard.2007.074765<?supplied-pmid 18063674?>18063674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>26KirouKALeeCGeorgeSLoucaKPetersonMGCrowMK Activation of the interferon-alpha pathway identifies a subgroup of systemic lupus erythematosus patients with distinct serologic features and active disease. Arthritis Rheum (2005) 52:1491–50310.1002/art.21031<?supplied-pmid 15880830?>15880830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>27Landolt-MarticorenaCBonventiGLubovichAFergusonCUnnithanTSuJ Lack of association between the interferon-alpha signature and longitudinal changes in disease activity in systemic lupus erythematosus. Ann Rheum Dis (2009) 68:1440–610.1136/ard.2008.093146<?supplied-pmid 18772188?>18772188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>28PetriMSinghSTesfasyoneHDedrickRFryKLalP Longitudinal expression of type I interferon responsive genes in systemic lupus erythematosus. Lupus (2009) 18:980–910.1177/0961203309105529<?supplied-pmid 19762399?>19762399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>29HopkinsonNDDohertyMPowellRJ Clinical features and race-specific incidence/prevalence rates of systemic lupus erythematosus in a geographically complete cohort of patients. Ann Rheum Dis (1994) 53:67510.1136/ard.53.10.675<?supplied-pmid 7979581?>7979581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>30MolinaJFMolinaJGarciaCGharaviAEWilsonWAEspinozaLR Ethnic differences in the clinical expression of systemic lupus erythematosus: a comparative study between African-Americans and Latin Americans. Lupus (1997) 6:6310.1177/096120339700600109<?supplied-pmid 9116721?>9116721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>31AlarconGSFriedmanAWStraatonKVMouldsJMLisseJBastianHM Systemic lupus erythematosus in three ethnic groups: III. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>A comparison of characteristics early in the natural history of the LUMINA cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>LUpus in MInority populations: NAture vs. Nurture. Lupus (1999) 8:197–20910.1191/096120399678847704<?supplied-pmid 10342712?>10342712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>32CooperGSParksCGTreadwellELSt ClairEWGilkesonGSCohenPL Differences by race, sex and age in the clinical and immunologic features of recently diagnosed systemic lupus erythematosus patients in the southeastern United States. Lupus (2002) 11:161–710.1191/0961203302lu161oa<?supplied-pmid 11999880?>11999880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>33RamosPSKellyJAGray-McGuireCBrunerGRLeiranANMeyerCM Familial aggregation and linkage analysis of autoantibody traits in pedigrees multiplex for systemic lupus erythematosus. Genes Immun (2006) 7:417–3210.1038/sj.gene.6364316<?supplied-pmid 16775618?>16775618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>34KariukiSNFranekBSKumarAAArringtonJMikolaitisRAUtsetTO Trait-stratified genome-wide association study identifies novel and diverse genetic associations with serologic and cytokine phenotypes in systemic lupus erythematosus. Arthritis Res Ther (2010) 12:R15110.1186/ar3101<?supplied-pmid 20659327?>20659327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>35BastianHMRosemanJMMcGwinGJrAlarconGSFriedmanAWFesslerBJ Systemic lupus erythematosus in three ethnic groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>XII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Risk factors for lupus nephritis after diagnosis. Lupus (2002) 11:15210.1191/0961203302lu158oa<?supplied-pmid 12004788?>12004788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>36SanchezEComeauMEFreedmanBIKellyJAKaufmanKMLangefeldCD Identification of novel genetic susceptibility loci in African American lupus patients in a candidate gene association study. Arthritis Rheum (2011) 63:3493–50110.1002/art.30563<?supplied-pmid 21792837?>21792837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>37PothlichetJNiewoldTBVitourDSolhonneBCrowMKSi-TaharM A loss-of-function variant of the antiviral molecule MAVS is associated with a subset of systemic lupus patients. EMBO Mol Med (2011) 3:142–5210.1002/emmm.201000120<?supplied-pmid 21268286?>21268286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>38LodolceJPKolodziejLERheeLKariukiSNFranekBSMcGrealNM African-derived genetic polymorphisms in TNFAIP3 mediate risk for autoimmunity. J Immunol (2010) 184:7001–910.4049/jimmunol.1000324<?supplied-pmid 20483768?>20483768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>39HarleyITWNiewoldTBStormontRMKaufmanKMGlennSBFranekBS The role of genetic variation near interferon-kappa in systemic lupus erythematosus. J Biomed Biotechnol (2010) 2010:70682510.1155/2010/706825<?supplied-pmid 20706608?>20706608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>40WeckerleCEFranekBSKellyJAKumabeMMikolaitisRAGreenSL Network analysis of associations between serum interferon-alpha activity, autoantibodies, and clinical features in systemic lupus erythematosus. Arthritis Rheum (2011) 63:1044–5310.1002/art.30187<?supplied-pmid 21162028?>21162028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>41KoKFranekBSMarionMKaufmanKMLangefeldCDHarleyJB Genetic ancestry, serum interferon-alpha activity, and autoantibodies in systemic lupus erythematosus. J Rheumatol (2012) 39:1238–4010.3899/jrheum.11146722505704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>42TanEMCohenASFriesJFMasiATMcShaneDJRothfieldNF The 1982 revised criteria for the classification of systemic lupus erythematosus. Arthritis Rheum (1982) 25:127110.1002/art.1780251101<?supplied-pmid 7138600?>7138600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>43ChamCMKoKNiewoldTB Interferon regulatory factor 5 in the pathogenesis of systemic lupus erythematosus. Clin Dev Immunol (2012) 2012:78043610.1155/2012/780436<?supplied-pmid 23251221?>23251221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>44LovgrenTElorantaMLBaveUAlmGVRonnblomL Induction of interferon-alpha production in plasmacytoid dendritic cells by immune complexes containing nucleic acid released by necrotic or late apoptotic cells and lupus IgG. Arthritis Rheum (2004) 50:186110.1002/art.20254<?supplied-pmid 15188363?>15188363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>45LovgrenTElorantaMLKastnerBWahren-HerleniusMAlmGVRonnblomL Induction of interferon-alpha by immune complexes or liposomes containing systemic lupus erythematosus autoantigen- and Sjogren’s syndrome autoantigen-associated RNA. Arthritis Rheum (2006) 54:191710.1002/art.21893<?supplied-pmid 16729300?>16729300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>46SalloumRFranekBSKariukiSNRheeLMikolaitisRAJollyM Genetic variation at the IRF7/PHRF1 locus is associated with autoantibody profile and serum interferon-alpha activity in lupus patients. Arthritis Rheum (2010) 62:553–6110.1002/art.27182<?supplied-pmid 20112359?>20112359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>47NiewoldTBKellyJAKariukiSNFranekBSKumarAAKaufmanKM IRF5 haplotypes demonstrate diverse serological associations which predict serum interferon alpha activity and explain the majority of the genetic association with systemic lupus erythematosus. Ann Rheum Dis (2012) 71:463–810.1136/annrheumdis-2011-200463<?supplied-pmid 22088620?>22088620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>48KoldobskayaYKoKKumarAAAgikSArringtonJKariukiSN Gene-expression-guided selection of candidate loci and molecular phenotype analyses enhance genetic discovery in systemic lupus erythematosus. Clin Dev Immunol (2012) 2012:68201810.1155/2012/682018<?supplied-pmid 22988468?>22988468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>49WuTMohanC Lupus nephritis – alarmins may sound the alarm? Arthritis Res Ther (2012) 14:129<?supplied-pmid 23270666?>23270666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>50RobinsonTKariukiSNFranekBSKumabeMKumarAABadaraccoM Autoimmune disease risk variant of IFIH1 is associated with increased sensitivity to IFN-alpha and serologic autoimmunity in lupus patients. J Immunol (2011) 187:1298–30310.4049/jimmunol.1100857<?supplied-pmid 21705624?>21705624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>51KariukiSNKirouKAMacDermottEJBarillas-AriasLCrowMKNiewoldTB Cutting edge: autoimmune disease risk variant of STAT4 confers increased sensitivity to IFN-alpha in lupus patients in vivo. J Immunol (2009) 182:34–8<?supplied-pmid 19109131?>19109131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>52LichtmanEIHelfgottSMKriegelMA Emerging therapies for systemic lupus erythematosus – focus on targeting interferon-alpha. Clin Immunol (2012) 143:210–2110.1016/j.clim.2012.03.005<?supplied-pmid 22525889?>22525889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
