<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran J Basic Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran J Basic Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJBMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Iranian Journal of Basic Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2008-3866</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-3874</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Mashhad University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Mashhad, Iran</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3874094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijbms-16-1075</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the Ex Vivo Expansion of UCB-Derived CD34+ in 3D DBM/MBA Scaffolds with USSC as a Feeder Layer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadat Hashemi</surname><given-names>Zahra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forouzandeh Moghadam</surname><given-names>Mahdi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soleimani</surname><given-names>Masoud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Medical Sciences, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Hematology, Faculty of Medical Sciences, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>*Corresponding author: Mahdi Forouzandeh Moghadam. Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Medical Sciences, Tarbiat Modares University, Intersection of Chamran and AL-E-Ahmad Highways, Tehran, Iran. Tel: +98- 912- 3937320; Fax: +98-21-82883861; email: foroz@modares.ac.ir*Corresponding author: Mahdi Forouzandeh Moghadam. Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Medical Sciences, Tarbiat Modares University, Intersection of Chamran and AL-E-Ahmad Highways, Tehran, Iran. Tel: +98- 912- 3937320; Fax: +98-21-82883861; email: foroz@modares.ac.ir</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013: Iranian Journal of Basic Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.
</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Objective(s): Ex vivo expansion of hematopoitic stem cells is an alternative way to increase umbilical cord blood (UCB)-CD34+ cells for bone marrow transplantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>For this purpose demineralized bone matrix (DBM) and mineralized bone allograft (MBA) as two scaffolds based on bone matrix and stem cell niche, were simultaneously used to enhance the effect of human mesenchymal progenitor cells (MPCs) - unrestricted somatic stem cells (USSCs) - as a feeder layer. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods: USSCs were isolated and characterized by morphological and immunological analysis then seeded on both scaffolds as a feeder layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>UCB-CD34+ were isolated by MACS method and were co-culture expanded by USSC in 3D and 2D environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>After 3 weeks expansion, cells were counted and were assessed by karyotype, flow cytometry, clonogenic activity, and long-term culture-initiating cells (LTC-IC). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results: Co-culture expansion in DBM and MBA was 29.22-fold and 27.77-fold, no significant differences in colony and LTC-IC were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Maximum number of colonies belonged to the day 14 with the 73% CFU-GM (Colony Forming Unit- Granulocyte/Macrophage) in contrast to the day 0 which was BFU-E/CFU-E (Burst/Colony Forming Unit-Erythroid). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry indicated that the percentage of CD34+ marker was decreased in USSC co-culture and the highest percentage was observed in simple 2D culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Conclusion: Because of acid extraction in the DBM production process, mineral materials were removed and the protein background that was more flexible was presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Therefore these results suggest that USSC-DBM can be a suitable ex vivo mimicry niche by intensifying of surface/volume ratio and supporting the stem cell differentiation and expansion. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Key Words</title><kwd>DBM</kwd><kwd><italic>Ex vivo</italic> expansion</kwd><kwd>MBA scaffold</kwd><kwd>UCB-CD34+</kwd><kwd>USSC cells</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Currently bone marrow transplantation (BMT) is considered a clinical treatment for many congenital and acquired blood diseases (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>For this treatment hematopoietic progenitor cells (HPCs) are used (2-3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>BMT is performed either as an autologous or an allogeneic transplantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The requirement for hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) in an allogeneic transplantation is 100,000 times greater than for an autologous transplantation (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>There are three sources for prior HSCs: bone marrow, peripheral blood and cord blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Between these 3 sources, cord blood sample is the healthy and safe source of HPC cells for the recipient (5, 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>But on the other hand the total number of cells derived from umbilical cord blood (UCB) was low and this is an important barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In adult recipients, BMT is limited mainly by a low CD34+ cell dose (7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>To overcome this problem, CD34+ expansion is recommended (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Therefore UCB CD34+ cells were ex vivo expanded and then injected into the patient to replicate (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In nature, HSCs are in the microenvironment, or niche, such that they are surrounded by stromal and mesenchymal cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The niche can control the number of stem cells in the body and prevent them from multiplying too. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Interaction between the stem cell and spatial position in the niche establish its equilibrium to proliferation or differentiation (10, 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Stem cells (SCs) cannot survive for long outside the niche (12). Ex vivo-like conditions are composed of a three-dimensional (3D) structure (scaffold) and a feeder layer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Scaffolding features are similar to the extracellular matrix (ECM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>ECM has an important role in physical and chemical signals that are amplified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The 3D environment for HSC niche with helper cells is associated with the basal material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In 3D cultures, cells are grown in a type of in vivo-like morphology and the interaction between them can be done better. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Three dimensional cultures in tissue engineering research by using biochemical materials as the scaffold is rapidly growing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>3D structures in tissue engineering is a multidisciplinary field and is a new and exciting technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>It has the potential to create organs and tissues de novo (13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>It involves the in vitro seeding and attachment of human cells onto the scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>These cells then proliferate, migrate and differentiate into the specific tissue while secreting the extracellular matrix components required for creating the tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>These scaffolds have some major properties: They are biocompatible, injectable and biodegradable (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The 3D structure is used for providing increased surface/volume ratio of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These factors let the scaffold improve the efficiency of the culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Scaffolds are critical, both ex vivo as well as in vivo, to mimic the in vivo milieu and allow cells to influence their own microenvironments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Here, we try to imitate HSC microenvironment or niche in 3D culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>For bone marrow and cartilage, the most commonly used scaffolds are MBA (mineralized bone allograft) and DBM (de-mineralized bone matrix) (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Basically, they are used for repair, clinical surgery, bone allograft and transplantation (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These are based on the bone matrix but the only difference between them is the lack of mineralized materials in DBM by the acid extraction method (17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>As described above, to provide a similar environment in vitro, human cord blood as a novel source of human mesenchymal progenitor cell (MPC) (18) - unrestricted somatic stem cells (USSCs) - was integrated in an attempt to use as a feeder layer (19-21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>USSC cells on the MBA and DBM scaffolds are same as the matrix for UCB-CD34+ cell growth support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The culture system appeared to provide a different microenvironment from the 2D flask culture and might be used as an alternative model for hematopoiesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Our goal then, understands the importance of the presence of the mineral materials for the expansion of HSCs and the extent of the influence of the self-renewal of stem cells in the 3D culture by USSC feeder in contrast to the 2D culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This research aims to increase the number of hematopoietic stem cells with minimal genetic manipulation in three-dimensional culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>However, to reduce the risk of rejection minimal genetic manipulation and techniques should be involved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Generation and expansion of USSCs from fresh UCB </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>UCB samples were collected from full term, normal deliveries according to the approved ethical procedures at Tarbiat Modares University (Iran, Tehran, Shariati Hospital). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>From each donor, informed consent was acquired according to patient sample collection for research studies protocol approved by the ethics committee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>After that USSCs were isolated according to a protocol by Kogler et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To isolate the mononuclear cells (MNCs) and reduce RBC contamination of the upper phase to the minimum level, low-density (less than 1.077 g/ml) cell isolation was performed by Ficoll-Hypaque gradient centrifugation (Pharmacia, Uppsala, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>After 2 washes by phosphate buffered saline (PBS), cells were cultured in T25 flasks and specific media: low-glucose DMEM supplemented with 10-7 M Dexamethasone, 30% FCS, 2 mM ultraglutamine, 100U/ml penicillin G, 100 µg/ml streptomycin, it will be better by used of Myelocult medium containing 12.5% FCS and 12.5% horse serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated at 37°C in 5% CO2 in a fully humidified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>After two weeks the adherent USSC colonies were observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Monoclonal antibodies for immunophenotyping of USSCs </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated antibodies (Abs) were obtained as follows: USSC cells were analyzed by flow cytometry assay to detect their markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>These cells were positive for CD166, CD73, CD105, CD90, CD44, weak positive expression for KDR, and negative for CD117, CD34, CD45 and Cadherin V. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Transdifferentiation of USSCs into adipocytes and osteoblasts </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In order to confirm the source USSCs as the human mesenchymal progenitor cells, and the process of differentiation, we check differentiation potential of USSC cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For osteogenic differentiation, the cultured cells were incubated in osteogenic medium containing DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS, β-glycerol phosphate 10 mM, dexamethasone 10-7M, and ascorbic acid bi-phosphate 50 µg/ml (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The culture media were changed twice a week for 3 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min, washed with PBS and stained with Alizarin-Red solution (in 60% isopropanol) for 10 min, followed by repeated washings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>To induce adipocyte differentiation, USSCs were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS, dexamethasone 250 nM, insulin 66nM, isobutyl-methylxanthine 0.5 mM, and indomethacine 0.2mM for 3 weeks and also for specific staining, cells were fixed and incubated with Oil-Red. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>USSCs were cultured as a feeder layer </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>These isolated cells were cultured on a 48-well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>When the cells reached 80% confluence, their mitotic activity was disabled by Mitomycin-C 10 µg/ml (Sigma) according to its protocol: culture media was removed and cells were incubated by mitomycin-C for 2 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>After incubation time it was washed 2 times by PBS and fresh media was added. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For 3D culture, these cells should seed on the scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>First MBA and DBM slices were cut to the desired size (6 to 8 mm sided cubic pieces) by the sterile scalpel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Then the surfaces of the scaffolds were prepared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To prepare and dispose, they were immersed overnight in the PBS with gelatin 0.1 % which opens the pores like a spongy tissue, ready to work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, nearly 3×106 USSC cells from three T75 culture flasks were removed by the trypsin 0.25% (GIBCO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This number of cells in the DMEM media supplemented by 30% FBS were added to MBA and DBM scaffolds (9 pieces each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>This concentrated cell suspension was rotating for 8 hours during the incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After this time the media was replaced by fresh DMEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This rotation is needed to push the cells into the pores of the scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>After 3 days, this feeder layer can be disabled by Mitomycin-C too. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>These scaffolds were placed in 18 wells of a 48 well plate that were previously coated with a USSC feeder layer (9 wells for DBM and 9 wells for MBA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Scanning  e lectron  m icroscope (SEM) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For SEM imaging, we should choose a process that preserves the structure of freshly killed material in a state that most closely resembles the structure and/or composition of the original living state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>For chemical fixation as the non-coagulative process, we need paraformaldehyde 4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>In this process, first the culture media was removed, and fixed in paraformaldehyde (pH 7) at 4oC for 20 min. the scaffold samples were then dehydrated through a graded ethanol series and ultra-structurally scoped using an electron microscope (Philips). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>HSC isolation by MACS ( m agnetic  a ctivated  c ell  s orting) method </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>MNCs were isolated as described above, and then the CD34+ cells were isolated from this MNC population, according to the manufacturer’s instructions for the CD34 cell isolation kit (Miltenyi Biotech, BergischGladbach, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The cell suspension was adjacent by blocking agent and an antibody labeled with a magnet to one hr at 4°C and dark place. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This antibody was against CD34 marker. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>After this period, samples were washed with EDTA-PBS buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, the suspension was passed through the LS separation columns (Miltenyi Biotech, BergischGladbach, Germany) and eventually with the help of the piston and pressure cells, CD34+ from other cord blood mononuclear cells were separated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>As a result the purity of CD34+ cells ranged from 85 to 95%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Ex vivo expansion of cord blood hematopoietic cells </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Isolated hematopoietic cells were then cultured in StemSpan (Stemcell Technologies #09600) containing stem cell factor (SCF) 100 ng/mL and FMS-like tyrosine kinase-3 100 ng/ml, and 100 ng/mL thrombopoietin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>They were separated and cultured in 48 well plates in four culture conditions: first in 2D culture (without feeder layer and scaffolds) that is simple 2D culture (S2D), second in 2D culture with the USSCs as a feeder layer (F2D), third in 3D culture (DBM scaffold accompanied by USSC feeder layer) and fourth in 3D culture again (MBA scaffold accompanied by USSC feeder layer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In every condition they were cultured in 9 wells of 48-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>These 9 wells were counted within 3 weeks expansion and were done triplicate per week. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Hematopoietic cells were analyzed before and after 3 weeks ex vivo expansion by two-color ﬂow cytometry (PARTEC, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Nearly 105 cells were re-suspended in PBS-5% FBS and were stained with ﬂuorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated anti-human CD34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>These cells were gated with low side scatter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In order to confirm the speciﬁcity of staining, we stained hematopoietic cells by an isotype control with FITC-mouse IgG1 in a replicate manner to ensure the speciﬁcity of staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Acquired data using PARTEC ﬂow cytometer were then analyzed by FloMax software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Clonogenic assay </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In the isolation day and at the end of 1st, 2nd and 3rd weeks for all 3 groups, we prepared three dilutions of expanded cells 500, 1000, 1500 per each culture condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Every cell dilution was mixed with 1 ml of Methocult™ GF+ H4435 methylcellulose medium (Stemcell Technologies #04435) in separate tubes, according to the manufacturer’s instructions, the contents of each tube were plated within separate wells of 6-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Plates were incubated at 37°C with more than 95% humidity and 5% CO2 for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>To maintain culture humidity, one well was filled with sterile water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>USSC cells in the specific media. A) USSC colonies after 2 weeks. B) USSC cells by 80% confluency </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Long-term culture-initiating cells  ( LTC-IC )  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>LTC-IC assay was performed according to the technique described below. Bone marrow cells were cultivated as feeder-layer cells in 96-well plate format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These cells were harvested and incubated with mitomycin-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A day later, the stromal layers were charged with CD34+ cells in the specific Myelocult medium (Stemcell Technologies #05100) containing 10−6M hydrocortisone (Stem Cell Technologies #07904). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>A minimum of 1  l03 up to a maximum of 4 × l03 expanded hematopoietic cells per well were plated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>After 5 weeks of incubation, cells were removed and assay in the CFC assay as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A well is scored as positive if one or more BFU-E, CFU-GM or CFU-GEMM is detected or as negative if no colonies are present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The LTC-IC frequency in the test cell population is calculated from the proportion of negative wells (no CFC present) and the method of maximum likelihood then statistical analysis can be performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Mitotic chromosome preparations for karyotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>After high expansion in cell count, the cells should be checked for chromosome number and banding pattern to determine if they were altered from the normal (expected) pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>For harvesting cells, at first 0.15 ml of 50 µg/ml Colchicine solution was added to each culture tube containing expanded CD34+ cells and followed by incubation at 37°C and centrifuge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Then 2-3 ml of prewarmed 0.075 M KCl solution was added to the cell pellet which after 10 min centrifugation at 500×g, were gently pipeted by fixative solution (3:1 (v/v) methanol/glacial acetic acid) followed by incubation at room temperature and centrifuge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>This step was repeated twice more by applying a small drop of cell suspension onto the surface of a slide and allowing it to spread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Slide was stained by Giemsa solution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Results were expressed as mean ± SD and analyzed by the T test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered to be significant at P&lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Population doubling time of USSCs cells in primary culture up to the 30 passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Average of PDT was 49.48 ± 0.3 hr </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>USSC colonies were observed after 2 weeks of USSC cell culture (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>After each passage these spindle-shaped cells reached complete confluency (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>It didn’t take longer to reach confluency and their morphology didn’t change with each passage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The results related to the PDT (population doubling time) in different passages of the USSCs are shown in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>PDT didn’t change during the experiment periods from primary culture to passage 30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Characterization of USSCs by flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>USSCs in 4th passage were subjected to flow cytometry for the presence or absence of hematopoietic and endothelial markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>USSCs typically expressed the surface antigens CD105, CD44 and CD73 (Figure 3), and showed low level of KDR but were negative for CD34 and CD45, which are the early hematopoietic markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Analysis of cell surface markers by FACS analysis were confirmed these isolated cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Differentiation of USSCs to  osteogenic and adipogenic </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>USSC cultures in adipogenic differentiation medium after 2 weeks, presenting fat vacuoles in the cytoplasm can be appeared by oil red staining (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>For osteogenic inductive medium, appearance of refringent crystals were be observed by Alizarin Red staining (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscope views </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>About 40% of scaffold surface pictures showed porosity. Figure 5 shows the surface of scaffolds without cells as the control, so that very small pores in the scaffold can be seen under a microscope in which these pores are so deeply dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>When the scaffolds were seeded by USSCs as the feeder layer, the empty scaffold is less clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Elongated and spindle-shaped cells covered the surface but few of these surrounded cells entered into the cavities and pores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Cells were more coated on the outer face. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Cell size was about 100 µm and with more magnification each cell could be observed separately as a light band. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>However, with the same zoom level on the control scaffold, only the dark face without the light bands were visible (Figure 5B, E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The effect of USSC and scaffold combination on the expansion of UCB-CD34+ over 3 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Values are expressed as mean ± SD for 3 numbers of experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Fold expansion was calculated based on the cell counts (1000) on day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Total Cells (fold exp.) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Groups </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>1st wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>2nd wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3rd wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>S2D (n=3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>13800±1600(13.8±1.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>53400±3200(53.4±3.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>101900±8000(101.9±8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>F2D (n=3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>28700±3400(28.7±3.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>104300±11000(104.3±11) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>194200±4600(194.2±4.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>MBA (n=3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>40800±4100(40.8±4.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>145500±5800(145.5±5.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>271700±13000(271.7±13.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>DBM (n=3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>44200±1600(44.2±1.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>176700±6400(176.7±6.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>305800±12700(305.8±12.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation: simple 2D culture (S2D), simple 2D culture with feeder (F2D), mineralized bone allograft (MBA), de-mineralized bone matrix (DBM) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Immunophenotypes of USSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>USSC preparations were labeled with the monoclonal Abs specific for the molecule indicated (filled histograms) or isotype controls (open histograms). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>USSC are positive for CD73, CD44 and CD105 but have weak positive expression for KDR </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Isolation and differentiation characteristics of human UCB-derived USSCs. A) The results of Oil Red-O-staining in differentiated adipogenic cells. B) Results of osteogenic differentiation by Alizarin Red-staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Ex vivo expansion of cord blood hematopoietic cells </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>UCB CD34+ cells were seeded at a concentration of 1×103 cells per each well in the 48-well plate in the hematopoietic stem cell expansion medium (StemSpan supplemented by 3 cocktail cytokines: Flt3-L, SCF, TPO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>CD34+ cells in 4 groups were expanded: S2D, F2D, DBM and MBA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>These 4 groups were counted after each week during 3 weeks by triplicate for each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The result is shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In F2D culture, the CD34+ cells were co-cultivated on the USSC-feeder layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>USSCs showed their ability to support the expansion of CD34+ cells over three weeks (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The highest cell count was in 3D culture but DBM was a little more than MBA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The total cell count on the USSC layer in DBM culture increased within the 21-day period, it was 44.2-fold ± 1.6-fold after 7 days, 176.7-fold ± 6.4-fold after 14 days, and 305.8-fold ± 12.7-fold after 21 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>SEM views of scaffold surface in black and white version. A-B) empty MBA without USSC cells. C) MBA with seeded USSC. D-E) empty DBM without USSC cells. F) DBM with seeded USSC </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The effect of USSC presence as the feeder layer on the colony formation of UCB-CD34+ over 3 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>CFC counts were performed from the expanding cultures at days 0, 7, 14, and 21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The results are expressed as mean ± SD for total cells, CFC, BFU-E/CFU-E, CFU-GM, and CFU-mix </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Total cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>CFC /103 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>BFU/CFU-E /103 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>CFU-GM /103 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>CFU-mix /103 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>1000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>30.9±2.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>22.6±0.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>9.5±1.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>2.8±0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>1st week </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>28700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>23.2±1.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>9.4±0.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>12.2±0.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>1.6±0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>40800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>16.0±1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>6.1±0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>7.3±1.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>1.0±0.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>44200 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>16.3±2.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>7.3±0.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>7.9±1.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>1.1±0.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>2nd week </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>104300 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>35.6±1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>8.8±1.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>26.2±0.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>0.6±0.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>145500 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>28.6±2.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>7.1±0.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>20.7±1.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>0.8±0.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>176700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>30.1±3.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>7.9±2.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>21.9±0.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>1.9±0.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>3rd week </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>194200 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>24.4±1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>6.2±0.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>17.1±0.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>1.1±0.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>271700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>22.5±1.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>3.1±0.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>17.9±0.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>1.5±0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>305800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>23.9±1.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>4.7±0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>18.4±1.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>1.0±0.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation: simple 2D culture with feeder (F2D), mineralized bone allograft (MBA), de-mineralized bone matrix (DBM), Colony Forming Count (CFC), Burst Forming Unit/Colony Forming Unit- Erythroid (BFU/CFU-E), Colony Forming Unit- Granulocyte/Macrophage (CFU-GM), Colony Forming Unit- mix (CFU-mix) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>CD34+ cells were enriched by nearly 90 percent (Figure 7) and subsequently after 3 weeks expansion, CD34+ cells were analyzed by FACS method to observe their CD34 marker ratio (Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The global competition indicated that the lowest CD34 marker belonged to the 3D culture (8.6 % and 9.2% respectively for DBM and MBA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>But no significant difference was observed between MBA and DBM in the kind of 3D condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The highest CD34 marker was observed in S2D culture (17.3%) and finally for the F2D group it was 10.5 %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Percent drop in CD34+ cells was greater in the three-dimensional culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>This problem can partly explain the high levels of secreted factors attributed myeloid line distinction, such as GM-CSF, M-CSF, IL-6, IL-11 and SCF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Also the IL-1B factor secretion by both USSC and CD34+ cells strongly enhanced the G-CSF production by USSC cells leading to the differentiation of CD34+ cells into a specific cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This low percentage in contrast to the highest expansion and CD34+ count in 3D condition can be ignored. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>On the first day we charged each group by 1000 cells with 89.57% CD34+ cells or nearly 900 CD34+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>For S2D, we counted 101900 cells by 17.3% or about 17600 CD34+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Therefore fold expansion by flow cytometry was 19.55-fold ± 1.5-fold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Other HSCs expansion evaluation by flow cytometry is shown in Figure 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The most expansion belonged to the DBM group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Colony assay </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Each week, nonadherent hematopoietic cells (CD34+ cells) from the adherent feeder cells were separated and analyzed by CFC to evaluate the progenitor content and CD34+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>As summarized in Table 2 and Figure 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>For total CFC, the highest CFC expansion was observed at day 14: 35.6-fold ± 1.8-fold, 28.6-fold ± 2.0-fold and 30.1-fold ± 3.3-fold for F2D, MBA and DBM, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Similarly, amplification of CFU-GM and BFU-E/CFU-E was highest, whereas CFC was reduced after 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The composition of CFC clearly showed that after 2 weeks about 73% of colonies obtained were CFU-GM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>But on day 0 nearly 73% of colonies were BFU-E/CFU-E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>When total number of cells generated in 3D culture was compared to 2D culture, significantly higher colony counts for 3D were determined at each time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Because these colony counts were in 1000 cells, so that in comparison with total cells in F2D, MBA and DBM the CFC counts were 3713±188, 4161±291 and 5318±583. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>USSCs co-cultivate with UCB-CD34+ over 1 A), 2 B), and 3 C) weeks expansion </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The frequency of long-term culture-initiating cells in different condition during 3 weeks expansion </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Frequency of LTC-IC cells </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Day 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>1 in 8372 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>1st wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>2nd wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>3rd wk </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>S2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>1 in 11634 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>S2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>1 in 14840 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>S2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>1 in 22478 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>1 in 7389 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>1 in 5125 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>F2D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>1 in 11650 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>1 in 7760 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>1 in 6192 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>MBA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>1 in 13289 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>1 in 7554 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>1 in 5992 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>DBM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>1 in 12673 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation: simple 2D culture (S2D), simple 2D culture with feeder (F2D), mineralized bone allograft (MBA), de-mineralized bone matrix (DBM) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>A) enumeration of CD34+ at isolation day was 89.57 percentage. B) CD34+ cells were labeled with FITC-conjugated antibody and B) with IgG1 as the control antibody </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>LTC-IC </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>After 3 weeks co-cultivation of CD34+ cells on the USSC layer (2D and 3D conditions) no significant differentiation between them was observed in contrast to the simple 2D culture where the total number of long-term culture-initiating cells dropped after each week (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The culture by feeder (F2D, MBA and DBM) could make an expansion in 1.13-fold, 1.07-fold and 1.10-fold in the first week and also in 1.63-fold, 1.35-fold and 1.39-fold in the second week in contrast to the day 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>But in the 3rd week this expansion dropped and maintaining of LTC-IC cells reached nearly 0.6-fold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Therefore USSC cells could only preserve the hematopoietic initiating cells just for 2 weeks in the ex vivo condition and make long term hematopoesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Karyotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>For research in genetics and cytogenetics, Karyotyping was developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The G-banded karyotype is useful in the identification of aberrant chromosomes and absent, additional, or aberrant chromosomes, which can include deletions, inversions, reciprocal translocations, duplications, insertions, and Robertsonian chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Figure 11 shows the G banding pattern in normal chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>No aberrations were obtained and did not alter the normal banding pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>The human karyotype contains 22 autosomal pairs and two sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The female karyotypes contain two large X chromosomes (the inactive X may be very darkly stained), whereas the male karyotypes contain one large X chromosome and a small one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Normal karyotype of the expanded CD34+ cells after 21 days in 3D DBM condition by 305.8-fold expansion was obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Chromosome count was 46 as in normal cells and no abnormalities in quantity (aneuploidy) or quality were observed and no fusion between stromal and HSCs occurred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The CD34+ stem cell populations after 3 weeks ex vivo expansion were evaluated by means of flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry assay showed that 18.3 % for S2D A), 11.5 % for F2D B), 8.2 % for MBA C) and 7.6 % for DBM D) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, at first, nutritious feeder layer (mesenchymal stem cells) was used for cell proliferation as the Dexter culture (1977). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>But Miller showed that growth factors can also create a similar environment for expansion (22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The nutrients and growth factors layer, for cell proliferation of SCID/ NOD were used simultaneously (23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>But they also understood that over a long period of time, this environment cannot provide reliable cell (24) and showed that stem cells are sensitive to their microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Here the porous tantalum scaffold (tantalum-coated porous biomaterial (TCPB)), only after a week, showed 1.5 increasing fold compared with the two-dimensional culture (25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>In this regard, the engineering matrices and other polymer or nanomer materials were used (26-31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>The result of these experiments for replication (32-34) or differentiation (35) of stem cells was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Finally it caused better BMT and other hematic transplantations (36-38) or even without entering the clinical stage, biological or synthetic structures were used for stem cell proliferation (39-42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In Tan and colleagues research -2011(43), three-dimensional structure was derived from the bone tissue for stem cell proliferation to achieve 7.5-fold expansion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>In this structure a feeder layer of mesenchymal stem cells was used but scaffolding explanation was not provided so the real significance of this scaffold is the substances that are present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>In other studies, non-mineralized bone matrix was used as scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>With general comparison of previous research, we want to investigate the applicability and effectiveness of simultaneously using the mineralized scaffold with USSCs feeder layer for proliferation of hematopoietic stem cells (15, 17, 44-47). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>The results of our research are also in line with previous studies and showed that proliferation in three-dimensional conditions is better. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Kinetics of ex vivo expansion of CD34+ cells by flow cytometry in different culture conditions after 21 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The results are expressed as mean fold ± SD for S2D, F2D, MBA and DBM.      P-value compare to the S2D for each condition was significant </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g009"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Kinetics of colony formation of CB-CD34+ cells expanded on USSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>CFC counts were performed from the expanding cultures at days 0 A) and 14 B) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g010"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Karyotype of the expanded CD34+ cells after 21 days in 3D condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Chromosome number is 46 like a normal cell and no fusion between stromal and HSCs in cytogenetic term were obtained </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijbms-16-1075-g011"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>b </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>In order to improve efficiency of the tissue and cell culture in tissue engineering, we need to create three-dimensional ex vivo conditions that mimic inside of body (in vivo). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, the cells are cultured on the suitable scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>To achieve this goal, we need to mimic the inside of body which contains co-culture of purpose cells with the stromal cells simultaneously (51, 52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>MNCs cannot form colonies in the culture without supportive environment (53). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>As described above the only difference between DBM and MBA is the lack of mineral in DBM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>We know that bone marrow is composed of a protein matrix and a mineral section necessary for hardness, rigidity and stability that enables the skeleton to resist gravitational and mechanical loading, also has the ability to transfer specific signals to stimulate cell division of stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Features of these two scaffolds are similar to bone tissue and were used for bone tissue engineering (54). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Three-dimensional geometry and topography of these porous scaffolds with the adherent stromal cells (USSCs) could emulate the bone marrow microenvironment and hematopoesis (55, 56). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>For HSCs, sticky stromal cells are considered as the co-culture to increase the density of blood cells (57, 58). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Production of extracellular matrix, hematopoietic cytokine, connection and interaction between molecules could be increased in the small cell area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Therefore DBM and MBA by USSC can be a suitable ex vivo mimicry niche by intensifying surface/volume ratio (59) and supporting the stem cell differentiation and expansion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Finally, the production of nutrient materials, growth factors, hormones, autocrine, paracrine, and exocrine (60) factors will be maximum just in the small location called local concentrations of factors (61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Stromal cells are a source of adhesion molecules and growth factors for supporting stem cell expansion (62). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>USSCs in contrast to the mesenchymal stem cells have the longer telomerase that cause more expansion capacity and self-renewal in these cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>USSC can produce a lot of cytokines such as CSF, LIF (Leukemia Inhibitory Factor), TGF-1β (Transforming Growth Factor-1 beta), VEGF (Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor), GM-CSF, M-CSF, IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, IL-11, IL-12, IL-15, SDF-1α (Stromal Derived Factor-1 alpha) (56). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>When feeder cells are in contact with the environment in three dimensions, the result is increased secretion of factors that can improve the efficiency of the feeder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Therefore focus on three factors increased secretion and this effect is direct contact of the humeral (61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>The scaffold was a 6-8mm sided cube and porosity was 40% so every aspect of the six-way area scaffold was 68.6mm2 {(7×7)+0.4×(7×7)}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>With regard to the sixth aspect, the general area of ​​the scaffold was 411.6mm2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>The well’s diagonal of each 48-well plate was 12mm therefore well area was 113.04 mm2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Finally for MBA and DBM the general surface was 524.64mm2 that was 4.64-fold of S2D. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Stem cells in the body depends on the three-dimensional mode will be simulate to differentiate or prolife state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Their power of proliferation cannot survive for long outside of niche (63). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Niche could control the number of stem cells in the body and prevent them from multiplying too (12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Stem cell expansion out of the niche such as in 2D culture or even in the erythropoesis Dexter culture with abnormal face, or uncontrolled proliferation can lead to aneuploidy and cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>HSCs niche has helper cells with basic materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>This background material or extracellular matrix has a lot of proteins such as fibronectin (64), collagen (65-66) and gelatin (67) that were synthesized for a lot of scaffolds based on them (68). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Acid extraction removes the minerals thus the protein surface of the scaffold (flexible microenvironment) is presented which is familiar for the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Therefore DBM will be so soft, porous and spongy (45) and the rate of cytokine production and ex vivo hematopoiesis-supporting activity of UCB- derived USSC in 3D culture is improved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>This is therefore suggested for better 3D culture results in tissue engineering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>This result shows that multiline age expansion of CD34 derived UCB is feasible in the feeder contact cultures without further addition of cytokines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank Dr Tavakoli in the Iranian Tissue Bank (ITB) for expert technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>This study was performed at the University of Tarbiat Modares and ﬁnancially supported by the Biotechnology Development Council (BDC) and the Graduate Studies Office to whom the authors are thankful for their support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>The results described in this paper were part of a student thesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>1BordignonCStem-cell therapies for blood diseases Nature20064411100111216810247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>2SienaSSchiavoRPedrazzoliPCarlo-StellaCTherapeutic relevance of CD34 cell dose in blood cell transplantation for cancer therapy J Clin Oncol200018136010715309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>3SeghatoleslamMJalaliMNikraveshMRHosseiniMAlamdariDHFazelATherapeutic benefit of intravenous administration of human umbilical cord blood-mononuclear cells following intracerebral hemorrhage in rat Iran J Basic Med Sci20121586023492836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>4EmersonSGEx vivo expansion of hematopoietic precursors, progenitors, and stem cells: the next generation of cellular therapeutics Blood19968730828605320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>5ToLHaylockDSimmonsPJuttnerCThe biology and clinical uses of blood stem cells Blood 19978922339116266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>6BakhtiaryMMarzbanMMehdizadehMJoghataeiMTKhoeiSTondarMCombination of stem cell mobilized by granulocyte-colony stimulating factor and human umbilical cord matrix stem cell: therapy of traumatic brain injury in rats Iran J Basic Med Sci20111432732923492840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>7GaoLChenXZhangXLiuYKongPPengXHuman umbilical cord blood-derived stromal cell, a new resource of feeder layer to expand human umbilical cord blood CD34+ cells in vitro Blood Cells Mol Dis20063632232816500123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>8DelalatBPourfathollahAASoleimaniMMozdaraniHGhaemiSRMovassaghpourAAIsolation and ex vivo expansion of human umbilical cord blood-derived CD34+ stem cells and their cotransplantation with or without mesenchymal stem cells Hematology 20091412513219490756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>9HaiJiang WXinNa DHuiJun DExpansion of hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells Am J Hematol20088392292618839435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>10GolipourZRagerdiKashani IAkbariMohammad HGRMalekFMahmoudiRDifferentiation of adipose-derived stem cells into schwann cell phenotype in comparison with bone marrow stem cells Iran J Basic Med Sci2010137684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>11BaghbanEslaminezhad MNazarianHFalahiFahimeh TLDaneshzadehMEx vivo expansion and differentiation of mesenchymal stem cells from goat bone marrow Iran J Basic Med Sci2009127079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>12SongYSongGStem cell niche and its roles in proliferation and differentiation of stem cells J Biomed Engin200926195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>13SachlosECzernuszkaJMaking tissue engineering scaffolds work Review: the application of solid freeform fabrication technology to the production of tissue engineering scaffolds Eur Cell Mater20035293914562270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>14ChungHJParkTGSurface engineered and drug releasing pre-fabricated scaffolds for tissue engineering Adv Drug Deliv Rev20075924926217482310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>15KastenPLuginbühlRVanGriensven MBarkhausenTKrettekCBohnerMComparison of human bone marrow stromal cells seeded on calcium-deficient hydroxyapatite,[beta]-tricalcium phosphate and demineralized bone matrix Biomaterials2003242593260312726713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>16BehniaHKhojastehASoleimaniMTehranchiAKhoshzabanAKeshelSSecondary repair of alveolar clefts using human mesenchymal stem cells Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod2009108e119615638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>17MauneyJRJaquiéryCVollochVHebererMMartinIKaplanDLIn vitro and in vivo evaluation of differentially demineralized cancellous bone scaffolds combined with human bone marrow stromal cells for tissue engineering Biomaterials2005263173318515603812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>18HalabianRMohammadiMHSalimiMAmaniMRoushandeAMAghaipoorMGenetically engineered mesenchymal stem cells stably expressing Iran J Basic Med Sci132430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>19ThibaultRAScottBaggett LMikosAGKasperFKOsteogenic differentiation of mesenchymal stem cells on pregenerated extracellular matrix scaffolds in the absence of osteogenic cell culture supplements Tissue Engin Part A200916431440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>20LangenbachFNaujoksCKersten-ThielePVBerrKDepprichRAKüblerNROsteogenic differentiation influences stem cell migration out of scaffold-free microspheres Tissue Engin Part A200916759766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>21HashemiSSoleimaniMZargarianSHaddadi-AslVAhmadbeigiNSoudiSIn vitro differentiation of human Ccrd blood-derived unrestricted somatic stem cells into hepatocyte-like cells on poly (Caprolactone) nanofiber scaffolds Cells Tissues Organs200819013514919092233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>22MillerCLEavesCJExpansion in vitro of adult murine hematopoietic stem cells with transplantable lympho-myeloid reconstituting ability Proc Natl Acad Sci1997941364813539391080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>23UedaTTsujiKYoshinoHEbiharaYYagasakiHHisakawaHExpansion of human NOD/SCID-repopulating cells by stem cell factor, Flk2/Flt3 ligand, thrombopoietin, IL-6, and soluble IL-6 receptor J Clin Invest20001051013102110749580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>24BhatiaMBonnetDKappUWangJCMurdochBDickJEQuantitative analysis reveals expansion of human hematopoietic repopulating cells after short-term ex vivo culture J Expe Med1997186619624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>25BagleyJRosenzweigMMarksDFPykettMJExtended culture of multipotent hematopoietic progenitors without cytokine augmentation in a novel three-dimensional device Exp Hematol19992749650410089912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>26FrankeKPompeTBornhäuserMWernerCEngineered matrix coatings to modulate the adhesion of CD133&lt; sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; human hematopoietic progenitor cells Biomaterials20072883684317034846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>27SagarBMMRentalaSGopalPSharmaSMukhopadhyayAFibronectin and laminin enhance engraftibility of cultured hematopoietic stem cells Biochem Biophys Res Commun20063501000100517045241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>28JiangX-SChaiCZhangYZhuoR-XMaoH-QLeongKWSurface-immobilization of adhesion peptides on substrate for ex vivo expansion of cryopreserved umbilical cord blood CD34&lt; sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells Biomaterials2006272723273216376984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>29ChuaK-NChaiCLeeP-CTangY-NRamakrishnaSLeongKWSurface-aminated electrospun nanofibers enhance adhesion and expansion of human umbilical cord blood hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells Biomaterials2006276043605116854459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>30FengQChaiCJiangXSLeongKWMaoHQExpansion of engrafting human hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells in three‐dimensional scaffolds with surface‐immobilized fibronectin J Biomed Mater Res Part A200678781791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>31DasHAbdulhameedNJosephMSakthivelRMaoH-QPompiliVJEx vivo nanofiber expansion and genetic modification of human cord blood-derived progenitor/stem cells enhances vasculogenesis Cell Transplant20091830519558779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>32SeongJMKimB-CParkJ-HKwonIKMantalarisAHwangY-SStem cells in bone tissue engineering Biomed Mater2010506200120924139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>33YildirimSBoehmlerAKanzLMöhleRExpansion of cord blood CD34&amp;plus; hematopoietic progenitor cells in coculture with autologous umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) is superior to cytokine-supplemented liquid culture Bone Marrow Transplant200536717915895114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>34RobinsonSNgJNiuTYangHMcMannisJKarandishSSuperior ex vivo cord blood expansion following co-culture with bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells Bone Marrow Transplant20063735936616400333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>35NakamuraYHiroyamaTMiharadaKKuritaRRed blood cell production from immortalized progenitor cell line Int J Hematol2011935921184289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>36SchoemansHTheunissenKMaertensJBoogaertsMVerfaillieCWagnerJAdult umbilical cord blood transplantation: a comprehensive review Bone Marrow Transplant200638839316751788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>37DavisCCMartiLCSempowskiGDJeyarajDASzabolcsPInterleukin-7 permits Th1/Tc1 maturation and promotes ex vivo expansion of cord blood T cells: a critical step toward adoptive immunotherapy after cord blood transplantation Cancer Res2010705249525820530666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>38ZhangYChaiCJiangX-STeohS-HLeongKWCo-culture of umbilical cord blood CD34þ cells with human mesenchymal stem cells Tissue Engin20061221612170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>39AggarwalRLuJPompiliVDasHHematopoietic stem cells: transcriptional regulation, ex vivo expansion and clinical application Curr Mol Med2012123422082480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>40ZhengJUmikawaMZhangSHuynhHSilvanyRChenBPEx vivo expanded hematopoietic stem cells overcome the MHC barrier in allogeneic transplantation Cell Stem Cell 2011911913021816363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>41DahlbergADelaneyCBernsteinIDEx vivo expansion of human hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells Blood20111176083609021436068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>42TungSParmarSRobinsonSDeLima MShpallEEx vivo expansion of umbilical cord blood for transplantation Best Pract Res Clin Haematol20102324525720837337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>43TanJLiuTHouLMengWWangYZhiWMaintenance and expansion of hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells in biomimetic osteoblast niche Cytotechnology20106243944820830608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>44GiardinoRNicoliAldini NFiniMTanziMFareSDraghiLBioabsorbable scaffold for in situ bone regeneration Biomed Pharm 200660386392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>45LinHZhaoYSunWChenBZhangJZhaoWThe effect of crosslinking heparin to demineralized bone matrix on mechanical strength and specific binding to human bone morphogenetic protein-2 Biomaterials2008291189119718083224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>46SundarSPendegrassCOddyMBlunnGTendon re-attachment to metal prostheses in an in vivo animal model using demineralised bone matrix J Bone Joint Surg20099112571262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>47ZhaoYLinHZhangJChenBSunWWangXCrosslinked three-dimensional demineralized bone matrix for the adipose-derived stromal cell proliferation and differentiation Tissue Eng Part A200815132118652539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>48ThilaganathanBNicolaidesKHMorganGSubpopulations of CD34-positive haemopoietic progenitors in fetal blood Br J Haematol1994876346367527650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>49SharaBGlukmanERubinsteinPMadrigalACord blood characteristics in stem cell transplantation2000 LondonMartin Dunitz </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>50SoleimaniMMozdaraniHPourfathollahAMortazaviYAlimoghaddamKNikogoftarMA co-culture system for expansion nonenriched cord blood Stem/Progenitor cells Biotechnology20054310315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>51XuJQinHWangXZhouQLuoFHouTRepair of large segmental bone defects using bone marrow stromal cells with demineralized bone matrix Orthop Surg20091344122009779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>52baghabanEslaminezhad MBagheriFZomorodianEMatrigel enhances in vitro bone differentiation of human marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells Iran J Basic Med Sci201013187194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>53HowsJMBradleyBAMarshJCLuftTCoutinhoLTestaNGGrowth of human umbilical-cord blood in longterm haemopoietic cultures Lancet199234073761352013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>54SharmaPCartmellSHajABone Tissue Engineering2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>55KoglerGSenskenSAireyJATrappTMuschenMFeldhahnNA new human somatic stem cell from placental cord blood with intrinsic pluripotent differentiation potential J Exp Med200420012313515263023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>56KoglerGRadkeTFLefortASenskenSFischerJSorgRVCytokine production and hematopoiesis supporting activity of cord blood-derived unrestricted somatic stem cells Exp Hematol20053357358315850835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>57KoglerGSenskenSWernetPComparative generation and characterization of pluripotent unrestricted somatic stem cells with mesenchymal stem cells from human cord blood Exp Hematol2006341589159517046580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>58RastegarTMinaeeMBHabibiRoudkenar MRaghardiKashani IAminiFAbolhasaniFImprovement of expression of α6 and β1 Integrins by the co-culture of adult mouse spermatogonial stem cells with SIM mouse embryonic fibroblast cells (STO) and growth factors Iran J Basic Med Sci20131613413924298380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>59PanoskaltsisNMantalarisAWuJHEngineering a mimicry of bone marrow tissue ex vivo J Biosci Bioeng2005100283516233847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>60MankaniMHKuznetsovSARobeyPGFormation of hematopoietic territories and bone by transplanted human bone marrow stromal cells requires a critical cell density Exp Hematol200735995100417960668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>61CamilleNAbboudAStructure of the marrow and the hematopoitic microenviroment20057th edSingapour Text book of Williams </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>62WinemanJPNishikawaSMuller-SieburgCEMaintenance of high levels of pluripotent hematopoietic stem cells in vitro: effect of stromal cells and c-kit Blood1993813657678513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>63BaghbanEslaminezhad MTalkhabiMZeynaliBEffect of Lithium chloride on proliferation and bone differentiation of rat marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells in culture Iran J Basic Med Sci200811143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>64FengQChaiCJiangXLeongKMaoHExpansion of engrafting human hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells in three dimensional scaffolds with surface immobilized fibronectin J Biomed Mater Res Part A200678781791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>65KassemMKristiansenMAbdallahBMesenchymal stem cells: cell biology and potential use in therapy Basic Clin Pharm Toxicol200495209214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>66PabbruweMEsfandiariEKafienahWTarltonJHollanderAInduction of cartilage integration by a chondrocyte/collagen-scaffold implant Biomaterials2009304277428619539365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>67GuoTZhaoJChangJDingZHongHChenJPorous chitosan-gelatin scaffold containing plasmid DNA encoding transforming growth factor-[beta] 1 for chondrocytes proliferation Biomaterials2006271095110316143394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>68BaghbanEslaminezhad MTaghiyarLMesenchymal stem cell purification from the articular cartilage cell culture Iran J Basic Med Sci200710146153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
