<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Qual Life Outcomes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Qual Life Outcomes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7525</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3584731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7525-11-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23317347</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-11-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="?"><plain>Does quality of life assessment in palliative care look like a complex screening program? </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Catania</surname><given-names>Gianluca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gianluca.catania@istge.it</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>massimo.costantini@istge.it</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Beccaro</surname><given-names>Monica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>monica.beccaro@istge.it</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Bagnasco</surname><given-names>Annamaria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>annamaria.bagnasco@unige.it</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Sasso</surname><given-names>Loredana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>l.sasso@unige.it</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>IRCCS A.O.U. San Martino – IST Istituto Nazionale per la Ricerca sul Cancro, Genoa, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Health Sciences, University of Genoa, Genoa 16132, Italy</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2013 Catania et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Catania et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.hqlo.com/content/11/1/7"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Palliative Care (PC) is an approach that improves the Quality of Life (QoL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>A number of QoL assessment tools have been developed and validated in PC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>It is not clear how QoL should be measured in PC practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>A procedure of QoL assessment in clinical practice can be defined as a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This is a typical complex intervention that should be appropriately developed and described in all its components and assessed for its effectiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study is to define a framework to help researchers to develop and evaluate clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in PC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>A study group of experts in PC and in research methodology was set up to define a framework that would describe the principles of clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in PC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The study group discussed the WHO Population Screening Principles as a possible useful framework. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The new principles had to be developed taking into account the following criteria: 1) specific to PC practice; 2) address a single underlying characteristic; 3) anchored to relevant literature; 4) consistent with the WHO PC definition. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>With regard to contents and the format of the principles, discussions occurred among the study group members through a cognitive process. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>We reviewed each of the WHO Population Screening Principles and adapted them to QoL assessment, taking into account the defined criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>As a result, a new framework, the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care was developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It consisted of 4 sections, for a total of 11 principles. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The WHO Screening Principles framework was used to outline the eleven essential principles to be considered in developing and/or evaluating clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in PC. The QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care identified could represent a methodological and ethical standard to be considered when developing and evaluating a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment in PC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Quality of life</kwd><kwd>Outcome assessment</kwd><kwd>Palliative care</kwd><kwd>Complex intervention</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Quality of life in palliative care </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Palliative Care is an approach that improves the Quality of Life (QoL) of patients and their families facing the problem associated with life-threatening illness, through the prevention and relief of suffering by means of early identification and impeccable assessment and treatment of pain and other problems, physical, psychosocial and spiritual [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>According to the World Health Organization (WHO) definition of health, formulated in 1948, in healthcare systems QoL is related to health and its physical and psychosocial dimensions [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In palliative care, a theoretical concept with a pragmatic approach is the Calman’s gap theory that described QoL as an individual experience conceptualized as the gap between a person‘s life experience and expectations [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>QoL is described as a dynamic, subjective and multidimensional concept including physical, emotional, psychological, social and spiritual dimensions [4-6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Such dimensions affect each other as well as patients’ overall QoL [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The challenge of assessing QoL in palliative care must take into account that QoL is based on the perspectives and priorities of the individual patient [7], where all the subjective dimensions interact with each other [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition, response shift phenomenon needs to be considered when measuring QoL, such phenomenon involves a change in the meaning of patients’ self-evaluation of QoL as a result of a change over time in their internal standards, values and priorities [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Quality of life assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>A number of QoL assessment tools have been developed and validated in palliative care [9] and their use described for research purposes [10], to support clinical practice [11], and as part of the quality programs [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For research purposes, a number of observational studies have described and analysed QoL impairments of palliative care patients in different settings [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Moreover, QoL has also been used as an outcome measure in observational [14], quasi-experimental [15] and experimental studies [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Two systematic reviews [17,18] concluded that QoL assessment is feasible in clinical trials and has the potential of providing valuable outcomes to further support clinical decision-making. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The European PRISMA group developed a research guidance aimed at improving outcome measures for patients and families [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The Institute of Medicine (IOM) identified Comparative Effectiveness Research (CER) in cancer care as a high priority where the ability to measure QoL is central to CER in oncology because survival and disease-free survival do not properly incorporate outcomes that are significant for policy-makers, physicians, and patients [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>QoL assessment in research is supported by detailed study protocols and rigorous guidelines (i.e. Good Clinical Practice) reporting the rationale of QoL assessment, the psychometric characteristics of QoL measures, and the detailed procedures for QoL assessment [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Higginson &amp; Carr [23] recommended QoL assessments in palliative care for purposes other than research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>As part of the quality programs, QoL assessments can be used as a criterion by which services are evaluated, or aimed at improving assessment skills among healthcare professionals or at ensuring that clinical audit focuses on what is important to patients rather than on the technical aspects of quality. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In support to clinical practice, QoL assessments have been proposed to assess variations in individual patients over the disease trajectory and to ensure that the individual plan of care is centered on the patient rather than on the disease [15,16,23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The challenge of quality of life assessment in clinical practice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A procedure of QoL assessment in clinical practice (i.e. a routine procedure and a thorough QoL assessment in palliative care patients) can be defined as a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>According to the definition proposed by the Medical Research Council (MRC) [24], it is a typical complex intervention that should be appropriately developed and described in all its components and assessed for its effectiveness [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A basic prerequisite for starting a process of assessment is to identify the optimal intervention and analyse all its components, and identify mechanisms that lead to improved outcomes and potential barriers to its application in a specific context [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>A theoretical framework for the development-evaluation-implementation process of a complex intervention has been developed [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>This framework has never been applied to a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment in palliative care, and no consensus exists on what should be the essential components of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>A specific framework for developing a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment in palliative care could be a useful guideline that would help stakeholders to better define the intervention in all its components and make it suitable for use as a reference either in practice, research or quality programs purposes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Aim of the study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study is to define a framework to help researchers to develop and evaluate clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In January 2011, a study group of experts in palliative care and in research methodology (one epidemiologist, one research nurse, one palliative care physician and two university nursing professors) was set up to define a framework that would describe the principles of clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The study group’s members came from two different institutions in the north of Italy – a teaching and research hospital and a university - and started working together to support one of the authors (GC) in his doctoral program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>As outlined in the latest MRC framework guidelines and from the standardization perspective, we used here the term “component” according to Hawe’s view [27] where the constant aspects of the intervention are the essential functions and the variable aspects are their form tailored to local conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The study group discussed the WHO Population Screening Principles [28] as a possible useful framework, as both interventions share a number of characteristics: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>• both are complex interventions with a number of interacting components sensitive to features of local contexts that present specific problems in standardizing and implementing the intervention, and in assessing its effectiveness; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>• both interventions are focused on assessment procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The screening is focused on diagnostic tests (i.e. smear test) offered to apparently healthy people for the early detection of a disease or condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The QoL clinical intervention is focused on assessment tools (i.e. the Palliative Outcome Scale – POS [29] offered to patients to identify and prioritise issues in one or more dimensions of QoL; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>• the assumption for both of these interventions is that early detection can positively modify, for screening programs, the natural history of the disease and, for QoL clinical interventions can modify the natural history of impairments or problems; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>• both deal with specific difficulties in defining, developing, documenting, and replicating the intervention and both require the use of qualitative and quantitative methodologies for their evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The framework of reference for developing a screening program in all its components is the WHO Population Screening Principles [28] that identifies and describes ten principles that could be used as a guideline to plan a new screening intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In breast cancer, for instance, such principles have proved to be effective in detecting early-stage disease and reducing overall mortality [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Wilson &amp; Junkner [28] listed the WHO Population Screening Principles at the time when technological advances in medicine made screening a topic of growing importance [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Similarly, patients’ QoL is the core element of healthcare practice in palliative care, in which QoL assessment has been proposed as the intervention aimed at improving practice related to screening for problems, targeting interventions, and monitoring outcomes in palliative care [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>It showed a positive effect of QOL data on physician–patient communication specifically focusing on continuity of information, facilitating rapport and inter-personal communication between patients and healthcare professionals [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>By using the ten WHO Population Screening Principles [28] as a framework, we developed the principles of clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care, as specified in the following procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the study group members met to sharing the proposal of one of the author (MC) to use the WHO Screening Principles as a framework to develop the principles of clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>We all agreed that the principles had to be developed taking into account the following criteria: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>1. specific to the palliative care practice; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2. address a single underlying characteristic; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>3. anchored to relevant literature in the Pubmed database using key words and synonymous related to each single principles (e.g. palliative care, disease trajectory, assessment tool); </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>4. consistent with the WHO palliative care definition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>One of the authors (GC) developed a first draft version of the WHO Screening Principles adapted to QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The format and the contents of the principles were discussed and emended during five meetings guided by one of the author (MC) through a cognitive process [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Such meetings were aimed at getting to an agreed final version of the principles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Consensus was reached when all the study group’s members agreed a unanimous decision to the final version. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>According to the development stage of the MRC framework for complex interventions [24], we assumed that a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment should be based on a number of components that form a coherent structure, and that all such components - standardized by form and functions - linked the interventions to the expected outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In this article, we hypothesized a supporting theory based on the WHO Population Screening Principles [28] that we modified and contextualized to QoL assessment in palliative care practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The WHO Population Screening Principles [28] describe the principles of a “complex intervention” (i.e. the population screening program) for an early identification of a disease or a pre-disease condition in healthy subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care consisted of the following 4 sections, for a total of 11 principles (see Table 1): section one includes three principles related to “the problem” (i.e. the QoL impairment); section two includes two principles dealing with the assessment tool; section three includes one principle focusing on the treatment/intervention; and section four includes five principles dealing with “the clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment”. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Application of WHO screening principles to QoL assessments in palliative care </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>THE WHO SCREENING PRINCIPLES </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>THE QoL ASSESSMENT PRINCIPLES IN PALLIATIVE CARE </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The disease, condition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The problem (the QoL impairment) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The condition should be an important health problem, in terms of prevalence (e.g. breast cancer) or for the serious consequences if not early discovered and treated (e.g. phenylketonuria). </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The problem should be a serious condition for the patient either in terms of prevalence (e.g. pain, depression) and/or distress for the patient (e.g. itch, hiccup) or the result of late detection and management of the problem (e.g. a new or unusual distressing symptom occurred over the disease trajectory). </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>There should be a recognizable latent or early symptomatic stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The problem should be highly unlikely to be reported by all the patients or recognized by the professional if not actively assessed. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The natural history of the condition, including development from latent to declared disease, should be adequately understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The trajectory of the problem should be sufficiently understood to assure a timely assessment to anticipate and appropriately address the problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The diagnostic test </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The assessment tool </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>There should be a suitable test or examination </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A validated, reliable and sensitive-to-change tool for detecting and measuring the problem should be available. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>There should be acceptable for the population </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The tool should be practical, easy to use and questions must not be distressing for the patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The treatment - intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>There should be an accepted treatment for patients with recognized disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>There should be an appropriate treatment/intervention for patients with the recognized problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The screening programme </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>There should be an agreed policy on whom to treat as patients </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>There should be an agreed policy on which a problem (or a problem with a certain degree of impairment) has to be addressed with appropriate treatment or intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Facilities for diagnosis and treatment should be available. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>There should be the possibility to appropriately administer the tool, including professionals trained with the procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The treatment-intervention for patients with QoL impairments should be available, including professionals trained for the treatment-intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The cost of case-finding (including diagnosis and treatment of patient diagnosed) should be economically balanced in relation to possible expenditure on medical care as a whole </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The cost of problem-finding (including all the steps from the administration of the tool until the end of the treatment – intervention delivered) should be economically justified. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Case-finding should be a continuing process and not a “once and for all” project. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>QoL assessment should be a continuing process and not a “once and for all” project. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The original WHO Population Screening Principles [28] are reported in Table 1 and, hereafter, the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care are italicised and described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The Problem (the QoL impairment) (3 principles) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The problem should be a serious condition for the patient either in terms of prevalence (e.g. pain, depression) and/or distress for the patient (e.g. itch, hiccup) or the result of late detection and management of the problem (e.g. a new or unusual distressing symptom occurred over the disease trajectory). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The assumption underlying this principle is that screening and monitoring for patients’ problems allow these to be noticed by the healthcare professionals [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>There is some evidence that when problems are identified, as well as those not necessarily obvious, some or all of them could be addressed by palliative care staff contributing significantly to the improvement of the patients’ QoL [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The problem should be highly unlikely to be reported by all the patients or recognized by the professional if not actively assessed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>This principle is met because using QoL assessment to identify which patients are mostly at risk of developing impairments in QoL dimensions that are primary in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Especially in the case of needs that are either not regularly assessed by staff or not reported by all the patients including spiritual, psychosocial and physical problems such as loneliness, anxiety, dry mouth and pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>As reported by Lunder et al. [35] and LeMay et al. [36] when patients’ needs are not addressed patients may consider ending their lives prematurely. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The trajectory of the problem should be sufficiently understood to assure a timely assessment to anticipate and appropriately address the problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>This principle suggests the need to adequately understand the trajectory of patient-centered outcomes before implementing clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>It is crucial to palliative care recognize the trajectory of the problems influencing the QoL dimensions in palliative care patients [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>For example, being aware of the changing prevalence and severity of the physical, psychological, social, and spiritual needs over the illness trajectory [38,39] is necessary to choose the most appropriate self-report measures of a screening programme and to prevent and address such impaired conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The assessment tool (2 principles) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A validated, reliable and sensitive-to-change tool for detecting and measuring the problem should be available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This principle suggests the need to measure QoL with instruments that can be comfortably used in clinical palliative care practice and that are valid, reliable and have the characteristic to detect over time any changes in the dimension(s) being measured (i.e. responsiveness). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Although there is no agreement on how QoL should be measured [9] a number of literature reviews identified a number of QoL instruments as appropriate for use in palliative care [9,40,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For example, the Palliative care Outcome Scale (POS) [29] is one of the most comprehensive, valid, and reliable QoL instruments applied in palliative care patients with a variety of diagnoses – dementia, chronic heart failure, chronic kidney disease, COPD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>It showed a statistically significant responsiveness to change between scores on admission and over time [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The tool should be practical, easy to use and questions must not be distressing for the patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This principle underscores the importance of having QoL measures that are acceptable for the palliative care population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Acceptability means that the instrument has to be practical, easy to use and not distressful for palliative care patients, especially when the disease is at a very advanced stage . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For example, the Palliative care Outcome Scale (POS) [29] was considered by patients as a valuable and not burdensome communication tool that helped them to identify their individual needs [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The treatment/intervention (1 principle) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>There should be an appropriate treatment/intervention for patients with the recognized problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>This principle is particularly important when developing and implementing a clinical intervention focused on the assessment of QoL in palliative care settings, because it highlights which criteria such intervention should meet, the availability of appropriate treatments, interventions and/or services to treat the recognized problem that is the impaired QoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>For example, an impaired physical dimension is commonly treated with an effective medical treatment and despite symptoms are clustered they are controlled without inducing unacceptable side effects [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Conversely, looking at spirituality, although it is recognized as an essential dimension of quality by the National Consensus Project for Quality Palliative Care [44] and the National Quality Forum (NQF), there is little evidence on what kind of spiritual care interventions effectively address spiritual needs while delivering palliative care [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Such principle focuses primarily on clarifying aspects of palliative care teams decision making that should be evidence based by integrating “the best research evidence with clinical expertise and patient values” [46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment (5 principles) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>There should be an agreed policy in relation to which a problem (or a problem with a certain degree of impairment) has to be addressed with appropriate treatment or intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This principle underlines the importance of defining individualized care plans based on impaired QoL dimensions where interventions are proposed to patients and their families according to the QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Impaired conditions should be discussed with patients and a careful evaluation of the causes should be included and followed up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>As a result of poor QoL scores or when conditions are worse compared to earlier assessments, policies related to dimensions included in the QoL assessment should be considered to ensure special attention and an appropriate treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>As part of a larger clinical intervention aimed at fostering the screening of impaired conditions where early detection and ongoing assessment would make a difference in the intervention and outcome, QoL measurement should trigger a process within policies defining what to do and how (i.e. intervention, treatment, professionals trained in delivering the intervention, service to which the patient refers) according to the patients’ care expectations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>There should be the possibility to appropriately administer the tool, including professionals trained with the procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This principle indicates that palliative care patients should be assessed for their needs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>As palliative care focuses on improving patients’ QoL, resources and facilities (i.e. treatments and services) should be available where patients can find skilled and trained healthcare professionals able to screen and monitor QoL over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The treatment-intervention for patients with QoL impairments should be available, including professionals trained for the treatment-intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>This principle states that patients requiring treatment should be able to obtain it [28] from trained professionals who have the skills to answer to patients needs with appropriate interventions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The cost of problem-finding (including all the steps from the administration of the tool until the end of the treatment – intervention delivered) should be economically justified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This principle suggests that according to the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) [47] a cost-effectiveness analysis of interventions is essential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment to establish whether the improvement in patients outcomes justified the expenditures relative to other choices should be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>As an example, costs could be related to staff time to (1) develop the clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment; (2) administer the QoL measure; (3) train the staff to use the tool; (4) help patients and their families to understand and monitor QoL changes [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in palliative care the decision to implement this type of clinical intervention should not be made on the basis of costs alone, but also considering the ethical issues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Researchers have shown that cost savings are accrued when clinical decision making recognizes patients’ preferences, values and needs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>From an ethical perspective this means that when treatments that no longer produce a benefit for the patient are discontinued, they can improve the patients’ QoL [49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>QoL assessment should be a continuing process and not a “once and for all” project. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This principle addresses the issue that QoL assessment should be made at the baseline and then monitored over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This approach allows to understand how symptoms and suffering develop, and fluctuate during the illness trajectory [50] and recognize patients’ experiences and evaluate the effectiveness of the interventions [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Palliative care aims to help patients and their families have a better QoL by preventing and treating symptoms related to the disease and to the treatment itself, and addressing patients’ psychosocial and spiritual needs [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The QoL assessment in clinical practice is an important part of palliative care resulting in several advantages for patients in terms of: 1) problem identification [37]; 2) facilitating patient decision making; 3) monitoring for changes [23],and 4) facilitating communication [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Although many QoL measures have been developed specifically for palliative care [9], evidence about effective interventions focused on QoL assessment implemented in clinical practice is lacking [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Before undertaking a study for evaluating how an intervention focused on QoL assessment works in everyday practice, it is essential to define the intervention and its components. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In this article, we defined a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment as a complex intervention because its components interact with one other in a system that, by its very nature, is complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>There is a need to identify and then include the key components of the clinical intervention in an coherent evidence-based structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Since clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment and the screening programs shared a number of characteristics, the WHO Screening Principles framework [28] was used to outline the eleven essential principles to be considered in developing and/or evaluating clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the principles identified could represent a methodological and ethical standard to be considered when developing and evaluating a clinical intervention focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care could be a methodological standard because they intended to provide a guidance aimed at developing an organized integrated clinical intervention where all the components along the QoL assessment are planned and interrelated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>A single underlying characteristic of the principles was developed in the attempt to provide a detailed guidance to evaluate each component of the clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care here proposed could also improve clinical practice by considering QoL assessment as a complex intervention and not simply a task where the introduction of the tool in clinical practice is the only important element. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The principles defining the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care may be considered as an ethical standard because they are provided in a way that respects people’s rights with palliative care needs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These principles could ensure that palliative care patients have recognized their right to have poor QoL identified early and followed-up, thus permitting to define appropriate interventions that would maximize benefits and minimize harms and positively influence the quality of patient care delivery and outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We started developing the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care in a way that has not been previously considered, by identifying both the theoretical basis and the key components using the MRC framework approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Although the MRC framework approach here applied gives strength to this development stage and to the next steps, the paucity of strong evidence in including each component in the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care may represent a limit for this first stage, as well as that fact that it has been based only on reflection and expertise of this study group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We reckon we have found some good claims and a new point of view when looking at QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Our findings may contribute to answering the initial question we included in the title of this paper and they could be the starting point for further research aimed at defining a framework to develop and evaluate clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Although this study provides a new insight on clinical interventions focused on QoL assessment in palliative care practice, our findings are based on intuitions, reflections and experiences of the study group members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Further studies are needed to identify the extent to which a broader group of palliative care experts agree on appropriateness and completeness of the principles described in the QoL Assessment Principles in Palliative Care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Thus, these proposed principles could benefit from a consultation through a Delphi process approach for reaching a wider consensus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>QoL: Quality of life; WHO: World health organization; IOM: Institute of medicine; CER: Comparative effectiveness research; MRC: Medical research council; POS: Palliative outcome scale; COPD: Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; NCP: National consensus project; NQF: National quality forum; AHRQ: Agency for healthcare research quality. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The five authors have no conflicts of interest, including specific financial interests and relationships and affiliation relevant to the subject matter or materials discussed in the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>GC, MC and MB contributed to conception and design of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>All the authors of the study discussed the theoretical model and results presented in this article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This paper was primarily written by GC, MC and MB and then revised, discussed, and amended by all the authors that approved the final version of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Giuseppe Aleo, MA (Lecturer of Scientific English, Department of Health Sciences, University of Genoa, Italy) for his English language editing of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec><title>Funding</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This study did not receive any financial support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>World Health Organization (WHO) definition of Palliative CareWorld Health Organization (WHO) definition of Palliative Care2002Geneva: WHO<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/cancer/palliative/definition/en">http://www.who.int/cancer/palliative/definition/en</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>World Health Organization (WHO)World Health Organization Quality of Life Assessment (WHOQOL): Position paper from the world health organizationSoc Sci Med199541140314098560308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>CalmanKCQuality of life in cancer patients: a hypothesisJ Med Ethics19841012412710.1136/jme.10.3.1246334159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>BowlingACarr AJ, Higginson IJ, Robinson PGCurrent state of the art in quality of life assessmentQuality of life20031London: BMJ Books18 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>KaasaSLogeJHDoyle D, Hanks G, Cherny N, Calman KQuality of life in palliative medicine – principles and practiceOxford Textbook of Palliative Medicine20043New York: Oxford University Press196210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>SirgyMJMichalosACFerrissALEasterlinRAPatrickDPavotWThe Quality-of-Life (QOL) Research Movement: Past, Present, and FutureSoc Indicators Res20067634346610.1007/s11205-005-2877-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>StielSPsychDKuesKKrummNRadbruchLElsnerFAssessment of quality of life in patients receiving palliative care: comparison of measurement tools and single item on subjective well-beingJ Palliat Med20111459960610.1089/jpm.2010.047321434826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>SprangersMASchwartzCEIntegrating response shift into health-related quality of life research: A theoretical modelSoc Sci Med1999481507151510.1016/S0277-9536(99)00045-310400253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>AlbersGEchteldMADe VetHCOnwuteaka-PhilipsenBDVan der LindenMHDeliensLEvaluation of quality-of-life measures for use in palliative care: a systematic reviewPalliat Med201024173710.1177/026921630934659319843620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>LipscombJGotayCCSnyderCFPatient-reported outcomes in cancer: a review of recent research and policy initiativesCA Cancer J Clin20075727830010.3322/CA.57.5.27817855485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>GotayCCAssessing cancer-related quality of life across a spectrum of applicationsJ Natl Cancer Inst Monogr20043312613315504923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>LorenzKADySMNaeimAWallingAMSanatiHSmithPShanmanRRothCPAschSMQuality measures for supportive cancer care: the Cancer Quality-ASSIST ProjectJ Pain Symptom Manage20093794396410.1016/j.jpainsymman.2008.05.01819359135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>SchniewindBRoseTWoltmannNWalterJBeckerTDohrmannPKüchlerTKurdowRClinical outcomes and health-related quality of life after thoracoscopic talc pleurodesisJ Palliat Med201215374210.1089/jpm.2011.014922248257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>LeungKKTsaiJSChengSYLiuWJChiuTYWuCHChenCYCan a good death and quality of life be achieved for patients with terminal cancer in a palliative care unit?J Palliat Med2010131433143810.1089/jpm.2010.024021126195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>BornemanTKoczywasMSunVPiperBFSmith-IdellCLaroyaBUmanGFerrellBEffectiveness of a clinical intervention to eliminate barriers to pain and fatigue management in oncologyJ Palliat Med20111419720510.1089/jpm.2010.026821271872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>McMillanSCSmallBJHaleyWEImproving hospice outcomes through systematic assessment: a clinical trialCancer Nurs201134899710.1097/NCC.0b013e3181f70aee20885302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>EfficaceFKemmlerGVignettiMMandelliFMolicaSHolznerBHealth-related quality of life assessment and reported outcomes in leukaemia randomized controlled trials: a systematic review to evaluate the added value in supporting clinical decision makingEur J Cancer2008441497150610.1016/j.ejca.2008.03.01718555682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>MontazeriAQuality of life data as prognostic indicators of survival in cancer patients: an overview of the literature from 1982 to 2008Health Qual Life Outcomes2009710210.1186/1477-7525-7-10220030832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>BauseweinCDavesonBBenaliaHSimonSTHigginsonIJOutcome measure in palliative care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The essentials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Prisma project booklet201124<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eapcnet.eu/Themes/Clinicalcare/Outcomemeasurement/Publicationsdocuments/tabid/1577/ctl/Details/ArticleID/277/mid/2998/Outcome-Measurement-in-Palliative-Care-The-Essentials.aspx">http://www.eapcnet.eu/Themes/Clinicalcare/Outcomemeasurement/Publicationsdocuments/tabid/1577/ctl/Details/ArticleID/277/mid/2998/Outcome-Measurement-in-Palliative-Care-The-Essentials.aspx</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Institute of Medice (IOM)Initial National Priorities for Comparative Effectiveness Research2009<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iom.edu/Reports/2009/ComparativeEffectivenessResearchPriorities.aspx">http://www.iom.edu/Reports/2009/ComparativeEffectivenessResearchPriorities.aspx</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>KilbridgeKLQuality-adjusted life-years, comparative effectiveness in cancer care, and measuring outcomes in the underservedOncology (Williston Park)20102453053620568594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>OsobaDBezjakABrundageMPaterJNational Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials GroupEvaluating health-related quality of life in cancer clinical trials: the national cancer institute of canada clinical trials group experienceValue Health200710Suppl 2S138S14517995472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>HigginsonIJCarrAJMeasuring quality of life: Using quality of life measures in the clinical settingBMJ20013221297130010.1136/bmj.322.7297.129711375237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>CraigPDieppePMacintyreSMitchieSNazarethIPetticrewMDeveloping and evaluating complex interventions: the new Medical Research Council guidanceBMJ2008337a165510.1136/bmj.a165518824488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>GrolRBakerRMossFGrol R, Baker R, Moss FQuality improvement research: the science of change in health careQuality improvement research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Understanding the science of change in health care20041London: BMJ Books3538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>CampbellNCMurrayEDarbyshireJEmeryJFarmerAGriffithsFGuthrieBLesterHWilsonPKinmonthALDesigning and evaluating complex interventions to improve health careBMJ200733445545910.1136/bmj.39108.379965.BE17332585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>HawePShiellARileyTComplex interventions: how "out of control" can a randomised controlled trial be?BMJ20043281561156310.1136/bmj.328.7455.156115217878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>WilsonJMGJungnerGPrinciples and practice of screening for disease1968WHO, Geneva<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/bulletin/volumes86/4/07-050112BP.pdf">http://www.who.int/bulletin/volumes86/4/07-050112BP.pdf</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>HearnJHigginsonIJDevelopment and validation of a core outcome measure for palliative care: the palliative care outcome scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Palliative Care Core Audit Project Advisory GroupQual Health Care1999821922710.1136/qshc.8.4.21910847883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>NelsonHDTyneKNaikABougatsosCChanBKHumphreyLU.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Preventive Services Task Force: Screening for breast cancer: an update for the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Preventive Services Task ForceAnn Intern Med200915172773719920273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>AndermannABlancquaertIBeauchampSDéryVRevisiting Wilson and Jungner in the genomic age: a review of screening criteria over the past 40 yearsBull World Health Organ200886431731910.2471/BLT.07.05011218438522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>VelikovaGKedingAHarleyCCocksKBoothLSmithABWrightPSelbyPJBrownJMPatients report improvements in continuity of care when quality of life assessments are used routinely in oncology practice: secondary outcomes of a randomised controlled trialEur J Cancer2010462381238810.1016/j.ejca.2010.04.03020570138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>MooreABFeldtJAMoore AB, Feldt JAFacilitating Community Decision-MakingFacilitating Community and Decision- Making Groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The Professional Practices in Adult Education and Human Resource Development19931Florida: Krieger Publishing Company </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>StevensAMGwilliamBA’hernRBroadleyKHardyJExperience in the use of the palliative care outcome scaleSupport Care Cancer2005131027103410.1007/s00520-005-0815-615846523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>LunderUFurlanMSimoničASpiritual needs assessments and measurementsCurr Opin Support Palliat Care2011527327821738034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>LeMayKWilsonKGTreatment of existential distress in life threatening illness: a review of manualized interventionsClin Psychol Rev20082847249310.1016/j.cpr.2007.07.01317804130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>DetmarSBMullerMJSchornagelJHWeverLDAaronsonNKHealth-related quality-of-life assessments and patient-physician communication: a randomized controlled trialJAMA20022883027303410.1001/jama.288.23.302712479768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>MurraySAKendallMBoydKSheikhAIllness trajectories and palliative careBMJ20053301007101110.1136/bmj.330.7498.100715860828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>MurraySAKendallMGrantEBoydKBarclaySSheikhAPatterns of social, psychological, and spiritual decline toward the end of life in lung cancer and heart failureJ Pain Symptom Manage20073439340210.1016/j.jpainsymman.2006.12.00917616334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>MularskiRADySMShugarmanLRWilkinsonAMLynnJShekellePGMortonSCSunVCHughesRGHiltonLKMaglioneMRhodesSLRolonCLorenzKAA systematic review of measures of end-of-life care and its outcomesHealth Serv Res2007421848187010.1111/j.1475-6773.2007.00721.x17850523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>JordhoyMSInger RingdalGHelbostadJLOldervollLLogeJHKaasaSAssessing physical functioning: a systematic review of quality of life measures developed for use in palliative carePalliat Med20072167368210.1177/026921630708338618073253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>SlaterAFreemanEPatients’ views of using an outcome measure in palliative day care: a focus group studyInt J Palliat Nurs20041034335115365487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>BookbinderMMcHughMESymptom management in palliative care and end of life careNurs Clin North Am20104527132710.1016/j.cnur.2010.04.00220804880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>National Consensus Project (NCP)Quality Palliative Care Guidelines<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nationalconsensusproject.org">http://www.nationalconsensusproject.org</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Otis-GreenSFerrellBBornemanTPuchalskiCUmanGGarciaAIntegrating spiritual care within palliative care: an overview of nine demonstration projectsJ Palliat Med20121515416210.1089/jpm.2011.021122304654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>SackettDLStrausSERichardsonWSRosenbergWHaynesRSackett DL, Straus SE, Richardson WS, Rosenberg W, Haynes RBIntroduction to evidence-based medicineEvidence-based medicine: how to practice and teach EBM20002Edinburgh: Churchill Livingstone112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)Focus on Cost-Effectiveness Analysis at AHRQ FactSheet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>AHRQ Publication No. 01-P023200Rockville, MD: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ahrq.gov/research/costeff.htm">http://www.ahrq.gov/research/costeff.htm</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>SnyderCFAaronsonNKChoucairAKElliottTEGreenhalghJHalyardMYHessRMillerDMReeveBBSantanaMImplementing patient-reported outcomes assessment in clinical practice: a review of the options and considerationsQual Life Res2012211305131410.1007/s11136-011-0054-x22048932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>YangYTMahonMMPalliative care for the terminally ill in America: the consideration of QALYs, costs, and ethical issuesMed Health Care Philos2011[Epub ahead of print] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>ElmqvistMAJordhøyMSBjordalKKaasaSJannertMHealth-related quality of life during the last three months of life in patients with advanced cancerSupport Care Cancer20091719119810.1007/s00520-008-0477-218581147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Granda-CameronCViolaSRLynchMPPolomanoRCMeasuring patient-oriented outcomes in palliative care: functionality and quality of lifeClin J Oncol Nurs200812657718258576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>BauseweinCSimonSTBenaliaHDowningJMwangi-PowellFNDavesonBAHardingRHigginsonIJPRISMAImplementing patient reported outcome measures (PROMs) in palliative care - users’ cry for helpHealth Qual Life Outcomes201192710.1186/1477-7525-9-2721507232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
