<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hematol Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Hematology &amp; Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-8722</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3035578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1756-8722-4-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21255411</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-8722-4-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Molecular mechanism of the schedule-dependent synergistic interaction in EGFR-mutant non-small cell lung cancer cell lines treated with paclitaxel and gefitinib </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>chenghuagz@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>She-Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>asjuan@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dsong@yahoo.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yi-Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>egfr@yahoo.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xu-Chao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zhxuchao3000@yahoo.com.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Zhi-Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>czh2112@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Jian-Su</surname></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jians609@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A8"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yi-Long</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>syylwu@live.cn</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Guangdong Lung Cancer Institute; Medical Research Center of Guangdong General Hospital &amp; Guangdong Academy of Medical Sciences. No.106, Zhongshan 2nd Rd, Guangzhou, Postal code:510080, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Thoracic oncology, the fifth affiliated hospital of Sun Yat-Sen university. No. 52, Meihua Dong Rd, Zhuhai, Postal code:519000, People's Republic of China</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2011 Cheng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cheng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jhoonline.org/content/4/1/5"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Chemotherapy combined concurrently with TKIs produced a negative interaction and failed to improve survival when compared with chemotherapy or TKIs alone in the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The present study investigated the sequence-dependent interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib and clarified the underlying mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The effects on cell proliferation, EGFR signaling pathway, and TGFα expression were evaluated in a panel of human NSCLC cell lines harboring EGFR mutations with three different combination sequences: sequential treatment with paclitaxel followed by gefitinib (T→G), sequential treatment with gefitinib followed by paclitaxel (G→T), or concomitant treatment (T + G). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The sequence-dependent anti-proliferative effects differed between EGFR-TKI-sensitive and -resistant cell lines carrying EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A synergistic anti-proliferative activity was obtained with paclitaxel treatment followed by gefitinib in all cell lines, with mean CI values of 0.63 in Hcc827, 0.54 in PC-9, 0.81 in PC-9/GR, and 0.77 in H1650 cells for the T→G sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The mean CI values for the G→T sequence were 1.29 in Hcc827, 1.16 in PC-9, 1.52 in PC-9/GR, and 1.5 in H1650 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The mean CI values for T+G concomitant treatment were 0.88 in Hcc827, 0.91 in PC-9, 1.05 in PC-9/GR, and 1.18 in H1650 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel produced a dose-dependent increase in EGFR phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel significantly increased EGFR phosphorylation compared with that in untreated controls (mean differences: +50% in Hcc827, + 56% in PC-9, + 39% in PC-9/GR, and + 69% in H1650 cells; p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The T→G sequence produced significantly greater inhibition of EGFR phosphorylation compared with the opposite sequence (mean differences: -58% in Hcc827, -38% in PC-9, -35% in PC-9/GR, and -30% in H1650 cells; p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Addition of a neutralizing anti-TGFα antibody abolished paclitaxel-induced activation of the EGFR pathway in PC-9 and H1650 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Sequence-dependent TGFα expression and release are responsible for the sequence-dependent EGFR pathway modulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The data suggest that the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib is an appropriate treatment combination for NSCLC cell lines harboring EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our results provide molecular evidence to support clinical treatment strategies for patients with lung cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Despite recent advances in early diagnosis and treatment, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is still a disease with a poor prognosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Platinum-based doublet chemotherapy is the mainstay of treatment for advanced NSCLC with good performance status [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Current data suggest that NSCLC chemotherapy has reached a therapeutic plateau [3,4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Gefitinib and erlotinib are orally active, reversible Her-1/epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In 2004, researchers found that EGFR-activating mutations correlated with clinical responses [5-7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The Iressa Pan-Asia Study (IPASS) trial indicated that gefitinib was superior to carboplatin plus paclitaxel as an initial treatment for patients with advanced NSCLC harboring an EGFR mutation [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The finding was further supported by two randomized studies (the WJTOG3405 and NEJ 002 trials) that consistently reported a high tumor response rate and progression-free survival (PFS) in patients with an EGFR mutation [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The EGFR mutation rate was higher in Asian than in western patients, explaining the higher response rate in East Asian patients [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Based on these studies, an EGFR mutation is currently the only established predictive factor for EGFR-TKIs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>An increasingly interesting area of clinical research is the development of rationale combinations of cytotoxic drugs with molecularly targeted therapies to increase the therapeutic potential by blocking cancer cell survival mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Recently, we have shown that the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib improves the antiproliferative effect compared with other sequences and produced a synergistic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We also found the sequence-dependent modulation of EGFR phosphorylation plays a role in this sequence-dependent antiproliferative effect [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, we did not focus on cell lines with mutant EGFR and the exact mechanism underlying the modulation of EGFR phosphorylation remains to be determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>While other studies indicated that TGFα release is responsible for EGFR activation induced by radiotherapy [13,14], we hypothesized that TGFα might play a role in the sequence-dependent antiproliferative effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Thus, the present study was performed in NSCLC cell lines harboring EGFR-activating mutations to investigate the synergistic interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib, and to determine the underlying mechanism(s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We found that sequence-dependent TGFα expression and release were responsible for the sequence-dependent EGFR pathway modulation and sequence-dependent antiproliferative effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Drugs and chemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Pure gefitinib, kindly provided by AstraZeneca (London, UK), was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) as a 20 mM stock solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel was purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA) and was dissolved in DMSO as a 1 mM stock solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Both drugs were diluted with culture medium before use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Primary antibodies: anti-pY1068 EGFR (phosphotyrosine-specific EGFR antibody) and anti-β-actin were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA, USA), anti-EGFR was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA), and anti-TGFα antibody[189-2130.1] was purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The human lung adenocarcinoma cell lines PC-9, Hcc827, and H1650 were kindly provided by Dr. Tony Mok (Chinese University of Hong Kong). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>These cell lines have been extensively characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>PC-9 is derived from a patient with adenocarcinoma, harboring an EGFR exon 19 in-frame deletion[E746-A750] that is highly sensitive to EGFR-TKIs[15], Hcc827 is derived from lung adenocarcinomas harboring an EGFR exon 19 in-frame deletion that is highly sensitive to EGFR-TKIs[16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>H1650 carries an EGFR exon 19 in-frame deletion mutation and is resistant to EGFR-TKIs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Martin et al. reported the homozygous deletion of PTEN in H1650 cells, which activated EGFR and contributed to erlotinib resistance[17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>PC-9/GR is a gefitinib-acquired resistant cell line that was established by chronic exposure of PC-9 cells to medium with increasing concentrations of gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Briefly, PC-9 cells were exposed to 10 nmol/L of gefitinib in medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum, and the concentration was increased in a stepwised manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Cells that were able to grow in 1 μmol/L gefitinib were obtained 6 month after initial expose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The decreased sensitivity did not recover even the cells were kept in culture for &gt; 4 month without gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These cells were grown in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), penicillin (100 UI/ml), and streptomycin (100 μg/ml) at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere with 5% CO2 and harvested with trypsin-EDTA when the cells were in exponential growth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of EGFR gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The exons encoding the intracellular domain of EGFR were amplified from genomic DNA and directly sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To further characterize additional mutation, we amplified the EGFR exon 19 to 20 from PC-9 or PC-9/GR cDNA, and the PCR products were subcloned into plasmid vector, then inserts were isolated and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Treatment regimens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Cell viability was determined using the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5- diphenyltetrazolium bromide) assay, according to the method of Mosmann and Carmichael [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the antiproliferative effects of combined treatment, cells were treated with three different sequences: I, pretreated with paclitaxel for 24 h, aspirated and washed once with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), followed by gefitinib for 48 h; II, pretreated with gefitinib for 48 h, aspirated and washed once with PBS, followed by paclitaxel for 24 h; III, treated concomitantly with paclitaxel plus gefitinib for 48 h, and then incubated in drug-free medium for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The different drug doses were combined using constant ratios of the IC50 values, calculated from previous cytotoxicity tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Thus, we used 0.125, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 times the IC50 dose in paclitaxel and gefitinib combination doses to calculate the CI value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The results of sequential treatment with paclitaxel and gefitinib were analyzed according to the method of Chou and Talaly [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The resulting combination index (CI) represented a quantitative measure of the degree of interaction between different drugs, with CI &gt; 1.1, CI = 0.9-1.1, and CI &lt; 0.9 indicating antagonistic, additive, and synergistic effects, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The CI value was calculated using the CompuSyn software (ComboSyn, Inc., Paramus, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Cells were seeded at 1 × 105 per plate on 10-cm plates and left to settle overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Cells were then treated by adding fresh medium containing drugs for the desired times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Soluble protein was extracted with the addition of RIPA lysis solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Lysates were cleared by centrifugation (12000 rpm, 4°C, 15 min), and soluble protein extracts were stored frozen at -80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Protein concentrations were quantitated using the bicinchoninic acid assay[21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Total cell extracts (30 μg of protein/well) were resolved on 8-10% acrylamide Tris-acetate gels, and then proteins were transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane, blocked for 1 h at room temperature in 5% w/v non-fat milk diluted in Tris-buffered saline Tween 20 (TBST), and finally incubated with appropriate primary antibodies under the conditions recommended by the manufacturers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The blots were then washed with TBST for 30 min and incubated with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody at room temperature for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Antibody binding was detected using an enhanced chemiluminescence system(Santa Cruz, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To quantify protein levels, films were scanned and analyzed with the Labworks software(World BioHazTec Corp, NM, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The relative protein levels were counted using a comparison with the untreated control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To compare the possible influence of TGFα gene expression on the sequence-dependent synergistic effect between paclitaxel and gefitinib, we used PC-9 cells to analyze the sequential modulation of TGFα expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The primer and probe design, total RNA isolation, cDNA synthesis, and quantification standards for real-time PCR were performed as described previously [22,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated using the Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The integrity of the total RNA was examined by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis, the quantity was determined based on the absorbance at 260 nm (A260), and the purity was analyzed based on the absorbance ratio at 260 and 280 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For pure RNA the ratio of A260/280 is ~2.0(A260/280; Amersham Biosciences GeneQuant, Pittsburgh, PA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>cDNA was synthesized from total RNA (1 μg) using AMV reverse transcriptase XL (Takara Bio, Inc., Shiga, Japan). β-actin served as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>To create real-time PCR standards, TGFα and β-actin were amplified using reverse transcriptase-PCR and specific primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The amplicons were cloned into the pMD18-T vector (Takara) and the sequence was confirmed by sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The purified recombinant DNA was quantified and then serially diluted in ultra-pure water to a final concentration ranging from 107 to 101 copies/μL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For quantification standards, we used 1-μL aliquots of 10-fold serial dilutions of plasmid DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A new standard curve was run for each real-time PCR, and each test run included a control containing non-target DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The amount of TGFα mRNA was normalized to the expression values of the housekeeping gene β-actin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>TGFα enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Medium was harvested from cells grown on 6-well dishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Samples were processed using the human TGFα quantikine ELISA kit (R&amp;D systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Results are presented as the mean ± standard error (SE) of at least three experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Statistical comparisons of sequence-dependent effects were conducted by student's t tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Statistics and graphs were generated using the GraphPad Prism software (ver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>5.00 for windows, GraphPad Software Inc, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The potential mechanisms for gefitinib resistance in PC-9/GR cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The gefitinib-acquired resistant PC-9/GR cells were obtained 6 months after initial exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>These cells were 100-fold more resistant than parental cells(Table-1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Additional mutations were not detected by direct sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The PCR product of PC-9 and PC-9/GR were subcloned into a plasmid vector, then the inserts were randomly selected and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Among the 20 sequences from PC-9/GR, we found 6 sequences were wild-type, 11 had only the 15-bp deletion, and 3 had both the 15-bp deletion and T790M mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These T790M mutation seemed to be the cause of gefitinib resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Of 10 colones isolated from PC-9, 4 had no mutation, and the others had the 15-bp deletion (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>PC-9/GR exon 20 sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Wild type by direct sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>3 of 20 clones had ACG &gt; ATG T790M mutation by clone sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>17 of 20 clones were wild type </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Sequence-dependent antiproliferative effects differed between EGFR-TKI-sensitive and EGFR-TKI-resistant NSCLC cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the antiproliferative effects of paclitaxel and gefitinib treatment, we performed a series of MTT cell growth assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Treatment with gefitinib alone for 72 h resulted in a dose-dependent inhibition of cancer cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Table 1 summarizes the IC50 of these two drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>PC-9 and Hcc827 were highly sensitive to gefitinib, while H1650 exhibited primary resistance and PC-9/GR showed acquired resistance to gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>All of these cell lines demonstrated similar sensitivities to paclitaxel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the growth inhibition effect on Hcc827, PC-9, PC-9/GR, and H1650 of three different sequences of combined paclitaxel and gefitinib treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Figure 2a shows the schema for in vitro sequential treatment between paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 2b and 2c, the antiproliferative effects between paclitaxel and gefitinib were sequence-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Although the differences were not marked, the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib was most efficacious against EGFR-mutant NSCLC cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>IC50 values for each drug were calculated by performing dose response experiments with gefitinib and paclitaxel </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>IC50 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Hcc827 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>PC-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>PC-9/GR </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>H1650 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>2.27 ± 0.15nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>2.33 ± 0.47nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>2.59 ± 0.62nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>3.29 ± 0.35nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Gefitinib </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>16 ± 1.12nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>19 ± 2nM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>2.1 ± 0.39 μM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>9.37 ± 0.52 μM </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The antiproliferative effect with paclitaxel and gefitinib is sequence-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Schema of sequential treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>B and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib produced the most potent antiproliferative effect in PC-9 and Hcc827 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>T → G, paclitaxel followed by gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>G → T, gefitinib followed by paclitaxel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>T + G, concomitant paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>T, paclitaxel alone for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>G, gefitinib alone for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The calculation of CI values revealed that the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib produced synergistic effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In Hcc827 and PC-9 cell lines, which were highly sensitive to EGFR-TKIs, the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib resulted in synergistic effects, with mean CI values of 0.63 in Hcc827, 0.54 in PC-9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Concomitant administration of the drugs resulted in both synergistic and additive effects, with mean CI values of 0.88 in Hcc827, 0.91 in PC-9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The gefitinib followed by paclitaxel sequence resulted in an additive and antagonistic interaction with mean CI values of 1.29 in Hcc827, 1.16 in PC-9 (Figure 3a,b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In the PC-9/GR cell line, which exhibited acquired resistance to EGFR-TKIs, the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib resulted in a synergistic and additive interaction with increasing drug concentrations (mean CI, 0.81). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the sequence of gefitinib followed by paclitaxel resulted in an antagonistic effect (mean CI, 1.52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Concomitant treatment with the two drugs resulted in additive and antagonistic effects (mean CI, 1.05)(Figure 3c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In the H1650 cell line, a synergistic and additive growth inhibition effect was found with the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib (mean CI, 0.77). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the sequence of gefitinib followed by paclitaxel resulted in an antagonistic interaction (mean CI, 1.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Simultaneous administration of the two drugs resulted in an additive and antagonistic interaction (mean CI, 1.18)(Figure 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Each experiment was repeated in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Synergism of sequence-dependent cytotoxicity between paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Points, mean values of three different experiments. ○ T → G, paclitaxel followed by gefitinib. □ G → T, gefitinib followed by paclitaxel. △ T + G, concomitant paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The sequence T → G produced the most potent cytotoxic growth inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The T → G sequence resulted in a synergistic effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Sequence-dependent modulation of the EGFR signaling pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>To gain insight into the mechanisms involved regulating the interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib, we examed the effect of paclitaxel on EGFR phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In cell lines of PC-9 and H1650, a dose-dependent increase in pEGFR levels were observed 24 hous after 1, 2 and 3 fold IC50 dose of paclitaxel exposure(Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Because EGFR-TKIs specifically target the tyrosine kinase activity of EGFR, we analyzed the sequence-dependent modulation of the EGFR signaling pathway using an IC50 dose of paclitaxel plus gefitinib combination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5, gefitinib significantly inhibited EGFR phosphorylation (p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>When Hcc827, PC-9, PC-9/GR and H1650 cell lines were exposed to paclitaxel alone, phosphorylated EGFR (pEGFR) levels increased significantly after paclitaxel exposure for 24 h than that in untreated control (mean difference, +50% in Hcc827, +56% in PC-9, +39% in PC-9/GR and +69% in H1650 cells respectively, p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The increase in pEGFR induced by paclitaxel was blocked by adding gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In the reverse sequence, gefitinib treatment for 48 h significantly inhibited pEGFR levels, compared with the untreated control level of pEGFR, and subsequent paclitaxel exposure for 24 h enhanced pEGFR levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The paclitaxel followed by gefitinib sequence produced significantly greater pEGFR inhibition than did the reverse sequence (mean difference, -58% in Hcc827, -38% in PC-9, -35% in PC-9/GR and -30% in H1650 respectively, p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Effect of paclitaxel on EGFR phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>PC-9 and H1650 cells were exposed to 1, 2 and 3 fold IC50 dose paclitaxel for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>A dose-dependent increase in EGFR phosphorylation levels were observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Sequential modulation of EGFR phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Cells were exposed to the IC50 dose of gefitinib and paclitaxel using different sequences. *Paclitaxel significantly activated the EGFR pathway compared with control after paclitaxel exposure for 24 h (p &lt; 0.05). # p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The phosphorylated EGFR (p-EGFR) level after treatment with paclitaxel followed by gefitinib was lower than that for gefitinib followed by paclitaxel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that paclitaxel may also have a self-limiting effect on its toxicity, via activation of the EGFR tyrosine kinase phosphorylation, leading to increased proliferation and survival of paclitaxel-mediated cytotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The increase in pEGFR can be blocked by adding gefitinib, which produces a synergistic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In the reverse sequence, however, the sequence of gefitinib followed by paclitaxel interferes with the inhibition of pEGFR by gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel-induced primary activation of EGFR is blocked by a neutralizing antibody to TGFα </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated that chemotherapy activates EGFR phosphorylation [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Multiple mechanisms allow for EGFR activation and persistent tumor cell proliferation, including activating mutations, receptor amplification, and ligand up-regulation [25,26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Other studies have found that radiation causes release of TGFα, which is responsible for activation of the EGFR signaling pathway [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>We next examined whether activation of the EGFR signaling pathway induced by paclitaxel is dependent on TGFα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel caused EGFR activation in PC-9 and H1650 cells after a 12-h exposure and lasted for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Addition of a neutralizing antibody to TGFα reduced the activation of EGFR (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrated that paclitaxel-induced EGFR activation was dependent on the function of TGFα. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Paclitaxel-induced activation of EGFR is blocked by adding neutralizing TGFα antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The dose of paclitaxel is 2-fold IC50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The dose of TGFα antibody is 0.15 μg/mL A.PC-9 B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>H1650 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>TGFα is a cognate ligand for EGFR, mediate tyrosine phosphorylation of the receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>We then determine the growth inhibition effect of an anti-TGFα antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>PC-9 and H1650 cells were grow into the medium containing increasing concentration of anti-TGFα antibody for 72 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The antibody show a modest growth inhibition effect, inhibited the growth of PC-9 and H1650 by about 30% at 500 ng/ml (Figure 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Growth inhibition of PC-9 and H1650 by an anti-TGFα.antibody. PC-9 and H1650 cells were grow into a 96 well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The following day, the cells were incubated with indicated concentration of anti-TGFα antibody for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The inhibition ratio were determined by MTT assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-7"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Sequence-dependent TGFα expression and release are responsible for the sequence-dependent EGFR pathway modulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>To further evaluate whether sequential modulation of the EGFR pathway is due to the release of TGFα, PC-9, Hcc827 and H1650 cells were treated with sequential paclitaxel and gefitinib as indicated in the treatment schema of Figure 2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Medium was subjected to ELISA to verify soluble TGFα levels and was normalized to cell numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 8a, paclitaxel exposure for 24 h significantly stimulated TGFα release. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Gefitinib significantly inhibited the release of TGFα (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The paclitaxel-followed-by-gefitinib sequence resulted in a significant reduction of TGFα levels, compared with the reverse sequence (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Sequential modulation of TGFα release and expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Cells were exposed to IC50 dose of paclitaxel and gefitinib with different sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>A, standard enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay analysis of soluble TGFα levels in PC-9, Hcc827 and H1650 cells. *p &lt; 0.05, significantly different from control. #P &lt; 0.05, T→G VS G→T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>B, reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction analysis of TGFα expression. *p &lt; 0.05, significantly different from control. #P &lt; 0.05, T→G vs. G→T. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-8722-4-5-8"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To gain further insight into the mechanisms involved in regulating the interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib, we examined changes in TGFα mRNA expression in treated PC-9, Hcc827 and H1650 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Quantitative PCR analysis of TGFα mRNA expression levels showed that in comparison with the respective control, paclitaxel significantly increased (p &lt; 0.01), while gefitinib significantly decreased TGFα mRNA expression (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The paclitaxel-followed-by-gefitinib sequence significantly decreased TGFα mRNA expression, compared with the reverse sequence (Figure 8b; p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The present study demonstrated that the antiproliferative effect with paclitaxel and gefitinib is sequence-dependent in EGFR-mutant NSCLC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>We found that the sequence of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib produced the most efficacious antiproliferative effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Other studies have demonstrated sequence-dependent interaction between EGFR-TKIs and chemotherapy in human cancer cell lines [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>These studies also revealed that pretreatment with erlotinib caused G1 arrest and effectively abrogated the activity of chemotherapy, resulting in decreased cytotoxicity and decreased apoptosis [28-30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Solit et al. reported schedule-dependent efficacy in an NSCLC xenograft model with paclitaxel and gefitinib [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Our study was novel because we found that sequence-dependent modulation of the EGFR signaling pathway might play a role in the sequence-dependent interaction in NSCLC cells harboring an EGFR mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We found that paclitaxel-induced activation of EGFR was dependent on the function of TGFα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Additionally, TGFα expression and release were sequence-dependent, which may responsible for the sequence-dependent interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>As EGFR-TKIs gefitinib and erlotinib are active in patients with NSCLC harboring EGFR mutations, combining them in treatment with chemotherapy was deemed promising [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>However, in the INTACT-1, INTACT-2, TALENT, and TRIBUTE clinical trials, the addition of gefitinib or erlotinib to first-line chemotherapy failed to improve survival [32-35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In a phase II trial of CALGB 30406, the concurrent combination of paclitaxel plus carboplatin with erlotinib showed a similar efficacy compared with erlotinib alone in patients with advanced lung adenocarcinoma [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Gandara et al. [37,38] proposed two hypotheses that seem reasonable to explain the negative results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>First, patients were not selected based on a predictive response marker, although other studies have reported that activating mutations in the EGFR tyrosine kinase domain were associated with a dramatic response to gefitinib and erlotinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Second, potentiation of the antagonistic interaction between concurrent EGFR-TKI and chemotherapy may have played a role, because in vitro and in vivo studies of administration of concurrent EGFR-TKI and chemotherapy have suggested antagonism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Davies et al. [39] have proposed the pharmacodynamic separation model: EGFR-TKIs primarily cause cell cycle arrest and accumulation of cells in G1; and thus, when administered concurrently with chemotherapy, can interfere with cell cycle-specific cytotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Our previous study[12] and other study[30] found that EGFR-TKI induces G1 arrest, which produced a negative interaction when combined concurrently with chemotherapy or followed by chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Chemotherapy has been shown to activate multiple signaling pathways [40] and, recently, to activate the EGFR pathway as well as to enhance ubiquitination and degradation [41,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The intracellular TK activity of EGFR is increased as a consequence of binding of various cognate ligands, including EGF, TGFα, and amphiregulin, leading to homodimerization of two EGFRs or heterodimerization of EGFR with other family members [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Improper activation of EGFR TK results in increased malignant cell survival, proliferation, invasion, and metastasis [44,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Several chemotherapy drugs were found to activate the EGFR signaling pathway [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Radiation has also been demonstrated to activate the EGFR signaling pathway by causing the release of TGFα, which is responsible for secondary activation of EGFR, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK), and Janus kinase (JNK) pathways [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In the present study, neutralizing TGFα abolished the paclitaxel induced-activation of EGFR, and paclitaxel may stimulate release of TGFα to activate the EGFR pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Autocrine loops are established when soluble factors secreted by cells bind to and stimulate receptors on their own surfaces [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>TGFα is a cognate ligand for EGFR and can establish an autocrine loop that leads to receptor hyperactivity[47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Ciardiello, et al. found that a TGFα-EGFR autocrine growth pathway is active in cancer cell lines, and gefitinib produced a dose-dependent inhibition of the secretion of TGFα[48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that paclitaxel may exert a self-limiting effect on its ability to kill and reduce the proliferation of autocrine-regulated tumor cells, potentially by increasing both the rates of transcription and activation of TGFα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Increased expression and release of TGFα leads to both increased EGFR and activation of the downstream signaling pathway, which, in turn, leads to both increased proliferation of tumor cells as well as other enhanced cytoprotective responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Increased TGFα expression and release can be blocked by subsequent administration of gefitinib, which can block TGFα-triggered EGFR signaling pathway activation and produce a synergistic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In contrast, initial exposure to gefitinib decreases TGFα expression and release, and subsequent paclitaxel treatment enhances TGFα expression and release, producing an antagonistic effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxic chemotherapy treatment for patients with advanced NSCLC has reached a plateau, but further improvements are expected with the integration of targeted therapies[49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>EGFR-TKIs treatment concurrent with chemotherapy failed to improve survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Alternative schedules of TKI administration in combination with chemotherapy, such as sequential and pulse administration, are under investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In the Fast-Act trial, a randomized phase II trial of sequential erlotinib and chemotherapy as first-line treatment of patients with advanced NSCLC, gemcitabine plus cisplatin or carboplatin (GC) were sequentially followed by erlotinib (GC-E) versus GC followed by a placebo (GC-P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that GC-E significantly improved PFS compared with GC-P [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Based on these results, Fast-Act II, a randomized phase III trial of sequential erlotinib and chemotherapy, is underway[52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In the final analysis of the pivotal IPASS trial, although there is significant improvement in PFS and RR for patients receiving gefitinib, overall survival was similar for gefitinib and carboplatin/paclitaxel, reported Chin-Hsin Yang[53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The effect of the initial randomized treatment therapy on overall survival is likely to have been confounded by subsequent study, particulary, the switching of patients to the alternative study treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>This suggests the sequence of therapy may not make a significant impact in patients with mutant EGFR, as long as such patients are exposed to an EGFR TKI in general, and whether it is given first-line or later translates into the same overall survival benefit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The limitation of this study is that because the short exposure time, the interaction of sequential treatment in vitro may not correlate the interaction between first-line and second-line treatment in clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The drug interaction patterns observed in vitro may not be similar to those observed clinically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Because the culture condition can perturb cell function and potentiate drug sensitivity, obtaining good correlations can be problematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, rescue effects and toxicity to normal cells/tissues that affect drug action in clinical setting are not considered by in vitro assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Because each patient has a unique pharmacogenetic makeup, correlating in vitro and clinical results is often not a straightforward process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>However, our study provided a rational for the ongoing clinical investigation of sequential treatment of NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In summary, our studies have demonstrated that sequential administrations of paclitaxel followed by gefitinib result in the most effective cytotoxic effects in NSCLC cell lines harboring EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The sequence-dependent modulation of TGFα expression and release might be responsible for the synergistic interaction between paclitaxel and gefitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Although the extrapolation of in vitro data to the clinical setting should be considered with caution, these results may have implications for the rational development of chemotherapeutic regimens for the treatment of NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Yi-long Wu has received speaking honoraria from AstraZeneca, Eli lilly, F.Hoffmann-La Roche and Pfizer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>No other potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>HC designed thses experiments, performed part of these experiments and drafted this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>YW designed these experiments, analyzed the results, guided these experiments and revised this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>SA and ZC carried out RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>DS and YZ carried out the western blot, XZ analyzed the experiment results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>JS carried out part of the MTT assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30772531), and Zhuhai Science &amp; Technology Bureau (No.20081040) </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>SocinskiMACrowellRHensingTELangerCJLilenbaumRSandlerABMorrisDTreatment of non-small cell lung cancer, stage IV: ACCP evidence-based clinical practice guidelinesChest200713223 Suppl277S289S10.1378/chest.07-138117873174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>FelipEStahelRAPavlidisNESMO Minimum Clinical Recommendations for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up of non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC)Ann Oncol200516Suppl 1i282910.1093/annonc/mdi82115888743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>SchillerJHHarringtonDBelaniCPLangerCSandlerAKrookJZhuJJohnsonDHComparison of four chemotherapy regimens for advanced non-small-cell lung cancerN Engl J Med20023462929810.1056/NEJMoa01195411784875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>SmitEFvan MeerbeeckJPLianesPDebruyneCLegrandCSchramelFSmitHGaafarRBiesmaBManegoldCThree-arm randomized study of two cisplatin-based regimens and paclitaxel plus gemcitabine in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: a phase III trial of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Lung Cancer Group--EORTC 08975J Clin Oncol200321213909391710.1200/JCO.2003.03.19514581415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>LynchTJBellDWSordellaRGurubhagavatulaSOkimotoRABranniganBWHarrisPLHaserlatSMSupkoJGHaluskaFGActivating mutations in the epidermal growth factor receptor underlying responsiveness of non-small-cell lung cancer to gefitinibN Engl J Med2004350212129213910.1056/NEJMoa04093815118073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>PaezJGJannePALeeJCTracySGreulichHGabrielSHermanPKayeFJLindemanNBoggonTJEGFR mutations in lung cancer: correlation with clinical response to gefitinib therapyScience200430456761497150010.1126/science.109931415118125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>PaoWMillerVZakowskiMDohertyJPolitiKSarkariaISinghBHeelanRRuschVFultonLEGF receptor gene mutations are common in lung cancers from "never smokers" and are associated with sensitivity of tumors to gefitinib and erlotinibProc Natl Acad Sci USA200410136133061331110.1073/pnas.040522010115329413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>MokTSWuYLThongprasertSYangCHChuDTSaijoNSunpaweravongPHanBMargonoBIchinoseYGefitinib or carboplatin-paclitaxel in pulmonary adenocarcinomaN Engl J Med20093611094795710.1056/NEJMoa081069919692680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>MitsudomiTMoritaSYatabeYNegoroSOkamotoITsurutaniJSetoTSatouchiMTadaHHirashimaTGefitinib versus cisplatin plus docetaxel in patients with non-small-cell lung cancer harbouring mutations of the epidermal growth factor receptor (WJTOG3405): an open label, randomised phase 3 trialLancet Oncol11212112810.1016/S1470-2045(09)70364-X20022809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>MaemondoMInoueAKobayashiKSugawaraSOizumiSIsobeHGemmaAHaradaMYoshizawaHKinoshitaIGefitinib or chemotherapy for non-small-cell lung cancer with mutated EGFRN Engl J Med362252380238810.1056/NEJMoa090953020573926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>WuYLZhongWZLiLYZhangXTZhangLZhouCCLiuWJiangBMuXLLinJYEpidermal growth factor receptor mutations and their correlation with gefitinib therapy in patients with non-small cell lung cancer: a meta-analysis based on updated individual patient data from six medical centers in mainland ChinaJ Thorac Oncol20072543043910.1097/01.JTO.0000268677.87496.4c17473659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>ChengHAnSJZhangXCDongSZhangYFChenZHChenHJGuoALLinQXWuYLIn vitro sequence-dependent synergism between paclitaxel and gefitinib in human lung cancer cell linesCancer Chemother Pharmacol in press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>DentPReardonDBParkJSBowersGLogsdonCValerieKSchmidt-UllrichRRadiation-induced release of transforming growth factor alpha activates the epidermal growth factor receptor and mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway in carcinoma cells, leading to increased proliferation and protection from radiation-induced cell deathMol Biol Cell19991082493250610436007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Schmidt-UllrichRKValerieKChanWWazerDELinPSExpression of oestrogen receptor and transforming growth factor-alpha in MCF-7 cells after exposure to fractionated irradiationInt J Radiat Biol199261340541510.1080/095530092145511011347074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>KoizumiFShimoyamaTTaguchiFSaijoNNishioKEstablishment of a human non-small cell lung cancer cell line resistant to gefitinibInt J Cancer20051161364410.1002/ijc.2098515761868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>AmannJKalyankrishnaSMassionPPOhmJEGirardLShigematsuHPeytonMJuroskeDHuangYStuart SalmonJAberrant epidermal growth factor receptor signaling and enhanced sensitivity to EGFR inhibitors in lung cancerCancer Res200565122623515665299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>SosMLKokerMWeirBAHeynckSRabinovskyRZanderTSeegerJMWeissJFischerFFrommoltPPTEN loss contributes to erlotinib resistance in EGFR-mutant lung cancer by activation of Akt and EGFRCancer Res20096983256326110.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-405519351834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>MosmannTRapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assaysJ Immunol Methods1983651-2556310.1016/0022-1759(83)90303-46606682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>CarmichaelJDeGraffWGGazdarAFMinnaJDMitchellJBEvaluation of a tetrazolium-based semiautomated colorimetric assay: assessment of chemosensitivity testingCancer Res19874749369423802100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ChouTCTheoretical basis, experimental design, and computerized simulation of synergism and antagonism in drug combination studiesPharmacol Rev200658362168110.1124/pr.58.3.1016968952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>SmithPKKrohnRIHermansonGTMalliaAKGartnerFHProvenzanoMDFujimotoEKGoekeNMOlsonBJKlenkDCMeasurement of protein using bicinchoninic acidAnal Biochem19851501768510.1016/0003-2697(85)90442-73843705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>AnSJNieQChenZHLinQXWangZXieZChenSLHuangYZhangAYYanJFKDR expression is associated with the stage and cigarette smoking of the patients with lung cancerJ Cancer Res Clin Oncol2007133963564210.1007/s00432-007-0214-017479290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>DongSGuoALChenZHWangZZhangXCHuangYXieZYanHHChengHWuYLRRM1 single nucleotide polymorphism -37C--&gt;A correlates with progression-free survival in NSCLC patients after gemcitabine-based chemotherapyJ Hematol Oncol31010.1186/1756-8722-3-1020226083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>GiovannettiELemosCTekleCSmidKNannizziSRodriguezJARicciardiSDanesiRGiacconeGPetersGJMolecular mechanisms underlying the synergistic interaction of erlotinib, an epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor, with the multitargeted antifolate pemetrexed in non-small-cell lung cancer cellsMol Pharmacol20087341290130010.1124/mol.107.04238218187583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>FranovicAGunaratnamLSmithKRobertIPattenDLeeSTranslational up-regulation of the EGFR by tumor hypoxia provides a nonmutational explanation for its overexpression in human cancerProc Natl Acad Sci USA200710432130921309710.1073/pnas.070238710417670948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>NormannoNDe LucaABiancoCStrizziLMancinoMMaielloMRCarotenutoADe FeoGCaponigroFSalomonDSEpidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) signaling in cancerGene2006366121610.1016/j.gene.2005.10.01816377102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>XuJMAzzaritiAColucciGParadisoAThe effect of gefitinib (Iressa, ZD1839) in combination with oxaliplatin is schedule-dependent in colon cancer cell linesCancer Chemother Pharmacol200352644244810.1007/s00280-003-0687-813680161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>LiTLingYHGoldmanIDPerez-SolerRSchedule-dependent cytotoxic synergism of pemetrexed and erlotinib in human non-small cell lung cancer cellsClin Cancer Res200713113413342210.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-292317545550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>GumerlockPHPrydeBJKimuraTEnhanced cytotoxicity of docetaxel OSI-774 combination in non-small cell lung carcinoma (NSCLC)Proc Am Soc Clin Oncol200322abstr 2661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>MahaffeyCMDaviesAMLaraPNJrPrydeBHollandWMackPCGumerlockPHGandaraDRSchedule-dependent apoptosis in K-ras mutant non-small-cell lung cancer cell lines treated with docetaxel and erlotinib: rationale for pharmacodynamic separationClin Lung Cancer20078954855310.3816/CLC.2007.n.04118186959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>SolitDBSheYLoboJKrisMGScherHIRosenNSirotnakFMPulsatile administration of the epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitor gefitinib is significantly more effective than continuous dosing for sensitizing tumors to paclitaxelClin Cancer Res20051151983198910.1158/1078-0432.CCR-04-134715756024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>GiacconeGHerbstRSManegoldCScagliottiGRosellRMillerVNataleRBSchillerJHVon PawelJPluzanskaAGefitinib in combination with gemcitabine and cisplatin in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: a phase III trial--INTACT 1J Clin Oncol200422577778410.1200/JCO.2004.08.00114990632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>HerbstRSGiacconeGSchillerJHNataleRBMillerVManegoldCScagliottiGRosellROliffIReevesJAGefitinib in combination with paclitaxel and carboplatin in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: a phase III trial--INTACT 2J Clin Oncol200422578579410.1200/JCO.2004.07.21514990633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>HerbstRSPragerDHermannRFehrenbacherLJohnsonBESandlerAKrisMGTranHTKleinPLiXTRIBUTE: a phase III trial of erlotinib hydrochloride (OSI-774) combined with carboplatin and paclitaxel chemotherapy in advanced non-small-cell lung cancerJ Clin Oncol200523255892589910.1200/JCO.2005.02.84016043829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>GatzemeierUPluzanskaASzczesnaAKaukelERoubecJDe RosaFMilanowskiJKarnicka-MlodkowskiHPesekMSerwatowskiPPhase III study of erlotinib in combination with cisplatin and gemcitabine in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: the Tarceva Lung Cancer Investigation TrialJ Clin Oncol200725121545155210.1200/JCO.2005.05.147417442998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>JannePAWangXFSocinskiMARandomized phase II trial of erlotinib (E) alone or in combination with carboplatin/paclitaxel (CP) in never or light former smokers with advanced lung adenocarcinoma: CALGB 30406J Clin Oncol20102815ssuppl;abstr 7503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>GandaraDNarayanSLaraPNJrGoldbergZDaviesALauDHMackPGumerlockPVijayakumarSIntegration of novel therapeutics into combined modality therapy of locally advanced non-small cell lung cancerClin Cancer Res20051113 Pt 25057s5062s10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-05-901216000614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>GandaraDRGumerlockPHEpidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors plus chemotherapy: case closed or is the jury still out?J Clin Oncol200523255856585810.1200/JCO.2005.05.03016043825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>DaviesAMHoCLaraPNJrMackPGumerlockPHGandaraDRPharmacodynamic separation of epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors and chemotherapy in non-small-cell lung cancerClin Lung Cancer20067638538810.3816/CLC.2006.n.02116800963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>TorresKHorwitzSBMechanisms of Taxol-induced cell death are concentration dependentCancer Res19985816362036269721870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>ChunPYFengFYScheurerAMDavisMALawrenceTSNyatiMKSynergistic effects of gemcitabine and gefitinib in the treatment of head and neck carcinomaCancer Res200666298198810.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-266516424033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>AhsanAHinikerSMRamanandSGNyatiSHegdeAHelmanAMenawatRBhojaniMSLawrenceTSNyatiMKRole of epidermal growth factor receptor degradation in cisplatin-induced cytotoxicity in head and neck cancerCancer Res7072862286910.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-429420215522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>BazleyLAGullickWJThe epidermal growth factor receptor familyEndocr Relat Cancer200512Suppl 1S172710.1677/erc.1.0103216113093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>CitriAYardenYEGF-ERBB signalling: towards the systems levelNature reviews20067750551616829981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>CiardielloFTortoraGEGFR antagonists in cancer treatmentN Engl J Med2008358111160117410.1056/NEJMra070770418337605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>SpornMBRobertsABAutocrine secretion--10 years laterAnn Intern Med199211754084141503333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>PutnamEAYenNGallickGESteckPAFangKAkpakipBGazdarAFRothJAAutocrine growth stimulation by transforming growth factor-alpha in human non-small cell lung cancerSurg Oncol199211496010.1016/0960-7404(92)90056-Q1341235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>CiardielloFCaputoRBiancoRDamianoVFontaniniGCuccatoSDe PlacidoSBiancoARTortoraGInhibition of growth factor production and angiogenesis in human cancer cells by ZD1839 (Iressa), a selective epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitorClin Cancer Res2001751459146511350918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>KatzelJAFanucchiMPLiZRecent advances of novel targeted therapy in non-small cell lung cancerJ Hematol Oncol20092210.1186/1756-8722-2-219159467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>MirshahidiHRHsuehCTUpdates in non-small cell lung cancer--insights from the 2009 45th annual meeting of the American Society of Clinical OncologyJ Hematol Oncol31810.1186/1756-8722-3-1820433767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>MokTSWuYLYuCJZhouCChenYMZhangLIgnacioJLiaoMSrimuninnimitVBoyerMJRandomized, placebo-controlled, phase II study of sequential erlotinib and chemotherapy as first-line treatment for advanced non-small-cell lung cancerJ Clin Oncol200927305080508710.1200/JCO.2008.21.554119738125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>RocheHLA Study of Tarceva (Erlotinib) or Placebo in Combination With Platinum-Based Therapy as First Line Treatment in Patients With Advanced or Recurrent Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer2009ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier NCT00883779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>YangCHFukuokaMMokTSeaFinal overall survival results from a phase III randomized, open-label, first-line study of gefitinib V carboplatin/paclitaxel in clinically selected patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer in Asia35th ESMO Congress2010Abstract LBA2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Presented October 11 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
