<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3534334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2180-12-183</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22913622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-12-183</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Real-time analysis of gut flora in Entamoeba histolytica infected patients of Northern India </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Anil Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>anilv228125@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ravirbl@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>Vineet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>vins_ahuja@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A4"><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>Jaishree</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jpaul33@hotmail.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>School of Life Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Gastroenterology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2012 Verma et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Verma et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/12/183"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Amebic dysentery is caused by the protozoan parasite Entamoeba histolytica and the ingestion of quadrinucleate cyst of E. histolytica from fecally contaminated food or water initiates infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Excystation occurs in the lumen of small intestine, where motile and potentially invasive trophozoites germinate from cysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The ability of trophozoites to interact and digest gut bacteria is apparently important for multiplication of the parasite and its pathogenicity; however the contribution of resident bacterial flora is not well understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We quantified the population of Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium, Ruminococcus, Lactobacillus, Clostridium leptum subgroup, Clostridium coccoides subgroup, Eubacterium, Campylobacter, Methanobrevibacter smithii and Sulphur reducing bacteria using genus specific primers in healthy (N = 22) vs amebic patients (E. histolytica positive, N = 17) stool samples by Real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Absolute quantification of Bacteroides (p = .001), Closrtridium coccoides subgroup (p = 0.002), Clostridium leptum subgroup (p = 0.0001), Lactobacillus (p = 0.037), Campylobacter (p = 0.0014) and Eubacterium (p = 0.038) show significant drop in their population however, significant increase in Bifdobacterium (p = 0.009) was observed where as the population of Ruminococcus (p = 0.33) remained unaltered in healthy vs amebic patients (E. histolytica positive). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We also report high prevalence of nimE gene in stool samples of both healthy volunteers and amebic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>No significant decrease in nimE gene copy number was observed before and after the treatment with antiamebic drug. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Our results show significant alteration in predominant gut bacteria in E. histolytica infected individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The frequent episodes of intestinal amoebic dysentery thus result in depletion of few predominant genera in gut that may lead to poor digestion and absorption of food in intestine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>It further disturbs the homeostasis between gut epithelium and bacterial flora. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The decrease in beneficial bacterial population gives way to dysbiosis of gut bacteria which may contribute to final outcome of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Increase in the copy number of nimE gene harboring bacteria in our population reflects possible decrease in the availability of metronidazole drug during treatment of amoebiasis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Gut flora</kwd><kwd>Entamoeba histolytica</kwd><kwd>RT-PCR</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Entamoeba histolytica, a micro-aerophilic intestinal protozoan parasite and the causative agent of invasive amoebiasis (colitis and amoebic liver abscess), remains a significant cause of morbidity and mortality in developing countries[1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It is well known that the parasite is constantly interacting with the intestinal gut flora however the contribution of the flora in the manifestation of the disease is poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The human gastrointestinal (GI) tract is nutrient-rich environment packed with a complex and dynamic consortia of trillions of microbes [2].The vast majority reside in our colon where densities approach 1011 - 1012 cells/ml, the highest density recorded for any microbial habitat [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>About 500–1000 bacterial species colonize the adult intestine,with 30–40 species comprising up to 97% of the total population [4,5]. Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium, Eubacterium, Clostridium, Peptococcus, Peptostreptococcus, Lactobacillus and Ruminococcus are considered to be predominant genera whereas Enterococcus, Methanobrevibacter and sulphur reducing bacteria (SRB) remain as the subdominant genera [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The entire system of the human gut microbiota functions as a ‘microbial organ’ within the intestine, which contributes to diverse mammalian processes including protective functions against pathogens and immune-system modulation, the metabolic function of fermenting non-digestible dietary fiber, anaerobic metabolism of peptides and proteins that results in the recovery of metabolic energy for the host [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The microbial diversity of the human gut is the result of co-evolution between microbial communities and their hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Microbial community structure is a very important factor that can influence predisposition to specific diseases in certain host contexts [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Ingestion of the cyst of E. histolytica through fecally contaminated food or water initiates infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Excystation in the intestinal lumen produces trophozoites and colitis results when the trophozoites penetrate the mucus layer and damages intestinal tissues [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The trophozoites proliferate in lumen and phagocytose resident flora. E. histolytica trophozoites are quite selective in respect to their interactions with different bacterial species and only those bacteria which have the appropriate recognition molecules get attached and ingested [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It has been observed that the nuclear DNA content of E. histolytica trophozoites growing in axenic cultures is at least 10 fold higher than in xenic cultures and re-association of axenic cultures with their bacterial flora led to a reduction of DNA content attaining the original xenic values indicating a flexible nature of the parasite genome [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Fluctuations in gut flora have been reported both in acute diarrhea and antibiotic associated diarrhea [12], but very few reports are available on status of gut flora in E. histolytica infected individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Earlier studies in our laboratory [1] have recorded fluctuations in the gut flora by a qualitative method during disease conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>5-Nitroimidazole drugs are still used as first line of defense against amoebic and other infections caused by anaerobes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These drugs are administered as pro drugs and one electron reduction of nitro group converts the pro drug into an active drug [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Enzymatic modification mediated by nim-class of genes is a well characterized resistance mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Certain Bacteroides species which are members of the normal colonic human microflora harbor nim genes [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Our study is based on the hypothesis that the Entamoeba histolytica (but not E. dispar) is an invasive organism and invades the mucus layer and subsequently the intestinal epithelium for colonization using the pathogenic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In this context we attempted to study the fluctuations in the gut microbiota that contributes to substantial metabolic changes in E. histolytica infected individuals compared to healthy individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In the present study we used Real Time PCR for absolute quantification of predominant gut bacterial population in E. histolytica patients suffering from dysentery for 5–7 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We also quantified the copy number of nim gene in stool sample of healthy vs E. histolytica patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Study subjects &amp; fecal sample collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Stool samples of healthy person (without any enteric disease) were collected as controls from volunteers of a community in Delhi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Initial survey involved discussion with the focus group and informed consent was taken from participating volunteers for the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Volunteers in age group of 21–40 year (mean age 31 year) were randomly recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Subjects who have taken any antibiotic/antiamoebic drug or suffered from any gastrointestinal disorder in past one month before sample collection were not included in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Twenty two stool samples were collected from healthy volunteers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Clinical diagnosis of amoebic colitis was based on standard criteria: patients experiencing days to weeks of dysentery (stool with blood and mucus) or diarrhea with cramps followed by abdominal pain and/or weight loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The sub acute onset of the disease was a helpful clue in the differential diagnosis because bacillary dysentery caused by Shigella, Salmonella, Campylobacter and EHEC E. coli mostly lead to a abrupt onset of the disease [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Since we did not take samples from individuals administered with any antibiotic, therefore cases of antibiotic associated diarrhea were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Stool samples of chronic/acute diarrhea as diagnosed by Gastroenterologist were collected from Gastroenterology department of All India Institute of Medical Sciences &amp; Safdarjung hospitals, New Delhi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The samples were transported to the laboratory at 4°C within 2 hrs and stored at -20°C until processed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the research ethics board of respective institutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The samples (n = 550) were collected with the informed consent of the patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Enrichment of entamoeba cysts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Cysts were enriched following the protocol of Knight et al., 1976 [16] with slight modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Briefly, fecal samples (1gm) were homogenized in 10 ml of autoclaved distilled water, strained through cheesecloth in 50 ml falcon tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>This suspension was centrifuged at 2000 rpm for 5 min and pellet was re-dissolved in 10 ml of 10% formaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>3 ml of diethyl ether was added to the tube and this mixture was vortexed and incubated at RT for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The mixture was subjected to centrifugation at 2000 rpm for 5 min, supernatant was removed and pellet was washed with double distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The Pellet containing concentrated cyst was re-dissolved in 400 μl T10E1 buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Cysts in T10E1 buffer was subjected to freeze-thaw cycle and thereafter to sonication in order to obtain crude DNA for Dot-blot hybridization experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Screening of samples by dot blot hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The crude cyst DNA was denatured by addition of NaOH to final concentration of 0.25 N in a total volume of 300 μl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The DNA was kept at room temperature for 30 minutes and then transferred on to ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The GS + nylon membrane of required size was cut and saturated in 0.4 M Tris-Cl, pH 7.5 for 15 min and the DNA were spotted on to the membrane with the help of mini-fold apparatus from Whatman, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The blots were air dried and UV cross linked before hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We used 4.5 kb rDNA fragment (EcoRI to Hind III site) from HMe region of EhR1 (rDNA plasmid in HM1:IMSS strain of E.histolytica) as probe for detection of Entamoeba positive samples that include both E.histolytica and E. dispar (Figure 1A) [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Screening of stool samples by Dot-Blot method. (A) Linear map of EhRI episome (24.5 kb) showing the position of HMe probe (4.5 kb in size) common for both E. histolytica and E. dispar), E - EcoR1 site and H- Hind III site; rDNA I and rDNA II represent two inverted repeats of transcription units with various restriction sites and repeats (B) Representative figure of Dot-blot analysis of stool sample using HMe probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Rows 1 to 6 (column A-D) represent spots of DNA from stool samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>About 20 ng of DNA was loaded on each spot in triplicate on nylon membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Row 7 was blank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Row 8 (column A) E. histolytica HM1: IMSS genomic DNA as positive control; (column B) E. dispar SAW760 genomic DNA as positive control; (column C) E.Coli DH5α as negative control; (column D) Plasmid with cloned HMe as positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>All samples were loaded in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Experimental details are provided in material and methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from the Dot blot positive samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of 200 mg stool sample was used for isolation using QIAamp mini stool kit (QIAGEN,Germany) as per manufacturer’s guidelines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>While isolating DNA from the stool samples through the above kit, pGEMT-easy plasmid containg 240 bp fragment of glycoprotein B (gB) gene of phocine virus (20 ng/200 μl of ASL buffer) was added in ASL buffer as internal control during the isolation of genomic DNA [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>PCR analysis of Dot blot positive samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>To differentiate Dot-blot positive samples into E. histolytica and E. dispar, primers were designed from EhSINE2 for E. histolytica and from 18 S and ITS2 region of rDNA circle for E. dispar respectively (Figure 2A &amp; B). Primer sequences were as follows; Eh-F 5’-GTCAGAGACACCACATGAA-3’, Eh-R 5’-GAGACCCCTTAAAGAAAC -CC-3’ and Ed-F 5’-GAAGAAACATTGTTTCTAAATCCAA-3’ &amp; Ed-R 5’-TTTATTAA CTC ACTTATA-3’ [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Screening of Stool samples by PCR. (A) Schematic representation of location of Entamoeba histolytica specific primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>BH16197 is Genbank accession number of Entamoeba histolytica SINE-2 (EhSINE2) element; (B) Schematic representation of location of Entamoeba dispar specific primer from rDNA molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>18 S, 5.8 S and 28 S are corresponding ribosomal gene sequences and ITS-1 and ITS-2 refers to internal transcribed spacer 1 and 2; (C) Detection of E. histolytica in stool DNA sample using E. histolytica specific primers, Lane 1 = Marker 100 bp, Lane 2 = EhHM1 genomic DNA as positive control, Lane 3 &amp; 4 stool sample DNA, Lane 5 = Genomic DNA of E. dispar SAW760 as negative control. Sample in lane 4 is E. histolytica positive; (D) Detection of E. dispar in Stool sample using E. dispar specific primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Lane 1 = Marker 1 kb, Lane 2,3,4 and 5 stool sample DNA, Lane 6 = Genomic DNA of E. dispar as positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Sample in Lane 3 and 5 are E. dispar positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Lane 4 stool sample is E. histolytica positive and was used as negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Primer designing for detection of predominant genera of gut flora </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Primer sets were designed to differentiate and quantitate the following major anaerobic genera –Bacteroides, Clostridium, Campylobacter, Bifidobacterium, Ruminococcus, Eubacterium, Lactobacillus, Methanobrevibacter and Sulfate-reducing bacteria (SRB).16S rRNA gene was targeted for designing primers except for SRB (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Sulphate reducing gene was targeted for quantifying members of SRB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Primers were commercially obtained from Sigma-aldrich, USA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Genus specific 16S rRNA targeted bacterial primers used in this study </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Sr no. </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Genus </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Primer sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>PCR Product (bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Tm(ºC) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>References </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Methanobrevibactr </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>F 5’- CGATGCGGACTTGGTGTTG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>184 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>59.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>R 5’-TGTCGCCTCTGGTGAGATGTC-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>59.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Peptostreptococcus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>F 5’-AACTCCGGTGGTATCAGATG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>270 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>55.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>[1] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>R 5’-GGGGCTTCTGAGTCAGGTA-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>56.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Ruminococcus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>F 5’-GAAAGCGTGGGGAGCAAACAGG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>302 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>65.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>R 5’- GACGACAACCATGCACCACCTG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>64.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Eubacterium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>F 5’-GTAGTCCACGCCGTAAACGATG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>278 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>60.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>R 5’-ACACGAGCTGACGACAACCATG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>62.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Bacteroides </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>F 5’- GGGGTTCTGAGAGGAAG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>54.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>R 5’- GCTACTTGGCTGGTTCAG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>56.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Lactobacillus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>F 5’-GCAGCAGTAGGGAATCTTCCA-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>340 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>64.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>[25] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>R 5’-GCATTYCACCGCTACACATG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>58.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>7. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Clostridium leptum subgroup </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>F 5’-CGTCAGCTCGTGTCGTGAGAT-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>125 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>60.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>R 5’-CGTCATCCCCACCTTCCTCC-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>62.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>8. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Clostridium coccoides subgroup </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>F 5’-GCCACATTGGGACTGAGA-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>170 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>56.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This study </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>R 5’-GCTTCTTAGTCAGGTACCG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>58.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>9. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Campylobacter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>F 5’-AGGGAATATTGCGCAATGGGGGAAA-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>180 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>58.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>R 5’- GATTCCGAGTAACGCTTGCACCCT-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>59.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>10. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Bifidobacterium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>F 5’-GATTCTGGCTCAGGATGAACGC-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>231 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>61.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>[21] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>R 5’-CTGATAGGACGCGACCCCAT-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>60.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>11. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Sulfate-reducing bacteria (APS reductase subunit A gene) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>F 5’-TGGCAGATMATGATYMACGG-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>396 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>54. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This study </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>R 5’-GGCCGTAACCGTCCTTGAA-3’ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>54.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Primers for detection and quantification of nim gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Primers were designed from nim gene after Stephanie Trinh et al. [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences were as follows; NIM-F (5’-ATGTTCAGAGAAATGCGGCGTAAGCG-3’) and NIM-R (5’-GCTTCCTTGCCTGTCAT GTGCTC-3’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Primers Nim-F and Nim-R designed by us amplify all the members of nim gene family viz. nimA, nimB, nimC, nimD and nimE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Primers were commercially synthesized from Sigma-Aldrich, USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Primers NIM-F&amp;R did not amplify genomic DNA derived from axenic culture of E. histolytica HM1-IMSS [1] and blast result of the selected primers did not show any homology with E. histolytica genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>NIM-F&amp;R primers amplified 458 bp fragment of nim gene from stool sample DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>This amplified fragment of 458 bp was cloned in pGEMT-easy vector and sequenced to ensure the amplification of correct gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The clone was subsequently used as a standard for quantification of nim gene by Real Time-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>PCR-RFLP of nim gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Primers NIM-F and NIM-R were used to amplify all the members of nim gene family from stool sample DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Members of nim gene family were differentiated by digesting the PCR product with restriction enzymes HpaII and TaqI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>HpaII digests nimA, nimC, nimD at different loci but not nimB and nimE where as TaqI digests nimA, nimB, nimE at different loci but not nimC and nimD[19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Reference strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Genus specific primers were used to amplify respected genera from DNA of stool sample of healthy individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The amplified product was cloned and sequenced and sequences were deposited in EMBL database to obtain the accession numbers (Table 2).These 16S rRNA gene fragment containing plasmids were used as reference strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Accession number of reference strain used in the study </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Bacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Source </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Accession no. </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Bacteroides </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>AM117604 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Methanobrevibacter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>FN813615 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Eubacterium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>FN813614 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Lactobacillus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>AM042701 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Bifidobacterium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>AM042698 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Clostridium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>AM042697 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Campylobacter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>AM042699 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Ruminococcus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>FN823053 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Sulfate-reducing bacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Stool of healthy individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>FN995351 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Real time PCR analysis of bacterial population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Quantification was done using ABI-7500 machine and power syber green PCR master mix kit from Applied Biosystems, USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Standard curve was the method of choice for absolute quantification of bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Standard curve was made using serial dilutions of plasmid (containing 16S rRNA gene fragment) of known concentrations on tenfold basis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>With the molecular weight of the plasmid and insert known, it is possible to calculate the copy number as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Step 1: Determining molecular weight (mw) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Weight in Daltons (g/mol) = (bp size of double stranded product)(330 Da x 2nt/bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Step 2: Molecular weight to copy number </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>X g/mol/Avogadro’s number (6.023 × 1023 molecules/mole) = X g/molecule </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Where X = the weight of one molecule or copy </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Where bp = base pairs, nt = nucleotides [20] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Real time PCR runs were performed in 96 well optical plates (each containing 1x PCR master mix, 4 pm/μl forward and reverse primer(optimized concentration) and 1μl plasmid DNA of tenfold dilutions or 1μl DNA from samples in 20μl reaction) for 40 cycles using an ABI 7500 sequence detector (Applied biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Default 7500 cycle conditions were used with only change in the annealing temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>A standard curve was drawn by plotting the natural log of the threshold cycle (Ct) against the natural log of the number of molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Melting curves were obtained from 55°C to 90°C, with fluorescence measurements taken at every 1°C increase in temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>All reactions were carried out in triplicate along with a non-template control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Ct values were calculated under default settings for the absolute quantification using the software provided with the instrument. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The equation drawn from the graph was used to calculate the precise number of target molecule (plasmid copy no. or number of bacteria) tested in same reaction plate as standard as well as in sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Graph of respective bacterial population is plotted as mean value with standard error. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Each sample was analyzed in triplicate for calculation of significant differences in bacterial population by the Man-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>P values of 0.05 or below considered as significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Paired samples collected from healthy volunteers before and after satronidazole treatment were analyzed by Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed rank test (two tailed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Analysis was done using GraphPad Prism-5 software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Screening of E. histolytica positive samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>DNA from concentrated cyst was subjected to Dot-blot hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Dot blot analysis of 550 samples yielded 39 samples (7%) that were positive for Entamoeba (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The DNA from Entamoeba positive samples were subjected to PCR using species specific primers of E. histolytica and E. dispar (Figure 2C &amp; D). Out of 39 samples, 17 samples (43%) were positive for E. histolytica. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>None of the samples in our study population were found positive for both the species of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Quantification of predominant flora </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>High quality DNA isolated from E. histolytica positive stool sample was subjected to Real Time analysis to assess the predominant gut flora that included Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium, Eubacterium, Clostridium leptum subgroup, Clostridium coccoides subgroup, Lactobacillus and Ruminococcus. Two subdominant genera Methanobrevibacter smithii and Sulphur reducing bacteria (SRB) were also quantified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Validation of primers designed by us for the above genera have already been reported [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In addition to the above primers, here we report a Real time analysis of nim gene copy number for which a standard curve and amplification curve have been drawn that shows specific and efficient quantification with slope = −3.6 and R2 =0.998 (Figure 3A &amp; B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Real-time analysis for quantification of different bacterial genera in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive (Eh + ve) samples. (A) Bacteroides (B) Clostridium coccoides subgroup (C) Clostridium leptum subgroup (D) Lactobacillus (E) Campylobacter (F) Eubacterium. P value = .05 or below was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>CI stands for confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Our analysis reveals that during healthy conditions, the members of Bacteroides were the most abundant in number among the predominant targeted genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>However, a significant decrease was observed in population of Bacteroides (p = .001) in E. histolytica positive samples when compared to that of Healthy control samples (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Simultaneously, we also observed a significant decrease in the population of Closrtridium coccoides subgroup (p = 0.002), Clostridium leptum subgroup (p = 0.0001), Lactobacillus (p = 0.037), Campylobacter (p = 0.0014) and Eubacterium (p = 0.038) in E. histolytica positive samples in comparison to control (Figure 4B, C, D, E and F respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, we observed a significant rise in the population of Bifidobacterium (p = 0.009) in amebic samples when compared with healthy control samples (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>No significant changes were observed in population of Rumminococcus (p = 0.33) (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Though we did not observe any significant change in the population of Methanobrevibacter (p = 0.96) and Sulphur reducing bacteria (p = 0.88) in amoebic samples but the prevalence rate was reduced (Additional file 1: Figure S1A &amp; B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Real-time analysis of population of (A) Rumminococcus in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive (Eh + ve) samples (B) Bifidobacterium in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive (Eh + ve) samples. P value = .05 or below was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>CI stands for confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Detection and identification of nim gene in stool samples. (A) Detection of nim gene using nim gene specific primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Lane 1 = Marker 100 bp, Lane 2 = clone of nim gene as positive control, Lane 3–5 = DNA from stool samples from healthy volunteer, Lane 6–8 = DNA from stool samples from E. histolytica positive patients and Lane 9 = No template control PCR (B) Restriction map of TaqI restriction sites in 458 bp nimE gene fragment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>(C) HpaII does not digest nimE,where as digestion of nimE by TaqI generates four fragment of 274 bp,155 bp,6 bp and 25 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Lane 1 = Marker 100 bp, Lane H1, H2, E1 and E2 show RFLP profile of PCR product digested with HpaII; Lane H3, H4, E3 and E4 show RFLP profile of PCR product digested with TaqI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>H1-H4, DNA from stool samples of Healthy volunteers and E1-E4 are DNA from stool samples of E. histolytica positive patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-5"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Copy no. of nim gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>We found the presence of nim genes in 72.7% of control stool samples (n = 22) and in 41% of Entamoeba histolytica infected patients (n = 17) by PCR (Figure 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Further the amplified product was cloned and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>BLAST analysis revealed 99% sequence homology with nimE gene (Accession no. AM117602.1), a member of nim gene family [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the PCR products from all the samples of healthy and amebic individuals were subjected to RFLP analysis using HpaII and TaqI restriction enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>PCR-RFLP pattern confirmed the presence of only nimE gene in all the samples analyzed (Figure 6B &amp; C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Real time analysis of nim gene in the stool samples exhibited sample to sample variation (4 × 102 to 4 × 105 copies) in the both category of samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>We observed a significant increase in copy no. of nim gene in E. histolytica positive samples vs samples from healthy persons (p = 0.025) (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Detemination of copy number of nimE gene by Real-time PCR. (A) Standard curve, slope = −3.6 and R2 = 0.998 showing good efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>(B) Dissociation curve showing specific amplification of target (nimE gene) and NTC = No template control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>(C) Absolute quantification of copy no. of nimE gene in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(D) Absolute quantification of copy no. of nimE gene in stool sample DNA of Healthy volunteers before and after satronidazole treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>P value = .05 or below was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>CI stands for confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>To see the effect of antiamoebic drug Satronidazole (Alchem pharmaceuticals) on nim gene copy number, healthy volunteers (n = 5) were advised to take the drug (300 mg tablets) twice daily after meals for 4 days and copy of nim gene was quantified before and after the treatment using the primers described here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed rank test (two tailed) analysis of copy no. of nim gene shows no significant change (p = 0.125) in stool samples collected before and after treatment (Figure 3D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Infection by E. histolytica is normally initiated by the ingestion of fecally contaminated water or food containing E. histolytica cysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis of colonic bacteria has been considered as a possible stimulus to induce the invasive behavior by the parasite [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Adult gut microbiota are quite stable in individuals and can even be restored after perturbation [24,25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Our earlier results have shown significant changes in expression of EhCaBP and LPG only after the axenic E. histolytica had been adapted to grow with bacterial flora for a number of generatiom, and not in short term culture [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>In the present study we tried to evaluate perturbations in commensal gut flora caused as result of E. histolytica infection using Real Time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>qPCR methodology is less expensive, more quantitative and is more efficient in terms of time and operation [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The absolute proportions of eight predominant commensal and two subdominant genera were quantified successfully in our samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Bacteroides species are a pleomorphic group of non-spore forming gram-negative anaerobic bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Bacteroides are the most dominant part of the normal indigenous flora in the human gut. Bacteroides are mostly represented by Bacteroides ovatus, Bacteroides uniformis Bacteroides vulgatus, Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron, Bacteroides distasonis, and less frequently by Bacteroides eggerthii and Bacteroides fragilis. These bacteria are significant contributors to the carbohydrate metabolism, nutrition and health of humans and animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>In 1999 Hooper et al. demonstrated that B. thetaiotaomicron can modify intestinal fucosylation in a complex interaction mediated by fucose repressor gene and a signaling system [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The significant decrease in population of Bacteroides during disease condition dampens the beneficial effects of this genera to host. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>In the human intestinal tract, Eubacterium is the second most common genus after the genus Bacteroides. The genus Eubacterium comprises a nutritionally diverse group of organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>The members of genus Eubacterium are known to produce butyrate [29], degrade flavonoids (from vegetables, fruits, nuts, and tea) [30] and are implicated in steroid and bile transformation in intestine [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The decrease in population of Eubacterium sp. observed in our study may reduce the butyrate production and may also affect the capacity of the host in proper digestion of the above ingredients of food. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Bifidobacterium species are common inhabitants of the gastrointestinal tract, and they have received special attention because of their health-promoting effects in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Members of Bifidobacteria produce enough acetate (SCFA) in proximal and distal colon by fermentation of glucose and fructose [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Members of both Bifidobacteria and Ruminococcus -Ruminococcus torques and Bifidobacterium bifidum are thought to ferment mucin and compete to colonise this substrate for their energy source [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Our result shows a significant increase in population of Bifidobacterium but no change in population of Rumminococcous despite decrease in population of several other targeted genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>It is quite well known that mucus secretion is increased in E. histolytica infection especially during dysentery which is probably result of a mechanism exerted by intestinal epithelial cells to counter the adherence of E. histolytica trophozoites to intestinal epithelial surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The protozoan parasite Entamoeba histolytica cleaves Mucin 2 (MUC2) in the non-glycosylated oligomerization domains by cysteine protease, thus breaking down the macromolecular structure and reducing mucus viscosity [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Perhaps under this condition, a cross-talk between the mucosal layer, bacteria and the parasite initiates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>As a result, the intestinal epithelial cells tend to produce more of mucin for protection that promotes colonization of Bifidobacteria in one hand and on the other hand the parasite competes to more release of mucin for its adhesion to epithelial layer. Bifidobacteria longum are known to protect the gut from enteropathogenic infection through production of acetate [32] and acetate is major energy source for colonocytes but a fine balance in population of different bacterial genera of gut is needed for healthy colon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>The C. leptum subgroup and C. coccoides subgroup are one of the most predominant populations of human fecal microflora which contains a large number of butyrate-producing bacteria [35,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Butyrate is a SCFA (Short chain fatty acids) having a strong effect on the cell cycle and acts as anti-inflammatory molecule in the gut. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Effects on mucosal defense include improved tight junction assembly, antimicrobial secretion and mucin expression [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The decrease in population of members of C. leptum subgroup and C. coccoides subgroup observed here leads to decrease in the production of SCFA and hence renders the host more susceptible for future infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The genus Lactobacillus comprises a large heterogenous group of low G + C gram positive, non sporulating, anaerobic bacteria belonging to phylum Firmicutes. Lactobacilli are known to fortify epithelial barrier by various mechanism such as induction of mucin secretion, enhancement of tight-junction functioning, upregulation of cytoprotective heat shock proteins and prevention of apoptosis of epithelial cells [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Probiotic strains of Lactobacillus are known to prevent infectious diarrhea, antibiotic associated diarrhea and diarrhea in children who are unusually more susceptible as a result of poor nutrition, impaired immune status or frequent exposure to pathogens [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>We observed significant decrease in population of Lactobacillus in gut flora of E. histolytica positive patients as compared to that of healthy individuals that support our earlier observation made by semi quantitative method [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Methanobrevibacter smithii is the dominant archaeon in human gut that affects the specificity and efficiency of bacterial digestion of dietary polysaccharides, thereby influencing host calorie harvest and adiposity [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that the low and variable prevalence of Methanobrevibacter smithii and Methanosphaera stadtmanae DNA in human stool contrasts with the paramount role of these methanogenic archaea in digestion processes and hypothesized that this contrast is a consequence of the inefficiencies of current protocols for archaea DNA extraction [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>In our samples prevalence of M. smithii in healthy individuals stool samples was 27.27 % and that was further reduced to 11.7 % in E. histolytica positive samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Real-time analysis shows no significant alteration in population of M. smithii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Variation in the loads of M. smithii under different pathophysiological condition such as during amebiasis has not been reported so far. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Suphate reducing bacteria (SRB) are a group of non spore forming, gram negative, dissimilatory sulphate reducing, anaerobic bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>SRB can be isolated from the intestinal tract of humans and various environmental sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Intestinal SRB’s growth and resultant hydrogen sulfide production have been implicated to damage the gastrointestinal tract and thereby contribute to chronic intestinal disorders [42]. Desulfovibrio fairfieldensis and D. desulfuricans have been associated with incidence of bacteremia and D. vulgaris has been associated with intra-abdominal infections [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of Sulphate reducing bacteria was 36.36% in healthy and 11.7% in amoebic individuals stool samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>However, the change was not statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>The genus Campylobacter is notorious for causing gastroenritis by C. jejuni but uncultured Campylobacter species e.g. Campylobacter hominis whose role is not clear yet, do exist in lower gastrointestinal tract of healthy humans [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>We observed significant decrease in population of Campylobacter in E. histolytica positive individual as compared to healthy individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>As our primers were genus specific, so decrease in Campylobacter was genera specific and not species specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Significant increase in the population of Campylobacter has been observed in IBD [21] but we did not find the same trend in amoebic patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Several species of Bacteroides are known to harbor nim genes e.g. B. fragilis, B. distasonis, B. thetaiotaomicron, B. vulgatus, B. ovatus but wide differences in MIC values of metronidazole are observed, ranging from 1.5 to &gt;256 mg/L and some are also found above the therapeutic breakpoint of 16 mg/L [45].Though the population of Bacteroides is decreased significantly in E. histolytica positive patients however we have observed high copy no. of nimE gene in the same. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>We attribute this increase to the presence of plasmid coded nimE gene as has been observed earlier in Veillonella sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>[46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Future analyses that target specific members of the Bacteroides group will shed further light on the species involved in the expansion of nimE gene. In 2006, Rani et al. reported presence of nim gene in stool samples of amebic individuals but not in healthy individuals [1] but our result show high prevalence rate of nim gene even in healthy individuals irrespective of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>However in a hospital based study carried out in Greece revealed low level of prevalence of nim gene in isolates of different anaerobic bacterial species from hospitalized patients [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Though the presence of nim gene in gut of healthy north Indian population is shocking but this may be explained due to easy over the counter drug availability in India. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Results on healthy individuals undergoing Satronidazole treatment indicate that nimE gene copy number does not show significant reduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>It can therefore be assumed that nimE gene harboring Bacteroides probably cause inactivation of nitroimidazole drug and thereby reduce the bioavailability of drug to the parasite and hence may help in sustaining the infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>The metabolic activities of the predominant gut flora have a significant effect on the health of the human colon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>The current findings of depleted populations of metabolically important bacteria like Bacteroides, C. leptum and C. coccoides sub groups, Lactobacillus sp., Eubacterium sp., and Campylobacter sp. add to our knowledge of the changes in the GI tracts of amebic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Such changes in bacterial population in the normal microbiota could have considerable consequences in terms of functional potential of gut flora and could result in metabolic conditions favorable for the establishment of opportunistic pathogens (e.g. Clostridium difficile). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>However, our study cannot conclude that observed changes in the gut flora is the cause or effect of the infection or the effect of dysenteric mechanism per se by the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Our findings could potentially guide implementation of dietary/probiotic interventions that impact the gut microbiota and improve GI health in individuals infected with Entamoeba histolytica. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>SRB: Sulphur reducing bacteria; RFLP: Restriction fragment length polymorphism; MUC2: Mucin 2; SCFA: Short-chain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>We declare that no competing interests exist among the authors </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>JP conceived and coordinated the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>AKV carried out the bacterial quantification experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>AKV and RV conducted the copy number calculation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>JP and AKV drafted the manuscript and conducted the statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>VA made the diagnosis of the patients, interpretation of data and collaborated in collection of the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Real time analysis of population of (A) Methanobrevibacter in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive samples (B) Sulphur reducing bacteria in Healthy vs E. histolytica positive sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>P value = .05 or below was considered significant. Cl stands for confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2180-12-183-S1.pptx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Click here for file </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgement</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by a research grant to JP from the Department of Biotechnology, Government of India. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>AKV is grateful to the Indian Council of Medical Research, New Delhi, India and RV to University Grants Commission, New Delhi for Research fellowships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>We gratefully acknowledge the subjects who participated in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>RaniRMurthyRSBhattacharyaSAhujaVRizviMAPaulJChanges in Bacterial profile during amebiasis: Demonstration of anaerobic bacteria in ALA pus samplesAm J Trop Med Hyg20067588088517123981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>JiaWLiHZhaoLNicholsonJKGut microbiota: a potential new territory for drug targetingNat Rev Drug Discov2008712312910.1038/nrd250518239669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>WhitmanWBColemanDCWiebeWJProkaryotes: The unseen majorityProc Natl Acad Sci USA1998956578658310.1073/pnas.95.12.65789618454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>SonnenburgJLAngenentLTGordonJIGetting a grip on things: how do communities of bacterial symbionts become established in our intestine?Nat Immunol2004556957310.1038/ni107915164016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>XuJGordonJIHonor thy symbiontsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2003100104521045910.1073/pnas.173406310012923294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>GuarnerFEnteric flora in health and diseaseDigestion200673suppl 151216498248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>O’HaraAMShanahanFThe gut flora as a forgotten organEMBO Rep2006768869310.1038/sj.embor.740073116819463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>LeyREPetersonDAGordonJIEcological and Evolutionary Forces Shaping Microbial Diversity in the Human IntestineCell200612483784810.1016/j.cell.2006.02.01716497592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>HaqueRHustonCDHughesMHouptEPetriWAJrAmoebiasisN Engl J Med20033481565157310.1056/NEJMra02271012700377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>MirelmanDAmeba-bacterium relationship in amoebiasisMicrobiol Rev1987512722842885733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>MukherjeeCClarkCGLohiaAEntamoeba Shows Reversible Variation in Ploidy under Different Growth Conditions and between Life Cycle PhasesPLoS Negl Trop Dis20082e28110.1371/journal.pntd.000028118714361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>SimonGLGorbachSLIntestinal flora in health and diseaseGastroenterology1984861741936357937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>LeirosHKSKozielski-StuhrmannSKappUTerradotLLeonardGAMcSweeneySMStructural Basis of 5-Nitroimidazole Antibiotic ResistanceJ Biol Chem2004279558405584910.1074/jbc.M40804420015492014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>TrinhSReyssetGDetection by PCR of the nim Genes Encoding 5-Nitroimidazole Resistance in Bacteroides sppJ Clin Microbiol199634207820848862561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>PetriWAJrAmebiasisCurrent treatment options in Infectious diseases20035269272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>KnightWBHiattRAClineBLRitchieLSA Modification of the Formol-Ether Concentration Technique for Increased Sensitivity in Detecting Schistosoma Mansoni EggsAm J Trop Med Hyg1976258188231008127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>SrivastvaSBhattacharyaSPaulJSpecies and strain-specific probes derived from repetitive DNA for distinguishing Entamoeba histolytica and Entamoeba disparExp Parasitol200511030330810.1016/j.exppara.2005.02.02015955328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>NiestersHGMClinical virology in realtimeJ Clin Virol200225S3S1212467772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>StubbsSLJBrazierJTalbotPRDuerdenBIPCR-Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism Analysis for Identification of Bacteroides spp. and Characterization of Nitroimidazole Resistance GenesJ Clin Microbiol2000383209321310970359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>WhelanJARussellNBWhelanMAA method for the absolute quantification of cDNA using real-time PCRJ Immunol Methods200327826126910.1016/S0022-1759(03)00223-012957413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>VermaRVermaAKAhujaVPaulJReal-Time Analysis of Mucosal Flora in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease in IndiaJ Clin Microbiol2010484279428210.1128/JCM.01360-1020861337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>AltschulSFGishWMillerWMyersEWLipmanDJBasic local alignment search toolJ Mol Biol19902154034102231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Galvan-MoroyoquiJMDomı′nguez-RoblesMDCFrancoEMezaIThe Interplay between Entamoeba and Enteropathogenic Bacteria Modulates Epithelial Cell DamagePlos Neg Trop Dis20082e26610.1371/journal.pntd.0000266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>SeksikPRigottier-GoisLGrametGSutrenMPochartPMarteauPJianRDoréJAlterations of the dominant faecal bacterial groups in patients with Crohn’s disease of the colonGut20035223724210.1136/gut.52.2.23712524406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>TannockGWMunroKHarmsenHJMWellingGWSmartJGopalPKAnalysis of the fecal microflora of human subjects consuming a probiotic product containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus DR20Appl Environ Microbiol2000662578258810.1128/AEM.66.6.2578-2588.200010831441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>BhattacharayaAAnandMTPaulJYadavNBhattacharayaSMolecular Changes in Entamoeba histolytica in Response to BacteriaJ Euk Microbiol19984528S33S10.1111/j.1550-7408.1998.tb04521.x9561781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>HartmanALLoughDMBarupalDKFiehnOFishbeinTZasloffMEisenJAHuman gut microbiome adopts an alternative state following small bowel transplantationProc Natl Acad Sci USA2009106171871719210.1073/pnas.090484710619805153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>HooperLVXuJFalkPGMidtvedtTGordonJIA molecular sensor that allows a gut commensal to control its nutrient foundation in a competitive ecosystemProc Natl Acad Sci USA1999969833983810.1073/pnas.96.17.983310449780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>KanauchiOFujiyamaYMitsuyamaKArakiYIshiiTNakamuraTHitomiYAgataKSaikiTAndohAToyonagaABambaTIncreased growth of Bifidobacterium and Eubacterium by germinated barley foodstuff, accompanied by enhanced butyrate production in healthy volunteersInt J Mol Med199931751799917526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>SimmeringRKleessenBBlautMQuantification of the Flavonoid-Degrading Bacterium Eubacterium ramulus in Human Fecal Samples with a Species-Specific Oligonucleotide Hybridization ProbeAppl Env Microbiol1999653705370910427069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>HopkinsMJMacfarlaneGTChanges in predominant bacterial populations in human faeces with age and with Clostridium difficile infectionJ Med Microbiol20025144845411990498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>FukudaSTohHHaselKOshimaKNakanishiYYoshimuraKTobeTClarkeJMToppingDLSuzukiTTaylorTDItohKKikuchiJMoritaHHattoriMOhnoHBifidobacteria can protect from enteropathogenic infection through production of acetateNature201146954354710.1038/nature0964621270894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>LeitchECWalkerAWDuncanSHHoltropGFlintHJSelective colonization of insoluble substrates by human faecal bacteriaEnv Microbiol2007966767910.1111/j.1462-2920.2006.01186.x17298367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>LidellMEMoncadaDMChadeeKHanssonGCEntamoeba histolytica cysteine proteases cleave the MUC2 mucin in its C-terminal domain and dissolve the protective colonic mucus gelProc Natl Acad Sci USA20061039298930310.1073/pnas.060062310316754877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>PrydeSEDuncanSHHoldGLStewartCSFlintHJThe microbiology of butyrate formation in the human colonFEMS Microbiol Lett200221713313910.1111/j.1574-6968.2002.tb11467.x12480096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>RobertCBernalier-DonadilleAThe cellulolytic microflora of the human colon: evidence of microcrystalline cellulose-degrading bacteria in methane-excreting subjectsFEMS Microbiol Eco200346818910.1016/S0168-6496(03)00207-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>WillingBPRussellSLFinlayBBShifting the balance: antibiotic effects on host–microbiota mutualismNat Rev Microbiol2011923324310.1038/nrmicro253621358670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>LebeerSVanderleydenJDe KeersmaeckerSCJGenes and Molecules of Lactobacilli supporting Probiotic ActionMicrobiol Mol Biol Rev20087272876410.1128/MMBR.00017-0819052326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Van NeilCWFeudtnerCGarrisonMMChristakisDALactobacillus therapy for acute infectious diarrhea in children:A meta analysisPediatrics200210967868410.1542/peds.109.4.67811927715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>SamuelBSHansenEEManchesterJKCoutinhoPMHenrissatBFultonRLatreillePKimKWilsonRKGordonJIGenomic and metabolic adaptations of Methanobrevibacter smithii to the human gutProc Natl Acad Sci USA2007104106431064810.1073/pnas.070418910417563350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>DridiBHenryMKhechineAERaoultDDrancourtMHigh Prevalence of Methanobrevibacter smithii and Methanosphaera stadtmanae detected in the Human Gut Using an Improved DNA Detection ProtocolPLoS One20094e706310.1371/journal.pone.000706319759898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>DeplanckeBHristovaKROakleyHAMcCrackenVJAminovRMackieRIGaskinsHRMolecular ecological analysis of the succession and diversity of Sulphate reducing bacteria in mouse gastrointestinal tractAppl Env Microbiol2000662166217410.1128/AEM.66.5.2166-2174.200010788396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>GoldsteinEJCCitronDMPerainoVACrossSADesulfovibrio desulfuricans Bacterimia and Review of Human Desulfovibrio infectionsJ Clin Microbiol2003412752275410.1128/JCM.41.6.2752-2754.200312791922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>LawsonAJLintonDStanleyJ16 s rRNA gene sequences of 'Candidatus Campylobacter horninis', a novel uncultivated species, are found in the gastrointestinal tract of healthy humansMicrobiol19981442063207110.1099/00221287-144-8-2063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>GalMBrazierJSMetronidazole resistance in Bacteroides spp. carrying nim genes and the selection of slow-growing metronidazole-resistant mutantsJ Antimicrob Chemother20045410911610.1093/jac/dkh29615190033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>MarchandinHJean-PierreHCamposJnimE Gene in a Metronidazole-SusceptibleVeillonellasp StrainAntimicrob Agents Chemother2004483207320810.1128/AAC.48.8.3207-3208.200415273153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>KatsandriAAvlamisAPantazatouAHouhoulaDPPapaparaskevasJDissemination of nim-class genes, encoding nitroimidazole resistance, among different species of Gram-negative anaerobic bacteria isolated in Athens, GreeceJ Antimicrob Chemother200610:1093/jac/dkl285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
