<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3829848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260239</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-26010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of Rice Black-Streaked Dwarf Virus P7-1 in Arabidopsis Results in Male Sterility Due to Non-Dehiscent Anthers </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RBSDV P7-1 Causes Male Sterility in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Qiufang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Yongjian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Key Laboratory of Monitoring and Management of Plant Virus Diseases, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhengguang</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Nanjing Agricultural University, China</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yjzhou@jaas.ac.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: FS QX TX YZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: FS XY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: FS QX YF YX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TZ YF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: FS YZ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e79514</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Sun et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sun et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Rice black-streaked dwarf virus (RBSDV), a member of the genus Fijivirus in the family Reoviridae, is propagatively transmitted by the small brown planthopper (Laodelphax striatellus Fallén). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>RBSDV causes rice black-streaked dwarf and maize rough dwarf diseases, which lead to severe yield losses in crops in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Although several RBSDV proteins have been studied in detail, the functions of the nonstructural protein P7-1 are still largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>To investigate the role of the P7-1 protein in virus pathogenicity, transgenic Arabidopsis thaliana plants were generated in which the P7-1 gene was expressed under the control of the 35S promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The RBSDV P7-1-transgenic Arabidopsis plants (named P7-1-OE) were male sterility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Flowers and pollen from P7-1-transgenic plants were of normal size and shape, and anthers developed to the normal size but failed to dehisce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The non-dehiscent anthers observed in P7-1-OE were attributed to decreased lignin content in the anthers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the reactive oxygen species levels were quite low in the transgenic plants compared with the wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that ectopic expression of the RBSDV P7-1 protein in A. thaliana causes male sterility, possibly through the disruption of the lignin biosynthesis and H2O2-dependent polymerization pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Plan, 2010CB126203), the National Nature Science Foundation of China (31201484, 31000841), the Special Fund for Agro-scientific Research in the Public Interest (201003031, 201303021). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Rice black-streaked dwarf virus (RBSDV), a member of the genus Fijivirus in the family Reoviridae, causes rice black-streaked dwarf and maize rough dwarf diseases, which lead to severe yield losses in crops in China, Japan, Korea, and other Asian countries [1], [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The virus is propagatively transmitted by the small brown planthopper (SBPH: Laodelphax striatellus Fallén) in a persistent circulative manner [1], [3]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Plants infected with RBSDV typically exhibit symptoms such as stunting, darkening of leaves, and white waxy or black-streaked swellings along the veins on the backs of the leaf blades and sheaths [1], [3]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The RBSDV virion is composed of icosahedral, two-layered particles approximately 75–80 nm in diameter and 10 segments of double-stranded genomic RNA (dsRNA), which are designed S1 to S10 with increasing order of electrophoretic mobility in polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) [6], [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>S1 encodes a putative 169-kDa RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, while S2 and S4 encode a major core structural protein and the outer shell B-spike protein, respectively [6], [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The protein encoded by S3 contains a conserved motif and is a putative guanylyltransferase [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Western blotting analysis of viral particles has suggested that the minor core capsid protein and major outer capsid protein are encoded by S8 and S10, respectively [8], [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Immunoelectron microscopy has revealed that S9 ORF1 P9-1 is a nonstructural protein that accumulates in the intracellular viroplasms in infected plants and insects [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>P9-1, a thermostable, α-helical protein, self-interacts to form dimers and is the minimal viral component required for viroplasm formation [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The protein encoded by S6 is a viral RNA silencing suppressor and has an intrinsic ability to interact with P9-1 [13]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>P7-1 is a nonstructural protein containing 363 amino acids (with a molecular mass of 41.0 kDa) that is translated from S7 ORF1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>P7-1 accumulates in tubule-like structures in infected plant and planthopper cells, suggesting that P7-1 is one of the constituents of these structures [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Recent studies demonstrate that RBSDV P7-1 forms punctuate points at plasmodesmata in Nicotiana benthamiana leaves [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Tubule-forming and plasmodesmatal localization of RBSDV P7-1 are usually thought to be involved in cell-to-cell movement of the virus in plant and insect cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, little else is known about the characteristics and functions of P7-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this study, we determined that RBSDV P7-1 is a pathogenicity determinant and that this protein affects normal plant development when expressed as transgenes in Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>RBSDV P7-1 transgenic Arabidopsis plants exhibited male sterility phenotype caused by a defect of secondary wall lignification in the anther endothecium and failure of anther dehiscence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, non-dehiscent anthers observed in transgenic plants were accompanied by decreased levels reactive oxygen species (ROS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that impairment in lignin biosynthesis and the H2O2-dependent polymerization in RBSDV P7-1 over-expressing Arabidopsis plants cause male sterility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Virus Isolates, Vectors, and Plant Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Rice plants infected with RBSDV were collected from Jiangsu Province in China under the permission of Plant Protection Station of Jiangsu Province, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Young instar nymphs of SBPHs (small brown planthopper, L.striatellus) were fed RBSDV-infected rice plants for 2 days to acquire the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A dot immunobinding assay (DIBA) [3] showed that 20–30% of adult insects were viruliferous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A virus-free planthopper population was generated using a pair of recently hatched nymphs, and nonvirulence was confirmed using reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Viruliferous or virus-free SBPHs were reared on healthy rice seedlings (Oryza sativa L. japonica. cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Wuyujing No. 3) in glass vessels at 22°C under alternating photoperiods of 14 h of light and 10 h of dark. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Arabidopsis (Col-0) seeds were donated by Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Hansong Dong (College of Plant Protection, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Plants were grown in potting soil in a growth chamber at 24°C under 200 µE·m−2·s−1 illumination and 16-h light/8-h dark cycle conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>RBSDV Inoculation Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Rice plants (Oryza sativa L. japonica. cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Nipponbare) were inoculated with 10 viruliferous (RBSDV) or virus-free (mock) nymphs per plant (4 or 5 leaves) and were kept in a growth chamber containing 30 plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>After incubation at 22°C for 4 days under artificial light, planthoppers were removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Plants were maintained in field conditions for symptom development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Construction of Overexpression Vector and Arabidopsis Transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To generate the RBSDV P7-1 overexpression plasmid, the coding region of the RBSDV P7-1 gene (from +1 to +1,089 bp) was amplified with primers containing the SacI and BamHI sites (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The resulting PCR product was digested with SacI and BamHI and ligated into the SacI-BamHI-cleaved pCHF3 vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>After DNA sequencing, the RBSDV P7-1 overexpression plasmid was introduced into Agrobacterium tumefaciens (strain EHA105), and the transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana Col-0 ecotype was performed by the floral-dip method [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Homozygous T3 generation plants were screened for kanamycin resistance and identified with genome PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>RBSDV P7-1 gene sequence has been deposited in NCBI Genbank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) under the accession number of KF532967. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Qenome DNA PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Arabidopsis genome DNA was isolated from leaves using SQ Plant DNA Kit (Omega Bioservices; Norcross, GA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>PCR reaction was performed using 10 µl Premix Taq (TAKARA; Dalian, China), 0.2 µM RBSDV S7-1 specific forward and reverse primers (Table S1), and 1 µl DNA in a total volume of 20 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>All samples were subjected to denaturation for 5 min at 95°C, followed by 30 cycles of 95°C for 30 s, 58°C for 30 s and 72°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>PCR products were detected using agarose gel electrophoresis, and images were obtained using the Bio-Rad Molecular Imager Gel Doc XR System (Bio-Rad; Hercules; CA, USA) after staining with ethidium bromide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Quantitative Real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed using SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix (Bio-Rad; Hercules; CA, USA) in a Bio-Rad iQ5 Real-Time PCR system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from leaves using the RNAiso Plus reagent (TAKARA; Dalian, China) and reverse transcribed using M-MLV Reverse Transcriptase (Promega; Fitchburg; WI, USA), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The EF1α gene, which is highly conserved and constitutively expressed in eukaryotes [18], was used as a reference control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Each quantitative PCR reaction was performed using 10 µl SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix, 0.2 µM forward and reverse primers, and 1 µl cDNA in a total volume of 20 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All samples were subjected to denaturation for 3 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 10 s and 58°C for 20 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>SYBR Green absorbance was detected at 58°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>All reactions were conducted in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Amplicon dissociation curves, i.e., melting curves, were recorded after cycle 40 by heating from 60°C to 95°C at a ramp speed of 1.9°C·min−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using iQ5 software (Bio-Rad; Hercules; CA, USA). Table S1 shows information regarding additional genes and primers employed in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Observation of Lignified Secondary Wall Thickening </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>For ethidium bromide staining, fresh anthers were washed in 10 mM PBS and 2% (v/v) Tween20 for 10 min and 10 mM PBS for 10 min, followed by staining with 0.05% (w/v) ethidium bromide (1 h, room temperature). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The anthers were then washed (10 mM PBS, 10 min), and the stained tissues were mounted on a glass slide and examined using Zeiss LSM710 confocal microscopy (Carl Zeiss Microscopy GmbH; Jena, Germany) under red fluorescence at 543 nm excitation [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To study lignin autofluorescence, the anthers were cleared in 70% (v/v) lactic acid for 3 days at 60°C, and the cleared tissues were examined using Zeiss LSM710 confocal microscopy (Carl Zeiss Microscopy GmbH; Jena, Germany) under UV light excitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>For phloroglucinol–HCl staining, flowers were fixed in FAA solution overnight and decolorized with an ethanol series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The flowers were then stained with 2% (w/v) phloroglucinol in 92% ethanol for 1 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the tissues were mounted with 18.5% (v/v) HCl, and red staining was immediately monitored using Leica M125 microscopy (Leica Microsystems; Bannockburn; IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Histochemical Detection of ROS, H2O2, and O2 − Radical </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The accumulation of ROS was visualized by a fluoluminescence assay with 2,7-dichlorofluorescein diacetate (DCFH-DA), which emits green fluorescence when oxidized by ROS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In this assay, anthers were infiltrated with a 100 µM/ml aquatic solution of DCFH-DA (Sigma; St. Louis; MO, USA) and subsequently observed with Zeiss LSM710 confocal microscopy (Carl Zeiss Microscopy GmbH; Jena, Germany) under GFP fluorescent light. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The H2O2 and O2 − levels were measured by 3, 3′-diaminobenzidine (DAB) and nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) (Sigma; St. Louis; MO, USA) staining, respectively [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Anthers were infiltrated in DAB solution (0.1% w/v, pH 3.8) and incubated overnight in darkness at 22°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, the anthers were infiltrated in NBT solution (0.1% w/v) in 10 mM PBS (pH 7.8) containing 10 mM NaN3 and then incubated in darkness at 22°C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>After incubation, the stained tissues were decolorized with acetic acid: glycerol: ethanol (1∶1∶3, v/v/v) solution at 95°C for 10 min and then photographed using Leica M125 microscopy (Leica Microsystems; Bannockburn; IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Scanning Electron Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Tissue samples of wild-type and P7-1-OE flower bud clusters were fixed overnight in 50 mM phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, pH 6.8) containing 1% (v/v) glutaraldehyde and 2% (v/v) paraformaldehyde at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The fixed tissues were rinsed twice (15 min each) with 100 mM PBS at RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The tissues were dehydrated in a graded ethanol series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Then, the samples were coated with gold and examined in an S-3000N Scanning Electron Microscope (Hitachi; Tokyo, Japan) at an accelerating voltage of 10 kV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Reproductive Development Symptoms Caused by RBSDV Infection in Rice Plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The growth and development of rice plants were affected by RBSDV infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The typical symptoms of RBSDV-infected rice plants include severe stunting and darkening of leaves [3]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>However, reproductive development in rice plants infected by RBSDV has not previously been studied in detail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Here, we characterized the reproductive development phenotype of RBSDV-infected rice plants, which were inoculated by viruliferous planthoppers, and we allowed disease symptoms to develop under field conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Two month after inoculation, the infected rice plants showed significantly stunted growth (Figure 1A) and produced poor spikelets (Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>At flowering stage, the spikelets of infected rice plants had viable pollen grains (Figure 1C), but the anthers failed to dehisce (Figure 1B) compared with mock rice plants which were inoculated by virus-free planthoppers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>As a result, at grain filling stage the infected rice plant showed partial to complete spikelet sterility (Figure 1E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Symptoms of rice plants infected with Rice black-streaked dwarf virus (RBSDV). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(A) The stunted symptom of rice caused by RBSDV infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>(B–C) RBSDV-infected rice plants showing non-dehiscent anthers (B) but normal viable pollen stained with I2 (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(D–E) The spikelets of RBSDV-infected rice plants at flowering (D) and at the grain filling period (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Rice plants were inoculated with viruliferous (RBSDV) or virus-free SBPHs (mock). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Expression of RBSDV P7-1 Protein Cause Male Sterility due to Non-dehiscent Anthers in Arabidopsis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To determine whether proteins encoded by RBSDV contributed to the variation in anther dehiscence and spikelet fertility of virus-infected rice plants, we investigated the effects of P7-1 on Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Specifically, we expressed the full-length P7-1 cDNA, under the control of the 35S-CaMV promoter, in transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The transgenic plants that constitutively expressed RBSDV P7-1 were selected using kanamycin medium (Figure S1A) and confirmed by genomic PCR (Figure S1B) and quantitative real-time RT-PCR analysis (Figure S1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>T3 generation plants from transgenic lines exhibiting high levels of overexpression of P7-1 (P7-1-OE#1, #2, and #5) were selected for further study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>During the vegetative growth stage, the growth and development of P7-1-OE#1, #2, #5, and wild-type Arabidopsis seedlings were indistinguishable (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>However, all transgenic lines (P7-1-OE#1, #2, and #5) showed significant abnormalities during reproductive growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Following fertilization, siliques of wild-type plants elongated and set seeds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>But in transgenic plants, siliques remained small, producing no seeds, indicating the high degree of sterility of Arabidopsis plants ectopically expressing RBSDV P7-1 (Figure 2B and 2C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Ectopic expression of RBSDV P7-1 causes male sterility in Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>(A) Phenotypes of P7-1 transgenic plants (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis during vegetative growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(B) Phenotypes of P7-1 transgenic lines (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis during reproductive development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(C) Silique phenotypes of P7-1 transgenic lines (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(D) Developmental series of P7-1-OE and wild-type flowers during anther stages 12 to 14. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>To investigate the cause of the sterile phenotype in transgenic plants overexpressing RBSDV P7-1, we examined the flowers under a microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>These observations revealed that in wild-type flowers, the anthers started to dehisce at stage 13 [21], and pollen grains were released to the stigmatic papilla (Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>However, at stage 13, P7-1-OE transgenic anthers did not dehisce normally, resulting in the failure to release pollen grains to the stigmatic papilla (Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Even at late stage 14, P7-1-OE anthers remained closed, and no pollen grains were released (Figure 2D, Figure S2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Analysis of anther morphology by scanning electron microscopy showed that at late stage 13, wild-type anthers spilt open along the stomium and released pollen grains, whereas P7-1-OE anthers remained intact, and no pollen grains were observed (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscopy and Alexander staining revealed that the pollen grains within the indehisced anthers of P7-1-OE plants were morphologically normal (Figure 3B) and viable (Figure S2B and S2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In addition, when used for hand pollination, the P7-1-OE pollen grains could fertilize egg cells (Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>These observations indicate that the sterility of the P7-1-OE lines is caused solely by defective anther dehiscence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron micrographs of anthers (A) and pollen grains (B) of P7-1 transgenic and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>P7-1-OE Anthers have Reduced Endothecium Secondary Wall Lignification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Secondary wall lignification, which mainly occurs around the endothecial cells, is thought to be critical for generating the forces required for anther dehiscence [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In wild-type plants, when the anthers were stained with ethidium bromide and visualized by confocal microscopy, lignified secondary walls could be observed in the endothecium as bands of striated spring-like thickenings at stages 12 and 13 (Figure 4A bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>By contrast, this thickening was absent in the P7-1-OE plants (Figure 4A top). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>To confirm the anther wall structure, lactic acid was used to clear the anthers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Under UV-illumination, a net-like structure of autofluorescent material could be seen at stage 12 or 13 in wild-type plants, indicating that there was lignification of the anther wall (Figure 4B, bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, these structures were not found in the P7-1-OE plants (Figure 4B, top). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we investigated the lignification patterns in both wild-type and P7-1-OE anthers using phloroglucinol staining, which is a histochemical stain commonly used for specifically staining lignin [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Phloroglucinol-stained substances accumulated to a high degree in wild-type anthers during their development, both at stage 13 and after flowering (Figure 5A and 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>By contrast, phloroglucinol staining was not observed in P7-1-OE anthers during flower development (Figure 5A and 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the expression levels of the lignin biosynthesis genes 4CL (4-coumarate:CoAligase), CCoAOMT (caffeoyl CoA O-methyltransferase), and C3H (cinnamic acid 3-hydroxylase) were low in P7-1-OE flowers, especially at stage 13 or later, compared with wild-type flowers (Figure 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>For example, at flowers development 13 stage, the relative expression level of 4CL, CCoAOMT were 0.8, 0.3 in P7-1-OE plants but 1.3, 0.7 in wild-type plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Endothecial secondary wall thickening in anthers from P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild-type plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>(A) Anthers were stained with ethidium bromide and visualized by confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Secondary thickening occurs in the endothecium (indicated by an arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Thickening is clearly observed in WT but is reduced P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) endothecium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>(B) Lactic acid-cleared anthers visualized by confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The secondary thickening network is clearly observed in WT plants, but not in P7-1 transgenic plants (P7-1-OE). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Histochemical staining of lignin components in P7-1 transgenic and WT Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(A) Phloroglucinol staining of P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis flowers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Phloroglucinol-stained material was highly accumulated in WT anthers but not in P7-1-OE anthers during flower development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(B) Magnified views of P7-1-OE and WT anthers stained with phloroglucinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(C) The expression levels of 4CL (4-coumarate:CoAligase), CCoAOMT (caffeoyl CoA O-methyltransferase), and C3H (cinnamic acid 3-hydroxylase) were detected in P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild type (WT) Arabidopsis flowers using quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) with the EF1a gene as an internal standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Results were presented as means±SE from three replications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Anthers of P7-1-OE Plants have Reduced ROS Level </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>To assess whether the sterility of P7-1-OE flowers was related to plant signaling molecules, we measured the ROS and NO (nitric oxide) levels in both transgenic and wild-type anthers using florescence staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Our results clearly demonstrated that there was no difference in NO content between P7-1-OE and wild-type anthers (Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the transgenic anthers accumulated significantly lower levels of ROS than wild-type plants (Figure 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We further investigated ROS production in anthers during development by histochemical staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>P7-1-OE anthers produced low levels of H2O2 (Figure 6B, DAB staining) but equivalent amounts of O2 − (Figure S5, NBT staining) compared with wild-type plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To gain further insight into the low ROS levels in P7-1-OE anthers, we analyzed the expression levels of genes in the ROS network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of some genes that encode ROS-scavenging enzymes, e.g., cytosolic ascorbate peroxidase1 (cAPX1), ascorbate peroxidase2 (APX2), and Fe superoxide dismutase (FSD1), increased in the P7-1-OE anthers about 2-fold higher than in wild-type, but the levels of ROS-producing related genes, e.g., respiratory burst oxidase homolog A (RBOHA) and respiratory burst oxidase homolog B (RBOHB), were reduced in the transgenic anthers compared with the wild type (Figure 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>These results show that the accumulation of ROS in anthers prior to dehiscence is nearly absent when RBSDV P7-1 is ectopically expressed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0079514-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079514.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Anthers from P7-1 transgenic plants exhibit low ROS and H2O2 contents compared with WT plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(A) ROS was detected by staining with DCFH-DA and visualized by confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>(B) H2O2 was detected by staining with DAB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(C) The expression levels of cytosolic ascorbate peroxidase1(cAPX1), ascorbate peroxidase2 (APX2), Fe superoxide dismutase (FSD1), respiratory burst oxidase homolog A (RBOHA), and respiratory burst oxidase homolog B (RBOHB) were detected in P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild type (WT) Arabidopsis flowers using qRT-PCR with the EF1a gene as an internal standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Results were presented as means±SE from three replications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079514.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Rice black-streaked dwarf and maize rough dwarf diseases, which are caused by RBSDV, lead to severe yield losses in crops in southeast Asian countries, especially China [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Although a great deal of effort has been made to elucidate the interactions between the virus, insect vectors, and host and environmental conditions, few RBSDV proteins involved in pathogenesis have been identified, and the biochemical basis of disease symptom development remains largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In this study, our results suggest that RBSDV P7-1 is a novel determinant of disease symptom development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>First, RBSDV infection caused alterations in anther development in rice plants, resulting in partial sterility due to non-dehiscent anthers (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, overexpressing RBSDV P7-1 in Arabidopsis produced plants with male sterility resulting from non-dehiscent anthers (Figure 2), which approximately mimicked the disease symptoms observed in rice anthers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The non-dehiscent anther phenotype of P7-1 transgenic plants was correlated with reduced secondary wall lignification in the endothecium and decreased ROS levels in the anthers (Figure 5 and 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that RBSDV P7-1 is likely to be a pivotal determinant of plant sterility symptoms caused by RBSDV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Previous studies using immunoelectron analysis have revealed that RBSDV P7-1 accumulates in tubular structures in virus-infected maize plants and in insects [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, P7-1 of SRBSDV (southern rice black-streaked dwarf virus), which is most closely related to RBSDV, has the intrinsic ability to form tubules growing from the non-host insect cell surface in the absence of other virus proteins [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Recent researches using live-cell imaging in Nicotiana benthamiana leaves also demonstrate that RBSDV P7-1 protein forms punctuate points at plasmodesmata [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>RBSDV P7-1 characteristics of tubule-forming and plasmodesmata localization suggest that this protein might be involved in virus intercellular movement, in infected insect and plant cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The pathogenesis of tubular proteins during viral morphogenesis has been reported in studies of other members of the family Reoviridae. For example, BTV (bluetongue virus) nonstructural tubular protein NS1 plays a direct role in cellular pathogenesis [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>RDV (rice dwarf virus) nonstructural tubular protein Pns10 functions as a viral suppressor of RNA silencing and plays important roles in enhancing viral replication, systemic movement, and invasion of new tissues [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the tubular proteins of reoviruses have multiple functions in viral morphogenesis, viral infection, and virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In support of this notion, our data show that overexpression of RBSDV tubular protein P7-1 in Arabidopsis causes male sterility, which mimics the phenotype observed in rice flowers infected with the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It will be interesting to examine whether RBSDV P7-1, like RDV Pns10, can function as a viral suppressor of RNA silencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In this study, we determined that the male sterility of P7-1-OE transgenic plants was due to the failure of anther dehiscence and pollen release, which may have been caused by the lack of lignification in the anther endothecium (Figure 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Actually, secondary lignified thickening in the endothecium is critical for providing the mechanical force required for anther dehiscence [22], [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This mechanism has been demonstrated experimentally by analyzing Arabidopsis mutants such as myb26 [29]–[31], NST1 (SECONDARYWALL THICKENING PROMOTING FACTOR1), and NST2 [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In these mutants, reduced lignification of anther endothecium results in anther indehiscent and male sterility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the triple ccc mutant, which carries mutations in monolignol biosynthesis genes, including CCR1 (cinnamoyl CoA reductase1), CAD c (cinnamyl alcohol dehydrogenase c), and CAD d, displays severe male sterility due to the lack of lignification in the anther endothecium [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Here, we showed that the transcriptional levels of the lignin biosynthesis genes 4CL, CCoAOMT, and C3H were reduced in the flowers of RBSDV P7-1 transgenic plants compared with the flowers of wild-type plants (Figure 5), although the expression levels of CCR1, CAD c, and CAD d were unchanged in the transgenic plants (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Thus, the reduced lignification of anthers is responsible for male sterility in P7-1-OE transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>It is well-established that secondary lignification in cell walls is dependent on the oxidative coupling of monolignol to form the polymer lignin, which is catalyzed by H2O2-dependent peroxidases and O2-dependent laccase [33], [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In the endodermal cells of roots, subcellular precision of lignin polymerization is achieved by restricted, localized peroxidase activity and the production of ROS substrate [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In the secondary thickening that occurs in anthers, lignin polymerization is dependent on the H2O2 contents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>For example, Arabidopsis plants ectopically expressing gamma carbonic anhydrase 2 (CA2) have significantly lower ROS contents than wild type, which results in a reduction in the H2O2-dependent polymerization pathway for lignin formation during anther development and accordingly, causes male sterility [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Our data also show that ectopic expression of RBSDV P7-1 in Arabidopsis causes male sterility in conjunction with low ROS contents in anthers compared with wild-type plants (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is reasonable to speculate that the male sterility of P7-1 transgenic plants is primarily achieved by the combinatorial action of reduced monolignol and ROS contents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In the future, it will be important to untangle the relationship between reduced production of ROS or lignin and RBSDV tubular protein P7-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Such information would significantly deepen our mechanistic understanding of the role of RBSDV P7-1 in viral virulence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Molecular identity of RBSDV P7-1 transgenic  Arabidopsis  plants. (A) Selection of P7-1 transgenic lines on MS medium with kanamycin or without kanamycin (MS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>(B) Genome DNA PCR showing that P7-1 was integrated as a unit in the transgenic lines. EF1α was used to control for DNA loading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>(C) qRT-PCR analysis showing the expression of P7-1 in wild-type and three independent transgenic lines using the EF1a gene as an internal standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Results were presented as means±SE from three replications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Alexander staining of pollen of  P7-1  transgenic and wild-type  Arabidopsis  plants. (A) Cytological comparisons of P7-1 transgenic lines (P7-1-OE) and wild type (WT) Arabidopsis anthers during development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>(B, C) Alexander staining pollen of P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Hand-pollinated pollen grains from P7-1 transgenic plants could fertilize egg cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>NO detected by staining with DAF-FM DA in P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT)  Arabidopsis  anthers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>O2− detected by staining with NBT in P7-1 transgenic (P7-1-OE) and wild-type (WT)  Arabidopsis  anthers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079514.s006"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>List of primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079514.s006.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We gratefully acknowledge Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Hansong Dong (Nanjing Agricultural University, China) for providing Arabidopsis (Col-0) wild-type seeds, and Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Xifeng Wang (Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, China) and Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Wenbiao Shen (Nanjing Agricultural University, China) for critically reading the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0079514-Shikata1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>1 ShikataE, KitagawaY (1977) Rice black-streaked dwarf virus: its properties, morphology and intracellular localization. Virology 77: 826–842.855190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Bai1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>2 BaiFW, YanJ, QuZC, ZhangHW, XuJ, et al (2002) Phylogenetic analysis reveals that a dwarfing disease on different cereal crops in China is due to rice black streaked dwarf virus (RBSDV). Virus Genes 25: 201–206.12416683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>3 WuJ, NiY, LiuH, RaoL, ZhouY, et al (2013) Development and use of three monoclonal antibodies for the detection of rice black-streaked dwarf virus in field plants and planthopper vectors. Virology J 10: 114.23575411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>4 ZhouT, WuLJ, WangY, ChengZB, JiYH, et al (2011) Transmission of rice black-streaked dwarf virus from frozen infected leaves to healthy rice plants by small brown planthopper (Laodelphax striatellus). Rice Sci 8: 152–156. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Hibino1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>5 HibinoH (1996) Biology and epidemiology of rice viruses. Annu Rev Phytopathol 34: 249–274.15012543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>6 ZhangHM, ChenJP, AdamsMJ (2001) Molecular characterisation of segments 1 to 6 of Rice black-streaked dwarf virus from China provides the complete genome. Arch Virol 146: 2331–2339.11811683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>7 WangZH, FangSG, XuJL, SunLY, LiDW, et al (2003) Sequence analysis of the complete genome of rice black-streaked dwarf virus isolated from maize with rough dwarf disease. Virus Genes 27: 163–168.14501194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Isogai1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>8 IsogaiM, UyedaI, LeeBC (1998) Detection and assignment of proteins encoded by rice black streaked dwarf fijivirus S7, S8, S9 and S10. J Gen Virol 79: 1487–1494.9634092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Supyani1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>9 SupyaniS, HillmanBI, SuzukiN (2007) Baculovirus expression of the 11 mycoreovirus-1 genome segments and identification of the guanylyltransferase-encoding segment. J Gen Virol 88: 342–350.17170467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>10 LiuH, WeiC, ZhongY, LiY (2007) Rice black-streaked dwarf virus minor core protein P8 is a nuclear dimeric protein and represses transcription in tobacco protoplasts. FEBS Lett 581: 2534–2540.17499245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Liu2"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>11 LiuH, WeiC, ZhongY, LiY (2007) Rice black-streaked dwarf virus outer capsid protein P10 has self-interactions and forms oligomeric complexes in solution. Virus Res 127: 34–42.17442443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Zhang2"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>12 ZhangC, LiuY, LiuL, LouZ, ZhangH, et al (2008) Rice black streaked dwarf virus P9–1, an α-helical protein, self-interacts and forms viroplasms in vivo. J Gen Virol 89: 1770–1776.18559948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Zhang3"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>13 ZhangLD, WangZH, WangXB, ZhangWH, LiDW, et al (2005) Two virus-encoded RNA silencing suppressors, P14 of Beet necrotic yellow vein virus and S6 of Rice black streak dwarf virus. Chin Sci Bull 50: 305–310. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>14 WangQ, TaoT, ZhangY, WuW, LiD, et al (2011) Rice black-streaked dwarf virus P6 self-interacts to form punctate, viroplasm-like structures in the cytoplasm and recruits viroplasm-associated protein P9–1. Virology J 8: 24.21241517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Sun1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>15 SunL, XieL, AndikaIB, TanZ, ChenJ (2013) Non-structural protein P6 encoded by rice black-streaked dwarf virus is recruited to viral inclusion bodies by binding to the viroplasm matrix protein P9–1. J Gen Virol 94: 1908–1916.23636822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Sun2"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>16 SunZ, ZhangS, XieL, ZhuQ, TanZ, et al (2013) The secretory pathway and the actomyosin motility system are required for plasmodesmatal localization of the P7–1 of rice black-streaked dwarf virus. Arch Virol 158: 1055–1064.23271163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Clough1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>17 CloughSJ, BentAF (1998) Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana . Plant J 16: 735–743.10069079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Berberich1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>18 BerberichT, SugawaraK, HaradaM, KusanoT (1995) Molecular cloning, characterization and expression of an elongation factor 1α gene in maize. Plant Mol Biol 29: 611–615.8534856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Thvenin1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>19 ThéveninJ, PolletB, LetarnecB, SaulnierL, GissotL, et al (2011) The simultaneous repression of CCR and CAD, two enzymes of the lignin biosynthetic pathway, results in sterility and dwarfism in Arabidopsis thaliana . Mol Plant 4: 70–82.20829305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Xie1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>20 XieY, MaoY, LaiD, ZhangW, ShenW (2012) H2 enhances Arabidopsis salt tolerance by manipulating ZAT10/12-mediated antioxidant defence and controlling sodium exclusion. PLoS ONE 7: e49800 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049800">10.1371/journal.pone.0049800</ext-link> 23185443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Sanders1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>21 SandersPM, BuiAQ, WeteringsK, McIntireKN, HsuYC, et al (1999) Anther developmental defects in Arabidopsis thaliana male-sterile mutants. Sex Plant Reprod 11: 297–322. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Wilson1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>22 WilsonZA, SongJ, TaylorB, YangC (2011) The final split: the regulation of anther dehiscence. J Exp Bot 62: 1633–1649.21325605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Mizuno1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>23 MizunoS, OsakabeY, MaruyamaK, ItoT, OsakabeK, et al (2007) Receptor-like protein kinase 2 (RPK2) is a novel factor controlling anther development in Arabidopsis thaliana . Plant J 50: 751–766.17419837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Liu3"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>24 LiuY, JiaD, ChenH, ChenQ, XieL, et al (2012) The P7–1 protein of southern rice black-streaked dwarf virus, a fijivirus, induces the formation of tubular structures in insect cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Virol. 156: 1729–1736. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Owens1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>25 OwensRJ, LimnC, RoyP (2004) Role of an arbovirus nonstructural protein in cellular pathogenesis and virus release. J Virol 78: 6649–6656.15163755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Ren1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>26 RenB, GuoYY, GaoF, ZhouP, WuF, et al (2010) Multiple functions of rice dwarf phytoreovirus Pns10 in suppressing systemic RNA silencing. J Virol 84: 12914–12923.20926568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Keijzer1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>27 KeijzerC (1987) The processes of anther dehiscence and pollen dispersal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The opening mechanism of longitudinally dehiscing anthers. New Phytologist 105: 487–489. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Bonner1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>28 BonnerL, DickinsonH (1989) Anther dehiscence in Lycopersicon esculentum Mill. New Phytologist 113: 97–115. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Dawson1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>29 DawsonJ, SözenE, VizirI, Van WaeyenbergeS, WilsonZA, et al (1999) Characterization and genetic mapping of a mutation (ms35) which prevents anther dehiscence in Arabidopsis thaliana by affecting secondary wall thickening in the endothecium. New Phytologist 144: 213–222. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-SteinerLange1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>30 Steiner-LangeS, UnteUS, EcksteinL, YangC, WilsonZA, et al (2003) Disruption of Arabidopsis thaliana MYB26 results in male sterility due to non-dehiscent anthers. Plant J 34: 519–528.12753590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Yang1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>31 YangC, XuZ, SongJ, ConnerK, BarrenaGV, et al (2007) Arabidopsis myb26/male sterile35 regulates secondary thickening in the endothecium and is essential for anther dehiscence. Plant Cell 19: 534–548.17329564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Mitsuda1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>32 MitsudaN, SekiM, ShinozakiK, Ohme-TakagiM (2005) The NAC transcription factors NST1 and NST2 of Arabidopsis regulate secondary wall thickenings and are required for anther dehiscence. Plant Cell 17: 2993–3006.16214898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Krknen1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>33 KärkönenA, KoutaniemiS (2010) Lignin biosynthesis studies in plant tissue cultures. J Integr Plant Biol 52: 176–185.20377679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Liu4"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>34 LiuCJ (2012) Deciphering the enigma of lignification: precursor transport, oxidation, and the topochemistry of lignin assembly. Mol Plant 5: 304–317.22307199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>35 LeeY, RubioMC, AlassimoneJ, GeldnerN (2013) A mechanism for localized lignin deposition in the endodermis. Cell 153: 402–412.23541512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0079514-Villarreal1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>36 VillarrealF, MartínV, ColaneriA, González-SchainN, PeralesM, et al (2009) Ectopic expression of mitochondrial gamma carbonic anhydrase 2 causes male sterility by anther indehiscence. Plant Mol Biol 70: 471–485.19326245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
