<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3115949</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21698287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-05803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Function</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Stress Responses</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Genetics</subject><subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Molecular Cloning, Characterization and Expression Analysis of Two Members of the Pht1 Family of Phosphate Transporters in Glycine max </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Two Phosphate Transporters in Soybean</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Zhaoyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jinming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Ruifang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Guanjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>Junyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Guohua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>National Center for Soybean Improvement, National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, College of Resources and Environmental Sciences, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Uversky</surname><given-names>Vladimir N.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of South Florida, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>hanx@njau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZW GX JG HX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: ZW RG GH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: ZW JZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: ZW HX. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e19752</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Wu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Phosphorus is one of the macronutrients essential for plant growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The acquisition and translocation of phosphate are pivotal processes of plant growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In a large number of plants, phosphate uptake by roots and translocation within the plant are presumed to occur via a phosphate/proton cotransport mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We cloned two cDNAs from soybean (Glycine max), GmPT1 and GmPT2, which show homology to the phosphate/proton cotransporter PHO84 from the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequence of the products predicted from GmPT1 and GmPT2 share 61% and 63% identity, respectively, with the PHO84 in amino acid sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The deduced structure of the encoded proteins revealed 12 membrane-spanning domains with a central hydrophilic region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The molecular mass values are ∼58.7 kDa for GmPT1 and ∼58.6 kDa for GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Transiently expressed GFP–protein fusions provide direct evidence that the two Pi transporters are located in the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Uptake of radioactive orthophosphate by the yeast mutant MB192 showed that GmPT1 and GmPT2 are dependent on pH and uptake is reduced by the addition of uncouplers of oxidative phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The K m for phosphate uptake by GmPT1 and GmPT2 is 6.65 mM and 6.63 mM, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>A quantitative real time RT-PCR assay indicated that these two genes are expressed in the roots and shoots of seedlings whether they are phosphate-deficient or not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Deficiency of phosphorus caused a slight change of the expression levels of GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The results of our experiments show that the two phosphate transporters have low affinity and the corresponding genes are constitutively expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Thereby, the two phosphate transporters can perform translocation of phosphate within the plant. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Phosphorus is one of the most important macronutrients required for plant growth and metabolism, and is the key component of nucleic acids, phospholipids and energy-providing ATP as well as several enzymes and coenzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Phosphorus is involved in energy metabolism, activation of metabolic intermediates, carbon assimilation, photosynthesis, respiration, signal transduction and enzyme regulation [1], [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In soil, plants acquire phosphorus in the form of orthophosphate (Pi) [4], [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Phosphate is the second most frequently limiting macronutrient for plant growth mainly because it exists in the soil in complex, insoluble, inorganic and organic forms that cannot be acquired directly by the plant [4], [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>For this reason, the concentration of Pi in soil solution can be as high as 10 µM but is present more often at concentrations as low as 1 µM [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Plants respond to phosphate deficiency by increasing the rate of Pi uptake by roots [4], and upregulation of the synthesis of a carrier system is believed to contribute to the observed increase of Pi acquisition [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>There are two Pi transport systems required by plants to facilitate absorption from diverse environments and enable subsequent transportation to all of the cells and subcellular compartments within the plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Kinetic characterization of the Pi uptake system of whole plants [10], [11] and cultured cells [12] suggests a high-affinity transport operating in the low micromolar range and a low-affinity system operating at higher concentrations (millimolar range) [7], [13], [14], [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Because the concentration of Pi in soil solution seldom exceeds 10 µM [8], the high-affinity transport is assumed to be the predominant system responsible for Pi uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Thus, a number of Pi transporters might function primarily in Pi uptake at the soil–root interface, whereas the others might participate predominantly in translocation within the plant and/or transport within certain tissues or cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>After uptake into the roots, Pi is mainly translocated symplastically to the xylem parenchyma cells, and secretion into the xylem for long-distance translocation to the shoot is facilitated by another type of transporter-like protein [8], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In plants that are not Pi-deficient, most of the Pi uptake by the roots is transported in the xylem to growing leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In Pi-starved plants, however, the limited supply of Pi from roots to shoots is augmented by increased mobilization of stored Pi in older leaves and retranslocation to both younger leaves and growing roots, from where Pi can again be recycled to the shoot [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the uptake and allocation of Pi in plants requires multiple transport systems that must function in concert to maintain homeostasis throughout growth and development [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Remobilization of phosphate stored in leaves has been demonstrated and the existence of a Pi transporter that facilitates this process has been inferred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Rae et al. have identified several genes in a barley genomic library that appear to be members of the Pht1 gene family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The sequence of HORvu;Pht1;6 suggested that it is also a member of the Pht1 gene family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The estimated K m of HORvu;Pht1;6 is 38561 µM, which is characteristic of a low-affinity transporter. HORvu;Pht1;6 is expressed in the above-ground part of the plant with strongest expression in old leaves and flag leaves and is less responsive to external concentrations of Pi, indicating that Pht1;6 is unlikely to function in the uptake of Pi by roots from soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Both of these organs are known to have a role in the nutrition of developing grains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The expression of Pht1;6 in these organs suggested that it might also play a role in the remobilization of nutrients during grain development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in situ hybridization showed that Pht1;6 is expressed in the phloem of vascular bundles in leaves and ears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Taken together, HORvu;Pht1;6 probably functions in the remobilization of stored Pi from leaves [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In rice, expression of OsPht1;2 (OsPT2) is increased significantly in response to Pi deficiency in root and shoot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>By using transgenic rice plants expressing the GUS reporter gene, OsPT2 was localized exclusively in the stele of primary and lateral roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The knock-down of OsPT2 by RNA interference significantly decreased long-distance transport of Pi from root to shoot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>These data suggested OsPT2 functions in translocation of the stored Pi in the plant [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, low-affinity Pi transporters have a wide range of roles in Pi uptake and translocation within the plant and are required to facilitate the movement of phosphate between subcellular compartments and organelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, most studies of Pi transporters in plants have focused on the roots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Soybean (Glycine max L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Merr.) is one of the most economically important leguminous seed crops that provide the majority of plant proteins, and more than a quarter of the world's food and animal feed [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, there is no report of soybean Pi transporters in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Here, we report the characterization of two Pi transporters from soybean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The two genes are designated GmPT1 and GmPT2 according to the rules recommended by the Commission on Plant Gene Nomenclature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The sequences of the two genes share great similarity with that of the plant proton–Pi cotransporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The primary functions of these genes appear to be as low-affinity Pi transporters within the plant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Cloning and Computational Sequence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We identified two single copy Pi transporter genes in soybean located on chromosomes Gm10 (41,391,168–41,393,008) and Gm20 (42,980,124–42,981,928). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>These genes are designated GmPT1 (accession number HQ392508) and GmPT2 (accession number HQ392509), respectively. GmPT1 is 1841- bp long (Figure 1A) and contains an open reading frame encoding a 536 amino acid polypeptide (molecular mass 58730.46 Da). GmPT2 is 1802 bp long (Figure 1A) and contains an open reading frame encoding a 536 amino acid polypeptide (molecular mass 58627.29 Da). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the open reading frame in both genes spans base pairs 23–1633. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These genes are 88.7% similar in nucleotide sequence and 97.9% similar in amino acid sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The two polypeptides share the greatest degree of similarity with the characterized Pi transporters from mouse-ear cress (Arabidopsis thaliana) [14], [25], tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum L.) [15], potato (Solanum tuberosum L.) [26] and barrel clover (Medicago truncatula) [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The two Pi transporters from soybean have a very high degree of identity with fungal Pi transporters from the mycorrhizal fungus Glomus versiforme (GvPT) and the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae (PHO84). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>GmPT1 shows 76% and 61% and GmPT2 shows 76% and 63% amino acid sequence identity with GvPT (accession number Q00908) and PHO84 (accession number P25297), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>DNA gel analysis of two soybean Pi transporters. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>DNA gel-blot analysis of GmPT1 and GmPT2 (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Lanes 2 and 3 contain GmPT1 and GmPT2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The size markers are shown to the right and left of the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The expression profile of the two proteins in different parts of the soybean seedling (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Seven days old soybean seedlings were used to examine the expression of GmPT1 and GmPT2 with cons15 as the control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Structure of the Soybean Pi Transporters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Hydropathy plots of the deduced polypeptides suggest that GmPT1 and GmPT2 consist of 12 membrane-spanning regions (Figure 2), a feature shared by other Pi transporters, irrespective of the level of affinity [14], [15], [19], [20], [25], [26], [27], [28], [29], [30], [31], [32], [33], [34], [35].Computational modeling of the encoded proteins predicted a conserved secondary structure containing 12 transmembrane (TM)domains with a large hydrophilic loop between TM6 and TM7 (Figure 2A) and the hydrophilic N and C termini located in the cytoplasm (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequences are similar to those of the other members of the Pht1 family of Pi transporters (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Several amino acid domains are highly conserved between these two Pi transporters and include sites for protein kinase C and casein kinase II-facilitated phosphorylation, as well as N-glycosylation (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The existence of a number of conserved putative phosphorylation sites present within the Pht1 family suggested that regulation of the transporters might occur at the post-translational level as well [6], [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Predicted topology of GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobicity profiles of GmPT1 and GmPT2 (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Hydropathy values for a window of 14 residues were calculated by DNAMAN version 6.0.3.93 using algorithms presented by Kyte and Doolittle [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobic regions correspond to positive index numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The arabic numerals refer to putative membrane-spanning domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A topological model for GmPT1 and GmPT2 (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The membrane-spanning domains of GmPT1and GmPT2 were predicted by HMMTOP [52] and their numbering is indicated by arabic numerals 1–12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The model was drawn with the aid of TOPO2 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sacs.ucsf.edu/TOPO2/">http://www.sacs.ucsf.edu/TOPO2/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Enlarged symbols indicate sites of significant structure–function importance: red, N-glycosylation; green, protein kinase C phosphorylation; blue, casein kinase II phosphorylation; cyan, tyrosine kinase phosphorylation; purple, Amidation; and magenta, N-myristoylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic relationship between GmPT1, GmPT2 and other plant and fungal Pi transporters. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Proteins (and accession numbers): PHO84 (P25297) from Saccharomyces cerevisiae; GvPT (Q00908) from Glomus versiforme; GiPT (AAL37552) from Glomus intraradices; Pht1;1 (Y07682), Pht1;2 (Y07681) Pht1;3 (O48639) and Pht2;1 (CAC15560) from Arabidopsis thaliana; StPT1 (Q43650) and StPT2 (Q41479) from Solanum tuberosum; MtPT1 (O22301) and MtPT2 (O22302) from Medicago truncatula; LePT1 (O24029) and LePT2 (O22549) from Lycopersicon esculentum; LaPT1(AAK01938) and LaPT2 (AAK38197) from Lupinus albus; NtPT1(AAF74025) from Nicotiana tabacum; OsPT1(AAN39042) and OsPT2 (AAN39043) from Oryza sativa; and GmPT1 (HQ392508) and GmPT2 (HQ392509) from Glycine max. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization of GmPT1 and GmPT2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The TBpred Prediction Server [36] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/tbpred/">http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/tbpred/</ext-link>) was used for searches that yielded unambiguous results with positive scores for the integral membrane protein (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>To verify the subcellular locations of GmPT1 and GmPT2, a green fluorescent protein (GFP)-tagged gene was fused to the 3′ end of the open reading frame of the GmPT1 or GmPT2 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The chimeric genes were placed under the control of the CaMV35S promoter and the constructs were transformed into onion epidermal cell by particle bombarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>As a control, a second set of cells was bombarded with the empty vector pBI-121-GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The cells were then examined by confocal laser scanning microscopy to determine the location of the GmPT1/GFP and GmPT2/GFP fusion proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>A clear GFP signal was observed at the periphery of cells bombarded with the GmPT1/GFP or GmPT2/GFP construction (Figure 4A–C and G–I for GmPT1 and GmPT2, respectively), whereas the signal was seen throughout cells expressing free GFP (Figure 4D–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Localization of the GmPT1/GFP and GmPT2/GFP fusion proteins to the periphery of the cells indicated that the two proteins are targeted to the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the results of earlier biochemical studies and together these data suggest that the GmPT1 and GmPT2 proteins are located in the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization of GmPT1/GFP and GmPT2/GFP fusion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Images showing onion epidermal cells expressing GmPT1/GFP (A–C), empty vector (D–F) and GmPT2/GFP (G–I) fusion protein examined under fluorescent-field illumination (A, D and G) to examine GFP fluorescence; under bright-field illumination (B, E and H) and by confocal microscopy for the overlay of bright and fluorescent illumination (C, F and I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The scale bars represent 100 µM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Functional and Biochemical Analysis in Yeast </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>We used uptake studies with inhibitors to confirm the pH dependence of Pi transport (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Pi transport activity was assessed at pH values in the range 4–7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Differences were detected in the activity profiles but the uptake rate was maximal at pH 4 and increased as the pH was reduced from 7 to 4 in each case (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>To investigate this influence of a proton motive force on Pi transport activity, the uncouplers 2,4-dinitrophenol (2,4-DNP) and carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone (CCCP), which destroy pH gradients across membranes, were applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>DNP at a concentration of 100 µM reduced the Pi uptake rate to 79% (GmPT1) and 82% (GmPT2) compared with 100% uptake in the inhibitor-free control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The rate of uptake was reduced to 77% (GmPT1) and 80% (GmPT2) by 100 µM CCCP and, to 82% (GmPT1) and 83% (GmPT2) by 100 µM Vanadate, an inhibitor of P-type H+-ATPases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The transporter rate was decreased significantly compared to that in the control (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>These results confirmed the hypothesis that Pi/H+ cotransport via GmPT1 and GmPT2 depends on the pH gradient across the cell membrane that is maintained by the endogenous plasma membrane H+-ATPases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Moreover, competition studies showed that different anions did not reduce the Pi uptake rate, demonstrating the high degree of specificity of GmPT1 and GmPT2 for Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Strains carrying the GmPT1 or GmPT2 cDNA generally uptake Pi at rates similar to those of the vector controls at millimolar concentrations of Pi (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Inorganic phosphate (Pi) uptake as a function of external pH. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Pi uptake rates for yeast MB192 cells expressing the indicated GmPT1, GmPT2 or carrying the control vector and wild type yeast cell were determined in medium at the indicated pH value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Values shown are the mean ± SE for three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0019752-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Pharmacology and specificity of GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0019752-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0019752.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Inhibitor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>32P uptake (% of the control) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>GmPT1Mean ± SE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>GmPT2Mean ± SE </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>CCCP (10 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>93±0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>96±0.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>CCCP (100 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>77±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>80±0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>DNP (10 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>92±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>94±0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>DNP (100 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>79±0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>82±0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Vanadate (10 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>92±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>96±0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Vanadate (100 µM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>82±0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>83±0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>NH4Cl (5 mM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>78±0.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>76±0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>KCl (5 mM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>75±0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>72±0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>NaAc (5 mM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>77±0.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>78±0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>CCCP, carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>DNP, 2,4-dinitrophenol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Inhibitors were added to yeast cells 30 s before addition of labeled Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>All assays were done at pH 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Values for each treatment were derived from three independent measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Water was used as the control treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>It was the pioneering work of Emmanuel Epstein that demonstrated ion uptake processes across the plasma membrane follow Michaelis–Menten kinetics [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In uptake experiments with radioactive Pi, the rate of transport was linear with time during the first 5 min of uptake under the conditions applied [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In three parallel experiments, the Lineweaver–Burk diagram, calculated using reciprocal uptake velocities at 5 min after addition of 32Pi, indicated that Pi uptake facilitated by GmPT1and GmPT2 followed Michaelis–Menten kinetics with an apparent K m value of 6.65 mM and 6.63 mM, respectively, (Figure 6A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Thus, GmPT1 and GmPT2 are low-affinity Pi transporters that are dependent on the proton gradient across the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Lineweaver–Burk plots of GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Lineweaver–Burk plot of Pi uptake of strains MB192-GmPT1 and MB192-GmPT2 versus external Pi concentrations that were used to estimate K m. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Expression pattern of GmPT1 and GmPT2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Root, stem and leaf tissues of 7-day-old soybean seedlings were used to examine the expression of GmPT1 and GmPT2 (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Expression of the two Pi transporters was enhanced in both root and shoot during the first 48 h of Pi starvation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The expression of GmPT1 and GmPT2 in seedling tissues was increased during the 3 h after the Pi-sufficient treated seedlings were transferred to a Pi-deficient solution at 48 h compared to the expression measured in Pi-sufficient plants (Figure 7A,C and E for GmPT1 and G, I and K for GmPT2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The transcript levels of GmPT1 and GmPT2 were little changed in plants that were grown in half-strength nutrient solution for 7 days and then transferred to a Pi-sufficient solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A decrease in the transcript abundance of GmPT1 and GmPT2 in the leaf, stem and root of hydroponically grown soybean seedlings was apparent within 3 h of Pi deprivation (Figure 7 B, D and F for GmPT1 and H, J and L for GmPT2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the expression level of the two genes was not altered markedly and the change tendencies were complicated irrespective of how the seedlings were treated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the GmPT1 and GmPT2 soybean Pi transporters were constitutively expressed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Expression levels of GmPT1 (A–F) and GmPT2 (G–L) during Pi treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The 7-day-old seedlings were grown by hydroponic culture with 0.5×Hoagland solution containing 5 µM Pi (A, C, E, G, I and K) or 1 mM Pi (B, D, F, H, J and L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Seedling tissues were harvested at 0, 1.0, 3.0, 12.0, 24.0 and 48.0 h after treatment (on the dash-dot line at the left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>After treatment for 48 h, the deficient/sufficient Pi-treated seedlings were transferred to sufficient/deficient Pi in Hoagland solution, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Seedling tissues were sampled at 0, 1.0 and 3.0 h after changing the nutrient solution (on the dash-dot line at the right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Leaf, A and B, G and H; stem, C and D, I and J; and root, E and F, K and L. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>GmPT1 and GmPT2 are members of the Pht1 family </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Our studies provide the first insights into the molecular nature of the proteins involved in phosphate transport in the soybean and reveal that soybean has phosphate transporters with sequence similarity to proton-coupled symporters from a large number of plants and fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These transporters belong to the phosphate: H+ symporter (PHS) transporter family of the major facilitator superfamily [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetically, the Pi transporters in plants and fungi belong to a closely related family, even though the similarity between the plant transporters is significantly higher than that between plants and fungi transporters [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>These genes have been grouped into the Pht1 family of proton–Pi cotransporters [40], which are energized by the plasma membrane proton ATPase [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition, at least one phosphorylation site and one N-glycosylation site among the potential protein modification sites are completely conserved in all plant transporters [14], [15], [26], [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>GmPT1 and GmPT2 are low-affinity Pi transporters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The results of uptake and kinetic studies led us to conclude that both GmPT1 and GmPT2 probably have a low affinity for Pi at millimolar concentrations, similar to the endogenous yeast low-affinity Pi uptake system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that Δpho87Δpho89Δpho90Δpho91 cells in a wild type strain do not show any significant defect in Pi uptake under high-Pi conditions; meanwhile, the loss of at least one low-affinity Pi transporter could result in an insufficient Pi uptake similar to the case of PHO84 inactivation under Pi-limiting conditions [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>These results revealed that the inactivation of low-affinity Pi transporters does not result in a substantial defect in Pi uptake, even though these proteins have been shown to play a role in Pi uptake. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The high-affinity Pi transporters are inducible in plants and fungi, whereas the low-affinity transporters are expressed constitutively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The Pht2 family in Arabidopsis is considered to be composed of low-affinity proton/Pi symporters, the expression of which is high in shoots and is not altered substantially during Pi starvation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The apparent low-affinity proton/Pi symporters that are highly expressed around vascular bundles suggests that those symporters play a role in loading shoot organs with Pi [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The profile of a Pi transporter </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The uptake and distribution of Pi in plants requires multiple Pi transport systems that must function in concert to maintain homeostasis throughout growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Phosphate uptake in plants is an energy-mediated co-transport process driven by a proton gradient generated by plasma membrane H+-ATPases [6], [42], [43], [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>At millimolar concentrations of intracellular Pi, Pi uptake is accomplished by transport of the anion across the membrane coupled to the transport of protons (H+-symport). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the driving force for Pi influx is the proton gradient generated by the H+-ATPases (Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It has been assumed that plant Pi transporters are proton/Pi co-transporters with a stoichiometry of 2–4 H+/Pi [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>By complementation of a knock-out of endogenous high-affinity Pi transporters of various yeast mutants, or by measuring the increase of Pi uptake in transformed plant cells, several Pi transporters of many plant species have shown common properties, indicating that there is an electrochemical proton gradient across the plasma membrane [6], [20], [26], [27], [30], [31], [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019752-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019752.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The Pi transporter mechanism in the plant cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>A membrane-integral proton ATPase undirectionally extrudes protons (H+) at the expense of ATP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The proton concentration gradient and membrane potential generated constitute a proton electrochemical potential (ΔμH) across the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Proton movement along the concentration and electrical gradients facilitates Pi movement by Pi transporters against a steep concentration gradient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the efflux mechanism helps to maintain Pi homeostasis in the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019752.g008"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The transport of Pi across plant membranes driven by the proton/Pi co-transporter mechanism is pH dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The observed increase of Pi uptake rates in response to decreasing pH is consistent with the operation of a proton/Pi symporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Our experiments show that the peak of Pi uptake is at pH 4.0 (Figure 5), which reflects the fact that the transport mechanism is a proton/Pi symport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The reduced uptake rate (Table 1) in the presence of uncouplers of pH gradients across membranes, such as DNP and CCCP, favors the latter interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This view is supported by the finding that addition of glucose before the uptake experiment with radioactive Pi enhances the uptake capacity of transformants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This effect could be caused by an enhanced proton extrusion that might result from preincubation with glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated the Pi transport activity of GmPT1 and GmPT2, which are low-affinity transporters in soybean, are dependent on the electrochemical gradient of protons as indicated by the pH dependence and the pharmacological assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Transiently expressed GFP protein fusions provide direct evidence that the two Pi transporters are located in the plasma membrane (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The results suggested also that the encoded proteins function in the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Low-affinity Pi transporters play important roles in Pi homeostasis within plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The transport of Pi across membranes is a pivotal step in the regulation of Pi use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Plants require multiple Pi transport systems to facilitate acquisition of Pi from diverse environments and to enable its subsequent transport to all of the cells and subcellular compartments of the plant [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The low concentration of Pi commonly found in the soil solution [8] has led to the hypothesis that only high-affinity Pi transporters can function for the uptake of Pi across the plasma membrane of root epidermal cells, whereas the low-affinity Pi transporters could be responsible for transport of Pi within the plant [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Initially, Pi is transported into root epidermal cells and subsequently loaded into the xylem for translocation to the aerial portions of the plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Under conditions of Pi deficiency, Pi can be retranslocated from shoot tissues to the roots via the phloem [2], [4], [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Two A. thaliana mutants exhibiting altered phosphate accumulation have been described, among which the pho1 mutant is deficient in the translocation of Pi from the roots to the shoots [46], whereas a mutation at the pho2 locus resulted in excessive accumulation of Pi in the leaves [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>OsPT2 is a low-affinity Pi transporter that is expressed in the root stele and leaf phloem and xylem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>On the basis of its tissue-specific expression pattern, OsPT2 is assumed to function in translocation of stored Pi in rice [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Over-expression of OsPT2 (PT2(O)) in transgenic plants resulted in accumulation of excess shoot Pi and growth retardation similar to that of rice pho2 mutants under Pi-sufficient conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>There is no significant difference in the concentration of Pi in either shoot or root between wild type and PT2(O) under Pi-deficient conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that over-expression of OsPT2 increases Pi uptake and translocation of Pi from root to shoot, resulting in the accumulation of excess Pi in shoots under abundant Pi conditions [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Knock-down of OsPT2 transgenic line r2-1 have shown that the concentration of Pi in the shoot is much lower than that of the wild type [21]; therefore, OsPT2 is responsible for translocation of the stored Pi in the plant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>When the supply of Pi is limited, plants grow more roots, increase the rate of Pi uptake by roots from soil solution, retranslocate Pi from older leaves, and deplete the vacuolar stores of Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>There is also significant retranslocation of Pi in the phloem from older leaves to the growing shoot and from the shoot to the root. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>In Pi-deficient plants, the restricted supply of Pi to the shoots from the roots via the xylem is supplemented by increased mobilization of stored P in the older leaves and retranslocation to both the younger leaves and growing roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This process involves both the depletion of Pi stores and the breakdown of organic P in the older leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>A curious feature of Pi-starved plants is that approximately one-half of the Pi translocated from the shoot to the root in the phloem is then transferred to the xylem and recycled back to the shoot [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Low-affinity Pi transporters in the Pht1 family are now thought to play this role in translocation of Pi within the plant, and this has been inferred from the spatial expression of these genes in several different plant species [7], [30], [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, low-affinity Pi transporters play important roles in Pi homeostasis within plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Prospects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Under conditions of Pi starvation, soybean can display its unique strategies to improve its acquisition and remobilization of Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In addition, the physiological and molecular processes in soybean under conditions of Pi deficiency appear more complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a global survey of Pi transporter expression in response to Pi starvation is necessary to understand the network of gene expression related to Pi acquisition, translocation, recycling and signal transduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In this study, we analyzed the temporal and spatial expression patterns of Pi transporters from soybean seedlings subjected to Pi starvation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>A BLAST search of the soybean genome, combined with cDNA cloning, showed that soybean possibly contains nine Pi transporter genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="?"><plain>In this study, we analyzed the expression levels of GmPT1 and GmPT2, but there could be other Pi transporters in soybean, which raises the question of whether other Pi transporters can affect Pi acquisition, translocation and remobilization and what is the relative contribution of these genes to overall Pi transporter function in plants? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="?"><plain>Multiple Pi transporter genes could result in finer control over protein expression; if so, how does each of these genes respond to deficiency of Pi stress? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Future studies of the expression of all soybean Pi transporters in response to different concentrations of Pi could address these questions, providing better understanding of the function of Pi transporter genes in soybean. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Plant material and growth conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Surface-sterilized soybean seeds (G. max cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>gantai) were sown in sterile, acid-washed quartz sand irrigated with 0.5×Hoagland solution containing 5 µM Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The seedings were maintained in a growth chamber with 70% relative humidity and a cycle of 16 h light at 29°C/8 h dark at 23°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>After 7 days, fresh roots were harvested for gene cloning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>At the same time, whole plants were transferred to 0.5×Hoagland solution for a Pi-deficiency time-course experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>For the experiment, 7-day-old seedlings were grown by hydroponic culture with 0.5×Hoagland solution containing 5 µM Pi (Pi deficient) or 1 mM Pi (Pi sufficient), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>All seedling tissues were harvested at 0, 1.0, 3.0, 12.0, 24.0 and 48.0 h after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>After Pi deficient/sufficient treatment for 48 h, the seedlings were transferred to Hoagland solution with sufficient/deficient Pi, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Seedling tissues were sampled at 0, 1.0, and 3.0 h after transplanting: the time points for sampling were 0, 1.0, 3.0, 12.0, 24.0, 48.0, 49.0, 51.0 and 60.0 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Gene Cloning </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Using the OsPT2 nucleotide sequence (accession number AF536962) as the query, a BALSTN [24] search was done on the web page of the phytozome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/search.php?show=blast">http://www.phytozome.net/search.php?show=blast</ext-link>) to identify sequences containing OsPT2 orthologs in the soybean genomic database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>This resulted in the identification of two cDNA clones designated GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Two pairs of primers were used for PCR amplification: for GmPT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>forward 5′-CAGGTAGCTGAGTTAGTGAGTGA-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>reverse 5′-CACGTATGATTTAGACAACACTTC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>for GmPT2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>forward 5′-CAGGTAGCAGAGTTAGTGAGTAAT-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>reverse 5′-ACAAGAATGAAATACACACCC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Full-length cDNA was amplified from the root cDNA template, using the primers at the end of the cDNA sequence, and then cloned into the pMD-19 Simple T vector (Takara) for sequence verification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Sequence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis was done with ANTHEPROT [51], Lasergene version 7.0.1 and DNAMAN version 6.0.3.93 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane regions and subcellular localization were predicted by HMMTOP [52] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.enzim.hu/hmmtop/index.html">http://www.enzim.hu/hmmtop/index.html</ext-link>) and the TBpred prediction server [36] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/tbpred/">http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/tbpred/</ext-link>), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>We used ScanProsite to scan the protein sequences for the occurrence of patterns stored in the PROSITE database [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The ScanProsite tools are available on the ExPaSy Molecular Biology of Geneva (Switzerland) website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://expasy.org/tools/scanprosite/">http://expasy.org/tools/scanprosite/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment was done with ClustalW [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>MEGA 4 [55] was used for analysis of the phylogenetic relationships of GmPT1 and GmPT2 and other Pi transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The evolutionary history was inferred using the neighbor-joining method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The bootstrap consensus tree inferred from 1000 replicates was taken to represent the evolutionary history of the taxa analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in less than &lt;60% bootstrap replicates were collapsed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The percentage of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) are shown next to the branches (next to the branches). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The evolutionary distances were computed using the Poisson correction method and are in units of the number of amino acid substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated from the dataset (complete deletion option). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>There are 460 positions in the final dataset. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Subcellular Localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>GFP was fused to the 3′ ends of GmPT1 and GmPT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>When expressed in onion epidermal cells, these gene fusions gave rise to Pi transporter::GFP fusion proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>A PCR-generated Xba I–BamH I fragment containing the open reading frame of GmPT1 and the Xba I–Xba I fragment containing the open reading frame of GmPT2 were subcloned in-frame upstream of the GFP gene in plasmid pBI-121-GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The primers were: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>for GmPT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>forward 5′- GCTCTAGAATGGCGGGAGGACAACTAG -3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>reverse 5′- CGGGATCCAACTGGAACCGTCCTA-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>for GmPT2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>forward 5′-GCT CTAGAATGGCAGGAGGACAACTAG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>reverse 5′-GCT CTAGAAACTGGAACCGTCCTAGC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Expression of the gene fusions was controlled by the CaMV35S-promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>DNA of the chimeric genes CaMV35S-GmPT1 and CaMV35S-GmPT2 and the pBI-121-GFP empty vector were introduced into onion epidermal cells by a particle bombardment system (Biolistic PDS-1000/He System; BioRad, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Bombarded samples were kept in the dark at room temperature for ∼24 h and then examined under a Leica TCS SP2 confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Yeast Manipulations and Pi Uptake Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The open reading frames of GmPT1 and GmPT2 were separately subcloned into yeast expression vector p112A1NE [56] to create GmPT1/p112A1NE and GmPT2/p112A1NE, where expression of GmPT1 or GmPT2 gene was driven by the alcohol dehydrogenase promoter 1 (ADH1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>These constructs were transformed into the yeast mutant MB192 (MATa  pho3-1 Δpho84::HIS3 ade2 leu2-3,112 his3-532 trp1-289 ura3-1, 2 can1) [28] as described [57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The yeast cells were grown until the logarithmic phase (when the absorbance at 600 nm was 1.0) on YNB liquid medium (Difco, Chemie Brunschwig AG, Basel, Switzerland), harvested, washed three times with Pi-free medium (YNB medium containing an equimolar concentration of potassium chloride instead of potassium phosphate), then suspended in the same medium and incubated at 30°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Different extracellular pH values in the range 4.0–7.0 were used for the pH-dependent Pi uptake experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Washed and Pi-starved cells were suspended and activated with 20% (w/v) glucose to guarantee optimal energization of the plasma membrane to 5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Then 1 ml of 1 mM 32Pi (final concentration of Pi 0.25 mM) was added, mixed and the cells were incubated with shaking at 30°C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Uptake was stopped by addition of 4 ml of ice-cold water and the cells were harvested immediately on glass microfiber filters (Whatman® GF/F grade) by vacuum filtration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The filters were washed twice with 4 ml of ice-cold water then transferred to scintillation vials and radioactivity was measured by a Beckman LS 6500 Scintillation Counter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Six different concentrations of Pi (2000, 1000, 500, 250, 100 and 50 µM) were used to derive the value of K m from the double reciprocal Lineweaver–Burk plot, which is less susceptible to skewing as a consequence of the multiple kinetics components; therefore, K m is an aggregate value reflecting the contribution of many individual kinetic constants [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>For inhibition studies, the reagents given in Table 1 were added 30 s before addition of the labeled Pi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Mes(2-(N-morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid) buffer at a final concentration of 25 mM was used to determine transport activity at different pH values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>RNA was extracted from root and shoot samples using TRIzol® reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR for the target genes, GmPT1 and GmPT2 and cons7 (accession number AW310136) [59] using gene-specific primers followed the protocol as described [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>PCR was done in triplicate using a reaction solution containing TaqMan buffer, 0.4 µM forward and reverse primers and 0.3 µM probe was done with the ABI 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>(Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Expression levels were normalized according to cons7 and fold change was calculated using the  method [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The following gene-specific primers and probe were used for real-time RT-PCR: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>for GmPT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>5′-CTTATGCTTATGGTTCTGTGTTCC-3′, </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>5′-CAGACATAATTGTAGCTGATAGAGG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>5′-(FAM) CACCACCAATCCCAAAGTCAAGCCA (TAMRA)-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>for GmPT2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>5′-GGCTTAACTCTTATGCTTATGGTTG-3′, </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>5′-CATGATTGTAGCTGATAGAGGGTAG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>5′-(FAM) CACCACCAATCCCAAAGCCAAGCCA(TAMRA)-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>for cons7 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>5′- TATAAACCTGGAGGATGCACTAGC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>5′- GTACATGGGAACCGTCATTCATC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>5′-(FAM) AACGGAAGCCTCAGAACCACACTTG(TAMRA)-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>We thank Professor Wenbiao Shen (College of Life Sciences, Nanjing Agricultural University) for critical reading and improvement of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the China transgenic Programme (2008ZX08004-002), the China 973 Programme (2009CB118400), and National public service sectors (agriculture) special research (nycytx-004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0019752-Karandashov1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>1 KarandashovVBucherM 2005 Symbiotic phosphate transport in arbuscular mycorrhizas. Trends Plant Sci 10 22 29 15642520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Rausch1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>2 RauschCBucherM 2002 Molecular mechanisms of phosphate transport in plants. Planta 216 23 37 12430011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Yuan1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>3 YuanHLiuD 2008 Signaling components involved in plant responses to phosphate starvation. J Integr Plant Biol 50 849 859 18713395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Schachtman1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>4 SchachtmanDPReidRJAylingSM 1998 Phosphorus Uptake by Plants: From Soil to Cell. Plant Physiol 116 447 453 9490752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Smith1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>5 SmithFWMudgeSRRaeALGlassopD 2003 2.Phosphate transport in plants. Plant Soil 248 71 83  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Rausch2"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>6 RauschCDaramPBrunnerSJansaJLaloiM 2001 A phosphate transporter expressed in arbuscule-containing cells in potato. Nature 414 462 470 11719809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Chiou1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>7 ChiouTJLiuHHarrisonMJ 2001 The spatial expression patterns of a phosphate transporter (MtPT1) from Medicago truncatula indicate a role in phosphate transport at the root/soil interface. Plant J 25 281 293 11208020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Marschner1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>8 MarschnerH 1995 Nutrient availability in soils. Mineral Nutrition of Higher Plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>2nd ed London Academic Press 483 507  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-GordonWeeks1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>9 Gordon-WeeksRTongYPDaviesTGELeggewieG 2003 Restricted spatial expression of a high-affinity phosphate transporter in potato roots. J Cell Sci 116 3135 3144 12799416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-UllrichEberius1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>10 Ullrich-EberiusCNovackyABelA 1984 Phosphate uptake inLemna gibba G1: energetics and kinetics. Planta 161 46 52 24253554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Raghothama1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>11 RaghothamaKG 1999 PHOSPHATE ACQUISITION. Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Bio 50 665 693 15012223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Furihata1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>12 FurihataTSuzukiMSakuraiH 1992 Kinetic characterization of two phosphate uptake systems with different affinities in suspension-cultured Catharanthus roseus protoplasts. Plant Cell Physiol 33 1151  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Muchhal1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>13 MuchhalUSRaghothamaKG 1999 Transcriptional regulation of plant phosphate transporters. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96 5868 5872 10318976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Muchhal2"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>14 MuchhalUSPardoJMRaghothamaKG 1996 Phosphate transporters from the higher plant Arabidopsis thaliana. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 10519 10523 8927627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>15 LiuCMuchhalUSUthappaMKononowiczAKRaghothamaKG 1998 Tomato phosphate transporter genes are differentially regulated in plant tissues by phosphorus. Plant Physiol 116 91 99 9449838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Okumura1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>16 OkumuraSMitsukawaNShiranoYShibataD 1998 Phosphate transporter gene family of Arabidopsis thaliana. DNA Res 5 261 269 9872450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Hamburger1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>17 HamburgerDRezzonicoEMacDonald-Comber PetetotJSomervilleCPoirierY 2002 Identification and Characterization of the Arabidopsis PHO1 Gene Involved in Phosphate Loading to the Xylem. Plant Cell 14 889 902 11971143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Jeschke1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>18 JeschkeWDKirkbyEAPeukeADPateJSHartungW 1997 Effects of P deficiency on assimilation and transport of nitrate and phosphate in intact plants of castor bean (Ricinus communis L.). J Exp Bot 48 75 91  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Versaw1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>19 VersawWKHarrisonMJ 2002 A chloroplast phosphate transporter, PHT2;1, influences allocation of phosphate within the plant and phosphate-starvation responses. Plant Cell 14 1751 1766 12172020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Rae1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>20 RaeALCybinskiDHJarmeyJMSmithFW 2003 Characterization of two phosphate transporters from barley; evidence for diverse function and kinetic properties among members of the Pht1 family. Plant Mol Biol 53 27 36 14756304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Ai1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>21 AiPenghuiSunShubinZhaoJianningFanXiaorongXinWeijie 2009 Two rice phosphate transporters, OsPht1;2 and OsPht1;6, have different functions and kinetic properties in uptake and translocation. Plant J 57 798 809 18980647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Shoemaker1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>22 ShoemakerRCSchlueterJDoyleJJ 2006 Paleopolyploidy and gene duplication in soybean and other legumes. Curr Opin Plant Biol 9 104 109 16458041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Graham1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>23 GrahamPHVanceCP 2003 Legumes: Importance and Constraints to Greater Use. Plant Physiol 131 872 877 12644639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Altschul1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>24 AltschulSFGishWMillerWMyersEWLipmanDJ 1990 Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol 215 403 410 2231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Smith2"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>25 SmithFWEalingPMDongBDelhaizeE 1997 The cloning of two Arabidopsis genes belonging to a phosphate transporter family. Plant J 11 83 92 9025304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Leggewie1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>26 LeggewieGWillmitzerLRiesmeierJW 1997 Two cDNAs from potato are able to complement a phosphate uptake-deficient yeast mutant: Identification of phosphate transporters from higher plants. Plant Cell 9 381 392 9090882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Liu2"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>27 LiuHTrieuATBlaylockLAHarrisonMJ 1998 Cloning and characterization of two phosphate transporters from Medicago truncatula roots: Regulation in response to phosphate and to colonization by arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 11 14 22 9425684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-BunYa1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>28 Bun-YaMNishimuraMHarashimaSOshimaY 1991 The PHO84 gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae encodes an inorganic phosphate transporter. Mol Cell Biol 11 3229 3238 2038328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Bunya1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>29 Bun-yaMShikataKNakadeSYompakdeeCHarashimaS 1996 Two new genes, PHO86 and PHO87, involved in inorganic phosphate uptake in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Curr Genet 29 344 351 8598055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Daram1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>30 DaramPBrunnerSPerssonBLAmrheinNBucherM 1998 Functional analysis and cell-specific expression of a phosphate transporter from tomato. Planta 206 225 233 9737001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Daram2"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>31 DaramPBrunnerSRauschCSteinerCAmrheinN 1999 Pht2;1 encodes a low-affinity phosphate transporter from Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 11 2153 2166 10559441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Liu3"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>32 LiuJQUhde-StoneCLiAVanceCAllanD 2001 A phosphate transporter with enhanced expression in proteoid roots of white lupin (Lupinus albus L.). Plant Soil 237 257 266  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Paszkowski1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>33 PaszkowskiUKrokenSRouxCBriggsSP 2002 Rice phosphate transporters include an evolutionarily divergent gene specifically activated in arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 99 13324 13329 12271140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Zhao1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>34 ZhaoLVersawWKLiuJHarrisonMJ 2003 A phosphate transporter from Medicago truncatula is expressed in the photosynthetic tissues of the plant and located in the chloroplast envelope. New Phytol 157 291 302  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Nagy1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>35 NagyRVasconcelosMJVZhaoSMcElverJBruceW 2006 Differential regulation of five Pht1 phosphate transporters from maize (Zea mays L.). Plant Biol (Stuttg) 8 186 197 16547863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Rashid1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>36 RashidMSahaSRaghavaGPS 2007 Support Vector Machine-based method for predicting subcellular localization of mycobacterial proteins using evolutionary information and motifs. BMC Bioinformatics 8 337 17854501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Epstein1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>37 EpsteinEHagenCE 1952 A Kinetic Study of the Absorption of Alkali Cations by Barley Roots. Plant Physiol 27 457 474 16654471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Epstein2"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>38 EpsteinERainsDWElzamOE 1963 Resolution of Dual Mechanisms of Potassium Absorption by Barley Roots. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 49 684 692 16591089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Pao1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>39 PaoSSPaulsenITSaierMHJr 1998 Major Facilitator Superfamily. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 62 1 34 9529885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Bucher1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>40 BucherMRauschCDaramP 2001 Molecular and biochemical mechanisms of phosphorus uptake into plants. J Plant Nutr Soil Sci 164 209 217  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Auesukaree1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>41 AuesukareeCHommaTKanekoYHarashimaS 2003 Transcriptional regulation of phosphate-responsive genes in low-affinity phosphate-transporter-defective mutants in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 306 843 850 12821119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-UllrichEberius2"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>42 Ullrich-EberiusCNovackyAFischerELuttgeU 1981 Relationship between energy-dependent phosphate uptake and the electrical membrane potential in Lemna gibba G1. Plant Physiol 67 797 801 16661757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-UllrichEberius3"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>43 Ullrich-EberiusCNovackyABelA 1984 Phosphate uptake in Lemna gibba G1: energetics and kinetics. Planta 161 46 52 24253554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Sakano1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>44 SakanoK 1990 Proton/phosphate stoichiometry in uptake of inorganic phosphate by cultured cells of Catharanthus roseus (L.) G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Don. Plant Physiol 93 479 16667491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Harrison1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>45 HarrisonMJDewbreGRLiuJ 2002 A Phosphate Transporter from Medicago truncatula Involved in the Acquisition of Phosphate Released by Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungi. Plant Cell 14 2413 2429 12368495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Poirier1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>46 PoirierYThomaSSomervilleCSchiefelbeinJ 1991 Mutant of Arabidopsis deficient in xylem loading of phosphate. Plant Physiol 97 1087 1093 16668493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Dong1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>47 DongBRengelZDelhaizeE 1998 Uptake and translocation of phosphate by pho2 mutant and wild-type seedlings of Arabidopsis thaliana. Planta 205 251 256 9637070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Delhaize1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>48 DelhaizeERandallPJ 1995 Characterization of a Phosphate-Accumulator Mutant of Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Physiol 107 207 213 12228355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Liu4"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>49 LiuFWangZRenHShenCLiY 2010 OsSPX1 suppresses the function of OsPHR2 in the regulation of expression of OsPT2 and phosphate homeostasis in shoots of rice. Plant J 62 508 517 20149131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Mudge1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>50 MudgeSRRaeALDiatloffESmithFW 2002 Expression analysis suggests novel roles for members of the Pht1 family of phosphate transporters in Arabidopsis. Plant J 31 341 353 12164813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Deleage1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>51 DeleageGCombetCBlanchetCGeourjonC 2001 ANTHEPROT: An integrated protein sequence analysis software with client/server capabilities. Comput Biol Med 31 259 267 11334635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Tusndy1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>52 TusnádyGESimonI 2001 The HMMTOP transmembrane topology prediction server. Bioinformatics 17 849 850 11590105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Sigrist1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>53 SigristCJCeruttiLde CastroELangendijk-GenevauxPSBulliardV 2010 PROSITE, a protein domain database for functional characterization and annotation. Nucleic Acids Res 38 D161 166 19858104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Thompson1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>54 ThompsonJDHigginsDGGibsonTJ 1994 CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice. Nucl Acids Res 22 4673 4680 7984417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>55 TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarS 2007 MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0. Mol Biol Evol 24 1596 1599 17488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Riesmeier1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>56 RiesmeierJWWillmitzerLFrommerWB 1992 Isolation and characterization of a sucrose carrier cDNA from spinach by functional expression in yeast. EMBO J 11 4705 4713 1464305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Gietz1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>57 GietzRDSchiestlRH 2007 High-efficiency yeast transformation using the LiAc/SS carrier DNA/PEG method. Nat Protocols 2 31 34 17401334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Wykoff1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>58 WykoffDDO'SheaEK 2001 Phosphate Transport and Sensing in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Genetics 159 1491 1499 11779791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Libault1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>59 LibaultMThibivilliersSBilginDDRadwanOBenitezM 2008 Identification of Four Soybean Reference Genes for Gene Expression Normalization. The Plant Genome 1 44 54  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Schmittgen1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>60 SchmittgenTDLivakKJ 2008 Analyzing real-time PCR data by the comparative C T method. Nat Protocols 3 1101 1108 18546601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Livak1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>61 LivakKJSchmittgenTD 2001 Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method. Methods 25 402 408 11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019752-Kyte1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>62 KyteJDoolittleR 1982 A simple method for displaying the hydropathic character of a protein. J Mol Biol 157 105 132 7108955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
