<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell. Mol. Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jcmm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1582-1838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1582-4934</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3981893</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444314</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.12220</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Crosstalk between AMPK activation and angiotensin II-induced hypertrophy in cardiomyocytes: the role of mitochondria </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hernández</surname><given-names>Jessica Soto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto-Torres</surname><given-names>Giselle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>Andrey V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khuchua</surname><given-names>Zaza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Javadov</surname><given-names>Sabzali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>a</label><institution>Department of Physiology, School of Medicine, University of Puerto Rico</institution><addr-line>San Juan, PR, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>b</label><institution>Department of Cardiac Surgery, Cardiac Surgery Research Laboratory, Innsbruck Medical University</institution><addr-line>Innsbruck, Austria</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>c</label><institution>Cincinnati Children's Research Foundation, University of Cincinnati</institution><addr-line>Cincinnati, OH, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Correspondence to: Sabzali JAVADOV, M.D., Ph.D., Department of Physiology, School of Medicine, University of Puerto Rico, San Juan 00936-5067, PR, USA., Tel.: 787-758-2525; ext. 2909, Fax: 787-753-0120, E-mail: <email>sabzali.javadov@upr.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 The Authors. Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>AMP-kinase (AMPK) activation reduces cardiac hypertrophy, although underlying molecular mechanisms remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this study, we elucidated the anti-hypertrophic action of metformin, specifically, the role of the AMPK/eNOS/p53 pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>H9c2 rat cardiomyocytes were treated with angiotensin II (AngII) for 24 hrs in the presence or absence of metformin (AMPK agonist), losartan [AngII type 1 receptor (AT1R) blocker], Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME, pan-NOS inhibitor), splitomicin (SIRT1 inhibitor) or pifithrin-α (p53 inhibitor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results showed that treatment with metformin significantly attenuated AngII-induced cell hypertrophy and death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Metformin attenuated AngII-induced activation (cleavage) of caspase 3, Bcl-2 down-regulation and p53 up-regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>It also reduced AngII-induced AT1R up-regulation by 30% (P &lt; 0.05) and enhanced AMPK phosphorylation by 99% (P &lt; 0.01) and P-eNOS levels by 3.3-fold (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Likewise, losartan reduced AT1R up-regulation and enhanced AMPK phosphorylation by 54% (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The AMPK inhibitor, compound C, prevented AT1R down-regulation, indicating that metformin mediated its effects via AMPK activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Beneficial effects of metformin and losartan converged on mitochondria that demonstrated high membrane potential (Δψm) and low permeability transition pore opening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Thus, this study demonstrates that the anti-hypertrophic effects of metformin are associated with AMPK-induced AT1R down-regulation and prevention of mitochondrial dysfunction through the SIRT1/eNOS/p53 pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>AMP kinase</kwd><kwd>metformin</kwd><kwd>mitochondria</kwd><kwd>angiotensin II receptors</kwd><kwd>hypertrophy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>AMP-kinase (AMPK), an important metabolic sensor, regulates energy metabolism in organs and tissues including the liver, adipose tissue, and skeletal and cardiac muscles 1,2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In response to various intra- and extracellular stimuli, it enhances fatty acid uptake, and oxidative metabolism, glucose transport, glycolysis and mitochondrial biogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Metformin, a biguanide drug with pleiotropic actions widely used for the treatment of patients with type 2 diabetes 3,4, is a powerful activator of AMPK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Apart from its anti-hyperglycaemic effects, metformin significantly improves cardiac function in patients and various animal models of heart failure 5, although underlying mechanisms of action remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>For example, in mice with heart failure induced by left coronary artery occlusion and subsequent reperfusion, metformin improved LV function and attenuated cardiac hypertrophy 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Similarly, metformin attenuated oxidative stress-induced cardiomyocyte apoptosis and prevented the progression of heart failure in dogs 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, metformin did not exert anti-hypertrophic effects on mice lacking functional AMPK or eNOS, which suggests that its effects are mediated via activation of the AMPK/eNOS pathway 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Cardiomyocyte hypertrophy, a major consequence of pressure or volume overload, plays a central role in the progression of heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Various paracrine and autocrine factors are involved in pathogenesis and regulation of cardiomyocyte hypertrophy, including angiotensin II (AngII), a key player of the renin–angiotensin system that induces cell hypertrophy, differentiation and apoptosis through activation of various intracellular signalling molecules including Gq protein, calcineurin, mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK) and several transcription factors 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>AngII type 1 (AT1R) and type 2 (AT2R) G protein–coupled receptors have been shown to mediate the effects of circulating and local (intracellular) AngII 9,10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>AT1R mediates pro-hypertrophic effects of AngII, but AT2R, in contrast, attenuates AT1R activation–induced cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Recent studies demonstrated that pro-hypertrophic effects of AngII can be mediated through mitochondria and induce cell death 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Although the exact underlying mechanisms remain unclear, AngII-induced depolarization of the mitochondrial membrane and increased production of mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) are associated with cardiomyocyte autophagy and hypertrophy 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Metformin, a promising pharmacological agent, may be used for the treatment of heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Most previous studies were conducted in vivo on intact hearts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, the heart contains many non-cardiomyocyte cell types, including fibroblasts, vascular endothelial cells, smooth muscle cells and immune cells, with cardiomyocytes accounting for only 30–40% of total heart cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, new studies using cultured cardiomyocytes are required to establish whether metformin exerts a direct anti-hypertrophic effect on these cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In this study, we elucidated the role of AMPK in AngII-induced hypertrophy in cultured H9c2 cardiomyocytes, providing additional evidence that AMPK activation improves mitochondrial function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrate that metformin exerted anti-hypertrophic effects on cardiomyocytes and prevented AngII-induced cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We observed a negative reciprocal interaction between AMPK activation and AT1R levels: metformin activated AMPK, annulling AngII-induced up-regulation of AT1R, whereas losartan (AT1R antagonist) enhanced AMPK activation in AngII-treated H9c2 cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, metformin attenuated mitochondrial dysfunction and hypertrophy through the eNOS/SIRT1/p53 pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Material and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>H9c2 embryonic rat cardiomyocytes were purchased from the American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA) and cultured according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In short, the cells were cultured in medium containing DMEM/Ham's F-12 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), supplemented with 10% foetal bovine serum, 10 μg/ml transferrin, 10 μg/ml insulin, 10 ng/ml selenium, 1% penicillin and streptomycin, 2 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 5 μg/ml linoleic acid, 3 mM pyruvic acid, 0.1 mM minimum essential medium non-essential amino acids, 10% MEM vitamin, 0.1 mM 5-bromo-2′-deoxyuridine, 100 μM L-ascorbic acid and 30 mM HEPES, pH 7.1, and maintained in 95% air and 5% CO2 at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Prior to all experiments, cells were serum-starved for 24 hrs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Cells with 85–90% confluence from passages 3–20 were used for experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Experimental protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Cells were treated with 200 nM AngII for 24 hrs in the presence or absence of 2 mM metformin (AMPK activator), 10 μM losartan (AngII type 1 receptor antagonist), 5 μM compound C (AMPK inhibitor), 300 μM Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME, pan-NOS inhibitor), 10 μM splitomicin (SIRT1 inhibitor) or 10 μM pifithrin-α (p53 inhibitor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>All drugs were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA) and added to the culture medium 45 min. before AngII administration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Cell viability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Cell viability was determined using the trypan blue exclusion method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The cells were cultured at a density of 5 × 105 cells on 100-mm dishes and exposed to AngII (0 nM, 200 nM, 500 nM, 1 μM or 5 μM) for 24 hrs in the presence or absence of 2 mM metformin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>After treatment, cells were rinsed with PBS, detached with Hyclone Trypsin (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and counted using the TC20 Automated Cell Counter (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The per cent of viable and dead cells was calculated from a total number of counted cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Cell area measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Plated cells (3 × 104 cells per 6-cm dish) were treated in accordance with the experimental protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>At the end of the experiment, the cells were viewed using a Leica DMIL LED inverted microscope (Wetzlar, Germany), equipped with a 3.2 MP scientific grade digital microscopy camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Six to eight random photographs were taken from each dish, and at least, 60 individual cell size measurements were made from each group using Accu-Scope Micrometrics SE Premium software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE and Western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Following the treatments, cells were washed twice with cold PBS and lysed in buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM tetrasodium phosphate, 40 mM β-glycerophosphate, 2 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetate (EDTA), 2 mM ethylene glycol-bis(2-aminoethylether)-N,N,N′,N′-tetraacetate (EGTA), 1% Triton X, 10% glycerol, 50 mM sodium fluoride, 0.2 mM sodium orthovanadate and protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The cell lysates were transferred to 1.5-ml Eppendorf tubes, homogenized and centrifuged at 10,000 × g for 5 min. at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was transferred to a fresh tube, and protein concentration was determined using the Bio-Rad Protein Assay Reagent (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Equal amounts of protein samples were resolved on SDS-PAGE and transferred onto Amersham Hybond ECL 0.45 μM nitrocellulose membranes (GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences, Piscataway, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The membranes were immunoblotted with actin, AMPK, P-AMPKαThr172, Bcl-2, caspase 3 full length, eNOS, P-eNOS (Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA, USA), AT1R, AT2R or p53 (Santa Cruz, Dallas, TX, USA) antibodies, followed by secondary antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The signals were visualized using Thermo Scientific Pierce ECL Western Blotting Detection reagents (Thermo Fisher Scientific) at VersaDoc 3000 Gel Imaging System (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial membrane potential </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>To monitor ΔΨm, cells (4 × 105 cells/well) plated in a 24-well culture plate were incubated for 30 min. with the membrane potential–sensitive dye JC-1 (10 μg/ml, 5,5′,6,6′-tetraethyl-benzimidazolylcarbocyanine iodide, Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The intensity of fluorescence was immediately measured using a Spectramax M3 microplate reader (Molecular Devices) at 527 and 590 nm for emission and 488 nm for excitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>For confocal microscopy, the cells, plated on glass-bottom dishes, were loaded with JC-1 for 30 min. at 37°C, and images were captured using a Zeiss LSM510 META (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial permeability transition pore (PTP) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To quantify mitochondrial PTP opening, cardiomyocytes were loaded with 5 μM calcein-acetoxymethylester (calcein-AM, Molecular Probes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Cobalt chloride (5 mM) was added to the culture medium to quench cytosolic and nuclear calcein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Cells were visualized with an Olympus IX73 inverted fluorescence microscope (Center Valley, PA, USA), and fluorescence was captured using an Olympus DP73 high-performance Peltier cooled digital colour camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Olympus CellSens Dimension Imaging software was used to analyse calcein fluorescence in cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Complex I activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Complex I activity was determined by measuring the decrease in the concentration of NADH at 340 nm and 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Cells were resuspended in hypotonic phosphate buffer containing 5 mM MgCl2 and 0.55 mg/ml saponin and, then, freeze-thawed three times to give the substrate access to the inner mitochondrial membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The assay was performed in phosphate buffer containing 1 mM KCN, 5 mM MgCl2, 2.5 mg/ml BSA, 2 μM antimycin, 100 μM decylubiquinone and 100 μM NADH, pH 7.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Specific activities were determined by calculating the slope of the reaction in the linear range and normalizing per mg of protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Total ROS levels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Cells were trypsinized with a 0.25% trypsin–EDTA solution (Thermo Scientific HyClone, Logan, UT, USA) and centrifuged at 500 × g for 5 min. at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The pellet was resuspended in culture medium, and cells were incubated with 20 μM 2′7 dichlorofluorescein diacetate (DCF-DA; Alexis Biochemicals) for 30 min. at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The cells were again centrifuged at 500 × g for 5 min. to remove medium with excess dye, and the pellets were resuspended in PBS and added to a 96-well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence intensity was measured using a Spectramax M3 plate reader (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) at an excitation of 485 nm and emission of 530 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial ROS levels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>To quantify mitochondrial ROS, cells (2 × 105 cells/well) in the 96-well culture plate were incubated with the mitochondrial superoxide–sensitive fluorescent dye MitoSOX Red (1 μM, Invitrogen) for 20 min. at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The intensity of fluorescence was measured using a Spectramax M3 microplate reader (Molecular Devices) at 510 and 580 nm for excitation and emission respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as means ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was evaluated using one-way anova, followed by Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test or an unpaired two-tailed Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered to be statistically significant when P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Metformin attenuates AngII-induced hypertrophy and cell death </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In the first set of experiments, we examined whether metformin exerts a direct anti-hypertrophic effect on AngII-treated cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>As previous studies demonstrate that metformin at high concentrations (≥5 mM) reduces the energy state of intact hearts 4, but at 2 mM, it exerts no direct effect on complex I activity 13 and high-energy phosphates 14, we used metformin at a concentration of 2 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Likewise, this study revealed no detrimental effects of 2 or 5 mM metformin on complex I activity in H9c2 cardiomyocytes (see below). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 1, cells treated for 24 hrs with 200 nM AngII demonstrated significant hypertrophy and a 22% (P &lt; 0.01) increase in cell size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Both metformin and losartan prevented cell hypertrophy significantly, reducing cell size in the presence of AngII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Cell size values were not significantly affected in cells pre-treated with L-NAME, splitomicin or pifithrin-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To assess the effect of metformin on cell death, the cells were pre-treated with 2 mM metformin in the presence of AngII at different concentrations (0 nM, 200 nM, 500 nM, 1 μM or 5 μM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>AngII-induced cell death was dose-dependent and, when treated with 5 μM AngII, reached a peak rate of 13.3% (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Metformin prevented cell death at all concentrations of AngII and, interestingly, demonstrated anti-apoptotic effects on cells treated with 200 nM AngII, preventing caspase 3 cleavage and Bcl-2 down-regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>However, when the cells were treated with 1 μM AngII, the presence or absence of metformin did not alter caspase 3 or Bcl-2 protein levels (Fig. 2B and C), suggesting that cell death occurs through necrosis, rather than apoptosis, at high concentrations of AngII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Thus, these data demonstrate that metformin exerts a direct, anti-hypertrophic effect on cardiomyocyte hypertrophy and prevents AngII-induced cell death. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The effects of metformin (Met) on cell size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Cell size was measured in H9c2 cells 24 hrs after treatment with AngII (200 nM) in the presence or absence of losartan (Los), Met, Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) and splitomicin (SP) or pifithrin-α (Pf). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(A) Representative images of individual cells, (B) cell size (μm), (C) cell size presented as percentage of control. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus AngII. n = 3–4 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The effects of metformin (Met) on AngII-induced cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(A) The effect of AngII (24 hrs), at concentrations ranging from 0 to 5 μM, on cell death, in the presence or absence of 2 mM Met was measured by Trypan blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(B and C) The effects of Met on caspase 3 (full size) and Bcl-2 protein levels in cells treated with 200 nM or 1 μM AngII. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus AngII. n = 3–4 per group (for apoptotic proteins) and 6–8 (for cell death) per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Metformin decreases AngII-induced up-regulation of AT1R </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>AT1R is a predominant AngII receptor in cardiac cells that is typically coupled to Gαq/11 and activates PKC, Ras, MAPKs, JAK-STAT and other pro-hypertrophy signalling molecules 15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In the first set of experiments, we examined whether metformin affected AT1R levels in AngII-treated H9c2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 3A, AngII up-regulated AT1R and AT2R by 38% (P &lt; 0.05) and 40% (P &lt; 0.05) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The presence of metformin or losartan completely prevented AT1R up-regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Also, losartan and metformin further increased AT2R levels by 94% (P = N.S.) and 124% (P &lt; 0.05), respectively, in AngII-treated cells, compared with the control group (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Neither the presence of compound C, splitomicin, nor L-NAME significantly affected AT2R levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Thus, our data demonstrate that metformin reduces AT1R and increases AT2R in AngII-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Compound C (AMPK inhibitor) abolished these effects in the presence of metformin, suggesting that anti-hypertrophic effects of metformin require AMPK activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The effect of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) or splitomicin (SP) on AngII type 1 (AT1R, A) and type 2 (AT2R, B) receptors in cell hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Western blot data were normalized to actin and expressed as fold change relative to control groups. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus Met. n = 6–8 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of AT1R is associated with AMPK activation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In the next group of experiments, we examined whether AT1R inhibition induces AMPK activation in cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of AMPK was accepted as an indicator of enzymatic activity, based on previous data showing that phosphorylation at Thr172 correlates with AMPK activation 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>AngII had no significant effect on P-AMPKαThr172, indicating no activation (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Pre-treatment with losartan and metformin increased AMPK phosphorylation by 54% (P &lt; 0.05) and 99% (P &lt; 0.05), respectively, compared with the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Neither treatment with splitomicin nor L-NAME affected AMPK phosphorylation (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that AngII, in the presence or absence of the pharmacological agents, did not affect total AMPK levels (Fig. 4C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Thus, these findings demonstrate that losartan may reduce AngII-induced cardiomyocyte hypertrophy, at least partially, via AMPK activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The effects of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), compound C (CC), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) or splitomicin (SP) on phospho-AMPK (P-AMPK, A and B) and total-AMPK (T-AMPK, C and D) in cell hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Western blot data were normalized to T-AMPK (for P-AMPK) and actin (for T-AMPK) and expressed as fold change relative to control groups. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus Los and Met. n = 6–8 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f4"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Metformin and losartan increase eNOS activation and reduce p53 in AngII-induced hypertrophy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrate that AMPK phosphorylates eNOS at Ser1177 and increases nitric oxide production in rat hearts 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Nitric oxide has opposite effects on cell metabolism and mitochondrial function; it protects cells against oxidative stress at low concentrations but exerts detrimental effects at high concentrations 17,18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Recent studies demonstrate that eNOS activation (P-eNOSSer1177) plays a central role in H2O2- and AngII-induced signalling in cardiac cells 19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, incubation of cells with AngII enhanced eNOS phosphorylation by 2.1 fold (P &lt; 0.05), compared with the control group (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, both losartan and metformin further increased eNOS activation by 3.3 (P &lt; 0.05) and 3.6 fold (P &lt; 0.05) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Pre-treatment with splitomicin or L-NAME completely prevented AngII-induced phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>AngII did not affect the total level of eNOS in the presence or absence of the pharmacological agents (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The effects of AngII on phospho-eNOS (P-eNOS, A) and total-eNOS (T-eNOS, B) in cardiomyocytes in the presence or absence of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME), and/or splitomicin (SP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Western blot data were normalized to actin and expressed as fold change relative to control groups. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus AngII; &amp;P &lt; 0.05 versus AngII+Met. n = 8–12 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Recent studies identified p53, a well-known tumour suppressor protein, as a key player in heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>It is activated in response to cellular stress, promoting apoptosis and development of heart failure 20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>AngII-induced hypertrophy up-regulated p53 and pro-apoptotic signalling pathways in cardiomyocytes 11,21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, there are no studies about the role of AMPK activation in AngII-induced p53 up-regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Our studies demonstrated that AngII increased the p53 levels by 58% (P &lt; 0.05), after 24 hrs of treatment (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Both metformin and losartan prevented p53 up-regulation in AngII-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>SIRT1 regulates p53 activity through acetylation/deacetylation 22,23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Pre-treatment of cells with splitomicin or L-NAME did not significantly change p53 levels (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Thus, these findings demonstrate that metformin reduces AngII-induced hypertrophy in cardiomyocytes through the regulation of the AMPK/SIRT1/eNOS/p53 pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig06" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The effects of AngII on the level of p53 in cardiomyocytes in the presence or absence of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) and/or splitomicin (SP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Western blot data were normalized to actin and expressed as fold change relative to control groups. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control; +P &lt; 0.05 versus AngII. n = 10–12 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f6"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Metformin prevents mitochondrial membrane depolarization and increases the electron transfer chain (ETC) complex I activity in AngII-treated cardiomyocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Hypertrophic signalling pathways mostly converge on mitochondria to regulate energy metabolism in response to various cellular stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>AMPK plays a central role in mitochondrial metabolism and ATP production by stimulating glucose uptake, fatty acid oxidation and glycolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>We examined whether metformin prevents AngII-induced mitochondrial dysfunction in H9c2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 7A and B, AngII reduced the membrane potential of mitochondria by 26% (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>All drugs, except splitomicin, prevented AngII-induced membrane depolarization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Particularly, pifithrin-α prevented membrane depolarization, indicating that AngII-induced mitochondrial dysfunction may be associated with p53 activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Indeed, p53 translocation to mitochondria may be associated with mitochondrial dysfunction and cell death, according to numerous studies performed by various groups 24,25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, physical interaction between p53 and cyclophilin D (CyP-D), a regulatory protein of the mitochondrial PTP, was found in the mitochondria of cancer cells 24 and in brains subjected to ischaemia/reperfusion 25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>However, our experiments with immunoprecipitation of p53 followed by immunoblotting of CyP-D revealed no physical interaction between these two proteins or other possible PTP components, such as adenine nucleotide translocase and voltage-dependent anion channels (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In addition, metformin and other pharmacological agents, except L-NAME, prevented AngII-induced PTP opening (Fig. 7C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, however, AngII did not induce a significant increase in either total or mitochondrial ROS production in the presence or absence of the tested pharmacological agents, except L-NAME, which significantly increased total ROS levels (Fig. 8A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Metformin may mediate its beneficial effects through direct inhibition of the ETC complex I activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>To elucidate this hypothesis, we assessed a direct effect of metformin on complex I activity in untreated cells (not pre-treated with AngII or pharmacological agents), at concentrations ranging from 0 to 20 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Low concentrations (2 and 5 mM) of metformin did not affect complex I activity, but 10 mM metformin inhibited it (Fig. 9A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, AngII alone did not significantly change complex I activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>However, pre-treatment of AngII-treated cells with metformin increased the activity of the complex (Fig. 9B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Thus, metformin prevents depolarization of mitochondria, inhibits PTP opening and improves ETC activity in AngII-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The beneficial effects of metformin on mitochondria are not associated with its direct interaction with complex I of the ETC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig07" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Effects of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME), splitomicin (SP) or pifithrin-α (Pf) on mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm) and permeability transition pores (PTP) in AngII-treated cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(A) Representative images of JC-1 fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The images were obtained using a Zeiss LSM510 META (Carl Zeiss) microscope from cells after incubation with JC-1 (10 μg/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The cells were treated with Los, Met, SP, L-NAME or Pf in the presence or absence of 200 nM AngII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>In addition, to demonstrate specificity of the fluorescence signal, the cells were treated with FCCP (carbonylcyanide-p-trifluoromethoxyphenylhydrazone), a chemical uncoupler of electron transport and oxidative phosphorylation that induces depolarization of the mitochondrial inner membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Red fluorescent images of dye aggregates (‘J-aggregates’) indicate high ΔΨm, whereas green images of monomeric dye (‘JC-1 monomers’) show low ΔΨm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(B) Quantitative results of JC-1 fluorescence intensity, measured using a Spectramax M3 microplate reader (Molecular Devices). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Data were normalized to cells and expressed as a percentage of the control group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control. n = 6–8 per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(C) Representative images of calcein fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Cells treated with Los, Met, SP, L-NAME or Pf in the presence or absence of 200 nM AngII for 24 hrs were co-loaded with cobalt chloride (5 mM) and calcein-AM (5 μM) and, then, imaged using an Olympus IX73 (Center Valley, PA, USA) inverted fluorescence microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(D) Quantitative results of calcein fluorescence, normalized to individual cells and expressed as a percentage of the control group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control; n = 4 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f7"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig08" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Effects of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) or splitomicin (SP) on total and mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels in AngII-treated H9c2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>(A) Total ROS levels were determined in the cells incubated with the ROS-specific probe, DCF-DA, after treatment with 200 nM AngII in the presence or absence of Los, Met, L-NAME or SP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In additional groups, the cells were treated with 50 μM H2O2 (positive control) or 1 μM AngII for 24 hrs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>(B) Mitochondrial ROS levels were measured under the same conditions using the mitochondrial-sensitive fluorescence dye, MitoSOX Red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In additional groups, the cells were treated with 50 μM H2O2 or 10 μM antimycin (positive control) for 24 hrs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Results were normalized per 106 cells (for total ROS) and 103 cells (for mitochondrial ROS) and expressed as a percentage of the control group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control; n = 6–8 per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f8"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig09" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Effects of losartan (Los), metformin (Met), Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME) or splitomicin (SP) on the activity of ETC. complex I, in the presence or absence of AngII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(A) Met, at concentrations ranging from 0 to 20 mM, was added directly to cell lysates isolated from control H9c2 cardiomyocytes, and the activity of complex I was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>(B) The complex I activity was measured in cardiomyocytes treated with 200 nM AngII, in the presence or absence of Los, Met, L-NAME or SP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Complex I activity was measured by monitoring the decrease in NADH concentration, normalized to mg of protein and expressed as a percentage of the control group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f9"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The results of this study demonstrate the following: (i) In response to AngII, there is a negative reciprocal relationship between AMPK and AT1R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Metformin activates AMPK, inducing down-regulation of AT1R, whereas losartan blocks AT1R and stimulates AMPK activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(ii) Both AMPK activation and AT1R inhibition increase eNOS phosphorylation and down-regulate p53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>(iii) The beneficial effects of AMPK activation and AT1R inhibition may be associated with the prevention of mitochondrial dysfunction in cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In Figure 10, we propose a mechanism for the anti-hypertrophic effect of metformin on AngII-induced cardiomyocyte hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrating anti-hypertrophic and anti-remodelling effects of metformin were mostly performed in vivo on intact hearts 7,26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>However, along with cardiomyocytes, intact hearts contain other cell types, including endothelial and smooth muscle cells, fibroblasts and other connective tissue cells, mast cells and immune system–related cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This study attempts to clarify the role of cardiomyocytes in the anti-hypertrophic action of metformin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Proposed mechanism of the anti-hypertrophic effect of metformin on AngII-induced hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcmm0018-0709-f10"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Metformin is a well-known AMPK activator, and accumulated data demonstrate that AMPK activation plays a central role not only in cardioprotection against ischaemia/reperfusion injury 27 but also in induction of anti-hypertrophic/anti-remodelling effects 28. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Currently, there are no studies elucidating the relationship between AMPK and AT1R in cardiomyocyte hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Our data demonstrate that metformin reduced the amount of AT1R in cultured cardiomyocytes; thus, it blocked the hypertrophic effects of AngII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The effect of metformin was attributed to AMPK activation, as the presence of compound C down-regulated AT1R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>AMPK may reduce AT1R levels through down-regulation of genes encoding the receptor, followed by P-AMPK translocation to the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In response to stress, AMPK subunits accumulate in nuclei, independent of kinase activation 29, where the nuclear AMPKα2 complex regulates gene transcription 30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In addition, active AMPK may abrogate the effect of AngII by inhibiting NAD(P)H oxidase, a downstream target of AT1R, as shown in endothelial cells 31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, losartan stimulated AMPK phosphorylation, suggesting that a negative reciprocal relationship may exist between AMPK and AT1R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that beneficial effects of metformin may also be mediated through AT2R stimulation, which would counteract AT1R and abrogate AT1R-mediated growth responses in cardiac hypertrophy 32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrate an increase 33, decrease 34 or no change 35 in AngII-induced activation of AMPK in cardiac cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We observed that AngII did not remarkably affect AMPK phosphorylation; however, losartan significantly stimulated AMPK phosphorylation by a yet unknown mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Our data are consistent with previous studies, which show that administration of the AT1R blockers, telmisartan and candesartan stimulated AMPK activity in cultured myotubes 36 and rat hypothalamuses 37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It remains unclear how AT1R inhibition stimulates AMPK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>We are tempted to speculate that AT1R-induced AMPK activation may be mediated through regulation of the upstream molecules, LKB1 and/or CamKK, and internalization and interaction of AT1R with AMPK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The beneficial effects of AMPK activation and AT1R inhibition on mitochondria may be mediated through the same mechanism(s) or independent pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>AngII binds to AT1R, activating the transcription factor, p53, and apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>p53 binding to AT1R gene promoter regions is primarily responsible for up-regulating the receptor 38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We found that losartan prevention of AT1R up-regulation was associated with decreased p53 levels, indicating that the latter mediates the AT1R-induced apoptotic pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, metformin- or losartan-induced AMPK activation can increase NAD+/NADH, which, in turn, stimulates the NAD+-dependent deacetylases sirtuins, including SIRT1, a regulator of p53 activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>According to previous studies, when metformin induces activation of AMPK and SIRT1, an inverse relationship exists between metformin-triggered AMPK-SIRT1 signalling and p53 protein levels in high glucose-exposed HepG2 cells 39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, in the presence of metformin, AMPK-induced p53 down-regulation may prevent AngII-induced AT1R up-regulation 38. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of eNOS at Ser1177 may be a downstream target of the AMPK/SIRT1 pathway 40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, both metformin and losartan increased P-eNOSSer1177 levels in our studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Splitomicin, however, prevented eNOS activation, indicating that SIRT1 is an upstream molecule of eNOS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Although eNOS inhibition enhanced AMPK activation in endothelial cells 41, our data revealed that treatment with L-NAME did not appreciably alter P-AMPK levels in cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This difference can be due to cell specificity, as different cell types were used in these studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Activation of the AMPK/eNOS pathway and subsequent metformin- or losartan-enhanced nitric oxide production may have various, further cardioprotective effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In addition to coronary vasodilatation, nitric oxide regulates cell metabolism, including mitochondrial function in cardiomyocytes 42. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>A number of studies 6,43, including ours, 13 demonstrate that metformin therapy attenuates mitochondrial dysfunction during ischaemia/reperfusion and heart failure via yet unknown mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Consistent with these reports, we found that metformin prevented AngII-induced depolarization of the mitochondrial membrane, an index of mitochondrial function in cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Likewise, both losartan and pifithrin-α may improve mitochondrial function, indicating that the effects of AMPK activation and AT1R inhibition converge on mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Various mechanisms can mediate the beneficial effects of AMPK activation on mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>For example, metformin protects the heart through PI3K- 43 and PPARα- 13 mediated inhibition of the mitochondrial PTP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, in response to oxidative stress, p53 translocates to mitochondria and forms the CyP-D-p53 complex, which is associated with mitochondrial PTP opening 24,25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In the presence or absence of metformin, we found no difference between control and AngII-treated groups with regard to the interaction of CyP-D with p53, although pifithrin-α abrogated AngII-induced membrane depolarization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that metformin-induced activation of the AMPK/SIRT1/eNOS pathway prevents AngII-induced, p53-dependent membrane depolarization and PTP opening in mitochondria, which is not associated with protein–protein interaction between p53 and CyP-D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>It appears that further studies are necessary to clarify the role of p53 in hypertrophy-induced mitochondrial dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>At high concentrations (&gt;10 mM), metformin may improve mitochondrial function, independent of AMPK activation via direct inhibition of complex I 44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>However, this study excluded that possibility, because 2 mM metformin did not inhibit complex I activity (Fig. 9A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, metformin activates AMPK, preventing AT1R up-regulation, and, vice versa, losartan down-regulates AT1R, stimulating AMPK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>As such, this study demonstrates a negative reciprocal relationship between AMPK activation and AT1R levels in AngII-induced cardiomyocyte hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In response to AngII administration, the AMPK/SIRT1/eNOS pathway abrogation of mitochondrial dysfunction mediates, at least partially, the beneficial effects of metformin and losartan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Our studies provide further evidence that AMPK can be targeted to promote cardiomyocyte survival via activation of several signalling pathways in hypertrophy and heart failure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Bryan Agostini and Alan Preston for critical reading of the manuscript, and Gabriela Bergollo for her assistance with cell size experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the National Heart, Lung, And Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health through Research Grant SC1HL118669 (to SJ), and in part, by the RCMI National Center for Research Resources NIH Grant G12RR-03051. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors confirm that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>1HardieDGHawleySAScottJWAMP-activated protein kinase–development of the energy sensor conceptJ Physiol200657471516644800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>2AradMSeidmanCESeidmanJGAMP-activated protein kinase in the heart: role during health and diseaseCirc Res20071004748817332438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>3BertrandLGinionABeauloyeCAMPK activation restores the stimulation of glucose uptake in an in vitro model of insulin-resistant cardiomyocytes via the activation of protein kinase BAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol2006291H2395016489105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>4ZhangLHeHBalschiJAMetformin and phenformin activate AMP-activated protein kinase in the heart by increasing cytosolic AMP concentrationAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol2007293H4576617369473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>5KirpichnikovDMcFarlaneSISowersJRMetformin: an updateAnn Intern Med2002137253312093242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>6GundewarSCalvertJWJhaSActivation of AMP-activated protein kinase by metformin improves left ventricular function and survival in heart failureCirc Res20091044031119096023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>7SasakiHAsanumaHFujitaMMetformin prevents progression of heart failure in dogs: role of AMP-activated protein kinaseCirculation200911925687719414638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>8MolkentinJDDornGW2ndCytoplasmic signaling pathways that regulate cardiac hypertrophyAnnu Rev Physiol20016339142611181961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>9ReidIAInteractions between ANG II, sympathetic nervous system, and baroreceptor reflexes in regulation of blood pressureAm J Physiol1992262E763781616014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>10SiragyHMAT(1) and AT(2) receptors in the kidney: role in disease and treatmentAm J Kidney Dis200036S4910986153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>11LiuQWangGZhouGAngiotensin II-induced p53-dependent cardiac apoptotic cell death: its prevention by metallothioneinToxicol Lett20091913142019808082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>12DaiDFRabinovitchPMitochondrial oxidative stress mediates induction of autophagy and hypertrophy in angiotensin-II treated mouse heartsAutophagy20117917821505274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>13Barreto-TorresGParodi-RullanRJavadovSThe role of PPARalpha in metformin-induced attenuation of mitochondrial dysfunction in acute cardiac ischemia/reperfusion in ratsInt J Mol Sci201213769470922837722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>14HawleySAGadallaAEOlsenGSThe antidiabetic drug metformin activates the AMP-activated protein kinase cascade via an adenine nucleotide-independent mechanismDiabetes2002512420512145153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>15CookJLReRNLessons from in vitro studies and a related intracellular angiotensin II transgenic mouse modelAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol2012302R4829322170617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>16LeiBMatsuoKLabinskyyVExogenous nitric oxide reduces glucose transporters translocation and lactate production in ischemic myocardium in vivoProc Natl Acad Sci USA200510269667115870202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>17BolliRCardioprotective function of inducible nitric oxide synthase and role of nitric oxide in myocardial ischemia and preconditioning: an overview of a decade of researchJ Mol Cell Cardiol200133189791811708836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>18JugduttBINitric oxide in heart failure: friend or foeHeart Fail Rev20027385912379823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>19SartorettoJLKalwaHPluthMDHydrogen peroxide differentially modulates cardiac myocyte nitric oxide synthesisProc Natl Acad Sci USA201110815792721896719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>20FujitaTIshikawaYApoptosis in heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>-The role of the beta-adrenergic receptor-mediated signaling pathway and p53-mediated signaling pathway in the apoptosis of cardiomyocytesCirc J2011751811821747195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>21GrishkoVPastukhVSolodushkoVApoptotic cascade initiated by angiotensin II in neonatal cardiomyocytes: role of DNA damageAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol2003285H23647212919932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>22LangleyEPearsonMFarettaMHuman SIR2 deacetylates p53 and antagonizes PML/p53-induced cellular senescenceEMBO J20022123839612006491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>23VaziriHDessainSKNg EatonEhSIR2(SIRT1) functions as an NAD-dependent p53 deacetylaseCell20011071495911672523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>24WolffSErsterSPalaciosGp53's mitochondrial translocation and MOMP action is independent of Puma and Bax and severely disrupts mitochondrial membrane integrityCell Res2008187334418504456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>25VasevaAVMarchenkoNDJiKp53 opens the mitochondrial permeability transition pore to trigger necrosisCell201214915364822726440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>26YinMvan der HorstICvan MelleJPMetformin improves cardiac function in a nondiabetic rat model of post-MI heart failureAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol2011301H4596821572014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>27RussellRR3rdLiJCovenDLAMP-activated protein kinase mediates ischemic glucose uptake and prevents postischemic cardiac dysfunction, apoptosis, and injuryJ Clin Invest200411449550315314686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>28FuYNXiaoHMaXWMetformin attenuates pressure overload-induced cardiac hypertrophy via AMPK activationActa Pharmacol Sin2011328798721552292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>29KodihaMRassiJGBrownCMLocalization of AMP kinase is regulated by stress, cell density, and signaling through the MEK-ERK1/2 pathwayAm J Physiol Cell Physiol2007293C14273617728396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>30SaltICellerJWHawleySAAMP-activated protein kinase: greater AMP dependence, and preferential nuclear localization, of complexes containing the alpha2 isoformBiochem J1998334177879693118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>31SchuhmacherSForetzMKnorrMalpha1AMP-activated protein kinase preserves endothelial function during chronic angiotensin II treatment by limiting Nox2 upregulationArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol201131560621205985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>32van KesterenCAvan HeugtenHALamersJMAngiotensin II-mediated growth and antigrowth effects in cultured neonatal rat cardiac myocytes and fibroblastsJ Mol Cell Cardiol1997292147579281446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>33NagataDTakedaRSataMAMP-activated protein kinase inhibits angiotensin II-stimulated vascular smooth muscle cell proliferationCirculation20041104445115262850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>34StuckBJLenskiMBohmMMetabolic switch and hypertrophy of cardiomyocytes following treatment with angiotensin II are prevented by AMP-activated protein kinaseJ Biol Chem200828332562918790741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>35JiangSYXuMMaXWA distinct AMP-activated protein kinase phosphorylation site characterizes cardiac hypertrophy induced by L-thyroxine and angiotensin IIClin Exp Pharm Physiol20103791925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>36FengXLuoZMaLAngiotensin II receptor blocker telmisartan enhances running endurance of skeletal muscle through activation of the PPAR-delta/AMPK pathwayJ Cell Mol Med20111515728120477906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>37MarquesMBRibeiro-OliveiraAJrGuimaraesJModifications in basal and stress-induced hypothalamic AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) activity in rats chronically treated with an angiotensin II receptor blockerStress2012155546122217206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>38PierzchalskiPReissKChengWp53 Induces myocyte apoptosis via the activation of the renin-angiotensin systemExp Cell Res199723457659223370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>39NelsonLEValentineRJCacicedoJMA novel inverse relationship between metformin-triggered AMPK-SIRT1 signaling and p53 protein abundance in high glucose-exposed HepG2 cellsAm J Physiol Cell Physiol2012303C41322378745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>40OtaHEtoMOgawaSSIRT1/eNOS axis as a potential target against vascular senescence, dysfunction and atherosclerosisJ Atheroscler Thromb201017431520215708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>41JinBYSartorettoJLGladyshevVNEndothelial nitric oxide synthase negatively regulates hydrogen peroxide-stimulated AMP-activated protein kinase in endothelial cellsProc Natl Acad Sci USA200910617343819805165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>42RakhitRDMarberMSNitric oxide: an emerging role in cardioprotection?Heart2001863687211559670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>43BhamraGSHausenloyDJDavidsonSMMetformin protects the ischemic heart by the Akt-mediated inhibition of mitochondrial permeability transition pore openingBasic Res Cardiol20081032748418080084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>44El-MirMYNogueiraVFontaineEDimethylbiguanide inhibits cell respiration via an indirect effect targeted on the respiratory chain complex IJ Biol Chem2000275223810617608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
