<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3960246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24647796</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-39100</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0092412</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Relations</subject><subject>Psychological Stress</subject><subject>Social Psychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care Policy</subject><subject>Psychological and Psychosocial Issues</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Mental Health and Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Mood Disorders</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Elevated Social Stress Levels and Depressive Symptoms in Primary Hyperhidrosis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Hyperhidrosis and Stress</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>Katharina M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schote</surname><given-names>Andrea B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>Katja Kerstin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>André</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Jobst</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Neurobehavioral Genetics, Institute of Psychobiology, University of Trier, Trier, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychology, Cognitive Psychology, University of Trier, Trier, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Sub-domain Self-Regulation and Health, Research Unit INSIDE, University of Luxembourg, Walferdange, Luxembourg</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Clinical Psychophysiology, Institute of Psychobiology, University of Trier, Trier, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Slominski</surname><given-names>Andrzej T.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>meyerjo@uni-trier.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KMG AS JM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: KMG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: KMG ABS KKS AS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KMG ABS KKS AS JM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: KMG ABS JM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e92412</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Gross et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gross et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Primary hyperhidrosis is defined as excessive sweating of certain body areas without physiological reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrotic individuals report a high psychological strain and an impairment of their quality of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Thus, the aim of the study is to investigate the relation between hyperhidrosis and different psychological as well as physiological aspects of chronic stress as a co-factor for the etiology of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In this study, forty hyperhidrotic subjects were compared to forty age- and sex-matched healthy control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The Trier Inventory of Chronic Stress (‘Trierer Inventar zum chronischen Stress’: TICS), the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) and the Screening for Somatoform Disorders (SOMS-2) were used to examine the correlation between primary hyperhidrosis and stress as well as accompanying depressive and somatic symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The cortisol awakening response of each subject was analyzed as a physiological stress correlate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In hyperhidrotics, we found a significant lack of social recognition as well as significantly more depressive symptoms compared to the control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A subgroup of patients with axillary hyperhidrosis had the highest impact on these increased issues of chronic stress, pointing to a higher embarrassment in these subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Especially in social situations, hyperhidrotics showed higher stress levels, whereby a vicious circle of stress and sweating is triggered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>However, the cortisol awakening response did not significantly differ between hyperhidrotics and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Moreover, affected persons suffer from more depressive symptoms, which may be caused by feelings of shame and a lack of self-confidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This initial study provides an impetus for further investigation to reveal a causative relationship between hyperhidrosis and its psychological concomitants. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>JM and ABS were supported by the German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG), grant GRK 1389. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Sweating, for example in Finnish Sauna or Turkish Hammam, is accepted as a form of promoting well-being and social interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, in everyday life, it is associated with lacking hygiene and classified as a social no-go. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it is often accompanied by a high psychological strain and, in worst cases, even social isolation [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In general, sweating can be divided into thermoregulatory and emotional sweating, both regulated by different physiological mechanisms [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>People affected with excessive emotional and increased thermoregulatory sweating, which exceed physiologically necessary levels, are diagnosed as hyperhidrotic [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrosis is separated into a primary and a secondary form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Primary hyperhidrosis, which was investigated in this study, is characterized by excessive sweating of particular body regions as a disease pattern per se. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Although objective measurements of the absolute sweat secretion can be performed, the impact of hyperhidrosis and its diagnosis highly depend on the individual perception and hence the psychological strain of the affected person. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In the ICD-10, localized hyperhidrosis is characterized as R61.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The mainly affected regions are the palms, the plants, the armpits and the face. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The prevalence in the U.S. is about 2.8% for primary hyperhidrosis, whereof one half of the patients suffer from axillary hyperhidrosis [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Palmar hyperhidrosis, which affects approximately 0.6 to 1% of the Western population, is often related to plantar hyperhidrosis [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Excessive sweating usually has its onset in adolescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>However, hyperhidrosis of palms and plants often already occurs in childhood [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The skin is the major organ in the sweating process and a barrier between the external and internal environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>It is made up of three different dermal layers: epidermis, dermis – with the adnexal structures including, amongst others, the sweat glands – and subcutaneous tissue [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Epidermal, dermal and adnexal structures communicate through the production of neurotransmitters, neuropeptides, neurohormones and hormones to regulate the local homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Likewise, skin cells express receptors for neuropeptides and neurotransmitters similar to those expressed in the central neuroendocrine systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Therewith, the skin is a potential target of neural responses [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the skin transfers sensory stimuli via afferent nerves to the central nervous system, where the thalamus as a central coordinator receives and sends neural signals to the central structures of the autonomic nervous system [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>As a putative cause of primary hyperhidrosis, the highly increased sympathetic activity of the autonomic nervous system is postulated [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Eccrine glands are, via the neurotransmitter acetylcholine, innervated by postgaglionic sympathetic fibres and lead to a subsequent increase of sweat secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>However, apocrine glands respond to emotional stimuli and are activated via innervation or via circulating catecholamines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Apoeccrine glands are mixed type glands and show a greater responsiveness to cholinergic and adrenergic stimuli than eccrine glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>They have a very high overall sweat rate and may contribute strongly to axillary sweating [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Since a sympathetic overactivity has also been shown in patients with somatization disorders [13], we were interested in the relationship of somatic symptoms and hyperhidrosis in affected persons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the primary form, secondary hyperhidrosis is characterized by excessive sweating caused by a variety of physiological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>These include, amongst others, obesity, menopause, infections, intoxication, malignant tumors and endocrinologic, cardiovascular or neurologic dysfunctions as well as certain medications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Most of the patients with secondary hyperhidrosis sweat generalized all over their body [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focus on self-perceived chronic psychological stress in persons affected by hyperhidrosis, which has a strong social component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In general, the body of a human being adapts successfully to environmental and internal challenges, which lead to complex physiological, psychological and behavioral responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This stress response depends on the situation, the kind of stressor and whether the stress is acute, episodic or chronic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Avoiding a handshake, wearing dark clothes, changing shirts several times a day, worrying about someone seeing the pit stains – all of this implies that psychological stress constitutes a strong social component in the everyday life of the hyperhidrotics [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Although there is evidence that affected persons suffer from a decreased quality of life only few studies have been performed [1], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Under discussion are the lack of self-confidence and bodily discomfort as well as feelings like shame and fear as mediators of disturbed interpersonal relationships [5] and social seclusion [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>These mental states cause even more psychosocial stress, which represents a considerable risk factor for the development of many diseases and disorders, such as depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Finally, the development of depressive symptoms observed in some hyperhidrotics [17] might be triggered by a vicious circle of sweating and psychosocial stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Psychosocial stress – as one possible issue in hyperhidrosis – leads to the activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The secretion of corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) and arginine-vasopressin in the hypothalamus leads to the production of adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) in the anterior pituitary, which results in the secretion of cortisol from the adrenal glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Cortisol as the major stress hormone acts on hypothalamus, pituitary and hippocampus and inhibits its own production by a negative feedback loop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the skin has its own stress response system providing local protection for the skin and internal homeostasis [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>This cutaneous HPA axis is activated by physiological stressors, such as bursts of radiation, mechanical energy or chemical and biological insults [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Probably, the skin can regulate the central HPA axis depending on the intensity and nature of the stressor [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the skin produces all peptide hormones being central constituents of the HPA axis [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>CRH, for example, is not only synthesized in the hypothalamus in consequence of an activated HPA axis, but also in the skin itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Moreover, CRH and its receptor CRHR1 were found in sweat glands [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The systemic HPA axis shows an increase in the cortisol response to awakening (cortisol awakening response, CAR) [19], which has been widely used as a sensitive and stable measurement for the physiological reactivity of the HPA axis under baseline conditions [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Thus, the CAR is not a measure for acute but rather for high chronic stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In meta-analyses, an increased CAR has been linked to job and general life stress, whereas a decreased CAR was correlated with fatigue, burnout or exhaustion [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The effects of stress-related factors on the CAR may actually depend on the duration of stressful conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Chronic stress might initially be associated with an increased HPA axis activity, whereas individuals can develop a HPA axis hypoactivity if chronic stress persists for a longer period of time [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>CAR has been thoroughly investigated with regard to depression revealing opposing results [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>However, so far, no study has ever addressed the correlation of CAR and hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that, due to the burden of their disorder, the hyperhidrotic subjects of our sample perceive more chronic psychosocial stress compared to the normohidrotic control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Based on this, we assume that the hyperhidrotic group suffers from more depressive symptoms than the controls as a result of the permanent exposure to psychosocial stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, for our group of hyperhidrotic subjects, we hypothesize a decreased CAR as a measure of HPA reactivity caused by very high chronic stress levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Finally, increased stress levels are accompanied by other symptoms induced by the autonomic nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Thus, it can be assumed that hyperhidrotic persons show more somatic symptoms compared to the control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>This is the first study focusing on hyperhidrosis and psychosocial stress by examining particular facets of chronic stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the University of Trier according to The Code of Ethics of the World Medical Association (Declaration of Helsinki) for experiments involving humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>All participants gave a written informed consent that they took part in the study voluntarily. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Sampling Techniques and Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We contacted local dermatologists and general practitioners to recruit an age- and sex-matched sample consisting of 40 subjects excessively sweating on palms, plants and/or armpits and 40 healthy control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The age of the hyperhidrotic subjects was between 19 and 72 years (M: 31.43; SD: 14.34) and the age of the control subjects was between 19 and 73 years (M: 31.83; SD: 14.58). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The sample consisted of university students, employees and unemployed persons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>All subjects were of European descent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The mean Body Mass Index (BMI) of the excessively sweating subjects was 24.49 kg/m2 (range: 17.63 to 41.12; SD: 5.37) and the one of the control group was 23.22 kg/m2 (range: 19.05 to 30.42; SD: 2.84). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>An overview is given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Persons with mental, endocrinological or metabolic disorders potentially indicating secondary hyperhidrosis were excluded from our sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, subjects were not allowed to use any medication except oral contraceptives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Additionally, women taking the oral contraceptives Yasmin, Yasminelle or Petibelle were excluded because of the component drospirenone, an antagonist of the mineralcorticoid receptor, which may affect the stress reactivity of the body through a modified cortisol release [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0092412-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0092412.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Specified description of the sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0092412-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0092412.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrotic subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Control subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Statistic </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>p </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Effect size φ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>age [mean (SD)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>31.43 (14.34) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>31.83 (14.58) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>t(78) = 0.124 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>0.902 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>age [N (%)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>19 to 30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>28 (35%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>28 (35%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>31 to 50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>6 (7.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>6 (7.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>51 to 73 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>6 (7.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>6 (7.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>sex [N (%)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>-male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>20 (25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>20 (25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>-female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>20 (25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>20 (25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>BMI [mean (SD)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>24.49 (5.37) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>23.22 (2.84) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>t(78) = 1.325 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>0.189 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>BMI [N (%)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>&lt;19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>2 (2.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>0 (0%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>19 to 24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>22 (27.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>27 (33.75%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 1.317 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>0.251 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>0.128 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>&gt;24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>16 (20%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>13 (16.25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0.487 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>0.485 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>0.078 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>employment [N (%)] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>-student </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>29 (36.25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>29 (36.25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>0.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>-employed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>9 (11.25%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>8 (10%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0.075 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>0.785 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>0.031 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>-unemployed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>2 (2.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>3 (3.75%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>?2(1) = 0.231 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>0.644 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>0.052 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Notes: BMI: Body Mass Index; SD: Standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Procedures and Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>All individuals were carefully screened by a trained psychologist (K.M.G.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>They underwent a medical and psychological anamnestic screening to gather information about their present and past medical status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Those individuals complaining about excessive sweating, who did not yet consult a dermatologist (30 out of 40 hyperhidrotic subjects), underwent a gravimetric measuring procedure of their sweat production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, weighted filter paper was pressed on the sweating body area and weighted after one minute [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>All participants exceeded the threshold values of 30 mg/min for palms and 50 mg/min for armpits, respectively [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>All hyperhidrotic subjects filled in parts A and B of the German version of the Hyperhidrosis Impact Questionnaire (HHIQ) [26], to provide information about the onset, the affected areas of the body and the extent of sweating of the respondents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the German versions of the following questionnaires were used: (1) The Trier Inventory for Chronic Stress (Trierer Inventar zum chronischen Stress: TICS) [27] consists of nine subscales, which measure the amount of self-reported chronic stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(2) By means of the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) [28] (German version: [29]), depressive symptoms can be revealed by counting up the single item values to a total sum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>(3) The Screening for Somatoform Disorders (SOMS-2) [30] serves as a self-report measure for somatic symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>All questionnaires are reliable and validated measuring instruments for the German market [27], [29], [30] and are summarized in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0092412-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0092412.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Means and standard deviations (in parentheses) of hyperhidrotic, axillary hyperhidrotic and control subjects for different questionnaires and cortisol. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0092412-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0092412.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrotic subjects N = 40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Axillary hyperhidrotic subjects N = 20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Control subjects N = 40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Difference (Hyperhidrosis - Control subjects) F(1,78)/p </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Difference (Axillary hyperhidrosis -Control subjects) F(1,58)/p </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>TICS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>-work overload </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>55.18 (11.50) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>59.00 (12.69) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>50.78(12.14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>2.77/0.100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>5.75/0.020* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>-social overload </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>52.55 (8.59) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>53.95 (7.66) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>48.30 (7.22) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>5.74/0.019* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>7.58/0.008* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>-pressure to succeed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>49.75 (8.62) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>51.32 (9.09) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>47.58 (7.86) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>1,39/0.242 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>2.64/0.110 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>-work discontent </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>56.10 (8.75) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>58.79 (7.61) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>52.72 (8.11) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>3.20/0.078 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>7.49/0.008* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>-excessive demands from work </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>59.60 (12.07) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>64.58 (9.81) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>54.33 (9.24) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>4.82/0.031* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>15.27/0.00025** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>-lack of social recognition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>56.07 (11.52) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>60.11 (9.19) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>48.13 (9.04) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>11.79/0.001** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>22.38/0.000015** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>-social tensions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>51.38 (11.26) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>53.21 (13.56) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>48.70 (10.96) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>1.16/0.285 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>1.87/0.177 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>-social isolation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>53.73 (9.93) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>56.53 (10.60) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>51.75 (10.81) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>0.73/0.397 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>2.55/0.116 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>-chronic worrying </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>56.03 (10.93) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>60.89 (9.76) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>50.98 (8.30) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>5.42/0.023* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>16.42/0.000156** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>-chronic stress screening scale </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>58.23 (11.87) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>63.26 (10.26) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>52.28 (7.89) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>6.98/0.010* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>20.50/0.000031** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>BDI-II </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>10.53 (8.71) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>14.26 (8.93) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>4.83 (3.13) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>15.15/0,000208** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>35.96/0.000000** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>SOMS-2 Symptom index </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>9.72 (7.76) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>11.32 (8.95) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>5.75 (4.70) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>7.68/0.007* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>9.88/0.003* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>CAR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>-AUCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>50.08 (21.05) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>50.73 (22.25) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>47.94 (18.18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>0.23/0.631 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>0.26/0.612 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>-AUCI </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>13.45 (14.77) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>11.69 (9.57) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>14.98 (14.17) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>0.22/0.640 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>0.84/0.365 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>AUCg: area under the curve with respect to ground; AUCi: area under the curve with respect to increase; BDI-II: Beck Depression Inventory; CAR: cortisol awakening response; SOMS-2: Screening for Somatoform Disorders; TICS: Trier Inventory of Chronic Stress; Notes: *significance at p &lt; 0.005; **corrected empirical significance at p &lt; 0.00089; method: analysis of variance (ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>All subjects sampled saliva using Salivettes (Sarstedt, Nümbrecht) on two consecutive days at the time of awakening and 30, 45 and 60 minutes thereafter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The collected saliva samples were analyzed in the biochemical laboratory of the University of Trier using an immunoassay with fluorescence detection [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>For all statistical analyses, SPSS 19.0 (Statistical Package for the Social Sciences, SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>To include the CAR in our analysis, areas under the curve with respect to ground (AUCG) and with respect to increase (AUCI) [32] were calculated for each subject using the single means of the four measurements of the first and the second day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>All subjects with negative results of the AUCI were set to zero in order to avoid negative areas and to state that no increase was seen in these subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The data derived from the questionnaires as well as the AUCG and the AUCI of the CAR were compared in an one-way ANOVA (analysis of variance) model with the between-subjects factor ‘group’ (‘hyperhidrosis’ and ‘healthy controls’) to detect possible differences between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a dummy variable was created to differ between axillary hyperhidrotics and other hyperhidrotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Again, three one-way ANOVAs were used to compare axillary hyperhidrotics to other hyperhidrotics, other hyperhidrotics to controls and axillary hyperhidrotics to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>A χ2 model was used to match the sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The data derived from the HHIQ were evaluated using descriptive statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The significance level for all tests was set to p = 0.05 and Bonferroni correction was calculated to correct for multiple comparisons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Thus, the corrected significance level for all tests is set to p = 0.00089. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, power analysis was performed using G*Power, version 3.1.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uni-duesseldorf.de/home/Fakultaeten/math_nat/WE/Psychologie/abteilungen/aap/gpower3/download-and-register">http://www.uni-duesseldorf.de/home/Fakultaeten/math_nat/WE/Psychologie/abteilungen/aap/gpower3/download-and-register</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrosis Impact Questionnaire </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Most of the subjects (47,5%) reported the onset of their hyperhidrosis at an age between 12 and 17 years, 35% were over 17 years old, 10% were between 6 and 11 and 7,5% were under the age of 6 when their excessive sweating began. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The body regions most frequently affected were the armpits (50%), followed by the palms (25%), the face (17,5%), the plants (5%) and the back (2,5%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>An overview about the following questionnaire and cortisol data and their statistical analysis is presented in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Trier Inventory of Chronic Stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The hyperhidrotics of our sample showed significantly higher values for “lack of social recognition” (p = 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Uncorrected, four other scales, “social overload” (p = 0.019), “excessive demands from work” (p = 0.031), “chronic worrying” (p = 0.023) and the “chronic stress screening scale” (p = 0.010), differed between both groups, reflecting a trend towards more chronic stress in our hyperhidrotic subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>All other scales did not differ significantly between both groups before or after correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Comparing only axillary hyperhidrotics to the control group, the hyperhidrotics had significantly higher scales for “excessive demands from work” (p  = 0.00025), “lack of social recognition” (p = 0.000015), “chronic worrying” (p = 0.000156) and the “chronic stress screening scale” (p = 0.000031) after Bonferroni correction indicating a higher stress level especially in subjects with axillary hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Comparing axillary hyperhidrotics to other hyperhidrotics, and other hyperhidrotics to the control group, no significant differences were found after Bonferroni correction (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Without correction, axillary hyperhidrotics showed significant higher scales for “social overload” (p = 0.048), “work discontent” (p = 0.039), “excessive demands from work” (p = 0.011), “lack of social recognition” (p = 0.031), “chronic worrying” (p = 0.003) and the “chronic stress screening scale” (p = 0.008) compared to other hyperhidrotics (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Beck Depression Inventory </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>As measured by the Beck Depression Inventory, 24 out of 40 hyperhidrotics (60%) reached total sum scores equal or greater nine, which represents the screening’s cut-off for an indication of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>In comparison, 4 out of 40 healthy control individuals (10%) provided a sum equal or greater nine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Overall, the hyperhidrotics showed a significantly higher BDI sum score than the healthy controls (p = 0.000208). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Comparing only axillary hyperhidrotics to the control group, an even bigger difference between those groups occurred (p = 0.000000) after Bonferroni correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>By comparing axillary hyperhidrotics to other hyperhidrotics, and other hyperhidrotics to the control group, no significant differences were found after correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Without correction, axillary hyperhidrotics would have a higher BDI-II sum score than other hyperhidrotics (p = 0.001) reflecting a trend towards more depressive symptoms in axillary hyperhidrosis compared to other hyperhidrotics (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Screening for Somatoform Disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Hyperhidrotics did not show significantly more somatic symptoms compared to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>However uncorrected, a trend towards increased somatic symptoms (p = 0.007), especially blushing and hot flashes, was reported by the hyperhidrotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Comparing axillary hyperhidrotics to the controls, axillary to other hyperhidrotics or other hyperhidrotics to the control group, no significant differences were found. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Cortisol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 2 (and Table S1), the total hormonal output measured by the area under the curve with respect to ground (AUCG) as well as the sensitivity of the HPA measured by the area under the curve with respect to increase (AUCI) showed no significant differences between all groups tested (p all ≥ 0.36). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The aim of the current study was to investigate the connection between hyperhidrosis and psychosocial parameters as well as cortisol as a physiological correlate of stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>In line with others [7], [26], the majority of the excessively sweating subjects of our sample reported the onset of their hyperhidrosis in childhood or puberty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>These important stages of life are very sensitive for changes and disturbances of the developmental processes of self-esteem and identity [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>We found that lack of social recognition as one indicator of chronic stress as well as the amount of depressive symptoms is significantly higher in the hyperhidrotics compared to matched healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, axillary sweating had the highest impact on increased TICS and BDI-II scores in the entire hyperhidrotic group, which may result in the higher impairment of axillary hyperhidrotics reported by Hamm and colleagues (2006) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, hyperhidrosis causes considerable disruptions of social and professional life, leading to severe limitations of the person’s quality of life [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Especially in social situations, excessive sweating, and most notably axillary sweating, might attract attention leading to a stressful condition for the hyperhidrotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Additionally, emotional processes stimulate or maintain the secretion of sweat resulting in a vicious circle of sweating and social stress described by Sonntag and Ruzicka (2004) [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Many people consider sweat as an indication for lacking hygiene and refuse persons who sweat excessively, resulting in the lack of social recognition found in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>So far, cause and consequence of sweating and stress are still unclear due to their reciprocal interaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>In our study, we could merely see a trend towards increased somatic symptoms caused by an overactivity of the autonomic nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>A dysfunction of the autonomic nervous system is discussed as one reason for somatoform disorders as well as for hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Thus, Shih and colleagues (1983) postulate an overactive sympathetic nervous system to be causative for hyperhidrosis [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Additionally, psychosocial stress might have a maintaining or reinforcing influence on both, excessive sweating and somatoform disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the disease itself might preserve as a stressor in the wake of chronification [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study investigating CAR in hyperhidrotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>A multitude of studies, summarized in a meta-analysis by Chida and Steptoe, showed that there is evidence of an increased CAR in individuals reporting chronic stress in general and the lack of social recognition in particular [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Although we found an increased lack of social recognition in our hyperhidrotics, we did not detect differences in their cortisol awakening response compared to our control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>However, measurable changes of the CAR are particularly expected in highly to pathologically stressed persons [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Indeed, we found that our hyperhidrotic subjects suffer from chronic stress but did not show highly psychopathological symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Thus, our results can be seen congruent with others. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Besides measuring CAR, other methods to approach HPA axis activity could be applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The Trier Social Stress Test [35] or the socially-evaluated cold-pressor stress test [36] could be used to investigate the cortisol release of hyperhidrotics after acute stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Another possibility would be a pharmacological intervention, using the dexamethasone suppression test to elucidate the feedback regulation of the HPA axis in excessively sweating people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The communication of cutaneous and systemic HPA axis might be another interesting parameter to look at in further studies on hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The skin can activate the systemic HPA axis via neural transmission to the brain (hypothalamus), via activation of the pituitary through skin-derived factors, or directly via the activation of the adrenal cortex [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been shown that environmental stressors, such as ultra violet radiation, stimulate the production of cutaneous CRH, which can act on the pituitary level of the systemic HPA axis [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Likewise, it would be interesting to investigate if the influence of psychosocial stressors is comparable to that of physical environmental stressors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, CRH has been investigated as a possible factor in disorders of adnexal skin structures, such as acne vulgaris [8], but not yet in excessive sweating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Thus, this might be a novel aspect in the research of hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Beyond the self-reported higher stress levels, the hyperhidrotics of our study manifested more depressive symptoms compared to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>The effect size of η2 = 0,163 indicates a remarkable effect (conventions after Cohen (1988) [37]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>60% of the hyperhidrotics scored values beyond the threshold for depression in the BDI-II, whereas merely 10% of the controls did. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Our results are comparable to a study of Lee and colleagues (2012), who found BDI values similar to ours [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>In comparison, Ruchinskas and colleagues (2002) detected depressive symptoms in merely 7% of the hyperhidrotics [38] and Weber and co-workers (2005) did not find any difference between hyperhidrotics and the normal population [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>These different results are justified by various measuring instruments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>In our study, the subjects could not be assigned randomly to the two conditions due to the nature of the independent variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a causative conclusion was hardly to draw because hyperhidrosis is not susceptible to manipulation in this quasi-experimental design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>However, psychopathological symptoms, for example triggered by self-imposed withdrawal, might rather represent the effect of hyperhidrosis than being its primary cause [38], [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Moreover, axillary sweating may constitute an endophenotype genetically and physiologically linked to a higher susceptibility for depression and should be investigated separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>In line with others [40], [41], we found a familial aggregation for different forms of primary hyperhidrosis including axillary and palmar hyperhidrosis (preliminary data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Previously, a heritability of 28% for palmar hyperhidrosis has been shown [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Therefore, further investigation of different endophenotypes of hyperhidrosis should include genetic analyses, too.A limitation of our study was the lack of medical diagnosis of hyperhidrosis in most of our subjects, who indicated that they were often too embarrassed by their condition to consult a physician. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Therefore, all subjects without prior diagnosis (75%) were tested using a gravimetric examination and the relevant thresholds were exceeded by all of them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we presumed that all excessively sweating subjects had a primary hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The exclusion of other medical conditions for the explanation of hyperhidrotic symptoms was conducted via personal anamnesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Questions related to details on the excessive sweating, chronic and acute diseases or disorders and intake of pharmaceuticals were asked to obtain the psychological and physiological status of each subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Thus, a secondary hyperhidrosis could be excluded with a high probability but not completely. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Additionally, putative expectation effects could occur due to the study design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>The hyperhidrotics of the sample participated explicitly because of their disease and the purpose of the study was obvious to them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Hence, they possibly focused on their psychological strain while filling in the questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Therefore, they might show a higher impact than they would have done under neutral conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Another limitation is the small sample size of our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>However, our sample (N = 80) is comparable to other studies investigating primary hyperhidrosis and would be sufficient to detect a medium effect of f = 0.25 with a significance level α = 0.05 and the power 1- β = 0.60 (conventions after Cohen (1988) [37]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>In a bigger sample, some of the other stress scales as well as a higher amount of somatic symptoms could probably be verified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>According to the limitations mentioned above, we would like to see our results as an initiation to further investigations in this domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we found that individuals with hyperhidrosis suffered from more chronic stress and showed more depressive symptoms compared to the general population but did not show a higher cortisol response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Axillary sweating had a higher impact on stress and depression than all other types of sweating taken together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>The knowledge of psychological concomitants of excessive sweating might contribute to a psychotherapeutic treatment in hyperhidrosis and therewith to the quality of life of persons concerned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0092412.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Means and standard deviations (in parentheses) of axillary, other hyperhidrotic and control subjects for different questionnaires and cortisol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0092412.s001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>We thank all participants of the study, Ulrike Winnikes for her technical support and Lukas Siebers for helpful discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0092412-Weber1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>1 WeberA, HegerS, SinkgravenR, HeckmannM, ElsnerP, et al (2005) Psychosocial aspects of patients with focal hyperhidrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Marked reduction of social phobia, anxiety and depression and increased quality of life after treatment with botulinum toxin A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Br. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 152(2): 342–345. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Ogawa1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>2 OgawaT (1975) Thermal influence on palmar sweating and mental influence on generalized sweating in man. . Jpn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 25(4): 525–536.1206808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Byrne1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>3 ByrneJ, WalshTN, HedermanWP (1990) Endoscopic transthoracic electrocautery of the sympathetic chain for palmar and axillary hyperhidrosis. Br J Surg 77(9): 1046–1049.2131796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Iwase1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>4 IwaseS, IkedaT, KitazawaH, HakusuiS, SugenoyaJ, et al (1997) Altered response in cutaneous sympathetic outflow to mental and thermal stimuli in primary palmoplantar hyperhidrosis. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Auton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Nerv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Syst. 64(2-3): 65–73.9203126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Strutton1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>5 StruttonDR, KowalskiJW, GlaserDA, StangPE (2004) US prevalence of hyperhidrosis and impact on individuals with axillary hyperhidrosis: results from a national survey. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 51(2): 241–248.15280843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Adar1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>6 AdarR, KurchinA, ZweigA, MozesM (1977) Palmar hyperhidrosis and its surgical treatment: a report of 100 cases. . Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Surg. 186(1): 34–41.879872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Benson1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>7 BensonRA, PalinR, HoltPJE, LoftusIM (2013) Diagnosis and management of hyperhidrosis. BMJ 347: f6800.24277380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Slominski1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>8 SlominskiAT, ZmijewskiMA, ZbytekB, TobinDJ, TheoharidesTC, et al (2013) Key role of CRF in the skin stress response system. . Endocr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Rev. 34(6): 827–884.23939821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Slominski2"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>9 SlominskiA, WortsmanJ, LugerT, PausR, SolomonS (2000) Corticotropin releasing hormone and proopiomelanocortin involvement in the cutaneous response to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Physiol. . Rev. 80(3): 979–1020. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Slominski3"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>10Slominski AT, Zmijewski MA, Skobowiat C, Zbytek B, Slominski RM et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>(2012) Sensing the environment: regulation of local and global homeostasis by the skin's neuroendocrine system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Adv Anat Embryol Cell Biol 212: v, vii, 1-115. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Shih1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>11 ShihCJ, WuJJ, LinMT (1983) Autonomic dysfunction in palmar hyperhidrosis. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Auton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Nerv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Syst. 8(1): 33–43.6875200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Wilke1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>12 WilkeK, MartinA, TerstegenL, BielSS (2007) A short history of sweat gland biology. Int J Cosmet Sci 29(3): 169–179.18489347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Drummond1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>13 DrummondPD, LanceJW (1987) Facial flushing and sweating mediated by the sympathetic nervous system. Brain 110 (Pt 3): 793–803. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Kopelman1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>14 KopelmanD, HashmonaiM, EhrenreichM, BahousH, AssaliaA (1996) Upper dorsal thoracoscopic sympathectomy for palmar hyperhidrosis: improved intermediate-term results. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Vasc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Surg. 24(2): 194–199.8752028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Wolosker1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>15 WoloskerN, Campos JRMde, KauffmanP, Oliveira LAde, MuniaMAS, et al (2012) Evaluation of quality of life over time among 453 patients with hyperhidrosis submitted to endoscopic thoracic sympathectomy.  J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Vasc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Surg. 55(1): 154–156.22047833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Eisenach1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>16 EisenachJH, AtkinsonJLD, FealeyRD (2005) Hyperhidrosis: evolving therapies for a well-established phenomenon. . Mayo Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Proc. 80(5): 657–666.15887434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>17 LeeHH, KimDW, KimDW, KimC (2012) Efficacy of glycopyrrolate in primary hyperhidrosis patients. Korean J Pain 25(1): 28–32.22259713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Skobowiat1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>18 SkobowiatC, DowdyJC, SayreRM, TuckeyRC, SlominskiA (2011) Cutaneous hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis homolog: regulation by ultraviolet radiation. . Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Metab. 301(3): E484–93.21673307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Clow1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>19 ClowA, HucklebridgeF, StalderT, EvansP, ThornL (2010) The cortisol awakening response: more than a measure of HPA axis function. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 35(1): 97–103.20026350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Chida1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>20 ChidaY, SteptoeA (2009) Cortisol awakening response and psychosocial factors: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Biol Psychol 80(3): 265–278.19022335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Hellhammer1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>21 HellhammerDH, WadeS (1993) Endocrine correlates of stress vulnerability. Psychother Psychosom 60(1): 8–17.8234641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Fries1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>22 FriesE, HesseJ, HellhammerJ, HellhammerDH (2005) A new view on hypocortisolism. Psychoneuroendocrinology 30(10): 1010–1016.15950390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Genazzani1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>23 GenazzaniAR, MannellaP, SimonciniT (2007) Drospirenone and its antialdosterone properties. Climacteric 10 Suppl 111–18. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Reinauer1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>24 ReinauerS, NeusserA, SchaufG, HölzleE (1993) Iontophoresis with alternating current and direct current offset (AC/DC iontophoresis): a new approach for the treatment of hyperhidrosis. . Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 129(2): 166–169.7654577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Sonntag1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>25 SonntagM, RuzickaT (2004) Hyperhidrosis-Causes and Current Therapeutic Strategies. Z Allg Med 80(7): 289–294. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Hamm1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>26 HammH, NaumannMK, KowalskiJW, KüttS, KozmaC, et al (2006) Primary focal hyperhidrosis: disease characteristics and functional impairment. Dermatology (Basel) 212(4): 343–353.16707884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Schulz1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>27Schulz P, Schlotz W, Becker P (2004) TICS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Trierer Inventar zum chronischen Stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Hogrefe, Göttingen, Bern, Toronto, Seattle. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Beck1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>28Beck A, Steer R, Brown G (1996) Manual for Beck Depression Inventory: second edition (BDI-II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>The Psychological Corporation, San Antonio. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Hautzinger1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>29Hautzinger M, Keller F, Kühner C (2009) BDI-II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Beck Depressions-Inventar., 2.Auflage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Pearson, Frankfurt Main. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Rief1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>30Rief W, Hiller W (2008) SOMS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Screening für Somatoforme Störungen., 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Auflage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Huber, Bern. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Dressendorfer1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>31 DressendorferRA, KirschbaumC, RohdeW, StahlF, StrasburgerCJ (1992) Synthesis of a cortisol-biotin conjugate and evaluation as a tracer in an immunoassay for salivary cortisol measurement. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol 43(7): 683–692.1472460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Pruessner1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>32 PruessnerJC, KirschbaumC, MeinlschmidG, HellhammerDH (2003) Two formulas for computation of the area under the curve represent measures of total hormone concentration versus time-dependent change. Psychoneuroendocrinology 28(7): 916–931.12892658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Erikson1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>33Erikson EH (1968) Identity, youth and crisis, vol 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Norton, New York, N.Y. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Barsky1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>34 BarskyAJ, BorusJF (1999) Functional somatic syndromes. . Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Intern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Med. 130(11): 910–921.10375340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Kirschbaum1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>35 KirschbaumC, PirkeKM, HellhammerDH (1993) The 'Trier Social Stress Test'—a tool for investigating psychobiological stress responses in a laboratory setting. Neuropsychobiology 28(1-2): 76–81.8255414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Schwabe1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>36 SchwabeL, HaddadL, SchachingerH (2008) HPA axis activation by a socially evaluated cold-pressor test. Psychoneuroendocrinology 33(6): 890–895.18403130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Cohen1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>37Cohen J (1988) Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences, 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Auflage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Academic Press, London. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Ruchinskas1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>38 RuchinskasRA, NarayanRK, MeagherRJ, FurukawaS (2002) The relationship of psychopathology and hyperhidrosis. . Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 147(4): 733–735.12366420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Ruchinskas2"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>39 RuchinskasR (2007) Hyperhidrosis and anxiety: chicken or egg? Dermatology (Basel) 214(3): 195–196.17377378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Kaufmann1"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>40 KaufmannH, SaadiaD, PolinC, HagueS, SingletonA, et al (2003) Primary hyperhidrosis—evidence for autosomal dominant inheritance. . Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Auton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Res. 13(2): 96–98.12720093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Higashimoto1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>41 HigashimotoI, YoshiuraK, HirakawaN, HigashimotoK, SoejimaH, et al (2006) Primary palmar hyperhidrosis locus maps to 14q11.2-q13. . Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>A 140(6): 567–572.16470694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0092412-Ro1"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>42 RoKM, CantorRM, LangeKL, AhnSS (2002) Palmar hyperhidrosis: evidence of genetic transmission. . J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Vasc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Surg. 35(2): 382–386.11854739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
