<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3362782</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2334-12-70</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22440090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-12-70</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Multicentre RCT and economic evaluation of a psychological intervention together with a leaflet to reduce risk behaviour amongst men who have sex with men (MSM) prescribed post-exposure prophylaxis for HIV following sexual exposure (PEPSE): A protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Llewellyn</surname><given-names>Carrie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>c.d.llewellyn@bsms.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>charles.abraham@pcmd.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Miners</surname><given-names>Alec</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>alec.miners@lshtm.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>h.e.smith@bsms.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>a.pollard@bsms.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Benn</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>paul.benn@nhs.net</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>martin.fisher@bsuh.nhs.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Brighton &amp; Sussex Medical School, Brighton, UK</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Peninsula College of Medicine &amp; Dentistry, Exeter, UK</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Camden Provider Services at Central and North West London NHS Foundation Trust, London, UK</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Brighton and Sussex University Hospitals NHS Trust, Brighton, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2012 Llewellyn et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Llewellyn et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/70"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP) following sexual exposure to HIV has been recommended as a method of preventing HIV infection in the UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Men who have sex with men (MSM) are the group most affected by HIV in the UK and their sexual risk taking behaviour is reported to be increasing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>One-to-one behavioural interventions, such as motivational interviewing (MI) have been recommended to reduce HIV in high risk groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The Information, Motivation and Behavioral skills (IMB) model has been shown to provide a good basis for understanding and predicting HIV-relevant health behaviour and health behaviour change, however the IMB has yet to be applied to PEP after risky sexual exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The primary aim of this trial is to examine the impact of MI augmented with information provision and behavioural skills building (informed by the IMB Model), over and above usual care, on risky sexual behaviour in MSM prescribed PEP after potential sexual exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>A secondary aim of this research is to examine the impact of the intervention on adherence to PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This study will also provide estimates of the cost-effectiveness of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A manualised parallel group randomised controlled trial with economic evaluation will be conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome is the proportion of risky sexual practices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcomes include: i) Levels of adherence to PEP treatment; ii) Number of subsequent courses of PEP; iii) Levels of motivation to avoid risky sexual behaviours; iv) Levels of HIV risk-reduction information/knowledge; v) Levels of risk reduction behavioural skills; vi) Diagnosis of anal gonorrhoea, Chlamydia and/or HIV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>250 participants will be asked to self-complete a questionnaire at four time points during the study (at 0,3,6,12 months). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The intervention will consist of a two-session, fixed duration, telephone administered augmented MI intervention based on the IMB model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>A newly developed treatment manual will guide the selection of persuasive communication strategies as appropriate for each participant and will be based on underlying change mechanisms specified by the IMB theoretical framework. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Information provision and skills building will also be included in the intervention package through the use of information leaflets and tailored action plans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Fidelity of intervention delivery will be assessed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The results from this NIHR funded study will identify whether it is appropriate and cost-effective to intervene using one-to-one telephone calls with MSM seeking PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>If the intervention is effective, further work will be needed on training staff to deliver the intervention competently. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Trial registration numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>UKCRN ID:11436; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.controlled-trials.com/ISRCTN00746242">ISRCTN00746242</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Sexual behaviour</kwd><kwd>HIV</kwd><kwd>Motivational interviewing</kwd><kwd>Post-exposure-prophylaxis</kwd><kwd>Intervention</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of HIV infections continue to rise in the UK, particularly amongst MSM and the reduction of new infections is a key component of the National Strategy for Sexual Health and HIV [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Recent reports on sexual health highlight the need to invest more in HIV prevention strategies [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The Community HIV and AIDS prevention (CHAPS) policy (led by the Terrence Higgins Trust) identifies post-exposure prophylaxis following sexual exposure (PEPSE) to the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) as one method of preventing HIV infection in the UK [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for treatment are derived from the existing use of antiretrovirals to prevent HIV infection after high risk occupational exposure to the virus ('needle-stick injuries') [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for prescribing PEP result from the clinician's assessment of risk of transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>If the risk of HIV transmission through particular sexual practices (such as unprotected anal intercourse) is of a similar magnitude as occupational exposures then PEP should be recommended [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Evidence suggests that PEP may reduce the risk of HIV infection if given within 72 hours and adhered to rigorously for 28 days [5,7,8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Sustained adherence is required to prevent treatment failure, however, non-adherence of a quarter to a third of those prescribed PEP has been reported [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The treatment can be challenging to patients due to side-effects such as diarrhoea, nausea, headaches and vomiting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The treatment is also costly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Men who have sex with men (MSM) are the group most affected by the HIV epidemic in the UK [11] and their sexual risk taking behaviour is reported to be increasing [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As part of a comprehensive strategy across HIV prevention and care, behavioural interventions remain an important tool in the global fight against HIV [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>One-to-one behavioural interventions, such as motivational interviewing (MI) have been recommended [15,16] to reduce HIV in high risk groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>NICE guidance places recommendations for one-to-one interventions within the context of current STI/HIV service provision [1,17] and states that these interventions are integral to the modernisation of sexual health services [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Seeking PEP after potential sexual exposure may indicate an unmet prevention need and provides an opportunity to target interventions thus potentially lowering the likelihood of further risk behaviour [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>We will implement a telephone-administered intervention based on motivational interviewing (MI) augmented with information and behavioural skills building (informed by the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills Model). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>MI is defined as a 'directive, client-centred counselling style for eliciting behaviour change by helping clients to explore and resolve ambivalence' [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>It is may be especially effective for individuals who are reluctant to change or who are ambivalent about changing their behaviour and may be particularly appropriate for MSM who may require a more tailored preventive strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A systematic review and meta-analysis of RCTs shows that MI outperforms traditional advice giving in the treatment of a range of behavioural problems and diseases [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>More recently, a pilot study has shown the effectiveness of telephone administered MI to reduce risky sexual behaviour in HIV infected rural populations [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The study will examine whether a two-session, telephone administered augmented motivational interviewing intervention based on the IMB model (Figure 1) reduces risky sexual behaviour (compared with 'treatment as usual'), in MSM prescribed PEP treatment after potential sexual exposure to HIV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Evidence suggests that the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills (IMB) approach could be used to explain sexual risk taking behaviour [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the IMB model has been shown to provide a good basis for understanding and predicting HIV-relevant health behaviour and health behaviour change in almost two decades of research [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This model further proposes that information relevant to the personal practice of preventive behaviour, motivation to practice prevention and behavioural skills for practicing prevention effectively, are fundamental determinants of HIV/STI preventive behaviour [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The IMB model proposes an intervention development process involving (1) elicitation of client resources and needs and, (2) matching intervention content to existing need and behaviour change objectives, (3) implementation of information, motivation and skill development techniques interventions according to protocol and, finally, (4) evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills Model (Fisher and Fisher, 1992). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2334-12-70-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Interventions based on this approach has been found to be effective in changing risky sexual behaviour among HIV negative and infected individuals in more than 25 studies [26] and in changing levels of adherence behaviour amongst people with HIV/AIDS [27,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The IMB has yet to be applied to a short term prophylactic regimen of medication after risky sexual exposure but its previous successful application to HIV risk reduction suggests that it is an appropriate model on which to base an intervention for those prescribed PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This study will also provide estimates of the cost-effectiveness of the intervention through the inclusion of an economic evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Objectives and hypotheses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The primary aim is to examine the impact of motivational interviewing augmented with information and behavioural skills building (informed by the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills Model), over and above usual care, on risky sexual behaviour in MSM prescribed PEP after potential sexual exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A secondary aim of this research is to examine the impact of the intervention on adherence to PEP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Specifically we hypothesize that compared with treatment as usual, those in the intervention arm will: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>1) Report a reduction in the proportion of risky sexual practices (less unprotected anal intercourse (UAI) (receptive and insertive), increased use of condoms, a reduction in partners); </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>2) Have greater levels of adherence to PEP treatment; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>3) Have lower rates of subsequent requests for PEP; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>4) Have lower incidences of HIV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>5) Have lower incidences of anal gonorrhoea and Chlamydia; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>6) Have greater motivation to avoid risky sexual behaviours; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>7) Have greater knowledge of risk reduction strategies; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>8) Have greater risk reduction behavioural skills. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Parallel group randomised controlled trial (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>CONSORT flowchart of study participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2334-12-70-2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Eligibility criteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Participants will be MSM, aged ≥16 years, prescribed PEP after sexual exposure, attending a Genito-urinary Medicine (GUM) clinic that are willing and able to give written, informed consent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The following groups of patients will be excluded: people who have received previous psychological support from a clinical psychologist in relation to their sexual risk taking; people with learning difficulties; or those unable to read study materials; or with no means of communication acceptable to the patient; or who are seeking PEP after sexual assault. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Recruitment procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The data collection plan is tailored to the standard patient care protocols stipulated in the BASHH guidelines for PEP [4], and the clinical processes in use at the recruitment sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>PEP is available from GUM or Accident &amp; Emergency (A&amp;E) Departments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Patients are routinely prescribed a 5-day course of PEP medication at general GUM clinics, or at A&amp;E departments outside of GUM hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Whichever mode of access, all patients attend a dedicated PEP clinic at GUM within 5 days of initial prescription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Recruiting at the GUM clinic will ensure all patients who are prescribed the full course of PEP (28 days) are included in the trial from either access route. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Eligible participants will be identified by a research nurse/health advisor at the GUM clinic and given study information and consent forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Participants have a two-week time period in which to consent and return baseline measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>This two week period allows the recruitment of patients at an early stage in their prescription, but at a time when their immediate anxiety should be reduced and they are able to give considered, informed consent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Baseline and follow-up assessments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Participants enrolled into the study will be asked to self-complete a questionnaire at four time points during the study (at 0,3,6,12 months). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The baseline questionnaire will be administered at the recruitment stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Upon receiving the consent forms and baseline assessments, participants will be randomly allocated to either intervention or control conditions (see randomisation section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The second questionnaire will be either posted to patients, accessed via an email link or the internet (as per consent) prior to their 3-month follow-up appointment with the clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Any patients who have not returned completed questionnaires before their '3-month' follow-up will be sent repeat copies1 (as per consent), and subsequently called on the telephone (if consented), and finally, may be approached by study staff at their clinic appointment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The third and fourth questionnaires will be posted to patients or accessed via an email link or the internet 6 and 12 months after the end of PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Repeat copies, and subsequent telephone calls/text messages, will be used as reminders. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The recruitment period is for 12 months to allow sufficient numbers of participants to be recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>A sample size of 250 (allowing for a 75% recruitment rate and 50% retention rate) is achievable within the time-frame from four sites and we anticipate that numbers will be higher given the increasing trends for PEP requests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Randomization and blinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Participants will be randomised after consent and collection of baseline measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The recruiting staff will not have access to the results of randomisation prior to recruiting the participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Randomisation will occur within each clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The allocation sequence will be generated and released to the interventionist on a case-by-case basis by an independent company who specialise in supplying random generated sequences for research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The randomisation sequence will be recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This is a single-blind trial, given the nature of the behavioural intervention, blinding of participants is not feasible and the interventionist will know that all those contacted are in the intervention arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The statistician will be blind to individual results during the trial and the allocation-to-trial-arm coding will be revealed when the dataset is sealed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The interventionist and supervisors will be blind to the baseline and follow-up measures which will not be involved in the delivery of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Anonymised responses will be entered onto the database by a person unconnected to the project. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Trial treatment arms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Control group: Treatment as usual </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Both of the groups will receive 'treatment as usual': Patients are initially seen by a HA/SpN for an initial consultation, 5 day prescription of PEP and blood tests (for HIV, Hepatitis B and liver function). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Patients receive their first follow-up appointment 5 days later to receive further PEP (if HIV-ve). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>After the 28 day treatment regimen patients receive either a face-to-face or telephone appointment with the HA/SpN to discuss their sexual health, adherence to PEP and the blood test results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>At 4 months after exposure (3 months after the end of PEP) patients are recalled by the HA for HIV testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In order to assess the impact of the intervention on outcome measures and IMB constructs, those allocated to the control group will be asked to complete all measures at 0,3,6, and 12 months. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Intervention group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The intervention group will receive 'treatment as usual' plus the addition of an intervention which will be delivered as two telephone sessions employing motivational interviewing (MI) augmented with information and skills building based on the IMB model of behaviour change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The first telephone call will be made within one week of the participant being consented into the trial and after baseline assessments are received. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The second call will occur 7 days (+/-2 days) later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The intervention will be completed by the end of the 28 day course of PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A telephone format is proposed to allow the same person to conduct all interventional sessions to control for provider differences and to facilitate recruitment from a wide geographical area in an economical manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>If shown to be effective, this intervention would be sustainable as an improvement to the routine care model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Duration and content of intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Telephone delivered MI </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Each telephone session will be a maximum of 30 minutes long. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The second session will contain similar content to the first but will reiterate and build on the risk reduction motivation from session 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In the case of drop-out between the 2 intervention sessions, the dose-response will be assessed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The interventionist will initially assess individual risk behaviours and any informational, motivational or skill deficits which have contributed to maintenance of participants' risky sexual behaviours and discuss particular areas related to risky sex e.g. the use of alcohol or drugs during sex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The interventionist will elicit self-motivational statements from the participant with the use of open-ended questions and will utilise MI strategies to increase motivation to change, including: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>1) Providing the participant with feedback about his risky sexual behaviours </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>2) Increasing the participant's sense of responsibility to reduce risky sexual behaviours </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>3) Providing brief and direct advice to create a desire for change </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>4) Providing a menu of options from which the participant can choose to reduce risk </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>5) Demonstrating empathy by listening carefully, and accurately understanding his problems </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>6) Enhancing self-efficacy to reduce risky sexual behaviours [29] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>If an individual discontinues with PEP before the end of the treatment, they will still be eligible to continue in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Data on adherence to PEP will be captured by the measures of adherence and a review of the medical notes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The role of the manual </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The manual will guide the selection of persuasive communication strategies appropriate for each participant and will be based on underlying change mechanisms specified by the IMB theoretical framework. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The manual describes how to elicit information and includes scripts describing likely sexual-risk scenarios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Specific behaviour change techniques are identified [30,31] and possible responses exemplified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Information provision and skills building </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Information about HIV risk behaviour, prevalence and strategies to minimise risk will be provided to those allocated into the intervention arm ('Ready for Action' Second Edition, and 'Get it on' condom guide both produced by the Terrence Higgins Trust). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This will be either sent by post, email or accessed via the internet (as preferred) after baseline measures have been returned but before the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The interventionist will prompt the participant to read the information if they have not already done so. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The skills building component of the intervention will be given during the telephone session in the form of interventionist-provided suggestions of practical strategies needed to master these skills. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>A well-specified action plan will be developed and agreed on (between interventionist and participant) during the session and the participant will be asked to write this down and enact it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The interventionist will also write down the agreed action plan and send this to the participant after the session (either by post,or email as indicated by participant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Questions about adherence to practicing the action plan are included in the follow-up questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Treatment fidelity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Assessing the fidelity of the treatment is an important component of successful research dissemination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Translating effective behavioural change interventions from this research setting to clinical practice can be facilitated better when treatment fidelity strategies are used as guidelines for implementing new interventions in clinical contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In order to monitor the reliability and validity of the intervention, assessment of both the interventionist and the participant will conducted as per National Institutes of Health (NIH) Behaviour Change Consortium 'best practice' recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Ensuring same treatment dose within conditions will be ensured by a fixed number of sessions and by delivery within the intervention period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Ensuring interventionist skill acquisition and minimising 'drift' in interventionist skills will be minimised by the development and use of a treatment manual; by monitoring and providing feedback to the interventionist; and by providing adequate training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The gold standard method to ensure standard delivery of the intervention is to evaluate or code the sessions (through audiotape) according to predefined criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A validated instrument, the Motivational Interviewing Skill Code (MISC) [29], will be used to provide structured feedback, to monitor and document adherence to MI principles during weekly supervision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The interventionist will also be required to complete a process evaluation checklist (adapted from the NHS Health Trainer Handbook [32]) after each intervention session to remind him to include the appropriate skills and content for each intervention and minimise bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The advisory board will be used to monitor whether the treatment protocol has been adhered to during the recruitment and intervention period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Reduction of differences within treatments will be ensured by the use of one trained interventionist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Primary outcome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The proportion of risky sexual practices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Risk Behaviour outcome measure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A Risk Behaviour outcome measure has been developed to include items of potential HIV transmission-risk sexual behaviour: number of episodes of unprotected anal intercourse (UAI) (receptive and insertive) over a three month time period with individuals of unknown or HIV positive status, consistency of condom use, number of partners using no protection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(Unprotected receptive oral sex with an HIV + ve person is associated with minimal HIV transmission risk and thus is not included). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcomes (and method of assessment) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>i) Levels of adherence to PEP treatment (Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS) [33] adapted for use in PEP). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>ii) Number of subsequent courses of PEP (self-report and medical record review). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>iii) Diagnosis of anal gonorrhoea and Chlamydia.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>iv) Diagnosis of HIV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>v) Levels of motivation to avoid risky sexual behaviours ('Measures of Motivation to Perform AIDS Preventive Behavior' questionnaire [34] adapted for use with MSM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This questionnaire provides assessment of attitudes, subjective norms and behavioural intentions in relation to HIV risk-reduction). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>vi) Levels of HIV risk-reduction information/knowledge ('Health and Relationships Survey' [34] adapted for use with MSM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Items are summed to form an HIV prevention information scale score). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>vii) Levels of risk reduction behavioural skills ('Behavioral Skills Measure' [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This consists of two subscales which assess the perceived difficulty of reducing HIV risk behaviour and the perceived effectiveness of methods to reduce risk). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>With the exception of adherence, all outcome measures will use a retrospective recall period of 'the past 3 months'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Other factors assessed by self-report questionnaire at each time point will be alcohol and substance use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Socio-demographic (age, ethnicity, education, employment, relationship status) will be assessed at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Experience of treatment side-effects will be assessed using a previously used measure at 3 month together with the measure of adherence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Frequency and duration of follow-up </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The primary and secondary outcomes ii, v, vi, and vii will be collected at 3, 6 and 12 months after the end of treatment (and the end of the intervention). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcome i. will be collected at 3 months only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Outcomes iii. and iv. will be collected at 12 months only. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The follow-up period is for 12 months to determine intervention sustainability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Participants will be contacted by telephone prior to each follow-up assessment to remind them of their participation in the study and to ask their preference for follow-up (postal, email/internet or face-to-face). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Analyses plan and power calculation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>For the analysis of main effects for the primary outcome a mixed-design ANCOVA will be used with one between-groups factor (treatment vs. control) and one within-groups factor (baseline, 3-,6- and 12-month measures). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>For this analysis the estimated effect size is f = 0.1 (based on a moderate estimate of effect size from a meta-analysis [24] of one to one interventions to reduce UAI in MSM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>90% power at 0.05 level of significance requires a sample of 250 (125 in each arm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcomes will be analysed for the same effect size but with significance adjusted to 0.01 and power to 80%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Piloting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>All study materials (measures, training manual, intervention, method for data sharing) will be piloted on a sample of MSM and refined in response to their feedback, together with input from the Advisory Board and Steering Group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Economic evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The economic evaluation will compare NHS costs of the intervention with usual care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Health outcomes will be expressed as quality-adjusted life-years (QALYs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Decision modelling techniques will be used to extrapolate the RCT results to predict longer term costs and health outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>A single economic model with an appropriate time horizon is proposed based on Bernoulli techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This approach has been used in a number of previously published studies [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>This is a conservative approach because it only partially accounts for chains of infections which may be prevented, rather than prevention of single infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The purpose of the Bernoulli model is to translate changes in sexual behaviour as observed in the trial into the probability of HIV transmission in order to estimate the number of averted transmissions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>To inform this model, baseline data will be collected to allow a more complex infectious diseases model to be built if the intervention is proven. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The data are likely to be useful for a range of other HIV modelling studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Intervention costs will be collected contemporaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The longer term costs and health effects of HIV infection will be estimated using published evidence since infection-associated sequelae will not occur during the trial period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Future costs and QALYs will be discounted at 3.5% per annum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Results will be reported as incremental cost per QALYs and cost-effectiveness acceptability curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Vulnerable patients and disclosures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>If during the intervention the patient discloses current harmful thoughts or behaviour towards themselves or another, they will be referred to their treating consultant, GP or psychiatric support provided by the GUM clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The breaking of confidentiality under these circumstances is detailed on the consent form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Anonymity and confidentiality of data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Participants anonymity will be protected by the allocation of a code (not a clinic or NHS number) for use on the database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Confidentiality and data sharing between participant sites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>All patient-related information to be shared through encrypted NHS email system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Ethical approval </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the National Research Ethics Service (NRES) Committee South East Coast - Surrey (ref: 11/LO/0718) in 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This paper describes the protocol of a randomised controlled trial to evaluate the impact of motivational interviewing augmented with information and behavioural skills building (informed by the Information-Motivation-Behavioural Skills Model), over and above usual care, on risky sexual behaviour in MSM prescribed PEP after potential sexual exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>A secondary aim of this research is to examine the impact of the intervention on adherence to PEP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>This study will also provide estimates of the cost-effectiveness of the intervention through the inclusion of an economic evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>One of the strengths of this study is that the intervention is targeting individuals who may be deemed as high risk: those who have presented for PEP treatment after a potential sexual exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Men who have sex with men (MSM) are the group most affected by the HIV epidemic in the UK [11] and their sexual risk taking behaviour is reported to be increasing [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>As part of a comprehensive strategy across HIV prevention and care, behavioural interventions remain an important tool in the global fight against HIV [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>One-to-one behavioural interventions, such as motivational interviewing (MI) have been recommended [15,16] to reduce HIV in high risk groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Although the intervention is tailored to the individual, our proposed intervention is manualised so that the content delivered will be similar and based on the principles of MI with the underlying change mechanisms specified by the IMB Model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>As part of this study a manual has been developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Specific behaviour change techniques used will then be able to be identified and quantified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Translating effective behavioural change interventions from the research setting to clinical practice can be facilitated better when treatment fidelity strategies are used as guidelines for implementing new interventions in clinical contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>We will be monitoring the reliability and validity of the intervention which is an additional strength of the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>A recent review [14] highlighted that the recruitment of MSM participants was the most challenging aspect of similar behavioural intervention studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>To overcome these barriers we are employing strategies to ensure that recruitment and retention are maximised, including: the refinement of assessment materials with the MSM community; the use of a telephone-based intervention to overcome geographic boundaries, time constraints and fear of public exposure as an MSM; the recruitment of individuals seeking PEP rather than the recruitment of high risk individuals from the community. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>This study will identify whether it is appropriate and cost-effective to intervene using a tailored intervention of one-to-one telephone calls with MSM prescribed the prophylactic treatment regimen after potential sexual exposure to HIV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>If the intervention is effective, further work will be needed on training staff to deliver the intervention competently. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Endnotes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>1 Maximum of 2 repeat copies and 1 text/call/email if consented by patient. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>2 Incidence data on rectal gonorrhoea and Chlamydia will be collected as this is directly related to the risky sexual behaviour that we are assessing in this trial i.e. directly related to condom use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>CL, MF, CA, HS, AP, PB, AM contributed to the design of the study and co-authored this article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Pre-publication history </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/70/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/70/prepub</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgements and funding</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This paper presents independent research commissioned by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) under its Research for Patient Benefit (RfPB) Programme (Grant Reference Number PB-PG-0110-21005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge the support of the National Institute for Health Research, through the Comprehensive Clinical Research Network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Thanks to Dr Matthew Hankins and Stephanie Goubet for statistical advice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Thanks to our Advisory Group who have been involved with developing materials during the developmental phase of this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Thanks to the clinicians and staff at the recruiting centres who have supported the study through the governance phase. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Department of HealthNational Strategy for Sexual Health and HIV2001London: DOH </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Department of HealthMoving forward: progress and priorities -working together for high quality sexual health: Government response to the Independent Advisory Group's review of the Sexual Health and HIV Strategy2009London: Department of Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Independent Advisory Group on Sexual Health and HIVBuilding on progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Enhancing the response to HIV in England2009London: Department of Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>FisherMBennPEvansBPozniakAJonesMMacLeanSDavidsonOSummersideJHawkinsDClinical Effectiveness Group (British Association for Sexual Health and HIV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>United Kingdom Guidelines for the use of post-exposure prophylaxis for HIV following sexual exposureInt J STD AIDS200617819210.1258/09564620677545582916464267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>CardoDMCulverDHCiesielskiCASrivastavaPUMarcusRAbiteboulDHeptonstallJIppolitoGLotFMcKibbenPSBellDMA case-control study of HIV seroconversion in health care workers after percutaneous exposure to HIV-infected blood: clinical and public health implicationsNew Engl J Med1997337211485149010.1056/NEJM1997112033721019366579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>KatzMGerberdingJPostexposure treatment of people exposed to the HIV virus through sexual contact or injection-drug useNew Engl J Med19973361097110010.1056/NEJM1997041033615129091810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>OttenRASmithDKAdamsDRPulliumJKJacksonEKimCNJaffeHJanssenRButeraSFolksTMEfficacy of postexposure prophylaxis after intravaginal exposure of pig-tailed macaques to a human-derived retrovirus (human immunodeficiency virus type 2)J Virol200074209771977510.1128/JVI.74.20.9771-9775.200011000253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>SchecterMdo LagoRFMendelsohnABMoreiraRIMoultonLHthe Praça Onze Study TeamBehavioral impact, acceptability, and HIV incidence among homosexual men with access to postexposure chemoprophylaxis for HIVJ Acq Immun Def Synd200435551952510.1097/00126334-200404150-00010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>DoddsCHammondGKeoghPHicksonFWeatherburnPPEP talk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Awareness of, access to post-exposure prophylaxis among Gay &amp; Bisexual men in the UK2006London: Sigma Research </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>KahnJOMartinJNRowlandMEBambergerJDChesneyMChambersDFeasibility of Postexposure Prophylaxis (PEP) against Human Immunodeficiency Virus Infection after sexual or injection drug use exposure: The San Francisco PEP StudyJ Infect Dis2001183570771410.1086/31882911181146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The UK Collaborative Group for HIV and STI surveillanceMapping the issues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>HIV and other sexually transmitted infections in the United Kingdom2005London: Health Protection Agency Centre for Infections </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>DoddsJPMerceyDEPerryJVJohnsonAMIncreasing risk behaviour and high levels of undiagnosed HIV infection in a community sample of homosexual menSex Transm Infect20048045145410.1136/sti.2004.01078515572612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>ElfordJBoldingGDavisMSherrLHartGTrends in sexual behaviour among London homosexual men 1998-2003: implications for HIV prevention and sexual health promotionSex Transm Infect20048045145410.1136/sti.2004.01078515572612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>HerbstJHBeekerCMathewAThe effectiveness of individual-, group-, and community-level HIV behavioral risk-reduction interventions for adult men who have sex with men: A Systematic ReviewAm J Prev Med2007324SS38S6717386336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Global HIV Prevention Working GroupBehavior Change and HIV Prevention: (Re) Considerations for the 21st CenturyGlobal HIV Prevention Working Group2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>National Institute for Health and Clinical ExcellenceOne to one interventions to reduce the transmission of sexually transmitted infections (STIs) including HIV, and to reduce the rate of under 18 conceptions, especially among vulnerable and at risk groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>NICE public health intervention guidance 32007London: NICE </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Medical Foundation for AIDS &amp; Sexual HealthRecommended standards for sexual health services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>United Kingdom2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>RietmeijerCRisk reduction counselling for prevention of sexually transmitted infections: how it works and how to make it workSex Transm Infect2007832910.1136/sti.2005.01731917283359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>WaldoCRStallRDCoatesTJIs offering post-exposure prevention for sexual exposures to HIV related to sexual risk behaviour in gay men?AIDS2000141035103910.1097/00002030-200005260-0001610853986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>MillerWRollnickSMotivational interviewing, preparing people to change addictive behavior1991New York: The Guildford Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>RubakSSandboekALauritzenTChristensenBMotivational interviewing: a systematic review and meta-analysisBrit J Gen Pract20055530531215826439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>CosioDHeckmanTGAndersonTHeckmanBDGarskeJMcCarthyJTelephone-administered motivational interviewing to reduce risky sexual behavior in HIV-infected rural persons: A pilot randomized clinical trialSex Transm Dis20103714014610.1097/OLQ.0b013e3181c1897520118830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>FisherJDFisherWACornmanDHAmicoRKBryanAFriedlandGHClinician-delivered intervention during routine clinical care reduces unprotected sexual behaviour among HIV-infected patientsJ Acq Immun Def Synd200641445210.1097/01.qai.0000192000.15777.5c </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>FisherJDFisherWADiClemente R, Crosby R, Kegler MThe information-motivation-behavioral skills modelEmerging Theories in Health Promotion Practice and Research2002San Fransisco: Jossy-Bass4070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>FisherJDFisherWAChanging AIDS risk behaviourPsychol Bull19921114554741594721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>FisherJDCornmanDHNortonWEFisherWAInvolving behavioral scientists, health care providers, and HIV-infected patients as collaborators in theory-based HIV prevention and antiretroviral adherence interventionsJ Acq Iimmun Def Synd200643Supplement 1S10S1710.1097/01.qai.0000248335.90190.f9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>FisherJDFisherWAAmicoKRAn information-motivation-behavioral skills model of adherence to antiretroviral therapyHealth Psychol20062546247316846321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>StaraceFMayerKHAmicoKRAdherence to antiretroviral therapy: an empirical test of the information-motivation-behavioral skills modelHealth Psychol20062515316216569106 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>MillerWRThe Motivational Interviewing Skill Code (MISC) Manual, version 12000<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://casaa.unm.edu/download/misc1.pdf">http://casaa.unm.edu/download/misc1.pdf</ext-link>15-4-2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>AbrahamCMichieSA taxonomy of behavior change techniques used in interventionsHealth Psychol20082737938718624603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>AbrahamCAbraham C, Kools MMapping change mechanisms and behaviour change techniques: A systematic approach to promoting behaviour change through textWriting Health Communication: An Evidence-Based Guide for Professionals2011London: SAGE Publications Ltd </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>British Psychological Society Health Psychology TeamImproving Health: Changing Behaviour, NHS Health Trainer Handbook2008London: Department of Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>MoriskyDAngAKrousel-WoodMWardHPredictive validity of a medication adherence measure in an outpatient settingJ Clin Hypertens200810534835410.1111/j.1751-7176.2008.07572.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>MisovichSFisherWFisherJDavis C, Yarber W, Bauserman R, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Thousand OaksA measure of AIDS prevention information, motivation, behavioral skills, and behaviorHandbook of Sexuality-Related Measures1998CA: SAGE328337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>ShepherdJKavanaghJPicotJCooperKHardenABarnett-PageEJonesJCleggAHartwellDFramptonGKPriceAThe effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of behavioural interventions for the prevention of sexually transmitted infections in young people aged 13-19: a systematic review and economic evaluationHTA2010147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
