<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3281816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22363402</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-10601</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Physiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physiological Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Signaling in Cellular Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Physiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physiological Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Constitutive Neutrophil Apoptosis: Regulation by Cell Concentration via S100 A8/9 and the MEK – ERK Pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">S100 A8/9 and Neutrophil Apoptosis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Atallah</surname><given-names>Mizhir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krispin</surname><given-names>Alon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trahtemberg</surname><given-names>Uriel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ben-Hamron</surname><given-names>Sandrine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grau</surname><given-names>Amir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verbovetski</surname><given-names>Inna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mevorach</surname><given-names>Dror</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>The Laboratory for Cellular and Molecular Immunology, Department of Medicine, Rheumatology Research Centre, Hadassah-Hebrew University Medical Center Jerusalem, Jerusalem, Israel</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bonini</surname><given-names>Marcelo G.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Illinois at Chicago, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>mevorachd@hadassah.org.il</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MA DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: MA AK UT SB AG IV DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: MA AK UT SB AG IV DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: MA DM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e29333</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Atallah et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Programmed cell death (PCD) is a fundamental mechanism in tissue and cell homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>It was long suggested that apoptosis regulates the cell number in diverse cell populations; however no clear mechanism was shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils are the short-lived, first-line defense of innate immunity, with an estimated t = 1/2 of 8 hours and a high turnover rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here we first show that spontaneous neutrophil constitutive PCD is regulated by cell concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Using a proteomic approach, we identified the S100 A8/9 complex, which constitutes roughly 40% of cytosolic protein in neutrophils, as mediating this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We further demonstrate that it regulates cell survival via a signaling mechanism involving MEK-ERK via TLR4 and CD11B/CD18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>This mechanism is suggested to have a fine-tuning role in regulating the neutrophil number in bone marrow, peripheral blood, and inflammatory sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Programmed cell death (PCD) is a fundamental mechanism in tissue and cell homeostasis, long thought to regulate cell number in diverse populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In developmental biology, PCD provides an efficient mechanism for eliminating unwanted cells, as shown in studies with the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Of the 1090 somatic cells formed during the development of an adult hermaphrodite, exactly 131 die, demonstrating the morphological features of apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In the mammalian immune system, clonal triggering results in lymphocyte proliferation followed by activation-induced cell death that ensures T cells will return to their original concentration, adding only a negligible number of memory cells [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Few studies in the human immune system have questioned the mechanism of constitutive leukocyte blood concentration regulation via PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In humans, neutrophils are the short-lived, first-line defense of innate immunity, with estimated t = 1/2 of 8 hours and a high turnover rate [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These cells, which represent 50–60% of the circulating leukocytes in normal conditions, are considered terminally differentiated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>They are rapidly recruited and accumulate in the early phase of inflammation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Under normal physiological conditions, absent triggers initiating neutrophil exit from the blood pool into tissues, human blood neutrophil counts are determined by the balance between neutrophil hematopoiesis, neutrophil mobilization from the bone marrow, the marginal pool, spontaneous constitutive PCD, and phagocytosis of apoptotic neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Human neutrophils are generated in bone marrow, mainly under the control of G-CSF and additional cytokines and growth factors, including M-CSF, GM-CSF, IL-6, IL-3 (reviewed by Metcalf [4]), and possibly IL-17 and IL-23 [5], as well as IL-22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Martin et al., and others, suggested that neutrophils are retained in the bone marrow through interaction of CXCL12 (stromal derived factor 1, or SDF-1) with its receptor CXCR4 [6]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In the blood pool, neutrophils circulate until they are marginated or develop morphological changes due to PCD, and are cleared by Kupfer cells in the liver [8] or by bone marrow macrophages [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Various cytokines regulate blood neutrophil counts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Catecholamines mobilize the marginal pool [10], while G-CSF, IL-17, and IL-23 [5] may modify counts via bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Yet, the major regulator of blood neutrophil counts and neutrophils at inflammatory sites is PCD, which allows only a short neutrophil life span, modulated according to specific needs, such as inflammation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Molecular events leading to this short neutrophil lifespan are better understood now. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>An important regulator of neutrophil apoptosis seems to be the Bcl-2 protein family, and a major event in spontaneous neutrophil PCD appears related to loss of anti-apoptotic proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Bcl-2 is lost during neutrophil differentiation, and not expressed by peripheral blood neutrophils [11]–[14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Bcl-xl is also expressed by neutrophils, and expression decreases upon TNFα-mediated apoptosis [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Mcl1 declines as neutrophils undergo spontaneous apoptosis, and is upregulated when cells are exposed to survival factors such as GMCSF, butyrate, ILβ, and LPS [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A1, expressed in neutrophils at the mRNA level [13], [15], is also upregulated by survival factors GCSF and LPS [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, neutrophils do not express survivin, an inhibitor-of-apoptosis protein (IAP), unless expression is induced by GCSF and GMCSF or in inflammatory conditions [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In contrast, pro-apoptotic proteins Bax, Bak, and Bad are constitutively expressed [13], [14], [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The extrinsic pathway may also be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils constitutively express Fas and Fas ligand, although the importance of Fas-induced death remains controversial [11], [18]–[20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In addition, neutrophil life expectancy can be modulated by various mediators (G-CSF, GM-CSF, IL1β, IFN-gamma, and LPS [21]–[25]) or functional events such as transmigration across the endothelium [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Despite our growing understanding of molecular control of neutrophil PCD, it remains unclear how specific neutrophil blood concentration is maintained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that cell concentration might serve as a neutrophil count regulator via a feedback mechanism affecting PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We examined the in vitro effect of cell number on spontaneous neutrophil PCD, and demonstrated that neutrophil PCD is strongly influenced by cell concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that secreted molecules mediate this effect, and used a proteomic approach, which showed that constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD is regulated by cell concentration through molecules released during neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We further show that the S100 A8/9 complex is a primary regulatory molecule regulating cell survival via CD11b/CD18 and TLR4, and through a signaling mechanism involving MEK-ERK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Cell culture medium consisted of RPMI 1640 (Invitrogen-Gibco, NY) supplemented with 1% L-glutamine and 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Biological Industries, Kibbutz Beit-Haemek, Israel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The APOPTEST-FITC Kit containing Annexin V-FITC was obtained from Nexins Research B.V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>(Hoeven, The Netherlands) or from MBL International (Cambridge, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Propidium iodide (PI) was from Molecular Probes (Eugene, OR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Recombinant proteins S100A8 and S100A9, and blocking antibodies were generously supplied by Dr. Philippe A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Tessier. (Laval University, Quebec, Canada). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The pan-caspase inhibitor zVAD-fmk was purchased from R&amp;D systems (Minneapolis, MN). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Mouse anti-human CD36-PE, mouse anti-human CD11b-PE, and isotype control IgG1-PE were obtained from Serotec (Oxford, UK), and isotype control mouse IgM-PE from Dako (Glostrup, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>DiOC6(3) (3,3-dihexyloxacarbocyanine iodide) was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>MEK inhibitor PD98059 was purchased from Cell Signaling (Danvers, MA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Antibody against the complex S100A8/9 for flow cytometry analysis was purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For blocking assays, rabbit polyclonal anti-S100A9 and anti-S100A8 were generously supplied by Dr Philippe A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Tessier, and blocking antibody against CD11b (BioLegend, San Diego, CA) was used at different dilutions as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Rabbit serum was obtained from Jackson Laboratories (Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Cell isolation and culturing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Blood neutrophils were isolated from fresh buffy coats obtained from healthy donors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>RBCs were sedimented by adding 6% hetastarch in 0.9% NaCl solution (Stem Cell Technologies, Vancouver, Canada) and kept at 25°C for up to 45 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The leukocyte-rich upper layer of the suspension was then collected and centrifuged on a density gradient with Ficoll-Paque (Amersham Biosciences, Uppsala, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Residual erythrocytes were removed by hypotonic lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were maintained in suspension, at different concentrations as indicated, in RPMI 1640 medium, 1% L-glutamine, and 1% penicillin/streptomycin, in 24-well plates at 37°C, in a humidified incubator containing 5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Cells were &gt;95% neutrophils as determined by morphological analysis and &gt;99% viable as determined by Trypan blue dye exclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2b1"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis assessment was performed as previously described [27] (For detailed method see – Methods S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Supernatant transfer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were suspended at concentrations of either 0.5×106/ml or 16×106/ml, for different times as indicated, at 37°C/5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After culturing, the supernatants of the high concentration were collected and added to fresh neutrophils from the same donor at concentration of 0.5×106/ml and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The neutrophils were then allowed to undergo constitutive spontaneous PCD and apoptosis was detected as described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Cells were fixed in 2% glutaraldedyde in cacodylate buffer (0.1M, PH 7.2–7.4) and washed three times in the same buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Cells were then postfixed in 1% OSO4 for 1 h at room temperature, washed in cacodylate buffer, dedydrated in gradient series of ethanol (25%, 50%, 75%, 95%, 100%×2), treated with propylene-oxide for 20 min (2 changes), and embedded in Araldite Resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Thin sections were prepared with an ultramicrotom and examined at an accelerated voltage of 100KW by transmission electron microscope (CM12, Philips, Eindhoeven, The Netherlands). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2d1"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Proteomic (SDS-PAGE and MS) and Western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Proteomic (SDS-PAGE and MS) and Western blotting were performed as previously described [28] (For detailed method see – Methods S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The two cell lines, Chinese hamster ovary (CHO), and CHO stably transfected with complement receptor CR3, were kindly provided by Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>R.R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Ingalls and D.T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Golenbock, Boston Medical Center, Boston, MA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Leukocyte adhesion deficiency patients and controls </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>LAD patients signed an informed consent approved by the Ethics Committee of Hadassah-Hebrew University Medical Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Controls consisted of age- and gender-matched healthy donors, who signed an informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Blood (10 ml) from healthy donors and heparinized blood (10 ml) from patients was drawn and evaluated on the same day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Detection of intracellular phosphorylated ERK by flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>For the assessment of phosphorylation of the ERK, freshly isolated neutrophils were treated as indicated and prepared for intracellular staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed with PBS, fixed with 2% formaldehyde for 10 min at 37°C, and permeabilized with 90% methanol for 30 min on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Cells then were rinsed and incubated for 10 min at RT in PBS containing 0.5% BSA (for blocking), and stained with either mouse anti-human phospho-p44/42 MAPK alexa fluor 488 (Cell Signaling Technology) or isotype control mouse IgG1 alexa fluor 488 (BioLegend). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The Student's t test and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) were used to compare mean data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used to analyze flow cytometry results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered statistically significant for p&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The effect of cell concentration on constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>We assumed constitutive spontaneous PCD requires one or more autoregulatory negative feedback mechanisms exerted by dying neutrophils that affect survival rates of the remaining cells (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Without this effect, one might assume that PCD increases at higher concentrations due to competition for nutrition and other ingredients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>We designed an experiment to examine the effect of various cell concentrations in the physiological range (peripheral blood neutrophil concentration ∼2−6×106/ml) on the constitutive spontaneous PCD rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A higher apoptotic cell concentration had a protective anti-apoptotic effect, and the rate of neutrophil PCD was inversely proportional to cell concentration, indicating an anti-apoptotic effect (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Whereas following 12h of spontaneous constitutive PCD only 5% of cells were still alive at a concentration of 0.5×106 neutrophils/ml, in conditions of 32 fold concentration, at 16×106 neutrophils/ml, more than 40% of the cells were still alive, as shown by Annexin V and PI negative staining (Fig. 2B) and verified by mitochondrial potential loss studies (not shown), both methods of apoptosis detection indicated early apoptosis state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon was further emphasized using cell count. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>There was loss of over 50% of cells through constitutive spontaneous PCD at concentrations of ­­­­0.5x106/ml for 12h (Fig. 2C), and this loss decreased in proportion to increasing cell concentrations up to 16x106/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>At concentrations above 16x106/ml, there was a decline in cell number and a prodeath effect, probably as a result of competition for nutrition and other ingredients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>A. Kinetics of spontaneous constitutive neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were isolated and allowed to undergo spontaneous constitutive PCD at a concentration of 1×106/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Samples were obtained at the indicated intervals, and the apoptosis rate was measured using Annexin V-FITC and PI staining. B. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) of spontaneous constitutive neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Morphology of viable or early apoptotic (white arrow) and apoptotic (black arrows) neutrophils is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic cells show the typical morphology of condensed cytoplasm and chromatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Cells were prepared for TEM as described in Materials and methods. C. Inhibition of spontaneous constitutive neutrophil PCD by pan-caspase inhibitor zVAD-fmk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Sample dot plots of AnnexinV-PI staining of neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD for 14 h at a concentration of 1×106/ml, in the presence or absence of 20 µM Zvad-fmk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Pan-caspase inhibition rescued cells from apoptotic death and viable cells are increased from 19 to 49% (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of 3 or more experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Spontaneous constitutive neutrophil PCD is cell concentration-dependent. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A. Neutrophils underwent spontaneous constitutive PCD for 12 h at cell concentrations ranging from 0.5×106/ml up to 50×106/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(The physiological blood concentration is 2−6×106/ml.) Apoptosis was assessed by AnnexinV-FITC and PI staining, as described in Materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Data represents the mean ± SD of 3 experiments. B. Sample dot plots of AnnexinV-PI staining of neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD for 12 h in (a) 0.5×106/ml, and (b) 16×106/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The percentage of viable, early (AnnexinV+/PI−) and late (AnnexinV+/PI+) apoptotic cells is indicated within the respective quadrants. C. Survival of neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD, based on cell counts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Data presented is the mean ± SD of 3 experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Thus, at physiological concentrations of neutrophils, there was an anti-apoptotic effect at higher neutrophil concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>We termed this a “community effect” ― neutrophils are encouraged to live longer as their community is enlarged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Factors mediating the community effect are present in the supernatant </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In order to determine whether the factor(s) responsible for the community anti-apoptotic effect are found in the supernatant, we exchanged media obtained from low- and high concentrations of constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The supernatants from high concentrations were collected and used as media for low-concentration constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD of the same donor, and the supernatants of low concentrations were used as media for constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD at high cell concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Media based on high-concentration PCD donors (16×106 cells/ml) rescued cells undergoing constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD at low concentration (0.5×106 cells/ml) from apoptosis, as compared with normal medium (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>High-concentration medium increased the rate of viable cells from 9% (upper left panel, Fig. 3B) to 31% (upper right panel, Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In the opposite experiment, low-concentration media had no effect on survival in high cell concentration samples (left and right lower panels, Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>All these experiments were based on at least three experiments each and results with Annexin V were verified using mitochondrial potential loss studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Identification of candidate molecules that induce the community effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>A. Supernatant of cells undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at high concentrations has rescued cells undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD from apoptosis at low concentrations, and improved their survival (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Data is representative of 3 experiments. B. Representative dot plot of supernatant transfer assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis was assessed by AnnexinV and PI staining of neutrophils after 12 h of spontaneous constitutive PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The transfer assay was performed as follows: neutrophils underwent spontaneous constitutive PCD at low (a, 0.5×106/ml) or high (c, 16×106/ml) concentration for 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The supernatant of the cells incubated at high concentrations was collected and used as media for neutrophils undergoing constitutive spontaneous PCD at low concentrations (b), and the supernatant of the cells incubated at low concentrations was collected and used for neutrophils undergoing constitutive spontaneous PCD at high concentrations (d). C. SDS-PAGE of differentially displayed proteins from high- and low-concentration spontaneous constitutive PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The supernatants of cells undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at high- and low concentrations were collected, and the proteins were purified as described in Materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Protein samples were electrophorized and stained with Coomassie, as shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Two proteins, ∼14 KD and ∼10 KD, were identified in the supernatant of cells undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at high concentrations (16×106/ml). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that in the presence of high neutrophil concentrations, anti-apoptotic factor(s) are secreted and provide a survival signal to the viable neutrophil community. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Proteomic analysis of the supernatants and identification of S100A8 and S100A9 as candidate molecules for mediation of the community anti-apoptotic signal </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We used a differentially displayed proteomic approach, as we have previously described [28], to search for secreted factor(s) in the supernatant that may be responsible for the “community effect” on neutrophil survival. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The secreted proteomes of neutrophils undergoing constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD at high concentrations (16×106/ml) and low concentrations (0.5×106/ml) were collected and compared by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed proteins were further analyzed by mass spectrometry (MS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Expression of two proteins, ∼10 KD and ∼14KD, represented the primary difference between the supernatants (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Both were expressed at significantly greater levels in supernatant of cells cultured at high neutrophil concentrations, versus supernatant of cells cultured at low concentrations, despite protein normalization according to cell number and equal protein loading in the gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Proteins were further identified by MS as S100A8 and S100A9, as the best candidates for the community effect (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The experimental approach was designed to use 2D gel; however, 1D gel identified with high certainty two candidate proteins that were chosen for further functional studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0029333-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.t001</object-id><caption><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Table 1. Proteins identified by mass spectrometry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0029333-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0029333.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Peptide sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Protein score (Mowse) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Identified protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Remarks </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>MTCKMSQLER NIETIINTFH QYSVKLGHPD TLNQGEFKEL VRKDLQNFLK KENKNEKVIE HIMEDLDTNA DKQLSFEEFI MLMARLTWAS HEKMHEGDEG PGHHHKPGLG EGTP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>330 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>S100A9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Reported role in inflammation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>MLTELEKALN SIIDVYHKYS LIKGNFHAVY RDDLKKLLET ECPQYIRKKG ADVWFKELDI NTDGAVNFQE FLILVIKMAW QPTKKAMKKA TKSS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>458 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>S100A8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Reported role in inflammation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>MVHLTPEEKS AVTALWGKVN VDEVGGEALG RLLVVYPWTQ RFFESFGDLS TPDAVMGNPK VKAHGKKVLG AFSDGLAHLD NLKGTFATLS ELHCDKLHVD PENFRLLGNV LVCVLAHHFG KKFTPPVQAA YQKVVAGVAN ALAHKYH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>207 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>beta globin chain variant </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Beta globin chain </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>VLSPADKTNV KAAWGKVGAH AGEYGAEALE RMFLSFPTTK TYFPHFDLSH GSAQVKGHGK KVADALTNAV AHVDDMPNAL SALSDLHAHK LRVDPWNFKL LSHCLLVTLA AHLPAEFTPA VHASLDKFLA SVSTVLTSKY R </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Chain C, T State Human Hemoglobin [alpha V96w] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Hemoglobin chain </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>RRPDFCLEPP YTGPCKARII RYFYNAKAGL CQTFVYGGCR AKRNNFKSAE DCMRTCGGA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>113 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Aprotinin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Protease inhibitor (synthetic) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Analysis of proteins identified by mass spectrometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Sequences corresponding to the identified peptides are bolded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Score was based on molecular weight search (MOWSE) peptide-mass database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The results identified S100A8 and S100A9 as candidate proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Functional studies suggest that S100A8-9 mediates the community effect </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We sought to verify S100A8 and A9 mediation of the community anti-apoptotic effect using recombinant human S100A8 and A9 (kindly provided by Philippe A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Tessier, Laval University, Quebec, Canada) added to neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Increased S100A9 and S100A8/9 levels had a dramatic rescue effect on the number of neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at low cell concentrations (* p&lt;0.05), paralleling the rescue effect of the high cell concentration supernatant (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Survival increased by more than 150%±35% in the presence of 5 µg/ml of S100A8/9, as measured by Annexin V and PI (** p&lt;0.02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The survival effect of S100A9 and the S100A8/9 complex was more prominent compared to S100A9 alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Only S100A9 had an effect already at a concentration of 1 µg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, S100A8 in higher concentrations of 2 and 5 µg/ml also had a significant rescue effect (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>To further verify the anti-apoptotic effect of S100A8/9, we measured mitochondrial transmemebrane potential as an additional early PCD evaluation, demonstrating a perfect correlation to the Annexin V-PI measurements (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Effect of S100A9 and S100A8 on neutrophil apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>A. S100A9 and S100A8 add-in experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Varying concentrations of S100A9, S100A8, and the S100A8/9 complex were added to supernatants of neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at a concentration of 0.5×106/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>After 10 hours apoptosis was evaluated using Annexin V-PI and mitochondrial staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Data is presented as mean ± SD of Annexin V-PI staining (* p&lt;0.05, ** p&lt;0.02). B. S100A9 and S100A8 add-in experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>A representative sample of Annexin V-PI and mitochondrial staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD without (a and c) or with (b and d) the addition of 2 µg/ml S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Cells were stained either with Annexin V-FITC (a and b) or with DiOC6 (c and d), as well as PI (a, b, c, d) and assessed by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Dot plots are representative of 6 experiments. C. The effect of anti-S100A8 and A9 on add-in experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils undergoing spontaneous constitutive PCD at a concentration of 0.5×106/ml for 12h, with rabbit polyclonal antibody dilutions of 1∶100, 1∶1000, and 1∶10,000 against S100A9 and S100A8, were then treated with 2 µg/ml S100A8/9 complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Rabbit serum at the same dilutions of 1∶100, 1∶1000, and 1∶10,000 was used as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis was assessed using Annexin V-FITC and PI staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Percentages of viable, early-, and late apoptotic cells are indicated within the respective quadrants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Dot plots are representative of 6 experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>We sought to verify whether S100A9 and S100A8/9 effects are blocked with specific antibodies, using rabbit polyclonal antibodies raised against human S100A8 or S100A9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Antisera were used at a range of dilutions between 1/10 and 1/10,000, as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Adding the antibodies reduced neutrophil survival by 30−40% in various dilutions (Fig. 4C), compared to control antibodies, and induced accelerated PCD similar to that seen in spontaneous constitutive PCD in low cell concentration supernatants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial transmemebrane potential as an additional early PCD evaluation, demonstrated a perfect correlation to the Annexin V-PI measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This further supports a role for S100A8/9 as the main factor triggering the community anti-apoptotic effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>S100A8/9 does not mediate the community effect via McL1, A1, the bcl-2 protein family, or survivin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We examined the expression of different members of the PCD intrinsic pathway, focusing on those known to be important in neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>McL1, an anti-apoptotic member, was expressed by freshly isolated neutrophils (see Figure S3), and expression was still detected during spontaneous constitutive apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Adding S100A8/9 did not change McL1 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>A1 protein has also been found to be expressed in neutrophils [13], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We found that A1 was expressed by freshly isolated neutrophils, with expression dramatically decreased during constitutive spontaneous PCD (see Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Adding S100A8/9 did not prevent decreased A1 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Bclxl was found to be expressed by freshly isolated neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Expression was neither decreased by constitutive spontaneous PCD, nor increased by adding S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We also examined the expression of Bcl2 and survivin proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>These two proteins were not expressed by freshly isolated neutrophils or during induction of constitutive spontaneous PCD, which is consistent with observations that peripheral blood neutrophils don't express these two proteins [11−14], . </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we could not identify an anti-apoptotic mechanism in the main intrinsic pathway players of neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The survival effect of S100A8/9 involves the MEK-ERK signaling pathway, and is partially mediated through TLR4 and the integrin CD11b/CD18 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>S100A8 and A9 specific receptors have not yet been identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, Vogl et al demonstrated that S100A8 specifically interacts with the TLR4-MD2 complex [29], and Newton RA et al suggested that a pertusis toxin-sensitive G-coupled protein receptor could be the S100A9 receptor [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>S100A8 and A9 have been shown to exert their effects via CD36 and CD11b/CD18 (Mac-1)   [30−32].CD11b/CD18 is well expressed in freshly isolated neutrophils, but CD36 is not (Fig. 5A, upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, CD11b/CD18 was suggested as a pro-apoptotic integrin [33], [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The survival effect of S100A8/9 is mediated through CD11b/CD18 and TLR4. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>A. Expression of CD11b on neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Upper panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils express CD11b/CD18 (isotype control is shown as filled histogram and anti- CD11b/CD18-PE in dotted line, middle) but not CD36 (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Following 12 h of spontaneous PCD (gray line, middle) there was a marked decrease in the expression of CD11b/CD18 in comparison to freshly isolated neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Addition of S100A8/9 resulted in two different cell populations: high and low-CD11b/CD18 (black line, right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Lower panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Correlation between CD11b and phosphatidylserine expression demonstrates that when neutrophils become apoptotic they downregulate CD11b expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>S100A8/9 upregulates CD11b expression. B. S100A8/9 dramatically increases CD11b on viable cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Viable cells (R1, black line) increase CD11b expression from a mean fluorescence of 552 to 1094 (p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic cells (R2, gray line) still maintain some of this effect and show a mean fluorescence of 473, compared to 362 in the absence of S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Filled histograms represent isotype control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were harvested after 12 h spontaneous constitutive PCD, with or without treatment with 2 µg/ml S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Histograms are representative of at least 3 different experiments. C. The survival effect of S100A8/9 in the presence of anti-CD11b/CD18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Upper panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were incubated for 12 h and treated with either anti-CD11b or the isotype control IgG1 before addition of S100A8/9 complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Integrin inhibition reduced the effect of S100A8/9 by 40−100% in comparison with the isotype control (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The average of 6 experiments is presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Lower panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>A representative dot plot is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Upper panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>S100A8/9 binds to CD11b/CD18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>CHO cells transfected with CR3 (black) or vector (gray) were evaluated for S100A8/9 binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>CR3-ransfected cells bound at rates almost twofold higher than CHO control cells (median fluorescence 13.3 vs. 6.6, p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The filled curve represents isotype control; the histogram is representative of 3 experiments. D. S100A8/9 effect on neutrophils from a CD11b/CD18-deficient patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Neutrophil expression of CD11b from a healthy control and a patient with leukocyte adhesion deficiency is shown in the upper panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Spontaneous constitutive apoptosis is shown in the lower panel, together with the S100A8/9 effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were isolated from a CD11b-deficient patient and a healthy control, as described in Materials and methods, incubated at a concentration of 1×106/ml and allowed to undergo spontaneous constitutive PCD for 10 h, with or without addition of S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis was assessed by Annexin V-PI staining. E. The survival effect induced by the complex S100A8/9 in the presence of pertussis toxin. Bordetella pertussis toxin at 100 and 500 ng/ml were added to neutrophils 45 min before adding S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils then were allowed to undergo constitutive spontaneous PCD that was assessed using AnnexinV-FITC and PI staining after 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The dot plots are representative of 3 experiments. F. The survival effect of S100A8/9 in the presence of anti-TLR4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were incubated for 10 h and treated with either anti-TLR4 or the isotype control IgG2a, as described in Materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of TLR4 abrogated the effect of S100A8/9 by 30−60% (p&lt;0.001) in comparison with the isotype control, as seen in upper panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The upper panel is presented as percentage of control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The experiment is a summary of four experiments (upper panel) with representative Plots in the lower panel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Following spontaneous constitutive PCD, we detected a homogeneous decrease in neutrophil expression of CD11b/CD18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Gating apoptotic (Annexin V-positive) versus nonapoptotic (Annexin V-negative) cells (Fig. 5B) revealed higher CD11b/CD18 expression on viable- versus apoptotic neutrophils (Fig. 5A−B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, adding S100A8/9 dramatically upregulated CD11b/CD18, establishing a new subpopulation with very high expression on viable cells (Fig. 5A−B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>We then blocked CD11b/CD18 prior to addition of S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>CD11b inhibition during constitutive spontaneous neutrophil PCD decreased cell survival by 20%, and in the presence of S100A8/9, CD11b inhibition cut the survival effect of S100A8/9 by 50−75% (Fig. 5C), suggesting that S100A8/9 may exert its survival effect, at least in part, by either binding or expressing CD11b, a known receptor involved in neutrophil apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>For further assessments, we used a CHO cell line transfected with CD11b/CD18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Transfected CHO cells increased binding of the S100A8/9 complex by almost twofold in comparison with control CHO cells (Fig. 5C, upper right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>However, when we examined the effect of recombinant S100A8/9 on CD11b/CD18-deficient neutrophils from a leukocyte adhesion deficiency (LAD) patient, results were less clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>As expected, CD11b-deficient neutrophils showed delayed PCD in comparison with neutrophils from healthy donors (Fig. 5D), however the S100A8/9 complex kept its protective anti-apoptotic effect on CD11b-deficient neutrophils, and survival was increased by 50−90%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>This supports the hypothesis that these proteins exert their survival effect only partially by CD11b/CD18, and other receptors are involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the role of one alternative candidate, we examined a G-coupled protein receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Pertusis toxin, which abrogates G-coupled protein receptor function, did not influence the survival effect of S100A8/9 (Fig. 5E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>An additional possible receptor is Toll-like receptor 4 [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Inhibiting TLR4 abrogated the survival effect of S100A8/9 by 25−60% (Fig. 5F), suggesting that both CD11b/CD18 and TLR4 may be involved in the pathway enabling these proteins to affect neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), one of the mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK), is involved in integrin signaling and Toll-like receptors in general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>It appears to mediate signals promoting cell proliferation, differentiation, and survival, as reviewed by Roux, et al [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>We assessed the role of ERK in the neutrophil S100A8/9 survival effect using intracellular staining of phosphorylated ERK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils exposed to S100A8/9 for 10 min showed more than a threefold increase in phosphorylation of the ERK kinase (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>This activation continues to a lesser extent following 30 and 60 min exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the inhibitor PD98059 (MEK inhibitor) reduced ERK phosphorylation by more than 50% (Fig. 6B) and abolished the S100A8/9 survival effect by 50−100% at various concentrations (Fig. 6C), suggesting that the S100A8/9 complex survival effect involves the MEK-ERK signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0029333-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029333.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Effects of the S100A8/9 complex are mediated through the MAPK-ERK pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>A. Phosphorylation of MAPK following exposure to S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils with or without treatment with 2 µg/ml S100A8/9 for various times as indicated, and then prepared for intracellular staining with mouse anti-human phospho-p44/42 MAPK alexa fluor 488 (gray) or isotype control (black), as described in Materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In the presence of S100A8/9, phosphorylation was increased by 3.22-fold after 10 min (p&lt;0.001), 1.5-fold after 30 min (p&lt;0.001), and decayed at 60 min (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Histograms are representative of 3 independent experiments. B. Reduced phosphorylation of MAPK following exposure to S100A8/9 in the presence of PD98059, a MAPK phosphorylation inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils were treated with the inhibitor PD98059 or with DMSO as a control for 30 min, and then treated with 2 µg/ml S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Cells were then harvested and prepared for intracellular staining of phospho-p44/42 MAPK (gray) or isotype control (black), as described in Materials and methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Treatment with PD98059 inhibitor reduced phosphorylation caused by the S100A8/9 complex (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Histograms are representative of 3 experiments. C. Effect of the S100A8/9 complex in the presence of MAPK-ERK inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The effect of S100A8/9 was assessed in the presence of PD98059. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils were treated with varying combinations and concentrations of DMSO (white bars), S100A8/9 complex (gray bars), or S100A8/9 complex with PD98059 (black bars), as indicated, for 30 min before adding S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils were allowed to undergo constitutive spontaneous PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Results represent the percentage of viable cells according to Annexin V-FITC and PI staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Data is representative of 3 experiments (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0029333.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic neutrophils are not activated neutrophils </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>As S100A8/9 was mainly reported thus far to be released during inflammation (see discussion), it may be attributed to release due to neutrophil activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>We wanted to further verify that apoptotic neutrophils are not activated due to extraction method or in vitro effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Therefore we analyzed three surface molecules that are upregulated upon neutrophil activation and downregulated upon neutrophil PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>In figures S1 and S2, CD16 and CD62L, both markers of neutrophil activation showed clear down regulation in the examined neutrophils, in correlation to apoptotic state [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In addition CD11b, is a third molecule, that is upregulated upon activation was downregulated in apoptotic neutrophils releasing S100A8 and S100A9 (see Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Taken together, S100 A8 and S100A9 were released in the context of apoptotic neutrophil death in non activated neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Neutrophils are responsible for the body's rapid and effective response to infection or injury [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Efficient function necessitates an optimal balance between a sufficient number of blood neutrophils, response to stimuli, and transmigration properties, on one hand, against regulation of the termination of a neutrophil-mediated inflammatory response on the other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Thus, control of neutrophil turnover in the bone marrow and circulation, and at inflammatory sites, is key to both homeostasis and inflammation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>PCD plays a critical role in neutrophil homeostasis for an optimal functioning in the human body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Polymorphonuclears comprise approximately 75% of all nucleated cells in the hematopoietic compartment of the newborn marrow, with the majority being neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Already in the bone marrow, large-scale neutrophil death and removal of neutrophils by phagocytes are seen [38].Yet, the major regulator of blood neutrophil counts, as well as neutrophil counts at inflammatory sites, is PCD, which allows only a short life span, with modulation according to needs such as inflammation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Here we show that the S100 A8/9 complex regulates neutrophil number and PCD in response to neutrophil concentration, by an anti-apoptotic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>S100A9 (MRP14) and S100A8 (MRP8) constitute roughly 40% of the cytosolic protein in neutrophils; their pure abundance implies an important role in neutrophil functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>However, our understanding of the mechanisms implicating both molecules in neutrophil/monocyte physiology remains incomplete, as reviewed by Nacken, et al [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>S100A9 and S100A8 readily form hetero- and homodimeric, trimeric, and tetrameric complexes, but apparently also exert specific functions as monomers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that S100A9 plays a prominent role in leukocyte trafficking and arachidonic acid metabolism, and elevated S100A9 and S100A8 levels are found in body fluids of inflamed tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>When neutrophils undergo PCD, they release S100A8/9, which partially protects surrounding neutrophils from PCD, a mechanism that may be of crucial importance in fine-tuning neutrophil concentrations in the bone marrow and blood, and in inflammatory sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>This finding is supported by the decrease in bone marrow neutrophils in S100A9-deficient mice [40], and the accumulation of S100A8/9 at inflammatory sites, where prolonged survival of neutrophils is usually needed for chemotaxis and neutrophil adhesion [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>As shown in figure 5A and supplemental figures 1 and 2, apoptotic neutrophils were not activated and their S100 A8 and S100 A9 release was associated with PCD and not inflammation or activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>S100A8 deficiency is lethal [41], thus further research to gain understanding of the role of S100A8/9 is partially limited to animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>By prolonging neutrophil life, S100A8/9 accumulation could be also a contributing mechanism to autoimmune conditions and the development of chronic inflammation or acute sterile danger-related inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>In conditions such as gout, monosodium urate monohydrate crystals induce the release of S100A8/A9 from neutrophils [42] and allow inflammatory attack by prolonging neutrophil life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>High S100A8/9 levels were found in chronically inflamed joints of patients with rheumatoid arthritis [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Our study also proposes an additional possible mechanism for neutropenia following chemotherapy, suggesting that low neutrophil concentration may be further aggravated due to accelerated PCD, induced at low neutrophil concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis needs further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>We were also able to gain a better understanding of the mechanism enabling S100A8/9 function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>S100A8/9 clearly upregulates and binds to CD11b, previously shown to be a major regulator of neutrophil PCD [44], with possible anti- or pro-apoptotic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>However, as shown here, this effect was retained in CD11b-deficient neutrophils, indicating additional mechanisms such as TLR4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Indeed, blocking TLR4 partially abrogated the S100A8/9 survival effect, suggesting that S100A8/9 is an endogenous TLR4 ligand mediating survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that the TLR4 agonist LPS and others inhibit neutrophil apoptosis [12], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Here we show for the first time an endogenous ligand that inhibits neutrophil apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Our results also show a role for the MEK/ERK pathway following activation by S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>This pathway has been well documented to mediate signaling of both integrins and Toll-like receptors, supporting a role for CD11b, TLR4, and possibly additional receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>This mechanism has been shown in the past to be anti-apoptotic in neutrophils via both intrinsic [46] and extrinsic [47] PCD pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The correlation between beta2-integrin and TLR4 has been suggested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>These two receptors may cooperate to produce signals that are transmitted into the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Also, TLR4 has been suggested to be an “inside-out” regulator of the beta2-integrins [48], and even a direct TLR4-beta2 integrin interaction has been suggested [49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Other possible functional proteins that could have a “community effect” may be found in the secreted proteome of apoptotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>An experimental approach using 2D gel may discover additional candidate proteins and functional studies may establish their potential role in PCD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>In summary, the physiological role of S100A8/9, the most abundant cytosol protein in neutrophils, was not previously understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>We propose that at physiological protein [50] and cell concentrations, its main function is in modulating neutrophil PCD, and that cell concentration is regulated by an autocrine and paracrine mechanism via S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Finally, a biological “proof” is presented here, suggesting that nature encourages “community life” at the level of neutrophil survival, which could be seen as a cellular illustration for human life. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029333.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic neutrophils downregulate CD16. The expression of CD16 (Fc gamma RIII) on neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils CD16 expession at time 0 (black line, median fluorescence of 382) and following 12 h of spontaneous PCD (gray line, median fluorescence of 35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Isotype control is shown as filled histogram. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0029333.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029333.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic neutrophils downregulate CD62L. The expression of CD62L (L-selectin) on neutrophils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Freshly isolated neutrophils CD62L expession at time 0 (black line, median fluorescence of 791) and following 12 h of spontaneous PCD (gray line, median fluorescence of 27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Isotype control is shown as filled histogram. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0029333.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029333.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis-related proteins during spontaneous constitutive PCD in the presence of S100A8/9. SDS-PAGE of McL1, Bcl-xl, A1, Bcl2, and survivin in spontaneous constitutive apoptosis, with and without addition of S100A8/9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>McL1 (39 KD) and Bcl-xl (26 KD) were detected in all conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>A1 (20KD) was detected from freshly isolated neutrophils but expression was downregulated significantly by spontaneous constitutive apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Addition of S100A8/9 did not rescue protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Bcl2 (25KD) and survivin (19KD) were not detected under any experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>The lysates of 40×106 neutrophils under different conditions, including freshly isolated, after 8–10 h of spontaneous constitutive PCD, or after 8–10 h of spontaneous constitutive PCD with addition of S100A8/9, were loaded and separated by SDS-PAGE, as described in Experimental Procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Proteins were transferred to the PVDF membrane and exposed to the appropriate primary antibody according to manufacturers' instructions, and then to secondary antibody conjugated with HRP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0029333.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029333.s004"><label>Methods S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Additional details of methods used in proteomics and programmed cell death evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0029333.s004.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><p>The authors wish to thank Shifra Fraifeld, a research associate in our Medical Center, for her editorial contribution during the preparation of this manuscript.</p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Funding: This research was partially supported by a grant from the Hadassah-Hebrew University Medical Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>No additional external funding received for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0029333-Ellis1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>1 EllisREYuanJYHorvitzHR 1991 Mechanisms and functions of cell death. Annu Rev Cell Biol 7 663 698 1809356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Krammer1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>2 KrammerPH 2000 CD95′s deadly mission in the immune system. Nature 407 789 795 11048730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Dancey1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>3 DanceyJTDeubelbeissKAHarkerLAFinchCA 1976 Neutrophil kinetics in man. J Clin Invest 58 705 715 956397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Metcalf1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>4 MetcalfD 2008 Hematopoietic cytokines. Blood 111 485 491 18182579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Stark1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>5 StarkMAHuoYBurcinTLMorrisMAOlsonTS 2005 Phagocytosis of apoptotic neutrophils regulates granulopoiesis via IL-23 and IL-17. Immunity 22 285 294 15780986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Hernandez1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>6 HernandezPAGorlinRJLukensJNTaniuchiSBohinjecJ 2003 Mutations in the chemokine receptor gene CXCR4 are associated with WHIM syndrome, a combined immunodeficiency disease. Nat Genet 34 70 74 12692554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Martin1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>7 MartinCBurdonPCBridgerGGutierrez-RamosJCWilliamsTJ 2003 Chemokines acting via CXCR2 and CXCR4 control the release of neutrophils from the bone marrow and their return following senescence. Immunity 19 583 593 14563322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Shi1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>8 ShiJGilbertGEKokuboYOhashiT 2001 Role of the liver in regulating numbers of circulating neutrophils. Blood 98 1226 1230 11493474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Furze1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>9 FurzeRCRankinSM 2008 The role of the bone marrow in neutrophil clearance under homeostatic conditions in the mouse. Faseb J 22 3111 3119 18509199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Joyce1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>10 JoyceRABoggsDRHasibaUSrodesCH 1976 Marginal neutrophil pool size in normal subjects and neutropenic patients as measured by epinephrine infusion. J Lab Clin Med 88 614 620 787457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Iwai1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>11 IwaiKMiyawakiTTakizawaTKonnoAOhtaK 1994 Differential expression of bcl-2 and susceptibility to anti-Fas-mediated cell death in peripheral blood lymphocytes, monocytes, and neutrophils. Blood 84 1201 1208 7519477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Moulding1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>12 MouldingDAQuayleJAHartCAEdwardsSW 1998 Mcl-1 expression in human neutrophils: regulation by cytokines and correlation with cell survival. Blood 92 2495 2502 9746790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-SantosBeneit1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>13 Santos-BeneitAMMollinedoF 2000 Expression of genes involved in initiation, regulation, and execution of apoptosis in human neutrophils and during neutrophil differentiation of HL-60 cells. J Leukoc Biol 67 712 724 10811013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Weinmann1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>14 WeinmannPGaehtgensPWalzogB 1999 Bcl-Xl- and Bax-alpha-mediated regulation of apoptosis of human neutrophils via caspase-3. Blood 93 3106 3115 10216108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Chuang1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>15 ChuangPIYeeEKarsanAWinnRKHarlanJM 1998 A1 is a constitutive and inducible Bcl-2 homologue in mature human neutrophils. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 249 361 365 9712701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Altznauer1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>16 AltznauerFMartinelliSYousefiSThurigCSchmidI 2004 Inflammation-associated cell cycle-independent block of apoptosis by survivin in terminally differentiated neutrophils. J Exp Med 199 1343 1354 15148334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Moulding2"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>17 MouldingDAAkgulCDerouetMWhiteMREdwardsSW 2001 BCL-2 family expression in human neutrophils during delayed and accelerated apoptosis. J Leukoc Biol 70 783 792 11698499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>18 BrownSBSavillJ 1999 Phagocytosis triggers macrophage release of Fas ligand and induces apoptosis of bystander leukocytes. J Immunol 162 480 485 9886423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Fecho1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>19 FechoKCohenPL 1998 Fas ligand (gld)- and Fas (lpr)-deficient mice do not show alterations in the extravasation or apoptosis of inflammatory neutrophils. J Leukoc Biol 64 373 383 9738665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Liles1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>20 LilesWCKienerPALedbetterJAAruffoAKlebanoffSJ 1996 Differential expression of Fas (CD95) and Fas ligand on normal human phagocytes: implications for the regulation of apoptosis in neutrophils. J Exp Med 184 429 440 8760796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Begley1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>21 BegleyCGLopezAFNicolaNAWarrenDJVadasMA 1986 Purified colony-stimulating factors enhance the survival of human neutrophils and eosinophils in vitro: a rapid and sensitive microassay for colony-stimulating factors. Blood 68 162 166 3487354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Colotta1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>22 ColottaFReFPolentaruttiNSozzaniSMantovaniA 1992 Modulation of granulocyte survival and programmed cell death by cytokines and bacterial products. Blood 80 2012 2020 1382715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Cox1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>23 CoxGGauldieJJordanaM 1992 Bronchial epithelial cell-derived cytokines (G-CSF and GM-CSF) promote the survival of peripheral blood neutrophils in vitro. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol 7 507 513 1384583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>24 LeeAWhyteMKHaslettC 1993 Inhibition of apoptosis and prolongation of neutrophil functional longevity by inflammatory mediators. J Leukoc Biol 54 283 288 8409750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Lopez1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>25 LopezAFWilliamsonDJGambleJRBegleyCGHarlanJM 1986 Recombinant human granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor stimulates in vitro mature human neutrophil and eosinophil function, surface receptor expression, and survival. J Clin Invest 78 1220 1228 3021817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Watson1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>26 WatsonRWRotsteinODNathensABParodoJMarshallJC 1997 Neutrophil apoptosis is modulated by endothelial transmigration and adhesion molecule engagement. J Immunol 158 945 953 8993015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Trahtemberg1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>27 TrahtembergUAtallahMKrispinAVerbovetskiIMevorachD 2007 Calcium, leukocyte cell death and the use of annexin V: fatal encounters. Apoptosis 12 1769 1780 17578666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Krispin1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>28 KrispinABlediYAtallahMTrahtembergUVerbovetskiI 2006 Apoptotic cell thrombospondin-1 and heparin-binding domain lead to dendritic-cell phagocytic and tolerizing states. Blood 108 3580 3589 16882710 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Vogl1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>29 VoglTTenbrockKLudwigSLeukertNEhrhardtC 2007 Mrp8 and Mrp14 are endogenous activators of Toll-like receptor 4, promoting lethal, endotoxin-induced shock. Nat Med 13 1042 1049 17767165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Newton1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>30 NewtonRAHoggN 1998 The human S100 protein MRP-14 is a novel activator of the beta 2 integrin Mac-1 on neutrophils. J Immunol 160 1427 1435 9570563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Kerkhoff1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>31 KerkhoffCSorgCTandonNNNackenW 2001 Interaction of S100A8/S100A9-arachidonic acid complexes with the scavenger receptor CD36 may facilitate fatty acid uptake by endothelial cells. Biochemistry 40 241 248 11141076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Ryckman1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>32 RyckmanCVandalKRouleauPTalbotMTessierPA 2003 Proinflammatory activities of S100: proteins S100A8, S100A9, and S100A8/A9 induce neutrophil chemotaxis and adhesion. J Immunol 170 3233 3242 12626582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Coxon1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>33 CoxonARieuPBarkalowFJAskariSSharpeAH 1996 A novel role for the beta 2 integrin CD11b/CD18 in neutrophil apoptosis: a homeostatic mechanism in inflammation. Immunity 5 653 666 8986723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Weinmann2"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>34 WeinmannPScharffetter-KochanekKForlowSBPetersTWalzogB 2003 A role for apoptosis in the control of neutrophil homeostasis in the circulation: insights from CD18-deficient mice. Blood 101 739 746 12393639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Roux1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>35 RouxPPBlenisJ 2004 ERK and p38 MAPK-activated protein kinases: a family of protein kinases with diverse biological functions. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 68 320 344 15187187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Dransfield1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>36 DransfieldIBuckleAMSavillJSMcDowallAHaslettC 1994 neutrophil apoptosis is associated with a reduction in CD16 (Fc gamma RIII) expression. J Immunol 153 1254 63 8027553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Kobayashi1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>37 KobayashiSDVoyichJMDeLeoFR 2003 Regulation of the neutrophil-mediated inflammatory response to infection. Microbes Infect 5 1337 1344 14613777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Sasaki1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>38 SasakiKIwatsukiHSudaMItanoC 1995 Accumulation and massive cell death of polymorphonuclear neutrophils in the developing bone marrow of the mouse: a histological study. Acta Anat (Basel) 153 111 118 8560963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Nacken1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>39 NackenWRothJSorgCKerkhoffC 2003 S100A9/S100A8: Myeloid representatives of the S100 protein family as prominent players in innate immunity. Microsc Res Tech 60 569 580 12645005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Manitz1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>40 ManitzMPHorstBSeeligerSStreyASkryabinBV 2003L of S100A9 (MRP14) results in reduced interleukin-8-induced CD11b surface expression, a polarized microfilament system, and diminished responsiveness to chemoattractants in vitro. Mol Cell Biol 23 1034 1043 12529407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Passey1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>41 PasseyRJWilliamsELichanskaAMWellsCHuS 1999 A null mutation in the inflammation-associated S100 protein S100A8 causes early resorption of the mouse embryo. J Immunol 163 2209 2216 10438963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Ryckman2"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>42 RyckmanCGilbertCde MedicisRLussierAVandalK 2004 Monosodium urate monohydrate crystals induce the release of the proinflammatory protein S100A8/A9 from neutrophils. J Leukoc Biol 76 433 440 15107458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Odink1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>43 OdinkKCerlettiNBruggenJClercRGTarcsayL 1987 Two calcium-binding proteins in infiltrate macrophages of rheumatoid arthritis. Nature 330 80 82 3313057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Mayadas1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>44 MayadasTNCullereX 2005 Neutrophil beta2 integrins: moderators of life or death decisions. Trends Immunol 26 388 395 15922663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Francois1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>45 FrancoisSEl BennaJDangPMPedruzziEGougerot-PocidaloMA 2005 Inhibition of neutrophil apoptosis by TLR agonists in whole blood: involvement of the phosphoinositide 3-kinase/Akt and NF-kappaB signaling pathways, leading to increased levels of Mcl-1, A1, and phosphorylated Bad. J Immunol 174 3633 3642 15749901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Petrin1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>46 PetrinDTurcotteSGilbertAKRola-PleszczynskiMStankovaJ 2006 The anti-apoptotic effect of leukotriene B4 in neutrophils: a role for phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase, extracellular signal-regulated kinase and Mcl-1. Cell Signal 18 479 487 15970427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-KotoneMiyahara1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>47 Kotone-MiyaharaYYamashitaKLeeKKYoneharaSUchiyamaT 2004 Short-term delay of Fas-stimulated apoptosis by GM-CSF as a result of temporary suppression of FADD recruitment in neutrophils: evidence implicating phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase and MEK1-ERK1/2 pathways downstream of classical protein kinase C. J Leukoc Biol 76 1047 1056 15328334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Luo1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>48 LuoBHCarmanCVSpringerTA 2007 Structural basis of integrin regulation and signaling. Annu Rev Immunol 25 619 647 17201681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Kagan1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>49 KaganJCMedzhitovR 2006 Phosphoinositide-mediated adaptor recruitment controls Toll-like receptor signaling. Cell 125 943 955 16751103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0029333-Frosch1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>50 FroschMStreyAVoglTWulffraatNMKuisW 2000 Myeloid-related proteins 8 and 14 are specifically secreted during interaction of phagocytes and activated endothelium and are useful markers for monitoring disease activity in pauciarticular-onset juvenile rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Rheum 43 628 637 10728757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
