<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Nanobiotechnology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Nanobiotechnology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Nanobiotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-3155</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4906686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12951-016-0194-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Selective killing of cancer cells by nanoparticle-assisted ultrasound </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosheleva</surname><given-names>Olga K.</given-names></name><address><email>olga@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Tsung-Ching</given-names></name><address><email>chuching@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Nelson G.</given-names></name><address><email>ngchen@nctu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><address><email>mhsiao@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chung-Hsuan</given-names></name><address><email>winschen@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Genomics Research Center, Academia Sinica, Taipei, 211 Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Institute of Biomedical Engineering, College of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National Chiao-Tung University, Hsinchu, 300 Taiwan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>46</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Intense ultrasound, such as that used for tumor ablation, does not differentiate between cancerous and normal cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>A method combining ultrasound and biocompatible gold or magnetic nanoparticles (NPs) was developed under in vitro conditions using human breast and lung epithelial cells, which causes ultrasound to preferentially destroy cancerous cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Co-cultures of BEAS-2B normal lung cells and A549 cancerous lung cells labeled with green and red fluorescent proteins, respectively, were treated with focused ultrasound beams with the addition of gold and magnetic nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>There were significantly more necrotic A549 cells than BEAS-2 cells when gold nanoparticles were added to the culture medium [(50.6 ± 15.1) vs. (7.4 ± 2.9) %, respectively, P &lt; 0.01]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This selective damage to cancer cells was also observed for MDA-MB231 breast cancer cells relative to MCF-10A normal breast cells after treatment with magnetic nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The data obtained for different cell lines indicate that nanoparticle-assisted ultrasound therapy (NAUT) could be an effective new tool for cancer-specific treatment and could potentially be combined with conventional methods of cancer diagnosis and therapy to further increase the overall cancer cure rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cancer cells</kwd><kwd>Nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>Ultrasound therapy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Cancer is a leading cause of death worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Many cancer patients die as a result of the severe side effects of chemotherapy or from a drug-resistance-related relapse after the original treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>It has been established that a typical tumor has a high degree of heterogeneity and can contain more than 100 cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>If a targeted drug is used, certain types of cancer cells may survive and become dominant in the tumor, eventually making the drug ineffective. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>If adequate physical treatment is applied, it should reduce not only the side effects but also the growth of drug-resistant cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Radiation therapy is one of the standard physical methods of cancer treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>There are various types of radiation therapies, including electromagnetic ionizing radiation (gamma-rays and X-rays), elementary particle ionizing beam radiation (electrons, protons and neutrons), and non-ionizing radiation (photons, microwaves and radio waves). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The ionizing radiation is intended to be directed only at the tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, radiation is difficult to focus; therefore, it also affects normal tissues when it passes through a patient’s body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Normal cells are affected by ionizing radiation, which produces undesirable side effects [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Moreover, ionizing radiation itself may cause DNA mutation in normal cells, causing these cells to become cancerous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Light is used as non-ionizing radiation in photodynamic therapy for tumors, and this method relies on the ability of certain photosensitizing dyes to absorb light and convert the energy into cytotoxic molecules, including singlet oxygen [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The main limitations of photodynamic methods are solid tumor hypoxia [3] and relatively low penetration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The other disadvantage of the method is the need to avoid light exposure for an extensive period after the treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Other non-ionizing radiation therapies are mainly based on hyperthermia in tumors as a result of the higher sensitivity of tumor cells to heat than their normal counterparts [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Hyperthermia has been induced by gold nanoparticle-assisted laser ablation [5], magnetic nanoparticle rotation under an alternating magnetic field [6], and high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Unlike other methods, focused ultrasound is the only non-invasive technology that can be used for local tumor ablation deep inside the body without causing severe harm to overlying skin or adjacent connective tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>For conventional HIFU transducers, the absorption efficiencies of the acoustic energy are generally similar for normal and malignant tissues such that precise focusing of ultrasound beams is required for selective tumor ablation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, normal tissue near the tumor region can still be damaged by high-intensity ultrasound waves reflected from interfaces [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a new physical method that does not cause DNA mutations or destroy normal cells is highly desirable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>To overcome the drawbacks of HIFU, we developed a new technique based on an HIFU instrument and biocompatible gold and magnetic nanoparticles (NPs) in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that adding NPs to culture media allowed for the use of lower ultrasound (US) intensities to treat and kill cells compared with those used in conventional US treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Nanoparticle-assisted ultrasound therapy (NAUT) allowed for the selective killing of malignant breast and lung epithelial cells over their normal counterparts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound treatment of lung cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound treatment of separate cell monolayers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The effect of ultrasound (US) and gold NPs on cancerous (A549) and normal (BEAS-2B) lung cells, as analyzed by counting viable cells (Q4) using flow cytometry, is shown in Fig. 1.Fig. 1Flow cytometry data for BEAS-2B normal lung cells (A) and A549 lung cancer cells (C) after US treatment with gold NPs and the corresponding numbers of live BEAS-2B (B, E) and A549 (D, E) cells. A, C Control (untreated) cells without NPs (a); control (untreated) cells with gold NPs (c); cells treated with US without NPs (b); cells exposed to US with gold NPs (d). *represents P &lt; 0.05, **represents P &lt; 0.01, ***represents P &lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry data for the propidium iodide viability test on BEAS-2B and A549 cells are provided in Fig. 1A, C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The mean numbers of viable BEAS-2B and A549 cells for five similar experiments, with calculated P values, are shown in Fig. 1B–E and Table 1.Table 1Percentage of live BEAS-2B and A549 cells in separate monolayers treated with US and gold NPs averaged for five similar experimentsCell linePercentage of live cells not treated with NPsPercentage of live cells treated with NPsPercentage of live cells treated with US alonePercentage of live cells treated with US and NPsBEAS-2B78.6 ± 1.480.9 ± 1.867.8 ± 3.357 ± 6.0A54982.7 ± 1.579.8 ± 1.860.5 ± 3.929.8 ± 7.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrate a slight decrease in the percentage of live cells from (67.8 ± 3.3) to (57 ± 6.0) % when gold NPs were added to US-treated normal BEAS-2B cells (Fig. 1B, E; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the percentage of live A549 cancer cells decreased from (60.5 ± 4.0) % for US-treated cells to (29.8 ± 7.5) % for the combination of US with NPs (Fig. 1D, E; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that A549 lung cancer cells are more sensitive to the damage caused by US than BEAS-2B normal lung cells are. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The addition of gold NPs to cell cultures leads to a significant increase in cancer cell death and shows the synergistic damaging effect of US and nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The BEAS-2B normal cells appear to be more resistant to this effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound treatment of cell co-cultures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>To compare the effect of ultrasound irradiation on normal and cancerous cells under identical experimental conditions, BEAS-2B and A549 human lung cells were co-cultured and modified with fluorescent green and red proteins, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Monolayers of the co-culture were then treated with US with and without the addition of gold NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This experiment sought to eliminate possible differences due to the variations in US treatments and culture conditions for cancerous and normal cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To estimate the cell damage, we analyzed trypan blue-stained cells under an optical microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent and phase-contrast images of trypan blue-stained BEAS-2B/A549 co-culture treated with different combinations of US and gold NPs are shown in Fig. 2A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The mean percentage of necrotic BEAS-2B and A549 cells for five similar experiments is presented in Fig. 2B, D and in Table 2.Fig. 2Phase-contrast and fluorescence images of trypan blue stained BEAS-2B and A549 co-cultures with and without US exposure (A) and the corresponding numbers of necrotic BEAS-2B (B, D) and A549 (C, D) cells. A Control (untreated) cells (a–d); cells treated only with US (e–h); cells treated with US and gold NPs (i–l); fluorescence images of normal cells (green) (a, e, i) and cancer cells (red) (b, f, j); phase-contrast images of the co-culture (c, g, k); merged fluorescence and phase-contrast images (d, h, l). *represents P &lt; 0.05, and **represents P &lt; 0.01Table 2Percentage of necrotic BEAS-2B and A549 cells in co-culture treated with a combination of US and gold NPsCell lineNo NP and no USUS but no NPUS and NPsBEAS-2B1.4 ± 0.92.6 ± 1.27.4 ± 2.9A5492 ± 1.618.8 ± 5.950.6 ± 15.1The number is the average for five similar experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Phase-contrast and fluorescence images of the control (untreated) samples without gold NPs are shown in Fig. 2Aa–d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Cells with dark- or blue-colored nuclei are necrotic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Only a few dead cells were observed in the control samples of either cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A few dead BEAS-2B cells are shown in Fig. 2Ae–h; these cells underwent US treatment without the addition of nanoparticles (Fig. 2B, D; Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions, the number of necrotic A549 cells was approximately (18.8 ± 6.0) % (Fig. 2C, D; Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence images of the co-culture treated with the combination of ultrasound irradiation in the presence of gold NPs are shown in Fig. 2Ai–l. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The combined treatment of cells resulted in (7.4 ± 3.0) and (50.6 ± 15.1) % necrotic BEAS-2B and A549 cells, respectively (Fig. 2B–D; Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Thus, the addition of gold NPs to the culture medium immediately before the US exposure enhances the damage to both types of lung cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>However, the synergistic cytotoxic effects of US and NPs are more pronounced on A-549 lung cancer cells under co-culture conditions than on their normal counterparts (BEAS-2B cells). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound treatment of breast cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>A similar selective killing effect on cancer cells was observed when a monolayer of MCF-10A normal breast cells and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells were treated with a combination of US and biocompatible magnetic nanoparticles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The flow cytometry data and the mean number of live cells for five similar experiments are shown in Fig. 3 and Table 3.Fig. 3Flow cytometry data for MCF-10A normal breast cells (A) and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells (C) with/without US treatment and magnetic NPs and the corresponding numbers of live MCF-10A (B, E) and MDA-MB-231 (D, E) cells. A, C Control (untreated) cells not treated with NPs (a); cells treated with US alone (b); cells exposed to US and magnetic NPs (c). *represents P &lt; 0.05, **represents P &lt; 0.01, ***represents P &lt; 0.001Table 3Percentage of live MCF-10A and MDA-MB-231 cells in separate monolayers treated with US and magnetic NPs, averaged for five similar experimentsCell linePercentage of live control cells not treated with NPsPercentage of live cells treated with US alonePercentage of live cells treated with US and NPsMCF-10A81.4 ± 2.766.3 ± 4.853 ± 7.1MDA-MB-23182.6 ± 3.455.4 ± 5.134.8 ± 9.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The flow cytometry data for MCF-10A normal cells and MDA-MB-231 malignant cells are provided in Fig. 3A, C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The number of live cells in Q4 decreased after US exposure from (81.4 ± 2.7) % for control samples to (66.3 ± 4.8) % for MCF-10A cells (Fig. 3B, E; Table 3) and from (82.6 ± 3.4) % for control samples to (55.4 ± 5.1) % for MDA-MB-231 cells (Fig. 3D, E; Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Compared with cells treated with US only, the addition of magnetic NPs to the culture media immediately before US exposure resulted in a reduction in the percentage of live MCF-10A cells, from (66.3 ± 4.8) to (53 ± 7.1) % (Fig. 3B, E; Table 3), and a decrease in the number of live MDA-MB-231 cells, from (55.4 ± 5.1) to (34.8 ± 9.8) %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>These findings demonstrate that lung and breast cells exhibit similar sensitivity to US irradiation, as well as to combined treatment with US and gold or magnetic NPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy images of ultrasound treated breast cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>To analyze the type of cell damage caused by US in combination with NPs, TEM images of H-184B5F5/M10 normal breast cells and MDA-MB-231 breast carcinoma cells were obtained (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Images a–c show the normal breast cells, and images d–f show the cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Images a and d are controls (no ultrasound exposure); images b and e are cells treated with ultrasound but not NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Images c and f depict cells treated with the combination of ultrasound and magnetic NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 4, the membranes of the cancer cells showed a more uneven structure after US treatment (Fig. 4e), particularly after treatment with US with NPs (Fig. 4f), than the membranes of the corresponding normal cells (Fig. 4b, c, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>No nanoparticles were found inside the cells.Fig. 4TEM images of H-184B5F5/M10 normal breast cells (a–c) and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells (d–f) cells, where a and d are control samples; b and e correspond to cells treated with US; c and f show the cells after combined treatment with US and magnetic NPs </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Analysis of nanoparticle uptake by the cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To assess whether the enhanced cytotoxicity in lung and breast cancer cells is due to uptake of nanoparticles by cancer cells before US treatment, inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) analysis of NP uptake by four cell lines (the breast cell lines MDA-MB-231 and MCF-10A and the lung cell lines A549 and BEAS-2B) was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The results showed similar uptake of both NPs by all cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>However, the uptake of gold NPs was approximately 1 % of the amount initially added to cells by weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>There was a lack of cellular uptake of magnetic NPs by all cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The conditions of cell sample preparation for the ICP-MS analysis were similar to the experimental conditions for the US treatment of cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Gold and super-paramagnetic iron oxide NPs possess a unique combination of physical and chemical properties, allowing these NPs to act as highly multifunctional anti-cancer agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Gold NPs have been tested as drug carriers [8], photothermal contrast agents [5], and radio-sensitizers [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The location of gold NPs in the body can also be determined using photoacoustic imaging [10], or optical coherence tomography [11] in combination with X-ray imaging [12] or electron microscopy [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Magnetic iron oxide NPs have been used as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) contrast agents [14], for magnetic hyperthermia treatment of cancer [15], and as magnetic drug carriers [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The advantages of biocompatible gold and magnetic NPs are their low toxicity and their ability to be used as contrast agents for various diagnostic methods for visualizing tumor tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In addition to thermal effects [17], ultrasound radiation is known to produce mechanical pressure that results in acoustic streaming and cavitation within cellular systems [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Free cavitation bubbles are formed in liquid media when the local liquid pressure drops below the saturated vapor pressure during the rarefaction period of the propagated ultrasound wave. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The inertial cavitation process leads to the creation of shock waves, sonoluminescence and the formation of free radicals, which can irreversibly damage cells [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>It is known that the threshold of inertial cavitation can be reduced by adding nucleation agents and changing the host fluid parameters [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>NPs may act as a permanent source of nucleation sites for cavitating bubbles, leading to the enhancement of inertial cavitation in culture media. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The extracellular effect of NPs was demonstrated by ICP-MS analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Both lung and breast cell lines exhibited low cellular uptake of gold NPs and a lack of cellular uptake for magnetic NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>No visible magnetic nanoparticles were observed in breast cells based on TEM imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The fact that the most substantial cell damage was observed when NPs were added to the cell culture immediately before US treatment provides indirect evidence that the effects are due primarily to an extracellular effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Increasing the cell incubation time with NPs resulted in higher viability of the cells after US exposure (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>It is known that malignant and normal cells differ in their metabolism and morphology [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The resistances of cancer and normal cells to physical stress are known to be different [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This conclusion is consistent with our experimental results and may explain why under the tension/compression force of ultrasound, cancer cells were preferentially damaged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This experiment shows that US exposure causes some cell damage to both normal and cancer cell types, but the effect is greater for cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>This effect was demonstrated for A549 lung cancer cells in co-culture with their normal counterparts (BEAS-2B cells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The preferential destruction of cancer cell membranes was also observed in the TEM images of breast cells pre-incubated with magnetic NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>However, the exact mechanism underlying the selective damage to cancer cells requires further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Although we used two pairs of “malignant/normal” lung and breast cell lines, two different types of NPs (gold and magnetic) and two types of cell treatment (in separate and co-cultured monolayers), selective killing of cancer cells was observed throughout the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This finding may indicate that a combination of certain types of NPs with US fields could become a universal tool for cancer treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Recently, we tried to apply NAUT to xenograft mouse model and observed the similar effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Detailed will be published separately. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In this study, we added NPs to cell cultures to determine whether the addition specifically enhanced the killing of cancer cells with low-intensity ultrasound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that the addition of NPs indeed enhanced the killing of lung and breast cancer cells while largely sparing their normal counterparts in a co-culture system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Our discovery suggests that the power of US can be reduced relative to that used for HIFU ablation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>For the treatment of malignant tumors in vivo, a decrease in US power would be valuable because it would allow for the selective destruction of cancer cells while sparing nearby healthy tissues and would reduce the reflection of US waves from bones and other reflective structures in the body. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Nanoparticle characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Gold nanoparticles (10 nm) were obtained from BBI International (Ted Pella, Redding, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>A TEM image of gold nanoparticles is shown in Fig. 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Each individual nanoparticle can be clearly observed.Fig. 5TEM image of nanogold used in this experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Preparation of magnetic nanoparticles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A mixed solution of ferrous and ferric ions in a molar ratio of 1:2 was prepared by dissolving 1.13 mmol FeCl2 × 4H2O and 2.26 mmol FeCl3 × 6H2O in an 80 cm3 aqueous solution of poly(vinylalcohol) (PVA) at 80 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>PVA with an average molecular weight of 88,000 (Acros Organics) was used to obtain aqueous solutions at concentrations of up to 14 g dm−3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Magnetic iron oxide was precipitated by adding 0.5 mol dm−3 of NaOH to the above-mentioned mixture while heating to 80 °C and stirring with a magnetic stirrer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The mixture was subsequently incubated at 80 °C for 30 min and cooled to room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The synthesis was performed in an oxygen-free environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) was performed with a JEM-2100F (JEOL, Japan) instrument operating at an accelerating voltage of 75 kV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>To prepare samples for TEM, a drop of the suspension (0.12 mg mL−1) was placed on a copper grid and dried under ambient conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The typical size of the metal core of magnetic NPs was approximately 4–6 nm and was narrowly distributed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Dynamic light scattering </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>A DynaPro NanoStar light scattering spectrometer (Wyatt Technology, Taiwan) with an emission laser wavelength of 658 nm was used to measure the hydrodynamic diameter of the ferrofluid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>All of the measurements were performed at an angle of 90°. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The hydrodynamic size of magnetic NPs was estimated to be 140 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Magnetometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>A drop of magnetic NPs (80 μL) was deposited onto a small piece of cotton and dried at room temperature for 3 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The sample was inserted into a gelatin capsule and fixed inside to avoid any shifts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The saturation magnetization of the sample was measured with a superconducting quantum interference device (SQUID) magnetometer (Quantum Design, MPMS5) at room temperature (300 K) with a magnetic field of 7 T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The saturation magnetization was estimated to be 54.87 emu g−1 of iron mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The anhysteretic magnetization curve corresponded to the superparamagnetic properties of the NPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Human A549 lung alveolar adenocarcinoma and BEAS-2B immortalized human bronchial epithelial cells were obtained from ATCC® (Manassas, VA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The A549 cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) with 10 % fetal bovine serum (FBS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Defined Keratinocyte-SFM culture medium (KSFM; Gibco® Cell Culture, USA) was used for the BEAS-2B cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The cells were cultured separately in a monolayer fashion with concentrations of 5 × 105 cells mL−1 per well and in a co-culture (1:1) with a total concentration of 4 × 105 cells mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The detailed steps of the protocol are as follows.Step 1A549 and BEAS-2B were infected with lentivirus contain green and red fluorescent protein genes, respectively, and selected with neomycin (G418) at 800 μg per mL until fluorescent cells survived and grew to confluency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Green fluorescent protein (GFP) gene cDNA was constructed into a lentiviral packaging vector to become pLAS2w.GFP-C.Pneo, and red fluorescent protein (RFP) gene cDNA was constructed to become pLAS2w.RFP-C.Pneo.Step 2Each cell line was plated with 2.5 × 105 cells in the same well of a 12-well plate with 10 % FBS DMEM medium overnight at 37 °C in 5 % CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Every well contained approximately 5 × 105 cells before ultrasound treatment.Step 3Cells were washed twice with 1 mL PBS, and 1 mL 10 % FBS DMEM medium was added to ensure the volume before ultrasound treatment in each well in a 12-well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Fifty microliters of gold NP solution (BBI International Co.; 10 nm; Au stock concentration of 50 μg/mL) was added into the wells to achieve a final concentration of 2.5 μg/mL of Au NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In the other testing group, 50 μL of polyvinyl alcohol (PVA)-coated magnetic NPs (with a size of less than 7 nm) were prepared by chemical co-precipitation of Fe(II)/Fe(III) salts to reach a final iron concentration of 60 μg/mL in the cell suspension.Step 4Ultrasound treatment The Sonablate-500 (Focus Surgery Inc., USA) was chosen as the ultrasound source for cell irradiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The dual-element self-focusing transducer was used in therapy mode with a 4-MHz resonant frequency and a 4-cm focal length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The probe was placed in a water tank with 4.5 L of degassed water for cell irradiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Distilled water was obtained from a Millipore Q Synthesis A10 water purification system (resistivity = 18 MOhm cm−1, TOC = 3 ppb) and was degassed for 3 h using an on-line membrane vacuum degasser (ERC 3000 W/N, Endeavor Responsibility Challenge Co, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The oxygen concentration in the water was measured prior to the experiments using an oxygen (dissolved) CHEMets Kit (K-7512, CHEMetrics Inc., USA) and was estimated to be 2–3 ppm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The water temperature in the tank was maintained in the range of 24–25 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The ultrasound power was adjusted using the software for the Sonablate-500. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The shape of the ultrasound focal spot was a 3-mm-wide by 12-mm-high prolate spheroid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The transducer was operated in the scanning mode and irradiated 25 spots (5 × 5) in the 15 × 15-mm area under a well for 3 min 45 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Thus, the treated region had a 3D 15 × 15 × 12-mm rectangular shape and was centered under the well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the center of the focal spot (with the maximum ultrasound intensity) was fixed at a distance of 3 mm under the culture plate’s surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Each point of the plate surface was irradiated with US for 3 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The size and location of the treated zone was similar for each well in the culture plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The temperature of the culture medium in a well was measured after US treatment using a thermocouple, and the temperature change was found to be less than 0.1 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Thus, the average thermal effect during US treatment of cells was negligible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For US experiments, a power of 8 W was used, according to the read-out from the Sonablate-500 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>For the clinical treatment of prostate cancer, an US power of ~40 W is typically used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>A corresponding total of 5.8 W radiated acoustic power was measured for an 8-W reading from the Sonablate software with a radiation force balance unit (UPM-DT-100AV, Ohmic Instruments Co.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A calibrated needle hydrophone (HNA-0400, Onda, CA, USA) was used to estimate the spatial-average temporal-average intensity, ISATA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Co-culture and cell analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>For US-treated co-cultures of BEAS-2B and A549 cells, the numbers of attached cells were analyzed by optical microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The attached cells were washed with 1 mL of PBS, followed by washing with an additional 1 mL of PBS with 0.1 mL of 0.4 % trypan blue for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Phase-contrast images of the attached cell monolayers were obtained via optical microscopy (Olympus IX71, USA) at 200× magnification and a digital camera (Olympus DP70). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>A mercury lamp (U-LH100HG) was used to produce separate fluorescence images of the cells modified with green and red fluorescent proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Cells stained blue were counted as dead cells under high magnification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Transparent cells were counted as live cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The percentage of dead cells was determined by counting all the dead cells divided by the number of cells counted in a high-power field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Five fields were counted, with the means and standard deviations shown relative to those of the controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>To collect ultrasound-treated cells for flow cytometry analysis, the medium was removed and washed in 0.5 mL PBS; 0.5 mL trypsin was added to detach the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Cells were harvested with treated medium, separated by pipetting several times and premixed with 1 μg mL−1 of propidium iodide (Sigma Aldrich, USA) before flow cytometry analysis by a BD FACS Canto II system (BD Biosciences, USA) using a 488-nm laser for excitation and a PE channel for fluorescence detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The numbers of live cells (Q4) were measured for control and ultrasound-treated cells using BD FACS Diva software version 6.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) of cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy was used to obtain images of H-184B5F5/M10 healthy breast cells and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells using the following procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The controls and US-treated cells were collected and fixed in 2.5 % glutaraldehyde and 0.1 M cacodylate buffer for 2 h at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The cells were washed twice for 15 min in the cacodylate buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>A secondary fixation was performed in 1 % osmium tetroxide for 1 h at 4 °C, followed by two additional 15-min washes in the same buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>After dehydration, the material was embedded in Spurr’s resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The resin was first diluted in acetone (1:1) and incubated at 4 °C with agitation for 2 h and then diluted in acetone (1:3) and incubated at 4 °C with agitation for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The pellet was transferred to pure Spurr’s resin and incubated at 60 °C for 48 h until completely polymerized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Sections measuring 70–90 nm were obtained using a Leica EM UC 7 ultra-microtome (Leica Microsystems GmbH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The sections were then placed on copper grids and were studied under a TEM (TEM Hitachi H-7000, High-Technologies Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>ICP-MS analysis of NP uptake by cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Four cell lines (MDA-MB-231, MCF-10A, A549, and BEAS-2B) were seeded in 12-well plates (5 × 105 cells per well) in different culture media and maintained in a humidified incubator for 24 h at 37 °C and 5 % CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells were cultured with Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10 % fetal calf serum (FCS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>MCF-10A normal breast cells were grown in DMEM/Ham’s F-12 with 5 % FBS, 10 μg mL−1 insulin, 5 μg mL−1 hydrocortisone, 20 ng mL−1 EGF and 100 ng mL−1 cholera toxin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A549 lung cancer cells were grown in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10 % FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>BEAS-2B normal lung cells were cultured in BEGM medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The culture medium was replaced with 1 mL of serum-free DMEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Gold or magnetic NPs were added to the cell suspensions at the same concentrations used for the ultrasound experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The cell cultures were incubated with NPs for 30 min at 37 °C with 5 % CO2 and washed three times with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS); 1 mL of concentrated HCl was added to every well, and the mixture was heated to 70 °C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Then, samples were dissolved 10 times in double-distilled water and analyzed using ICP-MS (Thermo Scientific XSERIES 2) to determine the amount of gold and iron in the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>NAUT</term><def><p>nanoparticle-assisted ultrasound therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HIFU</term><def><p>high-intensity focused ultrasound</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NPs</term><def><p>nanoparticles</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>US</term><def><p>ultrasound</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICP-MS</term><def><p>inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p>magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PVA</term><def><p>polyvinyl alcohol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEM</term><def><p>transmission electron microscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SQUID</term><def><p>superconducting quantum interference device magnetometer</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>NGC formulated the major idea of the experiments and performed initial experiments; CHC and MH organized and planned the project; OKK and TCL performed all experiments and wrote draft of the manuscript. OKK and TCL contributed equally to this work. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Financial support for this work from the Genomics Research Center, Academia Sinica, Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (Grant No. MOST 102-2113-M-001-002-MY5; 103-2923-M-001-004-MY3), and the National Health Research Institutes (Grant No. NHRI-EX103-10301EI) of Taiwan, R.O.C., is gratefully acknowledged. NGC would like to acknowledge financial support from the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (MOST 102-2221-E-009-118).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>1.LivraghiTSolbiatiLMeloniMFGazelleGSHalpernEFGoldbergSNTreatment of focal liver tumors with percutaneous radio-frequency ablation: complications encountered in a multicenter studyRadiology200322644145110.1148/radiol.226201219812563138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>2.FingarVHKikPKHaydonPSCerritoPBTsengMAbangEAnalysis of acute vascular damage after photodynamic therapy using benzoporphyrin derivative (BPD)Br J Cancer1999791702170810.1038/sj.bjc.669027110206280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>3.HarrisonLBlackwellKHypoxia and anemia: factors in decreased sensitivity to radiation therapy and chemotherapy?Oncologist20049314010.1634/theoncologist.9-90005-3115591420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>4.SetroikromoRWierengaPKvan WaardeMABrunstingJFVellengaEKampingaHHHeat shock proteins and Bcl-2 expression and function in relation to the differential hyperthermic sensitivity between leukemic and normal hematopoietic cellsCell Stress Chaperones20071232033010.1379/CSC-279.118229451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>5.HuangXJainPKEl-SayedIHEl-SayedMAPlasmonic photothermal therapy (PPTT) using gold nanoparticlesLasers Med Sci20082321722810.1007/s10103-007-0470-x17674122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>6.JohannsenMThiesenBWustPJordanAMagnetic nanoparticle hyperthermia for prostate cancerInt Hyperthermia20102679079510.3109/02656731003745740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>7.DubinskyTJCuevasCDigheMKKolokythasOHwangJHHigh-intensity focused ultrasound: current potential and oncologic applicationsAJR Am J Roentgenol200819019119910.2214/AJR.07.267118094311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>8.PaciottiGFMyerLWeinreichDGoiaDPavelNMcLaughlinREColloidal gold: a novel nanoparticle vector for tumor directed drug deliveryDrug Deliv20041116918310.1080/1071754049043389515204636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>9.Raoof M, Curley SA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Non-invasive radiofrequency-induced targeted hyperthermia for the treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Int J Hepatol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>2011. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>6 Article ID 676957. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>10.MallidiSLukeGPEmelianovSPhotoacoustic imaging in cancer detection, diagnosis, and treatment guidanceTrends Biotechnol20112921322110.1016/j.tibtech.2011.01.00621324541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>11.KimCSWilder-SmithPAhnYCLiawLHLChenZKwonYJEnhanced detection of early-stage oral cancer in vivo by optical coherence tomography using multimodal delivery of gold nanoparticlesJ Biomed200914034008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>12.RandDOrtizVLiuYDerdakZWandsJRTaticekMNanomaterials for x-ray imaging: gold nanoparticle enhancement of x-ray scatter imaging of hepatocellular carcinomaNano Lett2011112678268310.1021/nl200858y21644516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>13.HeckelKKiefmannRDorgerMStoeckelhuberMGoetzAEColloidal gold particles as a new in vivo marker of early acute lung injuryAm J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol2004287L867L87810.1152/ajplung.00078.200415194564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>14.SosnovikDENahrendorfMWeisslederRMagnetic nanoparticles for MR imaging: agents, techniques and cardiovascular applicationsBasic Res Cardiol200810312213010.1007/s00395-008-0710-718324368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>15.LaurentSDutzSHäfeliUOMahmoudiMMagnetic fluid hyperthermia: focus on superparamagnetic iron oxide nanoparticlesAdv Colloid Interface Sci201116682310.1016/j.cis.2011.04.00321601820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>16.KumarAJenaPKBeheraSLockeyRFMohapatraSMultifunctional magnetic nanoparticles for targeted deliveryNanomed Nanotech Biol Med20106646910.1016/j.nano.2009.04.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>17.AshtonDFDraperDOMyrerJWTemperature rise in human muscle during ultrasound treatments using flex-all as a coupling agentJ Athl Train19983313614016558500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>18.MartinJPrattBMWatmoughDJA study of ultrasound-induced microstreaming in blood vessels of tropical fishBr J Cancer198245161164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>19.NyborgWLUltrasonic microstreaming and related phenomenaBr J Cancer198245156160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>20.RieszPKondoTFree radical formation induced by ultrasound and its biological implicationsFree Radical Bio Med19921324727010.1016/0891-5849(92)90021-81324205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>21.DengCXXuQApfelREHollandCKInertial cavitation produced by pulsed ultrasound in controlled host mediaJ Acoust Soc Am19961001199120810.1121/1.4163048759969 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>22.HollandCKApfelREThresholds for transient cavitation produced by pulsed ultrasound in a controlled nuclei environmentJ Acoust Soc Am1990882059206910.1121/1.4001022269722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>23.ErtelAVergheseAByersSWOchsMTozerenAPathway-specific differences between tumor cell lines and normal and tumor tissue cellsMol Cancer200655510.1186/1476-4598-5-5517081305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>24.CrossSEJinYSRaoJGimzewskiJNanomechanical analysis of cells from cancer patientsNat Nanotechnol2007278078310.1038/nnano.2007.38818654431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
