<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dnares</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">dnares</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DNA Research: An International Journal for Rapid Publication of Reports on Genes and Genomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1340-2838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1663</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4263299</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsu028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dsu028</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Full Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Optimized Whole-Genome Amplification Strategy for Extremely AT-Biased Template </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oyola</surname><given-names>Samuel O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manske</surname><given-names>Magnus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campino</surname><given-names>Susana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Claessens</surname><given-names>Antoine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>William L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kekre</surname><given-names>Mihir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drury</surname><given-names>Eleanor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>Alistair</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MacInnis</surname><given-names>Bronwyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>Dominic P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Hinxton</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>MRC Centre for Genomics and Global Health</addr-line>, <institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 7BN</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</addr-line>, <institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 7BN</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Weatherall Institute of Molecular Medicine</addr-line>, <institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 9DS</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel. +44 1223-494-994. Fax. +44 1223-494-919. Email: <email>so1@sanger.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="fn1"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by Dr Yuji Kohara </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="dsu028.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Pathogen genome sequencing directly from clinical samples is quickly gaining importance in genetic and medical research studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, low DNA yield from blood-borne pathogens is often a limiting factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The problem worsens in extremely base-biased genomes such as the AT-rich Plasmodium falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We present a strategy for whole-genome amplification (WGA) of low-yield samples from P. falciparum prior to short-read sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We have developed WGA conditions that incorporate tetramethylammonium chloride for improved amplification and coverage of AT-rich regions of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We show that this method reduces amplification bias and chimera formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Our data show that this method is suitable for as low as 10 pg input DNA, and offers the possibility of sequencing the parasite genome from small blood samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>whole-genome amplification</kwd><kwd>AT-rich</kwd><kwd>malaria</kwd><kwd>tetramethylammonium chloride</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Timely detection of emerging genetic variants and other evolutionary features associated with important clinical phenotypes such as increased virulence and drug resistance are central to malaria control strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing of parasite populations has been identified as an effective tool for detecting genetic changes.1,2 Despite the current success in the sequencing technology, there remain significant challenges in achieving global genetic surveillance of parasite populations in the field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Most genome-scale analyses, such as whole-genome sequencing, require large amounts of clean genetic material that is often difficult to obtain,3 and therefore a serious impediment to genetic analysis on many clinical samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>A large number of valuable clinical specimens are collected in the form of small samples that yield low quantity and quality of genetic material.4–7 A common method for collecting clinical samples in the field is through heel/finger-pricks.5,7–10 However, the quantity and quality of parasite genetic material that can be extracted from these small blood samples usually fall below the threshold required by genome sequencing platforms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>To alleviate the problem of low DNA quantities, whole-genome amplification (WGA) is now routinely applied in many applications,3,11 but has yet to be optimized for use in genomes of extreme base composition such as Plasmodium falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Two major forms of WGA have been described: multiple displacement amplification (MDA)12,13 and PCR-based amplification methods.14,15 MDA has been the method of choice for a wider range of genome amplification studies, because it produces longer DNA products with extensive genome coverage.16 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>MDA is based on φ29 polymerase, which, in the presence of random hexamers annealed to denatured DNA, uses an MDA mechanism to synthesize high-molecular-weight DNA from very minute amounts of input material under isothermal conditions.17,18 The best results, however, have been obtained from genomes with relatively balanced base composition.11,19,20 Amplification of genomes with imbalanced base composition, such as the AT-rich P. falciparum, has remained a challenge.21,22 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In this study, we sought to identify and optimize a WGA system suitable for an AT-base-biased genome of P. falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Using standard conditions as outlined for each system, we tested the efficiency of non-MDA- and MDA-based methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Initial findings showed that MDA-based systems produced a more uniform genome coverage than non-MDA methods (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>We have optimized an identified MDA system to produce an improved genome coverage and a reduced base-bias with more accurate genome representation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>We show that our optimized WGA conditions are suitable for as low as 10 picograms (pg) P. falciparum input DNA, producing high-sequence concordance with unamplified genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This development promises a significant tool to aid implementation of the global genetic surveillance of parasite populations through small blood sample sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>DNA samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA was a gift from Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Chris Newbold (University of Oxford). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The clinical isolates were obtained from the Malaria Genetics Group's Sequencing Sample Repository at the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Other genomic DNA was extracted from 17 progeny clones of P. falciparum strains derived from genetic cross between 7G8xGB423 and a 3D7 strain (3D7_glasgow). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome amplification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>All non-MDA WGA were performed following individual kit manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>MDA-based WGA was performed using either REPLI-g Mini kit (Qiagen) or Genomiphi kit (GE Healthcare). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>For Genomiphi, the kit manufacturer's instructions were followed without modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>For the REPLI-g Mini kit, manufacturer's instructions were followed during preliminary tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The following modifications were performed in developing optimized conditions for the REPLI-g Mini kit: nuclease-free water and all tubes were UV-treated before use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>WGA reactions were performed in 0.2 ml PCR tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Buffer D1 stock solution (Qiagen) was reconstituted by adding 500 µl of nuclease-free water, and a working solution was prepared by mixing the stock solution and nuclease-free water in the ratio of 1 : 3.5, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Unmodified Buffer N1 was reconstituted by mixing Stop solution (Qiagen) and nuclease-free water in the ratio of 1 : 5.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Modified buffer N1 was prepared by including tetramethylammonium chloride (TMAC) at a concentration of 300 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To denature DNA templates, 5 µl of the DNA solution was mixed with 5 µl of buffer D1 (working solution prepared as described above). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The mixture was vortexed and centrifuged briefly before incubating at room temperature for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Denatured DNA was neutralized by adding 10 µl of either unmodified or modified buffer N1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Neutralized DNA was mixed by vortexing and centrifuged briefly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>To amplify the DNA template, denatured and neutralized sample was mixed with 29 µl of REPLI-g Mini Reaction Buffer and 1 µl of REPLI-g Mini DNA polymerase to obtain a final reaction volume of 50 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The reaction mixture was incubated at 30°C for 16 h using an MJ Research PTC-225 thermal cycling system (GMI, Inc., USA) with the heating lid set to track at +5°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Amplified DNA was cleaned using Agencourt Ampure XP beads (Beckman Coulter) using sample to beads ratio of 1 : 1 and eluted with 50 µl of EB (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Illumina library preparation and sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>All sequencing libraries were prepared as PCR-free. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome amplified or unamplified genomic DNA (1.5 μg in 75 µl of TE buffer) was sheared using a Covaris S2 (Covaris, Inc., Woburn, MA, USA) to obtain a fragment-size distribution of ∼300 to ∼600 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The sheared DNA fragments were end-repaired and A-tailed using the NEBNext DNA sample preparation kit (NEB), following an Illumina sample preparation protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Pre-annealed paired-end Illumina PCR-free adapters were ligated to the A-tailed fragments in a 50-µl reaction containing 10 µl of DNA sample, 1× Quick T4 DNA ligase buffer, 10 µl of PCR-free PE-adapter mixture, 5 µl of Quick T4 DNA ligase (NEB) and incubated at 20°C for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The ligation reaction was cleaned twice using Agencourt Ampure XP beads (Beckman Coulter). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Cleaned DNA was eluted with 20 µl of buffer EB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Aliquots were analysed using an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies) to determine the size distribution and to check for adapter contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Samples were sequenced using either Illumina Hiseq 2500 or Miseq technologies (San Diego, CA, USA) with 75 bp read length and the paired-end read options. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Corresponding WGA and non-WGA samples were run in the same lanes, using different multiplex tags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This strategy reduces potential confounding artefacts relating to sequencing chemistry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Read mapping and genotype concordance analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Reads were mapped against the P. falciparum reference sequence (http://plasmodb.org/common/downloads/release-10.0/Pfalciparum3D7/fasta/data/), using BWA (V0.6.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We analysed the genotype calls from 17 samples derived from the progeny clones of genetic crosses of 7G8xGB4 laboratory strains,23 including one parent reference strain 3D7 as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>For genotype concordance analysis, we generated de novo variation calls using samtools (V0.1.1.19) mpileup and bfctools (V0.1.17), calling on both WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>For in silico genotyping, we used a list of 20 737 high-quality single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) positions and alleles generated from the sequence of genetic crosses (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We performed in silico genotyping of both the WGA and non-WGA samples using samtools mpileup and counting alleles present in at least five reads. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><label>3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>WGA using standard methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We performed tests on various WGA systems to identify those suitable for AT-rich P. falciparum genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We compared non-MDA—Endcore-Rapid (NuGen), MALBAC (Yikon Genomics), Rapisome (Biohelix) and MDA—Repli_g (Qiagen) and Genomiphi (GE Healthcare) systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Our preliminary data (not shown) indicated that non-MDA methods were less tolerant to the AT-biased genome compared with their MDA counterparts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>With non-MDA amplification, we observed excess bias towards regions with high GC content and poor coverage of high AT regions of the genome resulting into high levels of allele dropout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Further optimization focused on the MDA systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Repli_g and Genomiphi are the most commonly used methods for MDA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Although both kits have shown similar results in many systems,24,25 the majority of studies have been with genomes of relatively balanced base composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Here, we have assessed the performance of Repli_g and Genomiphi by amplifying an AT-rich P. falciparum genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Amplification of pure P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA by both kits produced very similar results as assessed by genome coverage analysis metrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>However, amplification of host-contaminated clinical samples produced dissimilar results in terms of base composition and overall genome coverage (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Whereas amplification products generated by both Repli_g and Genomiphi did not maintain the exact original host/parasite DNA proportions, Genomiphi products were more biased towards the host DNA (Fig. 1), an observation suggesting bias towards templates of neutral base composition originating from the host genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Based on the level of bias, we chose to optimize Repli_g for amplification of the P. falciparum genome. Figure 1.Lorenz curves of genome coverage analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cumulative fraction of sequence reads against cumulative fraction of genome covered is shown for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The diagonal line represents an ideal perfect uniform coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The further the sample curves deviate from the diagonal line the more bias in genome coverage they are. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Repli_g (solid lines) and Genomiphi (dashed lines) sample pairs were normalized to equal number of reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Repli_g and Genomiphi amplification of P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA (3D7) resulted in identical coverage uniformity as shown in overlapping solid red (Repli_g_3D7) and dashed red (Genomiphi_3D7) curves, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Amplification of clinical samples with varied proportions of human DNA contaminations produced different uniformity of coverage with Genomiphi (dashed lines) showing slightly more bias than their corresponding Repli_g (solid lines) amplified samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>3D7, pure P. falciparum genomic DNA; PK76, clinical sample with 53% host DNA contamination amplified with either Genomiphi (Genomiphi_PK76) or Repli_g (Regpli_g_PK76); PD21, a clinical sample with 7% host contamination amplified with either Genomiphi (Genomiphi_PD21) or Repli_g (Regpli_g_PD21); PK67, a clinical sample with 19% host contamination amplified with either Genomiphi (Genomiphi_PK67) or Repli_g (Regpli_g_PK67). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Optimized WGA conditions reduce amplification bias and improve coverage on low complexity regions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Non-coding regions of P. falciparum DNA contain ∼90% A+T base composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Amplification of AT-rich genomes is a challenge to almost all commercially available polymerases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We have previously shown that addition of TMAC improves coverage of low GC regions of the genome during PCR,22 but the same has not been tested with φ29, the MDA polymerase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of TMAC on MDA, we amplified P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA of varied input amounts (0.1–2 ng) both in the presence and absence of TMAC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We compared the quantity and quality of both products and observed that, like many commercial PCR polymerases, φ29 is inhibited by TMAC at certain levels of concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We have determined 60 mM as a concentration that is non-inhibitory to the polymerase and optimal for WGA of an AT-biased genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Although the quantity of the amplification product was higher in the absence (standard procedure) than in the presence of 60 mM TMAC (data not shown), the quality of MDA product, in terms of coverage and base composition, was improved in the optimized procedure where TMAC was added (Figs 2 and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 2, amplification using a standard protocol (Std) resulted in excessive bias in regions of low complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Inspection of the over-amplified regions reveals sequences of low complexity and numerous repeat patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>We used a tandem repeat finder programme26 and revealed numerous sequences in tandem repeat conformation that may have affected amplification bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The top three tandem repeats are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Unlike the standard WGA protocol, our optimized amplification procedure abolished excessive amplification bias and produced a more uniform coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The mechanism by which this bias is corrected is not clear, but it is conceivable that TMAC stabilizes and stiffens the DNA backbone, thereby minimizing cis-priming by the looping of displaced DNA strands during amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>We also show that base composition bias increased with a decrease in the amount of input DNA during amplification with standard protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This bias was not observed in samples amplified with the optimized (Opt) conditions (Fig. 3). Figure 2.LookSeq analysis of coverage uniformity. Plasmodium falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA amplified with Repli_g following standard or optimized procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>gDNA (top panel) shows bulk genomic DNA sequenced without amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>All samples amplified using the standard (Std WGA) procedure show regions of amplification bias (marked by *1 and *2, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>), whereas their corresponding counterparts amplified following the optimized procedure (Optimized WGA) show less bias and relatively uniform coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Different amounts of input DNA were used for each sample set (Sample 1, 0.1 ng; Sample 2, 0.5 ng; Sample 3, 1 ng). Figure 3.GC content analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Different amounts of P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA (ranging from 0.1 to 2 ng as shown in sample names) were used as an input template for amplification by Repli_g following the standard or optimized procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Amplification products were sequenced as PCR-free and reads obtained were analysed for G+C content profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A non-WGA sample (gDNA) shows a GC content of ∼19.4%, a profile that was closely matched by products amplified using the optimized procedure (Opt). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Samples amplified following the standard procedure (Std) showed biased GC content shown as a shift towards the neutral base composition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Optimized conditions reduce chimera formation and maintain template base composition during MDA by φ29 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Formation of chimeric reads is a major problem with MDA technology.27 Chimeras cause serious mapping and assembly problems, and therefore reduce the quality and quantity of the WGA product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We analysed the formation of chimeras by comparing WGA products following standard and optimized procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The number of chimeric reads increased as the amount of input DNA was reduced (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>However, optimizing WGA condition by including TMAC additive decreased the formation of chimeras and improved the quality of reads in P. falciparum WGA. Figure 4.Bar graph of chimeric read analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Different amounts of P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA (ranging from 2 ng to 100 fg as shown in sample labels) were used as an input template for amplification by Repli_g following the standard or optimized procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Amplification products were sequenced as PCR-free, and reads obtained were normalized and analysed for the presence of chimeric reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>A non-WGA sample (control) showed the least number of chimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Using the standard procedure, the number of chimers increased with a decrease in the amount of input DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Samples amplified using the optimized procedure showed a decrease in chimer formation that remained low and steady from 2 ng to 100 pg of input DNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><label>3.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>WGA from 10 pg of input P. falciparum genomic DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Most studies with φ29 MDA have used an input DNA of ≥10 ng for WGA.19,20 In many cases, this amount may be difficult to obtain from valuable clinical specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>We set to find out the minimal amount of parasite DNA that can be successfully amplified by the optimized conditions to obtain uniform genome coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>We performed WGA on P. falciparum genomic DNA with an input amount ranging from 2 ng down to 100 femtograms (fg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>WGA products were multiplexed and sequenced using Illumina MiSeq or HiSeq 2500 machines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Sequence reads generated were analysed to determine the minimum threshold required to produce optimal coverage suitable for various whole-genome studies including genotyping by SNP analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To assess the quality of the sequence data generated from each input amount, reads were mapped to the reference genome using BWA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>CallableLoci program of the genome analyser tool kit (GATK)28 was used to inspect and count the proportion of the genome with high-quality base coverage (callable bases), positions of the genome with zero coverage (uncovered bases) and the size of coverage gaps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Using these metrics, we show that the number of callable loci (high-quality bases) remained relatively high for samples with input DNA ranging from 2 ng to 10 pg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, the quality of sequence data dropped sharply for samples with input DNA &lt;10 pg (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>A similar trend was observed with the proportion of gap sizes (length of uncovered bases, Fig. 5 bottom panel) and chimeric reads (Fig. 4), where a sharp increase in these values was observed for samples with input DNA &lt;10 pg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>From these observations, we concluded that 10 pg is the minimal amount of P. falciparum input DNA that produces quality genome coverage under the optimized MDA conditions described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>This amount of DNA is equivalent to only ∼380 parasite genomes. Figure 5.Determining the lowest threshold of input DNA mass for WGA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Different amounts of P. falciparum 3D7 genomic DNA (ranging from 2 ng to 100 fg, as shown in sample names) were used as an input template for amplification by Repli_g following the standard or optimized procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Samples were multiplexed and sequenced using a fast turn-around Illumina Miseq machine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Sequence reads mapped to the reference were normalized and analysed for coverage and base quality using the ‘CallableLoci’ program of GATK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>A non-WGA sample was used as an unamplified control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Input quantities ranging from 2 ng down to 10 pg produced reads with high-quality ‘callable’ bases covering over 60% of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Input DNA below the10-pg threshold produced poor base quality with only &lt;30% of genome covered with ‘callable’ bases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Input DNA &lt;10 pg showed a sharp increase in positions with zero coverage (bases uncovered) and an increase in gap sizes in genome coverage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><label>3.5.</label><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Detailed analysis of WGA products from a 10-pg input template DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Standard WGA methods produce products that show sequence representation bias, allelic dropout and amplification artefacts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These problems tend to increase as the amount of input template decreases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>To adequately evaluate the quality of the WGA products produced from an input of 10 pg—1,000-fold smaller than the standard input amounts—we performed analysis on genomic DNA extracted from P. falciparum strains derived from the progeny clones of genetic cross between 7G8xGB4 laboratory strains, as well as the 3D7 Strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA extracted from 17 progeny clones was sequenced both as WGA and as bulk genomic DNA (non-WGA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We performed detailed analysis by comparing sequence data generated from WGA and their matching unamplified genomic DNA (non-WGA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>WGA and non-WGA samples yielded a median of 3.5 and 3.4 billion base sequences, respectively, with 94.8 and 95.3% of the read mapping to the reference sequence (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>WGA samples showed coverage between 180× and 500×, whereas non-WGA samples showed coverage between 90× and 250×. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>A median of 1.5 and 1.2% of genome bases was not covered in WGA and non-WGA samples, respectively (Table 1). Table 1.Sequence coverage and mapping analysisSampleTotal reads (million)Total base (Gb)Mapped reads (%)Uncovered bases (%)WGANon-WGAWGANon-WGAWGA/non-WGAWGANon-WGAWGANon-WGA3D7_Glasgow30.843.52.33.30.798.898.60.20.0DEV_18_05_1174.550.75.63.81.594.695.01.11.2D2_18_05_1141.741.43.13.11.094.295.21.21.0WE269.735.25.22.62.095.195.11.21.3GB4_NIH45.237.93.42.81.294.294.51.31.1JC345.147.63.43.60.994.395.11.31.1JF649.157.33.74.30.994.395.51.41.1QF546.566.63.55.00.795.295.91.41.2NIC_18_05_1159.136.94.42.81.695.590.61.51.3NF1048.435.03.62.61.495.595.01.51.4XF12_18_05_1139.258.62.94.40.794.795.61.51.2AL2_13_05_1138.340.12.93.01.094.895.41.51.3XD846.945.03.53.41.093.695.51.61.27G8_NIH61.140.54.63.01.594.294.91.61.5JON51.371.83.85.40.794.095.41.61.1TF157.765.24.34.90.995.595.71.81.4JC934.061.32.54.60.695.095.62.51.2Median46.945.03.53.41.094.795.41.51.2Mean ± SD49.3 ± 1249.1 ± 123.7 ± 0.93.7 ± 0.91.0 ± 0.494.9 ± 1.295.2 ± 1.51.4 ± 0.41.1 ± 0.3Sequence reads obtained from WGA and non-WGA samples were analysed for coverage and mapping statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Nearly identical average number of sequence reads, mapping and coverage statistics were obtained for both WGA and non-WGA datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, coverage distribution was less uniform in WGA compared with non-WGA datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><label>3.6.</label><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Genotype concordance analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the fidelity of sequence representation by WGA, we analysed the genotype calls from 17 cross samples and the parent reference strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>We performed de novo and in silico genotype calls on sequence generated from both the WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Genotype concordance was determined by comparing SNP and InDel calls from matched pairs of both non-WGA and WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3f1"><label>3.6.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Concordance of de novo SNPs and InDel calls </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>For each pair of WGA and non-WGA sample, we generated de novo variation calls simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A median of 20,338 biallelic de novo SNPs with a quality score of ≥250 were called for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For the 3D7 reference strain (3D7_Glasgow), only 185 de novo SNPs were called (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Both of these numbers are well within the expected range for this method.1 As given in Table 2, call pairs were grouped into ‘Perfect Concordance’, ‘WGA New Alleles’ and ‘Undetermined’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Identical calls in both non-WGA and WGA samples had a median of 97.3% and a mean of 96.7% ± 1.2 that are in perfect concordance, and new alleles present only in the WGA samples (considered as WGA-introduced alleles) had a median of 1.2% and a mean of 1.8 ± 1.1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Most of the WGA-introduced alleles were due to a mixed call in WGA, where the non-WGA counterpart only showed the reference allele. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Discordant single-allele calls were extremely rare with a median of zero SNPs and a total of 10 occurrences across all the samples (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2a</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Additionally, de novo SNP calls in 5,075,789 well-covered coding positions (Table 2) produced perfect concordance with a median of 98.5% and a mean of 98.0 ± 1.4%, while the occurrence of WGA-introduced alleles dropped to a median of 0.7% and a mean of 0.8 ± 0.4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In this subset, no discordant calls (alt/ref or ref/alt) were observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2b</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Calls that were grouped as ‘Undetermined’ represent alleles that were missing or wrong alleles (present in the non-WGA samples but are neither the reference nor the alternative allele). Table 2.WGA and non-WGA SNP concordance analysisSampleDe novo SNP calls in all regionsDe novo SNP calls in good quality regionsPerfect concordance (%)WGA new allele (%)Undetermined (%)Perfect concordance (%)WGA new allele (%)Undetermined (%)JON93.84.41.897.21.61.2JF694.44.31.394.25.00.8D2_18_05_1195.02.62.496.92.20.9QF595.72.51.899.00.50.5QF596.32.61.198.50.80.7JC996.51.61.998.21.30.5XF12_18_05_1197.31.41.498.40.31.2NIC_18_05_1197.30.82.095.62.42.0NF1097.31.51.398.70.50.7DEV_18_05_1197.31.11.698.90.50.5JC397.41.11.698.60.60.8GB4_NIH97.41.11.598.50.50.9AL2_13_05_1197.41.21.499.00.60.5WE297.51.01.697.91.60.57G8_NIH97.51.11.497.12.40.5TF197.61.01.398.80.50.73D7_Glasgow97.81.11.1100.00.00.0Median97.31.21.598.50.60.7Mean ± SD96.7 ± 1.21.8 ± 1.11.6 ± 0.398.0 ± 1.41.3 ± 1.20.8 ± 0.4WGA and non-WGA data were analysed for de novo SNP calling concordance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Matching sequence data from cross samples were paired and the SNP calling was performed simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Concordance rates were generated by comparing WGA and related non-WGA calls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Columns on the left show comparison of all calls covering the entire genome, whereas columns on the right show a subset of all calls covering only the high-quality coding regions of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Values in the perfect concordance columns represent the proportion of calls that were identical in both WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>WGA new allele columns show the proportion of SNPs that were present only in the WGA and not in their matching non-WGA alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Undetermined column shows the proportion of SNPs that were called in wrong or missing alleles (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2)</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>As with SNPs, we also performed biallelic de novo InDel calls with a quality score of ≥250 for both WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>As given in Table 3, InDel calls from the whole genome with perfect concordance between WGA and non-WGA samples had a median of 97.6% and a mean of 96.8 ± 1.7%, and WGA-introduced InDels had a median of 1.5% and a mean of 2.4 ± 1.8%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Similarly, de novo InDel calls in the coding regions only produced near-perfect concordance with a median of 98.7% and a mean of 98.2 ± 1.4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>WGA-introduced InDels in these regions dropped to a median of 0.4% and a mean of 1.4 ± 1.3%. Table 3.WGA and non-WGA InDel concordance analysisSampleDe novo InDel calls in whole genomeDe novo InDel calls in good quality regionsPerfect concordance (%)WGA New InDels (%)UndeterminedPerfect concordance (%)WGA New InDels (%)Undetermined (%)3D7_Glasgow95.24.80.0100.00.00.0JC397.61.50.998.80.80.4QF597.22.10.696.13.60.3JF691.57.80.796.53.40.2TF198.21.20.599.40.50.1DEV_18_05_1198.11.00.899.20.30.57G8_NIH97.91.20.898.70.60.8GB4_NIH97.91.20.998.60.70.7WE298.01.10.999.00.70.3D2_18_05_1195.82.51.797.11.61.3NIC_18_05_1197.81.01.299.10.30.6NF1097.41.80.898.31.10.6XF12_18_05_1198.01.40.699.00.60.4AL2_13_05_1197.71.50.899.30.30.3XD895.53.90.795.73.60.7JON95.24.20.696.13.70.3JC996.42.90.798.41.50.1Median97.61.50.898.70.70.4Mean ± SD96.8 ± 1.72.4 ± 1.80.8 ± 0.398.2 ± 1.41.4 ± 1.30.4 ± 0.3WGA and non-WGA data were analysed for de novo InDel calling concordance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Calls were performed simultaneously on both WGA and related non-WGA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Columns on the left show comparison of all calls covering the entire genome, whereas columns on the right show a subset of all calls covering only the high-quality coding regions of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Values in the perfect concordance columns represent the proportion of calls that were identical in both WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>WGA new allele columns show the proportion of InDels that were present only in the WGA and not in their matching non-WGA alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Undetermined column shows the proportion of InDels that were called in wrong or missing alleles (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3)</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f2"><label>3.6.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Concordance of in silico genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Using a list of high-quality SNP positions and alleles from the genetic crosses, we performed in silico genotyping of both the WGA and non-WGA samples on 20,737 positions, counting alleles present in at least five reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Call comparisons between the WGA and non-WGA from same samples were grouped into ‘Perfect Concordance (identical)’, ‘WGA Missing Alleles’, ‘WGA New Alleles’ and ‘Undetermined’ (missing allele). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Identical alleles with perfect concordance between WGA and non-WGA samples had a median of 97.95% (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>A median of 0.48% calls represent alleles that were called in the WGA, but not in the non-WGA, samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>These reflect cases where the WGA sample had a mixed call and the non-WGA sample had a single-allele call. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>A median of 0.94% represent alleles that were missing in WGA, but were called in non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Discordant single-allele calls were extremely rare, with a median of zero and a mean of 2.9 SNPs per sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Four of the 17 samples showed such discordant calls, and only three samples had more than one such call. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The 3D7 (3D7_Glasgow) reference sample showed 99.58% identical calls, and only one new allele in WGA sample was returned as a mixed call (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). Figure 6.Boxplot of in silico genotyping concordance analysing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>A total of 20,737 high-quality SNP positions were genotyped in both WGA and non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Call comparison was performed between matched pairs of corresponding WGA and non-WGA datasets and results were grouped into ‘Perfect Concordance’, ‘WGA Missing Alleles’, ‘WGA New Alleles’ and ‘Undetermined’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Perfect_Concordance (identical alleles) had a median of 97.95% (range 83.11–99.58%; n = 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A median of 0.48% calls represent alleles that were called in the WGA samples, but not in the non-WGA samples (WGA_New_Alleles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>A median of 0.94% calls were present in non-WGA, but absent in WGA, samples (WGA_Missing_Alleles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The proportion of calls that were missing (Undetermined) had a median of 0.96% (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4)</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><label>4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>High-throughput DNA sequencing technologies have gained a wide range of applications in infectious disease research, including global surveillance of the emergence and spread of drug resistance, detection of regions of the genome under selection and identification of genetic determinants of clinical phenotypes through genome-wide association studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The P. falciparum genome presents inherent technical challenges to next-generation DNA sequencing, such as its extreme AT-richness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome sequencing of P. falciparum field isolates poses additional difficulties due to the small quantity of DNA often retrieved from patients in the clinical setting and the high degree of host DNA contamination from leucocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This study addressed the first of these key problems by developing a method for WGA capable of producing high-quality sequence data from just 10 pg of input P. falciparum DNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Although PCR-based WGA techniques, such as primer extension PCR, ligation-mediated PCR and degenerate oligonucleotide-primed PCR, have been successfully used in some studies such as single-cell amplification,29 their wider application has been limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>PCR-based WGA methods produce relatively shorter products, non-specific amplification artefacts and incomplete genome coverage.19,20,30 MDA has been associated with base-bias and generation of chimeric products.29 Nonetheless, MDA has been the method of choice for a wider range of genome amplification studies, because it produces longer DNA products with extensive genome coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>MDA also produces higher DNA yields with relatively less amplification bias.3,11,19 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Here, we have assessed MDA on an AT-rich genome using a range of input DNA quantities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We describe an optimized WGA method incorporating TMAC reagent that improves amplification coverage of the difficult AT-rich loci of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We establish 10 pg of input DNA as the lowest threshold from which our optimized WGA protocol generates an amplification product with optimal P. falciparum genome coverage for most genome sequencing analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This amount equates to ∼380 parasite genomes, equivalent to ∼1 µl of blood in a patient with 0.01% parasitemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we show that the optimized conditions significantly reduce the formation of chimeric reads, thereby improving the overall quality of the amplified product. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Standard WGA from such small quantities of input material is often associated with bias and incomplete genome coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A single-cell genomic approach that uses infected red blood cell sorting technology has recently been reported that achieved a genome coverage of ∼50% with a standard WGA method.31 Although genome coverage in single-cell approach is still low, this technology has opened avenues for single-cell genomics studies in malaria and offers great opportunities for dissecting multiple genotype infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Our optimized WGA method described here will be useful for optimizing genome coverage in such single-cell genome amplifications, as well as direct field applications for small sample sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>For improved malaria clinical sequencing, we routinely employ the combination of host depletion methods32,33 and the current optimized WGA procedure to generate high-quality whole genome sequencing data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We have assessed the quality of the amplified products generated from 10 pg input DNA using high-throughput sequencing of DNA extracted from 17 progeny clones derived from genetic crosses between two laboratory strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We performed a comparative analysis between the WGA data and their corresponding non-WGA counterparts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We show that coverage was sufficient for allele calling and other whole-genome analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Although the number of uncovered bases was slightly higher in WGA (median, 1.5%) than non-WGA (median, 1.2%) samples (Table 1), the difference was insignificant (t-test, P = 0.053, 95% CI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The same applies to preference for mitochondria DNA amplification, which showed a median of 2.6% in WGA against 0.6% in the non-WGA samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Another key aspect of P. falciparum whole-genome sequencing from clinical specimens is removing host DNA contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This can be achieved either at the blood sample processing stage through leucocyte depletion or through selective enrichment of parasite DNA after extraction.32–34 The combination of an effective method for removing human DNA that is applicable to the field setting, and the ability to perform whole-genome sequencing from very low quantities of input DNA as described in this study, has the potential to greatly increase the scope and scale of P. falciparum genomic research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>This, in turn, would contribute significantly to malaria genetic surveillance and control strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><label>5.</label><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The optimized amplification conditions described here have generated high-quality whole-genome sequence data (99.8% genome coverage) from a minute amount of input DNA, equivalent to &lt;400 P. falciparum genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>This work shows for the first time that accurate in silico genotyping and de novo calling of genetic variants is achievable on a WGA sample using &lt;1 ng of input DNA from an extremely AT-rich genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We anticipate that sequencing from small quantities of input DNA (&lt;1 ng) will become a significant aid to genetic and genomic studies of P. falciparum in the field, particularly when combined with effective methods for removal of host DNA contamination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu028/-/DC1">Supplementary Data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by the Wellcome Trust through the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute (098051), the Resource Centre for Genomic Epidemiology of Malaria (090770/Z/09/Z) and the Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics (090532/Z/09/Z). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The Centre for Genomics and Global Health is supported by the Medical Research Council (G0600718). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_21_6_661__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_dsu028_dsu028supp_tables.xls"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Jean-Bosco Ouedraogo (Institut de Recherche en Sciences de la Santé, Burkina Faso) and Francois Nosten (Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford) for providing field samples for analysis. We thank Richard Pearson and Thomas Otto for useful discussions on sequence analysis.</p><p><italic>Conflict of Interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DSU028C1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>1ManskeM.MiottoO.CampinoS.Analysis of Plasmodium falciparum diversity in natural infections by deep sequencingNature2012487375922722859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C2"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>2MiottoO.Almagro-GarciaJ.ManskeM.Multiple populations of artemisinin-resistant Plasmodium falciparum in CambodiaNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Genet.2013456485523624527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C3"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>3LaskenR.S.EgholmM.Whole genome amplification: abundant supplies of DNA from precious samples or clinical specimensTrends Biotechnol.200321531514624861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C4"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>4CoombsN.J.GoughA.C.PrimroseJ.N.Optimisation of DNA and RNA extraction from archival formalin-fixed tissueNucleic Acids Res.199927e1210454649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C5"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>5FarnertA.ArezA.P.CorreiaA.T.BjorkmanA.SnounouG.do RosarioV.Sampling and storage of blood and the detection of malaria parasites by polymerase chain reactionTrans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Hyg.19999350310492790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C6"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>6JacksonJ.LaikreL.BakerC.S.KendallK.Guidelines for collecting and maintaining archives for genetic monitoringConservation Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Resour.2012452736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C7"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>7ShiS.R.CoteR.J.WuL.DNA extraction from archival formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue sections based on the antigen retrieval principle: heating under the influence of pHJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Histochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Cytochem.20025010051112133903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C8"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>8BereczkyS.MartenssonA.GilJ.P.FarnertA.Short report: rapid DNA extraction from archive blood spots on filter paper for genotyping of Plasmodium falciparumAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Hyg.2005722495115772315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C9"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>9HwangJ.JaroensukJ.LeimanisM.L.Long-term storage limits PCR-based analyses of malaria parasites in archival dried blood spotsMalar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>J.20121133923043522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C10"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>10KainK.C.LanarD.E.Determination of genetic variation within Plasmodium falciparum by using enzymatically amplified DNA from filter paper disks impregnated with whole bloodJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.199129117141864936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C11"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>11SpitsC.Le CaignecC.De RyckeM.Whole-genome multiple displacement amplification from single cellsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Protoc.2006119657017487184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C12"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>12DeanF.B.HosonoS.FangL.Comprehensive human genome amplification using multiple displacement amplificationProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>USA2002995261611959976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C13"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>13DeanF.B.NelsonJ.R.GieslerT.L.LaskenR.S.Rapid amplification of plasmid and phage DNA using Phi 29 DNA polymerase and multiply-primed rolling circle amplificationGenome Res.2001111095911381035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C14"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>14TeleniusH.CarterN.P.BebbC.E.NordenskjoldM.PonderB.A.TunnacliffeA.Degenerate oligonucleotide-primed PCR: general amplification of target DNA by a single degenerate primerGenomics199213718251639399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C15"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>15ZhangL.CuiX.SchmittK.HubertR.NavidiW.ArnheimN.Whole genome amplification from a single cell: implications for genetic analysisProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>USA1992895847511631067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C16"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>16LaskenR.S.Genomic DNA amplification by the multiple displacement amplification (MDA) methodBiochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Trans.200937450319290880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C17"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>17MorinJ.A.CaoF.J.LazaroJ.M.Active DNA unwinding dynamics during processive DNA replicationProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>USA201210981152022573817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C18"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>18ZhangD.Y.BrandweinM.HsuihT.LiH.B.Ramification amplification: a novel isothermal DNA amplification methodMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Diagn.200161415011468700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C19"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>19PinardR.de WinterA.SarkisG.J.Assessment of whole genome amplification-induced bias through high-throughput, massively parallel whole genome sequencingBMC Genomics2006721616928277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C20"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>20PughT.J.DelaneyA.D.FarnoudN.Impact of whole genome amplification on analysis of copy number variantsNucleic Acids Res.200836e8018559357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C21"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>21KozarewaI.NingZ.QuailM.A.SandersM.J.BerrimanM.TurnerD.J.Amplification-free Illumina sequencing-library preparation facilitates improved mapping and assembly of (G+C)-biased genomesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Methods20096291519287394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C22"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>22OyolaS.O.OttoT.D.GuY.Optimizing Illumina next-generation sequencing library preparation for extremely AT-biased genomesBMC Genomics201213122214261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C23"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>23HaytonK.GaurD.LiuA.Erythrocyte binding protein PfRH5 polymorphisms determine species-specific pathways of Plasmodium falciparum invasionCell Host Microbe20084405118621009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C24"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>24HanT.ChangC.-W.KwekelJ.Characterization of whole genome amplified (WGA) DNA for use in genotyping assay developmentBMC Genomics20121321722655855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C25"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>25SpitsC.Le CaignecC.De RyckeM.Optimization and evaluation of single-cell whole-genome multiple displacement amplificationHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Mutat.20062749650316619243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C26"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>26BensonG.Tandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequencesNucleic Acids Res.199927573809862982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C27"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>27LaskenR.StockwellT.Mechanism of chimera formation during the multiple displacement amplification reactionBMC Biotechnol.200771917430586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C28"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>28McKennaA.HannaM.BanksE.The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing dataGenome Res.201020129730320644199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C29"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>29ZongC.LuS.ChapmanA.R.XieX.S.Genome-wide detection of single-nucleotide and copy-number variations of a single human cellScience20123381622623258894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C30"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>30SchneiderP.BaloghK.NaveranN.Whole genome amplification—the solution for a common problem in forensic casework?Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Congr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Ser.200412,61246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C31"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>31NairS.NkhomaS.C.SerreD.Single-cell genomics for dissection of complex malaria infectionsGenome Res.20142410283824812326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C32"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>32OyolaS.O.GuY.ManskeM.Efficient depletion of host DNA contamination in malaria clinical sequencingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.2013517455123224084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C33"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>33FeeheryG.R.YigitE.OyolaS.O.A method for selectively enriching microbial DNA from contaminating vertebrate host DNAPLoS ONE20138e7609624204593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSU028C34"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>34VenkatesanM.AmaratungaC.CampinoS.Using CF11 cellulose columns to inexpensively and effectively remove human DNA from Plasmodium falciparum-infected whole blood samplesMalar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>J.2012114122321373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
