<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Pediatr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Pediatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4683867</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-015-0528-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of suspected developmental delays in early infancy: results from a regional population-based longitudinal study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Valla</surname><given-names>Lisbeth</given-names></name><address><phone>+47 96236870</phone><email>Lisbeth.valla@r-bup.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wentzel-Larsen</surname><given-names>Tore</given-names></name><address><email>tore.wentzel-larsen@r-bup.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hofoss</surname><given-names>Dag</given-names></name><address><email>dag.hofoss@medisin.uio</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slinning</surname><given-names>Kari</given-names></name><address><email>kari.slinning@r-bup.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>National Network for Infant Mental Health in Norway, Center for Child and Adolescent Mental Health, Eastern and Southern Norway, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Center for Child and Adolescent Mental Health, Eastern and Southern Norway, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Norwegian Center for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Institute of Health and Society, Faculty of Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Department of Psychology, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>215</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Valla et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Prevalence estimates on suspected developmental delays (SDD) in young infants are scarce and a necessary first step for planning an early intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We investigated the prevalence of SDD at 4, 6 and 12 months, in addition to associations of SDD with gender, prematurity and maternal education. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This study is based on a Norwegian longitudinal sample of 1555 infants and their parents attending well-baby clinics for regular health check-ups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Moreover, parents completed the Norwegian translation of the Ages and Stages Questionnaires (ASQ) prior to the check-up, with a corrected gestational age being used to determine the time of administration for preterm infants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Scores ≤ the established cut-offs in one or more of the five development areas: communication, gross motor, fine motor, problem solving and personal-social, which defined SDD for an infant were reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Chi-square tests were performed for associations between the selected factors and SDD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>According to established Norwegian cut-off points, the overall prevalence of SDD in one or more areas was 7.0 % (10.3 % US cut-off) at 4 months, 5.7 % (12.3 % US cut-off) at 6 months and 6.1 % (10.3 % US cut-off) at 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The highest prevalence of SDD was in the gross motor area at all three time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>A gestational age of &lt; 37 weeks revealed a significant association with the communication SDD at 4 months, and with the fine motor and personal social SDD at 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Gender was significantly associated with the fine motor and problem solving SDD at 4 months and personal- social SDD at 6 months: as more boys than girls were delayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>No significant associations were found between maternal education and the five developmental areas of the ASQ. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Our findings indicate prevalence rates of SDD between 5.7 and 7.0 % in Norwegian infants between 4 and 12 months of age based on the Norwegian ASQ cut-off points (10.3–12.3 %, US cut-off points). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>During the first year of life, delay is most frequent within the gross motor area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Special attention should be paid to infants born prematurely, as well as to boys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Separate norms for boys and girls should be considered for the ASQ. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12887-015-0528-z) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ages and stages questionnaire</kwd><kwd>Suspected developmental delay</kwd><kwd>Prevalence</kwd><kwd>Infants</kwd><kwd>Screening</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Many studies have described the negative impacts of developmental delays in children, including emotional, behavioural and health problems later in life [1, 2], difficulties in parental child care and the parent-child relationship [3, 4], educational achievement [4, 5] and economic impacts on the families and societies [6–10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Early identification and intervention for developmental delays cause an improvement in the successful functioning of affected children [11–14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Research has demonstrated that intervention programmes are cost-effective and may have lifelong benefits, and also that developmental attainment is maximized when intervention is started early [11–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A necessary first step in order to plan for early intervention is estimation of prevalence of developmental delay and knowledge about the types of delays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Estimates from the World Health Organization (WHO) indicate that 5 % of the world’s children under 15 years of age have some type of moderate to severe disability [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In the United States developmental disabilities occur in 15 % of children from 3 to 17 years of age [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In Norway and Scandinavia, data on the developmental status on children is scarce and the few published studies of children below school age show divergent results, varying from 6.3 % to 33 % [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Developmental screening programmes have been shown to improve the identification and referral of children who have possible delays [20–22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>One of the validated screening tools recommended by the American Academy of Pediatrics is the Ages and Stages Questionnaires (ASQ) [23], which is a parent-completed tool for identifying infants and young children at risk for developmental delays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>To date, no such recommendation exists in Norway and the Scandinavian countries, however, a Norwegian translation of the ASQ 2nd edition with a Norwegian reference (N ref.) sample has been available since 2003 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The public health system in Norway provides free medical, mental and dental services for all children and youth from 0–18, and close to 100 % of parents with young infants come regularly to local well-baby clinics from birth and up to 5 years of age for weight control, vaccination and a developmental check-up of their infant [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Check-ups and developmental monitoring in the well-baby clinic are primarily done by public health nurses and a general practitioner (GP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Both the monitoring and check-ups are essentially based on clinical judgement and not on the use of standardized screening or assessment tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>No official definition exists regarding who is eligible for early intervention at the primary care level; thus the health providers’ clinical judgement, in combination with parent concerns, are the primary drivers for this decision. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>If specialist services are needed, the local GP has to make a formal referral and get written consent from the child’s parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Even so, there is a growing amount of interest for screening tools for developmental delay by professionals in primary care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Without accurate prevalence data based on standardized instruments, it is difficult for primary health care to adequately plan the necessary assessment and intervention responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A lack of estimates on developmental delays among infants and children also has provided an unclear picture for policy-makers for a decision to provide early intervention services, as well as for planning and estimating the costs of early social, medical and educational intervention programmes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Hence, there is a pressing need for empirical data on knowledge about the prevalence of children at risk of developmental delay in Norway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This study seeks to contribute to building a more comprehensive picture of young infants’ developmental status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Child development is influenced by bio-medical and socio-cultural factors that are in a continuous interaction [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A number of risk factors associated with an increased risk for developmental delay have been identified, including child gender, gestational age and the mothers’ educational level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Predictors of developmental delays can be useful in estimating the potential for delayed development in the population, in addition to providing an opportunity to create environments that support optimal development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to estimate prevalence rates of SDD among infants at 4, 6 and 12 months of age based on parent-completed ASQ, and to investigate associations of SDD with gender, gestational age &lt; 37 weeks and maternal education. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This study is based on a Norwegian population-based prospective cohort study on children’s early development from birth to two years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Recruitment took place between May 2011 and May 2012, and the participants were recruited from all existing well-baby clinics in five municipalities, both in urban and rural areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Every expectant or new mother who came to these clinics was invited to participate in the study by a mid-wife or a public health nurse at their first consultation, either during pregnancy or soon after birth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The study had no specific exclusion criteria since the well-baby clinics offer services to all families with children below 5 years who live in the municipality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Mothers of 1555 children and their partners consented to participate (88.5 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In &gt; 95 % of cases, it was the mother who completed the ASQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Mothers who did not consent to participate in the study differed from participating mothers in terms of having a lower educational level (p &lt; 0.001) and higher proportion of non-Scandinavian speaking mothers (p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>No significant differences were found in gender, birth weight and gestational age between participating and non-participating children. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The current study reports on infant developmental status at 4, 6 and 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The number of infants with a parent-completed ASQ form for each assessment point varied (4 months: n = 1244, 6 months: n = 1192 and 12 months: n = 832). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The background characteristics of the study population from each assessment point are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>One of the municipalities with four well-baby clinics did not collect ASQ information on the children at the 12-months consultation due to time restrictions at this particular consultation, which is the primary reason for the low number of ASQ data at 12 months.Table 1Characteristics of the study population     Children4 months6 months12 months n = 1244% n = 1192% n = 832%Gendera Girls56248.652547.637248.5Boys59451.457952.439551.5Gestational age &lt; 37 weekb 665.9595.5425.8Birth Weight &lt; 2500 grc 484.2403.6212.7     Mothers4 months6 months12 months n = 1244% n = 1192% n = 832%Married or cohabitantsd 110895.7106095.874696.5Higher educatione,f 72664.070264.952470.0 aGender has 1156 valid values at 4 months, 1104 at 6 months and 767 at 12 months, when at least one ASQ area is validity answered bGestation age 4 months (n = 1113) : range 26- 42 weeks, mean 39.5 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Gestation age 6 months (n = 1065): range = 27-42 weeks, mean 39.5 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Gestation age 12 months (n = 727): range 27-42 weeks, mean 39.5 weeks, when at least one ASQ question is validity answered cBirth Weight 4 months (n = 1156): range = 772-5180 gr, mean = 3530 gr, 6 months (n = 1103): range = 966- 5180 gr, mean = 3547 gr, 12 months (n = 766): range = 966-5040 gr, mean = 3566 gr, when at least one ASQ question is validity answered dMarital status has 1158 valid values at 4 months, 1106 at 6 months and 769 at 12 months,when at least one ASQ question is validity answered eHigher education: Had qualified from, or studied at the university or college fEducation has 1134 valid values at 4 mo, 1108 at 6 mo and 749 at 12 mo, when at least one ASQ area is validity answered </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The public health nurse or midwife provided written and oral information about the study to the parents based on procedures approved by the Norwegian Regional Committee for Medical and Health Ethics, and parents who volunteered gave their written consent to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>On enrolment or at the first check-up after birth, background information data such as educational level, civil status, child’s gender, gestational age, and birth weight were collected and recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The ASQ was mailed to the participants’ home address two weeks before the 4, 6 or 12 months well-baby clinic visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For infants born prematurely, the corrected age was used when completing the questionnaires [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The parents brought with them the completed ASQ to the scheduled appointment and the information on the ASQ was included as part of the overall clinical evaluation process that took place together with the parents and their child. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>All parents with ASQ screen positive infants were offered further evaluations of their child within two weeks, as well as referrals to specialist care in severe cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The infants’ development was assessed by the Norwegian version of the Ages and Stages Questionnaire, 2nd edition [18, 23], at 4, 6 and 12 month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The ASQ is a parent-completed, developmental screening instrument, and consists of 21 age-specific questionnaires intended for use from the age of 2 months to 60 months [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Each questionnaire in the ASQ consists of 30 items covering five areas: communication, gross motor, fine motor, problem solving, and personal-social. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Sum scores for the 6 ASQ areas were computed when all ASQ items were valid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Parents were asked to evaluate whether their child had achieved a milestone (“yes”, 10 points), had partly achieved a milestone (“sometimes”, 5 points) or had not yet achieved a milestone (“not yet”, 0 points). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Each area total score is compared to a cut-off score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>A child who obtains one or more area scores at or below the established cut-off levels is per definition suspected of developmental delay and should be referred for further evaluation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>According to the US manual for ASQ, children who score 2 SD or more below average are considered of a suspected delay [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The ASQ may be used in a variety of settings (mail, online, telephone, interview, home visit, office of child care or physician) and both as parent reported and reported by health professionals [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The original ASQ has been proven to be a valid and reliable screening test, even in its translated and culturally adapted versions in several studies in different populations of children [27–32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>According to the Norwegian manual, the cut-off is primarily based on the 2nd percentile [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A construct validation study based on the N ref.sample confirmed the Norwegian ASQ version as an effective diagnostic tool of developmental delay [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Because no Norwegian concurrent validation study has been published, we decided to present prevalence data based on both the Norwegian and US cut-off scores. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The summary of the data is presented as frequencies and percentages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The associations of SDD at 4, 6 and 12 months with gender, a gestational age of &lt; 37 weeks and maternal education were investigated by chi-square tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The level of significance was set at 0.05, and the data were analysed using the Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS) software package version 22 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Complete ASQ scores were available for 1244 of the participants at 4 months, 1192 at 6 months and 832 at 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of the participating children and their mothers at 4, 6 and 12 months are presented in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The mothers’ age at the three time point ranged from 17–44, with a mean age of 30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows the proportion of infants with SDD according to the Norwegian and US cut-off points in the five developmental ASQ areas at 4, 6 and 12 months.Table 2The percentage of infants scoring at or below the Norwegian (N ref.) and US cut-off values at 4, 6 and 12 months   4 months   6 months   12 months N ref.US N ref.US N ref.USCut-offCut-offCut-offCut-offCut-offCut-offCommunication1.4 %1.4 %0.6 %0.6 %0.7 %2.5 %Gross motor2.6 %2.6 %2.3 %5.9 %3.6 %8.7 %Fine motor1.9 %4.6 %1.8 %1.8 %0.4 %0.4 %Problem- solving2.5 %2.5 %1.0 %0.2 %1.8 %1.8 %Personal- social1.1 %3.6 %1.5 %3.7 %0.5 %1.4 %Scoring at or below at least one area7.0 %10.3 %5.7 %10.3 %6.1 %12.3 %Recommended cut-off scores in the US (Mean – 2 SD)and in the Norwegian manual (primarily based on the 2 percentile) in the areas of Ages and Stages Questionnaire, see Additional file 1  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 2, the overall prevalence of infants scoring at or below the cut-off points of at least one developmental area according to the Norwegian cut-off points was 7.0 % at 4 months (10.3 % according to the US cut-off), 5.7 % at 6 months (10.3 % by the US cut-off), and 6.1 % at 12 months (12.3 % by the US cut-off). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The percentage of infants with SDD in the communication, gross motor, fine motor, problem solving and social-personal areas varied between 1.1 and 2.6 % at 4 months, 0.6 and 2.3 % at 6 months and 0.4 and 3.6 % at 12 months by the Norwegian cut-off scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The highest prevalence was found in the gross motor area in all three age groups, 2.6 % at 4 months, 2.3 % at 6 months and 3.6 % at 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We also found that 1.8 % of infants with complete ASQ scores had a delay in more than one area at 4 months, 1.1 and 0.8 % at 6 and 12 months, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Table 3 shows the associations of gestational age &lt; 37 weeks, gender, maternal education with developmental delay for each area and age groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Gender was significantly associated with fine motor area (p = 0.029) and problem solving area (p =0.010) at 4 months and personal-social area at 6 months (p = 0.013), with a higher prevalence of SDD among boys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Gestational age of &lt; 37 weeks was significantly associated with delay in the communication area (p = 0.001) at 4 months and the fine motor (p = 0.049) and personal-social area (p &lt;0.001) at 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Maternal education had no significant associations with the areas of the Ages and Stages Questionnaire in any age group.Table 3Association between gender, gestational age, maternal education and the area of ASQ4 monthsCommunicationGross motorFine motorProblem solvingPersonal- socialPreva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Gender1.21.60.5383.42.00.1382.91.10.029*3.91.40.010*1.50.90.331Gest.age &lt; 37 weeks1.16.10.001*2.36.10.0581.73.00.4372.04.50.1681.11.50.787Maternal education1.51.50.9532.72.80.9541.02.60.0612.23.00.4141.01.40.5616 monthsCommunicationGross motorFine motorProblem- solvingPersonal- socialPreva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Gender0.90.40.3121.92.70.3952.11.30.3440.91.10.6432.40.60.013*Gest. age &lt; 37 weeks0.70.00.5202.41.70.7331.65.10.049*1.10.00.4191.18.5&lt;0.001*Maternal education0.80.60.6623.11.90.1681.91.60.7270.81.10.5891.91.40.59012 monthsCommunicationGross motorFine motorProblem- solvingPersonal- socialPreva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Preva  p Gender0.80.50.7032.34.30.1150.50.00.1692.31.30.3340.50.50.952Gest. age &lt; 37 weeks0.70.00.5783.17.10.1510.30.00.7261.92.40.8250.60.00.619Maternal education0.90.60.6262.23.80.2680.40.20.7690.40.20.5381.81.90.826 aPrev = Prevalence(%), boys vs girls, ≥37 weeks of gestational age vs &lt; 37 weeks gestational age, high vs low maternal education (higher education: had qualified from, or studied at the university or college).*Significant at p &lt; 0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to estimate the prevalence rates of SDD in a community sample of infants at 4, 6 and 12 months of age based on their ASQ scores in five developmental areas, as well as the associations of SDD with gender, prematurity (a gestational age of &lt; 37 weeks) and maternal education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The results suggest that between 5.7 to 7.0 % of young infants between 4 and 12 months had SDD according to the Norwegian ASQ cut-off points, and between 10.3 to 12.3 % according to the US cut-off points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The majority of these had an indication of delays in one area only, most frequently in the gross motor area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Prematurity was significantly associated with SDD in the communication area at 4 months and fine motor and personal-social areas at 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Significant associations were found between gender and the fine motor and problem solving areas at 4 months and the personal-social area at 6 months. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown substantial variations in the prevalence of developmental delay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A number of methodological issues make it difficult to compare available prevalence rates, such as differences in case definition and criteria, type of measures used, variations in age and whether the studies report on low or high risk populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Prevalences of developmental delay based on the National Health Interview Surveys (NHIS-CH), which is a parent completed questionnaire on development disability, reported that 15 % of US children between 3 and 17 years had a developmental disability [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The Health Intervention Survey (NHIS-D) on Disabilities reported that 3.4 % of all children had general developmental delays and 3.3 % had functional developmental delays among American children between 4 and 59 months [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A nationally representative longitudinal sample in the US showed that almost 13 % of the infants who were objectively measured by the Bayley Short Form-Research Edition at 9 and 24 month had developmental delays [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The results from the current study were based on a Norwegian version of the ASQ, and the data was gathered from well-baby clinics where almost the entire population of parents with young infants came regularly with their child for a developmental check-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>ASQ was implemented in all nine well-baby clinics in five municipalities with the intention of standardizing the general developmental monitoring and check-up by public health nurses, engaging parents as active partners and increasing the detection rate of infants at risk for SDD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Parents brought the completed ASQ form along to the 4, 6 and 12- month check-ups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, few prevalence estimates exist of SDD based on parent-completed ASQ data collected in a primary care setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Two studies yielded ASQ data collected from preventive health care clinics in the Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Prevalence rates for 4-year-old full-term children in the first study were 7.2 % for children with low sosio-economic status (SES), 4.8 % for intermediate and 2.8 % for high SES children [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The second study reported prevalence rates for full-term and moderate preterm children (43–49 months), at 4.2 % and 8.3 %, respectively [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The prevalence rates from these two studies are in line with the findings in the present study, which indicates prevalence rates between 5.7 and 7.0 % (Norwegian cut-off points, and between 10.3 and 13.3 % for US cut-off points). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Other studies among younger children report higher rates of SDD measured with ASQ than our study [18, 19, 37–40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A prevalence of 27 % was found in a well-child clinic among American children from 9 to 31 months [38], while another study reported a prevalence rate of 28.8 % among 9, 18 and 30 month old children who attended an ambulatory well-baby clinic in Chile [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>However, the Norwegian ASQ normative sample reported prevalence rates of 10.3 % at 4 months, 11.8 % at 6 months and 11.6 % at 12 months [18], and a more recent Norwegian population-based study of 6 month old infants from the capital of Norway found that approximately every third infant obtained an ASQ score at or below the cut-off scores in at least one area according to the Norwegian and US recommended cut-off scores [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The Norwegian ASQ normative sample had a relatively small sample size in each age group, and unlike the present study, the participants in both the previous Norwegian studies received an invitation letter, completed the ASQ at home and returned it by mail to the researchers without any feedback. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The prevalence rate found in the study by Alvik and Grøholt is unexpectedly high, especially when taking into consideration that infants with a birth weight below 2.5 kg and mothers with non-Scandinavian ethnicity were excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In addition, none of the 14 pictograms in the ASQ 6-month questionnaire were included in the ASQ form that the parents were asked to complete at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This might possibly have contributed to misinterpretations of the meaning of items and thus an incorrect response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Developmental delay in one area is often found to be correlated with delay in other areas [41, 42], but being late in one isolated area only is associated with less risk for the child [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In our community sample, we found that only 1.8 % of the infants had SDD in more than one area at 4 months, 1.1 % at 6 months and 0.8 % at 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The highest prevalence rate in the present study was found in the gross motor area during the first year of life, 2.6 % at 4 months, 2.3 % at 6 months and 3.6 % at 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This was also the case in the Norwegian reference sample at 12 months (5.5 %) [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Still these gross motor prevalences are considerably lower than studies on young children from the US and other countries [26, 33, 39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Motor development may differ in rate and sequence among infants and children from various cultural backgrounds [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>It is also well recognized that the development of gross motor skills during early childhood is of paramount relevance for a child’s overall development [45], and a developmental delay in the ASQ motor area in early life has been found to predict later communication [41] and cognitive skills [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Several factors affect motor development among children, such as a child’s characteristics (e.g. gender, age, ethnicity and somatic conditions), child-rearing practices, parental/social expectations and the quality and quantity of stimulation provided in home [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For example, the caregivers’ attitude and encouragement toward an infant’s tummy time or floor time might be related to the child’s motor performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Parents in Norway have 12 months leave and spend most of the day together with their infants, and the public health nurses encourage parents to stimulate their infant’s motor development in the first year of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>This may well have contributed to the relatively low prevalence rates in our sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Significant associations were found between gender and developmental delay in the fine motor and problem solving area at 4 months, and at the personal-social area at 6 months, with lower mean scores for boys in all areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The finding that boys have a significantly higher rate of delay is in accordance with other studies of gender differences in preschoolers [28, 33, 47, 48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>On average, Richter and Janson showed that the developmental stage for girls in a Norwegian population was higher than for boys in all ASQ areas, except for gross motor function, in which no significant differences were detected [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The gender differences found in this study correspond with the results from previous research, therefore it seems preferable to develop norms for the Norwegian version of the ASQ separately for boys and girls in order to avoid false-positive classifications of boys in further assessments and interventions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Premature birth (&lt;37 gestation weeks) was associated with a delay in the communication area at 4 months, and the fine motor and personal-social area at 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Developmental delays are common in preterm children and the risk increases with a decreasing geatation age (GA) [36, 49], which can be explained by the developmental stage of the central nervous system at birth [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Evidence from neuroscience shows that microstructural and neural connectivity processes are disturbed because of prematurity, and these disturbances may result in an atypical differentiation of neuronal pathways [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Premature birth was reflected by a delay in all five ASQ areas in the Norwegian study by Richter and Janson, although these negative consequences were seemingly more pronounced within the fine motor skills, problem solving skills and personal-social skills than the other areas [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Kerstjens and colleagues also found that both moderate and early preterm children measured with ASQ at 4 years of age had more frequent problems with fine motor, communication and personal-social functioning compared to their 4 year old peers born full-term [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Maternal education had no significant associations with the areas of the Ages and Stages Questionnaire in this study, in contrast to previous reported findings of the impact of maternal education upon child development [28, 31, 52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>There may be several explanations for why maternal education was not significantly related to infant development in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Firstly, this study was based on a Norwegian community sample, with a relatively high education level among the parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, our study was conducted on young infants between 4 and 12 months of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In this early stage of development, biomedical factors may have a greater impact on development than the parents’ educational level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In addition, the Norwegian society also provides a highly stable and comprehensive social, financial and health care network that protects mother and babies to a high degree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Prevalence estimates on SDD in young infants are scarce and a necessary first step in order to plan for early intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This study contributes to building a more comprehensive picture of young Norwegian infants’ developmental status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The sample is population-based with a relatively large sample size, and the ASQ is performed in a naturalistic setting in accordance with the recommended use of the instrument [26] . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>There were no exclusion criteria for participation in the study, but the families who did not want to participate differed from the participating parents in terms of having a lower educational level and a higher proportion of non-Scandinavian-speaking parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>This may have biased our results to some extent, but we did not find significant relationships between the mother’s education level and the child’s ASQ scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between the participating and non-participating children at the time of inclusion in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>However, there was a reduction in the proportion of low birth weight infants with a completed ASQ from 4 to 12 months of age, which may have influenced the results and reduced the estimated prevalence of SDD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The Norwegian version of the ASQ was used and the Norwegian ASQ items are well translated and back-translated; thus, there is little probability of translation distortion [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It would have been preferable if a concurrent Norwegian validation of ASQ was available, but no such validation yet exists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Hence, the results of SDD among 4–12 month old infants in Norway must be interpreted with some caution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The current study contributes to a limited knowledge base regarding the prevalence of infants at risk for developmental delay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This large, representative regional population-based sample suggests a prevalence rate of SDD between 5.7 and 7.0 % among infants between 4 and 12 months of age based on the Norwegian cut-off points (10.3–12.3 % according to US cut-off points). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>During the first year of life, delays are most frequently reported within the motor area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Special attention should be paid to infants born prematurely and to boys, and separate norms for boys and girls should be considered for the ASQ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec10"><title>Additional file</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12887_2015_528_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Norwegian (N.ref.)and US cut-off values at 4, 6 and 12 months Description of dataset- Shows the recommended cut-off scores in Norway and US at 4, 6 and 12 months. (PDF 20 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ASQ</term><def><p>Ages and Stages Questionnaires</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>N ref</term><def><p>the Norwegian reference sample</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DD</term><def><p>Developmental delay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GA</term><def><p>Gestational age</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GP</term><def><p>General practitioner</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>LV: Responsibility for the study design, data collection, analysis and interpretation, and in the writing of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>KS: Primary responsibility for the study design, Participated in the analytic framework of the study, with the data interpretation, and in the writing of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>DH: Has been involved in the statistical analysis, and in critically revising the manuscript for important intellectual content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>TWL: Was involved in and supervised the statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>All the authors have given their final approval of the final version of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We are indebted to all the participating families, and grateful to the staff at the well-baby clinics in Hamar, Løten, Tønsberg, Nøtterøy and Larvik. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>1.BakerBLMcIntyreLBlacherJCrnicKEdelbrockCLowCPre-school children with and without developmental delay: Behaviour problems and parenting stress over timeJ Intellect Disabil Res2003474-52173010.1046/j.1365-2788.2003.00484.x<?supplied-pmid 12787154?>12787154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>2.EmersonEEinfeldSEmotional and behavioural difficulties in young children with and without developmental delay: a bi-national perspectiveJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20105155839310.1111/j.1469-7610.2009.02179.x<?supplied-pmid 20015191?>20015191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>3.BrownMAMcIntyreLLCrnicKABakerBLBlacherJPreschool Children with and without Developmental Delay: Risk, Parenting, and Child DemandingessJ Ment Health Res Intellect Disabil2011432062610.1080/19315864.2011.596990<?supplied-pmid 22778798?>22778798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>4.BlanchardLTGurkaMJBlackmanJAEmotional, developmental, and behavioral health of American children and their families: a report from the 2003 National Survey of Children’s HealthPediatrics20061176e12021210.1542/peds.2005-2606<?supplied-pmid 16740820?>16740820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>5.BoyleCADecouflePYeargin-AllsoppMPrevalence and health impact of developmental disabilities in US childrenPediatrics1994933399403<?supplied-pmid 7509480?>7509480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>6.ChanEZhanCHomerCJHealth care use and costs for children with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: national estimates from the medical expenditure panel surveyArch Pediatr Adolesc Med200215655041110.1001/archpedi.156.5.504<?supplied-pmid 11980558?>11980558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>7.NewacheckPWKimSEA national profile of health care utilization and expenditures for children with special health care needsArch Pediatr Adolesc Med2005159110710.1001/archpedi.159.1.10<?supplied-pmid 15630052?>15630052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>8.QuachJOberklaidFGoldLLucasNMensahFKWakeMPrimary health-care costs associated with special health care needs up to age 7 years: Australian population-based studyJ Paediatr Child Health201450107687410.1111/jpc.12649<?supplied-pmid 24923806?>24923806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>9.SciberrasEWestruppEMWakeMNicholsonJMLucasNMensahFHealthcare costs associated with language difficulties up to 9 years of age: Australian population-based studyInt J Speech Lang Pathol2015171415210.3109/17549507.2014.898095<?supplied-pmid 24801409?>24801409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>10.WestruppEMLucasNMensahFKGoldLWakeMNicholsonJMCommunity-based healthcare costs for children born low birthweight, preterm and/or small for gestational age: data from the Longitudinal Study of Australian ChildrenChild Care Health Dev20144022596610.1111/cch.12040<?supplied-pmid 23461342?>23461342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>11.ManningMHomelRSmithCA meta-analysis of the effects of early developmental prevention programs in at-risk populations on non-health outcomes in adolescenceChild Youth Serv Rev20103245061910.1016/j.childyouth.2009.11.003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>12.AndersonLMShinnCFulliloveMTScrimshawSCFieldingJENormandJThe effectiveness of early childhood development programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A systematic reviewAm J Prev Med2003243 Suppl324610.1016/S0749-3797(02)00655-4<?supplied-pmid 12668197?>12668197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>13.McCormickMCBrooks-GunnJBukaSLGoldmanJYuJSalganikMEarly intervention in low birth weight premature infants: results at 18 years of age for the Infant Health and Development ProgramPediatrics200611737718010.1542/peds.2005-1316<?supplied-pmid 16510657?>16510657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>14.SpittleAJOrtonJDoyleLWBoydREarly developmental intervention programs post hospital discharge to prevent motor and cognitive impairments in preterm infantsCochrane Database Syst Rev20072Cd005495<?supplied-pmid 17443595?>17443595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>15.ReynoldsAJTempleJAWhiteBAOuSRRobertsonDLAge 26 cost-benefit analysis of the child-parent center early education programChild Dev201182137940410.1111/j.1467-8624.2010.01563.x<?supplied-pmid 21291448?>21291448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>16.World Health OrganizationThe global burden of disease: 2004 update2008GenevaWHO </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>17.BoyleCABouletSSchieveLACohenRABlumbergSJYeargin-AllsoppMTrends in the prevalence of developmental disabilities in US children, 1997-2008Pediatrics2011127610344210.1542/peds.2010-2989<?supplied-pmid 21606152?>21606152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>18.JansonHSmithLNorsk manualsupplement til “Ages and stages questionnaires”2003OsloR.BUP, Regionsenter for barne- og ungdomspsykiatri, Helseregion Øst/Sør </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>19.AlvikAGrøholtBExamination of the cut-off scores determined by the Ages and Stages Questionnaire in a population-based sample of 6 month-old Norwegian infantsBMC Pediatr20111111710.1186/1471-2431-11-117<?supplied-pmid 22182217?>22182217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>20.Hix-SmallHMarksKSquiresJNickelRImpact of implementing developmental screening at 12 and 24 months in a pediatric practicePediatrics20071202381910.1542/peds.2006-3583<?supplied-pmid 17671065?>17671065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>21.SchonwaldAHuntingtonNChanERiskoWBridgemohanCRoutine developmental screening implemented in urban primary care settings: more evidence of feasibility and effectivenessPediatrics20091232660810.1542/peds.2007-2798<?supplied-pmid 19171635?>19171635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>22.GuevaraJPGerdesMLocalioRHuangYVPinto-MartinJMinkovitzCSEffectiveness of developmental screening in an urban settingPediatrics2013131130710.1542/peds.2012-0765<?supplied-pmid 23248223?>23248223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>23.SquiresJPotterLBrickerDThe ASQ User’s guide19992Baltimore, MDBrookes </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>24.Sosial- og helsedirektoratetKommunenes helsefremmende og forebyggende arbeid i helsestasjons- og skolehelsetjenesten: veileder til forskrift av 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>April 2003 nr 4502004OsloSosial- og helsedirektoratet </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>25.SameroffAA unified theory of development: a dialectic integration of nature and nurtureChild Dev201081162210.1111/j.1467-8624.2009.01378.x<?supplied-pmid 20331651?>20331651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>26.SquiresJTwomblyEBrickerDPotterLThe ASQ-3 User’s guide20093Baltimore, MDBrookes </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>27.KlamerALandoAPinborgAGreisenGAges and Stages Questionnaire used to measure cognitive deficit in children born extremely pretermActa Paediatr20059491327910.1111/j.1651-2227.2005.tb02095.x<?supplied-pmid 16279000?>16279000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>28.RichterJJansonHA validation study of the Norwegian version of the Ages and Stages QuestionnairesActa Paediatr20079657485210.1111/j.1651-2227.2007.00246.x<?supplied-pmid 17462065?>17462065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>29.ElbersJMacnabAMcLeodEGagnonFThe Ages and Stages Questionnaires: feasibility of use as a screening tool for children in CanadaCan J Rural Med2008131914<?supplied-pmid 18208647?>18208647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>30.HeoKHSquiresJYovanoffPCross-cultural adaptation of a pre-school screening instrument: comparison of Korean and US populationsJ Intellect Disabil Res200852Pt 319520610.1111/j.1365-2788.2007.01000.x<?supplied-pmid 18261019?>18261019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>31.KerstjensJMBosAFten VergertEMde MeerGButcherPRReijneveldSASupport for the global feasibility of the Ages and Stages Questionnaire as developmental screenerEarly Hum Dev2009857443710.1016/j.earlhumdev.2009.03.001<?supplied-pmid 19356866?>19356866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>32.KapciEGKucukerSUsluRIHow Applicable Are Ages and Stages Questionnaires for Use With Turkish Children?Topics Early Child Spec Educ20103031768810.1177/0271121410373149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>33.SimpsonGAColpeLGreenspanSMeasuring functional developmental delay in infants and young children: prevalence rates from the NHIS-DPaediatr Perinat Epidemiol2003171688010.1046/j.1365-3016.2003.00459.x<?supplied-pmid 12562474?>12562474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>34.RosenbergSAZhangDRobinsonCCPrevalence of developmental delays and participation in early intervention services for young childrenPediatrics20081216e1503910.1542/peds.2007-1680<?supplied-pmid 18504295?>18504295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>35.PotijkMRKerstjensJMBosAFReijneveldSAde WinterAFDevelopmental delay in moderately preterm-born children with low socioeconomic status: risks multiplyJ Pediatr2013163512899510.1016/j.jpeds.2013.07.001<?supplied-pmid 23968750?>23968750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>36.KerstjensJMde WinterAFBocca-TjeertesIFten VergertEMReijneveldSABosAFDevelopmental delay in moderately preterm-born children at school entryJ Pediatr2011159192810.1016/j.jpeds.2010.12.041<?supplied-pmid 21324481?>21324481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>37.RydzDSrourMOskouiMMargetNShillerMBirnbaumRScreening for developmental delay in the setting of a community pediatric clinic: a prospective assessment of parent-report questionnairesPediatrics20061184e11788610.1542/peds.2006-0466<?supplied-pmid 17015506?>17015506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>38.SicesLStancinTKirchnerLBauchnerHPEDS and ASQ developmental screening tests may not identify the same childrenPediatrics20091244e640710.1542/peds.2008-2628<?supplied-pmid 19736268?>19736268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>39.Wei QW, Zhang JX, Scherpbier RW, Zhao CX, Luo SS, Wang XL, Guo SF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>High prevalence of developmental delay among children under three years of age in poverty-stricken areas of China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Public Health In Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>40.SchonhautLArmijoISchonstedtMAlvarezJCorderoMValidity of the ages and stages questionnaires in term and preterm infantsPediatrics20131315e14687410.1542/peds.2012-3313<?supplied-pmid 23629619?>23629619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>41.WangMVLekhalRAaroLESchjolbergSCo-occurring development of early childhood communication and motor skills: results from a population-based longitudinal studyChild Care Health Dev2014401778410.1111/cch.12003<?supplied-pmid 22970997?>22970997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>42.PiekJPDawsonLSmithLMGassonNThe role of early fine and gross motor development on later motor and cognitive abilityHum Mov Sci20082756688110.1016/j.humov.2007.11.002<?supplied-pmid 18242747?>18242747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>43.ValtonenRAhonenTLyytinenPTolvanenAScreening for developmental risks at 4 years of age: Predicting development two years laterNord Psychol20075929510810.1027/1901-2276.59.2.95 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>44.MaysonTAHarrisSRBachmanCLGross motor development of Asian and European children on four motor assessments: a literature reviewPediatr Phys Ther20071921485310.1097/PEP.0b013e31804a57c1<?supplied-pmid 17505292?>17505292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>45.PiekJPHandsBLicariMKAssessment of motor functioning in the preschool periodNeuropsychol Rev20122244021310.1007/s11065-012-9211-4<?supplied-pmid 22837070?>22837070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>46.CoolsWDe MartelaerKSamaeyCAndriesCFundamental movement skill performance of preschool children in relation to family contextJ Sports Sci20112976496010.1080/02640414.2010.551540<?supplied-pmid 21424981?>21424981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>47.BerglundEErikssonMWesterlundMCommunicative skills in relation to gender, birth order, childcare and socioeconomic status in 18-month-old childrenScand J Psychol20054664859110.1111/j.1467-9450.2005.00480.x<?supplied-pmid 16277649?>16277649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>48.RydellAMDiamantopoulouSThorellLBBohlinGHyperactivity, shyness, and sex: development and socio-emotional functioningBr J Dev Psychol200927Pt 36254810.1348/026151008X346996<?supplied-pmid 19994572?>19994572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>49.WoythalerMAMcCormickMCSmithVCLate preterm infants have worse 24-month neurodevelopmental outcomes than term infantsPediatrics20111273e622910.1542/peds.2009-3598<?supplied-pmid 21321024?>21321024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>50.VolpeJJBrain injury in premature infants: a complex amalgam of destructive and developmental disturbancesLancet Neurol2009811102410.1016/S1474-4422(08)70294-1<?supplied-pmid 19081519?>19081519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>51.LubsenJVohrBMyersEHampsonMLacadieCSchneiderKCMicrostructural and functional connectivity in the developing preterm brainSemin Perinatol2011351344310.1053/j.semperi.2010.10.006<?supplied-pmid 21255705?>21255705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>52.SeguinLXuQGauvinLZunzuneguiMVPotvinLFrohlichKLUnderstanding the dimensions of socioeconomic status that influence toddlers’ health: unique impact of lack of money for basic needs in Quebec’s birth cohortJ Epidemiol Community Health200559142810.1136/jech.2004.020438<?supplied-pmid 15598725?>15598725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
