<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Cancer. Journal International du Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0020-7136</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1097-0215</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4200311</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.28890</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cancer Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The sodium channel β1 subunit mediates outgrowth of neurite-like processes on breast cancer cells and promotes tumour growth and metastasis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Michaela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Millican-Slater</surname><given-names>Rebecca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>Lorna C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brackenbury</surname><given-names>William J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Biology, University of York</institution><addr-line>Heslington, York, YO10 5DD, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Histopathology, St James's University Hospital</institution><addr-line>Leeds, LS9 7TF, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. William J. Brackenbury, Department of Biology, University of York, Wentworth Way, Heslington, York YO10 5DD, UK, Tel: +44-1904-328284, Fax: +44-1904-328505, E-mail: <email>william.brackenbury@york.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Grant sponsor: Medical Research Council; Grant number: G1000508 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>135</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2338</fpage><lpage>2351</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Voltage-gated Na+ channels (VGSCs) are heteromeric proteins composed of pore-forming α subunits and smaller β subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The β subunits are multifunctional channel modulators and are members of the immunoglobulin superfamily of cell adhesion molecules (CAMs). β1, encoded by SCN1B, is best characterized in the central nervous system (CNS), where it plays a critical role in regulating electrical excitability, neurite outgrowth and migration during development. β1 is also expressed in breast cancer (BCa) cell lines, where it regulates adhesion and migration in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we found that SCN1B mRNA/β1 protein were up-regulated in BCa specimens, compared with normal breast tissue. β1 upregulation substantially increased tumour growth and metastasis in a xenograft model of BCa. β1 over-expression also increased vascularization and reduced apoptosis in the primary tumours, and β1 over-expressing tumour cells had an elongate morphology. In vitro, β1 potentiated outgrowth of processes from BCa cells co-cultured with fibroblasts, via trans-homophilic adhesion. β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells required the presence and activity of fyn kinase, and Na+ current, thus replicating the mechanism by which β1 regulates neurite outgrowth in CNS neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We conclude that when present in breast tumours, β1 enhances pathological growth and cellular dissemination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This study is the first demonstration of a functional role for β1 in tumour growth and metastasis in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We propose that β1 warrants further study as a potential biomarker and targeting β1-mediated adhesion interactions may have value as a novel anti-cancer therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>adhesion</kwd><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>fyn kinase</kwd><kwd>metastasis</kwd><kwd>voltage-gated Na<sup>+</sup> channel</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Although the death rate from breast cancer (BCa) is falling in many countries, it is still the leading cause of cancer-related deaths in women, due to metastasis.1,2 To metastasize, tumour cells undergo a complex sequence of events, including adhesion/detachment, migration, and invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Given that treatment options for metastatic BCa are mainly restricted to palliation, it is necessary to better understand the mechanism(s) involved in order to identify new targets and develop new therapies.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Voltage-gated Na+ channels (VGSCs) contain one pore-forming α subunit with smaller β subunits.4 There are nine α subunits, Nav1.1-Nav1.9, and four β subunits, β1-β4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The β subunits are members of the immunoglobulin superfamily of cell adhesion molecules (CAMs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>They modulate channel gating, and can function as CAMs both in the presence and absence of α subunits.5 They are substrates for secretase cleavage, releasing soluble intracellular domains that may regulate gene expression.6 The β1 subunit (gene: SCN1B) participates in trans-homophilic adhesion, resulting in cellular aggregation and cytoskeleton recruitment.7,8 β1 also interacts heterophilically with other CAMs, including β2, contactin, neurofascins, NrCAM, N-cadherin9–12 and the extracellular matrix protein, tenascin-R.13 β1 mediates neurite outgrowth by a trans-homophilic adhesion mechanism that requires fyn kinase, contactin and γ-secretase activity.5,14,15 β1 plays a critical role during central nervous system (CNS) development, regulating electrical excitability, proliferation, fasciculation, pathfinding and migration.15–17 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>VGSCs are widely expressed in cancers, and contribute to cellular behaviours associated with metastasis.18,19 In BCa, the predominant α subunit, Nav1.5 (gene: SCN5A), is expressed in MDA-MB-231 cells, where Na+ current potentiates invasion by enhancing cysteine cathepsin activity.20–22 SCN5A is up-regulated in tumours, associating with recurrence, metastasis and reduced survival.20,23 β1 is the predominant β subunit in MCF-7 cells, where it enhances cell-substrate adhesion, but slows transwell migration.24 Over-expression of β1 in MDA-MB-231 cells increases cell-cell adhesion and Na+ current.24 Both α and β1 subunits are expressed in lamellipodia of MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells, suggesting that their expression and function are not mutually exclusive.23 Thus, VGSC α and β subunits appear to play complex, dynamic roles in metastatic BCa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>However, the functional significance of β1-dependent adhesion, and its contribution to tumour growth and metastasis, are unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Our aim here was to study the involvement of β1 in BCa progression in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>We show that SCN1B mRNA/β1 protein are upregulated in BCa specimens, compared with normal breast tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Up-regulation of β1 potentiates tumour growth and metastasis in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In addition, β1 increases process outgrowth on BCa cells via a trans-homophilic adhesion mechanism that requires fyn kinase and Na+ current. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>We propose that β1 enhances metastatic behaviour of BCa cells by recapitulating mechanism(s) that are critical for neuronal migration during CNS development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that β1 warrants further study as a potential biomarker/therapeutic target. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In silico analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>SCN1B expression in microarrays was studied using Oncomine.25 Meta-analysis of correlations between SCN1B expression and histoclinical characteristics across multiple datasets was as described.26 Datasets, patients, specimen characteristics and assay methods are detailed/referenced at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oncomine.org">http://www.oncomine.org</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Molecular identity of all BCa cell lines was confirmed by short tandem repeat analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>All cell lines were grown in Dulbecco's modified eagle medium (DMEM) supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum and 4 mM l-glutamine.23 BT474 and SKBR3 cells were a gift from J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Rae, University of Michigan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells were a gift from M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Djamgoz, Imperial College London. “Control” MDA-MB-231 cells stably expressing enhanced green fluorescent protein (GFP) or MDA-MB-231 cells over-expressing β1-GFP C-terminal fusion24 (hereafter called “MDA-MB-231-β1” cells) were maintained in medium containing selective antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>MCF-10A cells were a gift from N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Maitland, University of York. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>R1610 Chinese hamster lung (CHL) fibroblasts and CHL fibroblasts stably expressing β1 were gifts from L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Isom, University of Michigan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>MDA-MB-231-GFP and MDA-MB-231 β1-GFP cells were stably transduced with recombinant lentivirus for firefly luciferase (AMS Biotechnology). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>For experiments using estrogen, MCF-7 cells were maintained in phenol red-free DMEM supplemented with 5% charcoal-stripped fetal bovine serum and 4 mM L-glutamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Cells were confirmed as mycoplasma-free using the DAPI method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Pharmacology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Tetrodotoxin (TTX) was diluted in culture medium to 30 µM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Staurosporine, PP2, estradiol and fulvestrant were prepared as stocks in DMSO and then diluted in culture medium to 10 nM−30 µM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In assays that exceeded 24 h, treatments were replaced daily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The effect of TTX on invasion was determined using Matrigel assays.23 The effect of staurosporine on apoptosis was determined using DeadEnd fluorometric TUNEL assays (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The effect of PP2 on cell viability and proliferation was determined using trypan blue and MTT assays.23 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation and RT-qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis were as described.27 QPCR was carried out using triplicate 12-µl reactions containing 20ng cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Amplification conditions were: 95°C for 30 s followed by 35 cycles of 95°C for 5 s and 60°C for 10 s on a Bio-Rad thermal cycler. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Relative gene expression was quantitated using the comparative CT method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Primers are in Supporting Information Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Patient tissue samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The study cohort contained tissue samples from 66 BCa cases obtained from the Breast Cancer Campaign Tissue Bank under tissue request number TR000017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Patients provided consent to the Breast Cancer Campaign Tissue Bank for their tissues to be used for research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The samples came from women aged 28–89 years, who were diagnosed between February 1992 and February 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>For 40 cases (60%), tumour samples came with matched surrounding normal breast tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Clinical and histopathological data were available for all cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry was performed on 5µm-thick sections using the EnVision+ System-HRP kit (Dako). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Sections were deparaffinized in Histo-Clear (National Diagnostics) followed by antigen retrieval at 95°C for 30 min in Target Retrieval Solution (Dako). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Sections were incubated with anti-β1 antibody (1:25; Abgent) for 30 mins and counterstained with dilute Mayer's hematoxylin and mounted in Faramount medium (Dako). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Slides were scanned at 40× using an Aperio ScanScope. β1 immunoreactivity was scored by two independent investigators (WJB and RMS, a breast histopathologist) using the Allred method.28 Briefly, the proportion of β1-positive cells was given a score (none: 0; &lt;1/100: 1; 1/100 to 1/10: 2; 1/10 to 1/3: 3; 1/3 to 2/3: 4; &gt;2/3: 5), followed by the intensity of staining (none: 0; weak: 1; intermediate: 2; strong: 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For each section, the proportion and intensity scores were summed to give a total score (0–8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>A score of 0–4 was considered “low” and 5–8 was considered “high.” Scoring was performed without prior knowledge of outcome data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Experiments were approved by the University of York Ethical Review Process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE was performed as described.15,29 The following antibodies were used: rabbit anti-β1 (1:100; Abgent), mouse anti-fyn (1:1,000; BioLegend), mouse anti-CD44 (1:1,000; AbD Serotec); rabbit anti-E-cadherin (1:1,000; Cell Signaling Technology); mouse anti-β-actin (1:30,000; Proteintech); and mouse anti-α-tubulin (1:10,000; Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Signals were quantified using ImageJ software. α-tubulin was used as loading control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Orthotopic breast tumour model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All animal procedures were carried out after approval by the University of York Ethical Review Process and under authority of a UK Home Office Project Licence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Six-week-old female Rag2−/− Il2rg−/− mice (mean weight: 16.6 ± 0.2 g) were obtained from the Yorkshire Cancer Research Unit, University of York. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Mice (4–5 per specific pathogen free cage) were selected at random for surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A 1 × 106 control MDA-MB-231-GFP or MDA-MB-231-β1-GFP cells expressing luciferase were suspended in Matrigel (20% v/v in saline) and injected into the left and right inguinal mammary fat pad of each animal whilst under isoflurane anaesthesia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A total of 13 mice were used (six injected with control cells and seven with β1 cells) across three independent replicated experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Tumour growth was monitored weekly by bioluminescence imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Mice were given intraperitoneal injection of D-luciferin in PBS (150 mg kg−1) and bioluminescence was visualized 10 min later under isoflurane anaesthesia using an IVIS100 system (PerkinElmer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Bioluminescence from tumours was quantified within manually defined regions of interest using Living Image software (PerkinElmer) and expressed as photon flux. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To quantify bioluminescence at sites of metastasis, mice were euthanized ∼10 min after injection with D-luciferin, primary tumours were removed and internal organs were exposed by dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Bioluminescence was measured from the entire mouse and then individual organs were removed for separate imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Measurements of the length and width of each tumour (in mm) were taken from mice daily with callipers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Tumour volume was calculated as 0.5 × (length × width2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Mice were euthanized when primary tumours reached 10% of starting body weight, or at the first sign of discomfort from metastatic burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Tumours and organ sites of metastasis were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde and frozen.14 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry (IHC) and immunocytochemistry (ICC) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For H&amp;E staining, sections were stained with Gill's hematoxylin and eosin Y and then scanned at 20X using a Zeiss AxioScan.Z1 slide scanner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The following primary antibodies were used for IHC/ICC15: rabbit anti-Ki67 (1:5,000; Abcam); rabbit anti-activated caspase-3 (1:200; R&amp;D Systems); rabbit anti-CD31 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology); mouse anti-skeletal myosin (1:400; Sigma); rabbit anti-β1 (1:200; Abgent); mouse anti-fyn (1:100; BioLegend); mouse anti-CD44 (1:100; AbD Serotec); rabbit anti-E-cadherin (1:200; Cell Signaling Technology); mouse anti-human nuclear antigen (HNA; 1:100; Millipore). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies were Alexa-568-conjugated goat anti mouse/rabbit, unless stated otherwise (1:500; Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Samples were mounted in Prolong Gold with DAPI (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Some samples were stained with Alexa-633-phalloidin (1:25; Invitrogen).23 Samples were viewed using 20× objectives on a Nikon Eclipse TE200 fluorescent microscope, or Zeiss Axio Observer.Z1 microscope with LSM 710 confocal laser scanner. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Image analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Images were exported into ImageJ for processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Confocal Z-series projections were flattened using the maximum signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Brightness/contrast was adjusted using the ImageJ “Auto” function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>ICC colocalization was evaluated using ImageJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Intensity correlation analysis (ICA) was performed on individual cells delineated with the freehand selection tool, and for each cell, the intensity correlation quotient (ICQ) was computed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For signal intensities that vary together, indicating colocalization, 0 &lt; ICQ ≤ 0.5, whereas for segregated staining, −0.5 ≤ ICQ &lt; 0.30 Measurements were from 20 cells per line. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The following measurements were made on IHC sections, for three mice per treatment group: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Density of Ki67+ or activated caspase-3+ cells17: the number of Ki67+ nuclei or active caspase-3+ cells was counted per 20X field of view. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Tumour vascularity31: the number of CD31+ vessels was counted per 20X field of view. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Metastasis to liver/lungs/spleen32: the number of GFP+ metastatic foci was counted per 20X field of view. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Length of tumour cell processes and muscle fibers: The longest visible process on cancer cells and the total length of individual muscle fibers within 20× fields of view was measured using the freeform line function in ImageJ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>VEGF ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured in 24-well plates (5 × 104/well). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>After 1, 2, and 3 days, culture medium was removed from individual wells and stored at −20°C until analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>VEGF secretion was determined by ELISA (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Measurements were obtained from duplicate wells from three repeat experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Process outgrowth assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Process outgrowth assays were based on Ref.14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Parental CHL fibroblasts or CHL fibroblasts expressing β1 were grown to confluence on 13mm diameter coverslips. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Freshly dissociated BCa cells were plated (2 × 104 cells/well) on top of the monolayers and allowed to grow for 24–48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Cultures were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde and the cancer cells were visualized with anti-GFP (1:1,000; NeuroMab), or anti-cytokeratin 18 (1:500; BioLegend) followed by Alexa-568-conjugated goat anti-mouse (1:500). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Images were acquired using a Nikon Eclipse TE200 fluorescent microscope with 40× objective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The longest process on each of the first 50 randomly selected, isolated cancer cells was measured using ImageJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Measurements were obtained from three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Deletion of β1 Ig domain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The Ig domain of β1 (amino acids 40–124) in pEGFPN124 was deleted using the Phusion site-directed mutagenesis kit (Thermo Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The β1Δ40–124-GFP construct was sequenced, and then transfected into MDA-MB-231 cells using Fugene (Roche).24 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>RNA interference </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>SiGENOME SMARTpool siRNA targeting FYN and siGENOME Non-Targeting siRNA Pool #1 (Dharmacon) were used at 50 nM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Transfection was performed using Dharmafect 1 reagent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Transfection efficiency was confirmed to be ≥90% using siGENOME positive control targeting GAPDH (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>S5c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and process outgrowth assay were performed 96h after transfection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Data are mean and SEM unless stated otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Matrix data were plotted using Matrix2png software.33 Statistical significance was determined with t tests or Mann–Whitney tests, and multiple comparisons were made using ANOVA and Tukey post hoc tests, unless stated otherwise. p values computed by Oncomine were corrected for multiple comparisons by Bonferroni method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Correlation between ESR1 and SCN1B expression was determined using Pearson's r test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Association between categorical classification criteria was determined with Fisher's exact test, or χ2 test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>For meta-analysis of association between SCN1B expression and histoclinical characteristics across multiple datasets, the binomial test was used.26 The binomial test p value indicates whether or not one criterion was associated with another in the observed number of datasets by chance, given the number of datasets studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier curves for survival were compared by log-rank tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Percent survival and hazard ratios are presented with 95% confidence intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Results were considered significant at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>β1 mRNA and protein are present in breast tumours </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We have previously shown that β1 mRNA/protein are expressed in BCa cell lines.24 Here, we used Oncomine to study the expression of SCN1B mRNA in normal breast and BCa specimens across multiple microarrays. SCN1B was expressed at a significantly higher level in BCa compared with normal breast in two out of eight datasets in which differential data were available (1.7-fold, p &lt; 0.05; and &gt;2.2-fold, p &lt; 0.05; Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>1a and 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We next performed a meta-analysis to investigate whether SCN1B expression correlates with histoclinical characteristics across multiple datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>High SCN1B expression associated with ER status in 8/21 (38.1%) of datasets (p &lt; 0.0001; Supporting Information Table S2; Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>S1a and S1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>There was no significant association between SCN1B and age, pathological tumour size, grade, recurrence, progesterone receptor, or HER2 status across the same datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Up-regulation of SCN1B expression in ER+ tumours correlated with several genomic neighbours on chromosome 19q (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>S1c).26 However, mRNA levels of the two SCN1B splice variants, β1 and β1B,34 which are both expressed across a panel of BCa cell lines (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>S1d and S1e), were unchanged in MCF-7 cells following treatment with estrogen or fulvestrant (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>S1f), suggesting that SCN1B is not estrogen-regulated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>β1 mRNA and protein expression in breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>(a) Expression of SCN1B mRNA in invasive lobular breast carcinoma (ILBCa) vs. normal in the Radvanyi Breast dataset (n = 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>(b) Expression of SCN1B in invasive ductal breast cancer (IDBCa) and ILBCa in the Turashvili Breast dataset (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Box plot dots, maximum and minimum values; whiskers, 90th and 10th percentile values; and horizontal lines, 75th, 50th, and 25th percentile values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>(c) Representative images of non-cancer breast tissue and (d) breast tumour tissue in which β1 was (i) absent, (ii) weakly positive, and (iii) strongly positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Insets, higher magnification images of tumour cells, scale bar, 50µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(e) Mean Allred score for normal breast and tumour samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM (n = 66). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(f) Kaplan–Meier analysis comparing BCa-specific survival of those with “low” (score &lt;5) vs. “high” (score ≥ 5) β1 expression (n = 62). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(g) Western blot of β1 and fyn in the MCF-10A non-cancer mammary epithelial cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>(h) Western blot of β1 and fyn across a panel of BCa cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Positive control = rat brain lysate. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We next studied the expression of β1 at protein level in human tissue samples by IHC. β1 immunoreactivity was mainly in the cytoplasm of epithelial and carcinoma cells, with variable expression at the plasma membrane ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>1c and 1d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This pattern of expression is consistent with previous observations in neurons and cancer cell lines.14,16,23 β1 expression was significantly higher in tumour than normal, non-cancer breast tissue samples (p &lt; 0.001; Fig. 1e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Of the cases where tumour had matched surrounding non-cancer tissue, 27 (68%) had higher β1 in tumour than non-cancer tissue, 7 (17%) had the same level of β1 in tumour and non-cancer tissue, and 6 (15%) had lower expression in tumour than non-cancer tissue. β1 expression in the tumour did not correlate with age, ER status, grade, menopausal status, or node status (Supporting Information Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Similarly, there was no relationship with BCa-specific survival ( Fig. 1f, Supporting Information Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the IHC data, β1 was also expressed at protein level in the non-cancer mammary epithelial MCF-10A cell line and across a panel of BCa cell lines (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>1g and 1h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Together, these data suggest that β1 may be up-regulated in a unique subset of breast cancers at mRNA and protein level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>β1 promotes tumour growth and vascularization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>We next investigated the role of β1 in tumour growth and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We orthotopically implanted luciferase-expressing MDA-MB-231 or MDA-MB-231-β1 cells into the mammary fat pads of female Rag2−/− Il2rg−/− mice and monitored tumour growth by bioluminescent imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>We chose this model because MDA-MB-231 cells rapidly form palpable tumours following orthotopic implantation, and the cells readily metastasise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>MDA-MB-231 cells express very low endogenous β1 (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>S2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>By contrast, MDA-MB-231-β1 cells over-express β1-GFP by &gt;40-fold relative to endogenous β1 (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>S2a and S2b).24 Over-expression of β1 had no effect on expression of CD44 or E-cadherin (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>S2c–S2e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Importantly, luciferase activity and GFP expression were very similar in both cell lines (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>S3a–S3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Photon flux from MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours increased faster than control MDA-MB-231 tumours, becoming statistically significant after 4 weeks ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>2a and 2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>To confirm the bioluminescent imaging data, we also analyzed tumour growth by daily calliper measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The volume of MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours increased more rapidly than MDA-MB-231 tumours, closely agreeing with the bioluminescent data ( Fig. 2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>During the 5-week study period, MDA-MB-231-β1 primary tumour burden reached 10% of starting body weight in 71% of mice, compared with only 17% for control tumours ( Fig. 2d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The survival of mice bearing MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours was significantly reduced compared to those bearing control tumours (p &lt; 0.05; hazard ratio = 6.3 [1.4–27.8]; Fig. 2e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrate that over-expression of β1 enhanced the growth of breast tumours, thus reducing survival. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Effect of β1 over-expression on breast tumour growth in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>MDA-MB-231 (“Control”) and MDA-MB-231-β1 (“β1”) cells were implanted into the inguinal mammary fat pads of female Rag2−/− Il2rg−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(a) Representative bioluminescent images of mice bearing control and β1 tumours, 4 weeks after implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>(b) Bioluminescence measured from primary tumours on the indicated days post-implantation (n ≥ 12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM; **p &lt; 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>(c) Calculated volume derived from calliper measurement of primary tumours over the same period (n ≥ 12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(d) Percentage of mice whose primary tumour burden reached 10% of starting body weight within the 5-week tumour growth period is shown for control and β1 tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>(e) Kaplan–Meier analysis comparing overall survival of mice bearing control and β1 tumours (n = 13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(f) Images of control and β1 tumour tissue sections stained with H&amp;E showing (i) mammary fat pad and (ii) skeletal muscle invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Arrows, infiltration of tumour cells (T) into fibroadipose tissue (F) or skeletal muscle fibers (M). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Insets, higher magnification images of invading tumour cells, scale bar, 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>(G) Invasion of control MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells ± TTX (30 µM) for 48 hr (n = 12; *p &lt; 0.05; Neuman–Keuls test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We next studied the structure and composition of the primary tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Both MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours were broadly similar, containing some invasion into surrounding fibroadipose tissue and skeletal muscle ( Fig. 2f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Although the in vitro invasiveness of MDA-MB-231-β1 cells was moderately higher than control MDA-MB-231 cells, blockade of α subunits with TTX inhibited invasion of both cell lines to a similar extent (p &lt; 0.05, Fig. 2g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Thus, α-subunit-dependent invasion of MDA-MB-231 cells20,21 appears to be unaffected by β1 over-expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The density of Ki67+ cycling cells was unchanged in MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours, compared to control tumours ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>3a and 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>However, the density of apoptotic cells expressing activated caspase-3 was significantly reduced by 84% in MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours, compared to control tumours (p &lt; 0.001; Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>3c and 3d). In vitro, staurosporine-induced apoptosis was significantly reduced in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells, compared to control MDA-MB-231 cells ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>3e and 3f), suggesting, together with the tumour data, that β1 over-expression enhances resistance to apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Finally, the density of vascular structures, revealed by labelling blood vessels with an antibody to the endothelial marker CD31, significantly increased by 1.5-fold in MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours, compared to control tumours, and VEGF secretion in vitro was significantly higher in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells than control MDA-MB-231 cells (p &lt; 0.01; Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>3g−3i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In summary, these data suggest that β1 over-expression increased the growth of MDA-MB-231 tumours, not by altering the density of cycling cells in the population, but, instead by reducing apoptosis and enhancing angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Effect of β1 upregulation on proliferation, apoptosis and angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>(a) Control and β1 tumour sections stained with anti-Ki67 (red) and DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>(b) Ki67-positive nuclei per field of view for control and β1 tumours (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>(c) Control and β1 tumour sections stained with anti-activated caspase-3 (red) and DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>(d) Activated caspase-3-positive cells per field of view for control and β1 tumours (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>(e) Images of control and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells treated for 24 hr with/without 0.5 µM staurosporine, analyzed by TUNEL assay (red), counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>(f) Proportion (%) of TUNEL-positive nuclei per field of view (n = 60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>(g) Blood vessels stained with endothelial marker CD31 (red) and DAPI (blue) in control and β1 tumour sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>(h) CD31-positive blood vessels per field of view for control and β1 tumours (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(i) VEGF content of culture medium of control and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells 1–3 days after plating (n = 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>β1 potentiates metastasis to liver and lungs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We monitored metastasis after 5 weeks by bioluminescent imaging following post mortem resection of primary tumours ( Fig. 4a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Although photon flux was slightly increased in mice bearing MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours compared those bearing MDA-MB-231 tumours, and in the liver and lungs ex vivo, this difference was not statistically significant ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>4b and 4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>To study metastasis to these organs in more detail at the cellular level, using a more sensitive method, we measured the density of GFP-expressing tumour cells within tissue sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>We detected GFP+ cells in sections both in isolation, and in multicellular foci ( Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>4d, 4f, and 4h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>GFP was co-expressed in cells with HNA (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>S3e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>HNA is present in human MDA-MB-231 cells, but absent in mouse cells, thus confirming that GFP expression was retained in the tumour cells once they had metastasized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In the spleen, the number of GFP+ cells per field of view was unchanged between groups ( Fig. 4e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>However, the number of GFP+ cells per field of view was significantly increased, by 5.9- and 3.0-fold, respectively, in the liver and lungs of MDA-MB-231-β1 tumour-bearing mice, compared to control (p &lt; 0.05 and 0.001, respectively; Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>4g and 4i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Thus, β1 over-expression promoted metastasis to the liver and lungs, but not the spleen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Effect of β1 over-expression on breast cancer metastasis in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>At 5 weeks following implantation, control and β1 tumours were removed post mortem prior to bioluminescent imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>(a) Representative bioluminescent images of metastases from control and β1 tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>(b) Bioluminescence measured from the indicated anatomical sites from control and β1 tumour-bearing mice (n ≥ 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>(c) Bioluminescence measured ex vivo from the spleen, liver, and lungs of control and β1 tumour-bearing mice (n ≥ 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>(d) Spleen sections from control and β1 tumour-bearing mice showing GFP signal (green) and DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>(e) GFP-positive cells per field of view of spleen (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>(f) Liver sections from control and β1 tumour-bearing mice showing GFP signal (green) and DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>(g) GFP-positive cells per field of view of liver (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>(h) Lung sections from control and β1 tumour-bearing mice showing GFP signal and DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>(i) GFP-positive cells per field of view of lung (n = 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Bars are mean + SEM; *p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f4"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>β1 promotes process outgrowth </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Enhancement of protrusions, e.g., pseudopodia, from cells is associated with increased motility in 3D cultures, invasion, and metastasis.35–37 Over-expression of β1 in MDA-MB-231 cells increases the length of processes protruding from the cell body in vitro.24 We therefore postulated that β1 might regulate cellular morphology in our tumour model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In the periphery of tumour sections, MDA-MB-231-β1 cells infiltrating surrounding skeletal muscle appeared more densely packed, and had a more elongate morphology than MDA-MB-231 cells ( Fig. 5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In these sections, processes extending from MDA-MB-231-β1 cells were significantly longer than processes on MDA-MB-231 cells ( Fig. 5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The length of muscle fibers was unchanged between tumour types ( Fig. 5c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Effect of β1 on process outgrowth in breast cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(a) Regions of skeletal muscle infiltration in control (i,iii,v) and β1 (ii,iv,vi) tumour sections showing GFP signal (green) and skeletal fast myosin (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate cells in β1 tumours that have more elongate processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Insets, higher magnification images of tumour cells showing processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Inset scale bar, 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>(b) Process length (µm) of control MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells in tumours (n ≥ 134 cells/each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(c) Length (µm) of muscle fibers in control and β1 tumours (n ≥ 79). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>(d) Images of MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL fibroblast monolayers, and stained with anti-GFP antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>(e) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers (n = 300). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(f) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231-β1Δ40–124 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers (n = 300). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>(g) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± 30 µM TTX (n ≥ 144). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>(h) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± 30 µM TTX (n = 150). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Bars are mean + SEM; ***p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>In the nervous system, β1 regulates neuronal morphology and neurite outgrowth via trans-homophilic adhesion.15 We therefore set out to test the hypothesis that this neuronal function of β1 is recapitulated when it is expressed in BCa cells, enhancing process outgrowth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>We examined the morphology of BCa cells plated on monolayers of control and β1-expressing CHL fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>CHL cells were chosen because they do not express endogenous β subunits.14 When plated on CHL cells, MDA-MB-231 cells produced thin processes with foci at the tips, morphologically similar to neurites with growth cones (Fig. 5d).15 MDA-MB-231 cells did not show any increase in process length when grown on β1-expressing monolayers ( Fig. 5e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>However, MDA-MB-231-β1 cells did respond, such that β1-expressing monolayers increased process length by 1.6-fold (p &lt; 0.001; Fig. 5e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A similar result was observed for MCF-7 cells, which express endogenous β1 (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>S4a and S4b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>There was no increase in process length of MDA-MB-231 cells over-expressing the Ig domain-deficient mutant β1Δ40–124 when grown on β1-expressing monolayers ( Fig. 5f), suggesting that the adhesion domain is required for β1-mediated process outgrowth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>In cerebellar granule neurons, β1-mediated neurite outgrowth requires the presence of Nav1.6 and is inhibited by the VGSC pore-blocking toxin TTX.16 We found that TTX (30 µM) inhibited β1-mediated process outgrowth in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (p &lt; 0.001; Fig. 5h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>However, it had no effect on process outgrowth in native MDA-MB-231 cells, which do not respond to β1-expressing fibroblasts (Fig. 5g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Together, these data suggest that β1 enhances process outgrowth on BCa cells via trans-homophilic adhesion between β1 expressed on the BCa cell, and β1 expressed on the adjacent fibroblast, similar to its function in neurons.14 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>β1-mediated process outgrowth requires fyn kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>In neurons, β1 increases neurite length via fyn kinase.15 CAM-mediated activation of fyn kinase is proposed to initiate the fyn-focal adhesion kinase (FAK) pathway, activating extracellular signal-regulated kinase 1/2, leading to neurite outgrowth.38 Fyn is upregulated in a number of cancers, where it contributes to an invasive phenotype.39 We found that fyn, like β1, was expressed in MCF-10A cells and BCa cell lines (Fig. 1g and 1h, Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>S2f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Given that fyn is required for β1-mediated neurite outgrowth, and fyn and β1 are coexpressed in brain membranes,15 we hypothesized that fyn and β1 may colocalize in BCa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>In MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells, β1 was expressed throughout the cytoplasm, on perinuclear internal membranes and lamellipodia ( Fig. 6a), consistent with previous observations, although the expression of β1 was clearly lower in the former.23 Importantly, fyn showed a broadly similar distribution to β1, with expression strongest on F-actin-rich lamellipodia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Intensity correlation analysis gave ICQ values &gt;0, indicating that the signals for β1 and fyn varied together30 ( Fig. 6b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>This result is consistent with β1 colocalizing with fyn. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig06" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>A mechanism for β1-mediated process outgrowth and migration in BCa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>(a) Images of MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Green: anti-β1 for parental MDA-MB-231 (with Alexa-488-conjugated secondary antibody) and GFP signal for MDA-MB-231-β1; red: anti-fyn; magenta: phalloidin to label the actin cytoskeleton; blue: DAPI to label nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>White boxes indicate locations of inset zoomed images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Phalloidin is omitted from merged image for clarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>(b) Intensity correlation-quotients (ICQ) for β1 and fyn in MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (n = 20/each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>(c) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± 5 µM PP2 (n ≥ 147). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>(d) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± 5 µM PP2 (n ≥ 223). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>(e) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± fyn siRNA (n = 150). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>(f) Process length (µm) of MDA-MB-231-β1 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± fyn siRNA (n = 150). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>(g) A model of possible signalling mechanism underlying β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells. β1 from an adjacent fibroblast or cancer cell interacts in trans with β1 on the BCa cell, initiating a signaling cascade via fyn kinase, leading to process outgrowth.15 Na+ conductance through the pore-forming α subunit is also required.16 Figure was produced using Science Slides software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Bars are mean + SEM; ***p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-f6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>We next investigated whether fyn activity is involved in β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Inclusion of the src family kinase inhibitor PP2 (5 µM) in the assay inhibited β1-mediated process outgrowth in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (p &lt; 0.001; Fig. 6d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>However, it had no effect on process outgrowth in control MDA-MB-231 cells, which do not respond to β1-expressing fibroblasts ( Fig. 6c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Importantly, 5 µM PP2 had no effect on cellular viability or proliferation (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>S5a and S5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>To establish whether fyn is specifically required for β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells over other members of the src family that are also inhibited by PP2, we next transiently down-regulated the expression of fyn in BCa cells using siRNA, prior to plating on fibroblast monolayers (Supporting Information Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>S5d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Down-regulation of fyn with siRNA abrogated β1-mediated process outgrowth in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (p &lt; 0.001; Fig. 6f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>However, there was no effect on baseline process outgrowth in control MDA-MB-231 cells ( Fig. 6e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>PP2 and fyn siRNA also inhibited β1-mediated process outgrowth in MCF-7 cells (Supporting Information Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>S4c and S4d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>In summary, blocking fyn expression/activity with PP2 or siRNA inhibited β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that fyn is a critical signalling intermediary in the mechanism underlying β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells (Fig. 6g), as it is in neurons.15 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>VGSCs are expressed in cells from a number of different cancers, where they are proposed to play a role in potentiating metastasis.18 VGSCs are unique among ion channels in that their “auxiliary” β subunits not only modulate channel activity, but are also CAMs.5 Expression of β subunits has been reported in breast, bone, cervical, colorectal, lung, and prostate cancer cell lines, and β1 is the dominant isoform in breast, cervical, lung and prostate cancer cell lines (reviewed in Ref.19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>However, in vivo evidence for β subunit expression in cancer is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>We found that β1 was up-regulated at mRNA and protein level in BCa specimens compared with non-cancer tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Similarly, β1 was expressed across a panel of BCa cell lines, although the relative mRNA and protein levels differed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>In addition, in tumour specimens, the positive relationship between SCN1B mRNA and ER status was not reflected at the protein level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Discrepancy between mRNA and protein levels has been reported previously for other VGSCs in other tissues.24,40,41 Therefore, the relationship between SCN1B mRNA and β1 protein levels may be subject to complex regulation, highlighting the critical importance of studying biomarker expression at both mRNA and protein levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>We did not observe a relationship between β1 expression and outcome in patient tumour specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>This may be due to the relatively small size of the dataset, and it would be worthwhile in the future to validate the data presented here against larger cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our data show that SCN1B/β1 is up-regulated at the mRNA and protein level in BCa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>We propose that β1 warrants further study as a potential biomarker for BCa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>β1 over-expression increased tumour growth in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this contrasts with the observation that over-expression of β1 slightly reduces proliferation in vitro,24 suggesting that the tumour microenvironment might be critical to the in vivo tumour-promoting function of β1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>In support of this, apoptosis was reduced in MDA-MB-231-β1 tumours, which may account for their increased size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Cell adhesion can promote apoptosis suppression in cancer cells via FAK activation42 and further work is required to establish whether or not β1-dependent adhesion promotes tumour cell survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>There was increased density of vascular structures in the β1 over-expressing tumours, and VEGF secretion was increased in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells in vitro, suggesting that β1 may enhance angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Several classes of CAMs are known to promote angiogenesis, including integrins, cadherins, and immunoglobulin superfamily CAMs,43 raising the possibility that β1 may contribute to promoting blood vessel development through heterophilic adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, over-expression of β2 in prostate cancer cells has the reverse effect, reducing tumour growth.44 Despite its structural similarity to β1, β2 appears to play a different role in the CNS, and is not essential for postnatal development.5 Thus, as in the CNS, different β subunits may perform distinct functions in different cancer microenvironments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>β1 is a multifunctional molecule that plays a critical role during CNS development.5 Although β1 is essential for regulating excitability through fine-tuning VGSC gating and kinetics,16 its function as a CAM is required for neurite outgrowth, migration, fasciculation and synaptic connectivity.15–17 In fact, β1 may function as a CAM, independent of channel activity under certain conditions.5 Other CAMs that regulate neuronal migration and pathfinding have been reported in tumours, where they play a pathological role and associate with poor prognosis.45 It is therefore not unreasonable to expect that β1 may do the same. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>We showed previously that β1 enhances cell-cell adhesion and cell-substrate adhesion in BCa cells in vitro.24 In the present study, we found that β1 over-expression in MDA-MB-231 cells caused a more elongate cellular morphology within tumours, and enhanced process outgrowth in vitro via trans-homophilic adhesion. β1-mediated process outgrowth did not occur in control MDA-MB-231 cells, which express a low level of endogenous β1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>The latter result suggests that β1 expression on the tumour cell may need to be above a threshold in order to induce process outgrowth and enhance tumour growth and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>We found that, as in neurons,15 β1-mediated process outgrowth in BCa cells required fyn kinase. β1-mediated neurite outgrowth in neurons is also activity-dependent.16 Interestingly, Na+ current promotes src family kinase activity and pro-invasive morphology in MDA-MB-231 cells,46 which fits with other data showing that α subunits potentiate the invasiveness of BCa cells.20–22,46,47 We found that TTX inhibited β1-mediated process outgrowth in MDA-MB-231-β1 cells, suggesting that, as in neurons,16 α subunit function is required (Fig. 6g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Thus, Nav1.5 and β1 may both promote mesenchymal-like elongate morphology in BCa cells, via a combination of Na+ current and adhesion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that β1 can enhance tumour growth and metastasis via a trans-homophilic adhesion mechanism that enhances process outgrowth on metastatic tumour cells, enabling their dissemination from the primary tumour and into surrounding tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>This would fit with the observation that outgrowth of processes, e.g., pseudopodia, from cancer cells increases motility, invasion, and metastasis.35–37 Thus, β1 may be involved in collective cell migration and invasion during tumour spreading,48,49 similar to its role in pathfinding and fasciculation during CNS development.15,17 However, we do not yet know whether β1 interactions in trans occur between adjacent tumour cells, or between tumour cells and stromal cells, or both. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Further complexity is added by the possibility that β1 may interact heterophilically with other CAMs,9–12 and/or extracellular matrix proteins13 present in the tumour microenvironment, dependent on cell types/status within the tumour. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Our data support the hypothesis that SCN1B/β1 recapitulates its neurodevelopmental role to promote breast tumour growth and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>This fits with a growing body of evidence implicating VGSCs as mediators of an invasive/metastatic phenotype.19 Up-regulation of genes, e.g. SCN1B, required for normal migration and invasion processes during development, may represent a critical event in the progression towards metastasis.50 We therefore propose that (i) β1 may represent a novel biomarker during disease development, and (ii) targeting β1-mediated adhesion interactions may have potential as novel anti-cancer therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The authors acknowledge the role of the Breast Cancer Campaign Tissue Bank in collecting and making available the samples used in the generation of this publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>1AutierPBoniolMLa VecchiaCDisparities in breast cancer mortality trends between 30 European countries: retrospective trend analysis of WHO mortality databaseBMJ (Clin Res Ed)2010341c3620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>2JemalABrayFCenterMMGlobal cancer statisticsCA Cancer J Clin201161699021296855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>3SteegPSTheodorescuDMetastasis: a therapeutic target for cancerNat Clin Pract Oncol2008520621918253104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>4CatterallWAFrom ionic currents to molecular mechanisms: the structure and function of voltage-gated sodium channelsNeuron200026132510798388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>5BrackenburyWJIsomLLNa channel beta subunits: overachievers of the ion channel familyFront Pharmacol201125322007171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>6KimDYCareyBWWangHBACE1 regulates voltage-gated sodium channels and neuronal activityNat Cell Biol200797556417576410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>7MalhotraJDKazen-GillespieKHortschMSodium channel β subunits mediate homophilic cell adhesion and recruit ankyrin to points of cell-cell contactJ Biol Chem200027511383810753953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>8MalhotraJDKoopmannMCKazen-GillespieKAStructural requirements for interaction of sodium channel b1 subunits with ankyrinJ Biol Chem200227726681811997395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>9Kazarinova-NoyesKMalhotraJDMcEwenDPContactin associates with Na+ channels and increases their functional expressionJ Neurosci20012175172511567041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>10MalhotraJDThyagarajanVChenCTyrosine-phosphorylated and nonphosphorylated sodium channel beta1 subunits are differentially localized in cardiac myocytesJ Biol Chem2004279407485415272007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>11RatcliffeCFWestenbroekRECurtisRSodium channel beta1 and beta3 subunits associate with neurofascin through their extracellular immunoglobulin-like domainJ Cell Biol20011544273411470829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>12McEwenDPIsomLLHeterophilic interactions of sodium channel beta1 subunits with axonal and glial cell adhesion moleculesJ Biol Chem2004279527445215466474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>13XiaoZCRagsdaleDSMalhotraJDTenascin-R is a functional modulator of sodium channel beta subunitsJ Biol Chem199927426511710473612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>14DavisTHChenCIsomLLSodium channel beta1 subunits promote neurite outgrowth in cerebellar granule neuronsJ Biol Chem2004279514243215452131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>15BrackenburyWJDavisTHChenCVoltage-gated Na+ channel β1 subunit-mediated neurite outgrowth requires fyn kinase and contributes to central nervous system development in vivoJ Neurosci20082832465618354028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>16BrackenburyWJCalhounJDChenCFunctional reciprocity between Na+ channel Nav1.6 and β1 subunits in the coordinated regulation of excitability and neurite outgrowthProc Natl Acad Sci USA20101072283820133873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>17BrackenburyWJYuanYO'MalleyHAAbnormal neuronal patterning occurs during early postnatal brain development of Scn1b-null mice and precedes hyperexcitabilityProc Natl Acad Sci USA201311010899423277545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>18FraserSPOzerlat-GunduzIBrackenburyWJRegulation of voltage-gated sodium channel expression in cancer: hormones, growth factors and auto-regulationPhilos Trans R Soc Lond Ser B Biol Sci20143692013010524493753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>19BrackenburyWJVoltage-gated sodium channels and metastatic diseaseChannels (Austin)201263526122992466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>20FraserSPDissJKChioniAMVoltage-gated sodium channel expression and potentiation of human breast cancer metastasisClin Cancer Res2005115381916061851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>21RogerSBessonPLe GuennecJYInvolvement of a novel fast inward sodium current in the invasion capacity of a breast cancer cell lineBiochim Biophys Acta200316161071114561467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>22GilletLRogerSBessonPVoltage-gated sodium channel activity promotes cysteine cathepsin-dependent invasiveness and colony growth of human cancer cellsJ Biol Chem200928486809119176528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>23YangMKozminskiDJWoldLATherapeutic potential for phenytoin: targeting Na(v)1.5 sodium channels to reduce migration and invasion in metastatic breast cancerBreast Cancer Res Treat20121346031522678159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>24ChioniAMBrackenburyWJCalhounJDA novel adhesion molecule in human breast cancer cells: voltage-gated Na+ channel β1 subunitInt J Biochem Cell Biol20094112162719041953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>25TomlinsSARhodesDRPernerSRecurrent fusion of TMPRSS2 and ETS transcription factor genes in prostate cancerScience2005310644816254181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>26RhodesDRAteeqBCaoQAGTR1 overexpression defines a subset of breast cancer and confers sensitivity to losartan, an AGTR1 antagonistProc Natl Acad Sci USA200910610284919487683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>27MycielskaMEPalmerCPBrackenburyWJExpression of Na+-dependent citrate transport in a strongly metastatic human prostate cancer PC-3M cell line: regulation by voltage-gated Na+ channel activityJ Physiol200556339340815611019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>28HarveyJMClarkGMOsborneCKEstrogen receptor status by immunohistochemistry is superior to the ligand-binding assay for predicting response to adjuvant endocrine therapy in breast cancerJ Clin Oncol19991714748110334533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>29PatinoGAClaesLRFLopez-SantiagoLFA functional null mutation of SCN1B in a patient with Dravet syndromeJ Neurosci200929107647819710327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>30LiQLauAMorrisTJA syntaxin 1, Galpha(o), and N-type calcium channel complex at a presynaptic nerve terminal: analysis by quantitative immunocolocalizationJ Neurosci20042440708115102922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>31ConleySJGheordunescuEKakaralaPAntiangiogenic agents increase breast cancer stem cells via the generation of tumor hypoxiaProc Natl Acad Sci USA20121092784922308314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>32JallalHValentinoMLChenGA Src/Abl kinase inhibitor, SKI-606, blocks breast cancer invasion, growth, and metastasis in vitro and in vivoCancer Res2007671580817308097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>33PavlidisPNobleWSMatrix2png: a utility for visualizing matrix dataBioinformatics200319295612538257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>34PatinoGABrackenburyWJBaoYVoltage-gated Na+ channel β1B: a secreted cell adhesion molecule involved in human epilepsyJ Neurosci201131145779121994374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>35AgarwalNAdhikariASIyerSVMTBP suppresses cell migration and filopodia formation by inhibiting ACTN4Oncogene2013324627022370640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>36PhilipparURoussosETOserMA Mena invasion isoform potentiates EGF-induced carcinoma cell invasion and metastasisDev Cell2008158132819081071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>37MeyerASHughes-AlfordSKKayJE2D protrusion but not motility predicts growth factor–induced cancer cell migration in 3D collagenJ Cell Biol2012197721922665521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>38ManessPFSchachnerMNeural recognition molecules of the immunoglobulin superfamily: signaling transducers of axon guidance and neuronal migrationNat Neurosci200710192617189949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>39YadavVDenningMFFyn is induced by Ras/PI3K/Akt signaling and is required for enhanced invasion/migrationMol Carcinog2011503465221480388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>40BrackenburyWJDjamgozMBActivity-dependent regulation of voltage-gated Na+ channel expression in Mat-LyLu rat prostate cancer cell lineJ Physiol20065733435616543264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>41Lopez-SantiagoLFPertinMMorisodXSodium channel beta2 subunits regulate tetrodotoxin-sensitive sodium channels in small dorsal root ganglion neurons and modulate the response to painJ Neurosci20062679849416870743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>42KurenovaEXuLHYangXFocal adhesion kinase suppresses apoptosis by binding to the death domain of receptor-interacting proteinMol Cell Biol20042443617115121855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>43LiDMFengYMSignaling mechanism of cell adhesion molecules in breast cancer metastasis: potential therapeutic targetsBreast Cancer Res Treat201112872121499686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>44JanssonKHLynchJELepori-BuiNOverexpression of the VSSC-associated CAM, beta-2, enhances LNCaP cell metastasis associated behaviorProstate20127210809222127840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>45SchaferMKAltevogtPL1CAM malfunction in the nervous system and human carcinomasCell Mol Life Sci20106724253720237819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>46BrissonLDriffortVBenoistLNaV1.5 Na(+) channels allosterically regulate the NHE-1 exchanger and promote the activity of breast cancer cell invadopodiaJ Cell Sci201312648354223902689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>47BrissonLGilletLCalaghanSNa(V)1.5 enhances breast cancer cell invasiveness by increasing NHE1-dependent H(+) efflux in caveolaeOncogene2011302070621170089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>48WolfKWuYILiuYMulti-step pericellular proteolysis controls the transition from individual to collective cancer cell invasionNat Cell Biol2007989390417618273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>49FriedlPLockerJSahaiESegallJEClassifying collective cancer cell invasionNat Cell Biol2012147778322854810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>50LiottaLAClairTCancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Checkpoint for invasionNature200040528728810830943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><def-list><def-item><term>BCa</term><def><p>breast cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAM</term><def><p>cell adhesion molecule</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CHL</term><def><p>Chinese hamster lung</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNS</term><def><p>central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMEM</term><def><p>Dulbecco's modified eagle medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p>estrogen receptor α</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAK</term><def><p>focal adhesion kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p>green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HNA</term><def><p>human nuclear antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICA</term><def><p>intensity correlation analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICC</term><def><p>immunocytochemistry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICQ</term><def><p>intensity correlation quotient</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IHC</term><def><p>immunohistochemistry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VGSC</term><def><p>voltage-gated Na<sup>+</sup> channel</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Figure 1. SCN1B mRNA expression in breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>(A) SCN1B expression profile in the Lu Breast dataset, segregated by ER status (n=129). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>(B) SCN1B expression vs. ESR1 expression in the Lu Breast dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(C) SCN1B expression in the context of genomic neighbours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Genes are sorted by their genomic distance to SCN1B (indicated underneath matrix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Colours indicate mean fold change in expression (from 0.65-1.8) in ER+ cases relative to ER- cases across five Oncomine datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(D) β1 and (E) β1B mRNA expression across a panel of BCa cell lines (qPCR relative to GAPDH, calibrator=SKBR3; n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>(F) Expression of β1, β1B, and GREB1 (relative to GAPDH) in MCF-7 cells treated with vehicle, or 10nM estradiol and/or 1μM fulvestrant (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Estradiol significantly increased mRNA level (reversed by fulvestrant) of the positive control, GREB1, an estrogen-regulated gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Box plot dots, maximum and minimum values; whiskers, 90th and 10th percentile values; and horizontal lines, 75th, 50th, and 25th percentile values. **P&lt;0.01; ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3465" position="anchor"/><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD10.txt" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3466" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Figure 2. β1, fyn, CD44 and E-cadherin protein levels in MDA-MB-231 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>(A) Western blot of β1 in control MDA-MB-231 cells (expressing eGFP) and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (overexpressing β1-eGFP C-terminal fusion, 67 kDa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>(B) Protein levels of β1 and β1-GFP, relative to ?-tubulin (n=3 repeats). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Bars are mean + SEM. ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>(C) Images of control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells labelled with anti-CD44 and anti-E-cadherin antibodies (red), and DAPI to label the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Positive control for E-cadherin labelling, MCF-7 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(D) Western blot of CD44 in control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>(E) Western blot of E-cadherin in control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Positive control=MCF-7 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>(F) Western blot of fyn kinase in control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD2.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3471" position="anchor"/><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD11.txt" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3472" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Luciferase and GFP expression in MDA-MB-231 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>(A) Representative bioluminescent image of luciferase activity in cultured control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells (1x105 cells/well), 10 min following addition of D-luciferin (1 mg/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>(B) Bioluminescence measured from cultured cells (n=6 wells/group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>(C) Images showing eGFP expression (green) in control MDA-MB-231 cells and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>(D) Quantification of eGFP signal intensity per cell (n=50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Individual cells were delineated using the freeform line tool in ImageJ in order to obtain a pixel intensity score per cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>(E) Metastasis in lung section from a β1 tumour-bearing mouse showing GFP expression (green) in tumour cells overlaying with human nuclear antigen (HNA) expression (red), counterstained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>White dashed lines delineate extent of metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 100μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Data are mean + SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD3.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3477" position="anchor"/><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD12.txt" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3478" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Figure 4. β1-mediated process outgrowth in MCF-7 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>(A) Typical images of MCF-7 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL fibroblast monolayers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 cells were visualised by staining with anti-cytokeratin 18 antibody (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 20μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>(B) Process length (μm) of MCF-7 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers (n=300). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>(C) Process length (μm) of MCF-7 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± 5μM PP2 (n=180). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>(D) Process length (μm) of MCF-7 cells grown on control or β1-expressing CHL monolayers ± fyn siRNA (n=150). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Bars are mean + SEM; ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD4.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3483" position="anchor"/><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD13.txt" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3484" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Targeting fyn expression/activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>(A) Viability (%) of MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells following treatment with PP2 (0.5, 1, 5, 10, 30μM) or vehicle for 24h, normalised to control (n=60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>(B) Proliferation of MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells following treatment with PP2 (0.5, 1, 5, 10, 30μM) or vehicle for 24h, normalised to control (n=9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>(C) GAPDH mRNA expression in MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells following transfection with non-targeting control siRNA (“Control”) or siRNA targeting GAPDH (“siRNA”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>QPCR relative to β-actin (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>In both cell lines, down-regulation of GAPDH expression with siRNA indicated transfection efficiency ≥90%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>(D) Fyn mRNA expression in MCF-7, MDA-MB-231 and MDA-MB-231-β1 cells following transfection with non-targeting control siRNA (“Control”) or siRNA targeting fyn kinase (“siRNA”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>QPCR relative to GAPDH (n=3 repeat transfections). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Data are mean ± SEM; ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="eps" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD5.eps" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3489" position="anchor"/><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="txt" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD14.txt" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3490" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD6.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3495" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Correlation between SCN1B expression and histoclinical characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD7.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3500" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD8"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Patient histoclinical characteristics and β1 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD8.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3505" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD9"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="ijc0135-2338-SD9.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e3510" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></back></article>
