<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://www.biomedcentral.com/xml/article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4067685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2180-14-152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-14-152</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Cell death in amastigote forms of Leishmania amazonensis induced by parthenolide </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Tiuman</surname><given-names>Tatiana Shioji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tati_tiuman@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Ueda-Nakamura</surname><given-names>Tânia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tunakamura@uem.br</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>alonso@if.ufg.br</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A4"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Celso Vataru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cvnakamura@uem.br</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ciências Farmacêuticas, Universidade Estadual de Maringá, Av. Colombo 5790, 87020-900 Maringá, Paraná, Brazil</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Instituto de Física, Universidade Federal de Goiás, Campus II, CEP 74001-970 Goiânia, Goiás, Brazil</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Tiuman et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tiuman et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/14/152"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Leishmania amazonensis infection results in diverse clinical manifestations: cutaneous, mucocutaneous or visceral leishmaniasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The arsenal of drugs available for treating Leishmania infections is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Therefore, new, effective, and less toxic leishmaniasis treatments are still needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We verified cell death in amastigote forms of Leishmania amazonensis induced by the sesquiterpene lactone parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The tested compound was able to concentration-dependently affect axenic and intracellular amastigotes, with IC50 values of 1.3 μM and 2.9 μM, respectively after 72 h incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>No genotoxic effects were observed in a micronucleus test in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide induced morphological and ultrastructural changes in axenic amastigotes, including a loss of membrane integrity, swelling of the mitochondrion, cytoplasmic vacuoles, and intense exocytic activity in the region of the flagellar pocket. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These results led us to investigate the occurrence of autophagic vacuoles with monodansylcadaverine and the integrity of the plasma membrane and mitochondrial membrane potential using flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In all of the tests, parthenolide had positive results. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that the antileishmanial action of parthenolide is associated with autophagic vacuole appearance, a reduction of fluidity, a loss of membrane integrity, and mitochondrial dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Considering the limited repertoire of existing antileishmanial compounds, the products derived from medicinal plants has been one the greatest advances to help develop new chemotherapeutic approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic></kwd><kwd>Amastigotes</kwd><kwd>Parthenolide</kwd><kwd>Cell death</kwd><kwd>Autophagy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Leishmaniasis is associated with high morbidity but low mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It is a poverty-related disease and has become a serious impediment to socioeconomic development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The true burden of this illness remains unclear because the notification of the disease is compulsory in only 32 of the 88 affected countries, and most of the affected people live in remote areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the disfiguring scars caused by Leishmania keep patients hidden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>An estimated 1.5 million new cases of cutaneous leishmaniasis and 500,000 cases of visceral leishmaniasis occur annually, with approximately 12 million people currently infected [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Moreover, cases of Leishmania and human immunodeficiency virus co-infection are becoming more frequent [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Leishmania (Leishmania) amazonensis infection results in diverse clinical manifestations, ranging from cutaneous to mucocutaneous or visceral involvement [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This is attributable to the genetic diversity of L. amazonensis strains, and this divergence extends to variations of chromosome size [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The arsenal of drugs available for treating Leishmania infections is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The basic treatment consists of administering pentavalent antimonial compounds [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, the choice of medication depends on the species involved and type of clinical manifestation [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The usefulness of antileishmanial drugs has been limited by their toxicity, and treatment failure is often attributable to drug resistance [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>To solve this problem, developing less toxic drugs and discovering cellular and molecular markers in parasites to identify the phenotype of chemoresistance against leishmanicidal drugs are necessary [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These problems led to the development of additional antileishmanial drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Some drug-delivery systems, plants, and synthetic compounds are being developed as effective treatments for the disease [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrated the in vitro activity of parthenolide, a sesquiterpene lactone purified from Tanacetum parthenium, against promastigotes and intracellular amastigotes (inside J774G8 macrophages) of L. amazonensis[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Moreover, significant alterations in promastigote forms were demonstrated by light microscopy and scanning and transmission electron microscopy [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the activity of parthenolide against L. amazonensis axenic amastigotes and demonstrated a possible mechanism of action of this compound in this life stage of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Antileishmanial assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The addition of 4.0 μM parthenolide to the culture of axenic amastigotes induced growth arrest and partial cell lysis after 48 h (i.e., growth inhibition up to 90%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>When the cells were treated with 2.0 μM parthenolide, the percentage of growth inhibition was approximately 70%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide had an IC50 of 1.3 μM and IC90 of 3.3 μM after 72 h incubation (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Effects of parthenolide (A) and amphotericin B (B) on the growth of L. amazonensis axenic amastigotes. After treatment with different concentrations of the drugs, parasites were counted, and the percentage of parasite growth inhibition was determined daily for 120 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The data indicate the average of the two independent experiments performed twice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis: the data of each incubation period were compared statistically at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Bars that are not indicated with letters in common are statistically different. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>A concentration of 1.0 or 0.5 μM of the reference drug amphotericin B inhibited more than 93% of L. amazonensis amastigote cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>This drug had an IC50 and IC90 of 0.22 μM and 0.45 μM, respectively, after culturing for 72 h (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide also inhibited the growth of intracellular amastigotes in mouse resident peritoneal macrophages after 24 h incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Treatment with 4.0, 3.2, 2.4, and 1.6 μM parthenolide reduced the proliferation of parasites into macrophages (survival index) by 82.5, 59.4, 37.3, and 6.1%, respectively, compared with the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The survival index indicated that parthenolide inhibited the intracellular viability and multiplication of Leishmania in infected murine macrophages and showed 50% inhibition of cell survival at a concentration of 2.9 μM (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Effect of parthenolide on amastigotes of L. amazonensis in mouse resident peritoneal macrophages. Peritoneal macrophage cells were infected with promastigote forms, and then intracellular amastigotes were treated with different concentrations of parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>After 24 h treatment, the survival index was calculated by multiplying the percentage of macrophages with internalized parasites and mean number of internalized parasites per macrophage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The results shown are from one representative experiment of two independent experiments performed in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The data were compared statistically at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Bars that are not indicated with letters in common are statistically different. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Previous studies showed that when J774G8 murine macrophages were treated with parthenolide, the 50% cytotoxic concentration (CC50) was 56.4 μM [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>By comparing the toxicity for J774G8 macrophages and activity against intracellular amastigotes, obtaining the selectivity index ratio is possible (CC50 for J774G8 cells/IC50 for protozoa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In the present study, parthenolide had an IC50 of 2.9 μM, presenting a selectivity index ratio of 19.4 (i.e., the compound is 19.4-times more selective against parasites than host cells). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Mutagenicity evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The results of the in vivo bone marrow micronucleus test in rats are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide did not induce genotoxic effects at a concentration of 3.75 mg/kg body weight, with no significant increase in the frequency of MNPCE (10.0 ± 1.6) compared with the vehicle control group (7.0 ± 1.8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>In contrast, a significant increase in the frequency of MNPCE was observed in the positive control group (cyclophosphamide; 27.0 ± 4.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In the present study, no clinical signs of toxicity were observed in treated animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>However, further studies should be performed with higher concentrations of parthenolide to exclude the possibility of genotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Micronucleated polychromatic erythrocyte (MNPCE) score in 2,000 reticulocytes from bone marrow of mice </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>MNPCE (mean ± SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Vehicle </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>7.0 ± 1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Cyclophosphamide </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>27.0 ± 4.0b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>10.0 ± 1.6a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Findings after 24 h oral treatment with vehicle (negative control), cyclophosphamide (positive control), and parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>aNo significant difference compared with negative control and significant difference compared with positive control (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>bSignificant difference compared with negative control (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Scanning and transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>To determine the morphological and ultrastructural changes in L. amazonensis axenic amastigotes induced by parthenolide, the cells were treated with the IC50 (1.3 μM) of the compound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Untreated controls showed no morphological (Figure 3A) or ultrastructural (Figure 3D) differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Similarly, cells incubated with 0.05% DMSO (i.e., the same concentration used in the final solutions of parthenolide) remained unaltered (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>When treated with parthenolide, changes in form were visualized by scanning electron microscopy (Figure 3B and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy showed a loss of membrane integrity associated with amphotericin B exposure at the IC50 concentration (Figure 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide caused intense swelling of the mitochondrion (Figure 3F) and cytoplasmic blebbing (Figure 3G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Finally, the ultrastructural analysis showed that amastigotes treated with parthenolide formed multiple cytoplasmic vacuoles (Figure 3H), and intense exocytic activity was observed in the region of the flagellar pocket, appearing as concentric membranes within the pocket (Figure 3I). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Scanning (A-C) and transmission (D-I) electron microscopy of axenic amastigotes of L. amazonensis treated with parthenolide. Amastigotes were incubated for 72 h in the absence (A and D) or presence (B, C, F-I) of the IC50 (1.3 μM) of parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For transmission electron microscopy, the treatment of amastigotes was also accomplished using the IC50 of amphotericin B as a reference drug that acts on the cytoplasmic membrane (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The arrows indicate plasma membrane blebs or loss of membrane integrity, and the asterisks indicate vesicles located in the cytoplasm or flagellar pocket. n, nucleus; f, flagellum; fp, flagellar pocket; m, mitochondrion; k, kinetoplast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Scale bars = 1 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Labeling of autophagic vacuoles with monodansylcadaverine </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We studied the incorporation of monodancylcadaverine (MDC) in cells in which autophagy was stimulated by parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Axenic amastigotes treated with the IC50 (Figure 4B) or IC90 (Figure 4C) of parthenolide showed an increase in the number of vesicles, indicating that the compound induced the formation of MDC-labeled vacuoles in the cytoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>MDC-positive cells were visualized in treated cells but not in control cells (Figure 4A) or amphotericin-treated cells (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>These results show that parthenolide treatment, unlike amphotericin B, led to the formation of autophagic vacuoles in L. amazonensis amastigotes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Monodansylcadaverine (MDC)-labeled vesicles in axenic amastigotes of L. amazonensis induced by parthenolide treatment. Amastigotes were incubated for 72 h in Schneider medium (control cells) (A) or in the presence of the IC50(B) or IC90(C) of parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The data are representative of at least three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Scale bars = 5 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-4"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometric measurement of amastigote culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Live L. amazonensis cells were incubated with propidium iodide and rhodamine 123, and fluorescence was measured by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The gated percentage of propidium iodide-stained amastigotes after treatment with amphotericin B (positive control) was 71.4%, much higher than untreated parasites (negative control) that presented 6.0% (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>When the cells were treated with 20 and 40 μM parthenolide, the percentages of labeled amastigotes were 34.2% and 56.2%, respectively (Figure 5B), possibly indicating a considerable increase in plasma membrane permeability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To prove that Leishmania cells functionally respond to the pharmacological alteration of ΔΨm, amastigotes were treated with the protonophore carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone (CCCP), which has been shown to interfere with mitochondrial membrane potential in various cell types [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The results showed that 82.5% of the amastigotes without treatment (negative control) presented a maximal increase in fluorescence, and with 200 μM CCCP, 46.7% showed fluorescence, indicating a loss of ΔΨm (Figure 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>We next observed ΔΨm reductions of 68.4% and 56.1% when the amastigotes were treated with 20 and 40 μM parthenolide, respectively, suggesting that this compound interferes with the mitochondrial membrane potential leading to alteration of ATP generation and in consequence cell damage takes place. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry analysis of propidium iodide- (A, B) and rhodamine 123- (C, D) labeled axenic amastigotes of L. amazonensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(A) Untreated cells: negative control (C-) and amphotericin B as positive control (C+). (B) Amastigotes treated with 20 or 40 μM parthenolide (Pt 20 or Pt 40). (C) Untreated cells: negative control and carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone as a positive control. (D) Amastigotes treated with 20 or 40 μM parthenolide (Pt 20 or Pt 40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The data are representative of at least two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-5"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>EPR spectra of spin-labeled Leishmania </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The experimental and best-fit EPR spectra of spin-label 5-DSA structured in the plasma membrane of Leishmania are shown in Figure 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>These EPR spectra are typical for cellular membranes that contain an appreciable amount of integral proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Treatment with parthenolide increased two EPR parameters, the outer hyperfine splitting, 2A//, and rotational correlation time, τC , indicating a significant reduction of membrane lipid dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>2A//is a practice parameter measured directly in EPR spectra that has been widely used to monitor membrane fluidity, although in principle it is a static parameter associated with the orientation distribution of the spin labels in the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The theoretical EPR spectrum of spin-label 5-DSA in the plasma membrane of Leishmania was best fitted using a model of two spectral components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the membrane has two populations of spin labels of distinct mobility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The EPR spectra of spin labels in lipid bilayers are well known to contain proteins sometimes composed of two spectral components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The more restricted component is associated with boundary lipids where the spin labels surround the hydrophobic regions of proteins, whereas the more mobile component arises from the spin labels located in the bulk bilayer phase, away from the protein [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The fitting program provides the τ c  and population of each component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Thus, the mean of the rotational correlation time was calculated as τ c  = N 1 *τ c1  + N 2 *τ c2 , in which N 1  and N 2  are the fractions of the population in components 1 and 2, respectively, and τ c1  and τ c2  are the corresponding rotational time correlations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Experimental EPR spectra (black line) and theoretical fits (red line) of spin-label 5-DSA in Leishmania membrane. The experiment was conducted at 26°C for samples untreated and treated with parthenolide at the indicated concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>EPR spectra were simulated with the NLLS fitting program, and the values of the parameter rotational correlation time, τC, obtained from the fit for each spectrum are indicated on a nanosecond scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The EPR parameter 2A//is the separation in magnetic-field units between the first and last resonance lines of the spectrum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The vertical lines indicate the 2A//for the control samples, and the smaller vertical lines illustrate the increase in 2A//for the sample treated with 9 × 109 molecules/cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The measured 2A//values and τC values indicate that the presence of parthenolide significantly reduced lipid fluidity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The estimated experimental errors for the 2A//and τC parameters are 0.5 G and 1.0 ns, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-14-152-6"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>For many years, parasites of the genus Leishmania have displayed extraordinary plasticity to face modifications in their environment [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The expansion of risk factors related to environmental changes and man-made transformations are making leishmaniasis a growing public health concern in many countries worldwide [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Leishmaniasis urgently needs novel drugs with improved features, and many compounds primarily derived from plants are promising leads for the development of novel chemotherapeutics [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The development of axenic cultures of amastigotes of Leishmania species yielded new opportunities to investigate the antileishmanial activities of new compounds directly at the mammalian stage of the parasite [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Assays that use intracellular amastigote cell cultures are relevant because this life cycle stage of the parasite is important to its pathogenicity, and data obtained exclusively from promastigote cell lines are insufficient [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in the present study, we determined the leishmanicidal activity of parthenolide, which is naturally occurring, in both axenic and intracellular amastigotes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>To discover better leishmanicidal compounds, the isolation and purification of the active ingredients of medicinal plants are gaining attention [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Many new natural product groups, such as terpenes, have exhibited antiprotozoal potential and attracted renewed interest with surprising efficacy and selectivity [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide is a lipophilic hydrocarbon compound formed by units of isoprene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The accumulation of lipophilic compounds in the cytoplasmic membrane and membrane constituents of microorganisms has considerable effects on the loss of cellular integrity and inhibition of respiratory cellular activity in mitochondria [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This interaction with cell membranes eventually leads to cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In our research, parthenolide had antileishmanial effects against axenic and intracellular amastigotes of L. amazonensis presenting IC50 of 1.3 after 72 h growth and 2.9 μM after 24 h growth, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The differences in IC50 values can be explained because the experiments with axenic amastigotes are directed against the relevant stage of the parasite whereas the use of intracellular amastigotes will give essential information on the capacity of the drugs to target intracellular organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The role played by the macrophages on drug-mediated toxicity may be important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Their presence may limit the availability of the compounds under evaluation [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The toxicity for J774G8 macrophages and the activity against intracellular amastigotes were compared by using the selectivity index ratio (CC50 for J774G8 cells/IC50 for protozoa) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The parthenolide was more selective against the intracellular amastigotes than the mammalian cells, with a selectivity index ratio of 19.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>It is generally considered that biological efficacy is not due to in vitro cytotoxicity when this index is ≥ 10 [23,24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The low toxicity against mammalian cells is an important criterion in the search for active compounds with antiprotozoal activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, the genotoxicity of parthenolide in a mouse model was determined using a micronucleus test and cyclophosphamide as the positive control because it is a known genotoxin [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Micronuclei are masses of cytoplasmic chromatin that appear outside the main nucleus as a result of chromosomal damage or damage to the mitotic apparatus in the erythroblasts of the test species, and they can be used as an indicator of the effects of agents that cause DNA damage [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In mice, micronuclei in mature erythrocytes in peripheral blood live approximately 1 month, providing a measure of average chromosomal damage [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Our results showed no differences in the frequency of MNPCE compared with the negative control, demonstrating no toxic effects on bone marrow at the dose tested (3.75 mg/kg body weight). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopic studies revealed extensive cytoplasmic vacuolization, leading to the examination of the possibility that parthenolide induces autophagic cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Autophagy cell death is a process that is thought to occur in all eukaryotes and is characterized by an accumulation of autophagic vacuoles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>This mechanism occurs for energy production for survival when cells recycle their cytoplasmic contents during periods of environmental stress or certain stages of development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A double-membrane vesicle called the autophagosome forms in the cytosol, engulfing organelles and bulk cytoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, these vesicles fuse with lysosomes, where their contents are degraded and recycled [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>One of the most frequently used methods to examine autophagy is staining with acidotropic dyes [29], and MDC is considered an autofluorescent compound and specific marker for autophagic vacuoles [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>MDC staining is only obtained when the compartments into which it loads are acidic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Neutralization of these compartments leads to a swift loss of MDC staining or lack of MDC uptake [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we suggest that the vacuoles that were observed under a transmission electron microscope are autophagosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Another study used MDC as a marker to analyze the molecular level of the machinery involved in the autophagic process [32] and was also used to demonstrate that antimicrobial peptides induce autophagic cell death in L. donovani[33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Amphotericin B was used as a positive control in some of our experiments because this polyene antibiotic forms aqueous and nonaqueous pores in membranes, which is the basis of leishmanicidal action [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Using transmission electron microscopy, we could see the loss of membrane integrity induced by this antimicrobial agent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Similarly, alterations in the cytoplasmic membrane, including membrane blebbing and disruption, could be visualized in axenic amastigotes treated with parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown that a flow cytometric membrane potential assay can be used as a reliable tool for studying the interactions between amphotericin B and the Leishmania membrane [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Alterations in membrane permeability are detected by propidium iodide nucleic acid stain that selectively passes through plasma membranes and bind to DNA, emitting high fluorescence when excited by an argon ion laser [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Since its introduction, the propidium iodide flow cytometric assay has also been widely used as a quantitative measure of cell apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>During apoptosis, DNA fragmentation occurs, with a subsequent loss of cellular DNA content [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Terpenoic compounds can produce major changes in the cellular and mitochondrial membrane structures of different pathogenic agents, modifying their permeability and integrity [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Ultrastructural findings also revealed mitochondrial damage induced by parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We used flow cytometry analysis to determine whether the compound interferes with the mitochondrial membrane potential of the amastigotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The flow cytometry results showed that transmembrane potential decreased, reflected by a reduction of rhodamine 123 fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Rhodamine 123 is a fluorescent cationic stain for mitochondria in living cells and is subsequently washed out of the cells once the mitochondrion’s membrane potential is lost [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The present results indicated an increase in proton permeability through the internal mitochondrial membrane, inhibition of electron transport, or decrease in mitochondrial substrate transport/oxidation, which would impair proton pumping by mitochondrial complexes and reduce adenosine triphosphate synthesis, resulting in parasite cell death [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>CCCP was used as positive control because it is an uncoupler of oxidative phosphorylation and reduces mitochondrial membrane potential by directly attacking the proton gradient across the inner mitochondrial membrane [12,40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Amastigotes treated with parthenolide presented severe plasma membrane and mitochondrial damage, suggesting an autophagic process [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Treatment with parthenolide induced shedding of the membranes into the flagellar pocket, appearing as concentric membranes and suggesting intense exocytic activity because this site is where endocytosis and exocytosis occur in trypanosomatids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Treatment of promastigote forms of L. amazonensis with edelfosine for 1 day [41] and parthenolide for 3 days [10] also led to the appearance of a large number of vesicles inside the flagellar pocket, suggesting a process of exacerbated protein production by cells as they attempt to survive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Other studies indicated that the plasma membrane of human promyelocytic leukemic HL-60 cells appears to be one of the targets of parthenolide because its integrity is lost very early during cell death, reflected by atypical apoptosis and primary necrosis (i.e., lysis of the membrane) [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The lipid spin probe 5-DSA was incorporated into the plasmatic membrane of Leishmania in the usual way, and the EPR spectra obtained were typical for cell membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the spectra of the Leishmania membrane were very similar to those for the same spin label in erythrocyte membranes [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The erythrocyte membrane of spin-labeled lipids has been well characterized by EPR spectroscopy and is considered to have certain rigidity, particularly because of its high content of protein and cholesterol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The presence of sesquiterpene parthenolide significantly increased the rigidity of the membrane of Leishmania when applied to the cell suspension at a ratio of 3 × 109 parthenolide molecules/cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide also showed dose-dependent anti-Leishmania activity against the amastigote form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The IC50 was 1.3 μM parthenolide/ml for a cell concentration of 1 × 106 cell/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the effect of parthenolide against the amastigote forms of Leishmania was observed at a ratio of 7.8 × 108 parthenolide molecules/cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The greatest change in membrane fluidity was observed at a concentration 3.8-fold higher than for growth inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Membrane stiffness, assessed by EPR spectroscopy of the spin label, has been associated with lipid peroxidation [44,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>A detailed study of the interaction between parthenolide and membranes and their role as a pro-oxidant in simpler systems is necessary to determine whether the membrane rigidity observed here was attributable to lipid peroxidation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Our results indicated that the antileishmanial action of parthenolide is associated with autophagic vacuole appearance, membrane stiffness, the loss of membrane integrity, and mitochondrial dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that parthenolide induced amastigote cell death by autophagy, but other mechanisms of cell death cannot be dismissed, such as apoptosis and necrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Considering the limited repertoire of existing antileishmanial compounds, continuously developing new leishmanicidal compounds is essential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In the ongoing search for the best antileishmanial compounds, products derived from plants are gaining ground. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The isolation and purification of the active components of medicinal plants has been one the greatest advances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Additionally, delineation of the biochemical mechanisms involved in mediating effect of these compounds would help develop new chemotherapeutic approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Parthenolide (minimum 90%) was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Steinheim, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Amphotericin B (Cristália, Produtos Químicos Farmacêuticos Ltda, Itapira, SP, Brazil) was used as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In all of the tests, 0.05% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) was used to dissolve the highest dose of the compounds and had no effect on the parasites’ proliferation or morphology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Axenic amastigotes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Promastigotes of the Leishmania species differentiate to amastigotes with the combination of low pH and high temperature [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The WHOM/BR/75/Josefa strain of Leishmania amazonensis, isolated by C.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Cuba-Cuba (University of Brasília, Brasília, Distrito Federal, Brazil) from a human case of diffuse cutaneous leishmaniasis, was used in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Axenic amastigote cultures were obtained by the in vitro differentiation of promastigotes from the stationary phase in 25 cm2 tissue culture flasks by progressive temperature increase and pH decrease [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The cultures were maintained at 32°C in Schneider’s insect medium (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), pH 4.6, with 20% fetal bovine serum through weekly serial sub-culturing for further studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Antiproliferative effect </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>For the parasite growth inhibition assays, L. amazonensis axenic amastigotes were harvested during the exponential phase of growth, and 106 cells were added to each well of a 24-well plate and treated with different concentrations of parthenolide and amphotericin B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Medium alone and 0.05% DMSO were used as negative controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>For each treatment, the parasites were observed and counted daily using a Neubauer chamber with an optical microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Each experiment was performed in duplicate and twice on different occasions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The antiproliferative effect (percentage of growth inhibition) was evaluated with 5 day treatment, and the data are expressed as the mean ± standard error of the mean (Microsoft Excel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The corresponding 50% and 90% inhibitory concentrations (IC50 and IC90) were determined from the concentration-response curves (Excel software). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Data were compared via one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey’s multiple range test for statistically significant differences at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Activity of parthenolide in infection of murine macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The effect of parthenolide on L. amazonensis-infected mouse peritoneal macrophages was evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The experimental protocol was approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of the Universidade Estadual de Maringá (no. 013/2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>BALB/c mice resident peritoneal cells were harvested in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; 0.01 M, pH 7.2) and centrifuged, and the sediment was resuspended in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Cells (1 × 105) were seeded on 13-mm coverslips in 24-well plates and incubated at 37°C in a 5% CO2 atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>After 15 h, macrophages were infected with promastigotes at a 10:1 parasite:cell ratio and incubated again for 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The remaining noninternalized parasites were removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The infected host cells were treated with parthenolide at concentrations of 4.0, 3.2, 2.4, and 1.6 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>After 24 h, the coverslips were washed with PBS, fixed in methanol, stained with Giemsa, mounted in Entellan (Merck), and examined under an optical microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The rate of cell infection and number of amastigotes per cell were evaluated by counting 200 random cells in duplicate cultures in at least two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The survival index was calculated by multiplying the percentage of infected macrophages and mean number of internalized parasites per macrophage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Data were compared via one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey’s multiple range test for statistically significant differences at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Genotoxicity study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>To assess the toxicity of parthenolide in mice, a micronucleus test was conducted in groups of five male and five female Swiss albino mice (Mus musculus) that weighed approximately 42 g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The animals were obtained from the Central Animal House of the Universidade Estadual de Maringá, Paraná, Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>They were housed in plastic cages at 22 ± 1°C and 55 ± 10% humidity, with a 12 h/12 h light/dark cycle and free access to water and food (Nuvilab Cr1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted according to experimental standards approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of the Universidade Estadual de Maringá (protocol no. 013/2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The animals received 3.75 mg parthenolide/kg body weight suspended in 10% DMSO by oral gavage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The negative control was a vehicle group, and the positive control was a group that received 40 mg cyclophosphamide/kg body weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The mice were examined regularly for mortality and clinical signs of toxicity until sacrifice by carbon dioxide asphyxiation, which occurred 24 h after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Both femurs were dissected, and bone marrow was flushed with fetal calf serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation for 5 min at 2,000 × g, 10 μl of the sediment was smeared on glass slides and air-dried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The smears were fixed with absolute methanol for 5 min and stained with May-Grunwald-Giemsa to detect micronucleated polychromatic erythrocytes (MNPCE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The number of micronucleated cells was counted in 2,000 reticulocytes per animal using an Olympus BH-2 microscope at 1,000× magnification [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The statistical analyses were made with a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Dunnet test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered significant at p value of less than 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Scanning and transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>After treatment with the IC50 (72 h) of parthenolide, axenic amastigotes were washed in PBS and fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer at 4ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>For scanning electron microscopy, amastigotes were placed on a specimen support with a poly-L-lysine-coated coverslip and washed in cacodylate buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The cells were dehydrated in an increasing ethanol gradient, critical-point-dried in CO2, sputter-coated with gold, and observed in a Shimadzu SS-550 SEM scanning electron microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>For transmission electron microscopy, amastigote forms were treated with the IC50 of parthenolide and the IC50 of amphotericin B and fixed as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The cells were postfixed in a solution that contained 1% osmium tetroxide, 0.8% potassium ferrocyanide, and 10 mM calcium chloride in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer, dehydrated in an increasing acetone gradient, and embedded in Epon resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Ultrathin sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and the images were examined in a Zeiss 900 transmission electron microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence of monodansylcadaverine during cell death </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Axenic amastigotes were treated with IC50 and IC90 equivalents of parthenolide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>After 72 h, the cells were washed and resuspended in PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>To verify the induction of autophagy by parthenolide, the cells were incubated with 0.05 mM monodansylcadaverine (MDC) at 37°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>After incubation, the cells were washed three times with PBS to remove excess MDC, immediately analyzed by fluorescence microscopy at an excitation wavelength of 360–380 nm and emission wavelength of 525 nm, and photographed using a charge-coupled-device camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>This study was qualitative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The antileishmanial activity of parthenolide (20 and 40 μM) on the integrity of the plasma membrane and mitochondrial membrane potential of axenic amastigotes (5 × 106 cells/ml) was determined after 3 h treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Amphotericin B (5.0 μM) and carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone (200 μM) were used as positive controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Untreated amastigotes were used as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Each flow-cytometric technique was evaluated by repeating each experiment three times to verify reproducibility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The integrity of the plasma membrane was assessed using L. amazonensis amastigotes at an average density of 5 × 106 cells suspended in 500 μl PBS and stained with 50 μl propidium iodide (2 μg/ml) for 5 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>To measure mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm), 1 ml of saline that contained 1 × 106 of treated amastigotes was mixed with 1 μl rhodamine 123 (5 mg/mL) for 15 min at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The cells were washed, resuspended in PBS, and incubated at the same temperature for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>A total of 10,000 events were analyzed per sample using a FACSCalibur cytometer, and numeric data were processed with Cellquest software (both from Becton Dickinson). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Propidium iodide and rhodamine 123 are excited with a 480 nm argon ion laser, and fluorescence emission occurs at 560–580 nm and 515–530 nm, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Spin-label 5-doxyl stearic acid (5-DSA), with a nitroxide radical moiety (doxyl) in the fifth carbon atom of the acyl chain, was purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>A small aliquot (3 μl) of stock solution of the spin label in ethanol (2 mg/ml) was transferred to a glass tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>After the solvent evaporated, approximately 2.4 × 108 cells of Leishmania suspended in 40 μl PBS was added to the film of the spin label with gentle agitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>In a second tube, 6 μl of a stock solution of parthenolide in chloroform (201 mM) was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>After evaporation of the solvent, the first spin-labeled cell suspension was placed on the parthenolide film and gently agitated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The cells were then introduced into a 1 mm inner diameter capillary column for electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) measurements, which was sealed by flame. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Samples were also prepared that contained double and triple the concentrations of parthenolide used in the first sample (using 12 and 18 μl of the solution of parthenolide in chloroform, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy was performed with a Bruker ESP 300 spectrometer (Rheinstetten, Germany) equipped with an ER 4102 ST resonator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The instrument settings were the following: microwave power, 10 mW; modulation frequency, 100 KHz; modulation amplitude, 1.0 G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Electron paramagnetic resonance spectra simulations were performed using the NLLS program developed by Budil and coworkers [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In the spectral calculations, the NLLS program includes the magnetic g- and A-tensors and rotational diffusion tensor, R, which are expressed in a system of Cartesian axes fixed in the spin-labeled molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>To reduce the number of parameters in the fittings and simplify the simulation, the average rotational diffusion rate, R bar , was calculated by the fitting program using the relationship R bar  = (R per  2 •R par ) 1/3 , in which R per  is the perpendicular component of the rotational diffusion, and R par  is the parallel component of the rotational diffusion. R bar  was converted to the parameter rotational correlation time, τ c , following the relationship τ c  = 1/6 R bar . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Similar to previous studies [49,50], the magnetic parameters were determined based on a global analysis of the overall spectra obtained in this work, and all of the EPR spectra were simulated using the same predetermined parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>In this work, the spectra were simulated with a model of two spectral components. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>TST conceived and designed the study, carried out all the experimental studies and drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>TUN participated in the design of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>AA assisted with EPR spectra and helped to draft the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>CVN conceived of the study, and participated in its design and coordination and helped to draft the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by grants from Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq), Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nivel Superior (CAPES), Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos (FINEP), Complexo de Central de Apoio a Pesquisa (COMCAP) – Universidade Estadual de Maringá, and Programa de Pós-graduação em Ciências Farmacêuticas – Universidade Estadual de Maringá. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>WHOLeishmaniasis: magnitude of the problemWorld Health Org2013[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/leishmaniasis/burden/magnitude/burden_magnitude/en/">http://www.who.int/leishmaniasis/burden/magnitude/burden_magnitude/en/</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Fernández-GuerreroMLRoblesPRivasPMójerFMuñízGGórgolasMVisceral leishmaniasis in immunocompromised patients with and without AIDS: a comparison of clinical features and prognosisActa Trop200490111610.1016/j.actatropica.2003.09.009<?supplied-pmid 14739017?>14739017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Carnaúba-JrDKonishiCTPetriVMartinezICPShimizuLPereira-ChioccolaVLAtypical disseminated leishmaniasis similar to post-kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis in a Brazilian AIDS patient infected with Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi: a case reportInt J Infect Dis20091350450710.1016/j.ijid.2009.01.022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>BarralAPedral-SampaioDGrimaldi JúniorGMomenHMcMahon-PrattDRibeiro De JesusAAlmeidaRBadaroRBarral-NettoMCarvalhoEMJohnson JúniorWDLeishmaniasis in Bahia, Brazil: evidence that Leishmania amazonensis produces a wide spectrum of clinical diseaseAm J Trop Med Hyg199144536546<?supplied-pmid 2063957?>2063957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>OliveiraJPCFernandesFCruzAKTrombelaVMonteiroECamargoAABarralAOliveiraCIGenetic diversity of Leishmania amazonensis strains isolated in northeastern Brazil as revealed by DNA sequencing, PCR-based analyses and molecular karyotypingKinetoplastid Biol Dis2007doi:10.1186/1475-9292-6-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>CroftSLCoombsGHLeishmaniasis – current chemotherapy and recent advances in the search for novel drugsTrends Parasitol20031950250810.1016/j.pt.2003.09.008<?supplied-pmid 14580961?>14580961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>TiumanTSSantosAOUeda-NakamuraTDias FilhoBPNakamuraCVRecent advances in leishmaniasis treatmentInt J Infect Dis201115e525e53210.1016/j.ijid.2011.03.021<?supplied-pmid 21605997?>21605997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>CroftSLSundarSFairlambAHDrug resistance in leishmaniasisClin Microbiol Rev20061911112610.1128/CMR.19.1.111-126.2006<?supplied-pmid 16418526?>16418526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>NateraSMachucaCPadrón-NievesMRomeroADíazEPonte-SucreALeishmania spp.: proficiency of drug-resistant parasitesInt J Antimicrob Agents20072963764210.1016/j.ijantimicag.2007.01.004<?supplied-pmid 17353113?>17353113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>TiumanTSUeda-NakamuraTCortezDAGDias FilhoBPMorgado-DíazJADe SouzaWNakamuraCVAntileishmanial activity of parthenolide, a sesquiterpene lactone isolated from Tanacetum partheniumAntimicrob Agents Chemother20054917618210.1128/AAC.49.11.176-182.2005<?supplied-pmid 15616293?>15616293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>TiumanTSUeda-NakamuraTDias-FilhoBPCortezDAGMorgado-DíazJANakamuraCVMorphologic and ultrastructural alterations in Leishmania amazonensis induced by 4a,5β-epoxy-germacra-1(10),11(13)-dien-12,6a-olideActa Protozool200746349355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>LinsingerGWilhelmSWagnerHHäckerGUncouplers of oxidative phosphorylation can enhance a Fas death signalMol Cell Biol19991932993311<?supplied-pmid 10207055?>10207055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>JostPCGriffithOHCapaldiRAVanderkooiGEvidence for boundary lipid in membranesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19737048048410.1073/pnas.70.2.480<?supplied-pmid 4346892?>4346892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>RotureauBAre new world leishmaniases becoming anthroponoses?Med Hypotheses2006671235124110.1016/j.mehy.2006.02.056<?supplied-pmid 16797861?>16797861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>WHOUrbanization: an increasing risk factor for leishmaniasisWklyEpidemiol Rec200277365370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>PolonioTEfferthTLeishmaniasis: drug resistance and natural products (review)Int J Mol Med200822277286<?supplied-pmid 18698485?>18698485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>SerenoDLemesreJLAxenically cultured amastigote forms as an in vitro model for investigation of antileishmanial agentsAntimicrob Agents Chemother199741972976<?supplied-pmid 9145854?>9145854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>SenRChatterjeeMPlant derived therapeutics for the treatment of leishmaniasisPhytomedicine2011181056105910.1016/j.phymed.2011.03.004<?supplied-pmid 21596544?>21596544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>KayserOKiderlenAFCroftSLNatural products as antiparasitic drugsParasitol Res200390S55S6210.1007/s00436-002-0768-3<?supplied-pmid 12937967?>12937967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SikkemaJDe BontJAMPoolmanBMechanisms of membrane toxicity of hydrocarbonsMicrobiol Rev199559201222<?supplied-pmid 7603409?>7603409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>FumarolaLSpinelliRBrandonisioOIn vitro assays for evaluation of drug activity against Leishmania sppRes Microbiol200415522423010.1016/j.resmic.2004.01.001<?supplied-pmid 15142618?>15142618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>SerenoDCordeiro Da SilvaAMathieu-DaudeFOuaissiAAdvances and perspectives in leishmania cell based drug-screening proceduresParasitol Int2007563710.1016/j.parint.2006.09.001<?supplied-pmid 17079188?>17079188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>WenigerBRobledoSArangoGJDeharoEAragónRMuñozVCallapaJLobsteinAAntonRAntiprotozoal activities of Colombian plantsJ Ethnopharmacol20017819320010.1016/S0378-8741(01)00346-4<?supplied-pmid 11694364?>11694364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>WenigerBVonthron-SénécheauCKaiserMBrunRAntonRComparative antiplasmodial, leishmanicidal and antitrypanosomal activities of several biflavonoidsPhytomedicine20061317618010.1016/j.phymed.2004.10.008<?supplied-pmid 16428025?>16428025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>WinterMJEllisLCJHutchinsonTHFormation of micronuclei in erythrocytes of the fathead minnow (Pimephales promelas) after acute treatment with mitomycin C or cyclophosphamideMutat Res2007629899910.1016/j.mrgentox.2007.01.010<?supplied-pmid 17398142?>17398142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>CostaMAIshidaKKaplumVKoslykEDde MelloJCUeda-NakamuraTDias FilhoBPNakamuraCVSafety evaluation of proanthocyanidin polymer-rich fraction obtained from stem bark of Stryphnodendron adstringens (BARBATIMAO) for use as a pharmacological agentRegul Toxicol Pharmacol20105833033510.1016/j.yrtph.2010.07.006<?supplied-pmid 20655967?>20655967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>HayashiMMacGregorJTGatehouseDGAdlerIBlakeyDHDertingerSDKrishnaGMoritaTRussoASutouSIn vivo rodent erythrocyte micronucleus assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Some aspects of protocol design including repeated treatments, integration with toxicity testing, and automated scoringEnviron Mol Mutagen20003523425210.1002/(SICI)1098-2280(2000)35:3&lt;234::AID-EM10&gt;3.0.CO;2-L<?supplied-pmid 10737958?>10737958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>EdingerALThompsonCBDeath by design: apoptosis, necrosis and autophagyCurr Opin Cell Biol20041666366910.1016/j.ceb.2004.09.011<?supplied-pmid 15530778?>15530778 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>KlionskyDJAbeliovichHAgostinisPAgrawalDKAlievGAskewDSBabaMBaehreckeEHBahrBABallabioABamberBABasshamDCBergaminiEBiXBiard-PiechaczykMBlumJSBredesenDEBrodskyJLBrumellJHBrunkUTBurschWCamougrandNCebolleroECecconiFChenYChinLSChoiAChuCTChungJClarkePGGuidelines for the use and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy in higher eukaryotesAutophagy20084151175<?supplied-pmid 18188003?>18188003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>BiederbickAKernHFElsässerHPMonodansylcadaverine (MDC) is a specific in vivo marker for autophagic vacuolesEur J Cell Biol199566314<?supplied-pmid 7750517?>7750517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>MizushimaNMethods for monitoring autophagyInt J Biochem Cell Biol2004362491250210.1016/j.biocel.2004.02.005<?supplied-pmid 15325587?>15325587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>MunafóDBColomboMIA novel assay to study autophagy: regulation of autophagosome vacuole size by amino acid deprivationJ Cell Sci200111436193629<?supplied-pmid 11707514?>11707514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>BeraASinghSNagarajRVaidyaTInduction of autophagic cell death in Leishmania donovani by antimicrobial peptidesMol Biochem Parasitol2003127233510.1016/S0166-6851(02)00300-6<?supplied-pmid 12615333?>12615333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>CohenBEAmphotericin B membrane action: role for two types of ion channels in eliciting cell survival and lethal effectsJ Membr Biol201023812010.1007/s00232-010-9313-y<?supplied-pmid 21085940?>21085940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Di GiorgioCFaraut-GambarelliFImbertAMinodierPGasquetMDumonHFlow cytometric assessment of amphotericin B susceptibility in Leishmania infantum isolates from patients with visceral leishmaniasisJ Antimicrob Chemother199944717610.1093/jac/44.1.71<?supplied-pmid 10459812?>10459812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>DenglerWASchulteJBergerDPMertelsmannRFiebigHHDevelopment of a propidium iodide fluorescence assay for proliferation and cytotoxicity assaysAnticancer Drugs1995652253210.1097/00001813-199508000-00005<?supplied-pmid 7579556?>7579556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>RiccardiCNicolettiIAnalysis of apoptosis by propidium iodide staining and flow cytometryNat Protoc200611458146110.1038/nprot.2006.238<?supplied-pmid 17406435?>17406435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>ScadutoRCJrGrotyohannLWMeasurement of mitochondrial membrane potential using fluorescent rhidanmine derivativesBiophys J19997646947710.1016/S0006-3495(99)77214-0<?supplied-pmid 9876159?>9876159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Menna-BarretoRFSGoncalvesRLSCostaEMSilvaRSFPintoAVOliveiraMFCastroSLThe effects on Trypanosoma cruzi of novel synthetic naphthoquinones are mediated by mitochondrial dysfunctionFree Radic Biol Med20094764465310.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.06.004<?supplied-pmid 19501647?>19501647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>GottliebEArmourSMHarrisMHThompsonCBMitochondrial membrane potential regulates matrix configuration and cytochrome c release during apoptosisCell Death Differ20031070971710.1038/sj.cdd.4401231<?supplied-pmid 12761579?>12761579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Santa-RitaRMHenriques-PonsABarbosaHSCastroSLEffect of the lysophospholipid analogues edelfosine, ilmofosine and miltefosine against Leishmania amazonensisJ Antimicrob Chemother20045470471010.1093/jac/dkh380<?supplied-pmid 15329361?>15329361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>PozarowskiPHalickaDHDarzykiewiczZNF-κB inhibitor sesquiterpene parthenolide induces concurrently atypical apoptosis and cell necrosis: difficulties in identification of dead cells in such culturesCytometry200354A11812410.1002/cyto.a.1005712879458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>AlonsoAMeirellesNCTabakMEffect of hydration upon the fluidity of intercellular membranes of stratum corneum: an EPR studyBiochim Biophys Acta1995123761510.1016/0005-2736(95)00069-F<?supplied-pmid 7619844?>7619844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>AlonsoAQueirozCSMagalhãesACChilling stress leads to increased cell membrane rigidity in roots of coffee (Coffea arabica L.) seedlingsBiochim Biophys Acta19971323758410.1016/S0005-2736(96)00177-0<?supplied-pmid 9030214?>9030214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>NepomucenoMFAlonsoAPereira-da-SilvaLTabakMInhibitory effect of dipyridamole and its derivatives on lipid peroxidation in mitochondriaFree Radic Biol Med1997231046105410.1016/S0891-5849(97)00135-4<?supplied-pmid 9358248?>9358248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>ZilbersteinDThe role of pH and temperature in the development of Leishmania parasitesAnnu Rev Microbiol19944844947010.1146/annurev.mi.48.100194.002313<?supplied-pmid 7826014?>7826014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Ueda-NakamuraTAttiasMSouzaWMegasome biogenesis in Leishmania amazonensis: a morphometric and cytochemical studyParasitol Res200187899710.1007/s004360000319<?supplied-pmid 11206117?>11206117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>BudilDELeeSSaxenaSFreedJHNonlinear-least-squares analysis of slow-motional EPR spectra in one and two dimensions using a modified Levenberg-Marquardt algorithmJ Magn Reson1996A120155189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Dos AnjosJLVNetoDDAlonsoAEffects of ethanol/L-menthol on the dynamics and partitioning of spin-labeled lipids in the stratum corneumEur J Pharm Biopharm20076740641210.1016/j.ejpb.2007.02.004<?supplied-pmid 17350812?>17350812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Dos AnjosJLVAlonsoATerpenes increase the partitioning and molecular dynamics of an amphipathic spin label in stratum corneum membranesInt J Pharm200835010311210.1016/j.ijpharm.2007.08.024<?supplied-pmid 17950546?>17950546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
