<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Science and Pollution Research International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0944-1344</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1614-7499</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4871916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6179</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-016-6179-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Seasonal variability of mercury concentration in soils, buds and leaves of Acer platanoides and Tilia platyphyllos in central Poland </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>Artur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6315-3758</contrib-id><name><surname>Frankowski</surname><given-names>Marcin</given-names></name><address><email>marcin.frankowski@amu.edu.pl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Water and Soil Analysis, Adam Mickiewicz University in Poznań, Umultowska 89b, 61-614 Poznań, Poland </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Responsible editor: Elena Maestri </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><fpage>9614</fpage><lpage>9624</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this paper, we present the results of mercury concentration in soils, buds and leaves of maple (Acer platanoides—Ap) and linden (Tilia platyphyllos—Tp) collected in four periods of the growing season of trees, i.e. in April (IV), June (VI), August (VIII) and November (IX) in 2013, from the area of Poznań city (Poland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The highest average concentration of mercury for 88 samples was determined in soils and it equaled 65.8 ± 41.7 ng g−1 (range 14.5–238.9 ng g−1); lower average concentration was found in Ap samples (n = 66): 55.4 ± 18.1 ng g−1 (range 26.5–106.9 ng g−1); in Tp samples 50.4 ± 15.8 ng g−1 (range 23.1–88.7 ng g−1) and in 22 samples of Tp buds 40.8 ± 22.7 ng g−1 (range 12.4–98.7 ng g−1) and Ap buds 28.2 ± 13.6 ng g−1 (range 8.0–59.5 ng g−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Based on the obtained results, it was observed that the highest concentration of mercury in soils occurred in the centre of Poznań city (95.5 ± 39.1 ng g−1), and it was two times higher than the concentration of mercury in other parts of the city. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Similar dependencies were not observed for the leaf samples of Ap and Tp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>It was found that mercury concentrations in the soil and leaves of maple and linden were different depending on the period of the growing season (April to November). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Mercury content in the examined samples was higher in the first two research periods (April IV, June VI), and then, in the following periods, the accumulation of mercury decreased both in soil and leaf samples of the two tree species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>There was no correlation found between mercury concentration in leaves and mercury concentration in soils during the four research periods (April–November). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>When considering the transfer coefficient, it was observed that the main source of mercury in leaves is the mercury coming from the atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Mercury</kwd><kwd>Soil</kwd><kwd><italic>Acer platanoides</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Tilia platyphyllos</italic></kwd><kwd>CV-AFS</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In the natural environment, mercury constantly undergoes complex transformations at different levels of its cycle in the air, water, soil, bottom sediments, plants and living organisms (Horvat et al. 1999; Melamed and Villas Bôas 2000; Ericksen and Gustin 2004; Brent and Berberich 2014; Looi et al. 2015; Ma et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Owing to its toxicity, mobility and long residence time in the atmosphere, mercury is considered as one of the major hazardous substances (Poissant et al. 2008; Wang et al. 2012; Pérez-Sanz et al. 2012; Rallo et al. 2014; Siudek et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Prior to its re-deposition on the surface of the land or ocean, mercury can be retained in the atmosphere for a period of 6 to 24 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Such pollutants as mercury can be transported thousands of kilometres from the emission source, causing regional and global pollution problems (Wang et al. 2012; De Simone et al. 2014; Jang et al. 2014; Wang et al. 2014b, Chételat et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there is a constant need to monitor mercury-related processes in order to understand the biogeochemical cycle of this element in the environment (Hellings et al. 2013; Lodenius 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>There are two ways of mercury transfer to plants: from the atmosphere and from the soil (Kabata-Pendias 2001; Ericksen and Gustin 2004; Poissant et al. 2008, Pérez-Sanz et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The availability of mercury in soil is low for plants, and its accumulation in roots is not observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The roots act as a barrier against mercury uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>This was found in the studies of polluted soils, in which a positive correlation between mercury concentrations in the soil and plants was not determined (Pérez-Sanz et al. 2012; Lodenius 2013; Amorós et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the main source of mercury in leaves is the atmosphere (Ericksen et al. 2003; Fay and Gustin 2007; Windham-Myers et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Transfer of mercury (gaseous and elemental mercury forms) from the atmosphere occurs by dry deposition and wet deposition (rain and snow) (Fay and Gustin 2007; Poissant et al. 2008; Adjorlolo-Gasokpoh et al. 2012; Niu et al. 2013; Lodenius 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>It was found that mercury concentration in leaves varies with the age of a plant, time of day and year (Ericksen et al. 2003; Rutter et al. 2011; Tabatchnick et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>High concentration of mercury in plants can cause negative biochemical effects such as changes in cell membrane permeability, inhibition of protein synthesis, bonding to sulphuryl groups, interference in photosynthetic and evaporation processes, and development of chlorosis (Kabata-Pendias 2001; Wang et al. 2012; Lodenius 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the trees growing in large urban areas and experiencing the adverse effects of mercury may develop conditions such as chlorotic spots, brown spots on the edges of the lamina, and shortening and deformation of buds and roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>It has been estimated that the average content of mercury in plants is 100–1000 ng g−1 (Yudovich and Ketris 2005; Garcia-Sánchez et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Mercury is adsorbed on colloids in soil, and the rate of this process depends primarily on the composition of the soil, amount of organic matter, quantity and type of clay minerals, hydrated oxides, pH and redox potential (Kabata-Pendias 2001; Pérez-Sanz et al. 2012; Zhang et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Mercury in soil originates from three sources:Natural processes, i.e. weathering of rocks, volcanic eruptions and geothermal activity.Anthropogenic activities and re-deposition of mercury previously emitted to the atmosphere (Wang et al., 2012; Wang et al. 2014a); it is believed that deposition from the atmosphere is the main anthropogenic source of mercury in soils (Gupta and Nirwan 2015).Leaves fallen from trees; they supply surface soil layers with mercury (Ericksen et al. 2003; Rutter et al. 2011; Tabatchnick et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Organic matter from the fallen leaves is mineralized, and mercury is released into the soil (Tabatchnick et al. 2012; Wang et al. 2012; Hellings et al. 2013; Rutter et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Soils from treeless areas contain less mercury than those from woodland areas (Ericksen et al. 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In dry soils, mercury bound to organic matter can be methylated by bacteria and become a source of methylmercury both for the soil and water (Kloke et al. 1984; Rutter et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Determination of natural mercury content in soils is difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>This value has been estimated to be between 20 and 190 ng g−1 (Li and Wu 1991; Curlic et al. 1995; Chen et al. 1999; Brabo et al. 2003; Wang et al. 2012), while the average content of mercury in soils of different world regions is in the range of 50–500 ng g−1 (Kabata-Pendias 2001; Wang et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Many authors have studied the effect of mercury concentration on the soil and air on the content of this metal in plants, especially in their leaves (Ericksen et al. 2003; Ericksen and Gustin 2004; Fay and Gustin 2007; Niu et al. 2013; Amorós et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, in most cases, the studies were carried out in laboratory conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>They were focused on assessing changes in the mercury content of plants during the experiment in which mercury concentrations in the soil or air were modified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Young or annual plants were most often used in the experiments, as they are more susceptible to pollution than older or perennial plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The aims of this study were to (1) determine total mercury content in the samples of soils and plants (buds and leaves) of two tree species: Acer platanoides (Ap) and Tilia platyphyllos (Tp); (2) present spatial distribution of mercury in the soil and plants of the Poznań area; (3) estimate the variability of mercury concentration in plants during different periods of the growing season: April (IV), June (VI), August (VIII) and November (XI); and (4) determine the relationship between mercury concentrations in soil samples and the two tree species, by using statistical tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Study area </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The city of Poznań (area: 261.8 km2, population: ~600 000) is located in the Wielkopolska province, in central Poland (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The city is a central part of the Poznań Agglomeration, bordering Luboń and Swarzędz towns and 11 municipalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Poznań has a direct access to five national roads and, on the south, to A2 motorway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The city has two airports: civilian and military. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The industry in Poznań is dominated by electrical engineering, chemical and food branches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The area examined in this study is under constant influence of a variety of industrial and municipal emission sources, which mainly include the following: heat and power plants CFPP Karolin and CFPP Garbary, local boiler rooms and household furnaces, where coal is the primary fossil fuel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The other mercury sources include the following: municipal and hospital waste landfills, cement plants, sewage treatment plants, factories and plants that use high-temperature industrial processes and road traffic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The average annual temperature in Poznań is about 8.5 °C, and the prevailing wind direction is northwest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Poznań has the lowest annual precipitation in Poland (&lt;550 mm), and a 32 % decline in precipitation occurs during the winter season. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The growing season for this area is one of the longest in Poland, from 200 to 220 days (RIEP 2012, 2013).Fig. 1Map of the study area with sampling points and potential emission sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Points located in the city centre are in the circle  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Sampling and chemical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Samples of buds, leaves (Tp and Ap) and soil were collected from the area of Poznań city in four periods of the growing season, from April to November 2013 (marked as IV, VI, VIII, XI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The research material came from 22 points located in Poznań. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>These sampling points were chosen from the areas where both tree species grow close to each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Additionally, soil samples were collected from the same points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The areas where samples (buds, leaves, soil) were collected are presented in Fig. 1, and sampling points located in the city centre are in the circle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Soil samples were collected from a 20-cm layer of soil, using the soil sampler, and placed in PE containers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Visible plant parts and stones were removed from the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Bud samples were collected in April (IV), and growing leaves—from June (VI) to August (VIII)—from a height of 1.5 m above the ground. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In November (IX), the leaves that fallen from the trees were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The plant material was placed in polyethylene bags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The geographical position of each sampling point was registered with a GPS navigation device Garmin 60 CSx (Table. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>After delivery to the laboratory, the research material (soil, leaves and buds) was dried at room temperature, then homogenized in an agate mortar and sieved through a 0.15-mm mesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The leaf samples were not washed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A 1.00 ± 0.01 g of each sample was weighted and placed in a digestion vessel made of PTFE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Then, 9 ml of HCl and 3 ml of HNO3 were added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The mixture was left for 12-h slow digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the samples were mineralized using a Mars 5 microwave digestion system, according to a modified EPA method no. 3051 (Frankowski et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Acids of the highest purity (Sigma-Aldrich, USA), dedicated to the analysis of mercury, were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Tin(II) chloride of low mercury content (Merck Darmstadt, Germany) was used for the preparation of the reduction solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Deionized water was obtained from the Hydrolab System (Poland) and additionally purified from trace amounts of mercury with a stream of argon for 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The calibration working solutions were prepared by appropriate dilution of the standard solution of 1000 ± 2 mg/l Hg(NO3)2 (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) in 12 % HNO3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Mercury concentration in soil and plant samples was determined using a cold-vapour atomic fluorescence spectrometer (CV-AFS)—Millennium Merlin Analyzer 10.025 (PS Analytical, England). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Similar analytical method for the determination of total mercury was applied by Boszke et al. (2008), Boszke and Kowalski (2006, 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>CV-AFS method validation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Certified reference materials for soil, SRM 2709, and leaves, SRM 1515 (National Institute of Standards and Technology, USA), were used to verify the analytical method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The CRMs were analysed in ten replicates, and the average value, standard deviation and recovery of the method [%] were calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The results of the mercury content in CRM are presented in Table 1.Table 1Mercury concentration in the certified reference materialsSRM 2709SRM 1515Certified value[ng g−1]1400 ± 8044 ± 4Determined value[ng g−1]1435 ± 3443 ± 2Recovery[%]102.5 ± 2.597.7 ± 4.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The results of mercury concentration in the samples of soil and plants (Ap and Tp) collected from the Poznań area are presented in Table 2 and in Figs. 2, 3 and 4.Table 2Mercury concentration in the samples of soil, buds and leaves of Ap and Tp [ng g−1]SampleCoordinationsConcentration of mercury [ng g−1]Soil Ap  Tp IVVIVIIIXIIVVIVIIIXIIVVIVIIIXI1N 52° 28′ 39.5″E 16° 47′ 04.1″58.7 ± 1.560.3 ± 1.290.7 ± 2.9132.9 ± 3.598.4 ± 3.164.2 ± 1.763.1 ± 1.664.8 ± 1.721.1 ± 0.879.6 ± 2.272.4 ± 2.051.0 ± 1.32N 52° 28′ 16.4″E 16° 51′ 21.0″29.0 ± 0.524.4 ± 0.322.6 ± 0.521.3 ± 0.512.4 ± 0.532.3 ± 0.933.1 ± 0.930.1 ± 0.927.8 ± 0.958.8 ± 1.555.4 ± 1.940.7 ± 1.03N 52° 28′ 23.4″E 16° 48′ 12.4″19.8 ± 0.324.6 ± 0.419.0 ± 0.619.1 ± 0.523.8 ± 0.644.4 ± 1.343.2 ± 1.438.1 ± 1.011.7 ± 0.649.8 ± 1.451.6 ± 1.526.7 ± 0.94N 52° 26′ 09.4″E 16° 50′ 34.6″32.8 ± 0.718.9 ± 0.117.4 ± 0.520.9 ± 0.617.9 ± 0.425.1 ± 0.848.4 ± 1.543.2 ± 1.237.1 ± 1.055.9 ± 1.554.2 ± 1.532.7 ± 1.05N 52° 24′ 54.5″E 16° 52′ 57.4″98.1 ± 2.964.9 ± 2.472.8 ± 2.879.2 ± 2.221.9 ± 0.646.8 ± 1.240.1 ± 1.039.2 ± 1.244.0 ± 1.278.8 ± 2.170.5 ± 1.938.8 ± 1.06N 52° 27′ 28.8″E 16° 54′ 48.6″38.5 ± 1.031.5 ± 0.929.8 ± 0.827.3 ± 0.848.5 ± 1.267.1 ± 1.960.5 ± 1.654.0 ± 1.431.2 ± 1.091.5 ± 2,495.3 ± 2.549.1 ± 1.17N 52° 27′ 03.9″E 16° 56′ 34.5″120.8 ± 2.9238.9 ± 5.0159.6 ± 5.2109.1 ± 3.145.5 ± 1.356.0 ± 1.655.3 ± 1.562.6 ± 1.918.4 ± 0.871.6 ± 1.956.3 ± 1.453.9 ± 1.58N 52° 26′ 27.9″E 16° 55′ 23.4″51.0 ± 1.167.8 ± 1.248.0 ± 1.649.1 ± 1.323.4 ± 0.938.7 ± 1.130.4 ± 0.948.2 ± 1.628.0 ± 0.944.3 ± 1.181.8 ± 2.240.1 ± 1.09N 52° 25′ 49.0″E 16° 56′ 35.5″109.3 ± 3.0148.3 ± 4.7112.8 ± 3.499.8 ± 2.739.2 ± 1.171.4 ± 1.973.4 ± 1.968.7 ± 1.828.6 ± 0.975.8 ± 2.066.8 ± 1.735.4 ± 1.010N 52° 24′ 40.1″E 16° 55′ 06.7″89.5 ± 2.7112.4 ± 3.979.9 ± 2.296.8 ± 2.860.0 ± 1.842.7 ± 1.553.6 ± 1.439.7 ± 1.016.3 ± 0.564.9 ± 1.755.5 ± 1.534.2 ± 1.111N 52° 24′ 02.0″E 16° 55′ 54.0″146.1 ± 4.374.8 ± 2.5111.3 ± 3.775.9 ± 2.060.5 ± 1.988.7 ± 2.536.5 ± 1.051.3 ± 1.424.7 ± 0.862.7 ± 1.640.0 ± 1.237.5 ± 1.212N 52° 24′ 24.3″E 16° 50′ 14.9″31.5 ± 0.723.1 ± 0.624.1 ± 0.524.9 ± 0.538.2 ± 1.248.8 ± 1.345.2 ± 1.446.9 ± 1.215.6 ± 0.676.9 ± 2.279.3 ± 2.543.0 ± 1.113N 52° 24′ 05.5″E 16° 52′ 24.2″117.0 ± 3.188.2 ± 2.562.3 ± 1.954.3 ± 1.418.1 ± 0.776.9 ± 2.070.6 ± 2.068.5 ± 1.825.0 ± 0.8106.9 ± 2,888.6 ± 2.555.6 ± 1.414N 52° 23′ 16.8″E 16° 51′ 40.5″49.5 ± 1.549.3 ± 1.350.2 ± 1.153.2 ± 1.329.4 ± 0.981.4 ± 2.288.3 ± 2.383.4 ± 2.515.2 ± 0.656.1 ± 1.455.3 ± 1.432.1 ± 0.915N 52° 24′ 29.7″E 16° 56′ 50.7″97.9 ± 2.0114.8 ± 3.856.3 ± 1.580.7 ± 2.534.2 ± 0.955.9 ± 1.636.3 ± 1.129.1 ± 1.132.1 ± 0.957.3 ± 1.526.5 ± 0.943.2 ± 1.216N 52° 22′ 36.4″E 16° 57′ 40.5″39.4 ± 0.754.8 ± 1.621.8 ± 0.539.8 ± 1.066.4 ± 1.960.9 ± 1.836.2 ± 1.023.1 ± 0.88.0 ± 0.334.1 ± 0.936.8 ± 1.327.0 ± 0.917N 52° 22′ 18.0″E 16° 59′ 42.8″27.3 ± 0.375.2 ± 2.084.7 ± 2.351.3 ± 1.316.1 ± 0.665.3 ± 1.944.9 ± 1.239.7 ± 1.118.5 ± 0.755.9 ± 1.830.8 ± 0.926.9 ± 0.718N 52° 21′ 05.7″E 16° 01′ 30.4″120.1 ± 3.5135.5 ± 4.288.9 ± 2.585.4 ± 2.816.8 ± 0.555.8 ± 1.532.3 ± 0.939.8 ± 1.222.0 ± 0.745.9 ± 1.241.0 ± 1.154.0 ± 1.419N 52° 19′ 55.4″E 16° 55′ 27.4″20.9 ± 0.222.0 ± 0.319.6 ± 0.614.5 ± 0.633.6 ± 0.848.9 ± 1.554.6 ± 1.438.0 ± 1.034.3 ± 1.064.7 ± 1.660.3 ± 1.548.9 ± 1.420N 52° 18′ 38.2″E 16° 58′ 39.4″60.9 ± 1.044.7 ± 1.292.6 ± 2.742.5 ± 1.269.1 ± 2.038.5 ± 1.327.3 ± 0.839.8 ± 1.255.6 ± 1.560.0 ± 1.628.6 ± 0.955.0 ± 1.521N 52° 25′ 29.1″E 16° 59′ 38.4″49.1 ± 1.858.7 ± 1.790.6 ± 2.792.2 ± 2.656.1 ± 1.772.1 ± 2.049.1 ± 1.447.8 ± 1.359.5 ± 1.755.9 ± 1.469.7 ± 1.969.7 ± 1.522N 52° 26′ 42.0″E 17° 00′ 33.0″29.5 ± 0.848.0 ± 1.5128.5 ± 3.621.1 ± 0.468.5 ± 2.060.6 ± 1.746.1 ± 1.441.3 ± 1.245.4 ± 1.372.3 ± 2.051.1 ± 1.457.4 ± 1.3Fig. 2Concentration of mercury in soil samples (ng g−1)Fig. 3Concentration of mercury in buds and leaves of Ap (ng g−1)Fig. 4Concentration of mercury in buds and leaves of Tp (ng g−1) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Based on the results of mercury concentrations in the samples of soil (n = 88), buds (n = 22) and leaves (n = 66) of the two tree species, the Shapiro-Wilk test was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>At the significance level of α = 0.05, the following p values were obtained: 0.000008 for soil samples, 0.084 for buds of Tp, 0.197 for buds of Ap, 0.054 for leaves of Tp and 0.093 for leaves of Ap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>It was found that the results of mercury in soil samples were not normally distributed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The t test for the samples of both tree species showed that there was no statistically significant differences between the mean values of Hg concentration only for the samples of linden leaves (VI–XI) and maple leaves (VI–XI) (p = 0.137) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The Wilcoxon test showed that the mean value of mercury for soil samples, 65.8 ± 41.7 ng g−1 (median 55.6 ng g−1), was statistically different from the mean values obtained for Tp and Ap bud samples (IV), and Tp leaf samples (VI–XI), but not statistically different from Ap leaf samples (VI–XI) (p = 0.086) (Table 3).Table 3Statistical summary of mercury concentrations (ng g−1) in the samplesSampleAverage ± S.D.MedianMinimumMaximumSoil (IV–XI)65.8 ± 41.755.614.5238.9 Ap tree buds (IV)40.8 ± 22.736.212.498.7 Ap leaves (VI–IX)50.7 ± 15.848.023.188.7 Tp tree buds (IV)28.2 ± 13.626.68.059.5 Tp leaves (VI–IX)55.4 ± 18.155.426.5106.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>When analysing the results of soil samples (Table 2) in terms of the points of origin, it was found that the highest concentration of mercury was determined in a sample collected at point no. 7 in June (VI), and it equaled 238 ng g−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Throughout the whole study period (four sampling campaigns, from April to November), that point was also characterized by the highest average mercury content in the soil—157.1 ng g−1 (median 140.0 ng g−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Lower average Hg concentrations were determined for point nos. 9—117.6 ng g−1 (median 111.1 ng g−1), 18—107.5 ng g−1 (median 140.0 ng g−1) and 11—102.0 ng g−1 (median 93.6 ng g−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The lowest average mercury concentrations (19.3–31.8 ng g−1) for four periods of research were obtained for point nos. 19, 3, 4, 2, 12 and 6, located on the outskirts of Poznań. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The places where the lowest levels of mercury in soils were measured are not well populated and can be described as the areas with low-density development and small network of roads, mainly local access roads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the highest concentrations of mercury in soil were determined in the samples collected in the centre of Poznań (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The results of the Mann-Whitney U test showed that the mean value of mercury in the soil samples taken from the Poznań centre, for all the measurement periods (IV–XI), amounted to 95.5 ± 39.1 ng g−1 (median 91.4 ng g−1) and was statistically different from the mean value of mercury for the other soil samples—48.8 ± 32.9 ng g−1 (median 39.0 ng g−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Mercury content of soils from the centre of Poznań was two times higher than that from other parts of the city. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Pasieczna (2012) concluded that mercury concentrations in soils located in the centre of a city are four times higher than those in samples collected on the outskirts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Tijhuis et al. (2002) measured the average mercury content of soils taken from the centre of Oslo to be 480 ng g−1, which was over eight times higher than in other parts of the city. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The average mercury content of soil samples collected from central Stockholm (860 ng g−1) was 50 times higher than the content of rural soils (arable land) collected from the vicinity of Stockholm city (Linde et al. 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The city centre of Poznań can be characterized by a very compact way of building and large network of narrow low-capacity streets which are often congested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Therefore, high mercury concentrations in soils of this area should be mainly linked to the effect of mercury emission to the air, from the combustion of fossil fuels in domestic furnaces during the heating season, liquid fuels consumed by cars and the re-emission from the air to soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Taking into account the fact that the highest mercury concentrations were determined at point nos. 7, 9 and 11, located very close to the main emitters for Poznań city, i.e. CFPP Garbary and Karolin, it can be assumed that these power plants have a major negative impact on Hg content of soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The prevailing wind direction, i.e. north-western, suggests that other potential mercury emitters, e.g. municipal landfill, airports and motorways, are of minor importance in this regard. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>During the spatial analysis of the results of average mercury content of Tp and Ap samples in four measurement periods (April–November), it was observed that the highest concentrations of mercury in the leaves of both tree species were not found for the same sampling points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The highest average Hg levels in Tp samples were determined at point nos. 1 and 14, respectively [72.6 ng g−1 (median 64.8 ng g−1) and 70.6 ng g−1 (median 81.4 ng g−1)], while the highest average Hg values for Ap were measured at point nos. 6 and 8, respectively [69.6 ng g−1 (median 72.1 ng g−1) and 66.8 ng g−1 (median 70.3 ng g−1)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>It was also observed that the points were the highest average mercury concentrations in Ap and Tp were measured did not coincide with the points of the highest concentrations in soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The results of mercury concentration in 22 samples collected in four measurement periods (IV–XI) are shown in Table 4.Table 4Statistical summary of mercury concentrations (ng g−1) in the examined samples, for the four research periods (IV–XI)SampleAverage ± S.D.MedianSoil IV65.3 ± 39.350.2Soil VI71.9 ± 52.559.5Soil VIII67.4 ± 40.467.5Soil XI58.7 ± 34.452.3 Ap IV40.8 ± 22.736.2 Ap VI56.5 ± 16.355.9 Ap VIII48.6 ± 15.445.7 Ap IX47.2 ± 14.742.3 Tp IV28.2 ± 13.526.4 Tp VI64.5 ± 16.461.4 Tp VIII57.6 ± 19.255.5 Tp IX43.3 ± 11.541.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The non-parametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test was selected to compare the obtained average values of mercury concentration in the samples of soil, buds and leaves of both tree species, collected in IV and VI (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>For samples collected in the other periods, the t test was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Based on the statistical analysis, it was found that the average values of mercury were statistically different only for the following months: April (IV)—for Ap and Tp (p = 0.0304), and soil and Tp (p = 0.0362), June (VI)—for soil and Ap (p = 0.011), August (VIII)—for soil and Tp (p = 0.00472) and November (XI)—for soil and Ap (p = 0.0445). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the correlation coefficient between the values of mercury content in different types of samples for all the measurement periods (IV–XI) was also conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>For samples collected in April (IV) and June (VI), the Spearman correlation was used, while the Pearson correlation was used for the other samples (Table 5).Table 5Correlation coefficients between the values of mercury content in soil, linden and maple samples collected in different research periodsSoil IVSoil VILinden IVLinden VIMaple IVMaple VISoil IVa 1.0000000.7741390.1744780.3032190.0254090.239118Soil VIa 0.7741391.0000000.0242800.373235−0.1552800.057094Soil VIIIb 1.0000000.6595640.0850550.335306−0.1832040.412237Soil XIb 0.6595641.0000000.2138420.367927−0.0049180.226696 aSpearman correlation coefficient bPearson correlation coefficients </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The performed statistical calculations (at p = 0.05) showed no correlation between the concentrations of mercury in soil, buds and leaves in the same periods of measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Similar results (lack of correlations) were obtained by e.g. Pérez-Sanz et al. 2012; Lodenius 2013; Amorós et al. 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>When analysing average Hg values for each type of samples taken in four periods (IV—XI), the variability of mercury concentrations in time was observed (Fig. 5).Fig. 5Average mercury concentrations (ng g−1) in the samples of soil, Ap and Tp, in different measurement periods </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Similar relationships related to the variability of mercury concentrations in time were found for leaf samples by Ericksen et al. (2003), Poissant et al. (2008), Rutter et al. (2011) and Tabatchnick et al. (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The distribution of average Hg concentrations for samples of Ap, Tp and soil was similar for each of the measurement months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The maximum average concentrations of mercury were found in June (VI), and in the following months, the concentrations decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>When analysing average mercury concentrations in soil and tree samples, it was observed that the average value of Hg for soils in November (XI) (58.7 ng g−1) was lower than the value determined in April (IV) (65.3 ng g−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Such situation can be explained by the accumulation of mercury, originating mainly from snow and dry deposition (associated with the heating season), in the surface layers of soil in winter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The frozen soil stops or reduces the infiltration of water with pollutants into the deeper layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Then, the sorption of mercury occurs in the uppermost soil layers which are rich in organic matter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The increase in the concentration of mercury in soils from April (IV) to June (VI) was probably related to the mercury supply from the atmosphere and mercury release after organic matter mineralization, e.g. from leaves, during the period of temperature increase in spring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Based on temperature measurements made by the Regional Inspectorate for Environmental Protection in Poznań, it was observed that during the heating season (December 2012—March 2013) preceding the study period, the temperature pattern was as follows: very cold December, moderately cold January and February and extremely cold March. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In March, the minimum daily average temperature was −6 °C, while in April, a significant increase in the temperature was registered, which resulted in the rapid growth of vegetation (RIEP 2012, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The probable reason for the highest concentrations of mercury in leaves, determined in June, was the fact that the plants uptake minerals, including mercury, from soil, and this process is the most intensive in the initial vegetative phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Additionally, gaseous mercury can be assimilated into the plant system from the atmosphere through the stomata of leaves, and mercury bound to particulate matter can be adsorbed on the surface of leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The exchange of mercury through leaf stomata is less intensive at the end of the growing season, which is related to the ageing of the leaves (Poissant et al. 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>It is believed that mercury content of plant roots corresponds to the content of soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>About 95–99 % of mercury uptaken by the root system remains in the roots, and only a small portion can be transported to the leaves (Ericksen and Gustin 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Bishop et al. (1998) reported that this transport equals up to 11 %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The value is primarily influenced by mercury form, the pH of soil, organic matter content and plant genotype (Alloway and Ayres 1999; Kabata-Pendias 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The relationship between mercury concentration in the plant and soil can be described by the transfer coefficient (metal concentration in the above-ground part of a plant divided by the concentration of this metal in the soil), proposed by Kloke et al. (1984), which is in a range of 0.01–0.1 for mercury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In the case of the analysed samples, the average transfer coefficient was 1.04 (median 0.82, range 0.14–2.79) for Tp and 1.11 (median 0.77, range 0.15–3.37) for Ap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In the following sampling periods, the coefficient equaled: IV—0.88, VI—1.11, VIII—1.11 and XI—1.12 in linden, and IV—0.61, VI—1.38, VIII—1.38 and XI—1.09 in maple. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Such high values indicated that the main source of mercury in the examined plants was the particulate matter adsorbed on the leaves of both tree species (leaves were not washed for the study) and the gas exchange through the stomata followed by the accumulation in leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>These conclusions are similar to those proposed by other researchers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Fay and Gustin (2007) found that the increase in mercury concentration in leaves is primarily caused by mercury in the atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>They observed that the variability in the concentrations of mercury in the air, from 3.1 to 30.1 ng m−3, accompanied by constant Hg concentrations in the soil (60 ng g−1), was followed by a 3.8-fold and 3.1-fold increase in mercury concentrations in the leaves of Juniperus scopulorum and Robini pseudoacaci, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>When the mercury concentration in soil was increased from 60 to 27,700 ng g−1, the increase in leaves was only 1.19-fold for J. scopulorum and 1.01-fold for R. pseudoacaci (Fay and Gustin 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Ericksen and Gustin (2004) observed similar dependencies on the basis of the results of Populus tremuloides investigations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>When comparing the average mercury concentrations obtained in the present study for the soil from Poznań area with the results of previous studies carried out for the same area (Table 6), it can be noticed that the mercury concentrations presented in this paper are lower than the results obtained in previous years (Falandysz et al. 1996; Lis and Pasieczna 2005; Boszke and Kowalski 2006; Frankowski et al. 2007; Kowalski et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In the case of soil, it was found that they are also lower than the concentrations of mercury in other large Polish cities, i.e. Katowice, Warsaw, Cracow and Gdynia (Pasieczna 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>When comparing the results of mercury in the leaves of the two tree species from Poznań with the literature data (Table 6), it was noticed that the concentrations have changed in the period of 8 years (Frankowski et al. 2007; Kowalski et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The present study shows a decline in mercury concentrations in leaves; however, they are still much higher than the values determined for Oborniki town (Frankowski et al. 2007), which is located about 40 km north of Poznań, at the edge of the Noteć Forest—one of the largest and least populated forest compounds in Poland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The average concentration of mercury in the Ap and Tp leaf samples from the Noteć Forest was 8.4 ng g−1 (6.8–9.2 ng g−1) and 10.9 ng g−1 (10.0–11.4 ng g−1), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Poissant et al. (2008) also measured lower concentrations of Hg in the leaves of Acer saccharum Marsh collected from forest areas, and the values were from 8.7 ± 1.5 to 30.8 ± 3.0 ng g−1 for different vegetative periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Based on the study results from the years 2005–2013, a tendency for high mercury concentrations could be observed for plant samples taken from the sampling point no. 1 (northern edge of Poznań). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In those years, the maximum or the highest values were determined at that point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The probable reason for such concentrations was a local emission source which introduced mercury into the atmosphere.Table 6Comparison of total mercury concentration (ng g−1) in soil and leaf samples determined in different studiesStudy areaType of sample(ng g−1) dry weightReferencePoznań, PolandSoilAverage 65.8; median 55.6 (range 14.5–238)This studyPoznań, PolandSoilAverage 96Falandysz et al. 1996 Poznań, PolandUrban soil of PoznańAverage 3120, median &lt;50 (range &lt;50–712,000)Lis and Pasieczna 2005 Poznań PolandSoil146 ± 130 (range 17–746)Boszke and Kowalski 2006 Poznań, PolandSoilAverage 132 (47–212)Kowalski et al. 2012 Katowice PolandSoil(Range 80–7550)Pasieczna 2012 Cracow, PolandSoil(Range &lt;50–1380)Pasieczna 2012 Warsaw PolandSoil(Range &lt;50–10,780)Pasieczna 2012 Gdynia, PolandSoilAverage 60 (range 60–300)Pasieczna 2012 Poznań, PolandLarge-leaved lindenAverage 48.4 (range 12.4–98.4)This studyPoznań, PolandNorway mapleAverage 48.3 (range 8.0–106.9)This studyPoznań, PolandLarge-leaved lindenAverage 123 (range 10–544)Frankowski et al. 2007 Poznań, PolandNorway mapleAverage 89.8 (range 6.6–328)Frankowski et al. 2007 Oborniki, PolandLarge-leaved lindenAverage 10.9 (range 10.0–11.4)Frankowski et al. 2007 Oborniki, PolandNorway mapleAverage 8.4 (range 6.8–9.2)Frankowski et al. 2007 Poznań, PolandLarge-leaved lindenAverage 165 (range 96–233)Kowalski et al. 2012 Poznań, PolandNorway mapleAverage 162 (range 116–207)Kowalski et al. 2012  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The recent decrease in mercury concentrations in soil and leaf samples from Poznań was the result of continuous improvements in air quality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>According to data from the Central Statistical Office (RIEP 2012, 2013), a decrease in the emissions of particulate matter and gaseous pollutants, mainly from the heat and power plants in Poznań, including CFPP Karolin and CFPP Garbary, has been observed recently in the Poznań Agglomeration (Environmental Protection Programme 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Due to large emissions of PM, its largest emitters—CFPPs in Poznań—changed the technology of ash removal and stopped using boilers which were the most burdensome for the environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The so-called low-stack emission was also decreased as a result of investments aimed at the conversion of the way of heating, from coal-fired domestic furnaces/boilers into central heating from CFPPs, or the replacement of coal-fired domestic boilers/furnaces, often in very poor condition, for modern gas- or liquid-fueled boilers which are more environment friendly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The increase of environmental awareness among Poles also contributed to the improvement of the quality of the air. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Until now, it was common for many people to burn wastes such as cardboards, newspapers and magazines, PET bottles, rubber and textiles in their household boilers/furnaces, especially at the beginning and end of the heating season. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Currently, as a result of public information campaigns and mandatory segregation of waste, many items are recycled or go to a landfill, instead of being burnt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Other investments which are more often carried out to reduce the air pollution include alternative energy sources, e.g. solar panels in public buildings, thermo-modernization of buildings, introduction of new technologies and installation of industrial dust collectors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Based on the investigations of soil, bud and leaf samples of Ap and Tp, carried out in four periods of the growing season, from April (IV) to November (XI), the following conclusions were drawn:Mercury concentrations in 88 samples of soil were statistically significantly higher than the values in buds and leaves collected from the area of Poznań. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The statistical analysis of buds and leaves of the two tree species revealed that only for the leaf samples of Tp and Ap there were no significant differences between the average concentrations of mercury.The analysis of the spatial variability in mercury content of soils showed a twofold higher concentrations of mercury in the city centre than in other parts of the city. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>There was no similar dependence observed for tree samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Higher concentrations in soils were primarily caused by the so-called low-stack emission from the combustion of fossil fuels in domestic furnaces/boilers during the heating season and by the emission from liquid fuels combusted by cars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>A negative impact of the two power and heat plants in Poznań, CFPP Garbary and CFPP Karolin, was also reported.The variability of mercury concentration in soils in different periods of the growing season, from April (IV) to November (XI), was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In the first two periods of measurements (IV, VI), mercury content was higher, while in the following periods, the accumulation of mercury both in soil and leaf samples was lower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>There was no correlation between mercury concentrations in leaves and mercury concentration in soils for any of the four measurement periods (April–November).Based on the analysis of the transfer coefficient, it was found that high concentrations of mercury in the examined trees were the result of mercury coming from the particulate matter adsorbed on leaves of both tree species, mercury associated with gas exchange through the stomata and its further accumulation in leaves.When comparing the past and current results of mercury concentration measured in soil and plant samples, it was noted that the values for the area of Poznań have decreased recently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>This is mainly the effect of the air quality improvements in Poznań, after the introduction of ecological policies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><notes notes-type="conflict-interest"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Adjorlolo-GasokpohAGolowAAKambo-DorsaJMercury in the surface soil and cassava, Manihot esculenta (flesh, leaves and peel) near goldmines at Bogoso and Prestea, GhanaBull Environ Contam Toxicol2012891106111010.1007/s00128-012-0849-723052587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Alloway B, Ayres D (1999) Chemical principles of environmental pollution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>PWN Warsaw </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Amorós J-A, Esbrí JM, García-Navarro F-J, Pérez-de-los-Reyes C, Bravo S, Villaseñor B, Higueras P (2014) Variations in mercury and other trace elements contents in soil and in vine leaves from the Almadén Hg-mining district. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>J Soils Sediments 14:773–777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Bishop KH, Lee Y-H, Munthe J, Dambrine E (1998) Xylem sap as a pathway for total mercury and methylmercury transport from soils to tree canopy in the boreal forest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Biogeochem 40:101–113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>BoszkeLKowalskiASpatial distribution of mercury in bottom sediments and soils from PoznańPoland Polish J Environ Stud20062211218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Boszke L, Kowalski A, Astel A, Baranowski A, Gworek B, Siepak J (2008) Mercury mobility and bioavailability in soil from contaminated area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Environ Geol 55:1075–1087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Boszke L, Kowalski A (2007) Total mercury in floodplain soils of the Warta river, Poland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Pol J Environ Stud 16 (4):517–523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>BraboEAngelicaRSilvaAFaialKMascarenhasASantosEJesusILoureiroEAssessment of mercury levels in soils, waters, bottom sediments and fishes of Acre state in Brazilian AmazonWater Air Soil Pollut2003147617710.1023/A:1024510312250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>BrentRNBerberichDAUse of artificial stream mesocosms to investigate mercury uptake in the South River, VirginiaUSA Arch Environ Contam Toxicol20146620121210.1007/s00244-013-9964-724253586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>ChenMMaLHarrisWBaseline concentrations of 15 trace elements in Florida surface soilsJ Environ Qual1999281173118110.2134/jeq1999.00472425002800040018x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Chételat J, Braune B, Stow J, Tomlinson S (2015) Special issue on mercury in Canada's North: Summary and recommendations for future research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Sci Tot Environ 509–510:260–262. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Curlic J., Sefcik P., Vojtas J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>(1995) Preliminary results on background values for some elements in Slovakian soils, In: Proceedings Conference “From soil survey to sustainable farming”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Stara Lesna. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>De SimoneFGencarelliCNHedgecockIMPirroneNGlobal atmospheric cycle of mercury: a model study on the impact of oxidation mechanismsEnviron Sci Pollut Res2014214110412310.1007/s11356-013-2451-x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Environmental Protection Programme for the city of Poznan for the years 2013-2016 with a perspective up to 2020 (in polish) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>EricksenJAGustinMSSchorranDEJohnsonDWLindbergSEColemanJSAccumulation of atmospheric mercury in forest foliageAtm Environ2003371613162210.1016/S1352-2310(03)00008-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>EricksenJAGustinMSFoliar exchange of mercury as a function of soil and air mercury concentrationsSci Total Environ200432427127910.1016/j.scitotenv.2003.10.03415081712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>FalandyszJKawanoMDanisiewiczDChwirABoszkeLGołębiowskiMBoryłoABadania nad występowaniem rtęci w glebach w PolsceBromat Chem Toksykol199629177181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>FayLGustinMAssessing the influence of different atmospheric and soil mercury concentrations on foliar mercury concentrations in a controlled environmentWat Air Soil Pollut200718137338410.1007/s11270-006-9308-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>FrankowskiMKowalskiAZiołaASiepakJDetermination of mercury in leaves of Acer plantanoides and Tilia platyphyllos in the area of the city of Poznań and its vicinityOceanol Hydrobiol Stud200736112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>FrankowskiMZioła-FrankowskaASiepakJFrom soil to leaves—aluminum fractionation by single step extraction procedures in polluted and protected areasJ Environ Manage20131271910.1016/j.jenvman.2013.04.03323651943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Garcia-SánchezAMurciegoAÁlvarez-AyusoEReginaISRodríguez-GonzálezMAMercury in soils and plants in an abandoned cinnabar mining area (SW Spain)J Haz Mat20091681319132410.1016/j.jhazmat.2009.03.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>GuptaSNirwanJEvaluation of mercury biotransformation by heavy metal-tolerant Alcaligenes strain isolated from industrial sludgeInt J Environ Sci Technol201512995100210.1007/s13762-013-0484-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>HellingsJAdelojuSBVerheyenTVRapid determination of ultra-trace concentrations of mercury in plants and soils by cold vapour inductively coupled plasma-optical emission spectrometryMicrochem J2013111626610.1016/j.microc.2013.02.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>HorvatMCovelliSFaganeliJLogarMMandićVRajarRŠircaAŽagarDMercury in contaminated coastal environments; a case study: the Gulf of TriesteSci Total Environ1999237–238435610.1016/S0048-9697(99)00123-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Jang H.-N, Kim J.-H, Jung S.-J., Back S.-K, Sung J.-H., Kim S.-H., Seo Y.-C., Keel S.-I., Lu X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>(2014) Mercury emission characteristics from coal combustion by supplying oxygen and carbon dioxide with limestone injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Fuel Process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Technol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>125:217–222. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Kabata-Pendias A (2001) Trace elements in soil and plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>CRC Press, Washington, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Kloke A., Sauerbeck D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>R., Vetter J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>(1984) The contamination of plants and soils with heavy metals and the transport of metals in terrestrial food chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Changing Met. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Cyc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Human Health, ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Nriagu, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>O. pp.113 − 141. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>KowalskiAFrankowskiMZioła-FrankowskaAMocek-PłóciniakASiepakJVariability of mercury concentrations in soil and leaves of Acer plantanoides and Tilia platyphyllos in Poznań city, PolandSoil Sed Contamin2012211022103110.1080/15320383.2012.712074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>LiJWuYHistorical changes of soil metal background values in select areas of ChinaWater Air Soil Pollut199157–5875576110.1007/BF00282939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>LindeMBengtssonHÖbornIConcentration and pools of heavy metals in urban soils in Stockholm, SwedenWater Air Soil Pollut200118310110.1023/A:1017599920280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>LisJPasiecznaAGeochemical Atlas of Poznania and the surrounding areas2005WarsawPolish Geological Institute </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>LodeniusMUse of plants for biomonitoring of air borne mercury in contaminated areasEnviron Res201312511312310.1016/j.envres.2012.10.01423472606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>LooiLJArisAZYusoffFMDHashimZMercury contamination in the estuaries and coastal sediments of the Strait of MalaccaEnviron Monit Assess2015187409910.1007/s10661-014-4099-525380712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>MaLZhongHWuY-GEffects of metal-soil contact time on the extraction of mercury from soilsBull Environ Contam Toxicol20159439940610.1007/s00128-015-1468-x25613855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>MelamedRVillas BôasRCApplication of physico-chemical amendments for the counteraction of mercury pollutionSci Tot Environ200026120320910.1016/S0048-9697(00)00634-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>NiuZZhangXWangSCiZKongXWangZThe linear accumulation of atmospheric mercury by vegetable and grass leaves: potential biomonitors for atmospheric mercury pollutionEnviron Sci Pollut Res2013206337634310.1007/s11356-013-1691-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>PasiecznaAMercury in topsoil of urban areas of PolandPrz Geol2012604658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Pérez-SanzAMillánRSierraMJAlarcónRGarcíaPGil-DíazMVazquezSLoboMCMercury uptake by Silene vulgaris grown on contaminated spiked soilsJ Environ Manage20129523323710.1016/j.jenvman.2010.07.018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>PoissantLPiloteMYumvihozeELeanDMercury concentrations and foliage/atmosphere fluxes in a maple forest ecosystem in Québec, CanadaJ Geophys Res200811310.1029/2007JD009510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>RalloMFuente-CuestaALopez-AntonMADíaz-SomoanoMMartínez-TarazonaMRMaroto-ValerMMSpeciation of Hg retained in gasification biomass chars by temperature-programmed decompositionFuel Proces Technol20141261410.1016/j.fuproc.2014.04.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>RIEP—Regional Inspectorate for Environmental Protection (2012 and 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>RutterAPSchauerJJShaferMMCreswellJEOlsonMRRobinsonMCollinsRMParmanAMKatzmanTLMallekJLDry deposition of gaseous elemental mercury to plants and soils using mercury stable isotopes in a controlled environmentAtm Environ20114584885510.1016/j.atmosenv.2010.11.025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>SiudekPFalkowskaLBrodeckaAKowalskiAFrankowskiMSiepakJMercury in precipitation over the coastal zone of the southern Baltic Sea, PolandEnviron Sci Poll Res2015222546255710.1007/s11356-014-3537-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>TabatchnickMDNogaroGHammerschmidtCRPotential sources of methylmercury in tree foliageEnviron Pollut2012160828710.1016/j.envpol.2011.09.01322035929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>TijhuisLBrattliBSaetherOA geochemical survey of topsoil in the city of Oslo, NorwayEnviron Geochem Health200224679410.1023/A:1013979700212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>WangJFengXAndersonCWNXingYShangLRemediation of mercury contaminated sites—a reviewEnviron Res2012125113123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>WangJFengXAndersonCWNWangHWangLThiosulphate-induced mercury accumulation by plants: metal uptake and transformation of mercury fractionation in soil—results from a field studyPlant Soil2014375213310.1007/s11104-013-1940-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>WangFWangSZhangLYangHWuQHaoJMercury enrichment and its effects on atmospheric emissions in cement plants of ChinaAtm Environ20149242142810.1016/j.atmosenv.2014.04.029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Windham-MyersLMarvin-DiPMKakourosEAgeeJLKieuLHStrickerCAFleckJAAckermanJTMercury cycling in agricultural and managed wetlands of California, USA: seasonal influences of vegetation on mercury methylation, storage, and transportSci Total Environ201448430831810.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.05.02723809880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>YudovichYKetrisMMercury in coal: a review: part 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>GeochemistryInternational J Coal Geol20056210713410.1016/j.coal.2004.11.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>ZhangHLiYLuoYChristiePAnthropogenic mercury sequestration in different soil types on the southeast coast of ChinaJ Soils Sed20151596297110.1007/s11368-015-1062-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
