<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4647564</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1395</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Metabolic and genomic analysis elucidates strain-level variation in Microbacterium spp. isolated from chromate contaminated sediment </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>Michael W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santo Domingo</surname><given-names>Jorge W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kourtev</surname><given-names>Peter S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>Roderick V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>James A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Learman</surname><given-names>Deric R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><email>deric.learman@cmich.edu</email></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute for Great Lakes Research and Department of Biology, Central Michigan University</institution>, <addr-line>Mount Pleasant, MI</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>National Risk Management Research Laboratory, Environmental Protection Agency</institution>, <addr-line>Cincinnati, OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Biology, Central Michigan University</institution>, <addr-line>Mount Pleasant, MI</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biological Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech)</institution>, <addr-line>Blacksburg, VA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="editor-1" contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>Shawn</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2015-11-10"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e1395</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2015-07-22"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2015-10-19"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Henson et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Henson et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/1395"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Hexavalent chromium [Cr(VI)] is a soluble carcinogen that has caused widespread contamination of soil and water in many industrial nations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Bacteria have the potential to aid remediation as certain strains can catalyze the reduction of Cr(VI) to insoluble and less toxic Cr(III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Here, we examine Cr(VI) reducing Microbacterium spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>(Cr-K1W, Cr-K20, Cr-K29, and Cr-K32) isolated from contaminated sediment (Seymore, Indiana) and show varying chromate responses despite the isolates’ phylogenetic similarity (i.e., identical 16S rRNA gene sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Detailed analysis identified differences based on genomic metabolic potential, growth and general metabolic capabilities, and capacity to resist and reduce Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the discrepancies between the isolates demonstrate the complexity inter-strain variation can have on microbial physiology and related biogeochemical processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd><italic>Microbacterium</italic></kwd><kwd>Chromium reduction</kwd><kwd>Strain-level variation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Central Michigan University’s College of Science and Technology</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Department of Biology</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-3"><funding-source>Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Central Michigan University’s College of Science and Technology, Department of Biology, and the Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Chromium (Cr) has become a major environmental pollutant due to its extensive use in industrial and mining industries (Barak et al., 2006; Brose &amp; James, 2010; Cheng, Holman &amp; Lin, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Chromium is the second most common contaminant at US Department of Energy sites, and without proper remediation could persist at dangerous levels well past 1,000 years from now (Okrent &amp; Xing, 1993; Riley, Zachara &amp; Wobber, 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Further, chromium is of particular concern because of its solubility in water and potential risk to drinking water; as well as the potential to inhibit the natural microbial communities engaged in the bioremediation of other pollutants (Bååth, 1989; Gough et al., 2008; Gough &amp; Stahl, 2011; Kourtev, Nakatsu &amp; Konopka, 2009; Nakatsu et al., 2005; Said &amp; Lewis, 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>As such, chromium contamination of soil and water poses risks to the United States and other industrial nations without proper remediation (Ackerley et al., 2004a; Beller et al., 2013; Cheng, Holman &amp; Lin, 2012; He et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Within the environment, chromium mainly persists in two forms: Cr(III) and Cr(VI) (Bartlett, 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Cr(VI) is highly toxic, soluble, and can be easily transported across cell membranes of both eukaryotic and prokaryotic organisms via sulfate and other active transporters (Ackerley et al., 2004b; Cheng, Holman &amp; Lin, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conversely, Cr(III) is sparingly soluble, thermodynamically stable, and found in oxide, hydroxide, and sulfate minerals, or complexed by organic matter (Barak et al., 2006; Brose &amp; James, 2010; Oze, Bird &amp; Fendorf, 2007; Oze et al., 2004; Viti et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>While the natural oxidation of Cr(III) is only mediated by a select number of abiotic substrates (e.g., manganese oxides and hydrogen peroxide), Cr(VI) reduction can be driven by various bacterial and abiotic factors (e.g., iron(II) and hydrogen sulfides) (Brose &amp; James, 2010; Oze et al., 2004; Viti et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Chromium (VI) compounds are highly toxic, mutagenic, and carcinogenic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Many microorganisms have been found to possess various mechanisms to reduce Cr(VI), which has potential impacts on bioremediation strategies (Suzuki et al., 1992). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Several bacterial species have been isolated and characterized detailing their unique mechanisms to reduce and resist Cr(VI) (Chovanec et al., 2012; Diaz-Perez et al., 2007; Field et al., 2013; He et al., 2010; Silver &amp; Phung, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>While certain bacteria can reduce Cr(VI) under anaerobic conditions (Beller et al., 2013; Chovanec et al., 2012; Lovley et al., 1993; Sheik et al., 2012), other bacteria possess soluble enzymes that facilitate reduction under aerobic conditions (Ackerley et al., 2004a; Barak et al., 2006; Cheung &amp; Gu, 2007; Gonzalez et al., 2005; Park et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In addition, bacteria can also utilize an efflux pump to aid resistance to chromate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>ChrA, part of the CHR superfamily, is a chromium transport protein that has been linked to Cr(VI) resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of this efflux pump has been determined by examining two model organisms, Cupravidus metallidurans and Pseudomonas aeruginos (Cervantes &amp; Ohtake, 1988; Cervantes et al., 1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In an in silico study, Ramirez-Diaz et al. (2008) identified 135 ChrA orthologs that were dominated by Proteobacteria representatives. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that chromate reduction under aerobic conditions can be catalyzed by soluble NADH/NADPH dependent oxidoreductases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Two of these chromate reductases have been well studied: ChrR in Pseudomonas putida (Park et al., 2000) and YieF in Escherichia coli (Barak et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>ChrR uses a one electron transfer to reduce Cr(VI) to Cr(V), a reactive intermediate, and then a second electron transfer to generate Cr(III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>While the reactive intermediate can re-oxidize into Cr(VI) (in the presence of oxygen), ChrR uses quinone reductase activity to help protect cells against reactive oxygen species (ROS) production (Ackerley et al., 2004a; Cheung &amp; Gu, 2007; Gonzalez et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>YieF, a sequence homolog of ChrR, utilizes a four electron transfer to reduce Cr(VI) to Cr(III). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The reductive mechanism of YieF also produces ROS, similar to ChrR, however, at a much lower rate (Ackerley et al., 2004b; Ramirez-Diaz et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Members of the genus Microbacterium have been shown to reduce chromate, however, the genes involved are not fully resolved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Indeed this is the case for Microbacterium sp. SUCR140 (Soni et al., 2014), Microbacterium sp. chr-3 (Focardi, Pepi &amp; Focardi, 2013), and Microbacterium sp. CR-07 (Liu et al., 2012), as each of the isolates have been shown to be effective reducers of chromate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Another example is the case for M. laevaniformans strain OR221 (Brown et al., 2012), a metal resistant bacterium whose genome has been described, however, its genome does not contain an annotated chrR or yieF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Here, we conducted a combined genomic, metabolic, and physiological analysis of chromate reducing bacteria from the Microbacterium genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Though the isolates were identical at the 16S rRNA level, we found considerable inter-strain genomic, metabolic, and Cr(VI) reduction and resistance variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This, taken together with their ability to resist and reduce high amounts of chromate, makes these isolates an interesting case study on microdiversity within highly related taxa as well as on chromate reduction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Methods &amp; Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Sample collection and isolation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Soil was collected in Seymour, IN from a Department of Transportation site known to have contamination from chromium, lead, and organic solvents (Kourtev, Nakatsu &amp; Konopka, 2006; Nakatsu et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Bill Jervis from the Indiana Department of Transport provided site access (no permit was required) and the project did not involve endangered or protected species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Bacterial strains were isolated from the contaminated soil as described in Kourtev, Nakatsu &amp; Konopka (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Briefly, isolates were enriched on 50% trypic soy agar (TSA) and 0.25 mM Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Colonies were picked from the TSA plates and placed in 50% TSB with .25 mM Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Individual isolates were grown at varying amounts of chromate enriched TSA and tryptic soy broth (TSB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The isolates were allowed to grow and then selected based on their varying abilities to resist and reduce Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Isolates were maintained on 50% TSA with 2 mM Cr(VI) as well as in 30% glycerol stocks stored at −80 °C to help preserve active pure cultures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Bacterial isolates used in this study (Cr-K1W, Cr-K20, Cr-K29, and Cr-K32) were grown in 250 ml of 50% TSB amended with 2 mM potassium chromate (K2CrO4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Following inoculation, isolates were incubated at 30 °C, 225 rpm for 24–72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Cells were harvested by centrifuging the cultures in 250 ml Nalgene bottles at 8,000 × g for 18 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was removed and the pellet was washed with autoclaved nanopure water following the same procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Cell pellets were extracted using the FastDNA® Spin Kit (MP Biomedical, Santa Ana, CA) with one modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Before extraction, cell pellets were resuspended in autoclaved nanopure water before 200 µl was transferred to the Lysis Matrix tube provided by the kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>DNA samples were recovered in 100 µl of DES solution and stored at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Chromate resistance and reduction experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All growth and reduction experiments were conducted in 50% TSB at 30 °C while shaking at 225 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Chromium was added when needed in the form of K2CrO4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Growth was measured on a UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Varian Cary 50, Agilent) at 600 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To test the ability of isolates to reduce Cr(VI), chromate was added to the media to a final concentration of 2 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Cultures, inoculated from −80 °C stocks, were grown overnight and then used to subculture fresh medium to an initial OD600 of 0.004. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Cultures were prepared in triplicates for each growth and reduction experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>OD600 and Cr(VI) reduction for each culture were measured at 6, 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, and 120 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>A Cr(VI) reduction assay was performed as described by Urone (1955), with minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Briefly, one mL of each culture was centrifuged at 7,000 rpm for seven minutes to remove biomass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Ten µL of the supernatant were added to 966 µL of deionized water to which 3.40 µL of sulfuric acid was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>1,5-Diphenylcarbazide (20 µL) was added to the sample and allowed to set for 10 min for full color development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Readings were taken on a Cary UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Agilent technologies, Santa Clara, CA) at 540 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Negative (uninoculated) controls of 50% TSB with 2 mM K2CrO4 were used to determine TSB-specific abiotic reduction of Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In addition, relative Cr(VI) reduction rates were calculated following Zhu et al. (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Resistance determinations were performed in 5 ml of 50% TSB to which K2CrO4 was added to final concentrations of 5, 10, 20, 40, 60, 80, and 100 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Cultures were prepared in triplicate for each resistance experiment and the OD600 was taken at 0 and 96 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Growth was determined against an abiotic control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Metabolic screening </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All four isolates were screened for their metabolic potential using Biolog’s GP2 plates (Hayward, CA) following the manufacturer’s protocol with minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Specifically, isolates were grown on Biolog Universal Growth (BUG) agar (Biolog, Hayward, CA) at 30 °C after which biomass was transferred to 25 ml of inoculating fluid (IF) (Biolog, Hayward, CA) containing sodium thioglycolate to achieve an OD600 between 0.68 and 0.75. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>An aliquot (150 µl) was placed into each well and then the plates were incubated for 22 h at 30 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Plates were read using Biolog’s OmniLog program (version 1.2.01) which corrects for any difference in OD600. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Absorbance values were converted to 0(-) for negative, 1(+) for positive, and .05(+/ − ) for borderline by the Biolog OmniLog program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Replicates with a minimum of two positives or borderlines or one positive and one borderline were considered positive for the metabolite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A total of 95 metabolites were tested per isolate (Table S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To ease data analysis, metabolites were grouped into 6 guilds (Zak et al., 1994): (1) carbohydrates, (2) carboxylic acids, (3) amino acids, (4) amines and amides, (5) polymers and (6) miscellaneous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The total number of positives for each guild was then calculated for each isolate and plotted using principal components analysis (PCA) in PAST3 (Harper &amp; Ryan, 2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Sequencing, de novo assembly, and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Whole genome shotgun sequencing was performed by multiplexing the genomic DNA onto one lane using the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform with 100 bp paired end reads using V2 chemistry at Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center’s Genetic Variation and Gene Discovery Core facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Raw Illumina genomic reads were trimmed of their adapter sequences using the default setting of the program Trimmomatic (version 0.27) (Lohse et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Trimmed reads were checked for quality using FastQC (version 0.10.2; http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/) and then trimmed for quality using the fastx_ trimmer (-Q33 -l 70) and fastx_ quality_ filter (-Q33 -q 30 -p 50) functions of the FastX toolkit program (version 0.13.2) (http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To determine the appropriate range of Kmer length for assembly, the program KmerGenie (version 1.5856) was used (Chikhi &amp; Medvedev, 2013; Zerbino &amp; Birney, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Cleaned pair end reads were assembled using the default setting of the assembly programs Velvet (version 1.2.10) (Zerbino &amp; Birney, 2008) and AbySS (version 1.3.6) (Simpson et al., 2009) at a range of Kmer surrounding the estimated Kmer size from KmerGenie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A third assembly was completed using the raw pair-end reads and the intergrated a5 pipeline assembly (Tritt et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This pipeline automates the processes of data cleaning, error correction, contig assembly, scaffolding, and quality control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The draft assemblies were compared and the best assembly picked for each isolate based on their total contigs, N50, genome size, max contig length, and mean contig length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>AbySS assemblies for all four isolates were used for all downstream analyses (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The average coverage of each genome was &gt;200×, with each assembly containing 30–81 contigs (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The contigs from the selected assembly were annotated and analyzed using the Departments of Energy’s Joint Genome Institutes IMG program (Markowitz et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Utilizing IMG’s data annotations, Pfam categories and their broad category gene counts for the respective genomes were extracted and normalized based on the sum of each row. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Principal component analysis (PCA) was then performed using PAST3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>All protein coding genes from the annotated draft isolate genomes were submitted to the Pacific Northwest National Laboratory’s Species Parallel and Orthology Solver (SPOCS) for analysis to determine pairs of orthologous and paraorthologous proteins between the closely related isolates (Curtis et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Analysis of genomes for the presence of chromate-related genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To increase the potential for finding chromate related genes, assembled contigs from the four representative isolate genomes were searched against a protein database of chromate related genes acquired from the UniprotKB database (http://www.uniprot.org/). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Three databases were downloaded containing the chromate related protein sequences of ChrA (efflux pump), ChrR (reductase), and YieF (reductase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Databases were obtained from text-based queries within the UniprotKB database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Because IMG based annotations did not return any chromate-related genes, assembled contigs were searched manually against individual databases with the BLASTX algorithm using a minimum e-value cutoff of 1e–05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Resultant nucleotide sequences with corresponding hits were translated using the translation tool from ExPAsy (http://expasy.org/) and examined to see if the sequences were found within a larger open reading frame (ORF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>For each sequence, the top sequence corresponding to an annotated protein with the highest bit and query coverage was selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The resultant amino acid sequence was searched using the protein BLAST tool from NCBI to further validate the gene candidate based on domain hits as shown within BLAST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Sequences were further scrutinized by examining the top resultant hit within IMG using their alignment tools and gene neighborhood viewer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees of the putative genes were made by using classic chrR and yieF genes downloaded from UniProtKB as well as from the top hits from homology searches within IMG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The protein sequences were aligned using ClustalW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic tree was then constructed using Maximum likelihood (bootstrap = 50) within the software MEGA (version 6.06) (Tamura et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Results &amp; Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Bacterial isolation and characterization of chromate resistance and reduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Four bacterial strains isolated from chromium contaminated soil samples (collected in Seymour, IN) were studied for their ability to resist and reduce Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>When introduced to Cr(VI), each isolate was able to grow and survive in a minimum of 2 mM chromate but differences in their growth were noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Overall, three isolates (Cr-K20, Cr-K29, and Cr-K32) grew to relatively dense cultures (OD ≥ 4.0) and had similar growth rates whether grown aerobically with or without Cr(VI) (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>1A–1D and Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Cr-K1W doubled in optical density when grown without Cr(VI) and it reached exponential growth earlier than the other isolates (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>When experiments were done with Cr(VI), Cr-K1W was also able to maintain a stable stationary phase for over 100 h, which was not observed for the other isolates under similar conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Chromate toxicity appeared to have the greatest effect on Cr-K1W when compared to the other three isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the isolate’s ability to grow and reduce chromate. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Chromate reduction (gray fill) and growth curves of Microbacterium spp. in the presence (black fill) or absence (no fill) of chromate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Negative (uninoculated) controls for chromate reduction are labeled in each graph with an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>(A) Cr-K1W, diamond; (B) Cr-K29, triangle; (C) Cr-K32, circle; (D) Cr-K20, square (n = 3, error bars are SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The isolates also had different abilities to reduce and resist chromate stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 were capable of reducing 2 mM chromate within 48 h (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>1C and 1D) and had the relatively fastest reduction rates (Table S1), while resisting up to 100 mM of chromate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Conversely, Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 were only able to resist up to 10 mM and reduced less than 1.2 mM of chromate after 120 h (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>1A and 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>These two isolates also had the lowest relative Cr(VI) reduction rates (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Taken together, a connection between reduction and resistance was evident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Chromate resistance has been shown to be connected to the efflux pump gene chrA, part of the CHR superfamily, (e.g., Diaz-Perez et al., 2007; Henne et al., 2009a; Ramirez-Diaz et al., 2008), which can provide a wide range of resistance, 0.3 mM–200 mM (Viti et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>However, the link between reduction and resistance in these isolates may point to the importance of a Cr(VI) reduction mechanism and other non-chromate specific responses in aiding resistance, instead of Cr(VI) resistance being driven solely by an efflux pump. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Metabolic fingerprinting of the isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Metabolic fingerprinting found variation between that isolates that is comparable to their growth differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>A survey of 95 potential metabolites showed a core group of 32 metabolites used among all four isolates (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, isolates Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 shared the ability to use an additional seven metabolites, while Cr-K29, Cr-K20, and Cr-K32 shared the ability to use 16 additional metabolites (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Of the four isolates, Cr-K20 had the most unique combination of metabolites utilized (n = 16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Both Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 exhibited the largest amount of overlap in substrate utilization, which may be related to why these isolates had very similar growth patterns (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>1B and 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The growth patterns of Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 were unique when compared to the other isolates, which was mirrored by their metabolic fingerprint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Of the six-substrate guilds, Carbohydrates and the Miscellaneous guilds exerted the greatest influence on separating Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 from Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The four remaining substrate guilds (Amines/Amides, Carboxylic acids, Amino Acids, and Polymers) appeared to help separate Cr-K1W away from the other three isolates (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>PCA of metabolic fingerprinting. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Principal component analysis plot of the four isolates based on their ability to utilize a metabolic substrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Genomic characterization of chromate reducing isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The four draft genomes obtained in this study had lengths between 3.79 and 3.91 Mbp with a GC content of ∼68% (Tables S2 and S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the 16S rRNA genes indicated that all four isolates had identical (1,405 bp) 16S rRNA sequences, and that they are Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(Actinobacteria phylum), specifically members of the Microbacterium oxydans clade (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Gene annotation of the four genomes documented between 3,616 and 3,806 predicted protein coding genes (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Genomes were assessed to be nearly complete with all genomes containing the 35 universal single copy marker genes (Raes et al., 2007) (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the genomes indicated that the four taxonomically closely-related chromium reducing Microbacterium isolates have a surprising amount of inter-strain genomic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>A broad based genome comparison of the four isolates showed that they share a large predicted protein core made up of 2,810 proteins (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In addition to the protein core, isolates Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 shared an additional 602 predicted proteins while isolates Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 shared 854 predicted proteins (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>When the annotated genomes were analyzed by Principal Component Analysis, using annotated Pfam proteins (Table S5), a similar grouping pattern was observed (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Of the 21 Pfam categories, Carbohydrate Transport and Metabolism, Transcription, and Inorganic Ion Transport and Metabolism, General Function, and Function Unknown were the most important factors separating the annotated draft genomes (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Genome analysis also confirmed the presence of certain metabolic genes that connect to the metabolic fingerprinting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>For example, the genome of all four isolates contained genes needed to utilize sucrose (glycosidases, starch and sucrose metabolism KEGG pathway) and all four isolates were capable of doing so. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Further, annotated genes for arabinose (L-arabinose isomerase and L-ribulose 5-phosphate 4-epimerase, pentose and glucuronate interconversions KEGG pathway) and xylose metabolism (xylose isomerase, pentose and glucuronate interconversions KEGG pathway) were only found for Cr-K1W and Cr-K20 and these were the only two isolates capable of utilizing those substrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>PCA of Pfam catagories. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Principal component analysis of 21 Pfam catagories from IMG annotations of the four Microbacterium sp. genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Top five eigenvalues were then plotted as the vectors after analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Bacterial chromate stress has been shown to impact broad metabolic functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>For example, a proteomics study of Arthobacter FB 24 demonstrated that, when the bacterium was exposed to chromate, a large number of proteins involved in metabolism (e.g., carbohydrate, energy production, and amino acid transport and metabolism) had altered expression (Henne et al., 2009b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In S. oneidensis MR-1, chromate stress response caused variation in iron and sulfur transport genes and also DNA repair genes (Brown et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Few genomic differences that related to sulfate transport are evident in the examined Microbacterium genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The faster reducers, K-29 and K-32, did have two additional genes that are related to iron transport (ABC-type Fe3+ transport system, permease component, and siderophore synthetase component). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Thus these may be related to their increased ability to thrive in high chromate conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Genomic annotations related to chromate reduction and resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The genomes of the four isolates examined contained putative chromate reductases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>An automated IMG annotation of the isolate draft genomes failed to identify chromate reductases or resistant genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Consequently, custom searches were performed to further examine the genomes for chromate related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Manual BLASTX searches were performed using the UniprotKB databases for ChrA, ChrR, and YieF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The search with known chromate transporters, ChrA homologues, returned no hits within any of the four isolate assembled genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>While past studies have found that the efflux pump gene, chrA, can provide chromate resistance (e.g., Diaz-Perez et al., 2007; Henne et al., 2009a; Ramirez-Diaz et al., 2008), the lack of this gene could suggest that other efflux pumps may be exporting chromate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The genome of each of the isolates did contain two metal associated efflux pumps (arsentite efflux pump and cation/multidrug efflux pump). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, the physiological link between reduction and resistance could suggest that Cr(VI) reduction is responsible for providing resistance to these isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Curated genome searches were able to identify multiple putative chromate reductases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>BLASTX searches against the ChrR UniprotKB database returned a hit in all four isolate genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The identified genes were homologues (50–51% identity) to a ChrR reductase in Thermus scotoductus (Opperman, Piater &amp; Van Heerden, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>IMG classified these genes as oxidoreductases and part of the Old Yellow Enzyme family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Cr-K32’s protein (microk32_01893, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529442617">2529442617</ext-link>) using IMG’s homolog toolkit, showed a 100% homology to the protein found in Cr-K29 (microk29_00100, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529452261">2529452261</ext-link>) and 89% in Cr-K20 (microk20_02158, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529450446">2529450446</ext-link>) but only 35% percent identity to the protein found in Cr-K1W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Since the sequence homology of the protein found in Cr-K1W was low, additional searches within this genome were conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The genome of Cr-K1W did have a protein identified as an NADH:FMN oxidoreductase from the Old Yellow Enzyme family (cellulok1w_02457, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529446915">2529446915</ext-link>) that shared 100% homology to the chrR-like gene found in Cr-K20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the four closest homologs’ gene neighborhoods within IMG showed high similarity of gene composition near the oxidoreductase despite the varying percent identity (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Further, jackhmmer searches (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/hmmer/search/hmmsearch), of the aligned genes found 51% protein identity, 68% similarity, and with an e-value of 3E–100 to Thermus scotaductus’ chromate reductase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>A similar curated search with YieF (ChrR sequence homologue) was also able to identify putative chromate reductases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The top result from a BLASTX search using the YieF databases identified a predicted flavoprotein in each of the individual isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the four individual isolate genes within IMG’s homology toolkit revealed high degrees of sequence similarity with Cr-K1W (cellulok1w_02457, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529446915">2529446915</ext-link>) and Cr-K20 (microk20_03386, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529451669">2529451669</ext-link>) having 100% homology and Cr-K29 (microk29_00694, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529452855">2529452855</ext-link>) and Cr-K32 (microk32_00074, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://img.jgi.doe.gov/cgi-bin/edu/main.cgi?section=GeneDetail&amp;page=geneDetail&amp;gene_oid=2529440805">2529440805</ext-link>) having 98% homology to one another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In addition, the genes were also homologues (65% for Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 and 69% for Cr-K1W and Cr-K20) to a predicted chromate reductase (ARUE_c41610) in an Arthrobacter sp. (Niewerth et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Gene neighborhoods of the resultant genes did not show as much conservation compared the putative ChrR-like genes, with only small regions around the gene being shared between the fastest reducers (Cr-K32 and Cr-K29) and slower reducers (Cr-K1W and Cr-K20) but no shared genes between all four (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>S5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Automated annotations of the isolate genomes failed to provide any putative chromate reductases, however, custom database searches were more successful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Each genome did contain genes with sequence homology to the chromate reductases, chrR and yieF, of non-model organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The putative chrR-like genes found in the isolates are homologous to a chrR gene (GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AM902709">AM902709</ext-link>) found in T. scotoductus, which has been experimentally shown to reduce chromate (Opperman, Piater &amp; Van Heerden, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The putative yieF genes found in the isolates were homologous to an annotated chromate reductase in Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>RUE61a, a known chromate reducer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Despite being found in all four isolates, the genes did showed sequence variability between the four isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Isolates Cr-K29 and Cr-K32 are the faster reducers and their putative genes share more sequence homology when compared to Cr-K1W and Cr-K20, the slower reducers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees of both the putative ChrR and YieF genes also displayed this variability with slow reducers or fast reducers being more closely related to one another (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>S6 and S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Neither putative gene was found to group with known chromate reducers, however, this may be an artifact from the lack of known chromate specific genes in Microbacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>While the reasons for the variable ability for each isolate to reduce chromate are still not well understood, the differences observed between the isolates may be related to sequence similarity, expression, or genome content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Understanding microdiversity is vital for the systematic understanding of how bacterial strains, and populations, can impact biogeochemical processes (Fuhrman &amp; Campbell, 1998; Jaspers &amp; Overmann, 2004; Johnson et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have documented genomic variation among closely related strains, which some term “ecotypes” (e.g., Hunt et al., 2008; Rocap et al., 2003; Welch et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Depending on the bacterium, inter-strain variation can have an impact on microbial function (Coleman &amp; Chisholm, 2010; Martiny, Coleman &amp; Chisholm, 2006) and at times this connection to function is nonexistent or not as clear (Meyer &amp; Huber, 2014; Simmons et al., 2008; Wilmes et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Though a “core” metabolic and genomic structure was seen among the four isolates, our data suggests that Cr(VI) reduction discrepancies within these isolates could be related to strain-level genetic and metabolic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Further, chromate resistance may be intertwined with the ability of a bacterium to reduce and transport chromate as well as the type of stress response the organism might have. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Fundamentally, the genomic variation between these isolates may point to bacterial adaptation in response to long-term exposure to multiple contaminants (e.g., lead, Cd) including Cr(VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Further analysis of these discrepancies will help define a Cr(VI) reduction mechanism within these isolates, and will lead to a greater understanding of the importance of inter-strain variation in microbial communities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-1</object-id><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Venn diagram of metabolite utilization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Venn diagram (4-way comparison) illustrating similarities between the four Microbacterium spp. metabolite utilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Intersections show the number of shared metabolites between two are more organisms bases on the Biolog data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s001.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-2</object-id><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of the four Microbacterium sp. isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree (bootstrap = 500) of four Microbacterium sp. isolates and representative Micobacterium species using their 16S rRNA genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s002.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information-Tables </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s003.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-4</object-id><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Venn diagram of genomic similarities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Venn diagram (4-way comparison) illustrating similarities between the four Microbacterium spp. genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Intersections show the number of shared proteins between two or more organisms based on reciprocal best BLAST hits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Numbers in parentheses depict the missing overlap sectors due to circular drawing and represent proteins shared between opposite genomes but absent in the other two genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s004.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-5</object-id><label>Figure S4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Gene neighborhoods of the putative chrR genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Gene neighborhoods of the putative chrR genes (red color) from the four Microbacterium sp. isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Genes of the same color are from the same clusters of orthologous groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s005.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-6</object-id><label>Figure S5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Gene neighborhoods of the putative yieF genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Gene neighborhoods of the putative yieF genes (red color) from the four Microbacterium sp. isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Genes of the same color are from the same clusters of orthologous groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s006.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-7"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-7</object-id><label>Figure S6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of putative chrR genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree (bootstrap = 50) of four putative chrR genes from the Microbacterium sp. isolates, closely related homologs, and representative chromate reductase genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s007.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-8"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1395/supp-8</object-id><label>Figure S7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of putative yieF genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree (bootstrap = 50) of four putative yieF genes from the Microbacterium sp. isolates, closely related homologs, and representative chromate reductase genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1395-s008.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><p>We would like to thank Dr. C. Titus Brown, Dr. Ian Dworkin, and Dr. Istvan Albert for consultation on computational methods during the MSU Next Generation Sequencing course. The US Environmental Protection Agency, through its Office of Research and Development, collaborated in the research described herein. Any opinions expressed in this paper are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the agency; therefore, no official endorsement should be inferred. Any mention of trade names or commercial products does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use. This is contribution number 60 of the CMU Institute for Great Lakes Research.</p></ack></SecTag><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The authors declare there are no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></SecTag><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Michael W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Henson conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Jorge W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Santo Domingo conceived and designed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Peter S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Kourtev performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Roderick V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Jensen contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>James A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Dunn performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-6" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Deric R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Learman conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>DNA Deposition</title><fn id="addinfo-1" fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The following information was supplied regarding the deposition of DNA sequences: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This BioProject has been deposited at DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank under accession <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="PRJNA236112">PRJNA236112</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></sec><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Ackerley et al. (2004a)AckerleyDFGonzalezCFKeyhanMBlakeRMatinAMechanism of chromate reduction by the Escherichia coli protein, NfsA, and the role of different chromate reductases in minimizing oxidative stress during chromate reductionEnvironmental Microbiology2004a685186010.1111/j.1462-2920.2004.00639.x15250887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-2"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Ackerley et al. (2004b)AckerleyDFGonzalezCFParkCHBlakeRKeyhanAMatinAChromate-reducing properties of soluble Flavoproteins from Pseudomonas putida and Escherichia coliApplied and Environmental Microbiology2004b7087388210.1128/AEM.70.2.873-882.200414766567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-3"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Bååth (1989)BååthEEffects of heavy metals in soil on microbial processes and populations (a review)Water, Air, and Soil Pollution19894733537910.1007/BF00279331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-4"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Barak et al. (2006)BarakYAckerleyDFDodgeCJBanwariLAlexCFrancisAJMatinAAnalysis of novel soluble chromate and uranyl reductases and generation of an improved enzyme by directed evolutionApplied and Environmental Microbiology2006727074708210.1128/AEM.01334-0617088379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-5"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Bartlett (1991)BartlettRJChromium cycling in soils and water—links, gaps, and methodsEnvironmental Health Perspectives199192172410.1289/ehp.9192171935847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-6"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Beller et al. (2013)BellerHRHanRYKaraozULimHBrodieELGenomic and physiological characterization of the chromate-reducing, aquifer-derived firmicute pelosinus sp. strain HCF1Applied and Environmental Microbiology201379637310.1128/AEM.02496-1223064329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-7"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Brose &amp; James (2010)BroseDAJamesBROxidation-reduction transformations of chromium in aerobic soils and the role of electron-shuttling quinonesEnvironmental Science &amp; Technology2010449438944410.1021/es101859b21105643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-8"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Brown et al. (2012)BrownSDPalumboAVPanikovNArlyawansaTKlingemanDMJohnsonCMLandMLUtturkarSMEpsteinSSDraft genome sequence for microbacterium laevaniformans strain OR221, a bacterium tolerant to metals, nitrate, and low pHJournal of Bacteriology20121943279328010.1128/JB.00474-1222628508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-9"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Brown et al. (2006)BrownSDThompsonMRVerberkmoesNCChoureyKShahMZhouJHettichRLThompsonDKMolecular dynamics of the Shewanella oneidensis response to chromate stressMolecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics200651054107110.1074/mcp.M500394-MCP20016524964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-10"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Cervantes &amp; Ohtake (1988)CervantesCOhtakeHPlasmid-determined resistance to chromate in Pseudomonas aeruginosaFEMS Microbiology Letters19885617317610.1111/j.1574-6968.1988.tb03172.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-11"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Cervantes et al. (1990)CervantesCOhtakeHChuLMisraTKSilverSCloning, nucleotide sequence, and expression of the chromate resistance determinant of Pseudomonas aeruginosa plasmid pUM505Journal of Bacteriology19901722872912152903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-12"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Cheng, Holman &amp; Lin (2012)ChengYHolmanH-YLinZRemediation of chromium and uranium contamination by microbial activityElements2012810711210.2113/gselements.8.2.107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-13"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Cheung &amp; Gu (2007)CheungKHGuJDMechanism of hexavalent chromium detoxification by microorganisms and bioremediation application potential: a reviewInternational Biodeterioration &amp; Biodegradation20075981510.1016/j.ibiod.2006.05.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-14"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Chikhi &amp; Medvedev (2013)ChikhiRMedvedevPInformed and automated k-mer size selection for genome assemblyBioinformatics1201330313710.1093/bioinformatics/btt31023732276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-15"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Chovanec et al. (2012)ChovanecPSparacino-WatkinsCZhangNBasuPStolzJFMicrobial reduction of chromate in the presence of nitrate by three nitrate respiring organismsFrontiers in Microbiology20123Article 41610.3389/Fmicb.2012.00416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-16"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Coleman &amp; Chisholm (2010)ColemanMLChisholmSWEcosystem-specific selection pressures revealed through comparative population genomicsProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2010107186341863910.1073/pnas.100948010720937887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-17"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Curtis et al. (2013)CurtisDSPhillipsARCallisterSJConlanSMcCueLASPOCS: software for predicting and visualizing orthology/paralogy relationships among genomesBioinformatics2013292641264210.1093/bioinformatics/btt45423956303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-18"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Diaz-Perez et al. (2007)Diaz-PerezCCervantesCCampos-GarciaJJulian-SanchezARiveros-RosasHPhylogenetic analysis of the chromate ion transporter (CHR) superfamilyFEBS Journal20072746215622710.1111/j.1742-4658.2007.06141.x17986256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-19"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Field et al. (2013)FieldEGerlachRViamajalaSJenningsLPeytonBApelWHexavalent chromium reduction by Cellulomonas sp. strain ES6: the influence of carbon source, iron minerals, and electron shuttling compoundsBiodegradation20132443745010.1007/s10532-012-9600-723135488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-20"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Focardi, Pepi &amp; Focardi (2013)FocardiSPepiMFocardiSEChamyRMicrobial reduction of hexavalent chromium as a mechanism of detoxification and possible bioremediation applicationsBiodegradation—life of science2013InTechAvailable at http://www.intechopen.com/books/biodegradation-life-of-science/microbial-reduction-of-hexavalent-chromium-as-a-mechanism-of-detoxification-and-possible-bioremediat978-953-51-1154-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-21"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Fuhrman &amp; Campbell (1998)FuhrmanJACampbellLMarine ecology—microbial microdiversityNature199839341041110.1038/30839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-22"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Gonzalez et al. (2005)GonzalezCFAckerleyDFLynchSVMatinAChrR, a soluble quinone reductase of Pseudomonas putida that defends against H2O2Journal of Biological Chemistry2005280225902259510.1074/jbc.M50165420015840577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-23"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Gough et al. (2008)GoughHLDahlALNolanMAGaillardJ-FStahlDAMetal impacts on microbial biomass in the anoxic sediments of a contaminated lakeJournal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences2008113G0201710.1029/2007jg000566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-24"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Gough &amp; Stahl (2011)GoughHLStahlDAMicrobial community structures in anoxic freshwater lake sediment along a metal contamination gradientThe ISME Journal2011554355810.1038/ismej.2010.13220811473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-25"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Harper &amp; Ryan (2001)HarperDRyanPPAST: paleontological statistics software package for education and data analysisPalaeontol Electronica2001419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-26"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>He et al. (2010)HeMLiXGuoLMillerSJRensingCWangGCharacterization and genomic analysis of chromate resistant and reducing Bacillus cereus strain SJ1BMC Microbiology20101022120723231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-27"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Henne et al. (2009a)HenneKLNakatsuCHThompsonDKKonopkaAEHigh-level chromate resistance in Arthrobacter sp strain FB24 requires previously uncharacterized accessory genesBMC Microbiology2009a919910.1186/1471-2180-9-19919758450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-28"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Henne et al. (2009b)HenneKLTurseJENicoraCDLiptonMSTollaksenSLLindbergCBabniggGGiomettiCSNakatsuCHThompsonDKKonopkaAEGlobal proteomic analysis of the chromate response in Arthrobacter sp strain FB24Journal of Proteome Research2009b81704171610.1021/pr800705f19231868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-29"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Hunt et al. (2008)HuntDEDavidLAGeversDPreheimSPAlmEJPolzMFResource partitioning and sympatric differentiation among closely related bacterioplanktonScience20083201081108510.1126/science.115789018497299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-30"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Jaspers &amp; Overmann (2004)JaspersEOvermannJEcological significance of microdiversity: identical 16S rRNA gene sequences can be found in bacteria with highly divergent genomes and ecophysiologiesApplied and Environmental Microbiology2004704831483910.1128/AEM.70.8.4831-4839.200415294821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-31"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Johnson et al. (2006)JohnsonZIZinserERCoeAMcNultyNPWoodwardEMSChisholmSWNiche partitioning among Prochlorococcus ecotypes along ocean-scale environmental gradientsScience20063111737174010.1126/science.111805216556835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-32"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Kourtev, Nakatsu &amp; Konopka (2006)KourtevPSNakatsuCHKonopkaAResponses of the anaerobic bacterial community to addition of organic C in chromium(VI)- and iron(III)-amended microcosmsApplied and Environmental Microbiology20067262863710.1128/AEM.72.1.628-637.200616391100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-33"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Kourtev, Nakatsu &amp; Konopka (2009)KourtevPSNakatsuCHKonopkaAInhibition of nitrate reduction by chromium(VI) in anaerobic soil microcosmsApplied and Environmental Microbiology192009756249625710.1128/AEM.00347-0919684175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-34"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Liu et al. (2012)LiuZMWuYLeiCFLiuPMGaoMYChromate reduction by a chromate-resistant bacterium Microbacterium spWorld Journal of Microbiology &amp; Biotechnology2012281585159210.1007/s11274-011-0962-522805940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-35"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Lohse et al. (2012)LohseMBolgerAMNagelAFernieARLunnJEStittMUsadelBRobiNA: a user-friendly, integrated software solution for RNA-Seq-based transcriptomicsNucleic Acids Research201240W622W62710.1093/nar/gks54022684630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-36"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Lovley et al. (1993)LovleyDRGiovannoniSJWhiteDCChampineJEPhillipsEJGorbyYAGoodwinSGeobacter metallireducens gen. nov. sp. nov., a microorganism capable of coupling the complete oxidation of organic compounds to the reduction of iron and other metalsArchives of Microbiology199315933634410.1007/BF002909168387263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-37"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Markowitz et al. (2012)MarkowitzVMChenIMAPalaniappanKChuKSzetoEGrechkinYRatnerAJacobBHuangJHWilliamsPHuntemannMAndersonIMavromatisKIvanovaNNKyrpidesNCIMG: the integrated microbial genomes database and comparative analysis systemNucleic Acids Research201240D115D12210.1093/nar/gkr104422194640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-38"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Martiny, Coleman &amp; Chisholm (2006)MartinyACColemanMLChisholmSWPhosphate acquisition genes in Prochlorococcus ecotypes: evidence for genome-wide adaptationProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2006103125521255710.1073/pnas.060130110316895994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-39"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Meyer &amp; Huber (2014)MeyerJLHuberJAStrain-level genomic variation in natural populations of Lebetimonas from an erupting deep-sea volcanoThe ISME Journal2014886788010.1038/ismej.2013.20624257443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-40"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Nakatsu et al. (2005)NakatsuCHCarmosiniNBaldwinBBeasleyFKourtevPKonopkaASoil microbial community responses to additions of organic carbon substrates and heavy metals (Pb and Cr)Applied and Environmental Microbiology2005717679768910.1128/AEM.71.12.7679-7689.200516332740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-41"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Niewerth et al. (2012)NiewerthHSchuldesJParschatKKieferPVorholtJADanielRFetznerSComplete genome sequence and metabolic potential of the quinaldine-degrading bacterium Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Rue61aBMC Genomics201213Article 53410.1186/1471-2164-13-534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-42"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Okrent &amp; Xing (1993)OkrentDXingLMFuture risk from a hypothesized rcra site disposing of carcinogenic metals should a loss of societal memory occurJournal of Hazardous Materials19933436338410.1016/0304-3894(93)85099-Z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-43"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Opperman, Piater &amp; Van Heerden (2008)OppermanDJPiaterLAVan HeerdenEA novel chromate reductase from Thermus scotoductus SA-01 related to old yellow enzymeJournal of Bacteriology20081903076308210.1128/JB.01766-0718263719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-44"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Oze, Bird &amp; Fendorf (2007)OzeCBirdDKFendorfSGenesis of hexavalent chromium from natural sources in soil and groundwaterProceedings of the National Academy of Science of the United States of America20071046544654910.1073/pnas.0701085104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-45"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Oze et al. (2004)OzeCFendorfSBirdDKColemanRGChromium geochemistry in serpintinized ultramafic rocks and serpintine soils from the Franciscan complex of CaliforniaAmerican Journal of Science20043046710110.2475/ajs.304.1.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-46"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Park et al. (2000)ParkCHKeyhanMWielingaBFendorfSMatinAPurification to homogeneity and characterization of a novel Pseudomonas putida chromate reductaseApplied and Environmental Microbiology2000661788179510.1128/AEM.66.5.1788-1795.200010788340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-47"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Raes et al. (2007)RaesJKorbelJOLercherMJVon MeringCBorkPPrediction of effective genome size in metagenomic samplesGenome Biology20078R1010.1186/Gb-2007-8-1-R1017224063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-48"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Ramirez-Diaz et al. (2008)Ramirez-DiazMIDiaz-PerezCVargasERiveros-RosasHCampos-GarciaJCervantesCMechanisms of bacterial resistance to chromium compoundsBiometals20082132133210.1007/s10534-007-9121-817934697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-49"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Riley, Zachara &amp; Wobber (1992)RileyRGZacharaJMWobberFJChemical contaminants on DOE lands and selection of contaminants mixtures for subsurface science research1992Washington, D.C.Department of Energy(Report DOE/ER-0547T) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-50"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Rocap et al. (2003)RocapGLarimerFWLamerdinJMalfattiSChainPAhlgrenNAArellanoAColemanMHauserLHessWRJohnsonZILandMLindellDPostAFRegalaWShahMShawSLSteglichCSullivanMBTingCSTolonenAWebbEAZinserERChisholmSWGenome divergence in two Prochlorococcus ecotypes reflects oceanic niche differentiationNature20034241042104710.1038/nature0194712917642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-51"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Said &amp; Lewis (1991)SaidWALewisDLQuantitative assessment of the effects of metals on microbial degradation of organic chemicalsApplied and Environmental Microbiology199157149815031854203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-52"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Sheik et al. (2012)SheikCSMitchellTWRizviFZRehmanYFaisalMHasnainSMcInerneyMJKrumholzLRExposure of soil microbial communities to chromium and arsenic alters their diversity and structurePLoS ONE20127e139510.1371/journal.pone.0040059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-53"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Silver &amp; Phung (2005)SilverSPhungLTA bacterial view of the periodic table: genes and proteins for toxic inorganic ionsJournal of Industrial Microbiology &amp; Biotechnology20053258760510.1007/s10295-005-0019-616133099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-54"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Simmons et al. (2008)SimmonsSLDibartoloGDenefVJGoltsmanDSThelenMPBanfieldJFPopulation genomic analysis of strain variation in Leptospirillum group II bacteria involved in acid mine drainage formationPLoS Biology20086e139510.1371/journal.pbio.0060177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-55"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Simpson et al. (2009)SimpsonJTWongKJackmanSDScheinJEJonesSJMBirolİABySS: a parallel assembler for short read sequence dataGenome Research2009191117112310.1101/gr.089532.10819251739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-56"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Soni et al. (2014)SoniSKSinghRAwasthiAKalraAA Cr(VI)-reducing Microbacterium sp. strain SUCR140 enhances growth and yield of Zea mays in Cr(VI) amended soil through reduced chromium toxicity and improves colonization of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungiEnvironmental Science and Pollution Research2014211971197910.1007/s11356-013-2098-724014225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-57"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Suzuki et al. (1992)SuzukiTMiyataNHoritsuHKawaiKTakamizawaKTaiYOkazakiMNad(P)H-dependent chromium(Vi) reductase of Pseudomonas ambigua G-1—a Cr(V) intermediate is formed during the reduction of Cr(Vi) to Cr(Iii)Journal of Bacteriology1992174534053451322884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-58"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Tamura et al. (2007)TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarSMEGA4: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0Molecular Biology and Evolution2007241596159910.1093/molbev/msm09217488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-59"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Tritt et al. (2012)TrittAEisenJAFacciottiMTDarlingAEAn integrated pipeline for de novo assembly of microbial genomesPLoS ONE20127e139510.1371/journal.pone.0042304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-60"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Urone (1955)UronePFStability of colorimetric reagent for chromium, S-diphenylcarbazide, in various solventsAnalytical Chemistry1955271354135510.1021/ac60104a048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-61"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Viti et al. (2013)VitiCMarchiEDecorosiFGiovannettiLMolecular mechanisms of Cr(VI) resistance in bacteria and fungiFEMS Microbiology Reviews20133863365910.1111/1574-6976.1205124188101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-62"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Welch et al. (2002)WelchRABurlandVPlunkettGRedfordPRoeschPRaskoDBucklesELLiouSRBoutinAHackettJStroudDMayhewGFRoseDJZhouSSchwartzDCPernaNTMobleyHLTDonnenbergMSBlattnerFRExtensive mosaic structure revealed by the complete genome sequence of uropathogenic Escherichia coliProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200299170201702410.1073/pnas.25252979912471157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-63"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Wilmes et al. (2010)WilmesPBowenBPThomasBCMuellerRSDenefVJVerBerkmoesNCHettichRLNorthenTRBanfieldJFMetabolome-proteome differentiation coupled to microbial divergencemBio520101e00246-1010.1128/mBio.00246-10 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-64"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Zak et al. (1994)ZakJCWilligMRMoorheadDLWildmanHGFunctional diversity of microbial communities: a quantitative approachSoil Biology and Biochemistry1994261101110810.1016/0038-0717(94)90131-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-65"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Zerbino &amp; Birney (2008)ZerbinoDRBirneyEVelvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphsGenome Research20081882182910.1101/gr.074492.10718349386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-66"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Zhu et al. (2008)ZhuWJChaiLYMaZMWangYYMaoHJZhaoKAnaerobic reduction of hexavalent chromium by bacterial cells of Achromobacter sp. strain Ch1Microbiological Research200816361662310.1016/j.micres.2006.09.00819216102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
