<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Hum Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Hum Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Hum. Neurosci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Human Neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1662-5161</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4128218</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2014.00615</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Verbal creativity in autism: comprehension and generation of metaphoric language in high-functioning autism spectrum disorder and typical development </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kasirer</surname><given-names>Anat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/174746"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mashal</surname><given-names>Nira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/41043"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Education Bar-Ilan University</institution><country>Ramat-Gan, Israel</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Gonda Multidisciplinary Brain Research Center, Bar-Ilan University</institution><country>Ramat-Gan, Israel</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Zbigniew R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Struzik, The University of Tokyo, Japan </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Dahlia Zaidel, University of California, Los Angeles, USA; Michael Francis Fitzgerald, Trinity College Dublin, Ireland </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="fn002">*Correspondence: <italic>Nira Mashal, School of Education Bar-Ilan University, Ramat-Gan 52900, Israel e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">nmashal2@gmail.com</email></italic></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Human Neuroscience. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>615</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Kasirer and Mashal.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p> This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Studies on creativity in participants with autism generally show impoverished performance as well as deficient comprehension of metaphoric language. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>However, very little is known about the ability to generate metaphors in this population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The present study examines verbal creativity in adults with autism-spectrum disorder (ASD) through tasks that rely on novel metaphoric language. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Seventeen adults with ASD (mean age = 21.06) and 17 typically developing peers (mean age = 22.71) participated in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>A multiple-choice questionnaire consisting of conventional and novel metaphors was used to test comprehension, and a sentence completion questionnaire was used to test generation of creative language. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results show similar performance in comprehension of conventional and novel metaphors in both groups, whereas adults with ASD generated more creative metaphors relative to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Scores on tests of vocabulary and naming contributed to the prediction of conventional metaphor comprehension, while scores on tests of mental flexibility contributed to the prediction of novel metaphor comprehension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In addition, scores on a test of non-verbal intelligence contributed to the prediction of metaphor generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The study points to unique verbal creativity in ASD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>autism</kwd><kwd>novel metaphors</kwd><kwd>executive functioning</kwd><kwd>metaphor generation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="58"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>People with autistic-spectrum disorder (ASD) experience difficulties in comprehension of figurative language, and tend to give literal interpretation to ambiguous syntactic expressions, to phrases that convey irony, humor, or sarcasm, to idioms, or to metaphors (Happé, 1993, 1995; Kerbel and Grunwell, 1998; Rapin and Dunn, 2003; Adachi et al., 2004; Rundblad and Annaz, 2010; Mashal and Kasirer, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Despite extensive research on comprehension of metaphoric language in autism, very little is known about how people with ASD generate metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In fact, earlier research on creativity in ASD has focused primarily on non-verbal rather than on verbal abilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Findings have mostly documented deficient performance in ASD, especially when using tasks that are imagination-oriented (e.g., Frith, 1972; Lewis and Boucher, 1991; Craig and Baron-Cohen, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The present study investigates comprehension and generation of novel metaphors in ASD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In a recent study we found that children with ASD (aged 12–15) differ from typically developing (TD) children in comprehension of conventional metaphors but not in comprehension of novel metaphors (Mashal and Kasirer, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In this study we used a multiple-choice task that included conventional metaphors (e.g., sharp tongue), novel metaphors (e.g., joy bits), and unrelated word-pairs (e.g., laundry rabbit). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Unlike conventional metaphors, which are coded in the mental lexicon, novel metaphors require the computation of on-line interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It might be the case that the ability to create novel semantic connections between apparently unrelated concepts is not impaired in ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Consistent with our results, Hermann et al. (2013) found that processing of novel metaphors in 20 adults with Asperger syndrome (aged 22–68) was similar to performance of age-matched TD individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The experiment included a semantic judgment task, in which participants were asked to make rapid decisions about the literal truth of a given sentence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The task consisted of four types of sentences: literally true high-typical sentences (e.g., Some lawyers are juvenile magistrates); literally true low-typical sentences (e.g., Some lawyers are tax advisors); metaphors (e.g., Some lawyers are scale rulers); and scrambled metaphors (e.g., Some lawyers are days off spring). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Responses to metaphors were significantly slower than were responses to the other types of expressions, but this pattern of results characterized both groups, with no impairment in performance seen in the ASD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Thus, there is evidence that people with ASD demonstrate no difficulties with figurative language, contrary to previous arguments in the literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Note that some earlier work has suggested that individuals with ASD do not comprehend figurative language due to difficulties in executive functions (Russell, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>According to this account, ASD impairs planning, set-shifting (flexibility), working memory, and inhibition (Ozonoff and Strayer, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that executive dysfunction contributes to the typical communication and social impairments in ASD (Landa and Goldberg, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, evidence for executive dysfunction in ASD remains equivocal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>For example, Robinson et al. (2009) found differences in inhibition, planning, and self-monitoring between individuals with ASD and TD participants, but no group differences in cognitive flexibility and verbal fluency were noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Other studies have recorded difficulties in linguistic and categorical (semantic) fluency in ASD (Rumsey and Hamburger, 1988). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Executive dysfunction has a considerable adverse impact on the ability to plan well formed novel linguistic constructs, and to shift from one meaning of a word or phrase to another, especially in the case of metaphoric language (Landa and Goldberg, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The ability to combine the two words that form a metaphor to a meaningful expression might thus be more affected by deficits in executive functions than the ability to interpret literal expressions (Amanzio et al., 2008). Mashal and Kasirer () have indeed demonstrated that executive dysfunction contributed to comprehension of novel metaphors among children with ASD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Executive functions are important not only for comprehension but also for the generation of metaphors (Dietrich, 2004; Chiappe and Chiappe, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To generate a metaphor that contains a topic and a vehicle, a speaker must first select the property that will be attributed to the topic, and then scan semantic knowledge for suitable vehicles that exemplify the abstract, higher-order attributive category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This process requires that one maintains access to the category while inhibiting features of both topic and possible vehicles that are irrelevant to the higher-order category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>That is, highly accessible but irrelevant semantic knowledge (e.g., adjectival descriptions of the topic) as well as many accessible but trite possibilities, such as idioms, clichés, and conventional metaphors must all be inhibited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Finally, the speaker must evaluate whether the metaphor conveys the desired meaning and emotional tone, and then revise it if necessary (Silvia and Beaty, 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>There is evidence that the generation of conventional and novel metaphors relies on different cognitive abilities (Bowdle and Gentner, 2005; Mashal, 2013). Silvia and Beaty (2013) suggested that generation of conventional metaphors is influenced by general knowledge or vocabulary, whereas generation of novel metaphors is affected by fluid intelligence and executive processes. Silvia and Beaty (2012) gave their participants two different prompts and instructed them to describe past emotional experiences through a metaphor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The first prompt asked people to “think of the most boring high-school or college class that you have ever had. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>What was it like to sit through?” For the next prompt, participants were asked to “think about the most disgusting thing you ever ate or drank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>What was it like to eat or drink it?” Six measures of inductive reasoning, primarily non-verbal and visuo-spatial, were used to assess fluid intelligence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Results showed that fluid intelligence predicted the creative quality of novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This suggests that people with high non-verbal intelligence can produce more creative metaphors than do people with lower intelligence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Within the ASD literature, creativity has been measured primarily by non-verbal tasks that involved the production of spontaneous sequences of colors, tones, or drawings (Frith, 1972; Lewis and Boucher, 1991; Liu et al., 2011) or by verbal fluency tasks (Boucher, 1988). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>No extensive investigation of generation of novel verbal concepts has been conducted. Craig and Baron-Cohen (1999) examined creative thinking in children with ASD by using the Torrance Creativity Test (Torrance, 1974). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Their participants could generate novel uses to an object (e.g., “what else can a pencil be?”), but they generated fewer such novel uses overall compared to TD children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Moreover, their ideas tended to be quite concrete rather than imaginary. Liu et al. (2011) emphasize that imagination is not necessarily important for successful performance on tasks that involve creativity and originality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>They used an exercise in divergent thinking which included 12 incomplete figures, and asked their participants to complete the figures in an original way as well as to title them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The completed drawings were assessed on domains of fluency, openness, flexibility, originality, and elaboration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>According to Liu et al., children with Asperger’s syndrome demonstrated better elaboration and originality than did age-matched TD peers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The main goal of the current study is to examine metaphor comprehension and generation in adults with high-functioning ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Generation of novel and original metaphors is assumed to measure verbal creativity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In addition, we examine executive functions and analyze the contribution of these functions to performance on the metaphor tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that adults with ASD will show difficulty in comprehension of conventional metaphors but not in comprehension of novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We further expect participants with ASD to be able to generate novel metaphors but to a lesser extent than TD participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Finally, we assume that executive functions will contribute to metaphor comprehension and generation in both the ASD and the TD groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>PARTICIPANTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Thirty-four participants took part in the study, 17 adults with high functioning ASD and 17 age-matched typically developing adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The ASD group consisted of 14 men and 3 women, ranging in age from 18 to 27 (mean age = 21.06, SD = 3.44), and the TD group consisted of eight men and nine women, ranging in age from 18 to 25 (mean age = 22.71, SD = 2.02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All participants were native Hebrew speakers who completed at least 12 years of formal education, without learning disabilities or attention problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The ASD group was recruited through classes integrated within regular high schools and through community services for persons with ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Diagnosis was done by a psychiatrist, in line with the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV (American Psychiatric Association, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Participants also completed the autism-spectrum quotient (AQ) questionnaire (Baron-Cohen et al., 2001), scoring above 26 on this measure (M = 29.17, SD = 2.03), as clinically accepted in Israel (Golan et al., 2009; Gold et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The TD group included 17 volunteers that were recruited from two different regular high schools and one college from central Israel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To be included in the study all participants had to score within the normal age-appropriate range on the screening tests described below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>If a participant scored outside this range he or she did not continue with the experimental tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>All participants signed an informed consent form prior to the research session. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Screening tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All participants underwent screening tests that included the test of non-verbal intelligence (TONI-3; Brown et al., 1997), a Hebrew naming test (Kavé, 2005a), and the vocabulary sub-test from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (Wechsler, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>As can be seen in Table 1, the groups did not differ in TONI or naming, but the ASD group performed less well on the vocabulary measure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Mean correct responses (and SD) on screening tests, by group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>ASD (N = 17) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>TD (N = 17) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>t </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>TONI-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>38.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>4.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>40.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>1.89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>1.652 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Hebrew naming </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>46.47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>1.73 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>46.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>1.82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>0.385 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Vocabulary </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>48.18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>6.46 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>55.82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>3.34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>4.334** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>**p &lt; 0.001.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Note: TONI-3, Brown et al. (1997), Hebrew naming test, Kavé (2005a), Vocabulary, Wechsler (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Metaphor comprehension </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We used the questionnaire developed by Mashal and Kasirer (2011) to test comprehension of conventional metaphors (e.g., sharp tongue) and novel metaphors (e.g., pure hand). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>For each metaphoric expression, four alternative responses were offered: a correct metaphoric interpretation, a literal interpretation, an unrelated interpretation, and a choice saying “this expression is meaningless.” Participants were instructed to choose the one answer they thought was the best of the four alternatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The questionnaire consisted of 20 items and scores were the sum of all correct answers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Metaphor generation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>To examine generation of metaphors we constructed a questionnaire that contained 10 concepts relating to common emotions (e.g., feeling sad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Participants were asked to create and write down a new way of expressing the meaning of the concept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Instructions emphasized originality so as to encourage participants to create a new expression rather than simply paraphrase the one presented in the questionnaire. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Thus, participants were asked “to create and write down a new expression, which is more comprehensible within your peer group than outside it.” We selected the concepts from the stimuli used by Levorato and Cacciari (2002) in their study of linguistic creativity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A preliminary test was conducted with 20 Hebrew speaking adults (age range 18–25) who were presented with concepts and asked to generate new expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Eight concepts were presented in the form of a metaphor (e.g., love is____) and eight concepts were presented in the form of a simile (e.g., feeling worthless is like____). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The aim of this procedure was to adjust the test to Hebrew. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Three metaphors and three similes did not produce metaphoric responses and were thus excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The final questionnaire included five metaphors and five similes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Two judges independently coded the obtained responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>They were asked to decide whether each expression was literal or figurative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A novel metaphoric response (e.g., feeling worthless is like a mirror smashed to pieces) received three points, a conventional metaphor or idiom (e.g., feeling embarrassed is like having a red face) received two points, and literal responses or paraphrases (e.g., feeling successful is like a victory) received 1 point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Unrelated expressions received no points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The maximum score was 15 for metaphors and 15 for similes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Scores were converted to percentages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Creativity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Creative ability was measured by the percent of responses that received three points on the generation test out of the 10 items. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Executive functions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Executive functions were assessed by the Ambiguous Word Meaning Generation Test (Mashal and Kasirer, 2011), verbal fluency tests (Kavé, 2005b), and the Trail Making Test (Reitan and Davison, 1974). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Ambiguous Word Meaning Generation Test. This test investigates the ability to activate different meanings of ambiguous words and then shift between them (Mashal and Kasirer, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Participants were presented with a list of 20 short unbiased sentences that ended with ambiguous words (e.g., Look at this bank). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>They were instructed to say aloud all meanings of the final word. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>For each participant, we counted the number of correct answers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Phonemic fluency. Following Kavé (2005b), phonemic fluency was assessed by obtaining the number of words generated in 1 min for the letters bet (b), gimel (g), and shin (sh). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We used a sum score of all words produced on the three letters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Semantic fluency. Following Kavé (2005b), semantic fluency was assessed by obtaining the number of words generated in 1 min for each of the following three semantic categories: animals, fruits and vegetables, and vehicles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>We used a sum score of all words produced on the three categories. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The Trail Making test. This test consists of two parts, A and B, requiring participants to connect a series of digits placed in random order on a sheet of paper in ascending order (TMT A), and to connect a series of numbers and letters in ascending order while alternating between numbers and letters (TMT B) (Reitan and Davison, 1974). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Scores were based on time to complete each task. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>PROCEDURE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Participants were tested individually in schools or in their homes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Screening tests were administered on a separate initial session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>On a second session, half of the participants were tested on the executive functioning tasks and then on the metaphor comprehension and generation tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The rest of the participants were tested in the reverse order. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>METAPHOR COMPREHENSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>To examine performance on the comprehension questionnaire, a 2 × 2 repeated measures ANOVA was conducted, with group (ASD, TD) as the between-subject variable and type of metaphor expression (conventional, novel) as the within-subject variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>No main effect of group was found, F(1,32) = 0.979, ns, η2 = 0.030 (see Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The main effect of metaphor expression was significant, F(1,32) = 5.725, p &lt; 0.05, η2 = 0.152, with better performance on conventional metaphors (M = 93.53%, SD = 11.25) relative to novel metaphors (M = 84.12%, SD = 20.91). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>There was no significant interaction between group and type of expression, F(1,32) = 1.811, ns, η2 (see Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Mean correct responses (and SD) on the comprehension questionnaire, by type of metaphor expression and group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>TD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>ASD </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Conventional </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>88.82% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>14.09 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>98.24% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>3.93 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Novel </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>84.71% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>18.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>83.53% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>23.70 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Percent of correct responses on the metaphor comprehension questionnaire, by group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00615-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>EFFECTS OF VOCABULARY ON COMPREHENSION TEST SCORES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Since vocabulary scores were significantly lower in the ASD group than in the TD group, we examined the effects of vocabulary knowledge on performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Vocabulary scores were significantly and positively correlated with comprehension of conventional metaphors, r(32) = 0.587, p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>There was no significant correlation between vocabulary scores and comprehension of novel metaphors, or between vocabulary scores and generation of either simile or metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Because vocabulary scores were found to be significantly correlated only with comprehension of conventional metaphors, we used vocabulary as a covariate in a further analysis of group effects on this measure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>When vocabulary was held constant, the effect of group remained non-significant, F(1,31) = 0.35, p = 0.56, η2 = 0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>METAPHOR GENERATION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>To examine performance on the generation questionnaire, a 2 × 2 repeated measures ANOVA was conducted, with group (ASD, TD) as the between-subject factor and linguistic constraint (metaphor, simile) as the within-subject variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>No main effect of group was found, F(1,32) = 3.633, ns, η2 = 0.102 (see Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The main effect of linguistic constraint was significant, F(1,32) = 30.460, p &lt; 0.001, η2 = 0.488, with worse performance on metaphors (M = 38.43%, SD = 28.00) than on similes (M = 61.96%, SD = 25.08). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>There was also a significant interaction between group and, F(1,32) = 5.288, p &lt; 0.05, η2= 0.142. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>A post hoc analysis revealed that the source of the interaction was in greater metaphor generation in the ASD relative to the TD group (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>No significant group difference was found for simile generation (p = 0.59) (see Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Mean correct responses (and SD) on the generation questionnaire, by stimuli and group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>ASD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>TD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Metaphor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>50.59% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>31.89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>26.27% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>16.91 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Simile </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>64.31% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>27.58 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>59.61% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>22.91 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Percent of correct responses on the generation questionnaire. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00615-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>CREATIVITY </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A t-test for independent samples revealed a significantly greater percent of original responses (receiving a score of 3) within the ASD group (M = 37.06%, SD = 31.38) than within the TD group (M = 19.41%, SD = 11.97), t(32) = -2.166, p &lt; 0.05 (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Percent of original responses on the generation questionnaire, by group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00615-g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Next we compared group performance on the five measures of executive functions with independent-samples t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>These analyses revealed significant group differences on all measures, with worse performance in the ASD group (see Table 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Mean correct responses (and SD) on measures of executive functions, by group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>ASD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>TD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Mean </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>SD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>t </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>AMGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>16.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>4.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>19.47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>0.80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>2.588* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Phonemic fluency </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>28.47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>11.11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>39.47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>9.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>3.162** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Semantic fluency </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>44.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>12.59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>57.53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>8.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>3.429** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>TMT-A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>43.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>18.48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>30.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>9.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>-2.771** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>TMT-B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>76.94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>30.96 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>59.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>16.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>-2.122* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Note: AMGT Ambiguous Words Meaning Generation Test; TMT Trail Making. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>PREDICTION OF METAPHOR SCORES BY BACKGROUND TEST SCORES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>To examine which test predicts comprehension and generation of metaphors, we used a set of four hierarchical and stepwise regression analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Predictors included scores on the screening tests (TONI, naming, and vocabulary) as well as scores on the tests of executive functions (AMGT, fluency, and TMT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>For the comprehension test, we conducted one analysis with conventional metaphors as the predicted variable and one analysis with novel metaphors as the predicted variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Similarly, for the generation task we conducted one analysis for metaphors and one analysis for similes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In each regression we first entered the group variable (ASD, TD), and then we entered scores on the three screening tests and the five measures of executive functioning in a stepwise manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Results of these regression analyses are presented in Table 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The order of the variables presents the order of significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>As can be seen in the table, performance on both the screening tests and the tests of executive functions explained a significant share of the variance across study groups in all four analyses but each dependent variable was predicted by different scores. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Summary of regression analyses predicting comprehension and generation by screening tests and measures of executive functions across groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Predictor variable </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>B </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>SE B </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>β </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>R2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>ΔR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>t </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Comprehension </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Conventional metaphors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>-2.98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>3.84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>-0.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>0.18* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>0.18* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>-0.77 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Vocabulary </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>0.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>0.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>0.44 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>0.35*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>0.17** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>2.51* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Naming </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>1.90 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>0.90 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>0.30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>0.43*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>0.08* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>2.11* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Novel metaphors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>8.39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>6.98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>0.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>0.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>0.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>1.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>TMT-B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>-0.40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>0.14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>-0.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>0.22* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>22.0** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>-2.94** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Generation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Metaphor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>30.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>8.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>0.54 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>0.19** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>0.19** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>3.52*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>TONI-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>3.12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>1.31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>0.37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>0.32** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>0.13* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>2.38* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Simile </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>12.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>7.77 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>1.60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>TONI-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>4.23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>1.19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>0.56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>0.29** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>0.28*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>3.54*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Comprehension of conventional metaphors was best predicted by vocabulary and picture naming, F(3,30) = 7.71, p &lt; 0.001, which accounted for 43.5% of the variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Comprehension of novel metaphors was best predicted by TMT-B, F(2,31) = 4.34, p &lt; 0.05, which accounted for 21.9% of the variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Generation of metaphors was best predicted by TONI-3, F(2,31) = 7.25, p &lt; 0.01, which accounted for 31.9% of the variance, and so was the generation of simile, F(2,31) = 6.46, p &lt; 0.01, in which the TONI-3 score accounted for 29.4% of the variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Group differences predicted metaphor generation with a positive beta coefficient, indicating that participants with ASD had higher scores on this test than did TD participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The present study examined metaphor processing in adults with ASD, differentiating between conventional and novel metaphors on tests of comprehension and generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Our results show that adults with ASD demonstrate no difficulties in comprehension of conventional and novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, adults with ASD outperformed age-matched TD peers in metaphor generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>An inspection of the type of metaphors generated indicated that the ASD group produced more original and creative metaphors than did the TD group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Whereas previous studies highlighted difficulties with metaphoric language comprehension in ASD (e.g., Happé, 1993, 1995; Ozonoff and Miller, 1996; Rundblad and Annaz, 2010; Kaland et al., 2011; Mashal and Kasirer, 2011), the current research shows similar comprehension of metaphors among ASD and age-matched TD peers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>One of the differences between our study and earlier studies might be that we examined adults, unlike previous studies that focused primarily on children and adolescents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the accumulated verbal knowledge that comes with age leads to greater familiarity with conventional metaphors within the ASD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Indeed, previous studies have emphasized the contribution of vocabulary to the comprehension of metaphors (Evans and Gamble, 1988; Nippold, 1998; Chiappe and Chiappe, 2007; Silvia and Beaty, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this observation, we found that higher vocabulary scores were correlated with better comprehension of conventional metaphors (but not with comprehension of novel metaphors). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The fact that we found equivalent comprehension across groups might also be related to the task that we used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>It is possible that presenting metaphors in a multiple-choice questionnaire facilitated comprehension and was easier than were previously used tasks, such as asking comprehension questions about metaphoric stories (Rundblad and Annaz, 2010), requiring sentence completion (Norbury, 2005), or having participants perform a semantic judgment task (Hermann et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>As expected, and in line with previous studies (Mashal and Kasirer, 2011; Melogno et al., 2012; Hermann et al., 2013), no difference was found between participants with ASD and TD age-matched peers in comprehension of novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Novel metaphor interpretation is not coded in the mental lexicon and hence is not dependent on previous knowledge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Indeed, unlike the correlation between vocabulary and comprehension of conventional metaphors, no association was found between vocabulary and comprehension of novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>The ability to understand novel semantic connections between seemingly unrelated concepts appears to be intact in ASD, probably because it does not rely on activation of lexicalized expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this finding, Melogno et al. (2012) emphasized that individuals with ASD can explain novel metaphoric phrases in unique ways that rely on phonological or semantic association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Thus, comprehension of novel metaphor is intact in ASD because it relies on good associative abilities rather than on lexicalized verbal knowledge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Another finding of the current study is that contrary to our hypothesis, participants with ASD generated more metaphors than did age-matched peers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>We were specifically interested in testing whether adults with ASD relied on previous knowledge, and were thus using familiar metaphors or idioms, or alternatively, whether they generated their own novel and original metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>We found that adults with ASD demonstrated greater verbal creativity than did TD individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Examples of creative sentence completions included phrases such as “Feeling successful is like seeing the view from the mountaintop” and “Feeling worthless is like offering a salad to South Americans.” These examples contrasted with more conventional figurative expressions provided by TD adults, such as “Feeling sad is to get the blues.” Our results suggest that adults with ASD can create unique verbal associations that are not restricted to previous knowledge, thus pointing to unique verbal creativity in ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that one in ten people with autism shows some savant skills in such categories as music, art, calendar calculations, or mathematics (Treffert, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Yet, most studies have indicated impoverished creativity in autism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>For example, in standardized tests such as the Torrance Creativity Test (Torrance, 1974), people with ASD demonstrate difficulties in cognitive flexibility and imaginative fluency, as well as lack of imagination and originality compared to TD participants (Craig and Baron-Cohen, 1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Why, then, do adults with ASD demonstrate greater creativity in metaphor generation when previous studies found that they were lacking in imagination? Baron-Cohen et al. (2009) suggest that the hypersensitivity that characterizes autism gives rise to excellent attention to details. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>With respect to verbal creativity, this attention to details is associated with weak central coherence, leading to greater appreciation of local features over global ones. Lyons and Fitzgerald (2005) emphasized that in contrast to their social impairments individuals with Asperger syndrome are gifted with creativity and originality, excellent memory, strong focus of attention and specific cognitive styles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>The unique verbal associations generated by the ASD group in the current study could thus reflect memory for details and weak central coherence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Another reason why adults with ASD generated more original metaphors might relate to difficulty in theory of mind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Mind-blindness makes one focus on one’s own thoughts, ignoring the addressee (Happé and Vital, 2009), possibly leading to production of expressions that are less conventional (Liu et al., 2011). Kanner (1946) was the first to note that the unique phrases produced by the children he studied could be interpreted as metaphoric language. Asperger (1941) also identified certain expressions in the speech of his patients that resembled the novel linguistic forms produced by young TD children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Asperger proposed that characteristics such as concrete intelligence and disregard of social conventions might be prerequisites for certain forms of new thinking and creativity (Gillberg, 2002). Fitzgerald (2004) also noted that individuals with Asperger syndrome have remarkable capacities for persistence and observation, high levels of energy and motivation, and abilities to focus intensely on a single topic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>It appears that some individuals with autism and Asperger syndrome are highly creative, imaginative and original and even their humor can range from word-play and sound associations to precisely formulated, truly witty comments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>According to Lyons and Fitzgerald (2004) some individuals with autism and Asperger syndrome also seem to master the cognitive processing of humor, i.e., incongruity and its resolution and switching of meanings as portrayed by the production of relatively sophisticated puns and word games. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>In our final analysis we sought to identify the extent to which executive functions as well as verbal and non-verbal skills contribute to the prediction of metaphor comprehension and generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>We found that while verbal abilities, i.e., vocabulary and picture naming, contribute to the comprehension of conventional metaphors, this is not the case with regard to novel metaphors, in line with previous studies (e.g., Nippold, 1998; Chiappe and Chiappe, 2007; Silvia and Beaty, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, executive functions were shown to predict novel metaphor comprehension, as has been previously reported (Pennington and Ozonoff, 1996; Amanzio et al., 2008; Mashal and Kasirer, 2011; Mashal, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>More specifically, the TMT-B, which demands mental flexibility, contributed to the prediction of novel metaphor comprehension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>We believe that comprehension of novel metaphors relies on flexibility because it is based on a shift between the literal and the metaphoric meanings of the words that appear in the new expression. Champagne-Lavau and Stip (2010) also found this correlation between the TMT-B and metaphor comprehension in schizophrenic and TD adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Finally, metaphor generation was predicted by non-verbal cognitive ability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Indeed, Silvia and Beaty (2012) have also emphasized the contribution of fluid intelligence to the generation of creative metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>It is possible that generation of metaphors, specifically novel ones, relies on the ability to come up with new solutions, assessed by tests of fluid intelligence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>We note that a similar connection was documented in our study between non-verbal intelligence and simile generation, although no group differences in simile generation were found. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Some limitations of the study should be taken into account. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Our measures of executive functions were rather limited and may need to be expanded to include the assessment of working memory and inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown that people with ASD may present difficulties in tasks that require response inhibition (e.g., Hughes and Russell, 1993; Hughes, 1996; Russell, 1997; Minshew et al., 1999; Hill, 2004; Robinson et al., 2009) or when they are required to shift from one response set to another (Ozonoff and Strayer, 1997; Ozonoff et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>It is possible that low response inhibition led to generation of unique verbal expressions by our ASD participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Future studies will have to examine whether inhibition is associated with metaphor generation in ASD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>In sum, our findings indicate that adults with ASD are not impaired on comprehension of conventional and novel metaphors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>We also found that adults with ASD generate more original metaphors relative to age-matched peers and that non-verbal skills contribute to this ability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>The study points to unique verbal creativity in ASD which has not been studied in this way before. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>AdachiT.KoedaT.HirabayashiS.MaeokaY.ShiotaM.WrightE. (2004). The metaphor and sarcasm scenario test: a new instrument to help differentiate high functioning pervasive developmental disorder from attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder.Brain Dev. 26 301–306 10.1016/S0387-7604(03)00170-015165670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>AmanzioM.GeminianiG.LeottaD.CappaS. (2008). Metaphor comprehension in Alzheimer’s disease: novelty matters. Brain Lang. 107 1–10 10.1016/j.bandl.2007.08.00317897706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>American Psychiatric Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(2013). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5th Edn Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>AspergerH. (1941). “Autistic psychopathy in childhood,” in Autism and Asperger Syndrome ed.Frith, TransU.FrithU. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press) 37–92 (Reprinted from Archive fur Psychiatrie und Nervenkrankheiten, 11776–136, 1944) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Baron-CohenS.AshwinE.AshwinC.TavassoliT.Chakrabarti B. (2009). Talent in autism: hyper-systemizing, hyper-attention to detail and sensory hypersensitivity. Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Sci. 364 1377–1383 10.1098/rstb.2008.0337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Baron-CohenS.WheelwrightS.SkinnerR.MartinJ.ClubleyE. (2001). The autism-spectrum quotient (AQ): evidence from Asperger syndrome/high-functioning autism, males and females, scientists and mathematicians. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Disord. 31 5–17 10.1023/A:100565341147111439754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>BoucherJ. (1988). Word fluency in high-functioning autistic children. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Disord. 18 637–645 10.1007/BF022118813215889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>BowdleB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>F.GentnerD. (2005). The career of metaphor. Psychol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Rev. 112 193–216 10.1037/0033-295X.112.1.19315631593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>BrownL.SherbenouR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>J.JohnsenS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>K. (1997). Test of Nonverbal Intelligence: TONI-3 3rd Edn. Austin, TX: PRO-ED </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Champagne-LavauM.StipE. (2010). Pragmatic and executive dysfunction in schizophrenia. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Neurolinguist. 23 285–296 10.1016/j.jneuroling.2009.08.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>ChiappeD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>L.ChiappeP. (2007). The role of working memory in metaphor production and comprehension. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Mem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Lang. 56 172–188 10.1016/j.jml.2006.11.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>CraigJ.Baron-CohenS. (1999). Creativity and imagination in autism and Asperger syndrome. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Disord. 29 319–326 10.1023/A:102216340347910478731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>DietrichA. (2004). The cognitive neuroscience of creativity. Psychon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Rev. 11 1011–1026 10.3758/BF0319673115875970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>EvansM.-A.GambleD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>L. (1988). Attribute saliency and metaphor interpretation in school-age children. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Child Lang. 15 435–449 10.1017/S03050009000124473209650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>FitzgeraldM. (2004). Autism and Creativity: Is There a Link Between Autism in Men and Exceptional Ability? London: Brunner-Routledge </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>FrithU. (1972). Cognitive mechanisms in autism: experiments with color and tone sequence production. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Autism Childhood Schizophr. 2 160–173 10.1007/BF015375695068668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>GillbergC. (2002). A Guide to Asperger’s Syndrome. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 10.1017/CBO9780511543814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Golan O. Gold R.Fridenzon S. (2009 May). “The Hebrew version of the autism spectrum quotient (aq-heb) as a screening instrument for adults with autism spectrum conditions,” in Poster Presented at the 8th Annual International Meeting for Autism Research (Imfar) Chicago, IL </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>GoldR.FaustM.GoldesteinA. (2010). Semantic integration during metaphor comprehension in Asperger syndrome. Brain Lang. 113 124–134 10.1016/j.bandl.2010.03.00220359737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>HappéF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>E. (1993). Communicative competence and theory of mind in autism: a test of relevance theory. Cognition 48 101–119 10.1016/0010-0277(93)90026-R8243028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>HappéF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>E. (1995). Understanding minds and metaphors: insight from the study of figurative language in autism. Metaphor Symb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Act. 10 275–295 10.1207/s15327868ms1004_3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>HappéF.VitalP. (2009). What aspects of autism predispose to talent? Philos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Sci. 364 1369–1375 10.1098/rstb.2008.0332 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>HermannI.HaserV.van ElstL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>T.EbertD.Muller-FeldmethD.RiedelA. (2013). Automatic metaphor processing in adults with Asperger syndrome: a metaphor interference effect task. Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Psychiatry Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 263 177–187 10.1007/s00406-013-0453-923455635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>HillE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>L. (2004). Evaluating the theory of executive dysfunction in autism. Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Rev. 24 189–233 10.1016/j.dr.2004.01.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>HughesC. (1996). Brief report: planning problems in autism at the level of motor control. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Disord. 26 99–107 10.1007/BF022762378819773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>HughesC.RussellJ. (1993). Autistic children’s difficulty with mental disengagement from an object: its implications for theories of autism. Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Psychol. 29 498–510 10.1037/0012-1649.29.3.498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>KalandN.MortensenE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>L.SmithL. (2011). Social communication impairments in children and adolescents with Asperger syndrome: slow response time and the impact of prompting. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Autism Spectr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Disord. 5 1129–1137 10.1016/j.rasd.2010.12.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>KannerL. (1946). Irrelevant and metaphorical language in early infantile autism. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Psychiatry 103 242–24621001998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>KavéG. (2005a). Standardization and norms for a Hebrew naming test. Brain Lang. 92 204–211 10.1016/j.bandl.2004.06.00415629492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>KavéG. (2005b). Phonemic fluency, semantic fluency, and difference scores: normative data for adult Hebrew speakers. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Neuropsychol. 27 690–699 10.1080/1380339049091849916019645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>KerbelD.GrunwellP. (1998). A study of idiom comprehension in children with semantic-pragmatic difficulties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Part II: between-groups results and discussion. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Lang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Disord. 33 23–44 10.1080/1368282982479109673217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>LandaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>J.GoldbergM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>C. (2005). Language, social, and executive functions in high functioning autism: a continuum of performance. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Disord. 35 557–573 10.1007/s10803-005-0001-116211332 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>LevoratoM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>C.CacciariC. (2002). The creation of new figurative expressions: psycholinguistic evidence in Italian children, adolescents and adults. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Child Lang. 29 127–150 10.1017/S030500090100495011968879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>LewisV.BoucherJ. (1991). Skill, content and generative strategies in autistic children’s drawings. Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Psychol. 9 393–416 10.1111/j.2044-835X.1991.tb00885.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="?"><plain>LiuM.-J.ShihW.-L.MaL.-Y. (2011). Are children with Asperger syndrome creative in divergent thinking and feeling? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>A brief report. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Autism Spectr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Disord. 5 294–298 10.1016/j.rasd.2010.04.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>LyonsV.FitzgeraldM. (2005). Asperger’s Syndrome, Gift or Curse? New York: Nova Scientific </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>LyonsV.FitzgeraldM. (2004). Humour in Autism. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Disord. 34 5 521–531 10.1007/s10803-004-2547-815628606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>MashalN. (2013). The role of working memory in the comprehension of unfamiliar and familiar metaphors. Lang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Cogn. 5 409–436 10.1515/langcog-2013-0024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>MashalN.KasirerA. (2011). Thinking maps enhance metaphoric competence in children with autism and learning disabilities. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Disabil. 32 2045–2054 10.1016/j.ridd.2011.08.01221985987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>MelognoS.ArdiaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>D.PintoM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>A.LeviG. (2012). Explaining metaphors in high-functioning Autism Spectrum Disorder children: a brief report. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Autism Spectr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Disord. 6 683–689 10.1016/j.rasd.2011.09.005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>MinshewN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>J.LunaB.SweeneyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>A. (1999). Oculomotor evidence for neocortical systems but not cerebellar dysfunction in autism. Neurology 52 917–922 10.1212/WNL.52.5.91710102406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>NippoldM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>A. (1998). Later Language Development: The School-age and Adolescent Years. Austin, TX: PRO-ED </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>NorburyC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>F. (2005). The relation between theory of mind and metaphor: evidence from children with language impairment and Autistic Spectrum Disorder. Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Psychol. 23 383–399 10.1348/026151005X26732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>OzonoffS.MillerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>N. (1996). An exploration of right-hemisphere contributions to the pragmatic impairments of autism. Brain Lang. 52 411–434 10.1006/brln.1996.00228653388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>OzonoffS.StrayerD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>L. (1997). Further evidence of intact working memory in autism. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Disord. 31 257–263 10.1023/A:101079490213911518480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>OzonoffS.StrayerD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>L.McMahonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>M.FillouxF. (1998). Inhibitory deficits in Tourette syndrome: a function of comorbidity and symptom severity. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Child Psychol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Psychiatry 39 11091118 10.1111/1469-7610.00415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>PenningtonB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>F.OzonoffS. (1996). Executive functions and developmental psychopathology. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Child Psychol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Psychiatry 37 51–87 10.1111/j.1469-7610.1996.tb01380.x8655658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>RapinI.DunnM. (2003). Update on the language disorders of individuals on the autistic spectrum. Brain Dev. 25 166–172 10.1016/S0387-7604(02)00191-212689694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>ReitanR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>M.DavisonL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>A. (1974). Clinical Neuropsychology: Current Status and Applications. New York: Wiley </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>RobinsonS.GoddardL.DritschelB.WisleyM.HowlinP. (2009). Executive functions in children with Autism Spectrum Disorders. Brain Cogn. 71 362–368 10.1016/j.bandc.2009.06.00719628325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>RumseyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>M.HamburgerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>D. (1988). Neuropsychological findings in high-functioning men with infantile autism. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Autism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Disord. 20 155–168 10.1007/BF022847152347817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>RundbladG.AnnazD. (2010). The atypical development of metaphor and metonymy comprehension in children with autism. Autism 14 29–46 10.1177/136236130934066720124503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>RussellJ.(Ed.) (1997). Autism as an Executive Disorder. Oxford: Oxford University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>SilviaP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>J.BeatyR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>E. (2012). Making creative metaphors: the importance of fluid intelligence for creative thought. Intelligence 40 343–351 10.1016/j.intell.2012.02.005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>SilviaP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>J.BeatyR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>E. (2013). Metaphorically speaking: cognitive abilities and the production of figurative language. Mem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>Cogn. 41 255–267 10.3758/s13421-012-0258-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>TorranceE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>P. (1974). The Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking: Technical-norms Manual. Bensenville, IL: Scholastic Testing Services </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>TreffertD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>A. (2009). The savant syndrome: an extraordinary condition. Philos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>Sci. 364 1351–1357 10.1098/rstb.2008.0326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>WechslerD. (1997). Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale 3rd Edn San Antonio, TX: Psychological Corporation </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
