<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mil Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mil Med Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Military Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-7467</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2054-9369</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4340678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">27</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40779-014-0027-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Mesenchymal stem cell therapy for acute radiation syndrome: innovative medical approaches in military medicine </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>Erik B</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><address><email>erik.b.eaton4.mil@mail.mil</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Varney</surname><given-names>Timothy R</given-names></name><address><email>timothy.r.varney2.civ@mail.mil</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">United States Army Medical Research Institute of Chemical Defense, 3100 Ricketts Point Road, Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland, 21010 US </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Eaton and Varney; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>After a radiological or nuclear event, acute radiation syndrome (ARS) will present complex medical challenges that could involve the treatment of hundreds to thousands of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Current medical doctrine is based on limited clinical data and remains inadequate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Efforts to develop medical innovations that address ARS complications are unlikely to be generated by industry because of market uncertainties specific to this type of injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>A prospective strategy could be the integration of cellular therapy to meet the medical demands of ARS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The most clinically advanced cellular therapy to date is the administration of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results of currently published investigations describing MSC safety and efficacy in a variety of injury and disease models demonstrate the unique qualities of this reparative cell population in adapting to the specific requirements of the damaged tissue in which the cells integrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This report puts forward a rationale for the further evaluation of MSC therapy to address the current unmet medical needs of ARS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We propose that the exploration of this novel therapy for the treatment of the multivariate complications of ARS could be of invaluable benefit to military medicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Acute radiation syndrome</kwd><kwd>Mesenchymal stem cell</kwd><kwd>Cell therapy</kwd><kwd>Hematopoietic syndrome</kwd><kwd>Gastrointestinal syndrome</kwd><kwd>Radiation injury</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The inclusion of cellular therapies in the treatment of battlefield injuries provides a novel and promising approach for addressing long-standing challenges in tissue repair with regard to both structural and functional improvements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The results of currently published investigations describing adult stem cell efficacy in a variety of injury and disease models demonstrate the unique qualities of reparative cell populations present in adult tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs), adipose derived stem cells, and endothelial progenitor cells, for example, exhibit a remarkable capacity to adapt to the requirements of the damaged tissue in which the cells integrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focus on the potential use of MSC therapy as a medical countermeasure for the treatment of acute radiation syndrome (ARS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>MSC therapy represents a single medical intervention that can simultaneously provide a broad range of therapeutic efficacy, with local activity, at multiple tissue and organ sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Although ARS is rare, it is a complex and medically challenging disorder that has the potential for large-scale incidence on the battlefield or in conjunction with a domestic terrorist attack. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Currently, medical intervention for numerous aspects of ARS is limited to supportive care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Since the end of the Second World War, nearly all radiation injuries have been caused by accidents in the medical and nuclear power industries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, the rise in global terrorism, the proliferation of nuclear technology, and the undocumented dispersal of enriched uranium, plutonium, and other radioactive compounds have intensified concerns regarding the use of a radiological or nuclear weapon to inflict extensive military casualties, civilian casualties, or both. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Detonating an improvised radiological device or nuclear warhead could necessitate the medical management of hundreds to thousands of patients with ARS, which typically occurs to some degree following a whole body dose of 1 Gray (Gy) or more [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The underlying pathology of ARS involves physical and chemical damage to DNA, which affects the rapidly dividing cells of the hematopoietic system and the gastrointestinal (GI) tract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>As a result, ARS symptoms are often subclassified into the hematopoietic and GI syndromes, which occur simultaneously at higher exposure levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>As discussed below, the therapeutic benefit of MSC therapy for these individuals could include the facilitation of hematopoietic recovery, enhancement of healing of the GI tract and the skin, and the possible mitigation or treatment of a variety of additional ARS complications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>MSC biology and clinical use </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>MSC-based therapeutics have emerged as the most clinically advanced multipotent stem cell therapy to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>At least 178 Phase II or Phase III trials have been completed or are currently recruiting patients to evaluate MSC therapy for the treatment of a diverse array of indications (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>, September 2014 [3]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A commercial product consisting of purified MSCs has received regulatory approval in both Canada and New Zealand for the treatment of graft vs. host disease (GvHD), a potentially lethal complication of allogeneic bone marrow transplant arising from the severe immune reaction of the donated immune cells against the host tissues (Osiris Therapeutics, Inc., Columbia, MD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The currently marketed cell-based treatment regimen does not contain embryonic cells or any constituent derived from fetal sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Although other forms of stem cell therapies based on induced pluripotent stem cells, embryonic stem cells, or umbilical cord blood continue to show promise in pre-clinical studies, MSC therapy represents an approach that is rapidly gaining acceptance in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>No other multipotent stem cell therapy has established an extensive safety profile in the clinical setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Intravenously (IV) infused MSCs have been shown to specifically migrate to sites of tissue damage in multiple preclinical injury models [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>MSC infusion mimics a naturally occurring process in which endogenous MSCs leave the bone marrow compartment in response to injury, enter the circulation, and travel to sites of tissue damage, guided by chemotactic homing signals released at each compromised site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The clinical development of MSC formulations for therapeutic use has involved the isolation of MSCs from bone marrow and expansion in culture [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Numerous studies have indicated that donor-derived, IV-administered MSCs retain the ability to localize to damaged tissue and facilitate repair in a variety of injury and disease settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Cell culture-expanded MSCs demonstrate the potential to form several specialized cell types, including neurons, skin, bone, fat, cartilage, tendon, muscle (cardiac and skeletal), epithelium (lung, gut, and kidney), and many others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Once engrafted within damaged tissues, MSCs participate in the healing process both directly, through differentiation to replace lost cell types, and indirectly, through the local secretion of cytokines and other bioactive molecules that facilitate a reduction in inflammation, the inhibition of scar formation, and the enhancement of endogenous mechanisms of tissue reconstruction [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The molecular basis for MSC homing to injury sites has been evaluated by several independent laboratories using both in vitro and in vivo approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The data describe MSC chemotaxis toward a variety of chemokines, including monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), macrophage inflammatory protein-1α (MIP-1α), interleukin-8 (IL-8), and stromal derived factor-1 (SDF-1) [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For example, Wang et al. [8] observed in vitro MSC migration toward purified MCP-1, MIP-1α, and IL-8, as well as toward extracts prepared from brain tissue injured by oxygen deprivation (ischemic injury). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The involvement of the specific chemokine in question was verified by the inhibition of directional migration in the presence of a blocking antibody to each cytokine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Once engrafted to damaged tissues, MSCs elicit a broad range of effects with regard to modulation of the inflammatory response to injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>MSCs express a low level of major histocompatibility (MHC) class I molecules, but they lack expression of MHC class II and the B7 co-stimulatory molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These molecules are involved in antigen presentation at the cell surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>MSCs are therefore rendered “immune privileged” by the capacity to evade recognition by both CD4+ T helper and CD8+ cytotoxic T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In addition to being immune privileged MSCs also actively attenuate immune activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Cell surface markers of lymphocyte activation, including CD25, CD38, and CD69, have been shown to decrease in the presence of MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>T cell proliferation is inhibited by MSCs through a block in cyclin D2 expression, resulting in cell cycle arrest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Finally, MSCs have also been shown to inhibit the innate immune response by blocking the IL-2-mediated activation of natural killer cells [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In addition to the initial anti-inflammatory properties of MSCs, engraftment induces the local secretion of multiple paracrine factors that facilitate wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>These factors include angiogenic, anti-apoptotic, mitogenic, and homing signals, such as vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), hepatocyte growth factor (HGF), insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), and SDF-1, resulting in the accumulation of several distinct populations of blood vessel precursor cells and other tissue-specific progenitor cells [7,9,11,12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Both preclinical and clinical studies have demonstrated the safety and efficacy of allogeneic (non-immunologically matched) MSC delivery (see recent reviews by Inamdar et al. [13]; Sheng et al. [14]; and Honmou et al. [15]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The general consensus for efficacy with the use of allogeneically derived MSCs is increasingly ascribed to anti-inflammatory and paracrine activity [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>However, significant interest still remains in evaluating the role of MSCs, as a stem cell population, in promoting wound repair by direct differentiation to replace cells lost to injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In the context of addressing the consequences of battlefield injury, we see a distinct and specific value for the use of either allogeneic or autologous (patient-derived) MSC therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The rationale for determining the MSC source will be dependent on the treatment goals for each indication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>For example, early treatment for a blast injury may be focused on the anti-inflammatory and paracrine properties of MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Stockpiled, “off-the-shelf” allogeneic MSCs would be appropriate for use in this case and could be administered in a Combat Support Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The use of MSCs for reconstructive procedures to replace significant tissue loss, however, would likely require autologously derived cells that would not be cleared by the immune system after the cells mature and begin to express donor-specific proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The characteristic anti-inflammatory, tissue repair, and hematopoietic support capabilities of this particular stem cell population suggest that MSC therapy may be ideal for inclusion in medical preparedness planning for a radiological or nuclear event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Given the broad applicability of MSC treatments to numerous diverse injuries and diseases, the development of MSC treatment for ARS is also likely to benefit treatment strategies for a wide array of additional conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Therapeutic potential of MSC treatment of hematopoietic syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The hematopoietic syndrome is the principal cause of mortality in radiation exposure doses from 1 to 10 Gy [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The manifest illness is typically characterized by intense immunosuppression, anemia, and thrombocytopenia resulting from the death and/or reduced replication of hematopoietic progenitor cells following irradiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Current data from studies on animals and humans suggest that the mean lethal dose of whole body radiation required to kill 50% of patients in 60 days is between 3 and 4 Gy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>When patients are given appropriate medical management with intravenous hydration, antiemetics, analgesics, antibiotics, and blood transfusions, the LD50 is estimated to lie between approximately 6 and 7 Gy [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Current guidelines recommend short-term cytokine therapy with granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (Neupogen® [Filgrastim, Amgen, Inc.]), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), and pegylated G-CSF to facilitate hematopoietic recovery [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Both in vitro and in vivo (including clinical) data indicate that the addition of MSC therapy to standard care can promote more rapid recovery of the hematopoietic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>MSCs constitutively secrete a broad range of hematopoietic cytokines, such as IL-6, IL-7, IL-8, IL-11, IL-14, IL-15, macrophage colony-stimulating factor, Flt-3 ligand, and stem-cell factor (SFC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>IL-1a induces MSC production of IL-1a, leukemia-inhibiting factor, G-CSF, and GM-CSF [18]. In vitro evaluations have provided detailed evidence that these factors, as well as other members of the MSC secretome (the array of proteins produced and secreted by MSCs), support the growth of hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) and their progeny in an ex vivo environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>MSC deposition of extracellular matrix constituents that are native to the bone marrow compartment is likely to significantly contribute to this phenomenon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Relevant to hematopoietic recovery after radiation exposure, in vitro studies have also shown a positive influence of the presence of MSCs on the expansion of irradiated blood cell precursors: irradiated CD34+ cells demonstrate a several-fold growth increase when cultured in the presence vs. the absence of MSCs [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>At higher radiation exposure levels, patients will require an HSC transplant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In a mass casualty scenario, the timely treatment of large numbers of patients will be challenging and will require innovative medical intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Preclinical work in animal models has evaluated the influence of HSC–MSC co-transplant on hematopoietic recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The results of these analyses suggest that HSC–MSC coinfusion facilitates HSC engraftment and hematopoietic recovery [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, MSC coinfusion increases the success rates of HSC transplants, even under sub-optimal transplant conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These scenarios include the transplantation of a limited number of HSCs [21,22] or situations in which transplanted HSCs have been obtained from two immunologically disparate donors [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Fortunately, the promising results obtained in preclinical studies are being realized in the clinical setting as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A successful clinical use has been the coinfusion of HSC–MSC following ablative radiation or chemotherapy for the treatment of both malignant and non-malignant disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A large body of data supports the concept that MSC therapy provides a safe and effective treatment modality to facilitate hematopoietic recovery and overall survival following medical intervention that involves an HSC transplant (reviewed in Tolar [24]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The majority of published reports discuss clinical outcomes from small or single-patient case studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Despite differences in the particular medical disorder, patient demographics, and treatment regimen, the collective results suggest an increase in both HSC graft stability and overall patient survival. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Importantly, larger clinical trials have evaluated results from a treated subject pool against relevant historical control patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These studies have demonstrated significant efficacy with the use of HSC–MSC coinfusion to promote the rapid recovery of cellular blood constituents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>For example, a Phase I/II clinical study by Ball et al. ([25]) followed 14 patients who were co-transplanted with donor MSCs and human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-disparate peripheral blood HSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The results were compared to 47 historic control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Study subjects were treated at the same two medical facilities as control patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The infusion dose ranged from 1 to 5 million MSCs/kg body weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>MSC-treated subjects experienced faster recovery in total leukocyte count (above 1.0 × 109/L) in comparison to historic controls, with patients in this study having a mean time to recovery of 11.5 days and the control group recovering in 14.9 days (P = 0.009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Although control subjects experienced a graft failure rate of 15%, all patients who were given MSCs in this study showed sustained hematopoietic engraftment without adverse reactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Rapid hematopoietic reconstitution was also reported for 28 subjects enrolled in a breast cancer study that had received high-dose chemotherapy followed by the coinfusion of peripheral blood stem cells and MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In this investigation, all patients received 1 to 2.2 million autologous MSCs/kg body mass in conjunction with G-CSF therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Neutrophil recovery (judged as greater than 500/μl) ranged from 6 to 11 days, with an average of 8 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Platelet engraftment (judged as greater than 20,000/μl) ranged from 4 to 19 days, with an average of 8.5 days [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Historical control data specifically relevant to this institute or by these researchers are not reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>However, these values for neutrophil and platelet recovery are more favorable compared with the results of large clinical trials published elsewhere in which patients received G-CSF treatment (e.g., Amadori [27], Usuki [28], Nivison-Smith [29], Godwin [30], Lowenberg [31], Hassan [32], Rowe [33], Stone [34], Ottmann [35]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Depending on the scale of a radiological or nuclear incident, medical response logistics, and the availability of suitable donors, the number of ARS victims that can be given an HSC transplant may be highly limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Studies in animal models and clinical investigations suggest that the infusion of allogeneic MSCs alone may be an achievable and efficacious alternative strategy for stimulating hematopoietic recovery in patients [36,37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A clinical approach that closely mimics this scenario is allogeneic MSC infusion to treat patients in which HSC engraftment has failed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In both cases, MSCs are administered without HSC coinfusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>MSC engraftment to the bone marrow enhances the HSC niche to a level that promotes the growth and maturation of residual HSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Although the currently available data are limited, MSC infusion as a rescue therapy for HSC graft failure has shown generally positive outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Significant improvement in the bone marrow microenvironment and, in some cases, rapid and sustained hematopoietic recovery, have been observed in subjects who had failed to respond to conventional treatment [38-40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>To provide timely administration under this scenario, an option would be to stockpile allogeneic MSCs that would be readily available in the event of a radiological or nuclear emergency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This option is an attainable goal because relatively few donors would be required to generate a sufficient number of doses to treat hundreds to thousands of patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Efficacy potential of MSC therapy for GI syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In addition to hematological crisis, victims exposed to radiation levels exceeding 7 Gy will develop complications that are characteristic of radiation-induced GI syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>These symptoms include dehydration, electrolyte imbalance, malaise, anorexia, severe diarrhea, and fever. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The basis of the injury to the GI tract is associated with the loss of rapidly dividing stem cells of the intestinal crypts, which replenish the epithelial layer of the gut during normal tissue turnover. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The resulting breach in the GI barrier, in combination with immune suppression, presents a high risk of life-threatening infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Patients diagnosed with GI syndrome have an extremely low survival rate, and no currently approved medical countermeasure specifically addresses this component of ARS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Similar to the influence of MSCs on HSCs within the bone marrow compartment, both in vitro and in vivo data support the role of MSC therapy in promoting the restoration of intestinal epithelium by nurturing the growth of the residual surviving crypt stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A mechanism through which this support occurs is the local secretion of growth factors and chemotactic signals that draw in epithelial progenitors to the sites of tissue damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Preclinical models of abdominal and total body irradiation have demonstrated increased survival with MSC infusion accompanied by intestinal crypt cell regeneration, restitution of the stem cell niche, and increased xylose absorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Serum levels of intestinal radioprotective factors (including R-Spondin1, KGF, PDGF and FGF2) and anti-inflammatory cytokines were increased, whereas inflammatory cytokines were down-regulated [41-43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Clinical data specifically related to irradiation injury of the gut are extremely limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>However, systemic allogeneic MSC infusion to accidentally over-irradiated prostate cancer patients with radiation-induced colitis has been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>These patients experienced a reduction in pain, diarrhea, hemorrhage, inflammation, and fistulization [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Additionally, successful clinical use of MSC therapy has been reported in treating certain inflammatory bowel diseases that involve the significant loss of intestinal epithelium, such as GvHD [45] and Crohn’s disease [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Considering the highly similar pathophysiology of these conditions, the same mechanisms that are active in the treatment of GvHD and Crohn’s disease may also be effective against the GI symptoms of ARS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A well-characterized model of GI syndrome in non-human primates recently developed by MacVittie et al. [47] may prove to be an invaluable tool for developing countermeasures for GI syndrome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Therapeutic rationale for MSC treatment of cutaneous and combined injury </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Battlefield injuries commonly involve severe and extensive cutaneous tissue damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of MSC treatment in promoting skin regeneration has been shown in multiple preclinical injury models, including laceration [48], thermal burn [49], and radiation exposure [50-52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The results of these studies demonstrate more expedient wound closure, decreased incidence of infection, increased vasculogenesis and elasticity, and reduced scar formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Lacerative injury concurrent with irradiation presents a daunting treatment challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This scenario has been specifically evaluated by Hao et al. ([53]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>A combined radiation–wound injury was generated in rats by producing an excisional wound equal to 2% body surface in subjects that had received 6 Gy total body irradiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>MSCs were then directly injected into the wound bed and margins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>At 14 days post-injury, the wound area was approximately half the size in MSC-treated animals vs. control subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Evidence that MSCs play a natural role in the process of skin regeneration in humans has been collected in a clinical study, in which the number of MSCs circulating in the peripheral blood of thermal-burn patients was quantified and compared to the number of circulating MSCs in the blood of healthy volunteers [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>MSC phenotype was determined by the positive expression of five specific cell surface markers and the negative expression of eight other markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The percentage of MSCs in circulating blood was more than 20-fold greater in burn patients compared to that in healthy individuals, and the degree of increase was correlated with the size and severity of the burn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>These results offer data from human subjects that suggest MSCs play an important role in skin regenerative processes because the cells appear to be mobilized from the bone marrow in response to injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In addition to MSC efficacy in facilitating hematopoietic recovery and in promoting gut and skin repair, both structural and functional improvements for a variety of other injury types have been described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>For example, the results of preclinical injury studies suggest effective MSC-based treatment of skeletal muscle [55], bone [56], tendon [57], lung [58], brain [59], heart [60], cornea [61,62], liver [63], and kidney [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The homing ability and adaptability of cellular therapy to conditions that are local to the injury site make this approach ideal for medical defense, particularly in cases involving more than one injury site or injury type. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>MSC production methodology at United States Army medical research institute of chemical defense </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A logical next step in expanding the clinical use of MSC therapy is to develop efficient and consistently reliable methods for the production of pharmaceutical quantities of MSC product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The United States Army Medical Research Institute of Chemical Defense (USAMRICD) has developed production methods designed to facilitate the clinical transition of an MSC-based countermeasure, with the intention of actualizing the availability of this promising cellular therapeutic to health care providers responsible for treating warfighters [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The establishment of a defined MSC manufacturing paradigm will be critical for the progression of the technology to the Army’s advanced development group (United States Army Medical Materiel Development Activity, USAMMDA), for work leading to potential FDA approval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Although this report has focused on the development of MSC technology to produce a medical countermeasure to ARS, such a product may be significant in the treatment of additional battlefield indications (such as trauma, chemical exposure, and blast injury). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>One improvement in MSC production methodology has proven to be the inclusion of fibronectin (Fn) as a surface coating for culture vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Fn is one of the most abundant extracellular matrix proteins in the bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The presence of Fn in MSC culture provides an environment that more closely mimics the endogenous MSC niche and promotes overall cell health and retention of stem cell differentiation potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>A second modification of standard practice that we have put in place is to actively prevent high cell density, including the initial (passage 0) MSC culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Although the maintenance of lower cell density is fairly easy to achieve during later cell passages, no report has suggested the dispersion of cells from original colonies formed by the initial plated bone marrow as a significant consideration in MSC production strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>This approach ensures that cells do not experience high density confluency for significant periods at any stage of the production process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The methods we have established for MSC culture expansion have induced consistently high yields in production lots derived from human and animal bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Freshly plated bone marrow forms small MSC colonies that are seen to generate an environment that supports the survival and growth of HSCs (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Cultures left to grow to form a complete monolayer show the common swirled pattern that is typical of 100% confluent MSC cultures (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Under appropriate conditions, MSCs can be induced to mature along the osteogenic (C-D) and adipogenic (E-F) pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Our methods allow for the generation of one production lot of high-quality, differentiation-capable MSCs that reach passage 3 in 16 days or less. “Passage 3” cells have completed an initial 5- to 7-day period of outgrowth from a plated bone marrow sample, followed by 3 rounds of expansion in cell culture that typically requires 2 to 3 days of growth each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In the absence of early passage 0 colony dispersal and an Fn-coated growth surface, MSC cultures require approximately twice the cultivation time to reach passage 3 [6,66,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A rapid MSC production methodology will be critical for applications that may require autologous MSC delivery, such as tissue engineering and reconstruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Finally, the manufacturing process for MSC production has been designed to be completely scalable using commercially available “multi-stack” cultivation vessels, with final cell yields that solely depend on the volume of bone marrow input at culture initiation.Figure 1Growth and differentiation of MSCs. Freshly plated bone marrow contains mature blood cells, HSCs, and MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Media changes result in the formation of small MSC colonies because of the differential adhesion properties of MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These small groups of adherent cells generate an environment that supports the survival and growth of HSCs and (Panel A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Long-term confluent MSC cultures form the typical swirled pattern characteristic of this cell type (Panel B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>MSCs can be induced to mature along the osteogenic differentiation pathway, as shown by calcium deposition staining (Panel C) and alkaline phosphatase activity staining (Panel D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Adipogenic maturation is signified by Oil Red O staining (Panel E) and LipidTox Red uptake (Panel F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The dynamic nature of medical threats that are faced by warfighters calls for the development of countermeasures that address a broad range of tissue pathologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The adaptability of the cellular therapy approach discussed in this report provides a promising option to address the unmet needs that are critically important in medical defense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Current preclinical and clinical results of MSC efficacy investigations have demonstrated success in a variety of injury and disease settings that share a similar pathophysiology to the indications of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The administration of MSCs by IV infusion has shown clinical benefit on surface wounds and can also reach tissue damage located deeper within the body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This capability is derived from the remarkable and well-demonstrated behavior of systemically delivered MSCs to distribute to sites of compromised tissue under the influence of chemokine homing signals produced at one or more injury sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The injury-specific distribution of MSCs following infusion provides a particular advantage in the treatment of combined injury (e.g., laceration in combination with exposure to chemically or radiologically induced tissue damage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>IV MSC delivery represents an approach in which the administration of a single therapeutic can facilitate tissue repair at multiple injury sites and for various injury types, in accordance with the specific requirements for the repair of each compromised site during the healing process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Significantly, the outstanding safety profile of this cellular therapeutic has been extensively demonstrated in the clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>To date, more than 1,400 patients enrolled in clinical trials have received the first marketed MSC therapeutic, Prochymal® (Osiris Therapeutics, Inc.), with no reports of serious adverse events linked to treatment (ClinicalTrials.gov, September 2014 [3]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The advancement of MSC therapeutics to address the broad array of rare but treatment-challenging injuries faced by warfighters will require the development of appropriate injury-specific preclinical models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Investigations designed to statistically evaluate MSC efficacy for the treatment of injuries induced by radiation, chemical, or blast exposure are critical for regulatory approval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The advancement of translational research directed toward treating battlefield injury will have multiple cross-over opportunities for dual-use applications within the general population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The challenging nature of modern warfare injuries requires that military medicine remain at the forefront of innovative medical approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>ARS</term><def><p>Acute radiation syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSC</term><def><p>Mesenchymal stem cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Gy</term><def><p>Gray</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GI</term><def><p>Gastrointestinal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GvHD</term><def><p>Graft vs. host disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IV</term><def><p>Intravenous</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCP-1</term><def><p>Monocyte chemoattractant protein-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIP-1α</term><def><p>Macrophage inflammatory protein-1α</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p>Interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDF-1</term><def><p>Stromal derived factor-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHC</term><def><p>Major histocompatibility</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VEGF</term><def><p>Vascular endothelial growth factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HGF</term><def><p>Hepatocyte growth factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IGF-1</term><def><p>Insulin-like growth factor-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>bFGF</term><def><p>Basic fibroblast growth factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GM-CSF</term><def><p>Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSC</term><def><p>Hematopoietic stem cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HLA</term><def><p>Human leukocyte antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USAMRICD</term><def><p>United States Army Medical Research Institute of Chemical Defense</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USAMMDA</term><def><p>United States Army Medical Materiel Development Activity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Fn</term><def><p>Fibronectin</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>EE: EE made substantial contributions to the analysis and interpretation of the published data and was substantially involved in writing the manuscript and revising it critically for important intellectual content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition, EE carried out the work and generated the graphics for Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>TV: TV is the Laboratory Principal Investigator, who made substantial contributions to the analysis and interpretation of the published data and was substantially involved in writing the manuscript and revising it critically for important intellectual content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Both authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In addition, both authors agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work and to ensure that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Authors’ information </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Dr. Timothy R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Varney, Principal Investigator, Research Interests: cellular therapy, chemical and radiological injury; SGT Erik B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Eaton, Medical Laboratory Technician. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Research Interests: combat casualty care, MSC biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to express their appreciation to CPT Robert Brodnick and CPT Carl Smith for their advice and administrative assistance, as well as to Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Dorian Olivera, Brian Keyser, and Al Ruff for their editorial comments. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="d30e728"><title>Funding source and disclaimer</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by the in-house Laboratory Independent Research (ILIR) program of the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Army. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The views expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not reflect the official policy of the Department of the Army, Department of Defense, or the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Government. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>1.WaselenkoJKMacVittieTJBlakelyWFPesikNWileyALDickersonWEMedical management of the acute radiation syndrome: recommendations of the Strategic National Stockpile Radiation Working GroupAnn Intern Med20041401037105110.7326/0003-4819-140-12-200406150-00015<?supplied-pmid 15197022?>15197022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>2.Gurudutta GU, Satija NK, Singh VK, Verma YK, Gupta P, Tripathi RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Stem cell therapy: a novel &amp; futuristic treatment modality for disaster injuries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Indian J Med Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>2012;135:15–25. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>3.ClinicalTrials.gov: [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">http://clinicaltrials.gov/</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>4.PittengerMFMartinBJMesenchymal stem cells and their potential as cardiac therapeuticsCirc Res20049592010.1161/01.RES.0000135902.99383.6f<?supplied-pmid 15242981?>15242981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>5.ChenJChoppMNeurorestorative treatment of stroke: cell and pharmacological approachesNeuroRx2006346647310.1016/j.nurx.2006.07.007<?supplied-pmid 17012060?>17012060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>6.PittengerMFMackayAMBeckSCJaiswalRKDouglasRMoscaJDMultilineage potential of adult human mesenchymal stem cellsScience199928414314710.1126/science.284.5411.143<?supplied-pmid 10102814?>10102814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>7.Meirelles LdaSFontesAMCovasDTCaplanAIMechanisms involved in the therapeutic properties of mesenchymal stem cellsCytokine Growth Factor Rev20092041942710.1016/j.cytogfr.2009.10.002<?supplied-pmid 19926330?>19926330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>8.WangLLiYChenXChenJGautamSCXuYMCP-1, MIP-1, IL-8 and ischemic cerebral tissue enhance human bone marrow stromal cell migration in interface cultureHematology2002711311710.1080/10245330290028588<?supplied-pmid 12186702?>12186702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>9.AskariATUnzekSPopovicZBGoldmanCKForudiFKiedrowskiMEffect of stromal-cell-derived factor 1 on stem-cell homing and tissue regeneration in ischaemic cardiomyopathyLancet200336269770310.1016/S0140-6736(03)14232-8<?supplied-pmid 12957092?>12957092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>10.CalkoenFGBrinkmanDMVervatCvan Ostaijen-Ten DamMMTen CateRvan TolMJMesenchymal stromal cells isolated from children with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis suppress innate and adaptive immune responsesCytotherapy20131528029110.1016/j.jcyt.2012.10.017<?supplied-pmid 23312448?>23312448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>11.NeussSBecherEWoltjeMTietzeLJahnen-DechentWFunctional expression of HGF and HGF receptor/c-met in adult human mesenchymal stem cells suggests a role in cell mobilization, tissue repair, and wound healingStem Cells20042240541410.1634/stemcells.22-3-405<?supplied-pmid 15153617?>15153617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>12.ChenJLiYKatakowskiMChenXWangLLuDIntravenous bone marrow stromal cell therapy reduces apoptosis and promotes endogenous cell proliferation after stroke in female ratJ Neurosci Res20037377878610.1002/jnr.10691<?supplied-pmid 12949903?>12949903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>13.InamdarACInamdarAAMesenchymal stem cell therapy in lung disorders: pathogenesis of lung diseases and mechanism of action of mesenchymal stem cellExp Lung Res20133931532710.3109/01902148.2013.816803<?supplied-pmid 23992090?>23992090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>14.ShengCCZhouLHaoJCurrent stem cell delivery methods for myocardial repairBiomed Res Int20132013547902<?supplied-pmid 23509740?>23509740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>15.HonmouOOnoderaRSasakiMWaxmanSGKocsisJDMesenchymal stem cells: therapeutic outlook for strokeTrends Mol Med20121829229710.1016/j.molmed.2012.02.003<?supplied-pmid 22459358?>22459358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>16.De MiguelMPFuentes-JulianSBlazquez-MartinezAPascualCYAllerMAAriasJImmunosuppressive properties of mesenchymal stem cells: advances and applicationsCurr Mol Med20121257459110.2174/156652412800619950<?supplied-pmid 22515979?>22515979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>17.DonnellyEHNemhauserJBSmithJMKazziZNFarfanEBChangASAcute radiation syndrome: assessment and managementSouth Med J201010354154610.1097/SMJ.0b013e3181ddd571<?supplied-pmid 20710137?>20710137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>18.MajumdarMKThiedeMAMoscaJDMoormanMGersonSLPhenotypic and functional comparison of cultures of marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) and stromal cellsJ Cell Physiol1998176576610.1002/(SICI)1097-4652(199807)176:1&lt;57::AID-JCP7&gt;3.0.CO;2-7<?supplied-pmid 9618145?>9618145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>19.MourcinFGrenierNMayolJFLatailladeJJSottoJJHerodinFMesenchymal stem cells support expansion of in vitro irradiated CD34(+) cells in the presence of SCF, FLT3 ligand, TPO and IL3: potential application to autologous cell therapy in accidentally irradiated victimsRadiat Res20051641910.1667/RR3384<?supplied-pmid 15966759?>15966759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>20.WangJFWuYFHarrintongJMcNieceIKEx vivo expansions and transplantations of mouse bone marrow-derived hematopoietic stem/progenitor cellsJ Zhejiang Univ Sci2004515716310.1631/jzus.2004.0157<?supplied-pmid 14674026?>14674026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>21.AngelopoulouMNovelliEGroveJERinderHMCivinCChengLCotransplantation of human mesenchymal stem cells enhances human myelopoiesis and megakaryocytopoiesis in NOD/SCID miceExp Hematol20033141342010.1016/S0301-472X(03)00042-0<?supplied-pmid 12763140?>12763140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>22.MaitraBSzekelyEGjiniKLaughlinMJDennisJHaynesworthSEHuman mesenchymal stem cells support unrelated donor hematopoietic stem cells and suppress T-cell activationBone Marrow Transplant20043359760410.1038/sj.bmt.1704400<?supplied-pmid 14716336?>14716336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>23.KimDWChungYJKimTGKimYLOhIHCotransplantation of third-party mesenchymal stromal cells can alleviate single-donor predominance and increase engraftment from double cord transplantationBlood20041031941194810.1182/blood-2003-05-1601<?supplied-pmid 14592834?>14592834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>24.TolarJLe BlancKKeatingABlazarBRConcise review: hitting the right spot with mesenchymal stromal cellsStem Cells2010281446145510.1002/stem.459<?supplied-pmid 20597105?>20597105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>25.BallLMBernardoMERoelofsHLankesterACometaAEgelerRMCotransplantation of ex vivo expanded mesenchymal stem cells accelerates lymphocyte recovery and may reduce the risk of graft failure in haploidentical hematopoietic stem-cell transplantationBlood20071102764276710.1182/blood-2007-04-087056<?supplied-pmid 17638847?>17638847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>26.KocONGersonSLCooperBWDyhouseSMHaynesworthSECaplanAIRapid hematopoietic recovery after coinfusion of autologous-blood stem cells and culture-expanded marrow mesenchymal stem cells in advanced breast cancer patients receiving high-dose chemotherapyJ Clin Oncol200018307316<?supplied-pmid 10637244?>10637244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>27.AmadoriSSuciuSJehnUStasiRThomasXMarieJPUse of glycosylated recombinant human G-CSF (lenograstim) during and/or after induction chemotherapy in patients 61 years of age and older with acute myeloid leukemia: final results of AML-13, a randomized phase-3 studyBlood2005106273410.1182/blood-2004-09-3728<?supplied-pmid 15761020?>15761020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>28.UsukiKUrabeAMasaokaTOhnoRMizoguchiHHamajimaNEfficacy of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in the treatment of acute myelogenous leukaemia: a multicentre randomized studyBr J Haematol200211610311210.1046/j.1365-2141.2002.03251.x<?supplied-pmid 11841402?>11841402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>29.Nivison-SmithIBradstockKFSzerJDurrantSDoddsAHermannRAllogeneic haemopoietic cell transplants in Australia, 1996–a multi-centre retrospective comparison of the use of peripheral blood stem cells with bone marrowBone Marrow Transplant200128212710.1038/sj.bmt.1703088<?supplied-pmid 11498740?>11498740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>30.GodwinJEKopeckyKJHeadDRWillmanCLLeithCPHynesHEA double-blind placebo-controlled trial of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in elderly patients with previously untreated acute myeloid leukemia: a Southwest oncology group study (9031)Blood19989136073615<?supplied-pmid 9572995?>9572995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>31.LowenbergBBoogaertsMADaenenSMVerhoefGEHagenbeekAVellengaEValue of different modalities of granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor applied during or after induction therapy of acute myeloid leukemiaJ Clin Oncol19971534963506<?supplied-pmid 9396403?>9396403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>32.HassanHTZanderARThrombocytopenia after high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation: an unresolved problem and possible approaches to resolve itJ Hematother1996540741410.1089/scd.1.1996.5.407<?supplied-pmid 8877716?>8877716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>33.RoweJMAndersenJWMazzaJJBennettJMPaiettaEHayesFAA randomized placebo-controlled phase III study of granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor in adult patients (&gt; 55 to 70 years of age) with acute myelogenous leukemia: a study of the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (E1490)Blood199586457462<?supplied-pmid 7605984?>7605984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>34.StoneRMBergDTGeorgeSLDodgeRKPaciucciPASchulmanPGranulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor after initial chemotherapy for elderly patients with primary acute myelogenous leukemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Cancer and Leukemia Group BN Eng J Med19953321671167710.1056/NEJM199506223322503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>35.OttmannOGHoelzerDGracienEGanserAKellyKReutzelRConcomitant granulocyte colony-stimulating factor and induction chemoradiotherapy in adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a randomized phase III trialBlood1995862444450<?supplied-pmid 7541660?>7541660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>36.HuKXSunQYGuoMAiHSThe radiation protection and therapy effects of mesenchymal stem cells in mice with acute radiation injuryBr J Radiol201083525810.1259/bjr/61042310<?supplied-pmid 20139249?>20139249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>37.LangeCBrunswig-SpickenheierBCappallo-ObermannHEggertKGehlingUMRudolphCRadiation rescue: mesenchymal stromal cells protect from lethal irradiationPLoS One20116e1448610.1371/journal.pone.0014486<?supplied-pmid 21245929?>21245929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>38.FouillardLBensidhoumMBoriesDBonteHLopezMMoseleyAMEngraftment of allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells in the bone marrow of a patient with severe idiopathic aplastic anemia improves stromaLeukemia20031747447610.1038/sj.leu.2402786<?supplied-pmid 12592355?>12592355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>39.FouillardLChapelABoriesDBouchetSCostaJMRouardHInfusion of allogeneic-related HLA mismatched mesenchymal stem cells for the treatment of incomplete engraftment following autologous haematopoietic stem cell transplantationLeukemia20072156857010.1038/sj.leu.2404550<?supplied-pmid 17252011?>17252011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>40.MeulemanNTondreauTAhmadIKwanJCrokaertFDelforgeAInfusion of mesenchymal stromal cells can aid hematopoietic recovery following allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell myeloablative transplant: a pilot studyStem Cells Dev2009181247125210.1089/scd.2009.0029<?supplied-pmid 19309241?>19309241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>41.SahaSBhanjaPKabarritiRLiuLAlfieriAAGuhaCBone marrow stromal cell transplantation mitigates radiation-induced gastrointestinal syndrome in micePLoS One20116e2407210.1371/journal.pone.0024072<?supplied-pmid 21935373?>21935373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>42.KinnairdTStabileEBurnettMSLeeCWBarrSFuchsSMarrow-derived stromal cells express genes encoding a broad spectrum of arteriogenic cytokines and promote in vitro and in vivo arteriogenesis through paracrine mechanismsCirc Res20049467868510.1161/01.RES.0000118601.37875.AC<?supplied-pmid 14739163?>14739163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>43.SemontAFrancoisSMouiseddineMFrancoisASacheAFrickJMesenchymal stem cells increase self-renewal of small intestinal epithelium and accelerate structural recovery after radiation injuryAdv Exp Med Biol2006585193010.1007/978-0-387-34133-0_2<?supplied-pmid 17120774?>17120774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>44.Voswinkel J, Francois S, Simon JM, Benderitter M, Gorin NC, Mohty M, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Use of Mesenchymal Stem Cells (MSC) in chronic inflammatory fistulizing and fibrotic diseases: a comprehensive review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>2013;ᅟ:ᅟ. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>45.RingdenOUzunelMRasmussonIRembergerMSundbergBLonniesHMesenchymal stem cells for treatment of therapy-resistant graft-versus-host diseaseTransplantation2006811390139710.1097/01.tp.0000214462.63943.14<?supplied-pmid 16732175?>16732175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>46.DuijvesteinMVosACRoelofsHWildenbergMEWendrichBBVerspagetHWAutologous bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stromal cell treatment for refractory luminal Crohn’s disease: results of a phase I studyGut201059121662166910.1136/gut.2010.215152<?supplied-pmid 20921206?>20921206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>47.MacVittieTJFareseAMBennettAGelfondDShea-DonohueTTudorGThe acute gastrointestinal subsyndrome of the acute radiation syndrome: a rhesus macaque modelHealth Phys201210341142610.1097/HP.0b013e31826525f0<?supplied-pmid 22929470?>22929470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>48.KimJWLeeJHLyooYSJungDIParkHMThe effects of topical mesenchymal stem cell transplantation in canine experimental cutaneous woundsVet Dermatol201324e242e25310.1111/vde.12011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>49.ShumakovVIOnishchenkoNARasulovMFKrasheninnikovMEZaidenovVAMesenchymal bone marrow stem cells more effectively stimulate regeneration of deep burn wounds than embryonic fibroblastsBull Exp Biol Med200313619219510.1023/A:1026387411627<?supplied-pmid 14631508?>14631508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>50.FrancoisSMouiseddineMMathieuNSemontAMontiPDudoignonNHuman mesenchymal stem cells favour healing of the cutaneous radiation syndrome in a xenogenic transplant modelAnn Hematol2007861810.1007/s00277-006-0166-5<?supplied-pmid 17043780?>17043780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>51.LatailladeJJDoucetCBeyECarsinHHuetCClairandINew approach to radiation burn treatment by dosimetry-guided surgery combined with autologous mesenchymal stem cell therapyRegen Med2007278579410.2217/17460751.2.5.785<?supplied-pmid 17907931?>17907931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>52.BeyEPratMDuhamelPBenderitterMBrachetMTrompierFEmerging therapy for improving wound repair of severe radiation burns using local bone marrow-derived stem cell administrationsWound Repair Regen201018505810.1111/j.1524-475X.2009.00562.x<?supplied-pmid 20082681?>20082681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>53.HaoLWangJZouZYanGDongSDengJTransplantation of BMSCs expressing hPDGF-A/hBD2 promotes wound healing in rats with combined radiation-wound injuryGene Ther200916344210.1038/gt.2008.133<?supplied-pmid 18701914?>18701914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>54.MansillaEMarínGHDragoHSturlaFSalasEGardinerCBloodstream cells phenotypically identical to human mesenchymal bone marrow stem cells circulate in large amounts under the influence of acute large skin damage: new evidence for their use in regenerative medicineTransplant Proc20063896796910.1016/j.transproceed.2006.02.053<?supplied-pmid 16647520?>16647520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>55.NatsuKOchiMMochizukiYHachisukaHYanadaSYasunagaYAllogeneic bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stromal cells promote the regeneration of injured skeletal muscle without differentiation into myofibersTissue Eng2004101093111210.1089/ten.2004.10.1093<?supplied-pmid 15363167?>15363167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>56.BruderSPKurthAASheaMHayesWCJaiswalNKadiyalaSBone regeneration by implantation of purified, culture-expanded human mesenchymal stem cellsJ Orthop Res19981615516210.1002/jor.1100160202<?supplied-pmid 9621889?>9621889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>57.LiuHFanHTohSLGohJCA comparison of rabbit mesenchymal stem cells and anterior cruciate ligament fibroblasts responses on combined silk scaffoldsBiomaterials2008291443145310.1016/j.biomaterials.2007.11.023<?supplied-pmid 18155134?>18155134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>58.OrtizLAGambelliFMcBrideCGauppDBaddooMKaminskiNMesenchymal stem cell engraftment in lung is enhanced in response to bleomycin exposure and ameliorates its fibrotic effectsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20031008407841110.1073/pnas.1432929100<?supplied-pmid 12815096?>12815096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>59.ChaoYXHeBPTaySSMesenchymal stem cell transplantation attenuates blood brain barrier damage and neuroinflammation and protects dopaminergic neurons against MPTP toxicity in the substantia nigra in a model of Parkinson’s diseaseJ Neuroimmunol2009216395010.1016/j.jneuroim.2009.09.003<?supplied-pmid 19819031?>19819031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>60.SchulmanIHHareJMKey developments in stem cell therapy in cardiologyRegen Med20127172410.2217/rme.12.80<?supplied-pmid 23346572?>23346572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>61.MaYXuYXiaoZYangWZhangCSongEReconstruction of chemically burned rat corneal surface by bone marrow-derived human mesenchymal stem cellsStem Cells20062431532110.1634/stemcells.2005-0046<?supplied-pmid 16109757?>16109757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>62.OhJYKimMKShinMSLeeHJKoJHWeeWRThe anti-inflammatory and anti-angiogenic role of mesenchymal stem cells in corneal wound healing following chemical injuryStem Cells2008261047105510.1634/stemcells.2007-0737<?supplied-pmid 18192235?>18192235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>63.ParekkadanBvan PollDSuganumaKCarterEABerthiaumeFTillesAWMesenchymal stem cell-derived molecules reverse fulminant hepatic failurePLoS One20072e94110.1371/journal.pone.0000941<?supplied-pmid 17895982?>17895982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>64.TogelFHuZWeissKIsaacJLangeCWestenfelderCAdministered mesenchymal stem cells protect against ischemic acute renal failure through differentiation-independent mechanismsAm J Physiol Renal Physiol2005289F31F4210.1152/ajprenal.00007.2005<?supplied-pmid 15713913?>15713913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>65.Varney TR, Bowens CM, Eaton EB, Lehman JG: Production Methods for a Mesenchymal Stem Cell Therapeutic as a Medical Defense Countermeasure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>2012, USAMRICD-TR-12-02. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>US Army Medical Research Institute of Chemical Defense, Aberdeen Proving Ground. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>ADA558893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>66.BascianoLNemosCFoliguetBde IslaNde CarvalhoMTranNLong term culture of mesenchymal stem cells in hypoxia promotes a genetic program maintaining their undifferentiated and multipotent statusBMC Cell Biol2011121210.1186/1471-2121-12-12<?supplied-pmid 21450070?>21450070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>67.Le BlancKRasmussonISundbergBGotherstromCHassanMUzunelMTreatment of severe acute graft-versus-host disease with third party haploidentical mesenchymal stem cellsLancet20043631439144110.1016/S0140-6736(04)16104-7<?supplied-pmid 15121408?>15121408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
