<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Vet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Vet. Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Veterinary Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-6148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4189602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25266944</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">222</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-014-0222-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>First report of Toxoplasma gondii in camels (Camelus dromedarius) in Ethiopia: bioassay and seroepidemiological investigation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gebremedhin</surname><given-names>Endrias Zewdu</given-names></name><address><email>endrias.zewdu@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>Hasen Awel</given-names></name><address><email>hasewole@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tesfamaryam</surname><given-names>Gebregergs</given-names></name><address><email>t.georg24@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tessema</surname><given-names>Tesfaye Sisay</given-names></name><address><email>tesfu74@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dawo</surname><given-names>Fufa</given-names></name><address><email>dawobf@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Terefe</surname><given-names>Getachew</given-names></name><address><email>getachew_terefe@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Marco</surname><given-names>Vincenzo</given-names></name><address><email>dimarco.vince@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name><address><email>marvitus@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Veterinary Laboratory Technology, Ambo University, Faculty of Agriculture and Veterinary Sciences, P.O. Box 19, Ambo, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Animal Sciences, Faculty of Agriculture, Mizan Tepi University, P.O. Box 260, Mizan, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>College of Veterinary Medicine, Jigjiga University, P.O. Box 307, Jijiga, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Institute of Biotechnology, College of Natural and computational Sciences, Addis Ababa University, P.O. Box 1176, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>College of Veterinary Medicine and Agriculture, Addis Ababa University, P.O. Box 34, Debre Zeit, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Italian National Reference Centre for Toxoplasmosis at Istituto Zooprofilattico Sperimentale della Sicilia A. Mirri, Palermo, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>222</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Gebremedhin et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasmosis is a major public health concern in many countries of the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>A cross-sectional and follow up experimental study designs were used for seroepidemiological and bioassay studies, respectively from November 2012 to April 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The objectives were to estimate the seroprevalence of T. gondii infection, to assess risk factors and to isolate the parasite from camels in the Fentale district, Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>A direct agglutination test (DAT) and indirect enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits were used to test camel sera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Hearts and tongues (each 25 g) from 31 seropositive camels were bioassayed in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Associations between seroprevalence and potential risk factors (collected using a questionnaire survey) were analyzed using logistic regression. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>An overall T. gondii prevalence of 49.62% (220/455) by DAT and 40.49% (179/451) by indirect ELISA test were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Herd level seroprevalence of 96.77% (30/31) (95% CI: 83.30– 99.92) by DAT was recorded and it was significantly higher in areas where wild felids are present (P = 0.038). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Multivariable logistic regression showed that the likelihood of acquiring T. gondii infection was significantly higher in camels in the Ilala pastoral association [PA] (82.26%) (Adjusted Odds ratio [aOR] = 10.8; P &lt; 0.001) than camels in the Galcha PA (31.43%), in camels of ≥ 8 years old (56.52%; aOR = 1.88; P = 0,033) than camels of ≤ 4 years old (34.26%) and in areas where domestic cats are present (aOR = 4.16; P = 0.006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>All camel owners were uneducated, handle aborted fetus with bare hands, and drink raw camel milk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>DAT and ELISA tests had moderate agreement (Kappa = 0.41). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Viable T. gondii were isolated from 16.13% (5/31) of DAT positive camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>One DAT positive but ELISA negative camel sample gave a cyst positive result. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>T. gondii infection of camels in the study district is widespread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Age, presence of domestic cats and study PA are independent predictors of T. gondii seropositivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Isolation of viable parasites from edible tissues of camels and the very poor knowledge of pastoralists about toxoplasmosis suggest the need for prevention of toxoplasmosis through bio-security measures, education and further investigation to unravel the impact of camel toxoplasmosis deserves consideration. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12917-014-0222-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>T. gondii</italic></kwd><kwd>Camel</kwd><kwd>DAT</kwd><kwd>ELISA</kwd><kwd>Seroepidemiology</kwd><kwd>Bioassay</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>A population over 2.3 million camels is estimated in Ethiopia [1], which is considered the third largest camel populated country in the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>All camels in Ethiopia are owned by pastoralists [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Camels play a central role in the livelihood of pastoralists through provision of milk, meat, and draught power and they also determine their wealth and social status [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Despite their social, ecological and economic importance in Ethiopia, until recently they were neglected by researchers and development planners and as a result little is known about productivity and health problems in camels compared to other livestock [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Camels suffer from various parasitic diseases, including toxoplasmosis, which have public health and economic importance [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasmosis is caused by an intracellular Apicomplexa protozoan, T. gondii, found worldwide and in an exceptionally broad host range on earth [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Camels acquire T. gondii infection through ingestion or inhalation of sporulated oocysts that are shed by cats or wild felids in the environment [8]. The prevalence of T. gondii infection in camels varies widely depending on the localities of the world [9], ranging from 3.12% in Iran [10] to 90.90% in Turkey [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>T. gondii infects one-third of the world human population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The infection can be life threatening during pregnancy and in immunocompromised individuals [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The disease is a major public health concern in many countries of the world [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In USA, it is the third leading cause of death from foodborne diseases [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Humans become infected with T. gondii mostly by ingesting raw or undercooked meat of infected animals or by ingesting food or water contaminated with oocysts [13] and the parasite can be transmitted to the fetus by the passage of tachyzoites through the placenta [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The presence of T. gondii in milk [10] and edible tissues [16] of carrier camels indicate the possibility of transmission to humans; particularly in pastoral communities in which raw milk, and to some extent raw meat, can be frequently consumed [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Recent reports from Ethiopia indicate high seroprevalence of toxoplasmosis in women of child-bearing age ranging from 70.29 to 87.4% [18-20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Studies done in different parts of Ethiopia over the last 24 years indicated high seroprevalence of T. gondii infection in sheep [21-23], goats [21,22,24,25], cattle [21], chicken [26] and cats [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, there is no single report of T. gondii infection in Ethiopian camels so far. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Although DAT and ELISA tests have been widely used for detection of T. gondii infection in epidemiological studies, there are no reports on the comparative evaluation of the diagnostic capability of these diagnostic tests in naturally infected camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This report compares serodiagnostic methods of T. gondii infection in camels using commercial kits (DAT and ELISA), and isolation of the parasite from edible camel tissues, to estimate the seroprevalence of toxoplasmosis in camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The role of the identified risk factors on the parasite transmission is also discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Study area and study animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted in the Fentale district (39.93°E to 39°56’0”E longitude and 8.975o N to 8.58’30” N latitude) which is located in the East Shewa Zone of Oromia Regional State, Ethiopia (Figure 1) at 190 Kms East of Addis Ababa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>It lies at an altitude range of 955-2007 meters above sea level, and has an annual rainfall ranging from 560 millimeter (mm) to 630 mm and mean temperature ranging from 29°C to 38°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The vegetation comprises mix of acacia trees, bushes and shrubs that are common to the lowland areas of Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>With its arid and semi-arid climate, pastoral and agro-pastoral production systems predominate in the area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The district is estimated to possess 48, 078 camels found in eighteen pastoral associations (PAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Pastoral and agro-pastoral production systems are practiced in 11 and 7 PAs, respectively [28].Figure 1Map of the Fentale district showing sampled pastoral associations (PAs) (adapted from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.google.com.et/search?q=Ethiopia+map&amp;btnG=&amp;tbm=isch&amp;gws_rd=ssl">https://www.google.com.et/search?q=Ethiopia+map&amp;btnG=&amp;tbm=isch&amp;gws_rd=ssl</ext-link> ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The study population consisted of camels of different age groups in selected PAs of the district managed under the two production systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The camels of both sex groups were classified by age into three categories (≤4 years, 4-8 years and &gt; 8 years) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Ages of camels were recorded based on information from the owners and also estimated according to their dentations [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Study design, sample size determination and sampling method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Cross-sectional and follow up experimental study designs were used for seroepidemiological and bioassay studies, respectively from November 2012 to April 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Out of 18 PAs, a total of 6 PAs (pastoral = 3, agro-pastoral = 3) were chosen conveniently based on accessibility of the PAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Camel herds in each of the selected PAs were stratified by herd size into three: small (1-9), medium (10-19) and large (≥20) camels [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Out of 58 camel herds found in the selected study PAs (n = 6), 31 herds were randomly selected using the lottery method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Then, all camels in selected herds were used to collect blood samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Since there has been no previous study on camel toxoplasmosis in Ethiopia, 50% expected prevalence (P) and 95% confidence interval (Z = 1.96) with a 5% desired absolute precision (d) was considered to arrive at the required sample size (n = 384) for the seroepidemiological study using the formula: n = P (1-P) Z2 /d2) [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Additionally, purposive sampling of blood from 70 camels was considered for sample selection by serology in order to use their heart and tongue for bioassay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Sample collection and transportation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Blood samples for serum separation were collected from the jugular vein of apparently healthy camels using labeled plain vacutainer tubes following proper physical restraining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For the bioassay, heart, tongue and blood sample of purposively selected 70 camels, originating from Fentale district but slaughtered at Akaki abattoir near Addis Ababa, were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The collected samples were kept in an icebox containing ice packs and immediately transported to the Ethio-Belgium post-graduate research laboratory, College of Veterinary Medicine and Agriculture, Debre Zeit, Ethiopia for serological testing and isolation of T. gondii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Sera were separated by centrifugation at 3200 rpm for 10 minutes, decanted into cryovials and stored at -20°C until used for serological assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Heart and tongue samples were kept at + 4°C for 1-3 days until serological results were known. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Questionnaire survey </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A close-ended questionnaire was designed and self-administered to collect data about the potential risk factors for camels to acquire T. gondii infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Awareness of camel owners about toxoplasmosis including the habits of consumption of raw camel meat and milk was also documented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The questions in the questionnaire included sex (male, female), age (≤4 years, 4-8 years and &gt; 8 years), production system (pastoral/agropastoral), presence of cats (yes/no), presence of wild felids (yes/no), source of drinking water (tap, stagnant: [lake, pond and well], river, mixed [river and stagnant]) and herd size (small:1-9, medium:10-19, large: ≥ 20 camels) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Information about history of abortion (yes/no), way of handling aborted fetus (wearing gloves, without wearing glove, washing hand after handling, without washing hand after handling) and method of disposal of aborted fetus (giving to cat, throwing along the way, burying) were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Moreover, camel owners consumption habits of camel meat (cooking, without cooking, both) and raw milk consumption (yes/no), educational level (uneducated, primary school, secondary school, tertiary/university) and awareness about: toxoplasmosis (yes/no), role of cat to transmit diseases to owner (yes/no), role of cat to transmit diseases to camel (yes/no) and camel migration (yes/no) and routes of migration were also gathered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Laboratory investigation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Direct agglutination test (DAT) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All sera samples collected were examined for the presence of antibodies (IgG) against T. gondii by the direct agglutination test (Toxo screen DA, biomerieux®, France) following the protocol of the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The kit was claimed by the manufacturer to have sensitivity and specificity of 96.22% and 98.80%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Sera were assayed at a screening dilution of 1:40 and 1:4000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A titer of 1:40 or 1:4000 or both was considered indicative of T. gondii exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Sedimentation of antigen at the bottom of the well and clear agglutination above half of the well at either dilution were recorded as negative and positive results respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>DAT positive samples were titrated to know the endpoint titer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Positive and negative controls were included in each test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Indirect enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A total of 451 (381 from field and 70 from abattoir) sera were tested for T. gondii IgG antibodies by the indirect ELISA kit (ID VET Innovative Diagnostic, ID Screen®, Montpellier, France) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The wells of the kit are coated with T. gondii P30 (SAG1) surface antigen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The kit uses non-species specific protein conjugate that is used in several animal species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>For interpretation of the result S/P% was calculated as: S/P% = (optical density [OD] 450 value of the sample – OD 450 value of the negative control)/(mean OD 450 value of the positive control – OD 450 value of the negative control) × 100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Any sample with S/P% ≤ 40%, 40% - 50% and ≥ 50% were considered as negative, doubtful and positive, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>With this cut-off the manufacturer claims the test to have more than 99% specificity and sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The test was considered valid if the mean OD value of the positive control (ODPC) is greater than 0.350 (ODPC &gt; 0.350) and the ratio of the mean OD value of the positive and negative controls (ODPC and ODNC) is greater than 3.5 (ODPC/ODNC &gt; 3.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The doubtful sera were retested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Bioassay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Heart and tongue tissue samples (pooled weight 50 g) from DAT positive camels (n = 31) slaughtered at Akaki abattoir, were processed for isolation of T. gondii as described previously [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Briefly, each sample was cut into small pieces, homogenized in a blender for 30 seconds, followed by soaking in 125 ml of saline solution for another 30 seconds (0.14 M sodium chloride). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>After homogenization 250 ml of pepsin solution (Merck KG.A, Darmstadt, Germany) was added (pH = 1.1–1.2) and incubated at 37°C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The homogenate was filtered through two layers of gauze and centrifuged at 3200 rpm for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was discarded and to the sediment 15 to 20 ml of 1.2% sodium bicarbonate (pH = 8.3) was added and centrifuged at 3200 rpm for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was discarded and the sediment was re-suspended in 5 to 10 ml of antibiotic saline solution (1000 U/ml penicillin and 100 μg of streptomycin/ml of saline solution). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The suspension was inoculated intraperitoneally (1 ml per mouse) into five apparently healthy T. gondii seronegative female Swiss-Albino mice (National Veterinary Institute, Debre Zeit) per sample (weighting 25–35 g) as described by Dubey [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Bioassays were performed within 1-3 days of the slaughter of the camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Separate knives, cutting boards, gloves, plastic cups/falcon tubes, and plastic bags for blending and pepsin digestion were used for each sample to avoid contamination among samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Tissue homogenate kept in 6 falcon tubes (50 ml) were centrifuged in 2 steps; the first and second batch in 4 and 2 floating buckets of the centrifuge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Approximately 110-140 minutes elapsed from the time the tissue was homogenized in saline to the time the material was pulled into syringes for mouse inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The inoculated mice were observed daily for illness for 60 days and information on number of survivors, dead, day of death, symptoms, and weight (initial and final) were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The mice were fed with pelleted feed and municipal chlorinated water ad-libitum. T. gondii isolate was considered as virulent if 100% mortality of mouse was observed within four weeks of infection [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Surviving mice were bled on day 60 after anesthetizing with di-ethyl ether (Biolab laboratories ltd, Israel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Brains of all mice were removed by sagittal dissection and then examined for tissue cysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The inoculated mice were considered infected with T. gondii when tissue cysts were found in brain tissues and/or the sera of mice react positively for the commercial DAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The brain was homogenized in 1 ml phosphate buffer saline (PBS) by using a mortar and pestle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The numbers of cysts in five aliquots of each 10 μl were counted under microscope with a 10 × and 40 × objective lens and summed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The total number of cysts in the brain of each mouse was determined by multiplying the number of cysts in the 50 μl sample examined with the dilution factor [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Data management and analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The data generated from field and laboratory investigations were entered and coded using Microsoft Excel® 2007 and analyzed using STATA version 11.0 for Windows (Stata Corp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>College Station, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistic was used to summarize the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The information from the questionnaire survey was used to define explanatory variables to be tested in a logistic regression model, for any assessment of association between the serological status of the camels (dependent variable) and the risk factors (independent variables). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Initially, all risk factors were individually screened by cross-tabulation for association with the likelihood of T. gondii infection using Chi-squared analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Non-collinear variables, with P-value &lt; 0.25 in the univariable analysis, were entered into the multivariable logistic regression model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>During the analyses the clustering nature of the outcome within a herd was considered by including herd as a clustering variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This enabled us to use a clustered sandwich estimator i.e., robust standard error rather than the standard error of the parameters estimated using maximum likelihood method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The results of the logistic regression for each variable were expressed as P-value and odds ratio (OR) with 95% confidence intervals to measure the strength of associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The seroprevalence results of DAT and ELISA tests were compared using the Chi-squared test and their concordance was determined by calculating the Kappa index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Using DAT as a reference test, the diagnostic sensitivity (Se), specificity (Sp), positive predictive value (PPV) and negative predictive value (NPV) of ELISA were calculated and interpreted following the recommendations of Dohoo et al. [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>A student t-test was employed to assess the mean weight difference between seropositive and seronegative mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered significant when P ≤ 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Ethical considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This research project was approved by the animal ethical committee of the College of Veterinary Medicine and Agriculture, Addis Ababa University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>All efforts were made to minimize animal suffering during the course of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Informed written consents were obtained from all camel owners who participated in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Animal level seroprevalence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>An overall T. gondii prevalence of 49.62% (220/455) by DAT and 40.49% (179/451) by indirect ELISA test were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Out of the 218 DAT positive sera, 16 (7.34%) were negative at 1:40 dilution but positive at 1:4000 dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The serum samples collected from the abattoir were excluded from risk factor assessment because of missing information for most variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant difference in seroprevalence was observed between studied PAs with the highest and lowest seroprevalence recorded from Ilala (82.26%) and Galcha (31.43%) PAs, respectively (P = 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The seroprevalence was also significantly different between age groups (P = 0.002), herd sizes (P = 0.011) and history of abortion (P = 0.003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>However, there was no statistically significant difference in seroprevalence between males and females (P = 0.757) and pastoral and agro-pastoral production systems (P = 0.683; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Using ELISA, the PA (P = 0.003) and history of abortion (P = 0.038) were significantly associated with seropositivity (see Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Of the seropositive samples 73.8% (138/187) had DAT end titer of ≥ 6000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The DAT end titer of the seropositive camels (n = 187) is shown in Figure 2.Table 1 T. gondii seroprevalence in camels of the Fentale district, stratified by explanatory variables as detected by DAT  Variable  Categories  No. tested  No. positive  % seroprevalence  Chi-square  P -value PAGalcha351131.4338.8441&lt;0.001 Tuttuti2118640.76Saraweba381744.74Garafafate10550.00Turo291758.62Ilala625182.26Total38518748.34SexFemale20910047.850.09610.757Male1768749.43Age≤4 yrs1083734.2612.61900.002 4-8 yrs1859852.97&gt;8 yrs925256.52PsPastoral30814848.050.16640.683Agro-pastoral773950.65HsSmall853945.889.06750.011 Medium1739856.65Large1275039.37AbortionNo1989045.458.62840.003 Yes111090.91StillbirthNo2079847.342.20110.138Yes22100.00NNMNo100.000.92180.337Yes20810048.08PA = pastoral association, Hs = herd size, Ps = production system, NNM = neonatal mortality, P-values of statistically significant variables were highlighted in bold; No. = number.Figure 2 DAT end titer of seropositive camels (n = 183).  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Herd level seroprevalence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Out of 31 camel herds examined, 30 (96.77%) (95% CI: 83.30– 99.92) and 29 (93.55%) (95% CI: 78.58– 99.21) herds were seropositive by the DAT and ELISA test, respectively (i.e., contain at least one seropositive camel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Using DAT, herd level seroprevalence of T. gondii infection was not significantly associated with PAs (P = 0.372), production system (P = 0.170), herd size (P = 0.576), history of abortion (P = 0.549) and presence of domestic cats (P = 0.549). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>However, there was significant association between herd seroprevalence and presence of wild felids (P = 0.038; Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Using ELISA, herd level seroprevalence was not associated with the studied variables except neonatal mortality (see Additional file 1: Table S2).Table 2 Herd level seroprevalence of T. gondii infection in camels of the Fentale district as detected by DAT  Variable  Categories  No. tested  No. positive  % seroprevalence  Chi-square  P -value PAGalcha441005.37330.372Tuttuti1111100Saraweba5480Garafafate22100Turo44100Ilala55100PsPastoral20201001.87880.170Agro-pastoral111090.91HsSmall151493.331.0220.576Medium1111100Large55100AbortionYes881000.35940.549No232195.65StillbirthYes331000.11070.739No282796.43NNMYes221000.07130.790No292896.55CatYes881000.35940.549No232295.65WfYes25251004.30560.038 No6583.33RiverYes2929100--PA = pastoral association, Hs = herd size, Ps = production system, Wf = presence of wild felids, NNM = neonatal mortality, No. = number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Risk factors for T. gondii seropositivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Univariable logistic regression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Epidemiological risk factors for acquiring T. gondii between DAT seroreactive and nonreactive camels were compared using univariable logistic regression analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>During the statistical analysis the first level/category (with lowest seroprevalence) of each independent variable was used as the reference category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The results showed that sex, herd size and production system had no significant association with T. gondii seropositivity of the camels (P &gt; 0.05) while study area, age, history of abortion, presence of domestic cats and presence of wild felids were found to be significantly associated with T. gondii infection (P &lt; 0.05) (Table 3).Table 3 Animal level Logistic regression analysis of predictors of T. gondii infection in Camels as detected by DAT  Variable  Category  No. of positive/tested (%)  Univariable  Multivariable  OR (95% CI)  P  OR (95% CI)  P PAGalcha11/35 (31.43)11-Tuttuti86/211 (40.75)1.5 (0.58-3.88)0.4021.55 (0.60-3.99)0.367Saraweba17/38 (44.74)1.77 (0.45-6.97)0.4171.5 (0.63-3.58)0.357Garafafate5/10 (50)2.18 (0.87-5.45)0.0950.6 3 (0.17-2.33)0.487Turo17/29 (58.62)3.1 (.77-12.34)0.1101.06 (.23-4.94)0.940Ilala51/62 (82.26)10.11 (4.3-24.21)&lt;0.001 10.8 (4.83-24.17)&lt;0.001 SexFemale100/209 (47.85)1Male87/176 (49.43)1.06 (0.70-1.62)0.767Age≤4 yrs37/108 (34.26)11-4-8 yrs98/185 (52.97)2.16 (1.28-3.64) 0.004 1.73 (0.99-3.02)0.053&gt;8 yrs52/92( 56.52)2.49 (1.34-4.65) 0.004 1.88 (1.05-3.37)0.033 Ps1 Pastoral148/308 (48.05)1Agro-pastoral39/77 (50.65)1.12 (0.46-2.64)0.814CatNo173/305 (43.28)11-Yes55/80 (68.75)2.88 (1.28-6.47) 0.010 4.16 (1.49-11.61)0.006 Wf2 No18/80 (22.5)11-Yes169/305 (55.41)4.28 (2.40-7.63) &lt;0.001 2.04 (0.86-4.83)0.104AbortionNo90/198 (45.45)11-Yes10/11 (90.91)12.0 (1.25-114.96) 0.031 9.23 (0.8-107.05)0.075Hs3 Small39/85 (45.88)1Medium98/173 (56.65)1.54 (0.59-4.01)0.376Large50/127 (39.37)0.76 (0.26-2.29)0.633 1Production system, 2Wild felids, 3Herd size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Multivariable logistic regression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Stillbirth and neonatal mortality were not included in the multivariable model due to collinearity with abortion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Five variables (study area [PAs], age, abortion, exposure to domestic and wild cats) that presented P-value &lt; 0.25 in the univariable analysis, were subjected to the multivariable regression model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The analysis showed a significant association between T. gondii seropositivity and study area (PAs) (P = 0.0001), age (P = 0.033) and the presence of domestic cats (P = 0.006; Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The results of the logistic regression analysis based on the results of the ELISA were presented as Additional file 1: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Camel owners food habit and awareness about toxoplasmosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>All (100%) camel owners who responded to the questionnaire survey were uneducated pastoralists, had no awareness about T. gondii, toxoplasmosis and its transmission to humans through raw meat and raw milk consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Camel meat consumption habit showed that 67.7% consume cooked meat and the rest (32.3%) consume either cooked or uncooked meat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>All respondents (100%) consume raw camel milk, handle aborted fetus with bare hands (no protection) and don’t wash their hands after handling aborted fetus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, none of the camel owners bury or burn aborted materials; rather they simply dispose of by throwing it in the field. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Comparison of seroprevalence results of DAT and ELISA tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Overall, the 451 serum samples were tested by both DAT and ELISA kits for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>A total agreement between the two tests was obtained on 132 positive samples (29.27%) and 186 (41.24%) negative samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>But 86 sera were positive only by DAT test and 47 sera were positive only by ELISA test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the two test results indicated that seropositivity differed significantly between the two kits (χ2 = 76.714, P &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, Kappa analysis demonstrated that the two tests had a moderate agreement in detecting T. gondii infection in camels (70.51% agreement, Kappa = 0.41; P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>By considering DAT as a reference test, the sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values of ELISA was calculated as 60.55%, 79.83%, and 73.74% and 68.38%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Bioassay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Of the 70 camel sera from the abattoir, 33 (47.1%) (95% CI: 35.09-59.45) and 29 (41.43%) (95% CI: 29.77-53.83) were IgG seropositive using DAT and ELISA, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Viable T. gondii cysts were isolated from 5 of 31 DAT seropositive bioassayed camels (16.13%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Out of the 31 DAT positive sera, 22 were positive for ELISA and one ELISA negative camel sample gave a cyst positive result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>For two seropositive camel samples, isolation of the parasite was not possible because of the death of all of the inoculated mice within a day of inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>On day 60 post-inoculation, out of 108 mice that survived, 22 (20.4%) were seropositive for T. gondii infection (i.e., out of 31 camel samples, 10 (32.3%) gave a seropositive result on mice). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Viable cysts were isolated in mice from 5 tissue samples from the camels (on 5 seropositive and 1 seronegative mice) (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>It was not possible to detect cysts from 17 of the seropositive mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Eleven out of 108 survived mice showed loss of weight (10.2%), of which 9 and 2 mice were seropositive and seronegative, respectively, i.e., 40.9% (9/22) of seropositive and 2.3% (2/86) of seronegative mice showed loss of weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The mean weight change between seropositive (infected, mean = 0.25 g ± 6.58) and seronegative (non-infected, mean = 5.55 g ± 3.41) mice was significantly different (P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The mean cyst count per mouse brain was 46.5 (range: 28 – 88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>One mouse that showed neurological signs (hind quarter paralysis, torticollis) and tachypnoea on day 20 post-inoculation became cyst negative but seropositive.Table 4 Isolation of T. gondii from naturally infected seropositive camels of East Shewa Zones, Central Ethiopia  Camel no.  Sex  Age group  DAT screening  Mice with cyst/examined (n)  Mice seropositive/examined (n)  Days of mice death PI (no. of mice dead) H1M≥8 Yrs1/400/50/5H2M≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/50/5H4M4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40001/50/5H6M≥8 Yrs1/400/30/31(1), 2(1)H9M≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40002/55/5H11M4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/40/41(3)H15F≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/30/32(3)H19M≥8 Yrs1/401/51/5H20M≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40001/55/5H23M≤ 4 Yrs1/40000/31/32(2)H25M≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40001/33/32(2)H28F≤ 4 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/43/41(2)H30F≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/11/14(1)H33,H43F≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/50/5H39M≥8 Yrs1/40000/50/5H44F4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/51/5H45F4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/41/41(1)H55F≤ 4 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/30/31(2)H56,H60,H65F4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/50/5H63F4-8 Yrs1/40000/50/5H59M4-8 Yrs1/40000/40/42(2)H61,H64F4-8 Yrs1/40000/40/42(1),2(1)H62F4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/40/41(1)H66F≤ 4 Yrs1/40000/51/5H67F≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/40/42(1)H68M4-8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/30/31(2), 1(3)H69F≥8 Yrs1/40 &amp; 1/40000/10/14(1) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec22" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec23"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Overall seroprevalence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>We report for the first time evidence for T. gondii infection and its seroprevalence, risk factors and bioassay results in Ethiopian camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>An estimated overall seroprevalence of 49.623% by DAT and 40.49% by ELISA tests were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Seventy-four percent of seropositive camels (from field samples) had DAT end titer of ≥ 6000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This might indicate actively circulating, recently acquired or recrudescence of previously acquired T. gondii infection in camels of the study area due to climatic stress, malnutrition and prevalent diseases like trypanosomosis [36] which reduce the animals’ resistance [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the seropositive sera that became negative at 1:40 but positive at 1:4000 dilutions (7.34%, 16/218) indicate prozone phenomenon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Presence of viable T. gondii cysts in 16.13% (5/31) of camels slaughtered for human consumption is definitive diagnosis of natural T. gondii infection and suggests the potential transmission of toxoplasmosis to humans through consumption of raw or undercooked camel meat or offal such as the liver which is commonly consumed by pastoralists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Considering the lower human population density (hence possibly lower domestic cat density), the arid and semi-arid climate of the Fentale district, which is hostile for the survival of oocysts in the environment, and the browsing habit of camel feeding (hence lower risk of acquiring T. gondii oocysts from the ground), the high seroprevalence found in the present study was not to our expectation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Recently, a relatively lower seroprevalence of T. gondii in goats (15.37%) [25] and in sheep (13.36%) [23] was reported from the same district. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>However, the high seroprevalence in camels of the current study in our opinion might be a function of cumulative effect of the age of camels [38] related to absence of regular culling programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the migration of camels to midland areas in search of feed, the poor veterinary service, inadequate attention by government, local change in landownership and increased farming [5] - which necessitate cat keeping to control rodents, might have additionally contributed to the high prevalence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The present seroprevalence (48.34%) is in close agreement with the 51.3% and 46% - 54.2% seroprevalence reported from Sudan [39] and Egypt [40,41], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>As compared to the present finding, much higher seroprevalence has been reported from Turkey (90.9%) and Sudan (67%) by Utuk et al. [11] and Elamin et al. [8], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Lower seroprevalence was recorded earlier from Iran 3.12% [10], Saudi Arabia 6.5% [42], 16% [43], 13.1% [44], Sudan (20%) [45], United Arab Emirates (22.4%) [46] and Egypt (17.4 - 31.4%) [9,47,48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The variation in seroprevalence between the present study and aforementioned African and Arabian countries might be due to the difference in density of cats and wild felids, climatic conditions [13], farming and management practices [49], sample size [45], cut-off values and sensitivity difference in the serological tests employed [13,42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Risk factors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Assessment of the association of T. gondii seroprevalence with potential risk factors was made with the aim of identifying factors relevant for prevention of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, using the results of DAT, a multivariable logistic regression model revealed that study PA (P = 0.001), exposure to domestic cats (P = 0.006) and age of the camels (P = 0.033) were found to be independent predictors of T. gondii seropositivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, only study PA (P = 0.006) and exposure to domestic cats (P = 0.011) were found to be independent predictors of T. gondii seropositivity using results of ELISA (see Additional file 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>This suggests that DAT is a more preferred test for assessing the risk factors in camels than ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Camels from Ilala PA (82.26%) are 10.8 times more likely to be seropositive than camels of Galcha PA (31.43%) [P &lt; 0.001]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The observed difference in seroprevalence across PAs could be due to differences in the age of camels sampled [50], the sample size [44], the degree of environmental contamination [13] and the frequency of exposure to risk factors [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The seroprevalence of T. gondii infection was higher in camels older than 8 years (OR = 2.49, 95% CI: 1.34, 4.65) as compared to camels ≤ 4 years old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Thus, the probability of T. gondii infection in camels increases as the age of the animal increases suggesting postnatal infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The high seroprevalence in older camels than young camels might be due to the higher likelihood of exposure of older camels to any one of the risk factors to acquire T. gondii infection [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This finding is in harmony with the studies conducted in Saudi Arabia [8,43] who reported a higher seroprevalence in adult than young camels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The univariable logistic regression showed that the odds of being infected by T. gondii infection was higher in aborted camels than non-aborted camels (OR = 12, 95% CI: 1.25, 114.95; P = 0.031) and in areas where the presence of wild felids was reported (OR = 4.28, 95% CI: 2.40, 7.63; P &lt; 0.001) than in their absence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>However, these variables were not independent predictors of seropositivity in the final logistic regression model (P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The high seroprevalence in aborted camels is consistent with biological features of T. gondii in sheep, goats and pigs. T. gondii has been reported as an important cause of abortion in Bacterian camels [53] and in zoo camels in USA [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>There was no statistically significant sex-linked difference in seroprevalence between male (49.43%; 95% CI: 42.0, 56.86) and female (47.85%; 95% CI: 41.0, 54.65) camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with studies in dromedaries of Sudan [8], Saudi Arabia [43] and bactrian camels of China [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Bioassay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>As far as the bioassay result is concerned, tissue cysts were isolated from 16.13% (5∕31) of DAT positive camels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Bradyzoite tissue cysts were detected by microscopy in 22.73% (5/22) of DAT positive mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This lower rate of detection of cyst by microscopy might be due to the low number of cysts in camel tissue and the low sensitivity of microscopy [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Cyst count has also been reported to vary depending on the virulence of T. gondii strain and number of passages in the mice [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Previously, viable tissue cysts have been isolated in cats from naturally infected camels in Saudi Arabia [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>It has also been reported that the success of isolation of T. gondii cysts as well as the number of tissue cysts produced vary considerably with the intermediate hosts, being higher in sheep, goats and pigs [49,57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The number of isolated tissue cysts ranged from 25 to 88 per brain of mice, which is low compared to the number of cysts/mouse brain isolated from sheep and goats of the same district (Gebremedhin et al., unpublished). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>More sensitive methods like PCR might detect the DNA of tissue cysts in the brain of seropositive mice presently reported perhaps as false negative due to the small volume of brain homogenate examined (50 μl), lower sensitivity of microscopy and the possible low burden of viable cysts in tissue of camels [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Even though detection of brain cysts was not possible, manifestations of tachypnoea and neurological signs by a mouse on day 20 post-inoculation might indicate the more virulent nature of the strain [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The death of mice in less than 3 days following i.p. inoculation was attributed to septic peritonitis that resulted from bacterial contamination of isolates or unintended puncturing of the intestine or other vital organs [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Comparison of seroprevalence results of DAT and ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the diagnosis of T. gondii infection of camels by DAT and ELISA showed moderate agreement (Kappa = 0.41, P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We think that the discrepancies between the results of DAT and ELISA might be ascribed to the difference in the sensitivity and specificity of the tests in camel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>DAT is more sensitive than ELISA which is in accordance with findings of Dubey [58] and Shaapan et al. [59] who reported DAT as the most sensitive test among all serological tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>It has also been reported that test performances may vary when applied on different animal species [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>For example, as opposed to our finding, Zhu et al. [61] from Beijing, China, reported significantly high T. gondii seroprevalence by ELISA (34.7%) as compared to DAT (23.1%, cut-off:1:25) in dogs (high degree of agreement, Kappa = 0.644), while no significant difference between the two tests was reported in the case of cats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The P30 ELISA test we used in the current study employs non-species specific conjugate and was recommended by the manufacturer to detect anti-T. gondii antibodies in ruminant, cat or pig sera, plasma or meat juice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>However, literature with regards to validation of this kit for camels was not accessible; consequently comparison of our results with others couldn’t be made possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, isolation of viable cysts from four of five camels positive by ELISA (out of ten camel tissues positive by bioassay using DAT, seven were also ELISA positive) coupled with the relatively higher specificity (79.83%) and PPV (73.74%) of ELISA in the present study, suggests the usefulness of the P30 ELISA test in epidemiological studies of camel toxoplasmosis particularly among highly disease prevalent populations and in instances of abortion storms [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Although in the present study DAT is more sensitive than ELISA, the subjective nature and longer waiting time before reading the results might limit widespread and large scale usage of DAT for epidemiological studies [61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Camel owners’ food habit and awareness about toxoplasmosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>From the questionnaire data it was evident that all of the respondents were uneducated and have a very poor knowledge of T. gondii and its mode of transmission between animals, to humans and the role of felids in the epidemiology of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The lack of knowledge about the disease is one of the main risk factors exposing individuals to the disease, as all of them drink raw camel milk and 32.3% responded that they eat either cooked or raw camel meat. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Human cases of toxoplasmosis have previously been linked directly to the consumption of raw goat’s milk [63] and camel milk [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Recently, T. gondii tachyzoites have been detected from milk of naturally infected camels in Iran using ELISA, PCR, cell culture and cat bioassay [10] and from experimentally infected camels in Sudan [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The high seropositivity and moderately high rate of isolation of viable tissue cysts from edible organs in the current study might be of great public health significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>This is due to the deep rooted habit of consumption of raw camel milk, offal (liver) and to a lesser extent, meat by the pastoral communities of the study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the absence of precautions in handling aborted materials and poor knowledge of pastoralists about toxoplasmosis and the role of cats in the transmission of the disease are additional suggestive evidences for the spread of toxoplasmosis to humans and among camels in the study district. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In the absence of a vaccine for camels and the difficulty in changing the pastoral extensive livestock management system to intensive management to reduce the prevalence of the disease, prevention of the disease through education of pastoralists remains a better alternative and perhaps a more economically feasible option to combat the disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The limitations of the current study include interviewee recall bias, the relatively small number of camels considered for bioassay and the inability to genotype the isolates due to a shortage of resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Further studies to improve the sensitivity and specificity of ELISA for diagnosis of toxoplasmosis in camels are required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec28" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>T. gondii infection of camels in the study district is widespread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Age, presence of domestic cats and study PA are independent predictors of T. gondii seropositivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Isolation of viable parasites from edible tissues of camels and the very poor knowledge of pastoralists about toxoplasmosis, suggest that people are at a higher risk of acquiring T. gondii infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Therefore, prevention of toxoplasmosis through biosecurity measures, education of pastoralists about the identified risks and further investigation to unravel the economic and public health implications of the high prevalence of T. gondii in the area deserves consideration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec29"><title>Additional file</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12917_2014_222_MOESM1_ESM.doc" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>containing results of analysis based on ELISA for animal level seroprevalence, Table S2. herd level seroprevalence and Table S3. logistic regression analysis of predictors of seropositivity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contribution </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>EZG conceived and designed the proposal, participated in the coordination and management of the study, collected, tested and analyzed the data and drafted the article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>HAY participated in sample collection, laboratory testing and drafting of article with inputs from GT, GT and FD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>TST, MV and V di M participated in the study design and edition of article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The financial support of Oromia Regional State Rural Capacity Building, Addis Ababa University (sub-thematic project-investigation on major camel diseases in Ethiopia and development of intervention strategies), VLIR-UOS project no. “ZEIN 2010 PR 372 “promotion of the PhD program in veterinary public health at the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine”, Belgium, the Italian National Reference Centre for Toxoplasmosis at the Istituto Zooprofilattico Sperimentale della Sicilia A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Mirri, Italy and partial financial support to Maria Vitale grant No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>RF 2007/RC 2009 from Italian Ministry of Health are highly acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Staff members of ID VET Innovative Diagnostic, Montpellier, France, are highly acknowledged for testing of camel sera using ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to extend their gratitude to the camel owners (pastoralists) and abattoir workers for their collaboration in the sampling and supplying information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The authors also wish to thank Mrs Philippa Woble for editing the language of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>1.CSA (Central Statistics Agency)Agricultural Sample Survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Report on livestock and livestock characteristics of private and peasant holdings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>II, Statistical Bulletin 4462009Addis Ababa, EthiopiaCentral Statistical Agency, Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>2.MOA (Ministry of Agriculture)Animal Census Report, Rep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>52000Addis Ababa, EthiopiaMinistry of Agriculture, Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>3.FAOProduction Yearbook, Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>562002RomeFood and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>4.DawoFMysterious mortality in camels (Camelus dromedarius) in Borana, Ethiopia: evidence of its association with reproductive age groupsRev Sci Tech201029621628<?supplied-pmid 21309459?>21309459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>5.MegersaBAn epidemiological study of major camel diseases in the Boran lowland, southern Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>DCG report No. 582010Oslo, NorwayDrylands Coordination Group151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>6.ParsaniHRSinghVMominRRCommon parasitic diseases of camelVet World20081317318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>7.BoothroydJCGriggMEPopulation biology of Toxoplasma gondii and its relevance to human infectionCurr Opin Microbiol2002543844210.1016/S1369-5274(02)00349-1<?supplied-pmid 12160866?>12160866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>8.ElaminEAEliasSDaugschiesARommelMPrevalence of Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in pastoral camels (Camelus dromedarius) in the Butana plains, mid-eastern SudanVet Parasitol19924317117510.1016/0304-4017(92)90158-6<?supplied-pmid 1413449?>1413449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>9.ShaapanRMFathia KhalilAMEvaluation of different Toxoplasma gondii isolates as antigens used in the modified agglutination test for the detection of toxoplasmosis in camels and donkeysAm-Eurasian J Agr Environ Sci200820083837841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>10.DehkordiFSRahimiEAbdizadihRDetection of Toxoplasma gondii in raw caprine, ovine, buffalo, bovine, and camel milk using cell cultivation, cat bioassay, capture ELISA, and PCR methods in IranFoodborne Pathog Dis20131012012510.1089/fpd.2012.1311<?supplied-pmid 23441913?>23441913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>11.UtukAEKirbasABaburCBalkayaIDetection of Toxoplasma gondii antibodies and some helminthic parasites in camels from Nevsehir province of TurkeyIsr J Vet Med2012201267106108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>12.MontoyaJGLiesenfeldOToxoplasmosisLancet20043631965197610.1016/S0140-6736(04)16412-X<?supplied-pmid 15194258?>15194258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>13.DubeyJPToxoplasmosis of Animals and Humans20102Boca Raton, FloridaCRC Press1239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>14.ElsheikhaMHAzabSMAbousamraKNRahbarHMElghannamMDRaafatDSeroprevalence of and risk factors for Toxoplasma gondii antibodies among asymptomatic blood donors in EgyptJ Parasitol20091041471147610.1007/s00436-009-1350-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>15.PetersenEToxoplasmosisSemin Fetal Neonatal Med20071221422310.1016/j.siny.2007.01.011<?supplied-pmid 17321812?>17321812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>16.HilaliMFataniAAl-AtiyaSIsolation of tissue cysts of Toxoplasma, Isospora, Hammondia and Sarcocystis (Camelus dromedarius) from camel meat in Saudi ArabiaVet Parasitol19955835335610.1016/0304-4017(94)00727-T<?supplied-pmid 8533274?>8533274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>17.MuksinSHailuDMotiYInfection rates, cyst fertility and larval viability of hydatid disease in camels (Camelus dromedarius) from Borena, Kereyu and Harar EthiopiaGlobal Veterinaria20117518522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>18.ZemeneEDelenasawYSolomonATarikuBAbdiSAhmedZSeroprevalence of Toxoplasma gondii and associated risk factors among pregnant women in Jimma town, Southwestern EthiopiaBMC Infect Dis20121233724310.1186/1471-2334-12-337<?supplied-pmid 23216887?>23216887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>19.GebremedhinEZAbebeAHTessemaTSTulluKDMedhinGVitaleMDi MarcoVCoxEDornyPSeroepidemiology of Toxoplasma gondii infection in women of child-bearing age in central EthiopiaBMC Infect Dis20131310111010.1186/1471-2334-13-101<?supplied-pmid 23442946?>23442946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>20.WalleFNigatuKAsterTTesfuKSeroprevalence and risk factors for Toxoplasmosis in HIV infected and non-infected individuals in Bahir Dar, Northwest EthiopiaParasites Vectors20136152310.1186/1756-3305-6-15<?supplied-pmid 23324409?>23324409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>21.BekeleTKasaliOBToxoplasmosis in sheep, goats and cattle in central EthiopiaVet Res Commun19891337137510.1007/BF00346069<?supplied-pmid 2588477?>2588477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>22.NegashTTilahunGPattonSPrévotFDorchiesPSerological survey on Toxoplasmosis in sheep and goats in Nazareth, EthiopiaRev Méd Vét2004155486487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>23.GebremedhinEZAgonafirATessemaTSTilahunGMedhinGVitaleMDi MarcoVCoxEVercruysseJDornyPSeroepidemiological study of ovine toxoplasmosis in East and West Shewa Zones of Oromia Regional State, Central EthiopiaBMC Vet Res2013911710.1186/1746-6148-9-117<?supplied-pmid 23768427?>23768427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>24.TeshaleSDumetreADardeMLMergaBDorchiesPSerological survey of toxoplasmosis in Ethiopia: Prevalence and risk factorsParasite20071415515910.1051/parasite/2007142155<?supplied-pmid 17645188?>17645188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>25.ZewduEAgonafirATessemaTSTilahunGMedhinGVitaleMDi MarcoVCoxEVercruysseJDornyPSeroepidemiological study of caprine toxoplasmosis in East and West Shewa Zones, Oromia Regional State, Central EthiopiaRes Vet Sci201394434810.1016/j.rvsc.2012.07.020<?supplied-pmid 22874923?>22874923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>26.TilahunGTiaoNFerreiraLROliveiraSVermaSKKwokOCHMollaBSavilleWJAMedhinGKassaTAlemeHGebreyesWADubeyJPSeroprevalence of Toxoplasma gondii from free-range chicken (Gallus domesticus) from Addis Ababa, EthiopiaJ Parasitol20139974074110.1645/12-25.1<?supplied-pmid 23259902?>23259902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>27.TiaoNDarringtonCMollaBSavilleWJATilahunGKwokOCHGebreyesWALappinMRJonesJLDubeyJPAn investigation into the seroprevalence of Toxoplasma gondii, Bartonella spp. feline immunodeficiency virus (FIV), and feline leukemia virus (FelV) cats from Addis AbabaEpidemiol Infect20131411029103310.1017/S0950268812001707<?supplied-pmid 22857007?>22857007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>28.ESZPEDO (East Shoa Zone Plan and Economic Development Office): Socio- Economic on East Shewa Zone. Oromia Regional State: 2011:1–105. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>29.AmeenMAAhmedMAParatuberculosis in Camel (Camelus dromedarius): The diagnostic efficiency of ELISA and PCROpen Vet Sci J20104414410.2174/1874318801004010041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>30.Camels Australia Export, Age: Determined by Dentition. Central Australian Camel Industry Association Inc (CACIA), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Camelsaust.com">http://www.Camelsaust.com</ext-link> Accessed on October 9, 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>31.OmerMBekeleMRahmetoAMeseleAAlemayehuRYunusASolomonMSeroprevalence of brucellosis in camels in and around Dire Dawa city, Eastern EthiopiaJ Anim Vet Adv2011101177118310.3923/javaa.2011.1177.1183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>32.ThrusfieldMVeterinary Epidemiology20073Oxford, UKBlackwell Science Ltd252266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>33.PenaHFGennariSMDubeyJPSuCPopulation structure and mouse virulence of Toxoplasma gondii in BrazilInt J Parasitol20083856156910.1016/j.ijpara.2007.09.004<?supplied-pmid 17963770?>17963770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>34.FritzHBarBPackhamAMelliAConradPAMethods to produce and safely work with large number of Toxoplasma gondii oocyst and bradyzoite cystJ Microbiol Method201288475210.1016/j.mimet.2011.10.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>35.DohooIMartinWStryhnHVeterinary Epidemiologic Research2003CanadaAVS Inc521539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>36.KassaTEqualeTChakaHPrevalence of camel trypanosomosis and its vectors in Fentale district, South East Shoa Zone, EthiopiaVet Arhiv201181611621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>37.RadostitsOMGayCCHinchcliffKWConstablePDVeterinary Medicine: A textbook of the diseases of cattle, horses, sheep, pigs and goats200610LondonSaunders15181522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>38.TenterAMToxoplasma gondii in animals used for human consumptionMem Inst Oswald Cruz200910436436910.1590/S0074-02762009000200033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>39.ManalYIMaijidAMAssociation of diarrhea with congenital toxoplasmosis in calf-camel (Camelus dromedarius)Int J Trop Med200831011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>40.DerbalaAAZayedAATawfikMAPrevalence of Toxoplasma antibodies in serum of cattle and camelsJ Egypt Vet Med Assoc199353319324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>41.RifaatMAMorsyTASadekMSAzabMEKhaledMLMSafarEHIncidence of toxoplasmosis among farm and slaughtered animals in coastal zone of EgyptJ Egypt Soc Parasitol19799193197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>42.Al-AnaziADPrevalence of Neospora caninum and Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in sera from camels (Camelus dromedarius) in Riyadh Province, Saudi ArabiaJ Egypt Soc Parasitol201141245250<?supplied-pmid 21980764?>21980764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>43.HusseinMFBakkarMNBasmaeilSMGarelnabiARPrevalence of Toxoplasmosis in Saudi Arabian camels (Camelus dromedarius)Vet Parasitol19882817517810.1016/0304-4017(88)90030-1<?supplied-pmid 3388734?>3388734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>44.Al-AnaziADAntibodies in sera from camels in western and southern region of central province, Saudi ArabiaJ Egypt Soc Parasitol201242659664<?supplied-pmid 23469639?>23469639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>45.KhalilMKElrayahIESeroprevalence of Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in farm animals (camels, cattle, and sheep) in SudanJ Med Anim Health201133639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>46.Abu-ZeidYAProtein G ELISA for detection of antibodies against Toxoplasma SAG1 in dromedariesJ Egypt Soc Parasitol200232247257<?supplied-pmid 12049260?>12049260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>47.HilaliMRomandSThulliezPKwokOCHDubeyJPPrevalence of Neospora caninum and Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in sera from camels from EgyptVet Parasitol19987526927110.1016/S0304-4017(97)00181-7<?supplied-pmid 9637230?>9637230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>48.Abu-Zeid Y, Enan M, Ahmed A, Shaheen H, Ramadan G, Al Shamsi U, Al Tayyari W: Genotyping of Toxoplasma gondii isolated from camels from Abu Dhabi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The 6thAnnual U.A.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>University Research Conference, 04/2005; 2006:24–26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>49.DubeyJPJonesJLToxoplasma gondii infection in humans and animals in the United StatesInt J Parasitol2008381257127810.1016/j.ijpara.2008.03.007<?supplied-pmid 18508057?>18508057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>50.CarneiroACCarneiroMGouveiaAMVilas-boasLSVitorRWSeroprevalence and risk factors of sheep toxoplasmosis in Minas Gerais, BrazilRev Méd Vét2009160527531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>51.VillariSVescoGPetersenECrispoABuffolanoWRisk factors for toxoplasmosis in pigs bred in Sicily, Southern ItalyVet Parasitol20091611810.1016/j.vetpar.2009.01.019<?supplied-pmid 19246158?>19246158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>52.RandallLZarnkeSDubeyJPKwokOCHVer HoefJMSeroprevalence for T. gondii in selected wild species from AlaskaJ Wildl Dis20003621922410.7589/0090-3558-36.2.21910813602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>53.Serrano-MartinezECollantes-FernandezEChavez-VelasquezARodriguez-BertosACasas-AstosERisco-CastilloVRosadio-AlcantaraROrtega-MoraLMEvaluation of Neospora caninum and Toxoplasma gondii infections in alpaca (Vicugna pacos) and llama (Lama glama) aborted foetuses from PeruVet Parasitol2007150394510.1016/j.vetpar.2007.08.048<?supplied-pmid 17931783?>17931783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>54.HagemoserWADubeyJPThompsonJRAcute toxoplasmosis in a camelJ Am Vet Med Assoc1990196347347<?supplied-pmid 2298664?>2298664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>55.WangHWangYHZhandDLToxoplasma gondii infection in Bacterian camel (Camelus Bactrianus) in ChinaVet Parasitol201319228828910.1016/j.vetpar.2012.09.028<?supplied-pmid 23084397?>23084397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>56.RagozAMYaiLEOliveiraLNDiasRAGoncalvesHCAzevedoSSDubeyJPGennriSMIsolation of Toxoplasma gondii from goats from BrazilJ Parasitol20099532332610.1645/GE-1854.118850769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>57.TenterAMHeckerothaARWeissLMToxoplasma gondii: from animals to humansInt J Parasitol2000301217125810.1016/S0020-7519(00)00124-7<?supplied-pmid 11113252?>11113252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>58.DubeyJPValidation of the specificity of the modified agglutination test for toxoplasmosis in pigsVet Parasitol19977130731010.1016/S0304-4017(97)00016-2<?supplied-pmid 9299699?>9299699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>59.ShaapanRMEL-NawawiFATawfikMASensitivity and specificity of various serological tests for detection of Toxoplasma gondii infection in naturally infected sheepVet Parasitol200815335936210.1016/j.vetpar.2008.02.016<?supplied-pmid 18406534?>18406534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>60.Mainar-JaimeRCBarberánMEvaluation of the diagnostic accuracy of the modified agglutination test (MAT) and an indirect ELISA for the detection of serum antibodies against Toxoplasma gondii in sheep through Bayesian approachesVet Parasitol200714812212910.1016/j.vetpar.2007.05.018<?supplied-pmid 17624672?>17624672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>61.ZhuCCuiLLZhangLSComparison of a commercial ELISA with the modified agglutination test for detection of Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in sera of naturally infected dogs and catsIranian J Parasitol201278995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>62.KlunIDjurkovic-DjakovicOThulliezPComparison of a commercial ELISA with the Modified Agglutination Test for the detection of Toxoplasma gondii infection in naturally exposed sheepZoonoses Public Health20075416516810.1111/j.1863-2378.2007.01032.x<?supplied-pmid 17456149?>17456149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>63.PaulMPotential risk factors for Toxoplasma gondii infection in cases with recently acquired toxoplasmosisPrzegl Epidemiol199852447454<?supplied-pmid 10321088?>10321088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>64.ManalYIMagzoubEMajidMDetection of Toxoplasma gondii tachyzoites in the milk of experimentally infected lactating She-CamelsJ Anim Vet Adv20065456458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
