<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4156656</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25168356</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6407</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-736</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide sequencing of small RNAs reveals a tissue-specific loss of conserved microRNA families in Echinococcus granulosus </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><address><email>baiyun@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhuangzhi</given-names></name><address><email>zhuangzhizhang@sina.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff23"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><address><email>jinl@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><address><email>kangh@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yongqiang</given-names></name><address><email>zhuyq@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><address><email>zhanglu@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><address><email>lix@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Fengshou</given-names></name><address><email>fengshou.ma@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><address><email>zhaoli6605@sina.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff23"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Baoxin</given-names></name><address><email>2423930978@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff23"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><address><email>Junli88828@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff24"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>Donald P</given-names></name><address><email>donM@qimr.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff25"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Wenbao</given-names></name><address><email>wenbao.zhang88@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff24"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Shengyue</given-names></name><address><email>wangsy@chgc.sh.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff22"/></contrib><aff id="Aff22"><label/>Shanghai-MOST Key Laboratory of Health and Disease Genomics, Chinese National Human Genome Center at Shanghai, 250 Bibo Road, Shanghai, 201203 China </aff><aff id="Aff23"><label/>Veterinary Research Institute, Xinjiang Academy of Animal Sciences, 151 East-Kelamayi Street, Urumqi, Xinjiang 830000 China </aff><aff id="Aff24"><label/>State Key Laboratory Incubation Base of Xinjiang Major Diseases Research, Clinical Medical Research Institute, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xinjiang Medical University, No. 1 Liyushan Road, Urumqi, Xinjiang 830054 China </aff><aff id="Aff25"><label/>Molecular Parasitology Laboratory, QIMR Berghofer Institute of Medical Research, Brisbane, QLD Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>736</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Bai et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are important post-transcriptional regulators which control growth and development in eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The cestode Echinococcus granulosus has a complex life-cycle involving different development stages but the mechanisms underpinning this development, including the involvement of miRNAs, remain unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Using Illumina next generation sequencing technology, we sequenced at the genome-wide level three small RNA populations from the adult, protoscolex and cyst membrane of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A total of 94 pre-miRNA candidates (coding 91 mature miRNAs and 39 miRNA stars) were in silico predicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Through comparison of expression profiles, we found 42 mature miRNAs and 23 miRNA stars expressed with different patterns in the three life stages examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, considering both the previously reported and newly predicted miRNAs, 25 conserved miRNAs families were identified in the E. granulosus genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Comparing the presence or absence of these miRNA families with the free-living Schmidtea mediterranea, we found 13 conserved miRNAs are lost in E. granulosus, most of which are tissue-specific and involved in the development of ciliated cells, the gut and sensory organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Finally, GO enrichment analysis of the differentially expressed miRNAs and their potential targets indicated that they may be involved in bi-directional development, nutrient metabolism and nervous system development in E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This study has, for the first time, provided a comprehensive description of the different expression patterns of miRNAs in three distinct life cycle stages of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The analysis supports earlier suggestions that the loss of miRNAs in the Platyhelminths might be related to morphological simplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>These results may help in the exploration of the mechanism of interaction between this parasitic worm and its definitive and intermediate hosts, providing information that can be used to develop new interventions and therapeutics for the control of cystic echinococcosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1471-2164-15-736) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Echinococcus granulosus</italic></kwd><kwd>microRNA</kwd><kwd>Deep sequencing</kwd><kwd>Differential expression</kwd><kwd>Life cycle stage development</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are a class of endogenous non-coding RNAs of around 22 nucleotides (nts) in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>They play a role as post-transcriptional regulators, partially or completely complementary binding to messenger RNA transcripts (mRNAs), usually resulting in direct degradation or translational repression of target genes [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In eukaryotes, miRNAs are involved in a broad variety of biological processes [3], such as embryonic development, cell proliferation, cell differentiation, and apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>To date, more than twenty thousand miRNAs from 223 species have been registered in the miRBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>, release 21.0, June 2014) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>miRNAs are usually highly conserved throughout the animal kingdom [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>They have been continuously added to Metazoan genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The emergence of vertebrates is characterized by a strong increase in miRNA families, and correlates with the increase in vertebrate morphological complexity [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Therefore, miRNAs may have significantly contributed to phenotypic evolution in animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Recently, a high rate of the loss of conserved miRNA loci has been found in the nematodes and the flatworms [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>This result suggested that the miRNA losses in Platyhelminths are not random events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, to date, there is no report about the mechanisms of miRNA losses in metazoan phylogenetics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Echinococcus granulosus is a flatworm and member of the Platyhelminthes, and is the causative agent of cystic echinococcosis (CE), a disease that is distributed throughout most areas of the world [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Currently, up to 3 million people are infected with E. granulosus [12], and, in some areas, 10% of the population has detectable hydatid cysts by abdominal ultrasound and chest X-ray [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This tapeworm requires two mammalian hosts to complete its life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The mature adult worm resides in the small intestine of a carnivore (definitive host) and releases worm segments or proglottides containing hundreds of eggs which contaminate vegetation and water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>When the eggs are swallowed by an intermediate host such as a sheep, the eggs hatch to release larval oncospheres into the digestive tract which are activated by bile and gastrointestinal enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The activated oncospheres penetrate the intestinal wall and migrate via the circulatory system to various organs (mainly the liver and lungs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In these organs, the oncospheres develop into hydatid cysts over many months and the cysts generate brood capsules within which protoscoleces (PSC) are produced asexually. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The cycle is completed when a canine (dog, wolf, fox) definitive host swallows PSC present in the hydatid cysts in infected offal, and the PSC develop into adult worms in the small intestine [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Although the life cycle of E. granulosus is well known, the mechanisms underlying the main developmental events throughout remain largely unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Our previous study of the transcriptome of E. granulosus revealed that 1,452 genes were up- or down-regulated in adult, PSC and cyst stages [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a global proteomic analysis of the expression characteristics of E. granulosus in larval and adult stages identified 22 adult-specific and 263 PSC-specific proteins [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>These studies suggested that transcriptional regulatory mechanisms are pivotal in the control of E. granulosus development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In regards to flatworms, miRNAs have been experimentally identified in Schmidtea mediterranea [18, 19], Schistosoma japonicum [20–22] and Schistosoma mansoni [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A PCR-based cloning study identified 26 mature miRNAs in PSC and the cystic stage of E. granulosus [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, due to the hitherto restricted experimental methods and the limited genomic information available, the numbers and expression profile of E. granulosus miRNAs are still unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Here, we used next generation sequencing technology (NGS) to further explore the diversity of E. granulosus miRNAs and their expression patterns in different life stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We expand the miRNA repertoire of E. granulosus and identify new miRNA encoding loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Through comparing miRNA families in the Platyhelminths, we found that the losses of E. granulosus miRNAs may be associated with the loss of ciliated cells, the gut and sensory organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The results significantly enhance our knowledge of miRNA species in E. granulosus and provide insights into miRNA evolution, biogenesis, and expression in parasites generally. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Deep sequencing of three small RNA libraries from E. granulosus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>To investigate the composition of small RNAs and the dynamic changes of miRNA expression during E. granulosus development, three small RNA libraries were constructed from adults, PSC and cyst membrane, and sequenced using Solexa sequencing technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After removing low-quality sequences, adaptor contaminants and RNAs smaller than 18 nts, we obtained 23,632,021, 20,978,758 and 15,975,894 high-quality reads of small RNAs sized 18–30 nts from adults, PSC and cyst membrane, respectively [Additional file 1: Table S1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Of these reads, 73.48% (adult), 73.31% (PSC) and 71.60% (cyst membrane) were 20 to 24 nts in length (Figure  1a), which is the typical size range for Dicer-derived products [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Through sequence mapping, 11,680,028, 12,966,593 and 9,375,095 reads from the three libraries perfectly matched to E. granulosus genome [16], [Additional file 1: Table S2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>After discarding known non-coding RNAs, such as rRNA, tRNA, snoRNA, repeat-associated RNA, and degraded fragments of mRNAs, the remaining 10,069,724, 11,775,532 and 8,025,262 small RNA reads from adults, PSC and cyst membrane, respectively, were used to search for both known and novel miRNAs (Figure  1b) [Additional file 1: Table S2].Figure 1 Size distribution and classification of the small RNAs in the different libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>(a) Length distribution of the sequencing reads in the three libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The length percentages were calculated by dividing the counts of 18–30 nts reads in each library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The lengths of the small RNA reads are mainly distributed from 20 to 24 nts. (b) Classification of the sequenced small RNAs from adults, cyst and protoscoleces (PSC), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The percentages were calculated by dividing the counts of reads matched to the genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Identification of known and novel miRNAs from E. granulosus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>To date, 23 mature miRNAs of E. granulosus have been identified [25] and are included in the miRBase database 20.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>By deep sequencing, we found that all of the known mature miRNAs were present in our data sets [Additional file 1: Table S3], the majority being abundant in all three libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we also identified 23 miRNA stars from the known miRNA precursors [Additional file 1: Table S3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In addition to known miRNAs, we also used miRDeep2 to predict and score novel miRNA precursors [27] and identified 94 miRNA candidates encoding 91 mature miRNAs and 39 miRNA stars [Additional file 1: Table S4 and S5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All these miRNAs can be folded into characteristic miRNA stem-loop secondary hairpin structures and have a 1-2 nt 3′overhang pattern generated by Dicer cleavage during mature miRNA generation [Additional file 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We evaluated evolutionary conservations by homologous searches to known metazoan miRNAs and found 11 pre-miRNAs were classified into known families based on their precursor sequences, whereas 83 did not show homology with other miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We further matched these predicted pre-miRNA candidates to the E. multilocularis genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/cgi-bin/blast/submitblast/Echinococcus">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/cgi-bin/blast/submitblast/Echinococcus</ext-link>) and found 82 of 94 miRNA candidates were evolutionarily conserved (identity ≥87%) in both species [Additional file 1: Table S6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>To validate the novel miRNAs, we randomly selected 22 mature miRNAs and 5 miRNA stars, and conducted stem-loop RT-PCR [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All the selected miRNAs were expressed in E. granulosus [Additional file 3: Figure S1], suggesting that the filter criteria were sufficiently strict for predicting novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>miRNA clusters are a group of miRNA genes located within a proximal distance on a chromosome [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In the present study, besides two published miRNA clusters, miR-71/2b/2d and miR-277/4988 [25], we identified two additional miRNA clusters located in closed loci (EG_S00041: 46,144-53,961 and pathogen_EMU_scaffold_007768: 2,420,386-2,428,006) in the genomes of both E. granulosus and E. multilocularis (Figure  2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>One cluster consists of four homologous novel miRNAs (new-15, new-24, new-61 and new-7) in the positive strand (Figure  2b), while the other one is composed of new-12 and new-22 in the reverse strand (Figure  2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignments of the precursors of these novel miRNAs showed that they contained similar sequence at the ‘seed region’ [Additional file 4: Figure S2], which indicated that they may play similar roles in target regulation and belong to the same family.Figure 2 Novel miRNAs and clusters detected in E. granulosus. (a) The location of miRNA gene clusters in E. granulosus scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The rightward arrow indicates the location of the miRNA gene at the positive strand, while the leftward arrow indicates the miRNAs at the minus strand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The secondary structures of Echinococcus cluster containing new-17, new-24, new-61 and new-7 (b) and the cluster containing new-12 and new-22 (c) were predicted by mfold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The sequence of the mature miRNAs is shaded in grep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Limited by the size of the miRNA cluster, we used “N” instead of 5464 nt RNA sequences at the location between new-61 and new-7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Comparison of miRNA families of E. granulosuswith other flatworms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>It is now well established that many miRNAs come in families with the same seed sequences (typically defined as position 2–7 or 2–8 from the 5′ end of the mature miRNA) [30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>From our 94 novel and 23 known miRNAs, 25 different miRNA families representing 29 miRNAs were classified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Of these, 24 families had been expected in the flatworms [8, 9], including one which is characteristic for Eumetazoa, 14 from Bilateria, 8 from Protostomia and one from Lophotrochozoa (Figure  3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This result was much more than the 16 miRNA families finding in a study by Fromm et al. [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the remaining one miRNA family (mir-3479) is only present in E. granulosus, S. mansoni and S. japonicum.Figure 3 Loss and gain of miRNA families in E. granulosus and other flatworms . (a) The table for conserved miRNAs found in E. granulosus and inferred loss/gain number of conserved miRNA families. (b) The acquisition (red) and loss (blue) of miRNA families for 4 flatworms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Numbers in white squares show evolutionary acquisition and loss of miRNA families in each flatworms; Numbers in black squares show acquisition and loss of miRNA families in flatworms, Neodermataand Trematoda + Cestoda. (c) The distribution of the conserved eumetazoan (blue), bilaterian (orange), protostomian (green), lophotrochozoan (purple), and Platyhelminthes (yellow) miRNA families in flatworms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We then compared the presence or absence of the conserved miRNA families of E. granulosus (Cestoda) with three other flatworms, S. mediterranea (Turbellaria) [18], Gyrodactylus salaris (Monogenea) [9] and S. japonicum (Trematoda) [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Similar to the previous study [9], 8 conserved bilaterian, protostomian, and lophotrochozoan miRNA families were not detected in the four flatworms (Figure  3b and c); these were mir-33, mir-34, mir-137, mir-193, mir-242, mir-252, mir-137 and mir-375. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, 8 miRNAs families, mir-29, mir-92, mir-216, mir-210, mir-315, mir-12, mir-750 and mir-1989 were only detected in the free living flatworm S. mediterranea, but not in G. salaris, E. granulosus and S. japonicum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Finally, there are 6 miRNA families (mir-76, mir-96, mir-184, mir-278, mir-2001 and mir-1175) that are present in S. mediterranea and G. salaris, but are absent in S. japonicum and E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Expression profiles of miRNAs in the three life stages of E. granulosus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Combining all detected known and novel miRNAs, 117 pre-miRNAs coding 114 mature miRNAs and 62 miRNA stars were identified in all the E. granulosus libraries [Additional file 1: Table S7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We used the ‘transcripts per million’ (TPM) approach to normalize the abundance value of each miRNA [Additional file 1: Table S8] [32, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Through further evaluating the relative abundance of the mature miRNAs, we found miR-71 was the most abundant miRNA with over 300,000 reads in each library (Table  1), which was similar to the miRNA patterns in S. japonicum [34] and C. elegans [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Whereas most of the conserved miRNAs were expressed constitutively at all development stages, more non-conserved miRNAs were stage-specifically expressed in E. granulosus.Table 1 The relative abundance of the top ten mature miRNAs in three life-stages of E. granulosus NameAdult*Cyst*PSC*Total egr-miR-71 325369.55546105.37302855.401174330.33 egr-miR-1 279745.1171718.95142856.71494320.77 egr-miR-7 16646.88215441.8010754.68242843.36 egr-let-7 13664.4431789.9895330.97140785.39 egr-miR-10 77170.1318409.0330980.17126559.32 egr-miR-4988 10474.3412561.2695883.37118918.97 egr-bantam 31467.5523201.1747866.69102535.41 egr-miR-9 8397.639500.1178860.0196757.75 egr-miR-61 25468.4210554.4939333.5175356.42 egr-miR-87 17502.5719390.6334640.8671534.06 *The relative expression levels of each miRNA were calculated by counting the numbers of respective miRNA reads normalized to the total number of reads of annotated miRNAs from each library. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The expression analysis showed that 65 miRNAs, comprising 42 mature miRNAs and 23 miRNA stars, exhibited statistically significant changes (a threshold of correct P-value &lt; 0.001 and fold-change &gt; 2.0) in at least one of the three life-stages during E. granulosus development (Figure  4a) [Additional file 1: Table S9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Further evaluation of the expression patterns indicated that 9 miRNAs were mainly expressed in the adult worms and six of them (new-7, new-12, new-15, new-22, new-24 and new-61) are derived from the two new miRNA clusters [Additional file 5: Figure S3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We used stem-loop real-time quantification RT-PCR to examine the expression of 35 randomly selected mature miRNAs and miRNA stars and 31 miRNAs were shown to be in accordance with the expression profiles detected by the Illumina sequencing [Additional file 1: Table S10].Figure 4 Different expression profiles of miRNAs in E. granulosus . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>(a) Heat maps of sequencing data from 65 differentially expressed miRNAs in the three libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The correct P-value &lt; 0.001 and fold-change &gt; 2.0 were used as the threshold criteria to define significant differences in miRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>MiRNA expression is displayed using a color key where green corresponds to low and red to high numbers of miRNA normalized reads. (b) Differentially expressed miRNAs through comparing the adult or cyst with the PSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Red arrow indicates the up-regulated miRNAs, and blue arrow represents the down-regulated miRNAs. (c) The different expression patterns of miRNAs through comparing the adult or cyst with the PSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The comparison between the adult and cyst was made and removed similar trends of miRNAs compared to the PSC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Since the larval PSC is an important transition life cycle stage, capable of developing either into an adult worm in the dog gastrointestinal tract or a secondary hydatid cyst in the intermediate host, we compared the expression levels of miRNAs in adult worms or cyst membrane with those in the PSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A total of 43 miRNAs (22 up-regulated and 21 down-regulated) in adult tissue and 42 miRNAs (4 up-regulated and 38 down-regulated) in the cyst membrane were identified (Figure  4b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Further removing similar trends of miRNA expression between adults vs PSC and cyst vs PSC, we found that 25 miRNAs (22 up-regulated and 3 down-regulated) and 24 miRNAs (4 up-regulated and 20 down-regulated) were specifically changed in the adult and cyst stage, respectively (Figure  4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Amongst these, 8 miRNAs appeared to show reverse trends in expression in the adult and cyst stages compared with PSC; miR-125, miR-277, miR-4989*, new-17*, new-87 and new-87* were up-regulated in adult worms but down-regulated in cyst membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In contrast, miR-124a and miR-124b were down-regulated in the former stage but up-regulated in the latter [Additional file 1: Table S11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>These results imply that miRNA expression variation in the different life stages may be associated with the direction of development of PSC into either an adult worm or a secondary hydatid cyst. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Target gene prediction and functional analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>To assign biological functions to the 65 differentially expressed miRNAs, we predicted putative target genes using the Miranda program [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Based on previously published EST sequences [16], we found 3,622 genes possibly targeted by 114 mature miRNAs and 62 miRNA stars [Additional file 1: Table S12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>By enrichment analyses on the predicted targets, we determined that 182 genes could be categorized into 24 significant GO terms (adjust P &lt; 0.05) [Additional file 1: Table S13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The major target genes in the biological process categories were involved in the regulation of cell differentiation (GO:0045595), determination of adult lifespan (GO:0008340) and response to nutrient (GO:0007584). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These results support our premise that the differentially expressed miRNAs may have important functions in the three different life cycle stages of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>By using real-time quantitative PCR, we observed that some differentially expressed miRNAs had obvious negative correlations with their target gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>For example, a high expressed miR-31 and a down-regulation of its target gene ATP2B3 (EG_03132) were simultaneously detected in the adult stage (Figure  5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in the adult and cyst stages of E. granulosus, obvious negative correlations were also observed between the expression of miR-7 and its putative target gene long-chain acyl-CoA synthetase (LCFACS, EG_02438) (Figure  5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Finally, we observed a clear positive correlation between the expression of let-7 and its putative target gene vitamin D receptor (VDR, EG_04794) (Figure  5c).Figure 5 Comparison of mRNA expression levels of predicted miRNA targets in different stages of E. granulosus . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(a) miR-31 vs ATP2B3, (b) miR-7 vs LCFACS showed nagetive correlation between expression of miRNA and their putative target genes, (c) let-7 vs VDR showed an positive correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The left and right Y-axes indicate the expression levels of the miRNAs and their targets, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Blue bars show the expression levels of the miRNAs (log2 scale) in adult worms (Adult), protoscoleces (PSC) and cyst germinal membranes (Cyst) of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Red dots lines represent the expression levels of related target genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we performed deep sequencing of small RNAs in three distinct developmental stages of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>By Bowtie mapping, there are 11,680,028, 12,966,593 and 9,375,095 18–30 nt reads were located the E. granulosus genome, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The remaining 40% unmapped reads could be ascribed to the following reasons: (1) some genetic polymorphisms may occur in the E. granulosus genome which interferes with Bowtie mapping; (2) unsatisfactory available genome data; some sequences are probably absent in the current draft genome of E. granulosus [16]; (3) miRNAs sequencing errors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>NGS may randomly produce some base calling errors and influence the accuracy of short reads; (4) post-transcriptional editing of miRNAs may also have contributed to the mismatches observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>It has been previously reported that the gain of miRNA genes in Metazoan species is associated with an increase in morphological complexity [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>However, a high rate of the loss of conserved miRNA loci has been found in many subgroups of the Platyhelminthes [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Basing on evolutionary conservation analysis, we also found a significant loss of conserved miRNAs in the Cestoda. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>A total of 22 conserved miRNA families were confirmed as not detectable in E. granulosus, suggesting that the loss of conserved miRNA loci in flatworms is not a random event in metazoan phylogenetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>It might relate to loss of targets in the corresponding species [37] or reduced morphological complexity [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A previous study revealed that miRNA invention is closely related to the evolution of tissue identities in bilaterian species [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Through comparing these lost miRNA families in E. granulosus, we found 8 are not detected in the parasitic Platyhelminthes compared with S. mediterranea and 6 are absent from S. japonicum and E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>On further analysis of their evolutionary origin, we observed that most of the lost miRNAs may be derived from some specific tissues, which have been reduced or lost in tapeworms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>For example, there are 8 conserved miRNA families expressed in the free-living S. mediterranea that are absent in the Neodermata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Among these, miR-12, miR-216 and miR-283 have been found mainly present in locomotor ciliated cells, while miR-29 and miR-92 are expressed in the gut [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>These organs have gradually disappeared in E. granulosus and some of the other parasitic Platyhelminthes groups because of a significant decrease in locomotor and digestive activities associated with the parasitic mode of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the Neodermata, there is a significant degeneration of peripheral sensory nervous system elements, such as, the loss of eyes in tapeworms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In bilaterians, miR-183 and miR-263 have been reported to have a conserved affiliation with sensory organ differentiation [7, 39] and miR-184 and miR-278 play essential roles in the development of eyes [40, 41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These sensory tissue-specific miRNAs are not detected in S. japonicum (Trematoda) and E. granulosus (Cestoda). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Thus, it seems that the loss of miRNA loci in E. granulosus may be related to the reduction or loss of some specific tissues in the Cestoda. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the biological evolution of one species to another is usually accompanied by the acquisition of new miRNA families in the newly evolved species [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Although previous studies did not report there was any miRNA family acquired in the Platyhelminthes [8, 9], we observed that mir-3479 was present in E. granulosus, S. mansoni and S. japonicum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>This result may be due to the lack of information in other taxa or due to evolutionary innovations to adapt to the new living environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>For tapeworms, in order to escape from host immune attack, E. granulosus produces many components to moderate the host immune response, such as EgAgB (antigen B), which interferes with human dendritic cell differentiation and maturation [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Further, one recent study has shown that three schistosome-specific miRNAs, Bantam, miR-10 and miR-3479, were detected in the plasma of S. japonicum-infected rabbits [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>These results imply that the gain of miR-3479 in E. granulosus or S. japonicum may have resulted as an evolved adaptation in the parasitic Platyhelminthes to moderate the host immune response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that there are no reports to date on the plasma levels of E. granulosus miRNAs in patients with CE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>However, some Dicrocoelium-specific miRNAs have recently been shown to be present in exosome-like vesicles [45] and similar secretory vesicles have been described previously in the early stages of E. granulosus development [46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Notably, two novel close miRNA clusters (new-15/ new-24/new-61/new-7 and new-12/new-22) were identified in E. granulosus and E. multilocularis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Beside the same genomic location, they display similar patterns of miRNA expression, suggesting that the expression of these novel miRNAs may be co-regulated by the same promoter elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, two clusters of miRNAs share the ‘GGCGCUU’ motif with the known sme-miR-2160. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been reported that sme-miR-2160 is enriched in planarian stem cells and is down-regulated in individuals in which stem cells had been abrogated by irradiation [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>These observations imply that these two clusters of miRNAs may be associated in E. granulosus with cell proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Moreover, since new-7/12/15/22/24/61 of E. granulosus contains six copies of the same seed sequences in the 5′ hairpin arms, these multiple copies may likely be functional, resulting in the dose-dependent regulation of their downstream targets [47, 48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Similar multiple copies of mir-2160 have been identified in S. mediterranea [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Development in E. granulosus involves a number of different life stages including the eggs, activated oncospheres, hydatid cyst, PSC and adult worms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It is a complicated and dynamic process and may be associated with miRNA regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>By comparing the differential expression pattern of miRNAs, our results showed that let-7 exhibited 3.2-fold and 2.6-fold increased expression in PSC and in the cyst, respectively, compared with the adult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>let-7 has been shown to regulate developmental timing in C.elegans through the direct target genes lin-41 and hbl-1 [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Thus, the observation of substantially increased expression of let-7 in the PSC and cyst might be associated with the capability of E. granulosus for bi-directional development, differentiating into an adult worm in the definitive host dog gastrointestinal tract or into a secondary hydatid cyst in the intermediate (or human) host [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Indeed, bi-directional development is a unique biological characteristic of E. granulosus and our previous study showed that some protein-coding genes, with high homology to the bile acid receptors and transporters, were located in the E. granulosus genome, and that nuclear hormone receptors, including the farnesoid X receptor (FXR) and VDR, may play a key role in stimulating the PSC to develop into adult worms [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Recently, the hormone receptors have been reported to directly activate transcription of the evolutionarily conserved let-7 and control the development of larvae to adults in C. elegans [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Here, we observed a positive correlation between the expression of let-7 and VDR, suggesting that VDR may induce crucial miRNA transcriptional events and promote adult development in E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, through miRNA target prediction analysis, we found let-7 could complementary bind to the VDR 3′ UTR sequences, suggesting that let-7 may mediate a negative feedback loop controlling the bile acid signal pathway in the development of PSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Recently, a feedback circuit between let-7-family miRNAs and DAF-12, a homolog of vertebrate FXR and VDR, has been found in C. elegans [52] . Additional experimental validations are required to explore this relationship in E. granulosus in future studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In summary, this study describes the first large scale identification and dynamic characterisation of miRNAs in three developmental stages of E. granulosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>A total of 114 mature miRNAs and 62 miRNA stars were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary conservation analysis suggested that the losses of miRNA families in E. granulosus may be associated with morphological reductions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Additionally, GO analysis revealed that the differentially expressed miRNAs and their targets may be involved in diverse development processes, including bi-directional differentiation and nervous system development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Understanding the regulatory processes involving miRNAs in E. granulosus may be helpful to explore the mechanism of interaction between this parasitic worm and its definitive and intermediate hosts, and provide new information to develop new interventions and therapeutics for the control of CE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Ethical approval for the use of dogs and sheep was given by the Animal Ethics Committee of Xinjiang Academy of Animal Science(XJAASaec2011031506). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The protocols for using dogs and sheep were covered under the &lt; The Guidelines for the Care and Use of Experimental Animals &gt; (China) National Science and Development Act 2006–398. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Preparation of E. granulosussamples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The preparation of E. granulosus samples for analysis was undertaken as previously described [53, 54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>PSC were aspirated aseptically from several sheep liver hydatid cysts collected from Xinjiang, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The PSCs were sedimented at 1000 × g for 15 minutes and digested by pepsin [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>After PSC were removed, cyst membranes were rinsed 10 times with PBS and checked microscopy to confirm no PSC attached on the membranes, and then cut into small pieces with a pair of scissors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The cut membranes were soaked in PBS in a flask and stirred for 10 min at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The flask was placed on bench at room temperature for 3 min to precipitate laminated layer and other cyst tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The membrane cells in supernatant were pelleted by centrifuging at 1400 g for 10 min at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The cells were resuspended with PBS and left on the bench for 3 min to precipitate remained PSC, the supernatant was centrifuged at 1400 × g for 10 min at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Adult worms were collected from experimentally infected dogs using procedures describe earlier [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>All parasite materials were subjected to a final wash in PBS and then they were suspended in 10 volumes of RNAlater (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA), and stored at -80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Total RNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Samples of the 3 different life cycle stages of E. granulosus (adult, cyst and PSC) were homogenized in lysis buffer and total RNA was extracted using mirVana™ miRNA isolation kits (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>RNA concentration and purity were monitored using a NanoDrop ND-1000 UV spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The RNA integrity was evaluated by an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA) [Additional file 6: Figure S4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Finally, all RNA samples were stored at -80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Small RNA library construction and deep sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We constructed each small RNA library using Illumina Small RNA v1.5 Sample Preparation Kits (Illumina, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Briefly, total RNA (5 μg) of each sample was resolved on denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) gels, and then fractions of 18 to 30 nt in size were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The isolated small RNAs were sequentially ligated to 3′adapters, using T4 RNA ligase 2 (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA), and 5′adapters using T4 RNA ligase (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The ligation products were reverse transcribed using SuperScript Reverse Transcriptase II (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) and amplified with 12 PCR cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Then, 6% (w/v) PAGE was used to purify the amplification products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Finally, the libraries were used for clustering and sequencing using an Illumina Genome Analyzer II (Illumina, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Computational analysis to search for novel miRNAs and other small RNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>After removing low quality sequence reads and trimming adaptor sequences through miRExpress [56], we collected small RNAs ranging from 18–30 nucleotides and count length distributions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Then, duplicated sequences were removed from the initial dataset to produce a nonredundant set of unique sequences, hereafter referred to as sequence tags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>To determine whether these small RNA sequences were from E. granulosus, we mapped these small RNA sequences by Bowtie [57] to the draft E. granulosus genome sequences [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Only those mapping perfectly onto the draft genome were further considered as candidate miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>If a sequence mapped to more than 10 loci in the genome, it was not considered for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Then, we compared all sequence tags against a database of known miRNA precursors sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>, release 21.0) [4], and profiled every annotated miRNA in each library. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Basing on our earlier findings [16] and scrutiny of the Rfam RNA family database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rfam.sanger.ac.uk">http://rfam.sanger.ac.uk</ext-link>), we discarded all sequences matching with known E. granulosus rRNAs, tRNAs, snRNAs and mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>With the annotation of repeat sequences in the E. granulosus genome, small RNAs positioned at repeat loci were identified and annotated as repeat-associated small RNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Finally, the remaining clean sequenced reads were used to search for both conserved and novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In order to identify new miRNAs, we used miRDeep 2.0 [27] to identify miRNAs without prior information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The software uses a Bayesian algorithm and provides a score based on the expected pattern of miRNA-duplex excision from the stem of the precursor hairpins by Dicer [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The secondary structures of putative precursors were identified using the RNAfold program [59] and computed by minimum free energy (MFE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We used the following criteria to filter the candidate miRNAs: (1) The lengths of mature miRNA ranged from 18 to 25 nucleotides; (2) The miRNA precursors should have a characteristic fold-back structure and MFE should be less than -20 Kcal/mol; (3) The miRDeep score should be more than 1; (4) The GC content of the mature miRNA should be 15%-85%; (5) Small RNAs with multiple loci in the E. granulosus genome were excluded (more than five times); (6) In order to remove accidental hits, only the precursors with at least 5 sequence reads in three libraries were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these predicted mature miRNAs were also compared with known miRNAs from other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>If the E. granulosus miRNAs shared &gt;80% homology with known miRNAs and had the same seed sequences (2–8 nt), the miRNAs were considered as conserved miRNAs and were thus named after the known miRNA [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We defined the mature miRNA and miRNA star basing on the total number of reads in three life stages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Detection of differential expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Using the quantifier module of miRDeep2, we summed up read counts for all known or novel mature miRNAs in the sequencing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Then, relative expression levels were calculated by counting the numbers of respective miRNA reads normalized to the total number of annotated miRNAs in each library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>After ignoring the simultaneously lowly expressed miRNAs in three libraries (less than 50 TPM at all stages), differential expression in the three libraries was evaluated using the statistical R package DEGseq [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioconductor.org/packages/2.6/bioc/html/DEGseq.html">http://www.bioconductor.org/packages/2.6/bioc/html/DEGseq.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Based on this statistical model, statistical significances were calculated using Fisher’s exact test and likelihood ratio test, and then corrected for multiple testing according to Benjamini-Hochberg multiple test method [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Potentially interesting miRNA candidates were chosen according to the criteria of a 2-fold expression level change and adjusted P-value &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>MicroRNA target prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>In order to seek miRNAs targets, we first predicted the 3′UTRs by combined analysis of the predicted mRNAs and the released EST scafford sequences for E. granulosus [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Only the sequences located at the 3′untranslated region of predicted genes were regarded as potential 3′UTR sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Then, the miRanda program [36] was used to predict the target genes for all mature miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The energy thresholds were set at ≤ -20 kcal/mol and other thresholds used a default value (score threshold, 120; gap-opening penalty, -9; gap-extend penalty, -4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Then, all ESTs sequences predicted to contain miRNA target sites, were annotated as earlier described [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology and pathway analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Target genes regulated by the different subgroups of miRNAs were collected and subjected to Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Based on NCBI-nr annotation, we used the BLAST2GO program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.BLAST2go.org/">http://www.BLAST2go.org/</ext-link>) to obtain GO annotation of every target [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Then, the hypergeometric test [64] was used to classify the GO category, and the false discovery rate (FDR) was calculated to correct the P-value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>KEGG pathway analysis was carried out using the KEGG Automatic Annotation Server for ortholog assignment and pathway mapping (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/tools/kaas">http://www.genome.jp/tools/kaas</ext-link>) [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The hypergeometric test was used to assess the significant pathway of enrichment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Quantitative RT-PCR of miRNAs and their targets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A stem-loop quantitative RT-PCR was performed to validate the miRNA expression levels in each developmental stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted using mirVanaTM miRNA isolation kits (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The total RNA was reverse transcribed in a 20 μl reverse transcription (RT) reaction using 500 ng total RNA, 1 U PrimeScript RT Enzyme Mix I (Takara Bio, Otsu, Japan), 4 μl of 5 × RT buffer, and 1 μl of 2 μM miRNA-specific stem-loop primers [Additional file 1: Table S14a] designed according to Chen et al. [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>5.8S rRNA was chosen as a reference and was reverse-transcribed with a specific reverse primer [Additional file 1: Table S14a]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The RT reaction mixture was incubated at 37°C for 30 minutes, then at 85°C for 5 seconds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>A control was set up at the same time with no RNA input. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>With the cDNA products as a template, quantitative PCR was carried out using SYBR® Premix Ex TaqTM (Takara Bio, Otsu, Japan) in a StepOne Plus real-time system (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in [Additional file 1: Table S14a and S14b]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>A 10 μl reaction mixture including 1 μl of diluted cDNA (1:5), 0.4 μl of each primer (10 mM), 5 μl SYBR Premix Ex Taq II and 3.6 ml H2O was placed in 0.2 ml eight-strip PCR tubes (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Cycling conditions were: 95°C for 30s, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 5 s and 60°C for 34 s, 72°C for 60s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>For each PCR, dissociation curve analysis was carried out to discriminate the specific products from the primer dimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The CT-values are the average of three technical and three biological replicates and fold changes of miRNAs and their targets in different samples were calculated by the 2-ΔΔCt method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The miRNA expression levels in each developmental stage were compared by using a two-tailed t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Correlation analysis was made using the Pearson correlation coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec21"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM1_ESM.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: A file of all supplementary tables in the present study. Table S1. Length distribution of the sequencing reads in three libraries of E. granulosus. Table S2. Raw data filtration and distribution of sequenced small RNAs across different categories. Table S3. All identified known mature miRNAs and miRNA stars. Table S4. All predicted novel miRNA precursors in E. granulosus. Table S5. All identified novel mature miRNAs and miRNA stars. Table S6. The conservation analysis of the E. granulosus miRNA candidates in present E. multilocularis. Table S7. Summary of all previously known and newly found miRNAs in E. granulosus. Table S8. Profiles of miRNAs from adult, protoscolex (PSC) and the cyst of E. granulosus. Table S9. The miRNAs with different expression patterns in the different development stages of E. granulosus. Table S10. Validation of miRNA expression patterns by stem-loop real-time quantitative PCR. Table S11. The different expression patterns of miRNAs in the adult or cyst compared with PSC. Table S12. Target genes of all detected miRNAs. Table S13. Gene Ontology (GO) abundance analysis of the putative target genes for the differentially expressed miRNAs in E. granulosus. Table S14. Sequences of stem-loop RT primers, forward primers and reverse primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>(XLS 3 MB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Additional file 2: The secondary structure predictions and homology sequence alignments of all predicted miRNAs. (PDF 218 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Additional file 3: Figure S1: Confirmation of expression of novel miRNAs using stem-loop PT PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>(PDF 443 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Additional file 4: Figure S2: Sequence alignment of six new E. granulosus miRNAs in two newly found cluster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(PDF 262 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Additional file 5: Figure S3: Stem-loop semi-quantitative PCR of six new E. granulosus miRNAs with 5.8 s rRNA as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>(PDF 294 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6407_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Additional file 6: Figure S4: The RNA integrity (RIN) of the Samples of the 3 different life cycle stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(PDF 298 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>miRNAs</term><def><p>microRNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>E. granulosus</italic></term><def><p><italic>Echinococcus granulosus</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>E. multilocularis</italic></term><def><p><italic>Echinococcus multilocularis</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CE</term><def><p>Cystic echinococcosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSC</term><def><p>Protoscolex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>ATP2B3</italic></term><def><p>Plasma membrane calcium-transporting atpase 3-like</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>LCFACS</italic></term><def><p>Long-chain acyl-CoA synthetase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MFE</term><def><p>Minimum free energy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>3′UTR</term><def><p>3′-untranslational regions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p>False discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPM</term><def><p>Transcripts per million</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes.</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The authors declared that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>SW and WZ coordinated the project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>WZ, L Zhao, BS, JL and XL participated in the E. granulosus sample preparation, and RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>SW, YB, L Zhang, HK and YZ directed and performed the small RNA sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>SW, YB and FM performed the sequence alignment and the novel miRNAs prediction, annotation and expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>YB, L Zhang, XL and FM carried out the quantitative RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>SW, WZ and DPM commented on the genome sequencing and analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>YB, DPM, WZ and SW wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81271868, 31260272, and 31260272), National Basic Research Program (973) of China (2010CB534906), Shanghai Municipal Commission for Science and Technology (10XD1403200, 11DZ2292600, and 13DZ2291800), and Shanghai Natural Science Foundation (13ZR1429500). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>High throughput sequencing data have been submitted to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) under accession number SRP034671. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The read-count files for each library have been submitted to NCBI Gene expression omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE54180. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>1.CarringtonJCAmbrosVRole of microRNAs in plant and animal developmentScience2003301563133633810.1126/science.1085242<?supplied-pmid 12869753?>12869753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>2.BartelDPMicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and functionCell2004116228129710.1016/S0092-8674(04)00045-5<?supplied-pmid 14744438?>14744438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>3.AmbrosVMicroRNA pathways in flies and worms: growth, death, fat, stress, and timingCell2003113667367610.1016/S0092-8674(03)00428-8<?supplied-pmid 12809598?>12809598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>4.KozomaraAGriffiths-JonesSmiRBase: integrating microRNA annotation and deep-sequencing dataNucleic Acids Res201139Database issueD15215710.1093/nar/gkq1027<?supplied-pmid 21037258?>21037258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>5.NiwaRSlackFJThe evolution of animal microRNA functionCurr Opin Genet Dev200717214515010.1016/j.gde.2007.02.004<?supplied-pmid 17317150?>17317150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>6.HeimbergAMSempereLFMoyVNDonoghuePCPetersonKJMicroRNAs and the advent of vertebrate morphological complexityProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200810582946295010.1073/pnas.0712259105<?supplied-pmid 18287013?>18287013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>7.ChristodoulouFRaibleFTomerRSimakovOTrachanaKKlausSSnymanHHannonGJBorkPArendtDAncient animal microRNAs and the evolution of tissue identityNature201046372841084108810.1038/nature08744<?supplied-pmid 20118916?>20118916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>8.TarverJESperlingEANailorAHeimbergAMRobinsonJMKingBLPisaniDDonoghuePCPetersonKJmiRNAs: small genes with big potential in metazoan phylogeneticsMol Biol Evol201330112369238210.1093/molbev/mst133<?supplied-pmid 23913097?>23913097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>9.FrommBWorrenMMHahnCHovigEBachmannLSubstantial loss of conserved and gain of novel MicroRNA families in flatwormsMol Biol Evol201330122619262810.1093/molbev/mst155<?supplied-pmid 24025793?>24025793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>10.EckertJDeplazesPBiological, epidemiological, and clinical aspects of echinococcosis, a zoonosis of increasing concernClin Microbiol Rev200417110713510.1128/CMR.17.1.107-135.2004<?supplied-pmid 14726458?>14726458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>11.CraigPSLarrieuEControl of cystic echinococcosis/hydatidosis: 1863–2002Adv Parasitol20066144350810.1016/S0065-308X(05)61011-1<?supplied-pmid 16735171?>16735171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>12.CraigPSMcManusDPLightowlersMWChabalgoityJAGarciaHHGavidiaCMGilmanRHGonzalezAELorcaMNaquiraCNietoASchantzPMPrevention and control of cystic echinococcosisLancet Infect Dis20077638539410.1016/S1473-3099(07)70134-2<?supplied-pmid 17521591?>17521591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>13.LiTItoAPengcuoRSakoYChenXQiuDXiaoNCraigPSPost-treatment follow-up study of abdominal cystic echinococcosis in tibetan communities of northwest Sichuan ProvinceChina PLoS Negl Trop Dis2011510e136410.1371/journal.pntd.0001364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>14.MoroPLGilmanRHVerasteguiMBernCSilvaBBonillaJJHuman hydatidosis in the central Andes of Peru: evolution of the disease over 3 yearsClin Infect Dis199929480781210.1086/520440<?supplied-pmid 10589894?>10589894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>15.McManusDPZhangWLiJBartleyPBEchinococcosisLancet200336293921295130410.1016/S0140-6736(03)14573-4<?supplied-pmid 14575976?>14575976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>16.ZhengHZhangWZhangLZhangZLiJLuGZhuYWangYHuangYLiuJKangHChenJWangLChenAYuSGaoZJinLGuWWangZZhaoLShiBWenHLinRJonesMKBrejovaBVinarTZhaoGMcManusDPChenZZhouYThe genome of the hydatid tapeworm Echinococcus granulosusNat Genet201345101168117510.1038/ng.2757<?supplied-pmid 24013640?>24013640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>17.CuiSJXuLLZhangTXuMYaoJFangCYFengZYangPYHuWLiuFProteomic characterization of larval and adult developmental stages in Echinococcus granulosus reveals novel insight into host-parasite interactionsJ Proteomics20138415817510.1016/j.jprot.2013.04.013<?supplied-pmid 23603110?>23603110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>18.FriedlanderMRAdamidiCHanTLebedevaSIsenbargerTAHirstMMarraMNusbaumCLeeWLJenkinJCSánchez AlvaradoAKimJKRajewskyNHigh-resolution profiling and discovery of planarian small RNAsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200910628115461155110.1073/pnas.0905222106<?supplied-pmid 19564616?>19564616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>19.PalakodetiDSmielewskaMGraveleyBRMicroRNAs from the Planarian Schmidtea mediterranea: a model system for stem cell biologyRNA20061291640164910.1261/rna.117206<?supplied-pmid 16849698?>16849698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>20.HaoLCaiPJiangNWangHChenQIdentification and characterization of microRNAs and endogenous siRNAs in Schistosoma japonicumBMC Genomics2010115510.1186/1471-2164-11-55<?supplied-pmid 20092619?>20092619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>21.XueXSunJZhangQWangZHuangYPanWIdentification and characterization of novel microRNAs from Schistosoma japonicumPLoS One2008312e403410.1371/journal.pone.0004034<?supplied-pmid 19107204?>19107204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>22.HuangJHaoPChenHHuWYanQLiuFHanZGGenome-wide identification of Schistosoma japonicum microRNAs using a deep-sequencing approachPLoS One2009412e820610.1371/journal.pone.0008206<?supplied-pmid 19997615?>19997615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>23.de SouzaGMMuniyappaMKCarvalhoSGGuerra-SaRSpillaneCGenome-wide identification of novel microRNAs and their target genes in the human parasite Schistosoma mansoniGenomics20119829611110.1016/j.ygeno.2011.05.00721640815 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>24.SimoesMCLeeJDjikengACerqueiraGCZerlotiniAda Silva-PereiraRADalbyARLoVerdePEl-SayedNMOliveiraGIdentification of Schistosoma mansoni microRNAsBMC Genomics2011124710.1186/1471-2164-12-47<?supplied-pmid 21247453?>21247453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>25.CucherMPradaLMourglia-EttlinGDematteisSCamiciaFAsurmendiSRosenzvitMIdentification of Echinococcus granulosus microRNAs and their expression in different life cycle stages and parasite genotypesInt J Parasitol2011413–443944810.1016/j.ijpara.2010.11.010<?supplied-pmid 21219906?>21219906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>26.HendersonIRZhangXLuCJohnsonLMeyersBCGreenPJJacobsenSEDissecting Arabidopsis thaliana DICER function in small RNA processing, gene silencing and DNA methylation patterningNat Genet200638672172510.1038/ng1804<?supplied-pmid 16699516?>16699516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>27.FriedlanderMRMackowiakSDLiNChenWRajewskyNmiRDeep2 accurately identifies known and hundreds of novel microRNA genes in seven animal cladesNucleic Acids Res2012401375210.1093/nar/gkr688<?supplied-pmid 21911355?>21911355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>28.ChenCRidzonDABroomerAJZhouZLeeDHNguyenJTBarbisinMXuNLMahuvakarVRAndersenMRLaoKQLivakKJGueglerKJReal-time quantification of microRNAs by stem-loop RT-PCRNucleic Acids Res20053320e17910.1093/nar/gni178<?supplied-pmid 16314309?>16314309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>29.Lagos-QuintanaMRauhutRLendeckelWTuschlTIdentification of novel genes coding for small expressed RNAsScience2001294554385385810.1126/science.1064921<?supplied-pmid 11679670?>11679670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>30.LewisBPBurgeCBBartelDPConserved seed pairing, often flanked by adenosines, indicates that thousands of human genes are microRNA targetsCell20051201152010.1016/j.cell.2004.12.035<?supplied-pmid 15652477?>15652477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>31.LewisBPShihIHJones-RhoadesMWBartelDPBurgeCBPrediction of mammalian microRNA targetsCell2003115778779810.1016/S0092-8674(03)01018-3<?supplied-pmid 14697198?>14697198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>32.MeyersBCTejSSVuTHHaudenschildCDAgrawalVEdbergSBGhazalHDecolaSThe use of MPSS for whole-genome transcriptional analysis in ArabidopsisGenome Res20041481641165310.1101/gr.2275604<?supplied-pmid 15289482?>15289482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>33.BrennerSJohnsonMBridghamJGoldaGLloydDHJohnsonDLuoSMcCurdySFoyMEwanMRothRGeorgeDEletrSAlbrechtGVermaasEWilliamsSRMoonKBurchamTPallasMDuBridgeRBKirchnerJFearonKMaoJCorcoranKGene expression analysis by massively parallel signature sequencing (MPSS) on microbead arraysNat Biotechnol200018663063410.1038/76469<?supplied-pmid 10835600?>10835600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>34.WangZXueXSunJLuoRXuXJiangYZhangQPanWAn “in-depth” description of the small non-coding RNA population of Schistosoma japonicum schistosomulumPLoS Negl Trop Dis201042e59610.1371/journal.pntd.0000596<?supplied-pmid 20161724?>20161724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>35.KatoMde LencastreAPincusZSlackFDynamic expression of small non-coding RNAs, including novel microRNAs and piRNAs/21U-RNAs, during Caenorhabditis elegans developmentGenome Biol2009105R5410.1186/gb-2009-10-5-r54<?supplied-pmid 19460142?>19460142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>36.EnrightAJJohnBGaulUTuschlTSanderCMarksDSMicroRNA targets in DrosophilaGenome Biol200351R110.1186/gb-2003-5-1-r1<?supplied-pmid 14709173?>14709173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>37.SperlingEAPetersonKJTelfordMJLittlewoodDTJmicroRNAs and metazoan phylogeny: big trees from little genesAnimal evolution-genomes, trees and fossils2009OxfordOxford University Press157170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>38.ErwinDHLaflammeMTweedtSMSperlingEAPisaniDPetersonKJThe Cambrian conundrum: early divergence and later ecological success in the early history of animalsScience201133460591091109710.1126/science.1206375<?supplied-pmid 22116879?>22116879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>39.AboobakerAATomancakPPatelNRubinGMLaiECDrosophila microRNAs exhibit diverse spatial expression patterns during embryonic developmentProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200510250180171802210.1073/pnas.0508823102<?supplied-pmid 16330759?>16330759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>40.Shalom-FeuersteinRSerrorLDe La ForestDSPetitIAberdamECamargoLDamourOVigourouxCSolomonAGaggioliCItskovitz-EldorJAhmadSAberdamDPluripotent stem cell model reveals essential roles for miR-450b-5p and miR-184 in embryonic corneal lineage specificationStem Cells201230589890910.1002/stem.1068<?supplied-pmid 22367714?>22367714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>41.NairzKRottigCRintelenFZdobnovEMoserMHafenEOvergrowth caused by misexpression of a microRNA with dispensable wild-type functionDev Biol2006291231432410.1016/j.ydbio.2005.11.047<?supplied-pmid 16443211?>16443211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>42.WheelerBMHeimbergAMMoyVNSperlingEAHolsteinTWHeberSPetersonKJThe deep evolution of metazoan microRNAsEvol Dev2009111506810.1111/j.1525-142X.2008.00302.x<?supplied-pmid 19196333?>19196333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>43.RiganoRButtariBProfumoEOrtonaEDelunardoFMarguttiPMatteiVTeggiASoriceMSiracusanoAEchinococcus granulosus antigen B impairs human dendritic cell differentiation and polarizes immature dendritic cell maturation towards a Th2 cell responseInfect Immun20077541667167810.1128/IAI.01156-06<?supplied-pmid 17210662?>17210662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>44.ChengGLuoRHuCCaoJJinYDeep sequencing-based identification of pathogen-specific microRNAs in the plasma of rabbits infected with Schistosoma japonicumParasitology2013140141751176110.1017/S0031182013000917<?supplied-pmid 23942009?>23942009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>45.BernalDTrelisMMontanerSCantalapiedraFGalianoAHackenbergMMarcillaASurface analysis of Dicrocoelium dendriticum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The molecular characterization of exosomes reveals the presence of miRNAsJ Proteomics201410523224110.1016/j.jprot.2014.02.012<?supplied-pmid 24561797?>24561797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>46.HolcmanBHeathDDThe early stages of Echinococcus granulosus developmentActa Trop1997641–251710.1016/S0001-706X(96)00636-5<?supplied-pmid 9095285?>9095285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>47.GiraldezAJCinalliRMGlasnerMEEnrightAJThomsonJMBaskervilleSHammondSMBartelDPSchierAFMicroRNAs regulate brain morphogenesis in zebrafishScience2005308572383383810.1126/science.1109020<?supplied-pmid 15774722?>15774722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>48.GiraldezAJMishimaYRihelJGrocockRJVan DongenSInoueKEnrightAJSchierAFZebrafish MiR-430 promotes deadenylation and clearance of maternal mRNAsScience20063125770757910.1126/science.1122689<?supplied-pmid 16484454?>16484454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>49.HunterSEFinneganEFZisoulisDGLovciMTMelnik-MartinezKVYeoGWPasquinelliAEFunctional genomic analysis of the let-7 regulatory network in Caenorhabditis elegansPLoS Genet201393e100335310.1371/journal.pgen.1003353<?supplied-pmid 23516374?>23516374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>50.SmythJDIn Vitro Cultivation Of Parasitic Helminths1990Boca RatonCRC Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>51.BethkeAFielenbachNWangZMangelsdorfDJAntebiANuclear hormone receptor regulation of microRNAs controls developmental progressionScience20093245923959810.1126/science.1164899<?supplied-pmid 19342589?>19342589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>52.HammellCMKarpXAmbrosVA feedback circuit involving let-7-family miRNAs and DAF-12 integrates environmental signals and developmental timing in Caenorhabditis elegansProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200910644186681867310.1073/pnas.0908131106<?supplied-pmid 19828440?>19828440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>53.LiJZhangCSLuGDWangJHWenHYanGQWeiXFLinRYMolecular characterization of a signal-regulated kinase homolog from Echinococcus granulosusChin Med J (Engl)2011124182838284422040489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>54.ZhangWLiJJonesMKZhangZZhaoLBlairDMcManusDPThe Echinococcus granulosus antigen B gene family comprises at least 10 unique genes in five subclasses which are differentially expressedPLoS Negl Trop Dis201048e78410.1371/journal.pntd.0000784<?supplied-pmid 20706625?>20706625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>55.ZhangWZhangZShiBLiJYouHTulsonGDangXSongYYimitiTWangJJonesMKMcManusDPVaccination of dogs against Echinococcus granulosus, the cause of cystic hydatid disease in humansJ Infect Dis2006194796697410.1086/506622<?supplied-pmid 16960785?>16960785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>56.WangWCLinFMChangWCLinKYHuangHDLinNSmiRExpress: analyzing high-throughput sequencing data for profiling microRNA expressionBMC Bioinformatics20091032810.1186/1471-2105-10-328<?supplied-pmid 19821977?>19821977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>57.LangmeadBTrapnellCPopMSalzbergSLUltrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genomeGenome Biol2009103R2510.1186/gb-2009-10-3-r25<?supplied-pmid 19261174?>19261174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>58.FriedlanderMRChenWAdamidiCMaaskolaJEinspanierRKnespelSRajewskyNDiscovering microRNAs from deep sequencing data using miRDeepNat Biotechnol200826440741510.1038/nbt1394<?supplied-pmid 18392026?>18392026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>59.GruberARLorenzRBernhartSHNeubockRHofackerILThe Vienna RNA websuiteNucleic Acids Res200836Web Server issueW707410.1093/nar/gkn188<?supplied-pmid 18424795?>18424795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>60.AmbrosVBartelBBartelDPBurgeCBCarringtonJCChenXDreyfussGEddySRGriffiths-JonesSMarshallMMatzkeMRuvkunGTuschlTA uniform system for microRNA annotationRNA20039327727910.1261/rna.2183803<?supplied-pmid 12592000?>12592000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>61.WangLFengZWangXZhangXDEGseq: an R package for identifying differentially expressed genes from RNA-seq dataBioinformatics201026113613810.1093/bioinformatics/btp612<?supplied-pmid 19855105?>19855105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>62.GrantGRLiuJStoeckertCJJrA practical false discovery rate approach to identifying patterns of differential expression in microarray dataBioinformatics200521112684269010.1093/bioinformatics/bti407<?supplied-pmid 15797908?>15797908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>63.ConesaAGotzSGarcia-GomezJMTerolJTalonMRoblesMBlast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics researchBioinformatics200521183674367610.1093/bioinformatics/bti610<?supplied-pmid 16081474?>16081474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>64.HosackDADennisGJrShermanBTLaneHCLempickiRAIdentifying biological themes within lists of genes with EASEGenome Biol2003410R7010.1186/gb-2003-4-10-r70<?supplied-pmid 14519205?>14519205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>65.MoriyaYItohMOkudaSYoshizawaACKanehisaMKAAS: an automatic genome annotation and pathway reconstruction serverNucleic Acids Res200735Web Server issueW18218510.1093/nar/gkm321<?supplied-pmid 17526522?>17526522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
