<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-6906</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-6914</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4262987</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25410596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0524-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Software</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Harvest suite for rapid core-genome alignment and visualization of thousands of intraspecific microbial genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Treangen</surname><given-names>Todd J</given-names></name><address><email>treangent@nbacc.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ondov</surname><given-names>Brian D</given-names></name><address><email>ondovb@nbacc.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>Sergey</given-names></name><address><email>korens@nbacc.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Phillippy</surname><given-names>Adam M</given-names></name><address><email>phillippya@nbacc.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">National Biodefense Analysis and Countermeasures Center, 110 Thomas Johnson Drive, Frederick, MD 21702 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>524</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Treangen et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome sequences are now available for many microbial species and clades, however existing whole-genome alignment methods are limited in their ability to perform sequence comparisons of multiple sequences simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here we present the Harvest suite of core-genome alignment and visualization tools for the rapid and simultaneous analysis of thousands of intraspecific microbial strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Harvest includes Parsnp, a fast core-genome multi-aligner, and Gingr, a dynamic visual platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Together they provide interactive core-genome alignments, variant calls, recombination detection, and phylogenetic trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Using simulated and real data we demonstrate that our approach exhibits unrivaled speed while maintaining the accuracy of existing methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The Harvest suite is open-source and freely available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://github.com/marbl/harvest">http://github.com/marbl/harvest</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13059-014-0524-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Rationale </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Microbial genomes represent over 93% of past sequencing projects, with the current total over 10,000 and growing exponentially. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Multiple clades of draft and complete genomes comprising hundreds of closely related strains are now available from public databases [1], largely due to an increase in sequencing-based outbreak studies [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The quality of future genomes is also set to improve as short-read assemblers mature [3] and long-read sequencing enables finishing at greatly reduced costs [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>One direct benefit of high-quality genomes is that they empower comparative genomic studies based on multiple genome alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Multiple genome alignment is a fundamental tool in genomics essential for tracking genome evolution [6–8], accurate inference of recombination [9–14], identification of genomic islands [15,16], analysis of mobile genetic elements [17,18], comprehensive classification of homology [19,20], ancestral genome reconstruction [21], and phylogenomic analyses [22–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The task of whole-genome alignment is to create a catalog of relationships between the sequences of each genome (ortholog, paralog, xenolog, and so on [25]) to reveal their evolutionary history [26,27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>While several tools exist (LS-BSR [28], Magic [29], Mavid [30], Mauve [31–33], MGA [34], M-GCAT [35], Mugsy [36], TBA [37], multi-LAGAN [38], PECAN [39]), multiple genome alignment remains a challenging task due to the prevalence of horizontal gene transfer [26,40], recombination, homoplasy, gene conversion, mobile genetic elements, pseudogenization, and convoluted orthology relationships [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In addition, the computational burden of multiple sequence alignment remains very high [41] despite recent progress [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The current influx of microbial sequencing data necessitates methods for large-scale comparative genomics and shifts the focus towards scalability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Current microbial genome alignment methods focus on all-versus-all progressive alignment [31,36] to detect subset relationships (that is, gene gain/loss), but these methods are bounded at various steps by quadratic time complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This exponential growth in compute time prohibits comparisons involving thousands of genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Chan and Ragan [43] reiterated this point, emphasizing that current phylogenomic methods, such as multiple alignment, will not scale with the increasing number of genomes, and that ‘alignment-free’ or exact alignment methods must be used to analyze such datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>However, such approaches do not come without compromising phylogenetic resolution [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Core-genome alignment is a subset of whole-genome alignment, focused on identifying the set of orthologous sequence conserved in all aligned genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the exponential complexity of multiple alignment, core-genome alignment is inherently more scalable because it ignores subset relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In addition, the core genome contains essential genes that are often vertically inherited and most likely to have the strongest signal-to-noise ratio for inferring phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The most reliable variants for building such phylogenies are single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Thus, core-genome SNP typing is currently the standard method for reconstructing large phylogenies of closely related microbes [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Currently, there are three paradigms for core-genome SNP typing based on read mapping, k-mer analyses, and whole-genome alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Read-based methods have dominated the bioinformatics methods landscape since the invention of high-fidelity, short-read sequencing (50 to 300 bp) [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This has made it very affordable to sequence, yet extremely challenging to produce finished genomes [47,48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Thus, comparative genomics has turned to highly efficient and accurate read mapping algorithms to carry out assembly-free analyses, spawning many mapping tools [49–52] and variant callers [53–55] for detecting SNPs and short Indels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Read-based variant calling typically utilizes a finished reference genome and a sensitive read mapper (BWA [51], Smalt), variant caller (samtools/bcftools [55], GATK [53]), and variant filter (minimum mapping quality, core genomic regions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This method has been shown effective in practice [56] and does not rely on assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, mapping requires the read data, which is not always available and can be orders of magnitude larger than the genomes themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In addition, mapping can be sensitive to contaminant, overlook structural variation, misalign low-complexity and repetitive sequence, and introduce systematic bias in phylogenetic reconstruction [57–59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Exact alignment methods, often formulated as k-mer matching, can produce high precision results in a fraction of the time required for gapped alignment methods [60–62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Spectral k-mer approaches have been used to estimate genome similarity [63], and k-mer based methods are commonly used to identify or cluster homologous genomic sequence [64,65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Recently, k-mers have also been extended to SNP identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>kSNP [66] identifies odd-length k-mers between multiple samples that match at all but the central position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The matched k-mers are then mapped back to a reference genome to locate putative SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Conveniently, this approach is suitable for both assembled genomes and read sets, but sensitivity is sacrificed for the improved efficiency of exact alignment [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Genome assembly [4,68–75], followed by whole-genome alignment [38,76,77], is the original method for variant detection between closely related bacterial genomes [78] and has been shown to perform well across multiple sequencing platforms [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In addition to SNPs, whole-genome alignment is able to reliably identify insertions and deletions (Indels) and other forms of structural variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Thus, whole-genome alignment is the gold standard for comprehensive variant identification, but relies on highly accurate and continuous assemblies, which can be expensive to generate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Lastly, and unlike reference mapping, whole-genome alignment is not easily parallelized or scaled to many genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Specifically for the task of whole-genome SNP typing, the choice of read- or genome-based methods can often depend on data availability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For example, of the 24,000 bacterial genomes currently in NCBI RefSeq [80], only 55% have associated SRA read data and analysis of the remaining 45% requires genome-based methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Thankfully, recent advances in both sequencing technology and assembly algorithms are making microbial genomes more complete than ever before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Modern de Bruijn assemblers like SPAdes [81] are able to generate high-quality assemblies from short reads [3], and long read technologies have enabled the automated finishing of microbial genomes for under $1,000 [82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>With the number of publically available genomes currently doubling every 18 months [1], and genome quality improving with the arrival of new technologies, we set out to solve the problem of aligning thousands of closely-related whole genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Rapid core-genome alignment and visualization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Here we present Parsnp and Gingr for the construction and interactive visualization of massive core-genome alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For alignment, Parsnp combines the advantages of both whole-genome alignment and read mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Like whole-genome alignment, Parsnp accurately aligns microbial genomes to identify both structural and point variations, but like read mapping, Parsnp scales to thousands of closely related genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To achieve this scalability, Parsnp is based on a suffix graph data structure for the rapid identification of maximal unique matches (MUMs), which serve as a common foundation to many pairwise [76,77,83] and multiple genome alignment tools [31–36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Parsnp uses MUMs to both recruit similar genomes and anchor the multiple alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>As input, Parsnp takes a directory of MultiFASTA files to be aligned; and as output, Parsnp produces a core-genome alignment, variant calls, and a SNP tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>These outputs can then be visually explored using Gingr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The details of Parsnp and Gingr are described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>MUMi recruitment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Parsnp is designed for intraspecific alignments and requires input genomes to be highly similar (for example, within the same subspecies group or &gt; =97% average nucleotide identity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For novel genomes or an inaccurate taxonomy, which genomes meet this criterion is not always known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To automatically identify genomes suitable for alignment, Parsnp uses a recruitment strategy based on the MUMi distance [84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Only genomes within a specified MUMi distance threshold are recruited into the full alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Compressed suffix graph </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Parsnp utilizes a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) data structure, called a Compressed Suffix Graph (CSG), to index the reference genome for efficient identification of multi-MUMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>CSGs have the unique property of representing an optimally compressed structure, in terms of number of nodes and edges, while maintaining all intrinsic properties of a Suffix Tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>CSGs were originally proposed as a more space-efficient alternative to Suffix Trees and first implemented in M-GCAT [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Node and edge compression of the Suffix Tree incurs a linear-time construction penalty, but facilitates faster traversal of the structure once built. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Provided sufficient memory, the CSG can be used to align genomes of any size; however, the current implementation has been optimized for microbial genomes, requiring approximately 32 bytes per reference base for CSG construction and 15 bytes per base for the aligned genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Note that because multi-MUMs are necessarily present in all genomes, the choice of a reference genome has no effect on the resulting alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Multi-MUM search </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Once built for the reference genome, all additional genomes are streamed through the CSG, enabling rapid, linear-time identification of MUMs shared across all genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>A divide-and-conquer algorithm, adapted from M-GCAT [35], recursively searches for smaller matches and iteratively refines the multi-MUMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Next, locally collinear blocks (LCBs) of multi-MUMs are identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These LCBs form the basis of the core-genome alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Parallelized LCB alignment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The multi-MUMs within LCBs are used to anchor multiple alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Gaps between collinear multi-MUMs are aligned in parallel using MUSCLE [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To avoid the unnecessary overhead of reading and writing MultiFASTA alignment files, Parsnp makes direct library calls via a MUSCLE API. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The MUSCLE library is packaged with Parsnp, but originally sourced from the Mauve code base [86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>As with Mauve, MUSCLE is used to compute an accurate gapped alignment between the match anchors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Though MUSCLE alignment can be computationally expensive, for highly similar genomes, the gaps between collinear multi-MUMs are typically very short (for example, a single SNP column in the degenerate case). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>SNP filtering and trees </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The final Parsnp multiple alignment contains all SNP, Indel, and structural variation within the core genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>However, given their ubiquity in microbial genome analyses, Parsnp performs additional processing of the core-genome SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>First, all polymorphic columns in the multiple alignment are flagged to identify: (1) repetitive sequence; (2) small LCB size; (3) poor alignment quality; (4) poor base quality; and (5) possible recombination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Alignment quality is determined by a threshold of the number of SNPs and Indels contained within a given window size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Base quality is optionally determined using FreeBayes [54] to measure read support and mixed alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Bases likely to have undergone recent recombination are identified using PhiPack [87]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Only columns passing a set of filters based on these criteria are considered reliable core-genome SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The final set of core-genome SNPs is given to FastTree2 [88] for reconstruction of the whole-genome phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Compressed alignment file </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>For simplicity and storage efficiency, the output of Parsnp includes a single binary file encoding the reference genome, annotations, alignment, variants, and tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Thousand-fold compression of the alignment is achieved by storing only the columns that contain variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The full multiple alignment can be faithfully reconstructed from this reference-compressed representation on demand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Since Parsnp focuses on aligning only core blocks of relatively similar genomes, the number of variant columns tends to increase at a sub-linear rate as the number of genomes increases, resulting in huge space savings versus alternative multiple alignment formats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Conversion utilities are provided for importing/exporting common formats to/from the binary archive file, including: BED, GenBank, FASTA, MAF, Newick, VCF, and XMFA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Interactive visualization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Developed in tandem with Parsnp, the visualization tool Gingr allows for interactive exploration of trees and alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In addition to the compressed alignment format, Gingr accepts standard alignment formats and can serve as a general-purpose multiple alignment viewer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Uniquely, Gingr is capable of providing dynamic exploration of alignments comprising thousands of genomes and millions of alignment columns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>It is the first tool of its kind capable of dynamically visualizing multiple alignments of this scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The alignment can be seamlessly zoomed from a display of variant density (at the genome level) to a full representation of the multiple alignment (at the nucleotide level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>For exploration of phyletic patterns, the alignment is simultaneously presented along with the core-genome SNP tree, annotations, and dynamic variant highlighting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The tree can be zoomed by clade, or individual genomes selected to expand via a fisheye zoom. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Structural variation across the genome can also be displayed using Sybil coloring [89], where a color gradient represents the location and orientation of each LCB with respect to the reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This is useful for identifying structurally variant regions of the core. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of performance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We evaluated Parsnp on three simulated datasets (derived from Escherichia coli (E. coli) K-12 W3110) and three real datasets (Streptococcus pneumoniae, Peptoclostridium difficile, and Mycobacterium tuberculosis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Parsnp is compared below versus two whole-genome alignment methods (Mugsy, Mauve), a k-mer based method (kSNP), and two commonly used mapping pipelines (based on Smalt and BWA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The Smalt pipeline replicates the methods of the landmark Harris et al. paper [90] that has been adopted in many subsequent studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The BWA pipeline is similar to the Smalt pipeline, but uses BWA for read mapping (Materials and methods). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Simulated E. coli W3110 dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To precisely measure the accuracy of multiple tools across varying levels of divergence, we computationally evolved the genome of E. coli K-12 W3110 at three different mutation rates: 0.00001 (low), 0.0001 (medium), and 0.001 (high) SNPs per site, per branch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>An average of 10 rearrangements were introduced, per genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Each dataset comprises 32 simulated genomes, forming a perfect binary tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Approximately 65X coverage of Illumina MiSeq reads was simulated and assembled for each genome to create draft assemblies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>For input, the whole-genome alignment programs were given the draft assemblies, and the mapping pipelines the raw reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: Figure S1 details the computational performance on the simulated datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Parsnp was the only method to finish in fewer than 10 min on the 32-genome dataset, with the other methods requiring between 30 min to 10 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Table 1 gives the accuracy of each tool on each dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The tools were benchmarked using true-positive and false-positive rates compared to a known truth, which captures the full alignment accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 plots the performance of all tools averaged across all mutation rates.Table 1Core-genome SNP accuracy for simulated E. coli datasets  Method  Description a  FP Low  FN Low  FP Med  FN Med  FP High  FN High  TPR  FDR Mauve WGA 1483181982,87710030,3780.9740.0004Mauve (c) WGA 0023866490.9990Mugsy WGA 1,261b 3951,9283,3711,33534,9230.9700.0036Mugsy (c) WGA 20201810.9990Parsnp CGA 23423453,494735,4660.9700.0001Parsnp (c) CGA 0240603010,9890.9920kSNP KMER 25960090819,7301,968916,1270.2800.0086Smalt MAP 3311001,3075522,9570.9810.0001BWA MAP 0168161,9472727,0910.97750.0000Data shown indicates performance metrics of the evaluated methods on the three simulated E. coli datasets (low, medium, and high). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Method: Tool used.(c) indicates aligner ran on closed genomes rather than draft assemblies.False positive (FP) and false negative (FN) counts for the three mutation rates (low, med, and high). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>True positive rate TPR: TP/(TP + FN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>False discovery rate FDR: FP/(TP + FP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>A total of 1,299,178 SNPs were introduced into the 32-genome dataset, across all three mutational rates. aParadigm employed by each method. bMugsy’s lower precision was traced to a paralog misalignment that resulted in many false-positive SNPs. CGA: core genome alignment, FN, number of truth SNP calls not detected, FP, number of SNP calls that are not in truth set, KMER: k-mer based SNP calls, MAP: read mapping, TP: number of SNP calls that agreed with the truth, WGA: whole-genome alignment.Figure 1 Core-genome SNP accuracy for simulated E. coli datasets. Results are averaged across low, medium, and high mutation rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Red squares denote alignment-based SNP calls on draft assemblies, green squares alignment-based SNP calls on closed genomes, and blue triangles for read mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Full results for each dataset are given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The whole-genome alignment methods performed comparably across all three mutation rates (Figure 1, red squares), with Mauve exhibiting the highest sensitivity (97.42%) and Parsnp the highest precision (99.99%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In addition, Parsnp identified 98% the rearrangement breakpoints within 1% of the rearrangement length (+/- 50 bp) with no breakpoint spans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Mugsy demonstrated slightly higher sensitivity than Parsnp but with lower precision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Mugsy’s lower precision was traced to a single fumA paralog [91] misalignment that generated a high number of false-positive SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>All genome alignment methods were affected by misalignment of repeats and missing or low-quality bases in the assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Performance of the individual methods was also measured in terms of branch SNP and length error with respect to the true phylogeny (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>These errors closely followed the false-negative and false-positive rates of each method, with no distinguishable pattern or branch biases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>On draft genomes, precise methods such as Parsnp yielded underestimates of branch lengths while more aggressive methods like Mugsy resulted in more overestimates (outliers not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The aggressive methods also showed more variance in performance across branches.Figure 2 Branch errors for simulated E. coli datasets. Simulated E. coli trees are shown for medium mutation rate (0.0001 per base per branch). (A) shows branch length errors as bars, with overestimates of branch length above each branch and underestimates below each branch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Maximum overestimate of branch length was 2.15% (bars above each branch) and maximum underestimate was 4.73% (bars below each branch). (B) shows branch SNP errors as bars, with false-positive errors above each branch and false-negative errors below each branch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The maximum FP SNP value is 6 (bars above each branch) and maximum FN SNP value is 23 (bars below each branch). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Note that the bar heights have been normalized by the maximum value for each tree and are not comparable across trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Outlier results from Mugsy were excluded from the branch length plot, and kSNP results are not shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>All genome alignment methods performed similarly on closed genomes, with Mauve and Mugsy exhibiting the best sensitivity (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Comparison on closed genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Mugsy, Mauve, and Parsnp all performed similarly on finished genomes (Figures 1 and 2, green squares), offering a significant boost in sensitivity over both draft assemblies and reference mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Mugsy, Mauve, and Parsnp all exhibited near perfect false-discovery rates (FDR), with Parsnp being the only method to not report a single false positive across the three datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Both Mauve and Mugsy were similarly near-perfect in terms of true-positive rates (TPR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The drop in sensitivity (0.9%) for Parsnp on full genomes can be explained by a lack of an LCB extension method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Mugsy was the most affected by draft genomes, going from best on closed genomes to demonstrating more false positives (Table 1) and LCB counts (Table 2) on draft genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Parsnp offered the overall best FDR of the genome alignment methods, and the fewest number of LCBs, averaged across both draft and closed genome datasets.Table 2 Comparison of locally collinear alignment block (LCB) count for simulated E. coli datasets, on assembled and finished genomes  Method  Low  Medium  High Mauve325363519Mauve (c)150174333Mugsy10,97711,19416,632Mugsy (c)237247351Parsnp205271344Parsnp (c)139190506Method: Tool used.(c) indicates aligner ran on closed genomes rather than draft assemblies.Low: &gt;99.99% similarity, Medium: &gt;99.9% similarity, High: &gt;99% similarity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Comparison to read mapping methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>On average, mapping-based methods were as precise and 0.5% to 1% more sensitive than alignment of draft genomes (Figure 1, blue triangles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Smalt showed the highest sensitivity, while BWA was the most specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The precision of the mapping approaches may be overestimated for this dataset due to the absence of non-core sequence that is known to confound mapping [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Parsnp was the only genome alignment method to match the precision of mapping, but with a slight reduction in sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>However, when provided with finished genomes, the whole-genome alignment methods excel in both sensitivity and specificity compared to read mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Thus, the performance divide between whole-genome alignment and mapping is entirely due to assembly quality and completeness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Using short reads, both the mapping and assembly-based approaches suffer false negatives due to ambiguous mappings or collapsed repeats, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Exceeding 99% sensitivity for this test set requires either longer reads (for mapping) or complete genomes (for alignment) to accurately identify SNPs in the repetitive regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Comparison on 31 Streptococcus pneumoniae genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Parsnp was compared to whole-genome alignment methods using the 31-genome S. pneumoniae dataset presented in the original Mugsy publication [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Angiuoli and Salzberg compared Mugsy, Mauve, and Nucmer + TBA to measure the number of LCBs and size of the core genome aligned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>On this dataset, Parsnp aligns 90% of the bases aligned by Mugsy, while using 50% fewer LCBs (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In addition, Parsnp ran hundreds of times faster than the other methods, finishing this 31-way alignment in less than 60 s.Table 3 Comparison to the 31  S. pneumoniae Mugsy benchmark  Method  Time  Core (bp)  LCBs Parsnp0.3 min1,428,4071,171Mugsy100 min1,590,8202,394Mauve377 min1,568,7151,366NUCmer + TBA80 min1,457,57527,075Time: Method runtime from input to output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Core: Size of the aligned core genome measured in base pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>LCBs: Number of locally colinear blocks in the alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Peptoclostridium difficile outbreak in the UK </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Parsnp and Gingr are particularly suited for outbreak analyses of infectious diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate this, we applied Parsnp to a recent P. difficile outbreak dataset [92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>To generate input suitable for Parsnp, we assembled all genomes using iMetAMOS [93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that this was a resequencing project not intended for assembly and represents a worst case for a core-genome alignment approach; reads ranged from 50 to 100 bp in length and some genomes were sequenced without paired ends. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The 826-way core genome alignment resulted in 1.4 Gbp being aligned in less than 5 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The core genome represented 40% of the P. difficile 630 reference genome, consistent with previous findings [94]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Specifically, previous microarray experiments have indicated that 39% of the total CDS in the evaluated P. difficile clade pertains to the core genome (1% less than identified by Parsnp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows a Gingr visualization of the 826-way alignment and clade phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Related outbreak clusters are immediately visible from the phyletic patterns of the alignment, confirming the primary clades of the tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In addition, the SNP heatmap highlights the phyletic signature of several subclades, in this case within the known hpdBCA operon [95] that is extremely well conserved across all 826 genomes.Figure 3 Gingr visualization of 826 P. difficile genomes aligned with Parsnp. The leaves of the reconstructed phylogenetic tree (left) are paired with their corresponding rows in the multi-alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>A genome has been selected (rectangular aqua highlight), resulting in a fisheye zoom of several leaves and their rows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>A SNP density plot (center) reveals the phylogenetic signature of several clades, in this case within the fully-aligned hpd operon (hpdB, hpdC, hpdA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The light gray regions flanking the operon indicate unaligned sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>When fully zoomed (right), individual bases and SNPs can be inspected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 shows a zoomed view of the 826 P. difficile genome alignment in Gingr, highlighting a single annotated gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Although no metadata is publically available for this outbreak dataset, we identified that bacA, a gene conferring antibiotic resistance to bacitracin, is conserved in all 826 isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>While alternative antibiotic treatments for P. difficile infections have been well-studied over the past 20 to 30 years [96], a recent study reported that 100% of 276 clinical isolates had high-level resistance to bacitracin [97]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In concordance with this study, our results indicate there may be widespread bacitracin resistance across this outbreak dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Thus alternative antibiotics, such as vancomycin, could represent better treatment options.Figure 4 Conserved presence of bacA antiobiotic resistance gene in P. difficile outbreak. Gingr visualization of conserved bacitracin resistance gene within the Parsnp alignment of 826 P. difficile genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Vertical lines indicate SNPs, providing visual support of subclades within this outbreak dataset. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Mycobacterium tuberculosis geographic spread </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>For a second case evaluation, we ran Parsnp on a M. tuberculosis global diversity dataset [98]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In this case, the raw SNP calls were kindly made available (Iñaki Comas, personal communication), facilitating a direct comparison to the published results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The variant pipeline of Comas et al. is similar to our BWA pipeline, but with all SNP calls intersected with MAQ SNPfilter, which discards any SNP with neighboring Indels ±3 bp or surrounded by &gt;3 SNPs within a 10 bp window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>To replicate this study using whole-genome alignment, we assembled all genomes from the raw reads using iMetAMOS and ran Parsnp on the resulting draft assemblies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Figure 5 summarizes the results of the comparison and Figure 6 shows a Gingr visualization of the resulting tree and alignment, with major clades confirmed by correlations in the SNP density display.Figure 5 Comparison of Parsnp and Comas et al. result on M. tuberculosis dataset. A Venn diagram displays SNPs unique to Comas et al. [98] (left, blue), unique to Parsnp (right, red), and shared between the two analyses (middle, brown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>On top, an unrooted reference phylogeny is given based on the intersection of shared SNPs produced by both methods (90,295 SNPs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>On bottom, the phylogenies of Comas et al. (left) and Parsnp (right) are given. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Pairs of trees are annotated with their Robinson-Foulds distance (RFD) and percentage of shared splits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The Comas et al. and Parsnp trees are largely concordant with each other and the reference phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>All major clades are shared and well supported by all three trees.Figure 6 Gingr visualization of 171  M. tuberculosis genomes aligned with Parsnp. The visual layout is the same as Figure 3, but unlike Figure 3, a SNP density plot across the entire genome is displayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Major clades are visible as correlated SNP densities across the length of the genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Given a lack of truth for this dataset, we constructed a reference phylogeny based on the intersection of the Parsnp and Comas et al. SNP sets, which excludes potential false positives produced by only one of the methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the accuracy of phylogenetic reconstruction by measuring the Robinson-Foulds distance [99] and calculating the number of shared splits between the resulting trees (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The Parsnp generated phylogeny has a higher percentage of shared splits with the reference phylogeny (94.1% versus 92.3% for Comas), while both methods exhibited a similar Robinson-Foulds distance to the reference phylogeny (0.0007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>When compared directly, Parsnp was found to share 90,295 of its 104,896 SNPs calls (86%) and 19,838 of its 22,131 SNP positions (90%) with the Comas et al. study, resulting in 90.5% shared splits between the reconstructed phylogenies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We further investigated the SNP calls unique to either Parsnp or Comas and found that the majority formed a few well-defined splits that were largely consistent with the reference phylogeny (Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>These SNPs are likely true positives that were missed by one of the two methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>A smaller fraction of unique SNPs formed single-genome splits, representing potential false positives due to sequencing or mapping error (1,503 for Parsnp, 3,016 for Comas). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Runtime and storage analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>To evaluate Parsnp’s scalability, we profiled performance across six datasets ranging from 32 genomes to 10,000 genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Runtime was observed to increase linearly with additional genomes (Additional file 1: Figure S2), requiring a few minutes for the 32 genome E. coli dataset, 1.5 h for the 826 genome P. difficile dataset, and a maximum of roughly 14 h to align the 10,000 genome set on a 2.2 GHz, 32-core, 1 TB RAM server (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In addition, for the 32-genome simulated E. coli datasets, Parsnp was 10 to 100 times faster than all other methods evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Maximum memory usage was 2 GB for the 145 Mbp E. coli dataset and 309 GB for the 21 Gbp S. pneumoniae dataset (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Memory usage can be explicitly limited via a command-line parameter (−−max-partition-size) but this results in increased runtime.Table 4 Performance profile of Parsnp runtime (MUM + alignment) on all evaluated datasets  Dataset  Num Genomes a  Aligned b (Mbp)  MUM c (min)  MUSCLE d (min)  Total e (min)  Mem f (GB)  E. coli (avg)321422242 M. tuberculosis 17142412203214 P. difficile 8261,39246398571 S. aureus SIM 10,00021,000668201869309Results were generated on a 32-core, 2.2 GHz, 1 TB RAM Linux server. Dataset: the genome set. aThe number of genomes aligned. bTotal Mbp aligned. cThe time spent finding maximal unique matches. dThe time spent performing gapped multi-alignment with MUSCLE. eTotal Parsnp runtime (sum of MUM and MUSCLE). fMaximum memory usage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In addition to runtime efficiency, Parsnp requires much less storage than the other approaches due to its binary alignment format and the compressive effect of assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>For the 32-genome E. coli dataset, Parsnp’s output totals just 4.5 MB, compared to 13 GB required to store compressed FASTQ [100] and VCF [101] files and 149 MB to store XMFA [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Storage reductions are amplified for larger datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>For example, the raw read data for the P. difficile dataset requires 1.4 TB of storage (0.6 TB compressed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Assembling these data reduces the total to 3.3 GB by removing the redundancy of the reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The XMFA alignment of these assemblies is 1.4 GB, and reference-compressed binary format occupies just 15 MB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This equates to roughly a 100,000X (lossy) compression factor from raw reads to compressed archive, requiring only 0.08 bits per base to store the full core-genome alignment plus other related information, which is competitive with related techniques like CRAM [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>As outbreak studies continue to expand in scale, whole-genome assembly and alignment presents a sustainable alternative to the current mapping-based strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Parsnp is orders of magnitude faster than current methods for whole-genome alignment and SNP typing, but it is not without limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Parsnp represents a compromise between whole-genome alignment and read mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Compared to whole-genome aligners, Parsnp is less flexible because it is designed to conservatively align the core genome and is less sensitive as a result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Additionally, Parsnp is currently limited to intraspecific analysis of closely-related species and strains; future improvements will target more sensitive match detection for increased tolerance of divergent genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Compared to read mapping, Parsnp is less robust and requires high-quality assemblies to maximize sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Thus, the right tool depends on the data and task at hand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Core-genome alignment and phylogeny reconstruction are critical to microbial forensics and modern epidemiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>When finished or high-quality genomes are available, Parsnp is both efficient and accurate for these tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In addition, even for fragmented draft assemblies, Parsnp exhibits a favorable compromise between sensitivity and specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, Parsnp matched the specificity of the mapping-based approaches on the simulated datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>However, multiplexed short-read sequencing followed by mapping still remains the most economical approach for sensitive analysis of large strain collections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, whole-genome alignment depends on genome assemblies for variant detection; the accuracy of these methods for SNP calling is directly proportional to the quality of the assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Thus, Parsnp is recommended for analyzing high-quality assemblies or when raw read data are not available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Assembled genomes have a number of advantages over read data - primarily compression and convenience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Storing, sharing, and analyzing raw read datasets incurs significant overhead from the redundancy in sequencing (often 100-fold), and this burden nearly resulted in the closure of the NCBI SRA database [103]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Adding additional orders of magnitude to the already exponential growth of sequencing data is not sustainable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Instead, information in the reads not currently stored in common assembly formats (for example, allelic variants) should be propagated to the assembled representation, forming a compressed, but nearly lossless format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In this way, genomes could be shared in their native, assembled format, saving both space and time of analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Here, we have taken a small step in that direction by identifying low quality bases, as computed by FreeBayes [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>This allows filtering of low quality and mixed alleles and improves the specificity of the assembly-based approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>However, more comprehensive, graph-based formats are needed to capture the full population information contained in the raw reads. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Parsnp was also built around the observation that high-quality, finished genome sequences have become more common as sequencing technology and assembly algorithms continue to improve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>New technologies, such as PacBio SMRT sequencing [104] are enabling the generation of reference-grade sequences at extremely reduced costs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This presents another opportunity for Parsnp - the construction and maintenance of core genomes and trees for clinically important species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>With well-defined reference cores, outbreaks could be accurately typed in real-time by mapping sequences directly to the tree using phylogenetically aware methods such as pplacer [105] or PAGAN [106]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Such a phylogenetic approach would be preferable to alternative typing schemes based on loosely defined notions of similarity, such as pulse-field electrophoresis (PFGE) [107] and multi-locus sequence typing (MLST) [108]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Parsnp offers a highly efficient method for aligning the core genome of thousands of closely related species, and Gingr provides a flexible, interactive visualization tool for the exploration of huge trees and alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Together, they enable analyses not previously possible with whole-genome aligners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated that Parsnp provides highly specific variant calls, even for highly fragmented draft genomes, and can efficiently reconstruct recent outbreak analyses including hundreds of whole genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Future improvements in genome assembly quality and formats will enable comprehensive cataloging of microbial population variation, including both point and structural mutations, using genome alignment methods such as Parsnp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Software and configurations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Mugsy [36] v1.23 and Mauve Aligner [31,33] v2.3.1 were run using default parameters on assembled sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>mauveAligner was selected instead of progressiveMauve due to improved performance on the simulated E. coli datasets, which do not contain subset relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>kSNP v2.0 [66] was run with a k-mer size of 25 on both the raw read data and the assemblies; the assemblies were merged with Ns using the provided merge_fasta_contigs.pl utility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Raw MAF/XMFA/VCF output was parsed to recover SNPs and build MultiFASTA files. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Smalt version 0.7.5 was run with default parameters for paired reads, mirroring the pipeline used in several recent SNP typing studies [90,109–111]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Samtools view was used to filter for alignments with mapping qualities greater than or equal to 30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Variants were called by piping samtools mpileup output into bcftools view with the -v (variants only), -g (genotype) and -I (skip Indels) flags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Variants were then filtered with VCFUtils varFilter with the -d (minimum read depth) parameter set to 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Variants for all samples of each set were called concomitantly by providing samtools mpileup with all BAM files. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>BWA [52] was run in its standard paired-end alignment mode with default parameters, using aln to align each set of ends and sampe to produce a combined SAM file. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Samtools view was used to filter for alignments with mapping qualities greater than or equal to 30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Variants were called by piping samtools mpileup output into bcftools view with the -v (variants only), -g (genotype) and -I (skip Indels) flags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Variants were then filtered with VCFUtils varFilter with the -d (minimum read depth) parameter set to 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>As with Smalt, variants for all samples of each set were called concomitantly by providing samtools mpileup with all BAM files. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>FastTree v2 [88] was used to reconstruct phylogenies using default parameters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>E. coli K-12 W3110 simulated dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The complete genome of E. coli K-12 W3110 [112], was downloaded from RefSeq (AC_000091). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>This genome was used as the ancestral genome and evolution was simulated along a balanced tree for three evolutionary rates using the Seq-Gen package [113] with parameters mHKY -t4.0 -l4646332 -n1 -k1 and providing the corresponding binary tree evolved at three evolutionary rates: 0.00001, 0.0001, and 0.001 SNPs per site, per branch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>This corresponds to a minimum percent identity of approximately 99%, 99.9%, and 99.99% between the two most divergent genomes, respectively, reflecting the variation seen in typical outbreak analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>No small (&lt;5 bp) or large Indels were introduced, but an average of 10 1 Kbp rearrangements (inversions and translocations) were added, per genome, using a custom script [114]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Paired reads were simulated to model current MiSeq lengths (2 × 150 bp) and error rates (1%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Moderate coverage, two million PE reads (64X coverage), was simulated for each of the 32 samples using wgsim (default parameters, no Indels), from samtools package version 0.1.17 [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Two of the simulated read sets were independently run through iMetAMOS [93] to automatically determine the best assembler. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The consensus pick across both datasets was SPAdes version 3.0 [81], which was subsequently run on the remaining 30 simulated read sets using default parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The final contigs and scaffolds files were used as input to the genome alignment methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>For mapping methods, the raw simulated reads were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>For accuracy comparisons, Indels were ignored and called SNPs were required to be unambiguously aligned across all 32 genomes (that is, not part of a subset relationship; SNPs present but part of a subset relationship were ignored). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>S. pneumoniae dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>A full listing of accession numbers for the 31-genome S. pneumoniae dataset is described in [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>For scalability testing, Streptococcus pneumoniae TIGR4 (NC_003028.3) was used to create a pseudo-outbreak clade involving 10,000 genomes evolved along a star phylogeny with on average 10 SNPs per genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>M. tuberculosis dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>We downloaded and assembled sequencing data from a recently published study of M. tuberculosis [98]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A total of 225 runs corresponding to project ERP001731 were downloaded from NCBI SRA and assembled using the iMetAMOS ensemble of SPAdes, MaSuRCA, and Velvet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The iMetAMOS assembly for each sample can be replicated with the following commands, which will automatically download the data for RUN_ID directly from SRA:&gt; initPipeline -d asmTB -W iMetAMOS -m RUN_ID -i 200:800&gt; runPipeline -d asmTB -a spades,masurca,velvet -p 16 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The M. tuberculosis dataset included a mix of single and paired-end runs with a sequence length in the range of 51 to 108 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The average k-mer size selected for unpaired data was 26, resulting in an average of 660 contigs and an N50 size of 17 Kbp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>For paired-end data, the average selected k-mer was 35, resulting in an average of 333 contigs and an N50 size of 43 Kbp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Assemblies containing more than 2,000 contigs, or 1.5X larger/smaller than the reference genome, were removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The final dataset was reduced to 171 genomes, limited to labeled strains that could be confidently matched to the strains used in the Comas et al. study for SNP and phylogenetic comparison. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>P. difficile dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Note, Clostridium difficile was recently renamed to Peptoclostridium difficile [115]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>We downloaded and assembled sequencing data from a recently published study of P. difficile [92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>A total of 825 runs corresponding to project ERP003850 were downloaded from NCBI SRA [86] and assembled within iMetAMOS this time only using SPAdes, which was identified as the best performer on the M. tuberculosis dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>The iMetAMOS assembly for each sample can be replicated with the following commands, which will download the data for RUN_ID directly from SRA:&gt; initPipeline -d asmPD -W iMetAMOS -m RUN_ID -i 200:800&gt; runPipeline -d asmPD -a spades -p 16 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The P. difficile dataset included paired-end runs with a sequence length in the range of 51 to 100 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SPAdes was selected as the assembler and run with k-mer sizes of 21, 33, 55, and 77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The assemblies had an average of 660 contigs and an N50 size of 138 Kbp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Assemblies containing more than 2,000 contigs, or 1.5X larger/smaller than the reference genome, were removed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Data and software availability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>All data, supplementary files, assemblies, packaged software binaries and scripts described in the manuscript are available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cbcb.umd.edu/software/harvest">https://www.cbcb.umd.edu/software/harvest</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The python script used to introduce rearrangements into the simulated genomes is also available for download at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/marbl/parsnp/tree/master/script">https://github.com/marbl/parsnp/tree/master/script</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Source code of the described software, including Parsnp and Gingr, is available for download from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://github.com/marbl/harvest">http://github.com/marbl/harvest</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec27"><title>Additional file</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13059_2014_524_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>SNPs unique to each method characterized by the five most common splits found. Figure S1. Runtime comparison for the whole-genome alignment methods on the simulated 32-genome E. coli W3110 dataset. Figure S2. Timing performance from 32 to 10,000 S. pneumoniae genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>Bp</term><def><p>base pair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERA</term><def><p>European Read Archive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Indel</term><def><p>insertion or deletion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LCB</term><def><p>locally collinear block</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Mbp</term><def><p>million base pairs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MUM</term><def><p>maximal unique match</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MUMi</term><def><p>similarity index based on maximal unique matches</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NGS</term><def><p>Next generation sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PE</term><def><p>paired-end</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>single-nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SRA</term><def><p>Sequence Read Archive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VCF</term><def><p>variant call format</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>XMFA</term><def><p>extendend multi-fasta format</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Todd J Treangen and Brian D Ondov contributed equally. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>TJT, BDO, and AMP conceived the method, designed the experiments, and drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>TJT implemented Parsnp and BDO implemented Gingr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>TJT, BDO, and SK performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Iñaki Comas for providing the raw data for the TB study; Xiangyu Deng for helpful comments on the manuscript and software; and Bradd Haley, Bill Klimke, Jason Sahl, Maliha Aziz, and Suzanne Bialek-Davenet for feedback on early versions of the software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>This work was funded under Agreement No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>HSHQDC-07-C-00020 awarded by the Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology Directorate (DHS/S&amp;T) for the management and operation of the National Biodefense Analysis and Countermeasures Center (NBACC), a Federally Funded Research and Development Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The views and conclusions contained in this document are those of the authors and should not be interpreted as necessarily representing the official policies, either expressed or implied, of the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Department of Homeland Security. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>In no event shall the DHS, NBACC, or Battelle National Biodefense Institute (BNBI) have any responsibility or liability for any use, misuse, inability to use, or reliance upon the information contained herein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>The Department of Homeland Security does not endorse any products or commercial services mentioned in this publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>1.PaganiILioliosKJanssonJChenIMSmirnovaTNosratBMarkowitzVMKyrpidesNCThe Genomes OnLine Database (GOLD) v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>4: status of genomic and metagenomic projects and their associated metadataNucleic Acids Res201240D571D579<?supplied-pmid 22135293?>22135293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>2.RaskoDAWebsterDRSahlJWBashirABoisenNScheutzFPaxinosEESebraRChinCSIliopoulosDKlammerAPelusoPLeeLKislyukAOBullardJKasarskisAWangSEidJRankDRedmanJCSteyertSRFrimodt-MollerJStruveCPetersenAMKrogfeltKANataroJPSchadtEEWaldorMKOrigins of the E. coli strain causing an outbreak of hemolytic-uremic syndrome in GermanyN Engl J Med2011365709717<?supplied-pmid 21793740?>21793740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>3.MagocTPabingerSCanzarSLiuXSuQPuiuDTallonLJSalzbergSLGAGE-B: an evaluation of genome assemblers for bacterial organismsBioinformatics20132917181725<?supplied-pmid 23665771?>23665771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>4.KorenSSchatzMCWalenzBPMartinJHowardJTGanapathyGWangZRaskoDAMcCombieWRJarvisEDAdamMPHybrid error correction and de novo assembly of single-molecule sequencing readsNat Biotechnol201230693700<?supplied-pmid 22750884?>22750884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>5.ChinCSAlexanderDHMarksPKlammerAADrakeJHeinerCClumACopelandAHuddlestonJEichlerEETurnerSWKorlachJNonhybrid, finished microbial genome assemblies from long-read SMRT sequencing dataNat Methods201310563569<?supplied-pmid 23644548?>23644548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>6.SnitkinESZelaznyAMThomasPJStockFGroup NCSPHendersonDKPalmoreTNSegreJATracking a hospital outbreak of carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae with whole-genome sequencingSci Transl Med20124148ra116<?supplied-pmid 22914622?>22914622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>7.Gonzalez-CandelasFBrachoMAWrobelBMoyaAMolecular evolution in court: analysis of a large hepatitis C virus outbreak from an evolving sourceBMC Biol20131176<?supplied-pmid 23870105?>23870105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>8.KennemannLDidelotXAebischerTKuhnSDrescherBDroegeMReinhardtRCorreaPMeyerTFJosenhansCFalushDSuerbaumSHelicobacter pylori genome evolution during human infectionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201110850335038<?supplied-pmid 21383187?>21383187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>9.YaharaKDidelotXAnsariMASheppardSKFalushDEfficient inference of recombination hot regions in bacterial genomesMol Biol Evol20143115931605<?supplied-pmid 24586045?>24586045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>10.NamouchiADidelotXSchockUGicquelBRochaEPAfter the bottleneck: Genome-wide diversification of the Mycobacterium tuberculosis complex by mutation, recombination, and natural selectionGenome Res201222721734<?supplied-pmid 22377718?>22377718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>11.DidelotXMericGFalushDDarlingAEImpact of homologous and non-homologous recombination in the genomic evolution of Escherichia coliBMC Genomics201213256<?supplied-pmid 22712577?>22712577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>12.DidelotXBowdenRStreetTGolubchikTSpencerCMcVeanGSangalVAnjumMFAchtmanMFalushDDonnellyPRecombination and population structure in Salmonella entericaPLoS Genet20117e1002191<?supplied-pmid 21829375?>21829375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>13.DidelotXLawsonDDarlingAFalushDInference of homologous recombination in bacteria using whole-genome sequencesGenetics201018614351449<?supplied-pmid 20923983?>20923983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>14.DidelotXDarlingAFalushDInferring genomic flux in bacteriaGenome Res200919306317<?supplied-pmid 19015321?>19015321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>15.DhillonBKChiuTALairdMRLangilleMGBrinkmanFSIslandViewer update: Improved genomic island discovery and visualizationNucleic Acids Res201341W129W132<?supplied-pmid 23677610?>23677610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>16.LangilleMGHsiaoWWBrinkmanFSEvaluation of genomic island predictors using a comparative genomics approachBMC Bioinformatics20089329<?supplied-pmid 18680607?>18680607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>17.TouchonMRochaEPCauses of insertion sequences abundance in prokaryotic genomesMol Biol Evol200724969981<?supplied-pmid 17251179?>17251179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>18.FuxeliusHHDarbyAMinCKChoNHAnderssonSGThe genomic and metabolic diversity of RickettsiaRes Microbiol2007158745753<?supplied-pmid 18031998?>18031998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>19.DessimozCGabaldonTRoosDSSonnhammerELHerreroJQuest for Orthologs C: Toward community standards in the quest for orthologsBioinformatics201228900904<?supplied-pmid 22332236?>22332236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>20.GabaldonTDessimozCHuxley-JonesJVilellaAJSonnhammerELLewisSJoining forces in the quest for orthologsGenome Biol200910403<?supplied-pmid 19785718?>19785718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>21.AlekseyevMAPevznerPABreakpoint graphs and ancestral genome reconstructionsGenome Res200919943957<?supplied-pmid 19218533?>19218533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>22.PhilippeHBrinkmannHLavrovDVLittlewoodDTManuelMWorheideGBaurainDResolving difficult phylogenetic questions: why more sequences are not enoughPLoS Biol20119e1000602<?supplied-pmid 21423652?>21423652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>23.PhilippeHDelsucFBrinkmannHLartillotNPhylogenomicsAnnu Rev Ecol Evol Syst200536541562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>24.HaywardAGrabherrMJernPBroad-scale phylogenomics provides insights into retrovirus-host evolutionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20131102014620151<?supplied-pmid 24277832?>24277832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>25.GabaldonTKooninEVFunctional and evolutionary implications of gene orthologyNat Rev Genet201314360366<?supplied-pmid 23552219?>23552219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>26.DaganTArtzy-RandrupYMartinWModular networks and cumulative impact of lateral transfer in prokaryote genome evolutionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20081051003910044<?supplied-pmid 18632554?>18632554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>27.DaleJPriceEPHornstraHBuschJDMayoMGodoyDWuthiekanunVBakerAFosterJTWagnerDMTuanyokAWarnerJSprattBGPeacockSJCurrieBJKeimPPearsonTEpidemiological tracking and population assignment of the non-clonal bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Burkholderia pseudomalleiPLoS Negl Trop Dis20115e1381<?supplied-pmid 22180792?>22180792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>28.SahlJWCaporasoJGRaskoDAKeimPThe large-scale blast score ratio (LS-BSR) pipeline: a method to rapidly compare genetic content between bacterial genomesPeer J20142e332<?supplied-pmid 24749011?>24749011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>29.SwidanFRochaEPShmoishMPinterRYAn integrative method for accurate comparative genome mappingPLoS Comput Biol20062e75<?supplied-pmid 16933978?>16933978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>30.BrayNPachterLMAVID: constrained ancestral alignment of multiple sequencesGenome Res200414693699<?supplied-pmid 15060012?>15060012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>31.DarlingAEMauBPernaNTprogressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain, loss and rearrangementPLoS One20105e11147<?supplied-pmid 20593022?>20593022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>32.DarlingAETreangenTJMesseguerXPernaNTAnalyzing patterns of microbial evolution using the mauve genome alignment systemMethods Mol Biol2007396135152<?supplied-pmid 18025691?>18025691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>33.DarlingACMauBBlattnerFRPernaNTMauve: multiple alignment of conserved genomic sequence with rearrangementsGenome Res20041413941403<?supplied-pmid 15231754?>15231754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>34.HohlMKurtzSOhlebuschEEfficient multiple genome alignmentBioinformatics200218S312S320<?supplied-pmid 12169561?>12169561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>35.TreangenTJMesseguerXM-GCAT: interactively and efficiently constructing large-scale multiple genome comparison frameworks in closely related speciesBMC Bioinformatics20067433<?supplied-pmid 17022809?>17022809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>36.AngiuoliSVSalzbergSLMugsy: fast multiple alignment of closely related whole genomesBioinformatics201127334342<?supplied-pmid 21148543?>21148543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>37.BlanchetteMKentWJRiemerCElnitskiLSmitAFRoskinKMBaertschRRosenbloomKClawsonHGreenEDHausslerDMillerWAligning multiple genomic sequences with the threaded blockset alignerGenome Res200414708715<?supplied-pmid 15060014?>15060014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>38.BrudnoMDoCBCooperGMKimMFDavydovEProgramNCSGreenEDSidowABatzoglouSLAGAN and Multi-LAGAN: efficient tools for large-scale multiple alignment of genomic DNAGenome Res200313721731<?supplied-pmid 12654723?>12654723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>39.PatenBHerreroJBealKFitzgeraldSBirneyEEnredo and Pecan: genome-wide mammalian consistency-based multiple alignment with paralogsGenome Res20081818141828<?supplied-pmid 18849524?>18849524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>40.OchmanHLeratEDaubinVExamining bacterial species under the specter of gene transfer and exchangeProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200510265956599<?supplied-pmid 15851673?>15851673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>41.WangLJiangTOn the complexity of multiple sequence alignmentJ Comput Biol19941337348<?supplied-pmid 8790475?>8790475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>42.LiuKWarnowTLarge-scale multiple sequence alignment and tree estimation using SATeMethods Mol Biol20141079219244<?supplied-pmid 24170406?>24170406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>43.ChanCXRaganMANext-generation phylogenomicsBiol Direct201383<?supplied-pmid 23339707?>23339707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>44.PosadaDPhylogenetic models of molecular evolution: next-generation data, fit, and performanceJ Mol Evol201376351352<?supplied-pmid 23695649?>23695649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>45.RobinsonERWalkerTMPallenMJGenomics and outbreak investigation: from sequence to consequenceGenome Med2013536<?supplied-pmid 23673226?>23673226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>46.BennettSSolexa LtdPharmacogenomics20045433438<?supplied-pmid 15165179?>15165179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>47.SchatzMCDelcherALSalzbergSLAssembly of large genomes using second-generation sequencingGenome Res20102011651173<?supplied-pmid 20508146?>20508146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>48.EarlDBradnamKSt JohnJDarlingALinDFassJYuHOBuffaloVZerbinoDRDiekhansMNguyenNAriyaratnePNSungWKNingZHaimelMSimpsonJTFonsecaNABirolIDockingTRHoIYRokhsarDSChikhiRLavenierDChapuisGNaquinDMailletNSchatzMCKelleyDRPhillippyAMKorenSAssemblathon 1: a competitive assessment of de novo short read assembly methodsGenome Res20112122242241<?supplied-pmid 21926179?>21926179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>49.Langmead B: Aligning short sequencing reads with Bowtie.Curr Protoc Bioinformatics 2010, Chapter 11:Unit 11 17. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>50.LangmeadBSalzbergSLFast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2Nat Methods20129357359<?supplied-pmid 22388286?>22388286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>51.LiHDurbinRFast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transformBioinformatics201026589595<?supplied-pmid 20080505?>20080505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>52.LiHDurbinRFast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transformBioinformatics20092517541760<?supplied-pmid 19451168?>19451168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>53.McKennaAHannaMBanksESivachenkoACibulskisKKernytskyAGarimellaKAltshulerDGabrielSDalyMDePristoMAThe Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing dataGenome Res20102012971303<?supplied-pmid 20644199?>20644199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>54.Garrison E, Marth G: Haplotype-based variant detection from short-read sequencing.arXiv 2012, 1207:3907. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3907">http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3907</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>55.LiHHandsakerBWysokerAFennellTRuanJHomerNMarthGAbecasisGDurbinRGenome Project Data Processing SThe Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtoolsBioinformatics20092520782079<?supplied-pmid 19505943?>19505943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>56.HarrisSRTorokMECartwrightEJQuailMAPeacockSJParkhillJRead and assembly metrics inconsequential for clinical utility of whole-genome sequencing in mapping outbreaksNat Biotechnol201331592594<?supplied-pmid 23839141?>23839141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>57.BertelsFSilanderOKPachkovMRaineyPBvan NimwegenEAutomated reconstruction of whole-genome phylogenies from short-sequence readsMol Biol Evol20143110771088<?supplied-pmid 24600054?>24600054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>58.LiHToward better understanding of artifacts in variant calling from high-coverage samplesBioinformatics20143028432851<?supplied-pmid 24974202?>24974202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>59.TreangenTJSalzbergSLRepetitive DNA and next-generation sequencing: computational challenges and solutionsNat Rev Genet201213364622124482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>60.VingaSAlmeidaJAlignment-free sequence comparison-a reviewBioinformatics200319513523<?supplied-pmid 12611807?>12611807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>61.PatroRMountSMKingsfordCSailfish enables alignment-free isoform quantification from RNA-seq reads using lightweight algorithmsNat Biotechnol201432462464<?supplied-pmid 24752080?>24752080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>62.WoodDESalzbergSLKraken: ultrafast metagenomic sequence classification using exact alignmentsGenome Biol201415R46<?supplied-pmid 24580807?>24580807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>63.ChorBHornDGoldmanNLevyYMassinghamTGenomic DNA k-mer spectra: models and modalitiesGenome Biol200910R108<?supplied-pmid 19814784?>19814784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>64.HauserMMayerCESodingJkClust: fast and sensitive clustering of large protein sequence databasesBMC Bioinformatics201314248<?supplied-pmid 23945046?>23945046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>65.GhodsiMLiuBPopMDNACLUST: accurate and efficient clustering of phylogenetic marker genesBMC Bioinformatics201112271<?supplied-pmid 21718538?>21718538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>66.GardnerSNHallBGWhen whole-genome alignments just won’t work: kSNP v2 software for alignment-free SNP discovery and phylogenetics of hundreds of microbial genomesPLoS One20138e81760<?supplied-pmid 24349125?>24349125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>67.HohlMRaganMAIs multiple-sequence alignment required for accurate inference of phylogeny?Syst Biol200756206221<?supplied-pmid 17454975?>17454975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>68.GnerreSMaccallumIPrzybylskiDRibeiroFJBurtonJNWalkerBJSharpeTHallGSheaTPSykesSBerlinAMAirdDCostelloMDazaRWilliamsLNicolRGnirkeANusbaumCLanderESJaffeDBHigh-quality draft assemblies of mammalian genomes from massively parallel sequence dataProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201110815131518<?supplied-pmid 21187386?>21187386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>69.SimpsonJTWongKJackmanSDScheinJEJonesSJBirolIABySS: a parallel assembler for short read sequence dataGenome Res20091911171123<?supplied-pmid 19251739?>19251739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>70.SimpsonJTDurbinREfficient de novo assembly of large genomes using compressed data structuresGenome Res201222549556<?supplied-pmid 22156294?>22156294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>71.MillerJRDelcherALKorenSVenterEWalenzBPBrownleyAJohnsonJLiKMobarryCSuttonGAggressive assembly of pyrosequencing reads with matesBioinformatics20082428182824<?supplied-pmid 18952627?>18952627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>72.PevznerPATangHWatermanMSAn Eulerian path approach to DNA fragment assemblyProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20019897489753<?supplied-pmid 11504945?>11504945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>73.Zerbino DR: Using the Velvet de novo assembler for short-read sequencing technologies.Curr Protoc Bioinformatics 2010, Chapter 11:Unit 11 15. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>74.MarguliesMEgholmMAltmanWEAttiyaSBaderJSBembenLABerkaJBravermanMSChenYJChenZDewellSBDuLFierroJMGomesXVGodwinBCHeWHelgesenSHoCHIrzykGPJandoSCAlenquerMLJarvieTPJirageKBKimJBKnightJRLanzaJRLeamonJHLefkowitzSMLeiMLiJGenome sequencing in microfabricated high-density picolitre reactorsNature2005437376380<?supplied-pmid 16056220?>16056220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>75.LiRFanWTianGZhuHHeLCaiJHuangQCaiQLiBBaiYZhangZZhangYWangWLiJWeiFLiHJianMLiJZhangZNielsenRLiDGuWYangZXuanZRyderOALeungFCZhouYCaoJSunXFuYThe sequence and de novo assembly of the giant panda genomeNature2010463311317<?supplied-pmid 20010809?>20010809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>76.KurtzSPhillippyADelcherALSmootMShumwayMAntonescuCSalzbergSLVersatile and open software for comparing large genomesGenome Biol20045R12<?supplied-pmid 14759262?>14759262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>77.DelcherALKasifSFleischmannRDPetersonJWhiteOSalzbergSLAlignment of whole genomes MUMMERNucl Acids Res19992723692369<?supplied-pmid 10325427?>10325427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>78.PernaNTPlunkettG3rdBurlandVMauBGlasnerJDRoseDJMayhewGFEvansPSGregorJKirkpatrickHAPosfaiGHackettJKlinkSBoutinAShaoYMillerLGrotbeckEJDavisNWLimADimalantaETPotamousisKDApodacaJAnantharamanTSLinJYenGSchwartzDCWelchRABlattnerFRGenome sequence of enterohaemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7Nature2001409529533<?supplied-pmid 11206551?>11206551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>79.LomanNJMisraRVDallmanTJConstantinidouCGharbiaSEWainJPallenMJPerformance comparison of benchtop high-throughput sequencing platformsNat Biotechnol201230434439<?supplied-pmid 22522955?>22522955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>80.TatusovaTCiufoSFedorovBO’NeillKTolstoyIRefSeq microbial genomes database: new representation and annotation strategyNucleic Acids Res201442D553D559<?supplied-pmid 24316578?>24316578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>81.BankevichANurkSAntipovDGurevichAADvorkinMKulikovASLesinVMNikolenkoSIPhamSPrjibelskiADPyshkinAVSirotkinAVVyahhiNTeslerGAlekseyevMAPevznerPASPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencingJ Comput Biol201219455477<?supplied-pmid 22506599?>22506599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>82.KorenSHarhayGPSmithTPBonoJLHarhayDMMcVeySDRaduneDBergmanNHPhillippyAMReducing assembly complexity of microbial genomes with single-molecule sequencingGenome Biol201314R101<?supplied-pmid 24034426?>24034426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>83.DelcherALPhillippyACarltonJSalzbergSLFast algorithms for large-scale genome alignment and comparisonNucleic Acids Res20023024782483<?supplied-pmid 12034836?>12034836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>84.DelogerMEl KarouiMPetitMAA genomic distance based on MUM indicates discontinuity between most bacterial species and generaJ Bacteriol20091919199<?supplied-pmid 18978054?>18978054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>85.EdgarRCMUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughputNucleic Acids Res20043217921797<?supplied-pmid 15034147?>15034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>86.Teacch D: Borrador sin revisión de traducción ni formato Contenidos. 1-341. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>87.BruenTCPhilippeHBryantDA simple and robust statistical test for detecting the presence of recombinationGenetics200617226652681<?supplied-pmid 16489234?>16489234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>88.PriceMNDehalPSArkinAPFastTree 2–approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignmentsPLoS One20105e9490<?supplied-pmid 20224823?>20224823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>89.MediniDDonatiCTettelinHMasignaniVRappuoliRThe microbial pan-genomeCurr Opin Genet Dev200515589594<?supplied-pmid 16185861?>16185861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>90.HarrisSRFeilEJHoldenMTQuailMANickersonEKChantratitaNGardeteSTavaresADayNLindsayJAEdgeworthJDde LencastreHParkhillJPeacockSJBentleySDEvolution of MRSA during hospital transmission and intercontinental spreadScience2010327469474<?supplied-pmid 20093474?>20093474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>91.van Vugt-LussenburgBMvan der WeelLHagenWRHagedoornPLBiochemical similarities and differences between the catalytic [4Fe-4S] cluster containing fumarases FumA and FumB from Escherichia coliPLoS One20138e55549<?supplied-pmid 23405168?>23405168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>92.EyreDWCuleMLWilsonDJGriffithsDVaughanAO'ConnorLIpCLGolubchikTBattyEMFinneyJMWyllieDHDidelotXPiazzaPBowdenRDingleKEHardingRMCrookDWWilcoxMHPetoTEWalkerASDiverse sources of C. difficile infection identified on whole-genome sequencingN Engl J Med201336911951205<?supplied-pmid 24066741?>24066741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>93.KorenSTreangenTJHillCMPopMPhillippyAMAutomated ensemble assembly and validation of microbial genomesBMC Bioinformatics201415126<?supplied-pmid 24884846?>24884846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>94.SebaihiaMWrenBWMullanyPFairweatherNFMintonNStablerRThomsonNRRobertsAPCerdeno-TarragaAMWangHHoldenMTWrightAChurcherCQuailMABakerSBasonNBrooksKChillingworthTCroninADavisPDowdLFraserAFeltwellTHanceZHolroydSJagelsKMouleSMungallKPriceCRabbinowitschEThe multidrug-resistant human pathogen Clostridium difficile has a highly mobile, mosaic genomeNat Genet200638779786<?supplied-pmid 16804543?>16804543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>95.DawsonLFDonahueEHCartmanSTBartonRHBundyJMcNerneyRMintonNPWrenBWThe analysis of para-cresol production and tolerance in Clostridium difficile 027 and 012 strainsBMC Microbiol20111186<?supplied-pmid 21527013?>21527013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>96.YoungGPWardPBBayleyNGordonDHigginsGTrapaniJAMcDonaldMILabrooyJHeckerRAntibiotic-associated colitis due to Clostridium difficile: double-blind comparison of vancomycin with bacitracinGastroenterology19858910381045<?supplied-pmid 4043661?>4043661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>97.VenugopalAAJohnsonSCurrent state of Clostridium difficile treatment optionsClin Infect Dis201255S71S76<?supplied-pmid 22752868?>22752868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>98.ComasICoscollaMLuoTBorrellSHoltKEKato-MaedaMParkhillJMallaBBergSThwaitesGYeboah-ManuDBothamleyGMeiJWeiLBentleySHarrisSRNiemannSDielRAseffaAGaoQYoungDGagneuxSOut-of-Africa migration and Neolithic coexpansion of Mycobacterium tuberculosis with modern humansNat Genet20134511761182<?supplied-pmid 23995134?>23995134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>99.RobinsonDFFouldsLRComparison of Phylogenetic TreesMath Biosci198153131147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>100.CockPJFieldsCJGotoNHeuerMLRicePMThe Sanger FASTQ file format for sequences with quality scores, and the Solexa/Illumina FASTQ variantsNucleic Acids Res20103817671771<?supplied-pmid 20015970?>20015970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>101.DanecekPAutonAAbecasisGAlbersCABanksEDePristoMAHandsakerRELunterGMarthGTSherrySTMcVeanGDurbinRGenomes Project Analysis G: The variant call format and VCFtoolsBioinformatics20112721562158<?supplied-pmid 21653522?>21653522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>102.Hsi-Yang FritzMLeinonenRCochraneGBirneyEEfficient storage of high throughput DNA sequencing data using reference-based compressionGenome Res201121734740<?supplied-pmid 21245279?>21245279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>103.LipmanDFlicekPSalzbergSGersteinMKnightRClosure of the NCBI SRA and implications for the long-term future of genomics data storageGenome Biol201112402<?supplied-pmid 21418618?>21418618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>104.KorlachJBjornsonKPChaudhuriBPCiceroRLFlusbergBAGrayJJHoldenDSaxenaRWegenerJTurnerSWReal-time DNA sequencing from single polymerase moleculesMethods Enzymol2010472431455<?supplied-pmid 20580975?>20580975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>105.MatsenFAKodnerRBArmbrustEVpplacer: linear time maximum-likelihood and Bayesian phylogenetic placement of sequences onto a fixed reference treeBMC Bioinformatics201011538<?supplied-pmid 21034504?>21034504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>106.LoytynojaAVilellaAJGoldmanNAccurate extension of multiple sequence alignments using a phylogeny-aware graph algorithmBioinformatics20122816841691<?supplied-pmid 22531217?>22531217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>107.TenoverFCArbeitRDGoeringRVMickelsenPAMurrayBEPersingDHSwaminathanBInterpreting chromosomal DNA restriction patterns produced by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis: criteria for bacterial strain typingJ Clin Microbiol19953322332239<?supplied-pmid 7494007?>7494007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>108.MaidenMCBygravesJAFeilEMorelliGRussellJEUrwinRZhangQZhouJZurthKCaugantDAFeaversIMAchtmanMSprattBGMultilocus sequence typing: a portable approach to the identification of clones within populations of pathogenic microorganismsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19989531403145<?supplied-pmid 9501229?>9501229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>109.Castillo-RamirezSCoranderJMarttinenPAldeljawiMHanageWPWesthHBoyeKGulayZBentleySDParkhillJHoldenMTFeilEJPhylogeographic variation in recombination rates within a global clone of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureusGenome Biol201213R126<?supplied-pmid 23270620?>23270620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>110.CroucherNJFinkelsteinJAPeltonSIMitchellPKLeeGMParkhillJBentleySDHanageWPLipsitchMPopulation genomics of post-vaccine changes in pneumococcal epidemiologyNat Genet201345656663<?supplied-pmid 23644493?>23644493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>111.CroucherNJHarrisSRFraserCQuailMABurtonJvan der LindenMMcGeeLvon GottbergASongJHKoKSPichonBBakerSParryCMLambertsenLMShahinasDPillaiDRMitchellTJDouganGTomaszAKlugmanKPParkhillJHanageWPBentleySDRapid pneumococcal evolution in response to clinical interventionsScience2011331430434<?supplied-pmid 21273480?>21273480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>112.HayashiKMorookaNYamamotoYFujitaKIsonoKChoiSOhtsuboEBabaTWannerBLMoriHHoriuchiTHighly accurate genome sequences of Escherichia coli K-12 strains MG1655 and W3110Mol Syst Biol200622006.0007<?supplied-pmid 16738553?>16738553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>113.RambautAGrasslyNCSeq-Gen: an application for the Monte Carlo simulation of DNA sequence evolution along phylogenetic treesComput Appl Biosci199713235238<?supplied-pmid 9183526?>9183526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>114.Parsnp github url. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/marbl/parsnp/tree/master/script">https://github.com/marbl/parsnp/tree/master/script</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>115.YutinNGalperinMYA genomic update on clostridial phylogeny: Gram-negative spore formers and other misplaced clostridiaEnviron Microbiol20131526312641<?supplied-pmid 23834245?>23834245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
