<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECAM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine : eCAM</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1741-427X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1741-4288</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4921679</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/1927534</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the Effect of Velvet Antler from Different Sections on Longitudinal Bone Growth of Adolescent Rats </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hye Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Myung-Gyou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2029-5849</contrib-id><name><surname>Leem</surname><given-names>Kang-Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Food &amp; Biotechnology, Hanseo University, Seosan 31962, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>College of Korean Medicine, Semyung University, Jecheon 27136, Republic of Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Kang-Hyun Leem: <email>hkkim1454@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Yuewen Gong </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>2016</volume><elocation-id>1927534</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 Hye Kyung Kim et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to compare the effectiveness of velvet antler (VA) from different sections for promoting longitudinal bone growth in growing rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>VA was divided into upper (VAU), middle (VAM), and basal sections (VAB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>An in vivo study was performed to examine the effect on longitudinal bone growth in adolescent rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In addition, in vitro osteogenic activities were examined using osteoblastic MG-63 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>VA promoted longitudinal bone growth and height of the growth plate in adolescent rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Bone morphogenetic protein-2 (BMP-2) in growth plate of VA group was highly expressed compared with control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The anabolic effect of VA on bone was further supported by in vitro study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>VA enhanced the proliferation, differentiation, and mineralization of MG-63 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The mRNA expressions of osteogenic genes such as collagen, alkaline phosphatase, and osteocalcin were increased by VA treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These effects of in vivo and in vitro study were decreased from upper to basal sections of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, VA treatment promotes longitudinal bone growth in growing rats through enhanced BMP-2 expression, osteogenic activities, and bone matrix gene expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In addition, present study provides evidence for the regional differences in the effectiveness of velvet antler for longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal bone growth, which determines the size and shape of the body frame, proceeds at a rate distinct from that of muscle and other tissues and is controlled by specific mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>During childhood and adolescence, the long bones grow at the ends of the bones which occur at the growth plate by endochondral ossification of epiphyseal plate [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Growth plate chondrocyte proliferation and hypertrophy lead to formation of new cartilage, chondrogenesis, and remodeling of the newly formed cartilage into bone tissue resulting in longitudinal bone growth [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The current methods for increasing final height include treatment with a growth hormone alone or in combination with an analog of gonadotropin-releasing hormone [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, it is generally too expensive and also has harmful side effects such as prepubertal gynecomastia, arthralgia, edema, benign intracranial hypertension, insulin resistance, and leukemia [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>On that account, there has been an increasing awareness of the benefits of natural products, and many plant-derived medicines have been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>However, the researches on animal medicines or functional foods are still relatively few, although animal medicines have been proven of various important components, such as proteins, peptides, fatty acids, glycosaminoglycans, prostaglandins, vitamins, minerals, dietary fiber, essential oils, and carotenoids [5, 6], which can be used in the prevention and treatment of various diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Velvet antler (VA), the immature antler of male deer, is traditionally used for thousands of years in Asian countries, such as Korea, China, Taiwan, and Mongolia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It is currently estimated that the global production of velvet antlers is near to 1300 tons/year, which is still rapidly growing to meet the requirements of medicinal markets [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>As a typical traditional animal medicine, VA has pharmacological effects to improve immune system, physical strength, and sexual function [7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>VA, also, has been reported to possess bone strengthening activity and has been used in treating arthritis, osteoporosis, and fracture in animal model or human clinical trials [9–12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>A whole VA stick is usually divided into four portions, with the value decreasing from the tip to the base. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Chemical analyses of VA revealed that there are regional differences in chemical composition: the contents of proteins and lipids decrease downward from the tip to the base, while those of ash, calcium, and collagen increase [13] suggesting the degree of calcification increased from tip to base section of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>During the ossification of deer antler, the total collagen content was found to be increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Typically, the antler is cut off near the base after it is about two-thirds of its potential full size, between 55 and 65 days of growth, before any significant calcification occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Traditionally, the market values of antlers are downgraded with increasing degree of calcification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, which parts of VA are suitable for preventing and managing bone health especially bone growth had not been clarified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The objective of the present study was to compare the effect of VA from different sections on longitudinal bone growth of adolescent rats and elucidate the underlying mechanisms for the effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>VA, obtained from farmed Elk deer 75 days after casting, was kindly provided by the Animal Genetic Resources Station (National Institute of Animal Science, South Korea). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>VA was divided into upper (VAU), middle (VAM), and basal (VAB) sections (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The criteria used for dividing the antler into three sections is defined as follows: upper section, top 15 cm of the part of the main beam to the 2nd division of a deer's antlers from its head; middle section, the upper half of the remaining main beam; and base section, the lower half of the remaining main beam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Total part of each section was sliced with a bone slicer, freeze-dried, and ground into powder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The powdered VA was immersed in 70% ethanol for 3 days, filtered, concentrated by vacuum evaporation, and finally subjected to freeze drying. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Respective yields of sections, from upper to basal, were 3.4% (VAU), 2.9% (VAM), and 1.7% (VAB). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal bone growth was determined in 3-week-old male Sprague-Dawley rats (Samtako Co., Osan, Korea). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The experimental procedures were performed in accordance with protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee, Semyung University (smecae 15-09-01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The animals were housed under controlled temperature and lighting conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The rats were randomly divided into four groups (n = 8); vehicle (control, distilled water) and upper (VAU), middle (VAM), and basal (VAB) sections of antler extract (100 mg/kg) were orally administered daily via stomach tube for 5 consecutive days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Treatment dose was decided from the preliminary study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>On the sixth day, all rats were sacrificed under chloral hydrate anesthesia for tissue analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Measurement of Longitudinal Bone Growth </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To measure the effect on longitudinal bone growth rate, calcein was used as a fluorescence marker to label the bone line on the surface of the tibia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Calcein plays the role of fluorescent dye under ultraviolet illumination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Calcein (10 mg/kg, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was injected intraperitoneally 24 h before sacrifice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The dissected tibias were fixed in 0.1 M phosphate buffered formalin for 2 h, decalcified, and dehydrated by immersing in 30% sucrose for 1 day at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Dehydrated bone was sectioned longitudinally at sagittal sections of proximal part with a thickness of 40 μm using a sliding microtome (HM440E, Zeiss, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Bone growth was measured by measuring the gap between fluorescent line formed by calcein and the epiphyseal end line of the growth plate at three different locations using a fluorescent microscope (BX60, Olympus, Tokyo, Japan), and the averages were obtained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Measurement of Growth Plate Height </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Cresyl violet staining (Sigma-Aldrich) was used to stain the chondrocytes in the growth plate of the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Each tibia sample was sectioned longitudinally at a thickness of 40 μm using a sliding microtome as described above and stained with cresyl violet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The growth plate height was measured at three different locations and the averages were obtained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Bone Morphogenetic Protein-2 Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For the detection of bone morphogenetic protein-2 (BMP-2) in the growth plate, the dehydrated tibia sections were incubated overnight in 1% Triton X-100 containing goat BMP-2 antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, diluted 1 : 500) at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Then, sections were incubated with anti-goat antibody (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA, diluted 1 : 200) for 60 min and stained with 0.05% 3,3-diaminobenzidine (Sigma Chemical Co.) containing 0.03% hydrogen peroxide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Cell Culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Human osteoblast-like MG-63 cells were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (Rockville, MD, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured at 37°C in a 5% CO2 atmosphere in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM, Gibco, MD, USA) containing 10% heat-inactivated FBS (Invitrogen, Grand island, NY, USA) and 100 U/mL penicillin/streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow cells prepared from the femur of male ICR mice were cultured in α-modified minimal essential medium (α-MEM, Gibco) containing 10% heat-inactivated FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After 3 days of culture, floating cells were removed and attached cells were used as osteoclast precursors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Osteoblasts Proliferation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The effects of VA from different sections on proliferation of MG-63 cell were determined by a colorimetric immunoassay kit (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany) which is based on quantitating bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) incorporation into the newly synthesized DNA of replicating cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cells were seeded (5,000 cells/well) in 96-well plates containing DMEM with 10% FBS and allowed to adhere overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The media were replaced with DMEM containing VA samples (10, 50, and 100 μg/mL) and incubated for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, BrdU was added to each well and reincubated for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>After 14 h of incubation at 37°C, labeling media was removed, cells were fixed, and the cells with BrdU label in the DNA were located with peroxidase-conjugated anti-BrdU antibody solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Then bound anti-BrdU with substrate was colorimetrically measured with a microplate reader (BioTek Inc., Winooski, VT, USA) at 450 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Alkaline Phosphatase Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity was measured using enzymatic assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cells, incubated in DMEM, were seeded in 12-well plates (50,000 cells/well) and incubated for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The medium was changed to osteogenic medium (DMEM with 10 mM β-glycerophosphate, 5 nM dexamethasone, and 50 μg/mL ascorbic acid); VA samples (50 and 100 μg/mL) were added to the cells and incubated for another 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The 50 and 100 μg/mL concentrations were chosen since the maximum effect and plateau had been gained under those two concentrations in cell proliferation assay results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The cells were then rinsed with PBS and lysed in 300 μL of 0.2% of Triton X-100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The cell lysates were centrifuged at 13,000 rpm for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The supernatant of the lysate was used for the measurement of ALP activity by measuring the release of p-nitrophenol from p-nitrophenylphosphate at pH 9.8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>2.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Collagen Content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Collagen synthesis was measured using picrosirius red method [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cells were seeded in 12-well plates (50,000 cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The medium was changed to osteogenic medium; VA samples (100 μg/mL) were added to each well and incubated for 7 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Cells were fixed with Bouin's fluid and stained with 0.1% Sirius red (Direct Red 80, Sigma-Aldrich) in a saturated aqueous solution of picric acid for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Stained dye was dissolved and the absorbance was measured at 540 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Calcium Deposition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The formation of calcium phosphate was determined by alizarin red-S assay [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cells were seeded and incubated as described above in the collagen assay process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>After 7 days, cells were fixed with 10% formaldehyde and stained with 2% of alizarin red-S (pH 4.2, Sigma-Aldrich) at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The stained alizarin red-S was extracted with 10% acetic acid, and the amount of calcium deposition was quantified using the absorbance of extracted alizarin red-S at 405 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>2.11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Real-Time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed to analyze relative gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cells were seeded in 6-well plates (100,000 cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The medium was changed to osteogenic medium; VA sample (100 μg/mL) was added to each well and incubated for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted using RNeasy® Protect Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA), and cDNA was synthesized from mRNA using QuantiTect® Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed using QuantiTect™ SYBR® Green PCR Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The PCR primer sequences are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Analyses were performed using Rotor-Gene Q® (Qiagen) and gene expression values were calculated based on the comparative ΔΔCT method according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>2.12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Osteoclastogenesis Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>For induction of osteoclastogenesis, osteoclast precursor cells prepared as described above were further cultured for 4 days with RANKL (50 ng/mL) and M-CSF (30 ng/mL) in the presence of VA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Osteoclasts were identified by staining tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP), a marker enzyme of osteoclasts [16], using commercial kit (TRAP 387-A Kit, Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>TRAP-positive multinucleated cells with ≥3 nuclei were counted as osteoclasts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>2.13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The data were expressed as mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's multiple comparison test was performed for statistical analysis (GraphPad Prism ver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>6), and P values of less than 0.05 (P &lt; 0.05) indicated significant differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>All in vitro experiments were performed with triplicate independent samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Effects on Cell Longitudinal Bone Growth </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>To determine the growth per day, instead of the total growth over a period, exact methods for measurement are necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Recently, the use of tetracycline or calcein as intravital markers of the growth process to label mineralizing bone in the rat has been reported [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In the present study, calcein was used to label newly formed bone for the determination of longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Calcein binds to free calcium and gets deposited in newly deposited bone, causing staining and fluorescence under ultraviolet illumination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The effects of the different sections of VA on the rate of longitudinal bone growth from the proximal tibia in the rat are depicted in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The fluorescent line corresponds to the injection of calcein which binds with calcium in the newly formed bone (Figure 2(a), lower arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The arrow between the fluorescent line formed by calcein (Figure 2(a), lower arrow) and epiphyseal end line of the growth plate (Figure 2(a), upper arrow) indicates the length of the bone growth during 24 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal bone growth was significantly increased by VAU treatment compared with the control (Figure 2(a)).  Figure 2(b) shows the numerical values of the longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal bone growth in control rat was 617.4 ± 34.2 μm/day, and administration of VAU significantly increased the longitudinal bone growth to 718.6 ± 48.6 μm/day (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>VAU, VAM, and VAB caused 16.4%, 9.6%, and 2.7% increase in longitudinal bone growth, respectively, compared with control, suggesting that the effect decreases downward from upper section to the base. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Although VAM caused slight increase in longitudinal bone growth, statistical significance was not observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The present study provides first evidence for the effectiveness as well as regional differences of VA on longitudinal bone growth in adolescent rats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Recently, Tseng et al. [19] compared the antiosteoporotic activity of VA from different sections using ovariectomy-induced osteoporosis animal model and suggest that the upper and middle sections of VA were equally effective in protecting bones from an estrogen-deficient state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, the effects on proliferation and mineralization of osteoblasts, MC3T3-E1 cells, were decreased downward from upper section to the base [19] supporting the results of the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In addition they reported that the level of insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) was decreased downward from upper section to base section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal bone growth is a function of growth plate chondrocyte proliferation and hypertrophy, and IGF-1 is reputed to augment longitudinal bone growth by stimulating growth plate chondrocyte proliferation [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Therefore, these data support the results of the present study, and one of the possible mechanisms may be explained by the IGF-1 level in each section of VA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Effects on Growth Plate Heights </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The growth plate, which is located at the distal end of the bone, is the main location where longitudinal bone growth occurs owing to the stimulation of chondrocyte proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The growth plate consists of four distinctive histological zones beginning with the resting zone and extending through the proliferative, hypertrophic, and ossification zones (Figure 3(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The topmost layer, the resting zone, contains chondrocytes that serve as stem-like cells for the growth plate, with the potential to generate clones of rapidly proliferating chondrocytes, which are located in the proliferative zone in the second layer of the growth plate [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The proliferative zone is the driving force behind bone elongation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Over time, as longitudinal growth proceeds, proliferative cells close to the hypertrophic zone undergo terminal differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>During this process, they stop proliferating and physically enlarge to become hypertrophic chondrocytes, composing the third, hypertrophic layer of the growth plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In the ossification zone, the chondrocytes eventually die and are transformed into bone matrix where longitudinal bone growth occurred [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Since the synchronized processes of chondrocyte proliferation and cartilage ossification in growth plate lead to longitudinal bone growth [23], the rate of longitudinal bone growth is regulated by the rate of chondrocyte proliferation of the growth plate [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the rate of chondrocyte proliferation was determined by measuring the height of the proximal tibia growth plate (Figure 3(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The height of the growth plate in the control group was 511.2 ± 21.6 μm, and administration of 100 mg/kg VAU and VAM significantly increased the height of the growth plate to 567.4 ± 23.4 μm and 566.2 ± 20.6 μm, respectively (Figure 3(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The effect of VAU (11.0%) was similar to that of VAM (10.8%), while VAB caused 6.3% increase which was not statistically significant compared with control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the effect of VAM was slightly lower but not statistically significant compared with VAU, and the effect decreases downward from upper section to the base. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Effects on BMP-2 Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>BMPs play important roles in regulating growth plate chondrogenesis and longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Of the various forms of BMP, BMP-2 plays an important role in the development of the epiphyseal growth plate [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>BMP-2 stimulates chondrocyte proliferation in the proliferative zone of the growth plate and also causes an increase in chondrocyte hypertrophy [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In this context, it has been suggested that alterations in the expression or production of BMP-2 can modulate the proliferation and activity of bone forming cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In the present study, protein expression of BMP-2 in growth plate was highly expressed in hypertrophic and ossification zones compared to resting and proliferative zones (Figure 4(a)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>As expected, BMP-2 expressions particularly in hypertrophic and ossification zones of the growth plates were increased in the VAU and VAM treated groups compared with the control group (Figures 4(a) and 4(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Numerical values of the BMP-2 expression were increased by 25.8%, 24.7%, and 10.5% with VAU, VAM, and VAB treatment, respectively, compared with control (Figure 4(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The effect on BMP-2 expression in growth plate, which is related to the bone growth and formation, was also decreased downward from upper section to the base. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the effect of VAM was similar to VAU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The results of the in vivo experiment suggest that treatment with VA increases longitudinal bone growth rate by promoting chondrocyte proliferation and chondrogenesis through the upregulation of BMP-2 expression in growth plate, and the effect decreases downward from upper section to the base. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Effects on MG63 Cell Osteogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Bone regeneration is regulated by a fine balance of biochemical and cellular events that ultimately stimulate osteoblasts to produce new tissue, in particular, new extracellular matrix composed mainly of collagen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The collagen matrix is then mineralized via ALP activity, which induces formation of calcium phosphate crystal seeds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Bellows et al. [27] reported that ALP is one of the osteoblast phenotype markers and an essential enzyme for mineralization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Hence, osteoblast proliferation, collagen content, and ALP activity, as early differentiation markers, and cellular calcium content, as a late marker of differentiation, were examined to investigate the effects of VA on the differentiation of MG-63 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>First, the effect of different sections of VA on osteoblast proliferation was examined by BrdU incorporation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5(a), MG-63 cell proliferation was significantly and dose-dependently increased with VAU and VAM treatment (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>MG-63 cell proliferation reached peak value at 50 μg/mL VAU treatment exhibiting 119% of the basal value, while VAM treatment reached peak at 100 μg/mL exhibiting 111% of the basal value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>VAB at the highest concentration (100 μg/mL) significantly (P &lt; 0.05) increased cell proliferation compared to the control exhibiting 106% of the basal value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Effects of VAU and VAM on increasing cell proliferation were significantly higher than those of control at 50 and 100 μg/mL concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the effect of VA on ALP activity in MG-63 cells was further determined at 50 and 100 μg/mL concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>VAU treatment significantly increased the ALP activity, an early-stage osteoblasts differentiation marker, at 100 μg/mL concentration (P &lt; 0.05, Figure 5(b)) compared with control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>VAM and VAB failed to affect ALP level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Hence, collagen content (Figure 5(c)) and calcium deposition (Figure 5(d)) were determined at 100μg/mL of VA concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Collagen synthesis was significantly increased with VAU (11.2%) and VAM (6.2%) treatment compared with control, and the increased collagen synthesis was significantly higher than VAB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Cellular calcium deposition was examined using Alizarin red-S staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Significant increases in mineralization were found with VAU and VAM treatment compared to the control and VAB group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Mineralization was significantly increased to 118% and 107% of the control by VAU and VAM treatment, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The anabolic effect of VA on bone was further supported by the findings in this study demonstrating that VA enhanced the proliferation, differentiation, and mineralization of osteoblastic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the effects of VAU were greater than the effect of VAM, suggesting that the effects were decreased from the upper section to the base section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Lee et al. [28] reported that VA water extract enhanced osteoblasts proliferation and mineralization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, Tseng et al. [19] reported that VAU and VAM dose-dependently increased osteoblasts proliferation as well as mineralization supporting the results of the present study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Effects on Osteogenic Gene Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>It is known that preosteoblastic cells produce proteins of the extracellular matrix including collagen at first and then to successively produce alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and osteopontin/osteocalcin during mineralization phase [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, there is increased expression of osteogenic genes in osteoblasts during the bone formation process, and these genes play roles in extracellular matrix formation and mineral deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Collagen (COL) is a primary gene product of osteoblasts during bone matrix formation and comprises 85–90% of the total organic bone matrix [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Noncollagenous matrix proteins also have a great importance in regulating of ossification and bone remodeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The most abundant noncollagenous protein produced by osteoblasts is osteocalcin (OCN), a phosphorylated glycoprotein which has high affinity for binding ionic calcium and physiologic hydroxyapatite [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Osteopontin (OPN) is an osteoblast-derived, heavily glycosylated protein of the bone matrix, which is expressed at late stages of differentiation, and its appearance closely correlates with the appearance of mineral [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In order to examine the anabolic effect of VA, the mRNA expressions of COL, ALP, OCN, and OPN in MG-63 cells were measured by real-time PCR (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>All sections of the VA (VAU, VAM, and VAB) treatment caused marked upregulation of COL and OCN mRNA levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the effects of VAM and VAB were not significantly different from the effect of VAU in COL and OCN expressions (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The effects of VAU, VAM, and VAB on COL mRNA expressions were increased 7.7-, 6.0-, and 5.8-fold, respectively, while those of OCN expressions were increased 22.5-, 20.2-, and 15.0-fold, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The expressions of ALP mRNA were significantly increased with VAU (3.7-fold) and VAM (3.5-fold) treatment compared with control and VAB group (1.2-fold). OPN mRNA expressions were not altered by all sections of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that VA may play role at early stage as well as late stage of osteoblast differentiation, and VA-induced COL, ALP, and OCN gene expression could accelerate mineralization, subsequently leading to an increase in the extent of calcium deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the effects on osteogenic gene expressions were decreased from upper section to basal section of VA, and the effect of VAM was similar to VAU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Lee et al. [28] reported that VA increased mRNA expression of bone sialoprotein which is related to bone mineralization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Effects on Osteoclastogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Osteoclasts are the only cell type capable of resorbing mineralized bone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>To examine the effect of VA on osteoclast differentiation, bone marrow-derived osteoclast precursor cells were cultured in osteoclastogenic media with different parts of VA extract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>TRAP-positive multinuclear osteoclasts were generated in response to stimulation from M-CSF and RANKL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The results showed that the addition of VA did not affect osteoclast formation (data not shown). Bacillus-fermented VA extract has been reported to inhibit osteoclast differentiation [32] which does not support the results of the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>However, Lee et al. [28] suggested that VA, fermented with Cordyceps militaris, contain more sialic acid than nonfermented VA, and the stimulatory effects on osteoblastic cell proliferation and ALP production were increased by fermentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the effect of nonfermented VA in the present study may not be strong enough to induce osteoclast differentiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, results of the present study suggest that VA promotes longitudinal bone growth in adolescent rats through, at least in part, MG-63 cell osteogenesis, and the effect was decreased downward from upper section to basal section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>VA stimulated the proliferation, differentiation, and mineralization of osteoblasts through upregulation of osteogenic gene expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>These results support the stimulating nature of VA toward the function of osteoblastic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Although the molecular mechanisms underlying osteoblast differentiation remain to be defined, the results of the present study suggest that BMP-2, which plays an important role in regulating osteoblast differentiation and subsequent bone formation, might participate in these mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the present study provides strong evidence for the regional differences in the effectiveness of VA in longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>However, further studies are needed to elucidate the bioactive chemical constituents associated with these effects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The present study has some limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Only a single dose of VA was used in the in vivo study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The dose for traditional use of VA is usually 1 g/day, taken all at once or divided throughout the day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the dose of 100 mg/kg/day given to the experimental rats in this study was equivalent to the traditional human dosing regimen of 1 g/day based on body surface area conversion, where animal dose is equal to human equivalent dose × 6.2, assuming that an adult person's weight is 60 kg [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the “Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science &amp; Technology Development (Project no. PJ010181)” of the Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>1IannottiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>P.Growth plate physiology and pathologyOrthopedic Clinics of North America19902111172-s2.0-00251220472404230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2GuytonA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>C.Text Book of Medical Physiology200010thPhiladelphia, Pa, USAWB Saunders </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>3LeschekE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>W.RoseS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>R.YanovskiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>A.Effect of growth hormone treatment on adult height in peripubertal children with idiopathic short stature: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trialThe Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism20048973140314810.1210/jc.2003-0314572-s2.0-324269991015240584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>4SouzaF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>M.Collett-SolbergP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>F.Adverse effects of growth hormone replacement therapy in childrenArquivos Brasileiros de Endocrinologia e Metabologia201155855956510.1590/S0004-273020110008000092-s2.0-8485544546122218437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>5ChenD.YaoW.-J.ZhangX.-L.Effects of Gekko sulfated polysaccharide-protein complex on human hepatoma SMMC-7721 cells: Inhibition of proliferation and migrationJournal of Ethnopharmacology2010127370270810.1016/j.jep.2009.12.0032-s2.0-7614909954019969061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>6GeG.-F.YuC.-H.YuB.ShenZ.-H.ZhangD.-L.WuQ.-F.Antitumor effects and chemical compositions of Eupolyphaga sinensis Walker ethanol extractJournal of Ethnopharmacology2012141117818210.1016/j.jep.2012.02.0162-s2.0-8486282828522366674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>7GilbeyA.PerezgonzalezJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>D.Health benefits of deer and elk velvet antler supplements: a systematic review of randomised controlled studiesNew Zealand Medical Journal2012125136780862-s2.0-8487276751123321886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>8SuiZ.ZhangL.HuoY.ZhangY.Bioactive components of velvet antlers and their pharmacological propertiesJournal of Pharmaceutical and Biomedical Analysis20148722924010.1016/j.jpba.2013.07.0442-s2.0-8488958382724029381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>9JoS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>J.KimJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>H.KimJ.-W.Comparative studies on velvet deer antler and ossified deer antler on the contents of bioactive components and on the bone mineral density improving activity for oophorectomized ratNatural Product Sciences20131943033102-s2.0-84897387866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>10TsengS.-H.SungH.-C.ChenL.-G.Effects of velvet antler with blood on bone in ovariectomized ratsMolecules2012179105741058510.3390/molecules1709105742-s2.0-8486691814822951396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>11GhoshP.RoubinR.SmithM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>M.SimJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>S.SunwooH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>H.HudsonR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>J.JeonB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>T.Rationale for the use of antler cartilage products and genes obtained from their cells to treat arthritis and repair cartilage defects following joint injuryAntler Science and Product Technology2001Edmonton, CanadaUniversity of Alberta112134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>12ZhangL.-Z.XinJ.-L.ZhangX.-P.FuQ.ZhangY.ZhouQ.-L.The anti-osteoporotic effect of velvet antler polypeptides from Cervus elaphus Linnaeus in ovariectomized ratsJournal of Ethnopharmacology2013150118118610.1016/j.jep.2013.08.0292-s2.0-8488543324923993908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>13JeonB.KimS.LeeS.Effect of antler growth period on the chemical composition of velvet antler in sika deer (Cervus nippon)Mammalian Biology200974537438010.1016/j.mambio.2008.07.0052-s2.0-67651095860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>14PuchtlerH.WaldropF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>S.ValentineL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>S.Polarization microscopic studies of connective tissue stained with picro Sirius red F3BABeiträge zur Pathologie1973150217418710.1016/s0005-8165(73)80016-22-s2.0-00157165644129194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>15PuchtlerH.MeloanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>N.TerryM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>S.On the history and mechanism of alizarin and alizarin red S stains for calciumJournal of Histochemistry and Cytochemistry196917211012410.1177/17.2.1102-s2.0-00144693364179464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>16MinkinC.Bone acid phosphatase: tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase as a marker of osteoclast functionCalcified Tissue International198234128529010.1007/bf024112522-s2.0-00203158216809291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>17GuskumaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>H.Hochuli-VieiraE.PereiraF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>P.Bone regeneration in surgically created defects filled with autogenous bone: an epifluorescence microscopy analysis in ratsJournal of Applied Oral Science201018434635310.1590/s1678-775720100004000052-s2.0-7795773598820835568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>18MundyG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>R.Growth factors as potential therapeutic agents in osteoporosisInstructional Course Lectures1997464954982-s2.0-00306267149143993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>19TsengS.-H.SungC.-H.ChenL.-G.Comparison of chemical compositions and osteoprotective effects of different sections of velvet antlerJournal of Ethnopharmacology2014151135236010.1016/j.jep.2013.10.0602-s2.0-8489149654824212078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>20WangJ.ZhouJ.BondyC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>A.Igf1 promotes longitudinal bone growth by insulin-like actions augmenting chondrocyte hypertrophyThe FASEB Journal19991314198519902-s2.0-003275108710544181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>21AbadV.MeyersJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>L.WeiseM.The role of the resting zone in growth plate chondrogenesisEndocrinology200214351851185710.1210/en.143.5.18512-s2.0-003622773811956168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>22BreurG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>J.VanEnkevortB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>A.FarnumC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>E.WilsmanN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>J.Linear relationship between the volume of hypertrophic chondrocytes and the rate of longitudinal bone growth in growth platesJournal of Orthopaedic Research19919334835910.1002/jor.11000903062-s2.0-00261535932010838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>23WeiseM.De-LeviS.BarnesK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>M.GafniR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>I.AbadV.BaronJ.Effects of estrogen on growth plate senescence and epiphyseal fusionProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200198126871687610.1073/pnas.1211804982-s2.0-003581099511381135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>24BassS.DelmasP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>D.PearceG.HendrichE.TabenskyA.SeemanE.The differing tempo of growth in bone size, mass, and density in girls is region-specificJournal of Clinical Investigation1999104679580410.1172/JCI70602-s2.0-003269921610491415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>25WozneyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>M.RosenV.Bone morphogenetic protein and bone morphogenetic protein gene family in bone formation and repairClinical Orthopaedics and Related Research199834626372-s2.0-00319742849577407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>26De LucaF.BarnesK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>M.UyedaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>A.Regulation of growth plate chondrogenesis by bone morphogenetic protein-2Endocrinology2001142143043610.1210/en.142.1.4302-s2.0-003511139911145607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>27BellowsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>G.AubinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>E.HeerscheJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>M.Initiation and progression of mineralization of bone nodules formed in vitro: the role of alkaline phosphatase and organic phosphateBone and Mineral1991141274010.1016/0169-6009(91)90100-E2-s2.0-00258453721868267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>28LeeH.-S.KimM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>K.KimY.-K.Stimulation of osteoblastic differentiation and mineralization in MC3T3-E1 cells by antler and fermented antler using Cordyceps militarisJournal of Ethnopharmacology2011133271071710.1016/j.jep.2010.10.0472-s2.0-7865139949821040772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>29AubinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>E.LiuF.MalavalL.GuptaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>K.Osteoblast and chondroblast differentiationBone1995172, supplement 1S77S8310.1016/8756-3282(95)00183-e2-s2.0-0029129229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>30SasanoY.ZhuJ.-X.KamakuraS.KusunokiS.MizoguchiI.KagayamaM.Expression of major bone extracellular matrix proteins during embryonic osteogenesis in rat mandiblesAnatomy and Embryology20002021313710.1007/PL000082422-s2.0-003410122310926093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>31SommerB.BickelM.HofstetterW.WetterwaldA.Expression of matrix proteins during the development of mineralized tissuesBone199619437138010.1016/S8756-3282(96)00218-92-s2.0-00302727378894143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>32ChoiS.-W.MoonS.-H.YangH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>J.Antiresorptive activity of bacillus -fermented antler extracts: inhibition of osteoclast differentiationEvidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine20132013974868710.1155/2013/7486872-s2.0-84874923576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>33Reagan-ShawS.NihalM.AhmadN.Dose translation from animal to human studies revisitedThe FASEB Journal200822365966110.1096/fj.07-9574lsf2-s2.0-4044908666517942826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Sections of velvet antler. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Fresh velvet antler was divided into upper (VAU), middle (VAM), and basal (VAB) sections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Effects of velvet antler on longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>(a) Fluorescence photomicrographs of longitudinal sections of the proximal tibias of control and VAU (100 mg/kg) treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>(b) Numerical values of longitudinal bone growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The arrow between the fluorescent line formed by calcein (lower arrow) and the epiphyseal end line of the growth plate (upper arrow) indicates the bone growth during the 24 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>VAU: upper section of VA; VAM: middle section of VA; VAB: basal section of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The data are expressed as means ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The bars with a different letter are significantly different from each other at the level of P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Effects of velvet antler on growth plate height. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(a) Cresyl violet stained sections of tibial growth plates of control and VAU (100 mg/kg) treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>(b) Numerical values of growth plate height. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Upper arrow indicates the resting zone where quiescent chondrocytes are waiting for the proliferation of the growth plates, and lower arrow indicates the ossification zone where cartilaginous matrix begins to calcify and replace with mineralized bone tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>VAU: upper section of VA; VAM: middle section of VA; VAB: basal section of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The data are expressed as means ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Values not sharing a common alphabet are significantly different from each other at the level of P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Effects of velvet antler on BMP-2 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>(a) Immunohistochemical localizations of bone morphogenetic protein-2 (BMP-2) in the growth plates of control and VAU (100 mg/kg) treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>(b) Densitometric results of immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>VAU: upper section of VA; VAM: middle section of VA; VAB: basal section of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Data are shown as a percentage of the control value (means ± SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Values not sharing a common alphabet are significantly different from each other at the level of P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Effects of velvet antler on cell proliferation (a), alkaline phosphatase activity (b), collagen synthesis (c), and calcium deposit (d) in MG-63 human osteoblast-like cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>VAU: upper section of VA; VAM: middle section of VA; VAB: basal section of VA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Data are shown as a percentage of the control value (means ± SD) of the three cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Values not sharing a common alphabet are significantly different from each other at the level of P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Effects of velvet antler on osteogenic gene expression in MG-63 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was used to measure mRNA levels following VA treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Expression of GAPDH was used to normalize all samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>(a) Collagen (COL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>(b) Alkaline phosphatase (ALP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>(c) Osteocalcin (OCN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>(d) Osteopontin (OPN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Data are shown as a fold of the control value (means ± SD) of the three cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Values not sharing a common alphabet are significantly different from each other at the level of P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-1927534.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide sequences of osteogenic genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Primer </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Direction </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Collagen (COL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>5′-GCG GCT CCC CAT TTT TAT ACC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>5′-GCT CTC CTC CCA TGT TAA ATA GCA-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>5′-AAA CCG AGA TAC AAG CAC TCC CAC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>5′-TCC GTC ACG TTG TTC CTG TTC AG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Osteocalcin (OCN) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>5′-CCA TGA GAG CCC TCA CAC TCC TC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>5′-GCT TGG ACA CAA AGG CTG CAC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Osteopontin (OPN) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>5′-AGG CTG ATT CTG GAA GTT CTG AGG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>5′-GAC TTA CTT GGA AGG GYC TGT GGG-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>GAPDH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>5′-TCA TCA ATG GAA ATC CCA TCA CC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>5′-TGG ACT CCA CGA CGT ACT CAG C-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
