<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4899918</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-016-3176-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The effect of an affordable daycare program on health and economic well-being in Rajasthan, India: protocol for a cluster-randomized impact evaluation study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nandi</surname><given-names>Arijit</given-names></name><address><phone>514.398.7849</phone><email>arijit.nandi@mcgill.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>Shannon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Parul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>Anoushaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Institute for Health and Social Policy &amp; Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics &amp; Occupational Health, McGill University, 1130 Pine Avenue West, Montreal, QC H3A 1A3 Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Institute for Financial Management and Research—Leveraging Evidence for Access and Development (IFMR-LEAD), Chennai, Tamil Nadu India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>490</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Nandi et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The provision of affordable and reliable daycare services is a potentially important policy lever for empowering Indian women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Access to daycare might reduce barriers to labor force entry and generate economic opportunities for women, improve education for girls caring for younger siblings, and promote nutrition and learning among children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, empirical evidence concerning the effects of daycare programs in low-and-middle-income countries is scarce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This cluster-randomized trial will estimate the effect of a community-based daycare program on health and economic well-being over the life-course among women and children living in rural Rajasthan, India. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This three-year study takes place in rural communities from five blocks in the Udaipur District of rural Rajasthan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The intervention is the introduction of a full-time, affordable, community-based daycare program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>At baseline, 3177 mothers with age eligible children living in 160 village hamlets were surveyed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>After the baseline, these hamlets were randomized to the intervention or control groups and respondents will be interviewed on two more occasions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Primary social and economic outcomes include women’s economic status and economic opportunity, women’s empowerment, and children’s educational attainment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Primary health outcomes include women’s mental health, as well as children’s nutritional status. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This interdisciplinary research initiative will provide rigorous evidence concerning the effects of daycare in lower-income settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In doing so it will address an important research gap and has the potential to inform policies for improving the daycare system in India in ways that promote health and economic well-being. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>(1) The ISRCTN clinical trial registry (ISRCTN45369145), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN45369145">http://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN45369145</ext-link>, registered on May 16, 2016 and (2) The American Economic Association’s registry for randomized controlled trials (AEARCTR-0000774), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialscienceregistry.org/trials/774">http://www.socialscienceregistry.org/trials/774</ext-link>, registered on July 15, 2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Child day care centers</kwd><kwd>Childcare</kwd><kwd>Nurseries</kwd><kwd>Women’s empowerment</kwd><kwd>Socioeconomic status</kwd><kwd>Health</kwd><kwd>Cluster randomized controlled trial</kwd><kwd>India</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>UK Government’s Department of International Development (DFID)</institution></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>International Development Research Centre (IDRC)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In low- and middle-income countries (LMICs), access to affordable daycare services, defined as “any type of institutional out-of-home care for children younger than five years of age” [1], is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>India, the setting for our trial, lacks a cohesive system of reliable and affordable daycare services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Recent government efforts, including the expansion of financial assistance for crèches (nurseries where young children are cared for during the workday) in 2005–2006 under the auspices of the Rajiv Gandhi National Crèche Scheme, remain inadequate [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A parallel program, the Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS), provides meals to children through local facilities called anganwadis, and expansion of the ICDS into a daycare program has been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>However, anganwadis reach only about one of every six children and are marked by insufficient hours of operation, poorly trained workers, chronic staff absenteeism, and substandard facilities [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It is unclear how existing programs can be adapted to satisfy the demand for full-day childcare. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Women are often charged with the dual responsibilities of child rearing and time-intensive domestic work [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Limited access to daycare represents a potential barrier to paid employment, whether in the formal or informal labor market [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Women who do enter the labor market by taking up paid employment often retain responsibilities for unpaid domestic work and childcare, forcing them to bring children to work, leave them home unattended, or entrust their care to older siblings [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The demand of caring for younger siblings is a key explanation for why adolescent girls, on average, dropout from school before boys [5]; this reduces the economic opportunities available to women directly by limiting their educational achievement and literacy and indirectly by hastening marriage and the time to first childbirth [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The provision of affordable and reliable daycare services is a potentially important policy lever for reducing gender inequality, improving health and socioeconomic well-being, and empowering women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For mothers, access to daycare might reduce barriers to labor force entry and generate economic opportunities, which is one of the building blocks for empowerment [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Additionally, access to daycare might improve women’s mental health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>For example, women report that they perform domestic duties out of compulsion rather than choice [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Access to daycare could alleviate “time poverty”, lower stress levels, and improve mental health and subjective well-being by reducing the conflicting demands on women’s time and increasing women’s autonomy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The provision of daycare may also benefit children and adolescents by removing the responsibility of caring for younger children, which limits educational opportunities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Under-nutrition and illiteracy remain challenges in many LMICs, especially India [10], and daycare programs could also improve children’s health and development outcomes through the provision of meals and learning programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>A conceptual model illustrating the potential links between lack of affordable and reliable daycare services and women’s diminished empowerment is shown in Fig. 1.Fig. 1Conceptual model </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Few empirical studies have evaluated the effects of providing daycare services in LMICs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Several quasi-experimental studies have examined impacts related to women’s economic opportunities and generally report positive effects on the probability of employment and hours worked [11–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Scarcely any studies have examined effects on other household members, although a randomized controlled trial in rural Mozambique showed that educational attainment for older siblings improved in households where a younger child attended preschool [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A systematic review published in 2012 [1] concluded that the influence of daycare on child health and nutrition is unclear, although three studies reported positive effects on developmental outcomes [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>There are several ways to build on extant work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>With respect to internal validity, the existing evidence draws heavily from non-experimental studies that are vulnerable to bias from unmeasured confounding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Appropriately designed quasi-experiments, for example by using instrumental variables, can be useful, but they rely on important assumptions that cannot be verified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Moreover, prior research utilizing instrumental variables [14] has reported effects on nutritional outcomes that were of a biologically implausible magnitude [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>With respect to external validity, prior work is derived almost entirely from Latin American countries and may not be generalizable to other regions, including South Asia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The demand to facilitate women’s labor force participation by providing access to affordable daycare services will continue to increase if India, as well as other LMICs, are to promote inclusive economic growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>However, there is presently a lack of credible research for constructing evidence-based policies for improving access to daycare in India in ways that benefit the health and socioeconomic well-being of women and children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This paper presents the protocol for a cluster-randomized trial, named the Uttam Unnati, or “great progress” study, which aims to address this research gap by evaluating the effect of a community-based daycare program on health and socioeconomic status among women and children living in rural Rajasthan, India. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This is a three-year cluster-randomized trial that examines the effects of introducing an affordable daycare program on health and economic well-being over the life-course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Briefly, a census was completed in late 2014, followed by a baseline survey in early 2015 among 3177 mothers with a child between one and six years of age living in 160 village hamlets from five blocks in the Udaipur district of Rajasthan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In the fall of 2015, Seva Mandir, a local non-governmental development organization that operates daycare programs in other areas in the Udaipur district, established daycares, called balwadis, in 80 randomly selected hamlets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The remaining 80 hamlets serve as control groups that are ineligible to receive a balwadi until after September 2017, by which point mothers will have been re-interviewed twice, in early 2016 and again in early 2017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The study timeline is shown in Fig. 2.Fig. 2Study design and research timeline </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Sample selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Power calculations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Power calculations were used to determine the sample size needed to detect an impact of our intervention on one of the study’s primary outcomes, women’s labor force participation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Given our basic cluster-randomized framework, with clusters specified at the level of the hamlet, the power analysis was based on the following parameters: the significance level, 1 − α, where α represents the probability of a type I error; the sample size per cluster, n; the number of clusters, J; the fraction allocated to treatment versus control, P; and the between and within-cluster variances, τ2 and σ2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Some of these parameters were considered fixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In particular, we assumed a fixed number of 160 clusters given the finite number of treatment naïve hamlets available in our study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We assumed that the proportion of women in the labor force was 30 % (variance = 0.3 * (1 − 0.3) = 0.21) based on pilot data that we had collected in areas lacking access to the balwadi program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We varied other parameters, specifically the sample size per cluster, in order to estimate the sample size necessary for achieving a power, (1 − κ), of 80 % for estimating a feasible and relevant minimum detectable effect size (MDE) in the presence of clustering, measured by the intra-cluster correlation (ICC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The MDE is given by [21]:\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ MDE=\left({t}_{\left(1-\kappa \right)}-{t}_{\alpha /2}\right)\times \sqrt{\frac{1}{P\left(1-P\right)}}\sqrt{\frac{n{\tau}^2+{\sigma}^2}{nJ}} $$\end{document}MDE=t1−κ−tα/2×1P1−Pnτ2+σ2nJ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>For degrees of clustering typical in social science surveys (between 0.01 and 0.05) [22], we determined that a sample size of 20 individuals per 160 clusters was adequate to provide 80 % power to detect MDEs that seemed feasible and relevant (5 to 7 percentage point differences in labor force participation rates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We consider this sample size to be conservative because it assumes no baseline covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>We have collected information in the baseline survey on pre-treatment covariates (including primary outcomes) and plan to include these covariates in our analysis of our outcomes, which should improve our precision [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Participants and village hamlets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In December 2014 and early January 2015, 160 hamlets were selected from five blocks (i.e., Badgaon, Girwa, Jhadol, Kherwara, Kotra) in the Udaipur District where Seva Mandir had not previously established balwadis (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>These hamlets satisfied five criteria determined a priori, specifically: (1) no readily accessible daycare within 1.5 kilometers to reduce the potential for contamination effects; (2) a minimum number of children (≥25) in the appropriate age range in the hamlet to ensure adequate demand; (3) an existing structure suitable for a daycare; (4) a qualified woman, living in the study hamlet or nearby, to operate the daycare; and (5) adequate demand from the village council (Panchayat) for a new daycare.Fig. 3Locations of study hamlets in Udaipur District, Rajasthan, India </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Survey procedures and participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Survey procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The survey questionnaire was translated from English to the localized Hindi language by a professional translator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The translator was instructed to retain the meaning of the questions as they were written in English, but to translate them for the local Hindi speaking audience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Once the translation was complete, a project staff member with knowledge of the local dialect reviewed the questionnaire to ensure that the Hindi version kept the original intent of the questions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The survey software was designed on SQL by the Institute for Financial Management and Research—Leveraging Evidence for Access and Development (IFMR-LEAD) software team. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The final software format was designed through an iterative process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The research associate gave an a initial set of written instructions to the software team, then tested each version of the electronic questionnaire and gave feedback to the team until all errors were corrected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The instructions included rules to reduce surveyor error in data entry, including: automatic skips across appropriate questions, acceptable ranges for relevant variables, flags or error messages when an invalid input has been placed, etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The final version of the survey included a fully functioning set of rules and skips to minimize error in the field. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We tested the face validity of the questionnaire by consulting individuals with local expertise and added, deleted, and revised existing indicators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In mid-2014 we pilot tested the questionnaire in a convenience sample of approximately 200 women from hamlets outside of our sampling frame. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The questionnaire was modified based on the results of the pilot study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We took multiple steps to correct and minimize potential for survey error. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The survey supervisor observed each surveyor for one survey each day, monitoring for correctness in asking survey questions, providing necessary clarifications, and responding to respondent questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A random set of 10 % of completed surveys was selected for back-checks, done to verify that each surveyor recorded the appropriate responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>To do this, the back-check team is given a list of questions asked in the survey that are unlikely to change over a short time period, like the number of children, respondent’s marital and educational status and employment history. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The back-check team independently re-interviewed the respondents and entered their responses into a software program designed to test these questions for identical responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>When a discrepancy is found between the original survey response and the back-check response, a third party was sent to verify the response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The response found to be correct by the third party is taken as the final response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Study participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In late 2014, we completed a household census in each of the 160 hamlets to confirm the eligibility of the hamlet, enumerate the population, and identify potential respondents for inclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Eligible households were those with at least one mother (biological or guardian) with a child between one and six years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>At this time, the respondent was considered eligible if they responded to the question “Do you have any children between one to six years of age” with a yes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Based on this, the total number of eligible households (n = 3899) was similar to our desired sample size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>From this list, we randomly selected one eligible respondent from each eligible household to complete a baseline survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At the time of the baseline survey, we developed a more rigorous approach for measuring the age of the respondent’s children, which included mapping dates to the respondent’s life history, local events and major holidays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This more rigorous method revealed that several “eligible” children were actually older or younger than our target population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A total of 343 respondents were labeled as ineligible due to not having a child between one to six years of age and these households were dropped from our sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Potential respondents were given the opportunity to refuse or consent to participation in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>After describing the study objectives, procedures, potential risks, potential benefits, voluntary nature, confidentiality and privacy protections, and compensation, each eligible respondent was asked if they would consent to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This was done in written form for respondents who could read and write and orally for those who could not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Each respondent who agreed to participate received a blanket, valued at 100 rupees (Rs.), as compensation at the completion of the survey interview. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>After accounting for the households that refused consent, could not be successfully reached after three visits, had migrated to another location, were ineligible or were deemed unable to respond due to any kind of illness or handicap, a total of 3177 respondents were included in the final sample (response rate = 89.0 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The mean completion time for the baseline survey was 50 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Follow-up surveys of baseline participants are scheduled for early 2016 (approximately six to eight months after the intervention started) and again in early 2017. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Randomization and intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Randomization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We used a stratified randomization procedure to randomly assign the 160 hamlets to treatment or control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We stratified by block (n = 5) to prevent variations in the distributions of blocks across treatment groups (e.g., if women in treated hamlets were more likely to reside in blocks with more economic opportunities). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Randomization was performed at McGill University by an investigator (SH) using a de-identified listing without block or hamlet names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Each hamlet was randomized to either the treatment or control within blocks using a random number generator in Stata software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Because four of the five blocks contained an odd number of hamlets, the randomization was done so that two of the four blocks would have an additional treated hamlet and the remaining two would have an additional control hamlet (so the result is 80 treated hamlets). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The de-identified listing, now with a treatment variable, was merged with identifying information, including block and hamlet names, by a separate investigator (AN) and conveyed to Seva Mandir for implementation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Table 1 shows the distribution of socio-demographic characteristics at baseline for the total, treated, and control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In general, baseline characteristics were balanced between the treatment and control arms of the trial, in both individual and cluster-level analyses.Table 1Baseline characteristics for the total sample and stratified by treatment arm, presented at the individual (n = 3177) and cluster (n = 160) levelsIndividual-level analysisTotal sampleControl hamletsTreated hamletsVariablea No.MeanSDNo.MeanSDNo.MeanSDAge (years)316929.876.86151729.876.90165229.866.83Any schooling31750.260.4415190.270.4416560.250.43Married31770.980.1215210.990.1116560.980.14Age married (years)307017.472.85146717.492.70160317.442.98No. sons31771.621.1615211.621.1616561.611.16No. daughters31771.651.2715211.601.2516561.691.28Hindu religion31750.720.4515190.730.4416560.720.45Worked in past 7 d31770.590.4915210.590.4916560.590.49Worked in past 12 mo31770.950.2215210.930.2516560.960.18Paid cash for work30160.090.2814200.090.2915960.090.28Days childcare prevents work30161.534.6614201.644.9715961.424.36Below poverty line31680.500.5015170.510.5016510.500.50Cluster-level comparisonTotal sampleControl hamletsTread hamletsNo.MeanSDNo.MeanSDNo.MeanSDAge (years)16029.891.938029.842.148029.931.70Any schooling1600.270.17800.280.18800.260.16Married1600.980.03800.990.03800.980.04Age married (years)16017.500.748017.490.738017.510.75No. sons1601.600.33801.610.34801.580.32No. daughters1601.650.34801.590.36801.700.31Hindu religion1600.720.15800.740.17800.710.14Worked in past 7 d1600.590.19800.600.19800.580.18Worked in past 12 mo1600.950.07800.940.08800.960.06Paid cash for work1600.090.10800.090.10800.090.09Days childcare prevents work1601.601.67801.781.88801.411.42Below poverty line1600.510.18800.520.19800.500.17 a Variables are: age in years (age); whether the respondent ever attended school (any schooling) or not; whether the respondent was married (married) or not married, including widowed, divorced, separated, or living together married; the age at marriage, if married (age married); the number of sons under age 18 y who live at home (no. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>sons); the number of daughters under age 18 y who live at home (no. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>daughters); Hindu religion (Hindu) or other, including other religion, no religion, or unknown; whether the respondent worked in the past seven days (worked in past 7 d) or not; whether the respondent worked in the past 12 months (worked in past 12 mo) or not; whether respondents who reported working in the past 12 months were paid in cash (paid cash for work) or not; the number of days in the past month that respondents who reported working in the past year were unable to work because of childcare (days childcare prevents work); and whether the household has a Below the Poverty Line card (below poverty line) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The intervention is the introduction of full time, affordable daycare centers in 80 treated hamlets in areas where they are not yet available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Each of the balwadis provides child-care, nutritious food and supplements, basic medicines, and preschool education to children one to six years old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The balwadi program also aims to increase immunization coverage of children by maintaining immunization records and following-up with parents and government nurses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Balwadis are operated by local women, called sanchalikas, who are hired and trained by Seva Mandir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Sanchalikas receive approximately 20 days of training each year regarding their roles and responsibilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The sanchalikas meet with children’s families on a quarterly basis to discuss their child’s progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The implementation of daycare programs in treatment villages was accompanied by a household marketing campaign to encourage sustained enrollment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Take-up rates of the intervention will be available after the mid-line survey is fielded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Blinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Due to the nature of the intervention it was not possible to blind study personnel or participants after the implementation of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>However, we did conceal the allocation of hamlets to treatment or control status until after the baseline survey in order to minimize opportunities for bias in recruitment of participants and the baseline survey. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Monitoring of the intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>We hired two field workers to conduct monthly site visits to each daycare in the treatment arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Each month, these study monitors visit all balwadis in random order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>During the visit, they verify that the balwadi is operating in the correct location, care is provided by a sanchalika, the balwadi structure is adequate, food is provided, the monitoring systems are operational; the monitors also collect other broad level indicators that the intervention is proceeding as planned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>General records for each balwadi maintained by Seva Mandir will be used to measure the average number of children attending the balwadi each month relative to the total enrollment, and the total number of days the balwadi was operating each month vis-à-vis the number of days it should have been open. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The daily operation of each balwadi and attendance of sanchalikas is being assessed using a camera monitoring system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>This system, which has been demonstrated to reduce teacher absenteeism [23], requires sanchalikas to take three self-timed photos each day (9:30 am to 10:00 am at opening, a second after 2.5 h, and a third after 6 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>These digital photos are then used to evaluate the number of days when the balwadi was run for at least 6 h, considered a full day of operation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The sanchalika’s payment is based on their attendance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Sanchalikas receive a monthly salary of Rs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>2,275 monthly if they are present for at least 21 days in a month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Each additional full day is incentivized with a bonus of Rs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>400 up to a maximum of Rs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>5,875 per month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Each day missed compared to the 21-day benchmark results in a penalty of Rs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>175 if the balwadi operated for more than ten days in that month and Rs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>50 if the balwadi operated for ten or less days in that month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we are measuring how frequently each balwadi is visited by community members; Seva Mandir requires that each balwadi is visited by a delegate from the specific block level every three months, by a delegate from the local zone once a month, and by a member of the village development committee once a month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Records maintained by the sanchalika are being used to measure the materials received at each balwadi, including educational materials, medicines, toys, and utensils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Outcome measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Our primary endpoint is women’s empowerment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>We adopted the conceptual approach of Kabeer [8, 9, 24], which incorporates both the personal and political dimensions of empowerment, and developed indicators that captured “women’s sense of self-worth and identity, their willingness to question their own subordinate status, their control over their own lives, and their voice and influence within the family” [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We constructed indicators of empowerment, adapted from the Indian National Family Health Survey [25] whenever possible to facilitate comparability, which encompassed four domains: (1) decision making within the family and control over income (e.g., who decides how the money you earn will be used: mainly you, mainly your husband, or you and your husband jointly?); (2) freedom of movement in the public domain (e.g., are you usually permitted to go to the following places—for example, a market within the village—to buy things: on your own, only if someone accompanies you, or not at all?); (3) participation in community and public life (e.g., are you a member of any type of association, group or club which holds regular meetings?); (4) and views and attitudes on critical gender issues (e.g., please tell me if you agree or disagree with each statement: A married woman should be allowed to work outside the home if she wants to). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>We plan to test the reliability of empowerment measures during the second survey wave. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We will also measure the primary mechanisms hypothesized to link access to daycare to women’s empowerment, including time use, economic opportunity, economic status, and mental health and well-being. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Use of time was measured using a structured questionnaire, adapted from a study by Beaman et al. (2012) [26], that asked respondents whether they spent any time in the past 24 h on specific activities (e.g., gathering fuel or firewood), how much time they spent on each activity, and whether this amount reflected the usual amount of time spent on the activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The questionnaire also asks whether respondents were paid in cash or in-kind for the activities they engaged in. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>We asked about employment experiences, including whether respondents work, their occupation, the type of work, the quantity of work, whether they are paid for their work in cash or in-kind, and what they do with their children while working. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Respondents reported the household income received in the past 12 months from various categories (e.g., agricultural income, business income, rents, remittances, government payments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Household wealth is measured using a series of questions about ownership of specific assets (e.g., telephone, bicycle, radio), environmental conditions (e.g., type of water source, sanitation facilities), and housing characteristics, (e.g., number of rooms, materials used for housing construction). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Additionally, respondents are asked about savings accounts held by household members, including for each account the type of account, its purpose, the total value, and whether the respondent can use the account to make purchases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Symptoms of common mental disorders (CMD) are being assessed using the 12-item General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12) developed by Goldberg [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The GHQ-12 produces results that are similar to the longer version of the GHQ and has been found to be a valid screening instrument for CMD in diverse settings [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, validation studies have not been conducted among women living in Rajasthan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, the GHQ-12 demonstrated high sensitivity and specificity in a validation study conducted in Goa, India using a cutoff score of 5/6 [29], a sample of primary care patients in Tamil Nadu using a cutoff score of 2/3 [30], and a sample of ethnic Indian women living in the United Kingdom using a cutoff score of 2/3 [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We used the Hindi version of the GHQ-12 translated by Gautam et al. [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>We asked mothers about the health of their children under the age of six. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>We asked about their child’s immunization coverage, including Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG), Diptheria-Tetanus-Pertussis (DTP), hepatitis, measles, and polio vaccines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>We also asked about the occurrence of specific symptoms over the past month, including fever, persistent cough, diarrhea, broken bones, cuts, or burns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we measured child length/height and weight using standardized techniques and this information will be used to derive children’s length/height-for-age, weight-for-age, weight-for-length/height, and body mass index (BMI)-for-age using the World Health Organization Child Growth Standards [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Other covariates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Other covariates included socio-demographic characteristics, including respondent’s age, educational attainment, religion, caste, and marital status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>We asked the respondent to report the following information for all children in the household who were less than eighteen years of age: literacy, enrollment in school, time spent in school in the prior year, highest level of education completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>For children not enrolled in school we asked about why they were not in school and their main occupation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we asked about the husband of married respondents, including their age, educational attainment, and occupation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistics, including comparisons of means and proportions, were used to compare socio-demographic characteristics between the treatment and control arms (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We will conduct intention-to-treat analyses assuming that respondents complied with their initial treatment assignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We will estimate the impact of the treatment, access to affordable daycare, on primary endpoints with marginal linear and log-linear regression models using generalize estimating equations to account for clustering at the hamlet level [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Multivariable regression will be used to control for block, which was used to stratify the randomization, and pre-treatment values of endpoints, in order to improve the precision of our estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Results will be reported on the absolute and relative scales as risk differences and risk ratios with their respective 95 % confidence intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Results will be reported following the CONSORT statements for randomized trials and cluster randomized trials [35, 36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Trial status </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>At the time of submission the intervention had been introduced in treatment areas and data collection as part of the mid-line survey was being planned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This paper provides the protocol for a cluster-randomized evaluation of the impact of access to affordable daycare on social, economic, and health outcomes of rural Indian women and their children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Prior evidence of daycare impacts on women has been limited by non-randomized designs, and outcomes have generally focused on children rather than mothers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Moreover, most prior research has been conducted in Latin America. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>We are monitoring and attempting to mitigate threats to the internal validity of our study, which include partial compliance, attrition, and spillovers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>First, partial compliance could occur if hamlets assigned to the treatment arm did not open a daycare center or closed a daycare center before the end of the study period; this would tend to reduce the difference in treatment receipt between treated and control clusters and dilute the true treatment effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>A daycare center might close in a treated hamlet if a government anganwadi were to open in the same hamlet (Seva Mandir does not operate balwadis in hamlets with a government anganwadi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a center might close if a sanchalika became unable to operate the center and a suitable replacement could not be identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Seva Mandir has worked in partnership with the community in the Udaipur District since 1968 and study hamlets were restricted to areas with adequate demand expressed by village councils; thus, we do not anticipate substantial non-compliance in our treatment arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Treatment effects might also be diluted if government anganwadis are established in control hamlets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Second, attrition could occur in our study if respondents are lost to follow-up during the study period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>We are attempting to prevent selection bias by minimizing losses to follow-up; strategies include making at least three visits to respondents’ homes to conduct interviews, collecting detailed address and telephone information to track individuals over time for follow-up interviews, and providing an incentive to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Given the relatively short time frame for our study we do not expect a substantial rate of attrition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Third, spillovers could occur if, for example, respondents of control villages enrolled their children in balwadis in treatment villages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In order to reduce potential spillovers, we utilized a cluster-level design and did not select control hamlets within a buffer of approximately 1.5 kilometers from a treated hamlet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Moreover, hamlets in the region are typically dispersed and daily travel between hamlets is relatively rare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Seva Mandir’s prior work suggests that the risk of women in a neighboring hamlet taking up day-care in a treated hamlet is low. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Rajasthan is among India’s poorer states and the results of our study may better generalize to other low-income contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>However, there may be limitations to our study in terms of external validity and potential scale-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Our study is being conducted in selected areas that have adequate demand to sustain a daycare center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we are evaluating a model of daycare designed by a non-governmental organization that has been operating in the region for many years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Whether results concerning the impact of the balwadi program can be generalized to other rural areas lacking affordable daycare service within India, or to different daycare models, is unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Caveats considered, there are several strengths to our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>First, randomization provides rigorous evaluation by ensuring that treatment and control groups are similar with respect to measured and unmeasured characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Second, randomization at the hamlet-level limits the potential for spillover or contamination effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Third, the extent to which the costs of day-care programs are offset by benefits is unknown and we will perform a prospective cost-effectiveness analysis to increase the policy relevance of our findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Cost-effective interventions to improve women’s empowerment are urgently needed, especially in regions where existing indicators suggest that women’s empowerment is low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Our cluster-level design, described in this study protocol, will help to improve the quality of evidence on whether providing community-run full-time daycare may improve economic opportunities and empowerment among rural women. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>BCG, Bacillus Calmette-Guérin; BMI, body mass index; CMD, common mental disorders; DTP, Diptheria-Tetanus-Pertussis; GHQ-12, 12-item General Health Questionnaire; ICDS, Integrated Child Development Scheme; IFMR-LEAD, Institute for Financial Management and Research—Leveraging Evidence for Access and Development; LMICs, low- and middle-income countries; MDE, minimum detectable effect size </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>ᅟ</title><p>ᅟ</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was carried out with financial support from the UK Government’s Department of International Development (DFID) and the International Development Research Centre (IDRC), Canada. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of DFID or IDRC.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p>The data collected as part of this ongoing trial will be made available at the end of the study, after all data have been collected and cleaned.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>AN, SH, PA, and SM developed the research question, conceptualized the study design, and oversee the trial protocol development and implementation. AC supports the implementation of the trial protocol and local management and monitoring of the trial. AN and SH wrote the initial draft of the paper. All authors reviewed the manuscript for important intellectual content, contributed to the interpretation and revision of the manuscript, and approved the final draft.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The Institutional Review Board of McGill University’s Faculty of Medicine and the Human Subjects Committee of the Institute for Financial Management and Research in Chennai, India approved this study. Potential respondents were given the opportunity to refuse or consent to participation in the study. After describing the study objectives, procedures, potential risks, potential benefits, voluntary nature, confidentiality and privacy protections, and compensation, each eligible respondent was asked if they would consent to participate. This was done in written form for respondents who could read and write and orally for those who could not.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>1.LeroyJLGadsdenPGuijarroMThe impact of daycare programmes on child health, nutrition and development in developing countries: a systematic reviewJ Dev Eff20124472496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>2.ChopraGEarly childhood care and education: right to survival and developmentChild rights in India2015New DelhSpringer4576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3.PalriwalaRNeethaNStratified familialism: the care regime in India through the lens of childcareDev Change2011421049107810.1111/j.1467-7660.2011.01717.x<?supplied-pmid 22165159?>22165159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>4.QuisumbingARHallmanKRuelMTMaquiladoras and market mamas: Women’s work and childcare in Guatemala City and AccraJ Dev Stud20074342045510.1080/00220380701204380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>5.LokshinMMGlinskayaEGarciaMThe effect of early childhood development programmes on women’s labour force participation and older children’s schooling in KenyaJ Afr Econ20041324027610.1093/jae/ejh009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>6.ChatterjeePIndia grapples with its child marriage challengeLancet20113781987198810.1016/S0140-6736(11)61860-6<?supplied-pmid 22171371?>22171371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>7.Sharma R, Sharma S, Nagar S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Extent of female school drop outs in Kangra District of Himachal Pradesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>J Soc Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>2007;15:201–4. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>8.Kabeer N, Mahmud S, Tasneem S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="?"><plain>Does paid work provide a pathway to women’s empowerment? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Empirical findings from Bangladesh: Institute of Development Studies; 2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Available from: http://www.ids.ac.uk/idspublication/does-paid-work-provide-a-pathway-to-women-s-empowerment-empirical-findings-from-bangladesh </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>9.Kabeer N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Women’s economic empowerment and inclusive growth: labour markets and enterprise development: UK DFID and IDRC; 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Available from: https://www.soas.ac.uk/cdpr/publications/papers/file80432.pdf </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>10.SubramanianSVSmithGDPatterns, distribution, and determinants of under- and overnutrition: a population-based study of women in IndiaAm J Clin Nutr200684633640<?supplied-pmid 16960179?>16960179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>11.Angeles G, Gadsden P, Galiani S, Gertler P, Herrera A, Kariger P, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The impact of daycare on maternal labour supply and child development in Mexico, 3ie Impact Evaluation Report 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>New Delhi: International Initiative for Impact Evaluation (3ie); 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>12.BerlinskiSGalianiSMcEwanPJPreschool and maternal labor market outcomes: evidence from a regression discontinuity designEcon Dev Cult Change2011931334410.1086/65712421174882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>13.CalderonGThe effects of child care provision in Mexico2012StanfordStanford University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>14.Attanasio O, Vera-Hernandez M: Medium- and long run effects of nutrition and child care: evaluation of a community nursery programme in rural Colombia, IFS report EWP04/06. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The Institue for Fiscal Studies; 2004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>15.DuFDongX-yWomen’s employment and child care choices in urban China during the economic transitionEcon Dev Cult Change20136213115510.1086/671714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>16.Barros R, Olinto P, Lunde T, Carvalho M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The impact of access to free childcare on women’s labor market outcomes: evidence from a randomized trial in low-income neighborhoods of Rio de Janeiro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>enGender Impact : the World Bank’s Gender Impact Evaluation Database [Internet]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18329757/impact-access-free-childcare-womens-labor-market-outcomes-evidence-randomized-trial-low-income-neighborhoods-rio-de-janeiro">http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18329757/impact-access-free-childcare-womens-labor-market-outcomes-evidence-randomized-trial-low-income-neighborhoods-rio-de-janeiro</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>17.Martinez S, Naudeau S, Pereira V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The promise of preschool in Africa: A randomized impact evaluation of early childhood development in rural Mozambique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>enGender Impact : the World Bank’s Gender Impact Evaluation Database [Internet]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18357375/promise-preschool-africa-randomized-impact-evaluation-early-childhood-development-rural-mozambique">http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18357375/promise-preschool-africa-randomized-impact-evaluation-early-childhood-development-rural-mozambique</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>18.BerlinskiSGalianiSGertlerPThe effect of pre-primary education on primary school performanceJ Public Econ20099321923410.1016/j.jpubeco.2008.09.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>19.BernalRFernándezCSubsidized childcare and child development in Colombia: Effects of Hogares Comunitarios de Bienestar as a function of timing and length of exposureSoc Sci Med201397241910.1016/j.socscimed.2012.10.029<?supplied-pmid 23312302?>23312302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>20.BehrmanJRChengYToddPEEvaluating preschool programs when length of exposure to the program varies: A nonparametric approachRev Econ Stat20048610813210.1162/003465304323023714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>21.GlennersterRTakavarashaKRunning randomized evaluations: A practical guide2013PrincetonPrinceton University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>22.BloomHSLearning more from social experiments: Evolving analytic approaches2005New YorkRussell Sage </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>23.DufloEHannaRRyanSPIncentives work: Getting teachers to come to schoolAm Econ Rev20121021241127810.1257/aer.102.4.1241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>24.KabeerNResources, agency, achievements: Reflections on the measurement of women’s empowermentDev Change19993043546410.1111/1467-7660.00125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>25.KishorSGuptaKWomen’s empowerment in India and its states: evidence from the NFHSEcon Polit Wkly200439694712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>26.BeamanLDufloEPandeRTopalovaPFemale leadership raises aspirations and educational attainment for girls: A policy experiment in IndiaScience201233558258610.1126/science.1212382<?supplied-pmid 22245740?>22245740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>27.GoldbergDIdentifying psychiatric illness among general medical patientsBMJ198529116116210.1136/bmj.291.6489.161<?supplied-pmid 3926105?>3926105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>28.Goldberg DP, Gater R, Sartorius N, Ustun T, Piccinelli M, Gureje O, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The validity of two versions of the GHQ in the WHO study of mental illness in general health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Psychol Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>1997;27:191–7. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>29.Patel V, Araya R, Chowdhary N, King M, Kirkwood B, Nayak S, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Detecting common mental disorders in primary care in India: a comparison of five screening questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Psychol Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2008;38:221–8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>30.KuruvillaAPothenMPhilipKBraganzaDJosephAJacobKThe validation of the Tamil version of the 12 item general health questionnaireIndian J Psychiatry199941217<?supplied-pmid 21455393?>21455393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>31.JacobKBhugraDMannAThe Validation of the 12-item General Health Questionnaire among ethnic Indian women living in the United KingdomPsychol Med1997271215121710.1017/S0033291796004436<?supplied-pmid 9300525?>9300525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>32.GautamSNijhawanMKamalPStandardisation of hindi version of Goldberg’s General Health QuestionnaireIndian J Psychiatry19872963<?supplied-pmid 21927210?>21927210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>33.WHO Multicentre Growth Reference Study Group and Mercedes de Onis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>WHO Child Growth Standards based on length/height, weight and age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Acta Paediatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Suppl 2006;450:76–85. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1651-2227.2006.tb02378.x/abstract;jsessionid=E4733CA7BD8C69D5955CADD81CD0704E.f03t04?userIsAuthenticated=false&amp;deniedAccessCustomisedMessage=">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1651-2227.2006.tb02378.x/abstract;jsessionid=E4733CA7BD8C69D5955CADD81CD0704E.f03t04?userIsAuthenticated=false&amp;deniedAccessCustomisedMessage=</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>34.ZegerSLLiangKYLongitudinal data analysis for discrete and continuous outcomesBiometrics19864212113010.2307/2531248<?supplied-pmid 3719049?>3719049 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>35.Moher D, Hopewell S, Schulz KF, Montori V, Gøtzsche PC, Devereaux P, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>CONSORT 2010 explanation and elaboration: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>J Clin Epidemiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>2010;63:e1–e37. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>36.CampbellMKElbourneDRAltmanDGCONSORT statement: extension to cluster randomised trialsBMJ200432870270810.1136/bmj.328.7441.702<?supplied-pmid 15031246?>15031246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
