<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mbt2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1751-7915</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1751-7915</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4554469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26152665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.12298</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Characterization of microbial community structure during continuous anaerobic digestion of straw and cow manure </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>Phillip B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eijsink</surname><given-names>Vincent G H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schnürer</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Microbiology, Swedish University of Agricultural Science, Uppsala BioCenter</institution><addr-line>P.O. Box 7025, SE-750 07, Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Chemistry, Biotechnology and Food Science, Norwegian University of Life Sciences</institution><addr-line>P.O. Box 5003, NO-1432, Ås, Norway</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
* For correspondence. E-mail <email>Anna.Schnurer@slu.se</email>; Tel. (+46) 18 673288; Fax (+46) 18 673392.
</corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Funding Information We acknowledge MicroDrive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.slu.se/microdrive">http://www.slu.se/microdrive</ext-link>) and The Swedish Energy Agency for the financial support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This work was also funded in part by the Research Council of Norway, Grant Numbers 190877/S60 and 203402/E20. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Journal compilation © 2015 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Society for Applied Microbiology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Responses of bacterial and archaeal communities to the addition of straw during anaerobic digestion of manure at different temperatures (37°C, 44°C and 52°C) were investigated using five laboratory-scale semi-continuous stirred tank reactors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that including straw as co-substrate decreased the species richness for bacteria, whereas increasing the operating temperature decreased the species richness for both archaea and bacteria, and also the evenness of the bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Taxonomic classifications of the archaeal community showed that Methanobrevibacter dominated in the manure samples, while Methanosarcina dominated in all digesters regardless of substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Increase of the operating temperature to 52°C led to increased relative abundance of Methanoculleus and Methanobacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Among the bacteria, the phyla Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes dominated within all samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Compared with manure itself, digestion of manure resulted in a higher abundance of an uncultured class WWE1 and lower abundance of Bacilli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Adding straw to the digesters increased the level of Bacteroidia, while increasing the operating temperature decreased the level of this class and instead increased the relative abundance of an uncultured genus affiliated to order MBA08 (Clostridia). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A considerable fraction of bacterial sequences could not be allocated to genus level, indicating that novel phylotypes are resident in these communities. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In recent years, the search for renewable energy resources to replace fossil fuels has received increasing attention worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Anaerobic digestion (AD) represents a highly interesting approach in this regard, since it allows various organic waste materials and dedicated energy crops to be converted to a renewable energy carrier (biogas), and produces a nutrient-rich residue that can be used as fertilizer in agriculture (Weiland, 2010; Appels et al., 2011; Nkoa, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Among various possible substrates, agricultural residues, such as manure and straw, offer great potential for AD (Wang et al., 2009; Appels et al., 2011; Tsavkelova and Netrusov, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, the use of these materials for biogas production is still somewhat restricted because of their high content of lignocellulose, which is difficult to degrade due to its intricate structure, with cellulose fibres tightly linked to hemicellulose and lignin (Tsavkelova and Netrusov, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Consequently, lignocellulosic materials typically result in slow degradation and low biogas yields (Angelidaki and Ellegaard, 2003; Hendriks and Zeeman, 2009; Frigon and Guiot, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Moreover, using straw for biogas production requires co-digestion with a nutrient-rich material, as straw has a high C/N ratio and low levels of trace metals (Lehtomäki et al., 2007; Estevez et al., 2012; Risberg et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The biogas potential of straw can be improved by a combination of different measures, but so far no clear and generally applicable solution has been identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>One way to improve the digestibility is to use pretreatment techniques, such as steam explosion, but such strategies increase energy consumption, possibly threatening the economic feasibility of the process (Hendriks and Zeeman, 2009; Frigon and Guiot, 2010; Galbe and Zacchi, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Some attempts have also been made to improve the degradation efficiency by using hydrolytic enzymes, as a pretreatment or direct additive, or by addition of specific cellulose-degrading bacteria (Parawira, 2012; Peng et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Although not providing clear answers yet, these studies clearly indicate the potential for improved degradation efficiency through increased knowledge of cellulose-degrading organisms, and eventually more efficient cellulose conversion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The formation of methane proceeds via a complex process involving four microbial steps: hydrolysis, fermentation, acetogenesis and methanogenesis (Zinder and Koch, 1984; Angelidaki et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>When lignocellulose-rich materials, such as straw, are used as substrate for biogas production, hydrolysis of cellulose was suggested to be the rate-limiting step (Noike et al., 1985; Lynd et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The taxonomy and phylogeny of microbial communities within the AD process have been studied by various culture-based and molecular methods, including construction of clone libraries and sequencing by targeting 16S rDNA and functional genes (Klocke et al., 2008; Liu et al., 2009; Sun et al., 2013; Vanwonterghem et al., 2014; Ziganshina et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In addition, the development and application of next-generation sequencing technologies has enabled time and cost-efficient studies of the microbial communities in various biogas processes (Werner et al., 2011; Sundberg et al., 2013; Ziganshin et al., 2013; Yang et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The microorganisms involved in the hydrolysis step have been studied in ruminating animals, and more recently also in the biogas process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the rumen of cattle, ubiquitous detected genera include Clostridium, Bacteroides, Succinivibrio, Prevotella and Ruminococcus (Dowd et al., 2008; Callaway et al., 2010). Fibrobacter, formerly grouped to Bacteroides, as well as Ruminococcus and uncultured bacteria have also been suggested to play important roles in cellulose hydrolysis in the rumen (Leschine, 1995; Ransom-Jones et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>For the biogas production process, just a few previous studies have specifically addressed the hydrolysis step. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In a recent study by Lebuhn and colleagues (2014), Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes were suggested to be important in a hydrolytic/acidogenic digester fed with dried hay and straw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These two phyla have also been shown to be important during batch digestion of wheat straw and swine manure (Li et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In a previous study, we investigated the cellulolytic community in biogas digesters operating at different temperatures with a mixture of straw and manure or manure alone, by specifically targeting the glycoside hydrolase families 5 and 48 (Sun et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In that study, all sequenced clones belonged to the phyla Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>However, the entire microbial community was not investigated, and the total response to the addition of straw and to the temperature shifts remains unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>To gain a better understanding of the response of the microbial community to straw-rich materials, in the present study the same laboratory-scale semi-continuous reactors were employed for extended analysis of both the bacterial and archaeal communities by means of 454-pyrosequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>More specifically, the aims of this study were to examine (i) the microbial communities using manure as sole substrate, (ii) the microbial response caused by addition of straw and (iii) the impact of different operating temperatures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Ecological index of archaeal and bacterial community </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Amplicon pyrosequencing of 25 samples yielded 77 791 and 64 731 non-chimeric reads for archaea and bacteria respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The number of operational taxonomic units (OTUs) per sample ranged from 12 to 25 for archaea and from 112 to 277 for bacteria (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic compositions as determined by principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) of unweighted UniFrac matrices (Fig. 1) for the archaeal and bacterial communities within the same digester at multiple sampling points over time were similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>For instance, the four sampling points of the parallel digesters RTcSS (reactors operated with steam-exploded straw and manure at 37°C, Risberg et al., 2013) were clustered closely together, indicating comparable phylogenetic structures within a total period of 91 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the communities in all parallel digesters running under the same conditions were also comparable, e.g. the community in duplicate reactors running with steam-exploded straw and manure at different temperatures (R37SS, R44SS and R52SS) was also similar at individual time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The estimated richness for all samples analysed at all sampling points based on the Chao1 index indicated that the observed phylotypes covered 23–93% and 48–82% of the archaeal and bacterial populations respectively (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In general, the species richness expressed as the number of observed OTUs decreased as the operating temperature increased for both bacteria and archaea (Table 1 and Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>For bacterial reads, no species richness difference was observed between manure itself and the digester operated with manure alone (RM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>However, a slightly lower bacterial species richness was observed in digesters that received straw in the substrate (digesters RTcSS and R37SS) than that operated with manure alone (RM) (Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In contrast, for archaea, no clear trend in species richness was observed when comparing the manure itself and the mesophilic digesters operating with manure, alone or combined with straw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The Simpson diversity index ranged from 0.53 to 0.78 for archaea and from 0.72 to 0.98 for bacteria (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For the bacterial community, a lower Simpson index was observed during the increase in operating temperature, suggesting lower community evenness in these digesters (R44SS and R52SS, digesters processing straw and manure at 44°C and 52°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Compared with the bacterial community, the Simpson index was generally lower for the archaeal community, and with the lowest value in R44SS compared with R37SS and R52SS (Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The Shannon diversity index varied from 1.46 to 2.64 for archaea and from 3.45 to 6.36 for bacteria (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Within the bacterial community, the Shannon index was comparably lower in digesters operating with straw at higher temperatures, i.e. at 44°C and 52°C compared with 37°C (Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For the archaeal community, a lower Shannon diversity index was observed in R44SS compared with R37/TcSS and R52SS (Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.05), and in RM compared with R37/TcSS (Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Summary of observed OTUs, Chao1, Shannon and Simpson index in manure (S1 and S2 correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (RTcSS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R37SS, R44SS and R52SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Sample </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Archaea </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Bacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Chao1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>OTUs </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Shannon </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Simpson </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Chao1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>OTUs </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Shannon </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Simpson </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Manure S1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2.081 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>0.648 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>358 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>270 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>6.361 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>0.971 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Manure S2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>2.404 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>0.693 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>420 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>274 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>6.167 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>0.957 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>RM Day 42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>2.028 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>0.639 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>487 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>266 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>6.355 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>0.975 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>RM Day 85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>1.848 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>0.607 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>553 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>277 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>6.292 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>0.972 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>RM Day 148 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>1.870 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>0.597 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>440 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>253 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>5.819 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>0.956 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R1 Day 9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>2.369 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>0.747 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>320 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>191 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>4.896 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>0.910 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R2 Day 9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2.367 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>0.723 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>371 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>225 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>5.550 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>0.949 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>R37SS R1 Day 9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>2.271 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>0.736 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>398 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>209 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>5.221 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>0.932 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>R37SS R2 Day 9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>2.309 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>0.714 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>425 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>203 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>5.197 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>0.934 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R1 Day 38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>2.643 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>0.777 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>309 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>197 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>5.463 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>0.952 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R2 Day 38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>47 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>2.612 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>0.759 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>319 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>198 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>5.524 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>0.953 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>R37SS R1 Day 38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>2.295 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>0.737 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>325 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>212 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>5.377 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>0.936 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>R37SS R2 Day 38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>2.117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>0.632 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>398 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>209 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>5.494 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>0.951 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R1 Day 80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>2.390 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>0.744 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>421 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>244 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>6.134 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>0.969 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R2 Day 80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>2.237 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>0.682 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>315 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>217 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>5.811 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>0.959 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>R37SS R1 Day 80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>1.740 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>0.533 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>374 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>229 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>5.688 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>0.950 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>R37SS R2 Day 80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>101 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>2.438 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>0.751 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>358 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>234 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>5.819 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>0.948 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R1 Day 99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>2.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>0.639 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>375 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>235 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>5.988 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>0.965 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>RTcSS R2 Day 99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>44 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>1.704 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>0.569 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>334 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>221 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>5.900 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>0.959 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>R37SS R1 Day 99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>2.530 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>0.736 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>321 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>232 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>6.064 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>0.968 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>R37SS R2 Day 99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>2.399 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>0.729 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>391 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>224 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>5.827 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>0.959 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>R44SS R1 Day 224 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>1.618 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>0.594 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>191 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>156 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>5.015 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>0.923 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>R44SS R2 Day 224 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>1.456 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>0.545 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>255 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>158 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>4.906 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>0.926 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>R52SS R1 Day 402 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>2.150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>0.718 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>149 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>112 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>3.446 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>0.717 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>R52SS R2 Day 402 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>2.233 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>0.731 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>165 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>119 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>4.023 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>0.787 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>(A) Archaeal and (B) bacterial phylogenetic distances between samples as determined by unweighted UniFrac principal coordinate analysis (red = manure; blue = digester RM; orange = digester RTcSS and R37SS; green = digester R44SS; purple = digester R52SS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbt20008-0815-f1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of archaeal communities across samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>For archaea, the OTU table was randomly subsampled 640 times prior to downstream analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>It was possible to assign more than 99.6% of the sequences at the phylum level, among which more than 98.1% belonged to the phylum Euryarchaeota (mainly the classes Methanomicrobia and Methanobacteria). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The rest of the sequences (&lt; 1.9%) were represented by Crenarchaeota and unclassified sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>For each sample, at least 95.1% of the sequences could be assigned to genus level (Fig. 2). Methanosarcina from the order Methanosarcinales, known to utilize both acetate and hydrogen, was the most dominant genus in digesters RM (97.4–99.5%), RTcSS and R37SS (90.3–98.8%), R44SS (96.9–97.7%), and R52SS (74.1–77.1%), while this genus represented only 1.3% and 6.4% of the reads from the two manure samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Sequences belonging to the acetoclastic methanogen, Methanosaeta, were only detected in two samples and at a low level, in RM on day 42 (1.1%) and in RTcSS R1 on day 9 (0.2%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>For hydrogenotrophic methanogens, the genus Methanoculleus represented less than 0.3% in all digesters operating at 37°C and 44°C, but corresponded to 6.9–11.9% in R52SS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>In the manure samples, the genus Methanoculleus represented less than 0.4% of the community; instead, the archaeal community was dominated by Methanobrevibacter from the order Methanobacteriales (85.2% and 93.3%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>However, the levels of Methanobrevibacter were low in all digesters (&lt; 3.1%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In addition, sequences related to the genus Methanobacterium were found at low levels in the low-medium temperature digesters (37–44°C) and in the manure (&lt; 2.5%), but were more abundant at the higher digestion temperature (12.3–14.4% in R52SS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Relative abundance of archaea 16S rRNA gene at the genus level in manure (S1 and S2 correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (RTcSS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R37SS, R44SS and R52SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbt20008-0815-f2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of bacterial communities across samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The bacterial OTU table was rarefied 1700 times according to the sample having the lowest sequence counts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>It was possible to assign at least 97.2% of the sequence reads at the phylum level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>However, only 10.7–38.8% of total sequences could be allocated to known genus (Fig. S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes and Cloacimonetes were identified as the three most dominant phyla within the bacterial community (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>In addition, sequences belonging to Acidobacteria, Actinobacteria, Chloroflexi, Fibrobacteres, Planctomycetes, Proteobacteria, Synergistetes, Tenericutes, Thermi and Verrucomicrobia were detected in some of the samples, but at low occurrence (below 3.3% for each sample). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Firmicutes was observed in all digesters as well as in the manure samples, with the highest relative abundance in the digesters operated at 52°C (97.6–97.8%), followed by the digesters operated at 44°C (76.5–82.5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>In the remaining samples, the relative abundance of sequences belonging to this phylum was 56.8–74.1% (manure), 45.9–50.4% (RM, digester operated with manure alone) and 32.6–49.5% (R37SS and RTcSS, Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Within the Firmicutes, sequences belonging to the classes Bacilli and Clostridia dominated (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The class Clostridia was represented in similar levels in the digesters operated at 37°C (26.8–41.9%) and in the manure samples (30.4–34.9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>However, in line with the increase in operating temperature, the relative abundance of sequences within this class increased and was 66.8–77.2% and 92.4–93.8% in R44SS and R52SS respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Within the class Clostridia, sequences belonging to the order Clostridiales and to the uncultured order MBA08 were found to be dominant (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Clostridiales was present in manure (29.4–33.7%) and all digesters (10.1–38.8) with the lowest relative abundance at 52°C (10.1–15.0%), while MBA08 was not detected in manure but in all digesters (1.9–74.4%) with the highest relative abundance at 52°C (67.1–74.4%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Within the order Clostridiales, the families Peptostreptococcaceae (5.4–18.1%) and Clostridiaceae (2.2–11.1%) were identified as the major groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>In addition, Lachnospiraceae, Ruminococcaceae, Syntrophomonadaceae, Peptococcaceae, Catabacteriaceae, Eubacteriaceae and Veillonellaceae were present at lower levels (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Within the Clostridiaceae, sequences belonging to the genera Clostridium and Sedimentibacter dominated (Fig. S2). Clostridium was detected in all sampling points (0.7–4.4%). Sedimentibacter was absent in R52SS but detected in the other samples, with a slightly higher level in digesters receiving straw (3.0–6.9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>For the class Bacilli, a higher relative abundance was seen in the manure samples (23.5–36.2%) than in all digester samples (2.3–8.6%, Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The orders Lactobacillales and Turicibacterales represented the major fraction of sequences within this class in all samples (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Lactobacillales had a higher relative abundance in manure samples compared with digester samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Relative abundance of bacterial 16S rRNA gene at the class level in manure (S1 and S2 correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (RTcSS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R37SS, R44SS and R52SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbt20008-0815-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Relative abundance of bacterial 16S rRNA gene at the order level in manure (S1 and S2 correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (RTcSS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R37SS, R44SS and R52SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbt20008-0815-f4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>For the phylum Bacteroidetes, the class Bacteroidia represented more than 98.8% of the sequences in all samples (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>However, at the genus level, most of the sequences within this phylum were represented by uncultured clones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The relative level of the phylum Bacteroidetes in the digester operating with manure was similar to that in the raw manure (21.0–39.4%), but lower than that in the digesters co-digesting straw at 37°C (40.0–65.1%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the response to straw addition, the relative abundance of Bacteroidetes decreased with increased operating temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>At 44°C and 52°C, Bacteroidetes represented 13.2–16.6% and 0.40% of the population respectively (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The candidate phylum Cloacimonetes was present at levels corresponding to less than 0.2% in the manure samples, but at higher levels in digesters operating with only manure (6.0–14.5%) (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>In the digesters operating with straw, the level of this phylum varied from 0.30% to 10.3% during operation at 37°C, and it was not detected at all in digesters operated at 44°C and 52°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Within all the digesters operated at 37°C, sequences belonging to the uncultured cluster WWE1 (at class level) contributed to the majority of this phylum (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The sequence analysis showed that the microbial community structure in digesters with the same treatment and in parallel digesters was relatively stable and similar over the whole operating period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>This stability indicates that the differences in communities observed for different groups of digesters in the present study were caused by different operating conditions (i.e. temperature, substrate) and not just by variations due to time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>For archaea, the dominant phylum was Euryarchaeota, as found previously in other pyrosequencing studies on anaerobic digesters (Cardinali-Rezende et al., 2009; Riviere et al., 2009; Ritari et al., 2012; Zakrzewski et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>For bacteria, Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes have been repeatedly identified as the main phyla in various anaerobic digesters (Klocke et al., 2007; Garcia et al., 2011; Jaenicke et al., 2011; Kampmann et al., 2012; St-Pierre and Wright, 2014; Lucas et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The presence of large proportions of unknown sequences at the genus level, as observed here, has also been reported in other amplicon sequencing studies (Zakrzewski et al., 2012; Lu et al., 2013; Li et al., 2014; Smith et al., 2014), as well as during construction of the a 16S rDNA clone library (Liu et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>It is clear that isolation and cultivation of uncultured microorganisms would provide deeper insights into their function in the AD process, as suggested previously (Narihiro and Sekiguchi, 2007; Curtis et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Manure versus mesophilic AD of manure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Manure can be used as the sole substrate during AD, but typically results in low biogas yields (Mata-Alvarez et al., 2000; Angelidaki and Ellegaard, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Co-digestion with more energy-rich materials can result in higher yields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the presence of manure can be a precondition for enabling AD of materials with a high C/N ratio and low buffering capacity, such as straw (Mata-Alvarez et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Manure contributes nitrogen, trace elements and buffering components, and thus creates more suitable conditions for the growth of microbes, including methanogens, in the AD process (Mata-Alvarez et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Possibly, effects by manure could also be caused by microbial inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>It is well known that the rumen has high cellulose-degrading efficiency and the bacteria involved in this may also be involved in degradation in the AD process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Methanogens active in the rumen may also contribute to methanogenesis in the biogas production process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>In our diversity index analysis of the archaeal and bacterial communities, no difference was observed between the manure and the digester operated with manure (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>However, community composition analysis revealed a clear difference between the digester and the manure for both archaea and bacteria (Figs 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>In the manure samples, Methanobrevibacter from the order Methanobacteriales was the most dominant archaeal genus (85.2% and 93.3%), showing similarity to the methanogenic community structure in the rumen of cows (Janssen and Kirs, 2008; Danielsson et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>However, when the manure was used as substrate for biogas production, the number of sequences affiliated to this hydrogenotrophic genus represented less than 3.2% and instead the Methanosarcina became dominant (&gt; 97%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>The cause of the decrease in relative abundance of Methanobrevibacter is not clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>The dominance of Methanosarcina is, however, in line with previous studies of manure-based digesters (Karakashev et al., 2005; Demirel and Scherer, 2008; Goberna et al., 2010; St-Pierre and Wright, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>High abundance of this methanogen has been suggested to be caused by its relatively high growth rate and ability to tolerate conditions inhibitory to other methanogens, such as presence of ammonia (De Vrieze et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>However, the digesters investigated in this study had low levels of ammonia, and similar to the manure (Risberg et al., 2013), thus this parameter is not the likely cause for the shift in the methanogenic community. Methanosarcina can also use the hydrogenotrophic pathway for methanogenesis, unlike the other acetotrophic methanogen Methanosaeta, and this might also enhance its competitive ability, even at low acetate levels as prevailing in the investigated digesters (De Vrieze et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Another possible explanation for the dominance of this methanogen is the once-per-day feeding regime, which has been reported before to select for Methanosarcina rather than Methanosaeta (Conklin et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the bacterial community identified Bacteroidetes (21.0–39.4%) and Firmicutes (45.9–74.1%) as the major phyla in both the manure samples and the digesters operating with manure (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>This confirms previous findings on bacterial populations in the rumen of cows (Kim et al., 2011; Danielsson et al., 2012), manure digesters (Kampmann et al., 2012; St-Pierre and Wright, 2014) and other biogas digesters (Krause et al., 2008; Schlüter et al., 2008; Lee et al., 2012; Sundberg et al., 2013; Ziganshin et al., 2013; Li et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>However, as for the archaeal population, statistical analysis revealed that the bacterial community in the digester was separated from the manure sample (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>This was most likely caused by the substantially higher amount (6.0–14.5%) of sequences related to the candidate phylum Cloacimonetes in the manure digesters than in the manure itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Representatives of this phylum seem not to be specific for manure as they have been detected also in digesters operating with other substrates (Cardinali-Rezende et al., 2009; Sundberg et al., 2013; Li et al., 2014) and in the rumen (Piao et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>In the present study, sequences belonging to the uncultured WWE1 contributed to the majority of the candidate phylum Cloacimonetes (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>This uncultured cluster was first discovered as a subdominant group (up to 10%) in an anaerobic sludge digester (Chouari et al., 2005), but later also in other anaerobic digesters (Riviere et al., 2009; Lucas et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>The genome of one species from this phylum, namely ‘Candidatus Cloacamonas acidaminovorans’, was recovered from a metagenomic study, which suggested it as a syntrophic bacterium capable of degrading propionate and amino acids (Pelletier et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>In a recent study, evidence emerged suggesting that this group of bacteria also is involved in the AD of cellulose, through an extracellular cellulose hydrolysis process and/or in the fermentation of organic substrates originating from cellulose (Limam et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Variation in the bacterial community between the manure and the digester was also seen at different taxonomic levels, with the most pronounced difference within the phylum Firmicutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Here, a significantly higher relative abundance of sequences belonging to the order of Lactobacillales (from class Bacilli) was observed in the manure samples than in the manure digester. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>The relative abundance of Clostridia was rather similar in all digesters, which resulted in a higher Clostridia/Bacilli ratio in the manure digester than in the manure itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>A higher level of Clostridia in relation to Bacilli was also seen in a previous study analysing three different manure digesters (St-Pierre and Wright, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The cause of the increase in Clostridia/Bacilli ratio in the digesters relative to the manure is not clear, but one possible explanation is that the availability of easily fermentable sugar is comparably lower in the anaerobic digester (Walter et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Microbial response caused by straw </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>As described in our previous paper, adding straw (steam-exploded or non-pretreated) as a co-substrate during the digestion of manure did not impact on the overall process stability or performance (gas yield and degree of degradation, Risberg et al., 2013); however, a response was obtained for the microbial community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>For archaea, no difference was observed for the major population during operation at 37°C with manure as the sole substrate or with a mixture of manure and straw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Addition of straw had a more pronounced effect on the bacterial community, for example reflected in a significant decrease in bacterial species richness compared with digestion of manure alone (Table 1 and Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>A similar decrease in species richness was observed in a study by Li and colleagues (2014), where addition of straw resulted in a decrease in the number of observed species and in the Shannon index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>This result possibly reflects selection and enrichment of specialists involved in degradation of the straw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>At the phylum level, the addition of straw resulted in an increase in the relative abundance of Bacteroidetes compared with the digesters processing manure alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>However, sequences affiliated with Firmicutes were at similar abundance in all digesters operated at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>This result was somewhat surprising, as Firmicutes contains many isolated cellulose degraders (Lynd et al., 2002), and several studies in biogas digesters have suggested representatives of this phylum, particularly belonging to the order Clostridiales, to be key players for degradation of cellulose (Krause et al., 2008; Hanreich et al., 2013; Li et al., 2013; Lu et al., 2013; Lebuhn et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>However, in the present study, a higher abundance of Sedimentibacter was observed in the digesters operating with straw, in similarity to a study by Li and colleagues (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>However, this is not necessarily an expected change, as the two species isolated and characterized from this genus so far are not capable of utilizing carbohydrates (Breitenstein et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>In line with our results, a recent metagenomic study also found an increase in the level of Bacteroidetes in anaerobic batch fermentation of straw and hay (Hanreich et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>In this study, the number of expressed sugar transporters increased simultaneously with the level of Bacteroidetes, which was assumed to be responsible for degradation of polysaccharides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Representatives of the phylum Bacteroidetes have been shown to have the capacity to degrade a wide variety of plant polysaccharides, including cellulose (Robert et al., 2007; Hatamoto et al., 2014; Naas et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>However, recent studies show that cellulose conversion in Bacteroidetes needs further investigation (Naas et al., 2014), and thus the role of this phylum during straw degradation remains somewhat unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>The straw in this study was pretreated by steam explosion (Risberg et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>This treatment disrupts the intricate structure of lignocellulose and releases more simple carbohydrates, possibly explaining the increased level of Bacteroidetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Impact of temperature </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>For archaeal and bacterial communities, the species richness decreased in line with the increase in process temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Similarly, Sundberg and co-workers (2013) observed that among 21 full-scale biogas digesters, thermophilic co-digestion plants had lower microbial richness than mesophilic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>A similar trend was also observed in a methanogenic digester processing organic household waste at 37°C and at 55°C, where a higher species richness was found for both the archaeal and bacterial community at the mesophilic temperature (Levén et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the species richness of the archaea was lowest at 44°C, suggesting that an increase in temperature with only a few degrees from 37°C has an impact on the diversity of this community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>This result was in line with a previous study where a significant decrease in species richness of methanogens was observed after an increase in operational temperature from 37°C to 42°C in lab-scale digesters processing municipal solid waste supplemented with albumin (Westerholm M., Isaksson S., Müller B., and Schnürer A., unpublished). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is apparent that temperature is a strong regulating factor for the microbial community in the biogas process, and an increase in temperature restricts the number of species present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Notably, the previously published operating data for these digesters show that this decrease in richness of both bacteria and archaea and in the evenness of bacteria did not affect the overall performance of the digesters (Risberg et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in the study by Westerholm et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(unpublished), the increase in temperature to 42°C even resulted in increased methane yields compared with operation at 37°C, in spite of a decreased species richness of methanogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>For the archaeal community, after an increase in operating temperature from 37°C to 52°C, there was an increase in the relative abundance of the genera Methanobacterium and Methanoculleus, from the order Methanobacteriales and Methanomicrobiales respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Similar results have been reported for a laboratory-scale biogas digester fed with only cattle manure during a temperature shift from 39°C to 55°C, where a decrease in relative abundance of Methanosarcina from 89% to 54% was accompanied by an increase of Methanoculleus spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(Ziganshin et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a sharp increase in the relative abundance of hydrogenotrophic methanogens Methanobacterium, Methanoculleus and Methanothermobacter has been observed in biogas digesters co-digesting cattle excreta and olive mill wastes during a temperature shift from 37°C to 55°C, likely induced by an increase in H2 partial pressure (Goberna et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>For the bacterial community, the relative abundance of Firmicutes increased during the transition to the thermophilic temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>This increase was mainly caused by a higher abundance of sequences related to the uncultured order MBA08 within the class Clostridia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this order was represented by a single uncultured genus, which partially explained the decreased species richness and evenness of the bacterial community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>The MBA08 cluster was first discovered in a thermophilic laboratory-scale digester processing municipal solid waste (Tang et al., 2004) and also later in a thermophilic garbage digester (Cheon et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Thus, it seems reasonable to assume that this cluster contains thermophilic Clostridia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>In our previous study using the same anaerobic digesters and using a functional gene approach for community analysis, we also found that the major response to the temperature rise was an increase in the relative abundance of organisms belonging to the class Clostridia (Sun et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>In contrast to Firmicutes, the relative abundance of Bacteroidetes decreased with the increase in operating temperature in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>This trend was also seen in our previous study (Sun et al., 2013) and in the study by Ziganshin and colleagues (2013), who observed a decrease in sequences related to this phylum during a temperature shift from 38°C to 55°C in digesters processing cattle manure and agricultural waste. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Moreover, introduction of cellulose into a thermophilic sludge digester resulted in increased abundance of Firmicutes and decreased abundance of Bacteroidetes (Lu et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>In addition, a high ratio of Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes has been observed in different digesters operated at high temperature, e.g. in three hydrolytic/acidogenic horizontal tubular digesters processing dried hay and straw, operating at 38°C, 45°C and 55°C (Lebuhn et al., 2014), in two digesters treating organic household waste at 37°C and 55°C (Levén et al., 2007), and in a thermophilic reactor operating with poultry manure (Smith et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Temperature clearly has a strong effect on the bacterial community in a biogas digester, and the high relative abundance of Clostridia suggested a competitive advantage for this class. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Comparing sequencing results from the manure used as substrate and the digesters operated under various conditions revealed that the microbial communities in the digesters were likely shaped by the operating conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>For archaea, the hydrogenotrophic methanogens present in the manure were outcompeted in the digester environment by Methanosarcina, which can utilize both hydrogen and acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>For bacteria, the relative abundance of Bacilli was higher in manure, while an uncultured cluster WWE1 affiliated to the phylum Cloacimonetes was more abundant in the digester operated with manure alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>After including straw for co-digestion with manure, no major changes were observed for the archaeal community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>However, for bacteria, the abundance of Bacteroidia increased, suggesting importance of this group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Both the archaeal and bacterial communities responded to increased operating temperatures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>For archaea, although Methanosarcina was the most dominant genus in all digester samples, Methanoculleus and Methanobacterium were considerably more abundant at the higher temperatures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>For bacteria, a decrease in the relative abundance of Bacteroidia was accompanied by an increase in Clostridia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>A considerable fraction of bacterial reads could not be allocated to genus level, meaning that more efforts to isolate and characterize unknown dominant microbes in anaerobic digesters are needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Such efforts could provide deeper insights into microbial function in the AD process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Experimental procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Anaerobic digesters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Samples for microbial community structure analysis were taken from five laboratory-scale semi-continuous stirred tank reactors (Dolly, Belach Bioteknik, Stockholm, Sweden) run under different conditions (Risberg et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>In addition to the digester samples, two samples were taken from the manure used as substrate for the digesters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>A detailed description of the digesters, the chemical composition of the manure and the process performance can be found in Risberg and colleagues (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>In this study, the phase referred to as ‘second experimental period’ was used for the microbial analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>In brief, five set-ups of digesters (designated RM, RTcSS, R37SS, R44SS and R52SS) were investigated in this study; all but RM operated in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>All digesters had the same hydraulic retention time (HRT) of 25 days, and the organic loading rate was maintained at around 2.8 g VS l−l day−l. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>The inoculum used for starting up the AD process (RTcSS and R37SS) originated from the digester RLcSS in Risberg and colleagues (2013), which operated at similar conditions with another batch of manure for 83 days (full load). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>All the digesters were fed 6 days a week and had stable and similar performance: the pH was 7.5–8.1, the ammonium-nitrogen level was 1.5–2.0 g kg−1 wet weight (1.2 g kg−1 wet weight for manure itself), no accumulation of acids occurred during the whole operating period, and the specific methane yield was 0.13–0.17 l CH4 kg−1 VS (Risberg et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Digester RM operated with cow manure as the sole substrate at 37°C, while two parallel digesters RTcSS operated with cow manure supplemented with steam-exploded straw (78/22% on a VS basis) at 37°C during the whole operating period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Another two parallel digesters R37SS were fed with the same substrate and initially operated under the same conditions as RTcSS at 37°C, but both digesters were then subjected to a temperature rise to 44°C and further to 52°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>After around three HRTs of operation at the corresponding temperature (i.e. 44°C and 52°C), the digesters were named R44SS and R52SS respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>The total operating time of the digesters was 402 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>For digesters RTcSS and R37SS, samples were withdrawn on days 9, 38, 80 and 99 of operation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>The starting point for this experiment was set to the day when the digesters had been in operation for three HRTs at full load. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>For digesters R44SS and R52SS, samples were taken after operation at the corresponding temperature (44°C and 52°C, respectively) for around three HRTs, i.e. on days 224 and 402. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>For digester RM, samples were taken on days 42, 85 and 148. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>A 20 ml sample was withdrawn from each digester and stored at −20°C until analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Total genomic DNA was prepared in triplicate using the FastDNA Spin Kit for Soil (MP Biomedicals, Santa Ana, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Aliquots of 200 μl digester sludge were used for extraction following the manufacturer’s protocol, and 60 μl water was used in the final elution of DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of extracted DNA were measured using the Quant-iT dsDNA BR Assay Kit (Invitrogen, Life Technologies Europe, Stockholm, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>454-pyrosequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Primers targeting the bacterial 16S rRNA gene integrated with 454 Life Sciences adaptors 8F (5′-CCT ATC CCC TGT GTG CCT TGG CAG TCT CAG CAA CAG CTA GAG TTT GAT CCT GG-3′) and 515R (5′-CCA TCT CAT CCC TGC GTG TCT CCG ACT CAG NNN NNN NNT TAC CGC GGC TGC T-3′) were used for amplification from genomic DNA by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (Stanley et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>For archaea, the primers 340F (5′-CCT ATC CCC TGT GTG CCT TGG CAG TCT CAG CAA AAG CTC CCT AYG GGG YGC ASC AG-3′) and 1 000R (5′-CCA TCT CAT CCC TGC GTG TCT CCG ACT CAG NNN NNN NNG GCC ATG CAC YWC YTC TC-3′) were used for amplification (Gantner et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>For samples from RM, RTcSS and R37SS, the PCR amplification was performed with iProof High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>For samples R44SS and R52SS, PCR amplification was conducted using Maxima Hot Start PCR Master Mix (Fermentas, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Hudson, NH, USA) for bacteria and Bio-Rad iQ™ Supermix (Bio-Rad) for archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Each PCR reaction contained 12.5 μl of corresponding reaction mix, 0.5 μM of each primer, 20 ng of DNA template and 9.5 μl of sterile water (25 μl final volume). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>The PCR programmes were as follows: initial denaturation at 98°C for 3 min, 30 cycles (35 cycles for archaea) of denaturation at 98°C for 10 s, annealing at 55°C (57°C for archaea) for 45 s and elongation at 72°C for 45 s, followed by a final extension step of 7 min at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>The size and purity of amplicons were checked by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Short, non-specific amplification products were removed with AMP beads (AMPure XP, Beckman Coulter Genomics, Danvers, MA, USA) using the manufacturer’s protocol but with a modified bead to DNA volume ratio of 0.7:1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of purified products were measured using the Quant-iT dsDNA BR Assay Kit (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>All PCR products were pooled in equal molar amounts and further checked on 2% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>The mixed pool of PCR products from manure samples, RM, RTcSS and R37SS, was sequenced at Norwegian Sequencing Centre in Oslo, while the one from R44SS and R52SS was sequenced at the Swedish Institute for Infectious Disease Control in Solna, using the Roche/454 GS Titanium technology platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Sequences have been deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive under the accession number SRP049689. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>16S rRNA gene sequence analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>The 16S rRNA gene sequences were processed using the qiime pipeline (Caporaso et al., 2010a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>In summary, the dataset was first quality trimmed by removing sequences that were less than 400 or more than 600 bp in length, contained ambiguous bases, had a mean quality score &lt; 25, contained a homopolymer run exceeding 6 bp, or did not contain a primer or barcode sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>The usearch quality filter was used to remove chimera sequences (Edgar, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>The OTUs were determined using uclust at a threshold of 97% (Edgar, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Representative sequences were selected as the most abundant sequence in each OTU and further aligned against the Greengenes core set (gg_13_8) using pynast software (Caporaso et al., 2010b; McDonald et al., 2012) and a minimum identity of 75%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Taxonomy was assigned to each OTU using the Ribosomal Database Project classifier (Wang et al., 2007) with a minimum confidence threshold of 80%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>The alignment was filtered to remove gaps and hypervariable regions using a Lane mask, and a maximum-likelihood tree was constructed from the filtered alignment using FastTree (Price et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>The OTU tables were rarefied (according to the sample containing the smallest set of sequences) to equalize sampling depth and avoid heterogeneity (i.e. avoid bias from unequal sampling effort). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>From the OTU tables and phylogenetic trees, an unweighted UniFrac distance matrix was constructed and further visualized with PCoA (Lozupone and Knight, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Rarefaction curve, observed species, chao1 (Hill et al., 2003), Shannon (Spellerberg and Fedor, 2003) and Simpson indices (Simpson, 1949) were computed by qiime alpha diversity analysis script (Caporaso et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Live Heldal Hagen for assistance with the Bioinformatics. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>AngelidakiIEllegaardLCodigestion of manure and organic wastes in centralized biogas plantsAppl Biochem Biotechnol20031099510512794286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>AngelidakiIKarakashevDBatstoneDJPluggeCMStephenWRStamsAJMAmyCRChapter sixteen – biomethanation and its potentialMethods in Enzymology2011New YorkAcademic Press327351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>AppelsLLauwersJDegrèveJHelsenLLievensBWillemsKAnaerobic digestion in global bio-energy production: potential and research challengesRenew Sust Energ Rev20111542954301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>BreitensteinAWiegelJHaertigCWeissNAndreesenJRLechnerUReclassification of Clostridium hydroxybenzoicum as Sedimentibacter hydroxybenzoicus gen. nov., comb. nov., and description of Sedimentibacter saalensis sp. novInt J Syst Evol Microbiol20025280180712054241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>CallawayTRDowdSEEdringtonTSAndersonRCKruegerNBauerNEvaluation of bacterial diversity in the rumen and feces of cattle fed different levels of dried distillers grains plus solubles using bacterial tag-encoded FLX amplicon pyrosequencingJ Anim Sci2010883977398320729286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>CaporasoJGKuczynskiJStombaughJBittingerKBushmanFDCostelloEKQIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing dataNat Meth2010a7335336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>CaporasoJGBittingerKBushmanFDDeSantisTZAndersenGLKnightRPyNAST: a flexible tool for aligning sequences to a template alignmentBioinformatics2010b2626626719914921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Cardinali-RezendeJDebarryRColturatoLDBCarneiroEChartone-SouzaENascimentoAAMolecular identification and dynamics of microbial communities in reactor treating organic household wasteAppl Microbiol Biotechnol20098477778919551378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>CheonJHongFHidakaTKoshikawaHTsunoHMicrobial population dynamics in a thermophilic methane digester fed with garbageWater Sci Technol20075517518217564383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>ChouariRLe PaslierDDaugaCDaegelenPWeissenbachJSghirANovel major bacterial candidate division within a municipal anaerobic sludge digesterAppl Environ Microbiol2005712145215315812049 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>ConklinAStenselHDFergusonJGrowth kinetics and competition between methanosarcina and methanosaeta in mesophilic anaerobic digestionWater Environ Res20067848649616752610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>CurtisTDaranJ-MPronkJTFreyJJanssonJKRobbins-PiankaACrystal ball – 2013Microb Biotechnol20136316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>DanielssonRSchnürerAArthursonVBertilssonJMethanogenic population and CH4 production in Swedish dairy cows fed different levels of forageAppl Environ Microbiol2012786172617922752163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>De VriezeJHennebelTBoonNVerstraeteWMethanosarcina: the rediscovered methanogen for heavy duty biomethanationBioresour Technol20121121922418081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>DemirelBSchererPThe roles of acetotrophic and hydrogenotrophic methanogens during anaerobic conversion of biomass to methane: a reviewRev Environ Sci Biotechnol20087173190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>DowdSCallawayTWolcottRSunYMcKeehanTHagevoortREdringtonTEvaluation of the bacterial diversity in the feces of cattle using 16S rDNA bacterial tag-encoded FLX amplicon pyrosequencing (bTEFAP)BMC Microbiol20088125doi: 10.1186/1471-2180-8-12518652685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>EdgarRCSearch and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLASTBioinformatics2010262460246120709691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>EstevezMMLinjordetRMorkenJEffects of steam explosion and co-digestion in the methane production from Salix by mesophilic batch assaysBioresour Technol201210474975622130086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>FrigonJ-CGuiotSRBiomethane production from starch and lignocellulosic crops: a comparative reviewBiofuels, Bioprod Biorefin20104447458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>GalbeMZacchiGPretreatment: the key to efficient utilization of lignocellulosic materialsBiomass Bioenerg2012467078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>GantnerSAnderssonAFAlonso-SáezLBertilssonSNovel primers for 16S rRNA-based archaeal community analyses in environmental samplesJ Microbiol Methods201184121820940022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>GarciaSLJangidKWhitmanWBDasKCTransition of microbial communities during the adaption to anaerobic digestion of carrot wasteBioresour Technol20111027249725621620691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>GobernaMGadermaierMGarcíaCWettBInsamHAdaptation of methanogenic communities to the cofermentation of cattle excreta and olive mill wastes at 37°C and 55°CAppl Environ Microbiol2010766564657120675446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>HanreichASchimpfUZakrzewskiMSchlüterABenndorfDHeyerRMetagenome and metaproteome analyses of microbial communities in mesophilic biogas-producing anaerobic batch fermentations indicate concerted plant carbohydrate degradationSyst Appl Microbiol20133633033823694815 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>HatamotoMKaneshigeMNakamuraAYamaguchiTBacteroides luti sp. nov., an anaerobic, cellulolytic and xylanolytic bacterium isolated from methanogenic sludgeInt J Syst Evol Microbiol2014641770177424556634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>HendriksATWMZeemanGPretreatments to enhance the digestibility of lignocellulosic biomassBioresour Technol2009100101818599291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>HillTCJWalshKAHarrisJAMoffettBFUsing ecological diversity measures with bacterial communitiesFEMS Microbiol Ecol20034311119719691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>JaenickeSAnderCBekelTBisdorfRDrögeMGartemannK-HComparative and joint analysis of two metagenomic datasets from a biogas fermenter obtained by 454-PyrosequencingPLoS ONE20116e1451921297863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>JanssenPHKirsMStructure of the archaeal community of the rumenAppl Environ Microbiol2008743619362518424540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>KampmannKRateringSKramerISchmidtMZerrWSchnellSUnexpected stability of Bacteroidetes and Firmicutes communities in laboratory biogas reactors fed with different defined substratesAppl Environ Microbiol2012782106211922247168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>KarakashevDBatstoneDJAngelidakiIInfluence of environmental conditions on methanogenic compositions in anaerobic biogas reactorsAppl Environ Microbiol20057133133815640206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>KimMMorrisonMYuZStatus of the phylogenetic diversity census of ruminal microbiomesFEMS Microbiol Ecol201176496321223325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>KlockeMMähnertPMundtKSouidiKLinkeBMicrobial community analysis of a biogas-producing completely stirred tank reactor fed continuously with fodder beet silage as mono-substrateSyst Appl Microbiol20073013915116697135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>KlockeMNettmannEBergmannIMundtKSouidiKMummeJLinkeBCharacterization of the methanogenic Archaea within two-phase biogas reactor systems operated with plant biomassSyst Appl Microbiol20083119020518501543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>KrauseLDiazNNEdwardsRAGartemannK-HKrömekeHNeuwegerHTaxonomic composition and gene content of a methane-producing microbial community isolated from a biogas reactorJ Biotechnol20081369110118611419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>LebuhnMHanreichAKlockeMSchluterABauerCPerezCMTowards molecular biomarkers for biogas production from lignocellulose-rich substratesAnaerobe201429102124785351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>LeeSHKangHJLeeYHLeeTJHanKChoiYParkHDMonitoring bacterial community structure and variability in time scale in full-scale anaerobic digestersJ Environ Monit2012141893190522426622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>LehtomäkiAHuttunenSRintalaJALaboratory investigations on co-digestion of energy crops and crop residues with cow manure for methane production: effect of crop to manure ratioResour Conserv Recy200751591609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>LeschineSBCellulose degradation in anaerobic environmentsAnnu Rev Microbiol1995493994268561466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>LevénLErikssonARBSchnürerAEffect of process temperature on bacterial and archaeal communities in two methanogenic bioreactors treating organic household wasteFEMS Microbiol Ecol20075968369317381521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>LiAChuYWangXRenLYuJLiuXA pyrosequencing-based metagenomic study of methane-producing microbial community in solid-state biogas reactorBiotechnol for Biofuels201363doi: 10.1186/1754-6834-6-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>LiJRuiJPeiZSunXZhangSYanZStraw- and slurry-associated prokaryotic communities differ during co-fermentation of straw and swine manureAppl Microbiol Biotechnol2014984771478024633443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>LimamRDChouariRMazéasLWuT-DLiTGrossin-DebattistaJMembers of the uncultured bacterial candidate division WWE1 are implicated in anaerobic digestion of celluloseMicrobiologyOpen2014315716724497501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>LiuFHWangSBZhangJSZhangJYanXZhouHKThe structure of the bacterial and archaeal community in a biogas digester as revealed by denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis and 16S rDNA sequencing analysisJ Appl Microbiol200910695296619187154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>LozuponeCKnightRUniFrac: a new phylogenetic method for comparing microbial communitiesAppl Environ Microbiol2005718228823516332807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>LuXRaoSShenZLeePKHSubstrate induced emergence of different active bacterial and archaeal assemblages during biomethane productionBioresour Technol201314851752424080290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>LucasRKuchenbuchAFetzerIHarmsHKleinsteuberSLong-term monitoring reveals stable and remarkably similar microbial communities in parallel full-scale biogas reactors digesting energy cropsFEMS Microbiol Ecol201591doi: 10.1093/femsec/fiv004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>LyndLRWeimerPJvan ZylWHPretoriusISMicrobial cellulose utilization: fundamentals and biotechnologyMicrobiol Mol Biol Rev20026650657712209002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>McDonaldDPriceMNGoodrichJNawrockiEPDeSantisTZProbstAAn improved Greengenes taxonomy with explicit ranks for ecological and evolutionary analyses of bacteria and archaeaISME J2012661061822134646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Mata-AlvarezJMacéSLlabrésPAnaerobic digestion of organic solid wastes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>An overview of research achievements and perspectivesBioresour Technol200074316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Mata-AlvarezJDostaJRomero-GüizaMSFonollXPecesMAstalsSA critical review on anaerobic co-digestion achievements between 2010 and 2013Renew Sust Energ Rev201436412427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>NaasAEMackenzieAKMravecJSchuckelJWillatsWGEijsinkVGPopePBDo rumen Bacteroidetes utilize an alternative mechanism for cellulose degradation?MBio20145e1401e1414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>NarihiroTSekiguchiYMicrobial communities in anaerobic digestion processes for waste and wastewater treatment: a microbiological updateCurr Opin Biotechnol20071827327817462878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>NkoaRAgricultural benefits and environmental risks of soil fertilization with anaerobic digestates: a reviewAgron Sustain Dev201434473492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>NoikeTEndoGChangJ-EYaguchiJ-IMatsumotoJ-ICharacteristics of carbohydrate degradation and the rate-limiting step in anaerobic digestionBiotechnol Bioeng1985271482148918553595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>ParawiraWEnzyme research and applications in biotechnological intensification of biogas productionCrit Rev Biotechnol20123217218621851320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>PelletierEKreimeyerABocsSRouyZGyapayGChouariR‘Candidatus cloacamonas acidaminovorans’: genome sequence reconstruction provides a first glimpse of a new bacterial divisionJ Bacteriol20081902572257918245282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>PengXBörnerRANgesIALiuJImpact of bioaugmentation on biochemical methane potential for wheat straw with addition of Clostridium cellulolyticumBioresour Technol201415256757124355075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>PiaoHLachmanMMalfattiSSczyrbaAKnierimBAuerMTemporal dynamics of fibrolytic and methanogenic rumen microorganisms during in situ incubation of switchgrass determined by 16S rRNA gene profilingFront Microbiol20145doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>PriceMNDehalPSArkinAPFastTree 2 – approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignmentsPLoS ONE20105e949020224823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Ransom-JonesEJonesDMcCarthyAMcDonaldJThe fibrobacteres: an important phylum of cellulose-degrading bacteriaMicrob Ecol20126326728122213055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>RisbergKSunLLevénLHornSJSchnürerABiogas production from wheat straw and manure – impact of pretreatment and process operating parametersBioresour Technol201314923223724121239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>RitariJKoskinenKHultmanJKurolaJKymäläinenMRomantschukMMolecular analysis of meso- and thermophilic microbiota associated with anaerobic biowaste degradationBMC Microbiol20121211422221383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>RiviereDDesvignesVPelletierEChaussonnerieSGuermaziSWeissenbachJTowards the definition of a core of microorganisms involved in anaerobic digestion of sludgeISME J2009370071419242531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>RobertCChassardCLawsonPABernalier-DonadilleABacteroides cellulosilyticus sp. nov., a cellulolytic bacterium from the human gut microbial communityInt J Syst Evol Microbiol2007571516152017625186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>SchlüterABekelTDiazNNDondrupMEichenlaubRGartemannK-HThe metagenome of a biogas-producing microbial community of a production-scale biogas plant fermenter analysed by the 454-pyrosequencing technologyJ Biotechnol2008136779018597880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>SimpsonEHMeasurement of diversityNature1949163688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>SmithASharmaDLappin-ScottHBurtonSHuberDMicrobial community structure of a pilot-scale thermophilic anaerobic digester treating poultry litterAppl Microbiol Biotechnol2014982321233423989973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>SpellerbergIFFedorPJA tribute to Claude Shannon (1916–2001) and a plea for more rigorous use of species richness, species diversity and the ‘Shannon–Wiener’ IndexGlobal Ecol Biogeogr200312177179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>St-PierreBWrightA-DComparative metagenomic analysis of bacterial populations in three full-scale mesophilic anaerobic manure digestersAppl Microbiol Biotechnol2014982709271724085391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>StanleyDGeierMSHughesRJDenmanSEMooreRJHighly variable microbiota development in the chicken gastrointestinal tractPLoS ONE20138e8429024391931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>SunLMüllerBSchnürerABiogas production from wheat straw: community structure of cellulose-degrading bacteriaEnergy Sustain Soc2013315doi: 10.1186/2192-0567-3-15 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>SundbergCAl-SoudWALarssonMAlmEYektaSSSvenssonBH454 pyrosequencing analyses of bacterial and archaeal richness in 21 full-scale biogas digestersFEMS Microbiol Ecol20138561262623678985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>TangYShigematsuTIkbalMorimuraSKidaKThe effects of micro-aeration on the phylogenetic diversity of microorganisms in a thermophilic anaerobic municipal solid-waste digesterWater Res2004382537255015159157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>TsavkelovaEANetrusovAIBiogas production from cellulose-containing substrates: a reviewAppl Biochem Microbiol201248421433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>VanwonterghemIJensenPDHoDPBatstoneDJTysonGWLinking microbial community structure, interactions and function in anaerobic digesters using new molecular techniquesCurr Opin Biotechnol201427556424863897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>WalterJBrittonRARoosSHost-microbial symbiosis in the vertebrate gastrointestinal tract and the Lactobacillus reuteri paradigmPNAS20111084645465220615995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>WangGGavalaHNSkiadasIVAhringBKWet explosion of wheat straw and codigestion with swine manure: effect on the methane productivityWaste Manage20092928302835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>WangQGarrityGMTiedjeJMColeJRNaïve bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomyAppl Environ Microbiol2007735261526717586664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>WeilandPBiogas production: current state and perspectivesAppl Microbiol Biotechnol20108584986019777226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>WernerJJKnightsDGarciaMLScalfoneNBSmithSYarasheskiKBacterial community structures are unique and resilient in full-scale bioenergy systemsProc Natl Acad Sci USA20111084158416321368115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>YangYYuKXiaYLauFKTangDWFungWMetagenomic analysis of sludge from full-scale anaerobic digesters operated in municipal wastewater treatment plantsAppl Microbiol Biotechnol2014985709571824633414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>ZakrzewskiMGoesmannAJaenickeSJünemannSEikmeyerFSzczepanowskiRProfiling of the metabolically active community from a production-scale biogas plant by means of high-throughput metatranscriptome sequencingJ Biotechnol201215824825822342600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>ZiganshinAMLiebetrauJProterJKleinsteuberSMicrobial community structure and dynamics during anaerobic digestion of various agricultural waste materialsAppl Microbiol Biotechnol2013975161517423624683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b85"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>ZiganshinaEEBagmanovaARKhilyasIVZiganshinAMAssessment of a biogas-generating microbial community in a pilot-scale anaerobic reactorJ Biosci Bioeng201411773073624418257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b86"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>ZinderSHKochMNon-acetoclastic methanogenesis from acetate: acetate oxidation by a thermophilic syntrophic cocultureArch Microbiol1984138263272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd1"><p><bold>Fig. S1.</bold> Rarefaction analysis of bacteria for manure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S2</xref> correspond to duplicate samples, in purple) and for laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM, in blue); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (R<sup>Tc</sup>SS, in green); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R<sup>37</sup>SS, in green; R<sup>44</sup>SS, in yellow; and R<sup>52</sup>SS, in red), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters. The operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were determined at the sequence-similarity threshold of 97%.</p><p><bold>Fig. S2.</bold> Relative abundance of bacterial 16S rRNA gene at the genus level in manure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S2</xref> correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (R<sup>Tc</sup>SS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R<sup>37</sup>SS, R<sup>44</sup>SS and R<sup>52</sup>SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters.</p><p><bold>Fig. S3.</bold> Relative abundance of bacterial 16S rRNA gene at the phylum level in manure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S2</xref> correspond to duplicate samples) and in laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (R<sup>Tc</sup>SS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R<sup>37</sup>SS, R<sup>44</sup>SS and R<sup>52</sup>SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters.</p><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Summary of barcode sequences used for manure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">S2</xref> correspond to duplicate samples) and for laboratory-scale digesters processing: (1) manure as sole substrate (RM); (2) stream-exploded straw and manure, operating constantly at 37°C (R<sup>Tc</sup>SS); and (3) steam-exploded straw and manure, operating temperatures 37°C, 44°C and 52°C (R<sup>37</sup>SS, R<sup>44</sup>SS and R<sup>52</sup>SS), where R1 and R2 represent parallel digesters.</p><media mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="mbt20008-0815-sd1.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e5496" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></back></article>
