<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Geriatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2318</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4743178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-016-0211-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Encountering aged care: a mixed methods investigation of medical students’ clinical placement experiences </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Annear</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><address><email>michael.annear@utas.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>Emma</given-names></name><address><email>emma.lea@utas.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name><address><email>amanda.lo@utas.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><address><email>laura.tierney@utas.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name><address><email>andrew.robinson@utas.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre, Faculty of Health, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 143, Hobart, TAS 7001 Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>School of Medicine, Faculty of Health, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 34, Hobart, TAS 7001 Australia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Health, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 135, Hobart, TAS 7001 Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>38</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Annear et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Residential aged care is an increasingly important health setting due to population ageing and the increase in age-related conditions, such as dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, medical education has limited engagement with this fast-growing sector and undergraduate training remains primarily focussed on acute presentations in hospital settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Additionally, concerns have been raised about the adequacy of dementia-related content in undergraduate medical curricula, while research has found mixed attitudes among students towards the care of older people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This study explores how medical students engage with the learning experiences accessible in clinical placements in residential aged care facilities (RACFs), particularly exposure to multiple comorbidity, cognitive impairment, and palliative care. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Fifth-year medical students (N = 61) completed five-day clinical placements at two Australian aged care facilities in 2013 and 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The placements were supported by an iterative yet structured program and academic teaching staff to ensure appropriate educational experiences and oversight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Mixed methods data were collected before and after the clinical placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Quantitative data included surveys of dementia knowledge and questions about attitudes to the aged care sector and working with older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Qualitative data were collected from focus group discussions concerning medical student expectations, learning opportunities, and challenges to engagement. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Pre-placement surveys identified good dementia knowledge, but poor attitudes towards aged care and older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Negative placement experiences were associated with a struggle to discern case complexity and a perception of an aged care placement as an opportunity cost associated with reduced hospital training time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Irrespective of negative sentiment, post-placement survey data showed significant improvements in attitudes to working with older people and dementia knowledge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Positive student experiences were explained by in-depth engagement with clinically challenging cases and opportunities to practice independent clinical decision making and contribute to resident care. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Aged care placements can improve medical student attitudes to working with older people and dementia knowledge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Clinical placements in RACFs challenge students to become more resourceful and independent in their clinical assessment and decision-making with vulnerable older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This suggests that aged care facilities offer considerable opportunity to enhance undergraduate medical education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, more work is required to engender cultural change across medical curricula to embed issues around ageing, multiple comorbidity, and dementia. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Medical students</kwd><kwd>Aged care facilities</kwd><kwd>Clinical placement</kwd><kwd>Older adults</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The medical profession has been challenged to engage more effectively with older adults [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Echoing global trends, the proportion of Australia’s population aged 65 and older is predicted to increase from 13 % in 2007 to 23 % in 2061 [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This cohort makes up the highest proportion of those seeking medical services – comprising 28 % of general practice visits in 2010 [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The challenge for the medical profession is to inculcate undergraduate interest in aged care in the context of an increasing prevalence of older people suffering chronic illness and multiple comorbidities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>While medical professionals from most specialities will encounter older patients, shortcomings have been noted in undergraduate curricula worldwide with regard to content about older-adult health [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Evidence suggests that management of acute illness associated with hospitalisation dominate medical curricula [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>For example, a United Kingdom survey identified a lack of teaching time in medical undergraduate curricula related to ageing, where less than two weeks of a five-year degree addressed health care for older people [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Across Australia, only 0.5 % of medical students’ clinical placement hours are undertaken in residential aged care facilities (RACFs – also referred to as nursing homes), compared to 78 % of clinical placement time in hospitals [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>RACFs in Australia provide a mix of high and low care as well as community outreach services for older people with cognitive and physical impairments (often multiple comorbidities) who require specialised care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These facilities are administered by private and not-for-profit organisations, with government funding support, to meet the needs of individuals who have been assessed as requiring institutional care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Limited medical student engagement with chronically unwell older adults may be exacerbated by a lack of interface between acute care and RACFs [10] and the absence of an established medical presence in these settings [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Concerns have also been raised about the adequacy of dementia-related content in undergraduate medical curricula [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In the context of an increasing prevalence of dementia associated with population ageing [13], educationalists from Australia and the United Kingdom have recommended expanding opportunities for experiential learning and skill development regarding dementia [12, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Current curricular deficiencies are likely to have a negative impact on students’ knowledge of and attitudes towards geriatric medicine [15, 16] and their capacity to effectively engage with cognitively impaired older adults [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Compounding curricular shortcomings are the mixed attitudes held by medical students towards care of older people [18–22], including what Higashi et al. [19] describe as persistent and implicitly negative attitudes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Persistent negative student attitudes towards aged care and older adults may be due to an educational culture that reinforces negative stereotypes about older adults [18], communication challenges that limit reciprocal and effective patient-centred relations [23], social distance between learners and RACF residents that reduces empathy [24], low levels of health literacy and compliance [24], or stark differences from the hospital training environment [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Despite prevailing negative sentiment, evidence suggests that RACFs provide an ideal setting for medical training and exposure to frail older people with complex health problems, including dementia [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In Australia, for example, 52 % of permanent RACF residents had a recorded diagnosis of dementia in 2011 [28], coexisting with an average of six long-term comorbidities [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>As the majority of aged care is provided in the community rather than hospitals [30], RACFs are a particularly appropriate setting for facilitating medical student engagement with aged care and frail older adults, many of whom have dementia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>There are a small number of published reports of undergraduate medical student RACF clinical placements in Australia and the United States [31–33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Clinical placements refer to one-off and embedded learning experiences for undergraduate students within particular healthcare settings for the purposes of increasing understanding about and exposure to a specialised sector (i.e. aged care, primary care, ambulance). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Two Australian studies have previously reported on programs that include medical students in inter-professional clinical placements at RACFs in Western Australia and Tasmania [32, 33], while a North American study evaluated mandatory geriatrics clerkships for third-year medical students [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These studies were limited, however, by small samples and a lack of explanatory qualitative data derived from medical students. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The current study explores first-hand medical student experiences of clinical aged care placements in Australia to understand how undergraduates engage with the available learning opportunities in a fast-growing, though largely unfamiliar, sector of health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Approach </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This study followed a mixed methods design [34] wherein quantitative and qualitative data were collected concurrently to provide verification of the study findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>A focus of this research was to provide students with opportunities for extended and reflective responses via focus group discussions, while also employing quantitative survey measures to systematically evaluate learning outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Setting, sampling, and recruitment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Mandatory five-day medical student placements were undertaken in two large Tasmanian RACFs (120–140 high care places) involved in the Wicking Teaching Aged Care Facilities Program (TACFP) [35] during 2013 and 2014 (with research data only collected during the first semester of 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Facilities were purposively selected as they were participants in the ongoing TACFP and had an enduring research relationship and memoranda of understanding with the research institution and associated School of Medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>All medical students undertaking their final (fifth) year of training at a Clinical School in southern Tasmania participate in RACF clinical placements, initiated via the TACFP from 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All available students (N = 75) within this Clinical School were sampled and undertook one week clinical placements in the two RACFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The medical student cohort was composed of young students who had limited previous exposure of the aged care environment and who had not previously experienced a clinical placement in this setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Over the course of the study, 10 groups of students attended RACF placements, with 5-7 students (n = 61) per group (randomly assigned by the School of Medicine course coordinator). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Before each clinical placement, students attended an information session about the research arm of the placement and were provided with the opportunity to give written consent to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the University of Tasmania Human Research Ethics Committee for Social Sciences (Ref. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>No. H0011576). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The clinical placement, and the broader Wicking TACFP, was underpinned by an iterative action research process that led participants, including 20 RACF staff who acted as mentors, through cycles of problem identification, planning, action and reflection, to improve the placement and overcome barriers to student engagement [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>A cycle of continuous improvement was engendered within the TACFP, which meant that successive student cohorts could expect to have progressively improved clinical placement experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Beginning in 2012, changes that were made to the clinical placement program to improve student engagement and learning included: a) the inclusion of a formal program of inter-professional learning; b) increased focus on dementia with on-site dementia education; c) increased contact time between medical students and residents to foster comprehensive assessments; d) revision of student calendars to ensure that RACF placements did not compete with clinical placements in other settings (i.e. hospitals); and e) reliable facility mentorship and General Practitioner (GP) tutor support to guide students through learning challenges, help them to identify appropriate clinical issues, and access appropriate patient information in an unfamiliar clinical environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Placements included clinical, non-clinical, and inter-professional learning opportunities, with a focus on collaborative assessments of volunteer residents and the presentation of resident case studies, which addressed student assessments and recommendations for improving care [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Up to 80 residents (across both facilities) were invited to participate in supervised and student-led health assessments by senior nursing staff at both facilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>As the assessments were not part of a research process, written consent from residents was not required and they were free to choose not to interact with students if they wished. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Family members of residents were also informed about the student placements and assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Oversight and assessment of medical student performance was undertaken by a GP tutor employed by the Clinical School who did not have direct responsibility for the care of RACF residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The tutor met with the students for 1.5 hours daily and facilitated sessions where, among a range of activities, she challenged them to critically analyse their understanding of the clinical issues experienced by residents and assessment of their case presentations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>When students were on the RACF wards, they were supported by registered nurses and professional care staff (referred to as extended care assistants or personal care assistants in Australia). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Medical students completed pre- and post-placement surveys of dementia knowledge (as a proxy measure for understanding of issues relevant to aged care) and participated in a one-hour focus-group discussion on the final placement day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The Dementia Knowledge Assessment Survey (DKAT 2), a reliable and valid measure of dementia knowledge [37], was administered in order to assess changes in student knowledge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Focus groups were convened by a researcher with training and experience in facilitated group discussions with support from a research assistant and note taker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Each focus group discussion lasted for 60 mins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Semi-structured questions addressed pre-placement expectations; differences from hospital training environments; learning opportunities and challenges; and interactions with residents, staff, and other student learners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="?"><plain>Examples of questions asked of respondents included, a) how was the aged care placement different from other clinical placements that you have experienced during your undergraduate training, b) how, if at all, has this aged care placement affected your understanding of the health issues faced by older people, and c) has this clinical placement experience changed your level of interest in pursuing a career in geriatric medicine? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Probing questions were also used to follow-up new lines of enquiry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>All discussions were audio-recorded and transcribed to facilitate analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In most student focus groups there was a clear demarcation between those who found the clinical placement rewarding and those who felt it was not an appropriate location for medical training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This created a tense climate with much debate and deliberation about the value of the learning experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In this context, the experience of the facilitator was crucial to ensuring that all voices were heard and diverse perspectives represented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Descriptive and inferential analyses of demographic and survey data were performed using SPSS (version 20) [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The Wilcoxon signed rank test was used to evaluate potential changes in dementia knowledge scores and expected/actual enjoyment from the beginning to the end of the placement week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The Wilcoxon signed rank test provides a mechanism for testing whether non-linear data from a group of respondents differs significantly over two time points, usually following an intervention (clinical placements in this case). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Qualitative data from 10 medical student focus group discussions were evaluated to assess their RACF placement experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Focus-group data were analysed using techniques commonly employed in thematic analysis of subjective reports [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>NVIVO (version 10) qualitative data analysis software was used to facilitate the organisation and coding of data [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A two-step coding procedure was employed, which was previously described by Lofland and Lofland [39] and is influenced by principles of Grounded Theory Analysis [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Transcripts were initially examined to identify broad categorical statements (also referred to as descriptive or initial codes) relating to clinical placement experiences and interactions with older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Following this, analytical (focussed) coding was used to identify respondent statements that best reflected latent or underlying themes that were contained within the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Analytic codes formed the basis of memos (summarised statements about the content of emergent ideas), which were developed into more detailed research themes (presented in the results section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This approach to coding is often referred to as inductive qualitative thematic analysis and is a commonly articulated approach in the social sciences and health services research [39, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Emergent themes were verified by two researchers (MA and EL) who coded the data independently to improve inter-rater reliability, procedures that are consistent with standard qualitative analysis guidelines for enhancing rigor in data analysis [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The level of agreement between the two researchers was calculated at &gt;95 % using the NVIVO coding comparison query. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>All themes were confirmed by the medical course coordinator (AL) for the fifth-year undergraduate program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of themes involved the medical course co-ordinator reading the draft analysis in its entirety and testing theme descriptions against her experiences of coordinating the placement and discussions with medical students. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The medical course coordinator did not participate in the focus group discussions and was well-placed to provide an informed perspective on the thematic descriptions that was independent of the subjective student experience. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Cohort characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>During 2013 and 2014, 75 medical students attended clinical placements in the two RACFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In total, 61 students completed the research component of the placement (81 % response rate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>One student withdrew from the medical training course and did not complete the research, while 13 students did not attend the data collection and focus-group sessions as they had either not provided consent or failed to attend the discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In general, the medical student cohort were not satisfied when notified that they would be undertaking a placement in an RACF nor were they positively predisposed to working with older adults (see Table 1 below).Table 1Demographic and attitudinal characteristics of 2013 and 2014 student cohortsDemographic and attitudinal information2013 (n = 23)2014 (n = 38)Age (mean years and standard deviation)25 (SD = 4)24 (SD = 3)Female gender57 %47 %Born in Australia83 %63 %English as first/main language100 %84 %Prior aged care experience Previous work/training experience in an RACF9 %8 % Previous visit to an RACF for any reason70 %53 %Pre-placement attitudes towards aged care Satisfied when notified of RACF placement13 %16 % Expect to enjoy working with older adults39 %39 %Post-placement attitudes towards aged care Understanding of RACFs has increased96 %92 % Enjoyed working with older adults72 %83 % </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Quantitative findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Following a five-day RACF placement, there was a modest, statistically significant 5 % increase in dementia knowledge among the medical student cohort, z = -2.63, p = .009, with a moderate effect size (r = .37). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>At the end of the clinical placement, the mean dementia knowledge score among the medical student cohort was 19.41 out of 21.00. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Despite scoring at the upper limit of the DKAT 2, medical students exhibited comparatively lower scores on items addressing symptoms and care provision: a) difficulty swallowing occurs in late-stage dementia (54 % scored correctly); b) movement is limited in late-stage dementia (59 % scored correctly); c) it is important to correct a person who has dementia when they are confused (70 % scored correctly). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Across the five-day program, there was a statistically significant 37 % improvement in medical students’ expected and actual enjoyment of working with older people from the beginning to the end of the clinical placement week, z = -3.08, p = .002, with a moderate effect size (r = .27), indicating a large improvement in attitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Knowledge and attitude data indicate a high level of student engagement with the RACF learning experience by the end of the placement week. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Qualitative findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Thematic analysis of qualitative data revealed four themes and contrasting learning experiences among the medical student cohorts across the two-year project: 1) dementia challenges assessment competence ; 2) aged care is perceived as an unnecessary opportunity cost; 3) aged care placements stimulate problem solving and critical reflection; and 4) contributing to resident health reinforces training and clinical decision making. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>These themes reflect a continuum of learning experiences among final year medical students who attended an RACF clinical placement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Theme 1: Dementia challenges assessment competence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>During the focus group discussions, student comments suggested that some struggled to engage with the relevance of the clinical placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>These students had difficulty recognising the complexity of the care needs of frail RACF residents, most of whom had multiple comorbidities and cognitive impairment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In the absence of an immediately accessible medical supervisor, these students assessed residents with limited or no reference to the opinions of facility staff, family members, or their interdisciplinary peers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>When they encountered residents with dementia, they reported experiencing a sense of futility because they did not know how to gather information from non-communicative respondents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In this context, dementia was seen as compromising their capacity to undertake a medical assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>For example, one student commented, “I had a patient with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>I spent 15 minutes with her before I decided that there wasn’t much more I could say or do” (EM5030, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Another student reported,We get told to do these comprehensive medical assessments, which are fine if you have a cognitively intact patient, but if you’ve got a patient with dementia there’s only so much you can do in this setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>One of my patients was in quite an advanced stage and I couldn’t really hold any sort of conversation with her. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>(BM5061, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>A key intent of the placement involved students developing recommendations for care changes arising from their assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Yet despite being assigned a resident by the GP tutors because of complex presentation and dementia, the absence of acute presenting symptoms were viewed as medically uninteresting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>One student recounted their experience of attempting to assess two high care RACF residents with dementia:From a medical point of view, there’s not a whole lot to do. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>We can take a good history, we can do a full examination and a Mini-Mental [State] Examination… but there isn’t an acute problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>My [assigned] patients… neither of them have anything really medical to talk about. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>They’re both very stable, it doesn’t take me very long to finish assessing them… there are no problems to manage (BM5018, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In this example, the student struggles to discern the complexity of a high-care residents’ situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In these circumstances, it appears that some students have difficulty engaging with the complexity implicit in residents with multiple comorbidities and dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Arguably, such cases were seen as beneath medical interest due to the absence of acute presenting symptoms amenable to treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Theme 2: Aged care is perceived as an unnecessary opportunity cost </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The lack of capacity to undertake comprehensive medical assessments of residents was explained, in part, by these students’ attitudes towards the aged care environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Some perceived the experience as an opportunity cost that was of little relevance for their forthcoming hospital intern year and which took time away from more important learning opportunities in the hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>As one student noted,[The RACF placement] wasn’t really that useful as a final year [student] in terms of the exams we’ve got coming up…we are going to be [hospital] interns next year and we need to be capable and confident in that regard (BM5005, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a number of medical students questioned whether the clinical placement might be better positioned earlier on in the course when the pressures of pending hospital internships were less imminent: “I think [the placement] would be of more benefit to more junior medical students in interacting with the patients and getting exposure to the vast amount of clinical signs that you may or may not get to see in the hospital setting” (EM5041, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Further, among the 2013 cohort, this sentiment was more pronounced because time for the one-week aged care placement was taken from a clinical rotation based on student preferences (referred to as a ‘selective’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>One student commented that the RACF placement reduced, “Our selective time in the [hospital] department – neurosurgery could use me for another week (BM5003, 2013)”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In this context, the 2013 clinical placements began with difficulty as students were displeased that hospital-based learning experiences, which they perceived as the most valuable clinical learning experiences, were considered to be lost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>This further reinforced the notion of the RACF placement as an opportunity cost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Other students also perceived RACF placements as lacking challenge, being low status, and conveying a negative stigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>One student reflected, “There is a lot of stigma with geriatrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>No one gets excited about it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>I haven’t come across too many [medically trained] people that love it” (EM5030, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Relatedly, students were challenged to conceptualise their role within the aged care setting in the absence of an established medical hierarchy, which further undermined the status of the clinical placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>For example, students in the 2013 cohort commented on the routine absence of doctors from RACFs, which they viewed as a barrier to learning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>As one student noted, “There is not a doctor here all the time and no one that we can speak to for advice on what you do or [how to] find out more information, so it’s just not the right environment” (BM5036, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Indeed, this was the first time in their undergraduate student training that no readily accessible medical supervision was available at all times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Further, reflecting a negative sentiment, even when these students identified alternative management options in the absence of a treating physician, they reported a sense of futility with respect to their capacity to influence resident care outcomes:We come in here and we’re given our patients and we assess them, but there’s not a GP here… We have our suggestions on how management plans can be changed and we’ve picked up these problems in these patients, but there’s nothing we can do to fix them (BM5038, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Despite the intermittent presence of a GP tutor and ongoing availability of senior nurse mentors, these students considered the lack of ready access to medical staff within the RACF to be a factor that undermined the RACF as an appropriate training environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Theme 3: Aged care placements stimulate problem solving and critical reflection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Deleterious experiences and negative sentiments in the RACF context were not ubiquitous across the entire medical student cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>While some students struggled to discern the complexity among volunteer residents and viewed the clinical placement as an opportunity cost, others saw an opportunity to extend their competency and develop capability for independent clinical decision making, particularly with respect to the management of frail elderly people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These students developed the skills to compile a comprehensive collateral history, which included thoroughly reviewing resident notes, seeking the views of interdisciplinary peers and colleagues (including nursing and paramedic students and RACF staff members), taking the time to look for non-verbal cues, and observing resident behaviour and mobility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>When these students were confronted by residents with dementia (and other conditions that challenged their assessment capability), they took up the challenge to extend their knowledge and skills. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>One student outlined the challenge associated with gaining a more holistic understanding of residents:I suppose [the placement] forced us to be more resourceful in how we gather clinical information… Seeing someone who doesn’t necessarily have an acute illness episode and… just trying to figure out a whole picture and ongoing generalised management plan, which considers their wishes without relying too heavily on a resident who’s not able to give you a good picture (BM5017, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Another student recounted their experience of seeking out alternative informants who could facilitate the development of a patient history. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>This student also recognised the value of this approach across clinical settings:If you can’t get good history [from a person with dementia], that’s an opportunity to talk to the nurse and [to] see how much [information] you can get from them [about the resident]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Then you can also speak to their families in order to get the full picture, and so you go through a process of investigating a particular patient with dementia and seeing how you take collateral histories…That’s useful no matter where you’re working (BM5006, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>When these students engaged with the challenges presented by interaction with residents with dementia, their reports suggested that they developed valuable skills that assisted them to become more resourceful clinical problem solvers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>They also experienced moments of revelation evident in their surprise when confronted with the complexity of high-care RACF residents, with the associated issues of polypharmacy, comorbidity, and chronicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>One student commented, “The most beneficial aspect of the placement was to look at polypharmacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We were assigned some time to look at the drugs our patients were on and how they could be altered – that was quite beneficial” (EM5044, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Another reflected,I had a good week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Not only did I get exposed to the elderly and see their issues of cognition, falls risk, depression, but I really got to see and visualise how these problems interact… So many of the residents had those issues and I learnt from that… I think it’s definitely a beneficial [placement] week and one that I’d recommend (BM5061, 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In instances such as these, medical undergraduates embraced the challenges and learning opportunities inherent in the RACF placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The challenges of aged care were reframed as cues for self-directed learning and independent clinical decision making that facilitated the development of recommendations for improving resident health and quality of life. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Theme 4: Contributing to resident health reinforces training and clinical decision making </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>With greater appreciation of the complex health issues faced by residents, students were often empowered to address problems they encountered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>While all students were tasked with performing a comprehensive assessment of a volunteer resident, some recognised that they were in a position to provide a new diagnosis, revise a resident’s management plan, or make recommendations that could improve health and quality of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>One student commented, “People are actually taking on board and thinking about using [our recommendations]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>I really enjoyed that because it’s really good for us and also good for the residents” (EM5029, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Opportunities to identify and address health problems in an older-adult cohort reinforced clinical training, bedside manner, and provided a framework for independent learning and clinical decision making. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>One student reflected on building rapport with a resident and addressing her ongoing health concerns:The most enjoyable [aspect of the placement] was speaking to my resident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>I really got to know who she was. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>She really benefitted from that and I really enjoyed it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>When I was speaking to her I said, “These are the medical issues that I think are important, would you like me to see what could be done to address these?” She really appreciated it, and she had some great ideas about what she’d like changed, and now it’s been given a voice [in my recommendations]… I’m really quite proud of what I found and what could potentially be put in place (EM5030, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Students also developed a new appreciation of how the clinical placement would support them in their role as hospital interns engaged with frail older patients requiring transfers to or from RACFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>One student stated that their placement experience, “Will help a lot in getting our patients ready to be discharged to a nursing home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Now we know what facilities are available… We also know what the limitations of these facilities are” (BM5058, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Another student recounted,Our focus [in fifth year] is on how we’d be working in the hospital, because obviously we train the majority of time in hospital and then next year we are going to be in the hospital [as interns]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>It’s good to have the community [RACF] perspective because patients might be transferred to and from nursing homes under our medical and surgical teams (BM5050, 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Understanding the health challenges faced by RACF residents and gaining insight into the functioning of the aged care sector imbued these students with confidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>They gained understanding and capability when conceptualising how they might collaborate and interact with RACFs as future medical practitioners and how to assess and make recommendations to improve quality of life for older people in a range of settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>This paper investigated medical student experiences during a five-day clinical placement at two regional Australian RACFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Survey data collected at the beginning of the placement indicated that most medical students had limited previous engagement with the aged care sector and commenced with an expectation that they would not enjoy the experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The data show that less than 20 % of students were satisfied with the prospect of an aged care placement, and one in three expected to enjoy working with older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>These findings are consistent with critiques of medical education that report a lack of interface between aged and acute care [10] and negative attitudes among medical students towards the care of older people and geriatric specialisations [18, 31, 44, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Such evidence suggests that negative sentiment is widespread among medical undergraduates and not unique to the cohort of students involved in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Although negative student attitudes are well documented [18, 31, 44, 45], few researchers have offered evidence to explain why such attitudes persist among medical undergraduates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Survey data from the current study concerning negative pre-placement sentiments were supported by focus-group results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Two themes emerged that provided explanation for students’ negative attitudes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Firstly, some students struggled to engage with residents with a significant cognitive impairment, such as dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>These students were challenged by problems with communication, lack of a clearly defined acute presentation, and the complex issues of multiple comorbidity and chronicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>These difficulties may be, in part, explained by student expectations for traditional patient-centred medicine that is challenged when a resident cannot communicate effectively or enter into a reciprocal physician-patient relationship [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In such circumstances, medical students may not have been adequately prepared, with appropriate clinical skills or situational awareness, to make sense of the undifferentiated comorbidities and communication challenges that characterise most frail older people resident in RACFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The response to this situation among students who lack such skills may be, as reported in the results, to conclude that either assessment is futile in the face of seemingly irresolvable communication challenges or to infer that the resident is clinically stable thereby apparently contradicting the appropriateness of conducting an assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Researchers have previously reported that medical students are not adequately prepared by their curricula for communication challenges encountered with cognitively impaired patients [17–47] and that they hold perceptions of older people’s health problems as frustrating and of little clinical interest [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Despite these sentiments, there is evidence to suggest that residents of aged care facilities do not always receive optimal health care [48–50] and can benefit from additional assessment and more targeted management, even when this is provided by students [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>A second theme that explains negative attitudes among medical students towards aged care and older adults suggests that students conceptualised the clinical placement as an opportunity cost that reduced training time in preferred hospital settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Some students had difficulty conceptualising the aged care environment as an appropriate setting for medical students due to the lack of an established medical hierarchy and differences from the hospital environment where they spend the majority of their placement time [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The study findings indicate that medical student learning is oriented around acute care environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Such settings work to develop more than just a particular set of clinical and professional skills. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>They also engender particular cultural values that take root in early medical education, a process that is often referred to as the hidden curriculum [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The hidden curriculum describes the learning that occurs through informal interactions with students, faculty members, and medical professionals, which shapes values, attitudes, and professional identity [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Prominent themes that have been reported in the hidden curriculum include patient dehumanisation, disease-focussed medicine, ritualised professional identity, and emotional neutralisation [25, 51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In some ways, the aged care placements may have exposed elements of the hidden curriculum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>This is reflected in students devaluing the aged care context as a site for productive and important learning and their struggle to engage with patients who do not fit the profile of an acute presentation amenable to treatment or cure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The RACF placement was intentionally challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Students encountered older-adult volunteers who exhibited a range of complex cognitive and physical symptoms that moved students beyond their comfort zone and previous experiences of diagnosing and treating a single clinical problem (such as a fracture or infection). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>While some students struggled to engage with this level of complexity, many students indicated that they valued this experience and that it had extended their competence and increased their understanding of older-adult health issues and the aged care sector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Clinical placements in aged care settings set up the conditions to differentiate between those students who are ready to engage with the complexity of aged health care and those who remain wedded to hospital training environments with expectations for acute presentation, omnipresent medical supervision, and high status settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>There was a clear continuum of experience among medical students, with some capable of understanding and engaging with the challenge of aged care and others who viewed the experience as confrontational and beyond their developmental needs as trainee medical professionals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Post-placement survey data indicated that positive knowledge and attitudinal changes occurred among medical students who participated in the five-day aged care placement – indicating positive placement engagement outcomes across the cohort irrespective of some negative sentiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Medical students scored highly on the DKAT 2, indicating good knowledge of dementia before the placement, and displayed a significant increase in knowledge at the end of the placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Changes in dementia knowledge were supported by self-reported improvements in understanding of the aged care environment among the majority of students who responded to the post-placement survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the survey data indicated that attitudes towards working with older adults improved significantly over the course of the clinical placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The results of this study reinforce mixed international evidence for variable medical student attitudes towards older adults, aged care, and geriatric medicine [18–22, 45, 52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>International research shows that although students may hold negative, neutral or positive attitudes towards older adults prior to clinical engagement, exposure to this cohort as part of medical training can significantly improve attitudes [21, 45, 53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Importantly, it has also been shown that an enduring or improved positive attitude towards older adults increases the likelihood that medical students will consider a career in geriatric medicine [22, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Considering the ageing demographic profile of western societies, this highlights the imperative to provide students with positive placement experiences that overcome the perceived lack of clinical interest associated with older adults in an aged care setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Qualitative themes emerging from this study also highlight positive student learning experiences and meaningful encounters with vulnerable residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Student reports indicated that the aged care placement stimulated problem solving and critical reflection about the complex health challenges in high care settings and provided opportunities for students to contribute to resident health and quality of life. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The third research theme indicates that, through student engagement in the assessment of older adults, there were powerful cues for learning that facilitated their appreciation of the complex health challenges in high-care environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>While some students were confronted and confused by non-communicative residents, an absence of an acute illness or exacerbation, and the insidious effects of chronicity, multiple comorbidities, and polypharmacy, others used the experience as an opportunity to extend their skills in accessing critical information through collateral history taking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The capacity to take a collateral history has been identified as a particularly important skill for physicians in the diagnosis and management of dementia [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>This is because people with dementia (and other cognitive impairments) often have difficulty clearly articulating their needs (for example, thirst or pain management) and may use behaviours, bodily movements, or incoherent vocalisation in an effort to communicate [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Although comparatively limited research has been undertaken that has explored learning outcomes for medical students on clinical placements that include older adults, researchers have noted that attitudes towards and perceptions about this cohort improve with interpersonal contact [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Further, it has been hypothesised that socialisation and empathy building tasks with older adults helps to reduce the stigma of providing healthcare to this cohort and challenge perceptions of the futility of treatment [20, 56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Researchers and medical educators who have investigated student engagement with older adults continue to recommend clinical engagement with the aged care sector as a means of improving competencies in the area of geriatric medicine [53, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>These findings highlight the importance of medical students having in-depth engagements with aged care residents in order to develop an informed understanding of the complexity of health care management needs beyond the hospital walls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Such skills will be critical in responding to the expansion of the older-adult population and growing prevalence of conditions such as dementia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The fourth research theme indicated that students value the opportunity to use their training and emerging clinical decision-making skills to address the complex problems of older residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>As part of the placement, students not only performed a collaborative and comprehensive medical assessment, but also made recommendations for improving the health and quality of life of volunteer residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>These recommendations were presented to RACF staff at the end of the placement and recorded in the residents’ medical notes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>This is among the most innovative aspects of the program and an approach to experiential learning that is gaining popularity in Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>In a small-scale Western Australian study of undergraduate placements in aged care, Seaman et al. [32] reported that undergraduate medical students and their tutors valued opportunities to make contributions to the health of residents through exchanging knowledge and new techniques with RACF staff and interacting directly with vulnerable older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In another Australian study, Elliott et al. [33] reported that medical students (in collaboration with nursing and paramedic students) “enhance quality of care” for aged care residents by improving facility vibrancy, increasing meaningful social contact, providing opportunities for residents to engage in teaching activities, and increasing capacity for, and confidence of, care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Although embedded placement experiences in aged care settings or interactions with people with dementia remain relatively uncommon within undergraduate medical education [9, 12], community based experiential learning is considered to offer advantages over classroom and simulation-based activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Following a systematic review of studies of experiential medical education, Doran and colleagues [58] reported that community based clinical placements support workforce acclimatisation, appropriate professional socialisation, improved patient-physician relations, and critical self-reflection concerning both biomedical and psychosocial competencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Doran et al. [58] identified that community based placements help to vivify clinical practice and increase student understanding of how the health system functions in the real world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Exposing medical students to complex, and often difficult to discern, health issues in aged care provides them with an avenue for detailed investigation and opportunities to meaningfully improve the health-related quality of life of residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In this way, they are able to practise and refine their clinical decision-making skills in ways that can be carried over into diverse clinical settings, such as the treatment of a person with dementia in hospital and discharge into community care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Further work is required, however, to embed aged care placements as part of ongoing medical curricula adaptations to 21st century population and health system changes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Successful learning outcomes achieved in the aged care placement were underpinned by support from RACF mentors, clinical oversight from a GP tutor, and a highly structured yet iterative placement program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Medical educators have recommended that successful pre-vocational clinical placements in RACFs rely on strong administration, internal and university support, and careful integration of staff, students, and residents within the program [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>They also suggest that continual improvement and adaptability are important to address student expectations and emerging challenges in the learning environment [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The data from the current study suggests that improvements in knowledge and attitudes may be achieved among some medical students following five days of embedded clinical training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Although positive outcomes have been achieved in this placement, the persistence of negative attitudes and encounters among some students suggests that more work is required to refine the placement structure in the future and, more importantly, to address a pervasive culture in medical education that devalues aged care and older adults as irrelevant or unworthy of the attention of medical students. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>When medical student placements have been embedded as part of curricula in the United States, for example, educators noted a political backlash citing negative perceptions among senior faculty staff (viewed as taking time away from important internal medicine placements) and the transmission of negative attitudes within learner cohorts [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Such embedded attitudes among teaching staff and students may also relate to limited resources for teaching and assessing geriatric medicine competencies where curricula focus predominantly on biomedical knowledge and hospital-based medicine [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Powers et al. [31] indicate that strong leadership and support from within medical schools may ultimately be the critical factor in ensuring the success of aged care clinical placements. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Limitations and future research opportunities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>There are few measures of dementia knowledge that can reliably gauge understanding of the syndrome among cohorts with a high level of education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Potential ceiling effects in the DKAT 2 may limit the extent to which pre- and post-placement knowledge differences can be reliably ascertained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Limitations in the measure used in this study potentially underestimate knowledge change due to a lack of sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Further work is required to develop a measure of dementia knowledge that is sensitive enough to measure knowledge change among highly educated individuals in the health sector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>A recently published dementia knowledge scale developed by members of the research team (MA and AR) will address this gap in future studies [59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>This study was also preliminary in nature and the scale of investigation was limited to two RACFs that hosted medical students from a southern Tasmanian Clinical School during 2013 and 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Future national expansion of the TACF program would be desirable to attain a nationally representative sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>As all students were from the same Clinical School, it is not yet possible to determine the extent to which different undergraduate medical curricula and cultures influence student engagement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In this research, students were embedded in RACFs for five days and well supported by an onsite University medical tutor and senior mentors (experienced nurses and care staff) from the participating facilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The long-standing nature of the clinical placement program (which began in 2011) and high level of faculty and RACF support and supervision arguably provided an optimal learning experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>However, it is possible that replication of these placements in the context of a less supportive environment, where staff members may exhibit negative attitudes towards students or medical tutors could not routinely attend the placements, may be a threat to effectiveness of such learning opportunities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In RACFs, there is currently limited engagement of GPs with residents and few permanent appointments in this sector [60, 61], which could undermine student perceptions about the relevance of the placement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>This situation, however, does not reflect a lack of need or complexity in aged care, but rather the traditional role of the GP in the community (where they are often based in clinics or practices). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>In this respect, it was necessary to have a GP tutor onsite each day to supervise and direct student activities as well as helping them to understand the relevance of the placement at a time when GP roles are altering with demographic changes (including population ageing). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The GP tutor was not present at all times, allowing students to develop their independent clinical decision making, but they were available at the end of each day to support and contextualise the placement experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Researchers in other institutions should take care to ensure that placement programs are well designed with sufficient engagement from the aged care sector and educational institution support to achieve an optimal mix of independent learning and supervision. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The placement of students in RACFs also has the opportunity to elicit impacts beyond student learning and influence care quality for residents and changes in the clinical behaviour of staff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>While a small number of studies have reported the positive impacts of health student placements on resident quality of life [32, 33], few have investigated how students potentially change the clinical practice of RACF staff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>It is possible that embedding fifth-year medical students (who have a high level of training in such topics as pharmaceuticals, pain management, and diagnosis) may bring a greater level of awareness to the aged care sector about the need to provide best-evidence care – even towards the very end of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>This is an area of potential future investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Clinical placements in RACFs challenge medical students to become more resourceful and independent in their assessment and decision making with vulnerable older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>While not all students can be highly engaged with the learning opportunities over a relatively short five-day placement, our mixed methods findings suggest that many find the experience to be rewarding and relevant in the context of their undergraduate training and preparations for hospital internship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Critical elements of a successful placement include a high degree of structure, support and supervision from medical tutors and senior RACF staff, and an iterative approach to program design that address emergent challenges and student concerns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Remaining challenges include inculcating positive attitudes among medical undergraduates towards the aged care sector and older adult health (including dementia) and achieving a better balance between acute and non-acute training opportunities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Considering that the placement program described in this paper is arguably the most intensive and large-scale engagement with the aged care sector and older-adult health that Australian undergraduate medical students have within a five-year undergraduate degree, there appears to be a horizon of opportunity to make inroads into knowledge, attitudes, and clinical competence by increasing experiential education in this sector. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DKAT 2</term><def><p>Dementia Knowledge Assessment Tool Version 2.</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GP</term><def><p>General Practitioner</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RACF</term><def><p>Residential Aged Care Facility</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TACFP</term><def><p>Teaching Aged Care Facilities Program</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>MA acted as a project officer for the clinical placement program (TACFP), collected research data, conducted the quantitative and qualitative data analysis, and prepared the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>EL assisted with research design and data analysis, participated in data collection, and was involved in drafting the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>AL acted as the medical student tutor and course coordinator and assisted in drafting the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>LT conducted literature searches and assisted in drafting and editing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>AR developed the placement program, conceived of the study, secured funding for administration and evaluation, and assisted with manuscript preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><fn><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Authors’ information </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>MA has a PhD in gerontology from the University of Otago and works with the Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre leading programs to develop and evaluate educational initiatives that aim to improve knowledge of dementia and health outcomes for care recipients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>EL has a PhD in public health from the University of Adelaide and is a Research Fellow in the Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>She was project manager of the Wicking Teaching Aged Care Facilities Program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>AL is a General Practitioner and Senior Lecturer in Primary Health who has previously worked as the aged care clinical placement tutor and course coordinator with the University of Tasmania. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>LT has a Bachelor of Health (Hons) from Macquarie University and works with the Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre on programs to develop and evaluate educational initiatives that aim to improve knowledge of dementia and health outcomes for care recipients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>AR is the co-director of the Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre and Professor of Aged Care at the University of Tasmania. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>AR conceived of and implemented the TACFP program in Tasmania and in other sites across Australia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The researchers acknowledge funding from the Wicking Trust, Health Workforce Australia, the Department of Social Services (previously the Department of Health and Ageing), and the School of Medicine (University of Tasmania), which provided substantial support for the placement and evaluation programs (none of these funding organisations influenced the design or collection of data for this manuscript). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The researchers also acknowledge Dr Kate-Ellen Elliott and Dr Megan Stronach for their assistance with data collection at one of the two participating RACFs. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>1.MasudTBlundellAGordonALMulpeterKRollerRSinglerKEuropean undergraduate curriculum in geriatric medicine developed using an international modified Delphi techniqueAge Ageing201443569570210.1093/ageing/afu019<?supplied-pmid 24603283?>24603283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>2.OakleyRPattinsonJGoldbergSDauntLSamraRMasudTEquipping tomorrow’s doctors for the patients of todayAge Ageing201443444244710.1093/ageing/afu077<?supplied-pmid 24958744?>24958744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>3.Australian Bureau of Statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Population projections, Australia: 2012 (base) to 2101. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats">http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats</ext-link> (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Accessed 15 Jan 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>4.Australian Institute of Health and Welfare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>General practice activity in Australia 2000–01 to 2009–10: 10-year data tables. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aihw.gov.au/publication-detail/">http://www.aihw.gov.au/publication-detail/</ext-link> (2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Accessed 20 Dec 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>5.Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The State of Aging and Health in America 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/features/agingandhealth/">http://www.cdc.gov/features/agingandhealth/</ext-link> (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Accessed 3 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="?"><plain>6.PartridgeMRMedicine: a rethink? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Are entrants to the profession and the way it is organised fit for purpose?Clin Med201414322522810.7861/clinmedicine.14-3-225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>7.DensenPChallenges and opportunities facing medical educationTrans Am Clin Climatol Assoc20111224858<?supplied-pmid 21686208?>21686208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>8.GordonALBlundellADhesiJKForrester-PatonCForrester-PatonJMitchellHKUK medical teaching about ageing is improving but there is still work to be done: the Second National Survey of Undergraduate Teaching in Ageing and Geriatric MedicineAge Ageing201443229329710.1093/ageing/aft207<?supplied-pmid 24375323?>24375323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>9.Health Workforce Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Clinical training 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hwa.gov.au/">http://www.hwa.gov.au/</ext-link> (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Accessed 5 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>10.RobinsonAHornerBNew approach to old schoolAged Care Insite201461011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>11.HoekJFRibbeMWHertoghCMPMvan der VleutenCPMThe role of the specialist physician in nursing homes: the Netherlands’ experienceInt J Geriatr Psychiatry200318324424910.1002/gps.816<?supplied-pmid 12642894?>12642894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>12.TulloESGordonALTeaching and learning about dementia in UK medical schools: a national surveyBMC Geriatr201313293510.1186/1471-2318-13-29<?supplied-pmid 23537386?>23537386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>13.World Health Organisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Dementia: a public health priority. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mental_health/publications/dementia_report_2012/en/">http://www.who.int/mental_health/publications/dementia_report_2012/en/</ext-link> (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Accessed 20 April 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>14.BeerCWatsonNCaputoLHirdKFlickerLStudents and teachers’ preferences for undergraduate dementia education in Western AustraliaGerontol Geriatr Educ201132327329010.1080/02701960.2011.599900<?supplied-pmid 21846237?>21846237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>15.NagleBJUsitaPMEdlandSDUnited States medical students’ knowledge of Alzheimer diseaseJ Educ Eval Health Prof2013101510.3352/jeehp.2013.10.423441241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>16.VisvanathanRSilakongTYuSDedicated teaching block for undergraduate geriatric medicine improves knowledgeAustralas J Ageing201130423423810.1111/j.1741-6612.2011.00505.x<?supplied-pmid 22176571?>22176571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>17.DrickamerMALevyBIrwinKSRohrbaughRMPerceived needs for geriatric education by medical students, internal medicine residents and facultyJ Gen Intern Med200621121230123410.1111/j.1525-1497.2006.00585.x<?supplied-pmid 17105521?>17105521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>18.MeiboomADiedrichCDe VriesHHertoghCScheeleFThe hidden curriculum of the medical care for elderly patients in medical education: a qualitative studyGerontol Geriatr Educ2014361304410.1080/02701960.2014.966902<?supplied-pmid 25288267?>25288267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>19.HigashiRTTillackAASteinmanMHarperMJohnstonCBElder care as “frustrating” and “boring”: understanding the persistence of negative attitudes toward older patients among physicians-in-trainingJ Aging Stud201226447648310.1016/j.jaging.2012.06.007<?supplied-pmid 22939544?>22939544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>20.GonzalesEMorrow-HowellNGilbertPChanging medical students’ attitudes toward older adultsGerontol Geriatr Educ201031322023410.1080/02701960.2010.503128<?supplied-pmid 20730650?>20730650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>21.KishimotoMNagoshiMWilliamsSMasakiKHBlanchettePLKnowledge and attitudes about geriatrics of medical students, internal medicine residents, and geriatric medicine fellowsJ Am Geriatr Soc20055319910210.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53018.x<?supplied-pmid 15667384?>15667384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>22.HughesNJSoizaRLChuaMHoyleGEMacDonaldAPrimroseWRMedical student attitudes toward older people and willingness to consider a career in geriatric medicineJ Am Geriatr Soc200856233433810.1111/j.1532-5415.2007.01552.x<?supplied-pmid 18179490?>18179490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>23.HolmanHLorigKPatients as partners in managing chronic disease: partnership is a prerequisite for effective and efficient health careBMJ2000320723452652710.1136/bmj.320.7234.526<?supplied-pmid 10688539?>10688539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>24.StreetREpsteinRGlanzKRimerBViswanathKKey interpersonal functions and health outcomesHealth Behavior and Health Education: Theory, Research and Practice20084San FranciscoJossey-Bass </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>25.GaufbergEHBataldenMSandsRBellSKThe hidden curriculum: what can we learn from third-year medical student narrative reflections?Acad Med201085111709171610.1097/ACM.0b013e3181f57899<?supplied-pmid 20881818?>20881818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>26.Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Residents living in residential care facilities: United States, 2010. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db91.pdf">http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db91.pdf</ext-link> (2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Accessed 17 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>27.Health Workforce Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Mapping clinical placements: capturing opportunities for growth-supply (clinical training provider) study. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hwa.gov.au/">http://www.hwa.gov.au/</ext-link> (2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Accessed 11 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>28.Australian Institute of Health and Welfare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Residential aged care in Australia 2010–2011: a statistical overview. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aihw.gov.au/WorkArea/DownloadAsset.aspx?">http://www.aihw.gov.au/WorkArea/DownloadAsset.aspx?</ext-link> (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Accessed 17 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>29.Australian Institute of Health and Welfare: Dementia in Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Australian Institute of Health and Welfare: Canberra, 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>30.Productivity Commission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Caring for older Australians, Report no. 53: final inquiry report. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aihw.gov.au/WorkArea/DownloadAsset.aspx?id=10737422896">http://www.aihw.gov.au/WorkArea/DownloadAsset.aspx?id=10737422896</ext-link> (2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Accessed 17 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>31.PowersCSavidgeAAllenRCooper-WittCImplementing a mandatory geriatrics clerkshipJ Am Geriatr Soc200250236937310.1046/j.1532-5415.2002.50071.x<?supplied-pmid 12028222?>12028222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>32.Seaman KL, Bulsara CE, Saunders RD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Interprofessional learning in residential aged care: providing optimal care for residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Aust J Prim Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>2014;21(3):360-364. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>33.ElliottKEJAnnearMJBellEJPalmerAJRobinsonALResidents with mild cognitive decline and family members report health students ‘enhance capacity of care’and bring ‘a new breath of life’in two aged care facilities in TasmaniaHealth Expect20141861927194010.1111/hex.12236<?supplied-pmid 25041246?>25041246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>34.Creswell JW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Research design: Qualitative, quantitative, and mixed methods approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Thousand Oaks, California: Sage; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>35.RobinsonALeaETierneyLSeeCMarlowAMorleyCTeaching aged care facilities: implementing interprofessional prevocational education and practice in residential aged care2013HobartWicking Dementia Research and Education Centre, University of Tasmania </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>36.KemmisSMcTaggartRDenzinNLincolnYParticipatory action research: communicative action in the public sphereThe sage handbook of qualitative research20063CaliforniaSage Publications Inc </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>37.ToyeCLesterLPopescuAMcInerneyFAndrewsSRobinsonALDementia Knowledge Assessment Tool Version Two: development of a tool to inform preparation for care planning and delivery in families and care staffDementia201413224825610.1177/1471301212471960<?supplied-pmid 24339059?>24339059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>38.IBM CorpIBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 20.02011ArmonkIBM Corp </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>39.LoflandJLoflandLAnalysing social settings: a guide to qualitative observaion and analysis19953BelmontWadsworth Publishing Company </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>40.QSR International: NVIVO qualitative data analysis software Version 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>41.CharmazKConstructing grounded theory2014CaliforniaSage </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>42.AnnearMLeaERobinsonAAre care workers appropriate mentors for nursing students in residential aged care?BMC Nurs2014131445210.1186/s12912-014-0044-8<?supplied-pmid 25530713?>25530713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>43.KittoSChestersJGrbichCQuality in qualitative research: criteria for authors and assessors in the submission and assessment of qualitative research articles for the Medical Journal of AustraliaMed J Aust20081884243246<?supplied-pmid 18279135?>18279135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>44.MadanAKAliabadi-WahleSBeechDJAgeism in medical students’ treatment recommendations: the example of breast-conserving proceduresAcad Med200176328228410.1097/00001888-200103000-00019<?supplied-pmid 11242582?>11242582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="?"><plain>45.Ní ChróinínDCroninECullenWO’SheaDSteeleMBuryGWould you be a geriatrician? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Student career preferences and attitudes to a career in geriatric medicineAge Ageing201342565465710.1093/ageing/aft093<?supplied-pmid 23917484?>23917484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>46.EpsteinRMFranksPFiscellaKShieldsCGMeldrumSCKravitzRLMeasuring patient-centered communication in patient–physician consultations: theoretical and practical issuesSoc Sci Med20056171516152810.1016/j.socscimed.2005.02.001<?supplied-pmid 16005784?>16005784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>47.van Weel-BaumgartenEBolhuisSRosenbaumMSilvermanJBridging the gap: How is integrating communication skills with medical content throughout the curriculum valued by students?Patient Education and Counseling20139021778310.1016/j.pec.2012.12.004<?supplied-pmid 23273436?>23273436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>48.CastleNGEngbergJStaff turnover and quality of care in nursing homesMed Care200543661662610.1097/01.mlr.0000163661.67170.b9<?supplied-pmid 15908857?>15908857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>49.TakaiYYamamoto-MitaniNOkamotoYKoyamaKHondaALiterature review of pain prevalence among older residents of nursing homesPain Manag Nurs201011420922310.1016/j.pmn.2010.08.006<?supplied-pmid 21095596?>21095596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>50.De BellisAOpinion piece: Australian residential aged care and the quality of nursing care provisionContemp Nurse201035110011310.5172/conu.2010.35.1.100<?supplied-pmid 20636183?>20636183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>51.LamianiGLeoneDMeyerECMojaEAHow Italian students learn to become physicians: a qualitative study of the hidden curriculumMed Teach2011331298999610.3109/0142159X.2011.577467<?supplied-pmid 22225437?>22225437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>52.BensadonBATeasdaleTAOdenheimerGLAttitude adjustment: shaping medical students’ perceptions of older patients with a geriatrics curriculumAcad Med201388111630163410.1097/ACM.0b013e3182a7f071<?supplied-pmid 24072114?>24072114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>53.AtkinsonHHLambrosADavisBRSLawlorJSLovatoJSinkKMTeaching medical student geriatrics competencies in 1 week: an efficient model to teach and document selected competencies using clinical and community resourcesJ Am Geriatr Soc20136171182118710.1111/jgs.12314<?supplied-pmid 23710572?>23710572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>54.FeldmanHHJacovaCRobillardAGarciaAChowTBorrieMDiagnosis and treatment of dementia: 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>DiagnosisCan Med Assoc J2008178782583610.1503/cmaj.07079818362376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="?"><plain>55.AnnearMToyeCMcInerneyFEcclestonCTranterBElliottKWhat should we know about dementia in the 21st Century? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>A Delphi consensus studyBMC Geriatr201515511325559550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>56.SamraRGriffithsACoxTConroySKnightAChanges in medical student and doctor attitudes toward older adults after an intervention: a systematic reviewJ Am Geriatr Soc20136171188119610.1111/jgs.12312<?supplied-pmid 23750821?>23750821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>57.De WittJBWeckmannMNguyenCMParsonsCHughesCMA cross-national cross-sectional survey of the attitudes and perceived competence of final-year medicine, nursing and pharmacy students in relation to end-of-life care in dementiaPalliative Med201327984785410.1177/0269216313483661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="?"><plain>58.DornanTLittlewoodSMargolisSAScherpbierASpencerJYpinazarVHow can experience in clinical and community settings contribute to early medical education? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>A BEME systematic reviewMed Teach200628131810.1080/01421590500410971<?supplied-pmid 16627313?>16627313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>59.AnnearMToyeCEcclestonCMcInerneyFElliottKTranterBDementia Knowledge Assessment Scale (DKAS): development and preliminary psychometric propertiesJ Am Geriatr Soc201563112375238110.1111/jgs.13707<?supplied-pmid 26503020?>26503020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>60.O’HalloranJBrittHValentiLGeneral practitioner consultations at residential aged-care facilitiesMed J Aust200718728891<?supplied-pmid 17635090?>17635090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>61.GadzhanovaSReedRMedical services provided by general practitioners in residential aged-care facilities in AustraliaMed J Aust200718729294<?supplied-pmid 17635091?>17635091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
