<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECAM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine : eCAM</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1741-427X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1741-4288</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4931053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/6784689</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Antidepressant-Like Effects of Fractions Prepared from Danzhi-Xiaoyao-San Decoction in Rats with Chronic Unpredictable Mild Stress: Effects on Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal Axis, Arginine Vasopressin, and Neurotransmitters </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Li-Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2267-8296</contrib-id><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Can</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Jun-Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Wei-Kang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Basic Theory of Chinese Medicine, School of Preclinical Medicine, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, 232 Waihuandong Road, Higher Education Mega Center, Panyu District, Guangzhou 510060, China</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Pathophysiology, School of Preclinical Medicine, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, 232 Waihuandong Road, Higher Education Mega Center, Panyu District, Guangzhou 510060, China</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Pathophysiology, School of Preclinical Medicine, Sun Yat-Sen University, 58 Zhongshan Er Road, Guangzhou 510080, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Can Yan: <email>gzyancan@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Maria Camilla Bergonzi </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>2016</volume><elocation-id>6784689</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 Li-Li Wu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to investigate the antidepressant-like effects of two fractions, including petroleum ether soluble fraction (Fraction A, FA) and water-EtOH soluble fraction (Fraction B, FB) prepared from the Danzhi-xiaoyao-san (DZXYS) by using chronic unpredictable mild stress-induced depressive rat model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that DZXYS could ameliorate the depression-like behavior in chronic stress model of rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of hyperactivity of HPA axis and the modulation of monoamine and amino acid neurotransmitters in the hippocampus may be the important mechanisms underlying the action of DZXYS antidepressant-like effect in chronically stressed rats. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Depression is the commonest psychiatric disorder with such main clinical features as significant and lasting depression, mental retardation, cognitive impairment, and depression and somatic symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, depression is a risk factor for the onset of type 2 diabetes mellitus, hypertension, coronary heart disease, cancer, and so on [1], which is projected to become the second biggest contributor to the global burden of disease and disability by 2020 according to WHO's prediction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Monoamine neurotransmitters disorder and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis hyperactivity, widely recognized, are the two important mechanisms of the occurrence of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>At present, based on the hypothesis of monoamine neurotransmitters function deficiency, antidepression drugs, such as the tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), the selective norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), the selective norepinephrine-dopamine reuptake inhibitors, and the monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs), have been developed, which are mainly by inhibiting the transporter function of 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT), dopamine (DA), and norepinephrine (NE) to block the reuptake of monoamine neurotransmitters to increase the concentration of those neurotransmitters mentioned above in synaptic cleft to improve the symptoms of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>But now, the efficacy of those drugs has been faced with serious challenges [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>It is noted that inhibition of HPA axis activity is a very effective antidepressant treatment, but so far new antidepression drugs taking the HPA axis as the target have not been successfully tested by the clinical trials [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the need for more effective and safer antidepression drugs continues to command attention in neuropsychopharmacology within the psychotherapeutic community. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) has offered prospective alternative therapy for the treatment of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The records of treating mental disorders could be found in ancient medicinal books, and herbal decoction Danzhi-xiaoyao-san (DZXYS), also called Jiawei-xiaoyao-san, is one of the most popular classical ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The first description of DZXYS is recorded in Jiaozhu Furen Liangfang “Edited and Commented Effective Formulae for Woman” written by Xue Yi (1487–1559) in Ming Dynasty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This herbal formula is composed of the following herbs: Radix Bupleuri, Paeoniae Radix Alba, Angelica sinensis, bighead atractylodes rhizome, Poria cocos, bark of tree peony root, Fructus Gardeniae, Mentha haplocalyx, and Licorice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It is well known that DZXYS decoction plays an important role in the clinical therapy of depression-related disorders in China [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In Chinese medicinal theory, DZXYS decoction exhibits therapeutic effects by releasing constraint and encouraging the free-flow of liver qi, clearing liver heat, nourishing blood, and invigorating spleen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Although this decoction has been used frequently, thus far, it remains unclear as to which active fraction of the DZXYS is responsible for the antidepressant effect and its possible regulatory mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to investigate the antidepressant-like effects of two fractions, including petroleum ether soluble fraction (Fraction A, FA) and water-EtOH soluble fraction (Fraction B, FB) prepared from the DZXYS by using chronic unpredictable mild stress- (CUMS-) induced depressive rat model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The underlying mechanism of antidepression was mainly explored by measuring the function of HPA axis and the contents of monoamine and amino acid neurotransmitters in hippocampus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In addition, as a neuropeptide, the arginine vasopressin (AVP) contents in plasma and hypothalamus were detected in the study in order to further explore the antidepressant mechanisms of DZXYS in modulating HPA axis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Plant Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Medical plants (dried crude herbs) used for preparation of DZXYS were purchased from Medicinal Materials Company of Guangzhou, Guangzhou, China, and authenticated by Professor Ming-Ping Liu, Chinese Materia Medica College, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>DZXYS consists of nine dried crude herbs listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The ratio of Radix Bupleuri, Paeoniae Radix Alba, Angelica sinensis, bighead atractylodes rhizome, Poria cocos, bark of tree peony root, Fructus Gardeniae, Mentha haplocalyx, and Licorice is 2 : 2 : 2 : 2 : 2 : 2 : 2 : 1 : 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The voucher specimens were conserved at the herbal herbarium of Chinese Materia Medica College, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The voucher specimens of the herbal materials were deposited for possible future comparison. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Preparation of Fractions from DZXYS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The crude powdered mixture of DZXYS, 5000 g, according to the prescription proportion, was added with petroleum ether (bp 60–90°C) and then water-bath-heated and refluxed for 4 times (2 h, 1.5 h, 1.5 h, and 1.5 h); the petroleum-soluble fraction (Fraction A, FA, yield: 1.24%) and precipitate were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The precipitate was extracted for 3 times (2 h, 1.5 h, and 1.5 h) with boiling water, and then the combined water extracts were filtered and concentrated to 2500 mL solution which was concentrated under reduced pressure and fractionated by the addition of 1710 mL of 95% ethyl alcohol (EtOH) to give a water-EtOH soluble supernatant fraction (Fraction B, FB, the yield: 25.9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>FA and FB were lyophilized into dry powders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this paper, the doses of FA and FB were expressed in terms of dried weight of herbal material used for extraction per unit body weight of experimental rats (g/kg). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Drugs, Reagents, and Chemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Imipramine hydrochloride (IMI) was purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The assay kits of corticosterone (CORT), corticotrophin-releasing hormone (CRH), adrenocorticotropin (ACTH), and arginine vasopressin (AVP) were purchased from Nanjing Jiancheng Institute of Biotechnology, Nanjing, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The standard 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT), dopamine (DA), and norepinephrine (NE) were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Disodium ethylenediaminetetraacetate (EDTA) and the standard amino acids including glutamic acid (Glu), aspartic acid (Asp), γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA), and taurine (Tau) were obtained from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>All other reagents used were of analytical grade. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Experimental Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Male Wistar rats weighing 180–220 g were purchased from the Laboratory Animal Center of Nanfang Medical University, Guangzhou, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Animals were allowed 1 week to adapt to the surroundings before beginning any experimentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Animals were maintained on a 12 h light/dark cycle under controlled temperature of 22 ± 2°C and had free access to food and water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All animals handling procedures were performed in strict accordance with the China legislation on the use and care of laboratory animals and were approved by the Animal Experimentation Ethics Committee of the Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>All efforts were made to minimize the number and suffering of animals needed to produce reliable data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Chronic Unpredictable Mild Stress (CUMS) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The stress procedure performed here mainly referred to Willner [6] with some modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the CUMS protocol consisted of the sequential application of a variety of unpredictable mild stressors: (1) food deprivation for 24 hours, (2) water deprivation for 24 hours, (3) exposure to an empty bottle for 1 hour, (4) cage tilt (45°) for 7 hours, (5) overnight illumination, (6) soiled cage (200 mL water in 100 g sawdust bedding) for 24 hours, (7) forced swimming at 8°C for 6 minutes, (8) physical restraint for 2 hours, and (9) exposure to a foreign object (e.g., a piece of plastic) for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>These stressors were randomly scheduled over a one-week period and repeated throughout the 4 weeks of experiment (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Nonstressed animals were left undisturbed in their home cages except during housekeeping procedures such as cage cleaning. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Treatment of Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In experiments, animals were randomized into seven groups of ten individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The control animals were unstressed and intragastrically given daily 2 mL distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For another six groups, the animals were treated simultaneously with CUMS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The drugs (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg/day, FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, and IMI at 20 mg/kg/day, suspended in distilled water) were intragastrically given daily 1 h before the stress exposure for the entire 4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Following each stress session, animals were returned to their home cages and were able to access food and water freely for the remainder of the day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Rat Sucrose Preference Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Sucrose preference test was carried out at the end of 4-week CUMS exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The test was performed as described previously [7] with minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Briefly, after one week of the single cage feeding adaptation, the rats received a week of double bottle training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>One bottle was 1% sucrose solution (w/v) 100 mL (in the cage on the left), another was pure water 100 mL (in the cage on the right), and two bottles were fixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Sucrose solution and pure water were added every morning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>After one-week training, the rats were deprived of water and food for 24 hours, and then 1 h sucrose solution consumption experiments were conducted to measure the basis of sucrose preference at 9:00 am in which rats were housed in individual cages and were free to access two bottles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After 4 weeks of experiment, the sucrose preference was conducted again by the method described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The sucrose preference was calculated by the following formula: sucrose preference (%) = sucrose consumption/total liquid consumption × 100% [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Forced Swimming Test (FST) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The forced swimming test was performed according to the method of Porsolt [9] with modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Briefly, rats were forced to swim in a transparent glass vessel (25 cm in height and 14 cm in diameter) filled with 15 cm of water at 24 ± 1°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The total duration of immobility (seconds) was measured during the last 4 minutes of a single 6-minute test session [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Rats were considered immobile when they ceased struggling and remained floating motionless in the water except the movements necessary to keep their heads above the water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Decrease in the duration of immobility during the FST was taken as a measure of antidepressant activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>2.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Tail Suspension Test (TST) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The duration of immobility time induced by tail suspension was measured according to the method of Steru [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Rats both acoustically and visually isolated were suspended above the floor by adhesive tape placed approximately 1 cm from the tip of the tail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The remaining immobile time of TST was quantified for 6 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Rats were considered immobile only when they hung passively and completely motionless. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>2.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Open-Field Test (OFT) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The OFT was based on the method of Archer [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The OFT apparatus consisted of a clear acrylic box (100 cm × 100 cm × 50 cm) with a lid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The floor was divided by drawn lines into 36 areas of about 25 sq.cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The test was performed in a light- and sound-attenuated shield box with a dim light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The locomotor activity counts and the rearing counts were recorded for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>All test sessions were recorded by a video camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Between subjects, the box was thoroughly cleaned with cotton and 95% ethanol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>2.11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>CORT, CRH, ACTH, and AVP Contents in Plasma Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>After the end of the experimental period, all rats were sacrificed by decapitation between 10:00 and 11:00 am in the laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>After decapitation, the blood samples were collected into heparinized Eppendorf tubes and immediately centrifuged for 1 min (10,000 rpm) at 4°C to separate plasma, which was then frozen at −20°C until subsequent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>CORT, CRH, ACTH, and AVP contents in plasma were determined by using competitive radioimmunoassay according to the manufacturer's instruction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>2.12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>CRH, ACTH, and AVP Contents in Hypothalamus Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>After decapitation, the brains were rapidly removed and immersed into the boiling saline for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Hypothalamus was dissected according to the method described by Yan et al. [13], weighed, and then homogenized in 0.2 mL of 1 M acetic acid solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>After incubation for 100 minutes at room temperature, homogenate solution was mixed with 0.2 mL of 1 M NaOH solution and centrifuged for 20 min (3500 rpm) at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The supernatants were collected and stored at −40°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Radioimmunoassay was performed to measure CRH, ACTH, and AVP in hypothalamus following the manufacturer's instruction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>2.13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Monoamine and Amino Acid Neurotransmitters Contents in Hippocampus Determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>After the end of the experimental period, all rats were sacrificed by decapitation between 10:00 and 11:00 am in the laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>After decapitation, the whole rat brains were rapidly removed and the hippocampus was carefully dissected according to the method described previously [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The contents of 5-HT, 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA), DA, and NE in hippocampus were determined by using an electrochemical high-performance liquid chromatography system (EC-HPLC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Tissues were placed in 0.1 N perchloric acid (including 0.1% aminothiopropionic acid), then sonicated, and centrifuged twice for 20 min at 10,000 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The supernatants were stored at −80°C until being analyzed for the contents of DA, 5-HT, and NE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The pellets were digested in 1 mL of 0.5 N NaOH for measurements of protein concentration using Bio-Rad assay reagents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>For EC-HPLC analysis, samples were loaded onto a Waters 7125 plus autosampler (Waters, Milford, USA) and the mobile phase was delivered at a constant rate of 1 mL/min by a Waters Model 515 pump (Waters, Milford, USA) through a C18, 5 mm, 250 mm × 4.6 mm analytical column (HiQsil, Japan) placed in a column heater (35°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The LC amperometric potential was set to 0.75 V with reference to an Ag-AgCl reference electrode and the sensitivity of the detector was modified according to the content of amines in the sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The mobile phase consisted of 0.1 M monosodium phosphate, 0.15 mM EDTA, 2 mM NaCl, 1.4 mM octyl sodium sulfate, and 12% methanol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The signal from the detector was recorded and the data was analyzed using a N2000 Workstation (Institute of Intelligent Information Engineering, Zhejiang University, Zhejiang, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The monoamine neurotransmitter contents were expressed as ng/g weight of tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Amino acids in hippocampus were determined by OPA precolumn derivatization and RP-HPLC with a high-performance liquid chromatography system (Hewlett-Packed 1100 series, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The derivatization procedure was accomplished by an online autoinjector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The derivatives were separated on a Hypersil ODS and the signals were detected with a programmable fluorospectrophotometer detector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Mobile phase A was 10 mmol/L, PH 7.2 sodium phosphate buffer (PB) containing 0.5% (φ) tetrahydrofuran, and B was PB-methanol-acetonitrile (50 : 35 : 15 by volume). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The elution program was 100% A with 0% B at the start (0 min) and 0% A with 100% B at the end (25 min) of the program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>OPA-reactive compounds were detected at excitation wavelength of 340 nm and emission wavelength of 450 nm, and chromatograms were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.14"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>2.14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The significance of the difference was statistically evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) as well as the least significant difference test. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Sucrose Preference Test in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 2, compared with the control group, CUMS decreased the sucrose preference in rats significantly (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Compared with the CUMS group, FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly increased the sucrose preference (P &lt; 0.01, Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Forced Swimming Test (FST) in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In FST, compared with the control group, the duration of immobility in rats with CUMS increased significantly (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Compared with the CUMS group, FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly decreased the duration of immobility (P &lt; 0.05, Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Tail Suspension Test (TST) in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In TST, compared with the control group, the duration of immobility in rats with CUMS increased significantly (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Compared with the CUMS group, FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly decreased the duration of immobility (P &lt; 0.05, Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Open-Field Test (OFT) in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In the OFT, compared with the control group, both the locomotor activity and the rearing counts for 5 min were lower in the rats with CUMS (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The results showed that the rats with CUMS appeared to have depressant-like behavioral changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly increased the locomotor activity and the rearing counts (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01, Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>CORT, CRH, and ACTH Contents in Plasma and Hypothalamus in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 2, CUMS significantly increased the contents of CORT, CRH, and ACTH in plasma in rats (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Compared with the control group, the contents of CRH and ACTH in hypothalamus in rats with CUMS were also higher (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Compared with the CUMS group, FA at 0.172 g/kg, FB at 3.608 g/kg, and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly decreased the CORT, CRH, and ACTH contents in plasma and hypothalamus (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>AVP Contents in Plasma and Hypothalamus in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 3, CUMS significantly increased the AVP contents both in hypothalamus and in plasma (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The AVP contents could be significantly decreased in both hypothalamus and plasma by FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Monoamine Neurotransmitters Contents in Hippocampus in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 4 and Figures 6 and 7, compared with the control group, CUMS markedly decreased the contents of 5-HT and DA (P &lt; 0.01) and increased the NE content in hippocampus (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg) significantly increased the contents of 5-HT and DA and decreased the content of NE in hippocampus (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>As a positive control, IMI (20 mg/kg) could increase the 5-HT content and decrease the NE content in hippocampus (P &lt; 0.01) but had no effect on DA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>As a metabolite of serotonin, the ratio of 5-HIAA/5-HT could be used as an index for the turnover of 5-HT [15, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Here, the ratio of 5-HIAA/5-HT was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The amount of 5-HIAA was not altered in hippocampus of rat with CUMS (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>FB (3.608 g/kg) as well as IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly elevated the amount of 5-HIAA (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The ratio of 5-HIAA/5-HT (P &lt; 0.05) was significantly increased by CUMS, which could be reversed by FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Amino Acid Neurotransmitters Contents in Hippocampus in Each Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Compared with the control group, the contents of Glu and Asp in hippocampus were significantly higher (P &lt; 0.01), while the GABA and Tau contents were significantly lower (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg) significantly decreased the contents of Glu and Asp in the hippocampus (P &lt; 0.05 or P &lt; 0.01, Figure 8) but had no effects on GABA and Tau. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Traditional Chinese medicine has offered a possible therapy for the treatment of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>DZXYS, an ancient Chinese herbal decoction, has been used in Chinese medicinal herbal mixture for antidepression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>However, its action mechanism has not been revealed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we provided different lines of evidence to support the antidepression role of DZXYS in CUMS rat model system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The pathogenesis of depression model established by using stress factors is more consistent with that of depression in human beings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The symptoms such as reduced activity, decreased exploratory behavior, and reduced sucrose preference appear in stressed animals, which are similar to the changes of behavior and the loss of interest or pleasure in the clinical diagnosis of depression [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The CUMS model of depression is accepted as a valuable method for evaluating antidepressant effects in animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In the present study, FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg) prepared from DZXYS exhibited a significant increase of sucrose preference in the rats with CUMS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The FST, TST, and OFT are the most widely used as behavioral tools for assessing antidepressant activity [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Characteristic of rat behaviors scored in both tests is termed immobility, which reflects behavioral despair as seen in human depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The duration of immobility time in rats that are trapped and forced to swim is closely related to helplessness [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>It was observed from our results that there was significant prolongation of immobility time in these groups after modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The two fractions at 0.172 g/kg and 3.608 g/kg, respectively, could significantly decrease the duration of immobility both in FST and in TST and significantly increase the locomotor activity in OFT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>These results may further confirm that the DZXYS has an antidepressant activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The nervous system and the endocrine system are closely related, which constitute a complete network to maintain homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>HPA axis activation and the resulting increase in glucocorticoid (GC) secretion are the two most important features of the stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>When in stress state, the hypothalamus releases CRH and AVP in response to a stressor, which in turn activate the secretion of ACTH from the pituitary, which finally stimulates the secretion of cortisol (in humans) or CORT (in rodents) from the adrenal cortex [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>From the actual situation of human depression, stressful life events play an important role in depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Stressor or stressful environment usually precedes depressive symptoms, which leads to neurobiochemical changes associated with depression [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Since the 1970s, people have found that the HPA axis is involved in the pathological mechanism of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Many studies suggested that HPA axis activation results in some of the symptoms and signs in depression [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it has been found that the damage of HPA axis is more severe in patients with refractory depression [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Hyperactivity of HPA axis often occurs in both depressed patients and animal models, which is mainly presented as hypersecreted CRH and higher contents of ACTH and GC [24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Combined with receptors in multiple target tissues (including HPA axis), GC could exert physiological effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>When in state of stress, GC is hypersecreted and then combined with glucocorticoid receptor (GR), thereby inhibiting the hypothalamus to secrete CRF and AVP by negative feedback to restore the hyperactivated HPA axis to the basal level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, chronic stress could result in the state of persistent hyperactivity of the HPA axis; excessive GC constantly stimulates GR, which leads to the injury of hippocampal neurons and the dysfunction of emotion regulation center, and then induces depression [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>As observed in our experiment, the CUMS could significantly increase the contents of CORT, CRH, and ACTH in both plasma and hypothalamus in rats, accompanied by the depressive-like behavioral alterations; thus, we confirmed that HPA axis hyperactivity is related to the pathogenesis of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Results from the present study demonstrated that FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg) prepared from DZXYS could significantly decrease the CORT, CRH, and ACTH contents in plasma and hypothalamus, which suggested that antidepressant effects exerted by DZXYS were partly due to inhibiting the hyperactivity of the HPA axis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Some previous studies have shown that there are significant increases of AVP neurons expression and AVP level in the paraventricular nucleus, AVP reactivity in the pituitary, and AVP mRNA expression in the supraoptic nucleus in depressed patients [27, 28], which also suggests that AVP changes in the paraventricular nucleus and supraoptic nucleus may be the basis for the onset of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In addition, AVP level in the plasma in depressed patients is higher than that in the healthy control group, which is related to the severity of the disease [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>AVP, a nonapeptide synthesized in hypothalamic nuclei, is critical for the regulation of the activity of the HPA axis representing a major component of the stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>CRH and AVP act synergistically in bringing about ACTH release from the corticotropes of the anterior pituitary, which in turn stimulates cortisol output from the adrenal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>AVP is involved in the pathogenesis of depression by regulating the HPA axis function [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>In order to further explore the effect of DZXYS on HPA axis, the levels of AVP in plasma and hypothalamus were measured in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that, in rats with CUMS, AVP levels significantly increased in plasma and hypothalamus, which could be significantly reversed by the treatment of FA (0.172 g/kg), FB (3.608 g/kg), and IMI (20 mg/kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Combined with the results of HPA axis determination in our study, it suggested that DZXYS could regulate the HPA axis by acting on the AVP to exert antidepressant effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>As a significant contribution to depression, “monoamine hypothesis” has been proposed in the 20th century, thereby setting up the foundation for today's antidepressant treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Monoamine neurotransmitters, such as 5-HT, DA, and NE, are the important bioactive substances in central nervous system which participate in many physiological activities of the body, including emotion, learning, and memory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>NE plays an important role in maintaining arousal and is involved in the brain reward system and learning and memory function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The concentration of NE in the hypothalamus is significantly decreased, which suggests that the dysfunction of central NE is related to depression [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Dysfunction of 5-HT is related to depressed mood, anxiety, inhibition of movement, loss of appetite, sleep disorders, circadian rhythm disorders, and so on in depression [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Dopamine (DA) is involved in the regulation of motivation, volition, interest/pleasure, and attention/concentration, all of which are likely to be impaired in depressed patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Several previous reports have suggested that depression may often be accompanied by a relative hypodopaminergic state [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>According to the “monoamine hypothesis,” the decreased releasing and lower contents in the synapse of 5-HT, DA, or NE in central nervous system are involved in pathogenesis of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is well known that many antidepressant drugs currently in use exert effects by regulating the reuptake and metabolic balance of monoamine neurotransmitters [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Our experimental results showed that the 5-HT and DA contents significantly decreased, while the NE content and the ratio of 5-HIAA/5-HT significantly increased in hippocampus in rats, accompanied by the depressive-like behavioral alterations, which confirm that the dysfunction of monoamine neurotransmitters plays an important role in the pathogenesis of depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Amino acid neurotransmitters can be divided into two types of excitatory amino acid and inhibitory amino acid; the former includes Glu and Asp, while GABA and Tau belong to the latter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Some of the studies, whether in rodent models of depression or in depressed patients, indicate that the increase of the Glu concentration is closely related to depression [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>As an important inhibitory neurotransmitter in the brain, GABA decreases significantly in the patients of depression [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the change of the ratio of excitatory/inhibitory amino acid in the brain has an important influence on the incidence of depression [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we found that the contents of Glu and Asp significantly increased, while the GABA and Tau contents decreased in hippocampus in depressed rats; it is suggested that CUMS could lead to the imbalance of excitatory/inhibitory amino acids in the brain, which may account for the mechanism underlying the behavioral changes in rats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In the rat and other mammalian species, including human beings, HPA axis and neurotransmitters system are closely interacted in central nervous system (CNS) (particularly in hippocampus) and greatly involved in stress related disorder [38, 39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Under the chronic stress, as high concentration of GC could induce the liver to produce tryptophan pyrrole enzyme, it could degrade the tryptophan in the blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Tryptophan is the precursor of 5-HT and its reduction could lead to synthesis of 5-HT and so lead to 5-HT content decrease in the brain, thus causing depressive symptoms [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In a stress state, HPA axis function becomes hyperactive and 5-HT synthesis significantly decreases as a result of insufficient tryptophan transported into the CNS [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Moreover, high concentration of GC can make 5-HT transporter (5-HTT) expression increase in hippocampus, amygdala, dorsal raphe nucleus, and other brain areas by GR dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The increased 5-HTT will increase the reuptake of 5-HT in synaptic cleft, which aggravates the decrease of 5-HT concentration and the severity of the symptoms in depressed patients [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Stress can affect the excitability of neurons of locus coeruleus (LC), raphe nucleus, and substantia nigra by HPA axis and 5-HT and NE/DA play an important role in the change of emotion and mood [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In the study of social stress in mice, by using the intracellular recording technique in vitro, it is found that CRH can directly activate noradrenergic neurons of the LC, thus resulting in the increase of NE in the brain [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In addition, some of the studies indicate that 5-HT, DA, and NE can stimulate the hypothalamus to secret CRH, which suggest that a positive feedback neural circuit exists between hypothalamic neurons and neurons secreting 5-HT, DA, and NE [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>In chronic stress, high GC concentration may increase the releasing of excitatory amino acid from the synaptic vesicle of the glutamatergic nerve endings and inhibit its reuptake at the same time, which causes the persistent increase of excitatory amino acid [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The accumulation of Glu can cause hippocampal toxicity, and the high level of extracellular Glu may in turn make the HPA axis more hyperactive to secrete more GC [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Glu directly injected into paraventricular nucleus (PVN) in hypothalamus could accelerate the release of ACTH [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>GABA could inhibit the releasing of ACTH, CORT, and CRH in hypothalamus and reregulate the hyperactivity of HPA axis; Tau, as an inhibitory amino acid, has the synergistic action with GABA to exert the effect on inhibiting the activation of HPA axis [49, 50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Our data indicated that FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg) significantly increased the 5-HT and DA contents and decreased the NE content in the hippocampus; meanwhile, the ratio of 5-HIAA/5-HT in rats with CUMS could be reversed by FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg), which may account for primary monoamine neurotransmitters regulating mechanism underlying DZXYS antidepressant effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we found that although having no effects on GABA and Tau, FA (0.172 g/kg) and FB (3.608 g/kg) significantly decreased the contents of Glu and Asp in hippocampus, which suggested that DZXYS could reduce the excitatory toxicity caused by the accumulation of Glu and Asp in hippocampus in depressed rats, partly regulating the imbalance of the ratio of excitatory/inhibitory amino acid that may be involved in its antidepressant effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>There is a close relationship between HAP and neurotransmitters in regulating emotion and behavior in depression [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>As observed in our experiment, it could be speculated that the amelioration produced by DZXYS on the neurotransmitter system may be associated with its effect on HPA axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>However, the cellular and molecular biological mechanism of exerting regulating effect of DZXYS between the HPA axis and neurotransmitters remains to be further studied in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, in the present study, the antidepressant effects of two fractions (petroleum ether soluble fraction, FA, and water-EtOH soluble fraction, FB) prepared from DZXYS were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrated that DZXYS could ameliorate the depression-like behavior in chronic stress model of rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms of action of DZXYS might be accounted for by inhibiting hyperactivity of HPA axis and modulating monoamine and amino acid neurotransmitters in the hippocampus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Thus, we confirmed that DZXYS has the potential to be a beneficial remedy for the treatment of depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Because of multiple using of plants in a traditional herbal medicine and the complexity of the pathological mechanism of depression, it is undoubted that there exist more other active fractions from DZXYS and further regulatory mechanisms of DZXYS in antidepression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>These works are currently being conducted in our laboratory. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (no. 30500660) and by the New Century Outstanding Talent Support Project of National Ministry of Education (no. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>NCET-05-0750). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interests.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>1KnolM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>J.TwiskJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>R.BeekmanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>F.HeineR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>J.SnoekF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>J.PouwerF.Depression as a risk factor for the onset of type 2 diabetes mellitus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysisDiabetologia200649583784510.1007/s00125-006-0159-x2-s2.0-3364642331716520921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>2ChenK.HuangS.-C.CaiS.-L.HaoW.New advances in the biological basis of depression and new targets for antidepressant treatmentJournal of Clinical Psychiatry2015253208210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>3LiuJ.-M.ShiF.LvY.-N.Advances in the study of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis in the role of antidepression drugsHerald of Medicine20133215659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>4LuoH.-C.QianR.-Q.ZhaoX.-Y.Clinical observation on effect of danzhi xiaoyao powder in treating depressionChinese Journal of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine20062632122142-s2.0-3454771569916613263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>5LiL.-J.The effect of Danzhi Xiaoyao powder combined with escitalopram on the general recovery in patients with depression after ischemic strokeChinese Journal of Practical Nervous Disease2015182168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>6WillnerP.Validity, reliability and utility of the chronic mild stress model of depression: a 10-year review and evaluationPsychopharmacology1997134431932910.1007/s0021300504562-s2.0-00314403259452163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>7ZhuK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Y.MaoQ.-Q.IpS.-P.A standardized chinese herbal decoction, kai-xin-san, restores decreased levels of neurotransmitters and neurotrophic factors in the brain of chronic stress-induced depressive ratsEvidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine201220121314925610.1155/2012/1492562-s2.0-84866165011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>8WuL.-L.LiuY.ChenQ.-H.YanC.Effects of timeshare administration of Jiaweisinisan on biological rhythm of rats with chronic stressChinese Pharmacological Bulletin201430686787410.3969/j.issn.1001-1978.2014.06.0282-s2.0-84903776434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>9PorsoltR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>D.BertinA.JalfreM.Behavioral despair in mice: a primary screening Test for antidepressantsArchives Internationales de Pharmacodynamie et de Therapie197722923273362-s2.0-0017651126596982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>10ZomkowskiA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>E.SantosA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>S.RodriguesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>S.Evidence for the involvement of the opioid system in the agmatine antidepressant-like effect in the forced swimming testNeuroscience Letters2005381327928310.1016/j.neulet.2005.02.0262-s2.0-1934437568515896484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>11SteruL.ChermatR.ThierryB.SimonP.The tail suspension test: a new method for screening antidepressants in micePsychopharmacology198585336737010.1007/bf004282032-s2.0-00219904913923523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>12ArcherJ.Tests for emotionality in rats and mice: a reviewAnimal Behaviour197321220523510.1016/s0003-3472(73)80065-x2-s2.0-00158373384578750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>13YanC.XuZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>W.LiY.Comparative study on effect of liver-regulating, kidney-tonifying and spleen-invigorating recipes on monoamine neurotransmitter in plasma and hypothalamus of rats with chronic psychological stressChinese Journal of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine20022212925928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>14YanC.WuL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>L.XuZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>W.ShiY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>F.PanY.Effect of Jiaweisinisan on the levels of some aminoacids in hippocampus of rats with chronic stressChinese Journal of Pathophysiology2005211020322034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>15CommissiongJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>W.Monoamine metabolites: their relationship and lack of relationship to monoaminergic neuronal activityBiochemical Pharmacology19853481127113110.1016/0006-2952(85)90484-82-s2.0-00218338922581578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>16SchwartingR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>W.HustonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>P.Behavioral concomitants of regional changes in the brain's biogenic amines after apomorphine and amphetaminePharmacology, Biochemistry and Behavior199241467568210.1016/0091-3057(92)90211-W2-s2.0-0026586730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>17ChenJ.HuangH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>P.Stress induced depression and monoaminergic system HomeostasisJournal of Biology20133017881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>18CryanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>F.MarkouA.LuckiI.Assessing antidepressant activity in rodents: recent developments and future needsTrends in Pharmacological Sciences200223523824510.1016/s0165-6147(02)02017-52-s2.0-003657022212008002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>19CryanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>F.MombereauC.VassoutA.The tail suspension test as a model for assessing antidepressant activity: review of pharmacological and genetic studies in miceNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews2005294-557162510.1016/j.neubiorev.2005.03.0092-s2.0-1994438020015890404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>20ChenL.ChenM.WangF.Antidepressant-like effects of shuyusan in rats exposed to chronic stress: effects on hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal functionEvidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine20122012994084610.1155/2012/9408462-s2.0-84867799875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>21HolsenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>M.LancasterK.KlibanskiA.HPA-axis hormone modulation of stress response circuitry activity in women with remitted major depressionNeuroscience201325073374210.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.07.0422-s2.0-8489736424123891965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>22HeuserI.The hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal system in depressionPharmacopsychiatry1998311101310.1055/s-2007-9792882-s2.0-00316129079524978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>23FraserS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>A.KroenkeK.CallahanC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>M.HuiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>L.WilliamsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>W.Jr.UnützerJ.Low yield of thyroid-stimulating hormone testing in elderly patients with depressionGeneral Hospital Psychiatry200426430230910.1016/j.genhosppsych.2004.03.0072-s2.0-324266278215234826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>24ParianteC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>M.LightmanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>L.The HPA axis in major depression: classical theories and new developmentsTrends in Neurosciences200831946446810.1016/j.tins.2008.06.0062-s2.0-5054909288518675469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>25Martínez-MotaL.Cruz-MartínezJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>J.Márquez-BaltazarS.Fernández-GuastiA.Estrogens participate in the antidepressant-like effect of desipramine and fluoxetine in male ratsPharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior200888333234010.1016/j.pbb.2007.09.0032-s2.0-36248967586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>26CowenP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>J.Not fade away: the HPA axis and depressionPsychological Medicine20104011410.1017/s00332917090055582-s2.0-7664914479719335939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>27StemmelinJ.LukovicL.SalomeN.GriebelG.Evidence that the lateral septum is involved in the antidepressant-like effects of the vasopressin V1b receptor antagonist, SSR149415Neuropsychopharmacology2005301354210.1038/sj.npp.13005622-s2.0-1114431676615367924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>28BrunnerJ.KeckM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>E.LandgrafR.UhrM.NamendorfC.BronischT.Vasopressin in CSF and plasma in depressed suicide attempters: preliminary resultsEuropean Neuropsychopharmacology200212548949410.1016/s0924-977x(02)00071-82-s2.0-003678887012208567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>29GoekoopJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>G.De WinterR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>P.WolterbeekR.WiegantV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>M.Support for two increased vasopressinergic activities in depression at large and the differential effect of antidepressant treatmentJournal of Psychopharmacology201125101304131210.1177/02698811103725492-s2.0-7995512226120624797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>30DinanT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>G.ScottL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>V.Anatomy of melancholia: focus on hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis overactivity and the role of vasopressinJournal of Anatomy2005207325926410.1111/j.1469-7580.2005.00443.x2-s2.0-2494457183816185250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>31RootD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>H.HoffmanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>F.GoodC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>H.Norepinephrine activates dopamine d4 receptors in the rat lateral habenulaJournal of Neuroscience20153583460346910.1523/JNEUROSCI.4525-13.20152-s2.0-8492332799125716845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>32GodaR.OtsukaT.IwamotoA.Serotonin levels in the dorsal raphe nuclei of both chipmunks and mice are enhanced by long photoperiod, but brain dopamine level response to photoperiod is species-specificNeuroscience Letters20155939510010.1016/j.neulet.2015.03.0352-s2.0-8492525081725797183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>33TakamuraN.NakagawaS.MasudaT.The effect of dopamine on adult hippocampal neurogenesisProgress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry20145011612410.1016/j.pnpbp.2013.12.0112-s2.0-8489163856224374069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>34BertonO.NestlerE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>J.New approaches to antidepressant drug discovery: beyond monoaminesNature Reviews Neuroscience20067213715110.1038/nrn18462-s2.0-3144444170116429123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>35SanacoraG.TreccaniG.PopoliM.Towards a glutamate hypothesis of depression: an emerging frontier of neuropsychopharmacology for mood disordersNeuropharmacology2012621637710.1016/j.neuropharm.2011.07.0362-s2.0-8005411623821827775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>36ZhaoX.WangC.ZhangJ.-F.Chronic curcumin treatment normalizes depression-like behaviors in mice with mononeuropathy: involvement of supraspinal serotonergic system and GABAA receptorPsychopharmacology2014231102171218710.1007/s00213-013-3368-22-s2.0-8490087260424297305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>37SanacoraG.GueorguievaR.EppersonC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>N.Subtype-specific alterations of γ-aminobutyric acid and glutamate in patients with major depressionArchives of General Psychiatry200461770571310.1001/archpsyc.61.7.7052-s2.0-304269671515237082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>38CubałaW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>J.LandowskiJ.Serotoninergic system and limbic-hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis (LHPA axis) in depressionPsychiatria Polska20064034154302-s2.0-3374742213017037809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>39LanfumeyL.MongeauR.Cohen-SalmonC.HamonM.Corticosteroid-serotonin interactions in the neurobiological mechanisms of stress-related disordersNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews20083261174118410.1016/j.neubiorev.2008.04.0062-s2.0-4584915003218534678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>40BardenN.Implication of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis in the physiopathology of depressionJournal of Psychiatry and Neuroscience20042931851932-s2.0-304266211815173895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>41LaiC.-H.WuY.-T.Duloxetine's modest short-term influences in subcortical structures of first episode drug-naïve patients with major depressive disorder and panic disorderPsychiatry Research - Neuroimaging2011194215716210.1016/j.pscychresns.2011.03.0112-s2.0-8005407628121820879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>42ZhangJ.FanY.LiY.ZhuH.WangL.ZhuM.-Y.Chronic social defeat up-regulates expression of the serotonin transporter in rat dorsal raphe nucleus and projection regions in a glucocorticoid-dependent mannerJournal of Neurochemistry201212361054106810.1111/jnc.120552-s2.0-8487058118223061525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>43De MiguelZ.VegasO.GarmendiaL.ArregiA.BeitiaG.AzpirozA.Behavioral coping strategies in response to social stress are associated with distinct neuroendocrine, monoaminergic and immune response profiles in miceBehavioural Brain Research2011225255456110.1016/j.bbr.2011.08.0112-s2.0-8005296432421864582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>44JedemaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>P.GraceA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>A.Corticotropin-releasing hormone directly activates noradrenergic neurons of the locus ceruleus recorded in vitroThe Journal of Neuroscience200424439703971310.1523/jneurosci.2830-04.20042-s2.0-744423304515509759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>45CalogeroA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>E.BernardiniR.GoldP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>W.ChrousosG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>P.Regulation of rat hypothalamic corticotropin-releasing hormone secretion in vitro: potential clinical implicationsAdvances in Experimental Medicine and Biology198824516718110.1007/978-1-4899-2064-5_132-s2.0-00242251512906518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>46MagariñosA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>M.McEwenB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>S.FlüggeG.FuchsE.Chronic psychosocial stress causes apical dendritic atrophy of hippocampal CA3 pyramidal neurons in subordinate tree shrewsThe Journal of Neuroscience19961610353435402-s2.0-00299881918627386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>47CompèreV.LiS.LeprinceJ.TononM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>C.VaudryH.PelletierG.In vivo action of a new octadecaneuropeptide antagonist on neuropeptide Y and corticotropin-releasing hormone mRNA levels in ratMolecular Brain Research2005141215616010.1016/j.molbrainres.2005.08.0122-s2.0-2774458271116154662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>48RaberJ.Detrimental effects of chronic hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis activation: from obesity to memory deficitsMolecular Neurobiology199818112210.1007/BF027414572-s2.0-00317241369824846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>49StrousR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>D.MaayanR.WeizmanA.The relevance of neurosteroids to clinical psychiatry: from the laboratory to the bedsideEuropean Neuropsychopharmacology200616315516910.1016/j.euroneuro.2005.09.0052-s2.0-3364482640916257183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>50SingewaldN.ZhouG.-Y.SchneiderC.Release of excitatory and inhibitory amino acids from the locus coeruleus of conscious rats by cardiovascular stimuli and various forms of acute stressBrain Research19957041425010.1016/0006-8993(95)01102-12-s2.0-00288231348750960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>51HashimotoK.The role of glutamate on the action of antidepressantsProgress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry20113571558156810.1016/j.pnpbp.2010.06.0132-s2.0-7865036996620600468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Schedule of chronic unpredictable mild stress (CUMS) procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The CUMS protocol consisted of the sequential application of a variety of unpredictable mild stressors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>These stressors were randomly scheduled over a one-week period from day 1 to day 7 and repeated for 4 weeks during the entire experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the sucrose consumption in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Each column represents mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.01 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the duration of immobility in FST in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.05 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.05 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the duration of immobility in TST in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.05 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the duration of immobility in OFT in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.05 and ## P &lt; 0.01 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the contents of DA in hippocampus in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.05 and ## P &lt; 0.01 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the contents of NE in hippocampus in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.01 as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>The effect of DZXYS (FA at 0.086 and 0.172 g/kg and FB at 1.804 and 3.608 g/kg, intragastrically) on the contents of Glu, Asp, GABA, and Tau in hippocampus in rats with chronic unpredictable mild stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>IMI at daily dosage of 20 mg/kg was set as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± SD, n = 10. ∗ P &lt; 0.05 and ∗∗ P &lt; 0.01 as compared with control group; # P &lt; 0.05 and ## P &lt; 0.01, as compared with CUMS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2016-6784689.008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Different components in the formula of DZXYS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Pharmaceutical name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Family name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Plant part </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Chinese name </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Radix Bupleuri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Umbelliferae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Root </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Chai hu </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Paeoniae Radix Alba </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Ranunculaceae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Root </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Bai shao </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Angelica sinensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Umbelliferae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Root </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Dang gui </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Bighead atractylodes rhizome </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Compositae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Rhizoma </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Bai zhu </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Poria cocos </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Polyporaceae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Sclerotium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Fu ling </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Bark of tree peony root </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Ranunculaceae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Root-bark </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Mu dan pi </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Fructus Gardeniae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Rubiaceae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Fruit </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Zhi zi </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Mentha haplocalyx </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Lamiaceae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Leaf </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Bo he </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Licorice </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Leguminosae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Root </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Gan cao </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>The contents of CORT, CRH, and ACTH in plasma and hypothalamus in each group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Dose </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>CORT </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>CRH </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>ACTH </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Plasma (ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Plasma (ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Hypothalamus (ng/g) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Plasma (ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Hypothalamus (ng/g) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain> 12.60 ± 6.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain> 3.31 ± 0.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain> 20.65 ± 12.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain> 42.11 ± 19.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain> 19.65 ± 8.97 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>CUMS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain> 22.69 ± 13.49∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain> 7.38 ± 1.78∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain> 36.74 ± 8.73∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain> 51.44 ± 25.80∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain> 22.79 ± 7.33∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>FA (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>0.086 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain> 22.32 ± 13.31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain> 7.37 ± 1.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain> 35.35 ± 8.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain> 50.56 ± 24.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain> 22.42 ± 7.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>0.172 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain> 14.74 ± 10.30## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain> 5.33 ± 0.79# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain> 23.02 ± 12.8## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain> 46.83 ± 23.32## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain> 20.83 ± 6.92# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>FB (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>1.804 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain> 20.00 ± 6.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain> 7.25 ± 1.77 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> 33.36 ± 10.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain> 51.32 ± 10.28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain> 22.26 ± 9.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>3.608 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain> 10.91 ± 3.30## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain> 3.95 ± 0.12## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain> 16.04 ± 9.34## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain> 44.47 ± 20.31# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain> 20.59 ± 6.88# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>IMI (mg/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain> 10.23 ± 3.21## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain> 3.67 ± 0.13## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain> 15.44 ± 9.02## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain> 42.26 ± 20.01## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain> 19.13 ± 6.76## </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 10). <sup><italic>∗</italic></sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, as compared with control group. <sup>#</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <sup>##</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, as compared with CUMS group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>The AVP contents in plasma and hypothalamus in each group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Dose </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>AVP </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Plasma (pg/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Hypothalamus (pg/mg) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain> 14.70 ± 4.80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain> 58.50 ± 17.80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>CUMS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain> 25.20 ± 7.30∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain> 309.20 ± 70.41∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>FA (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>0.086 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain> 24.23 ± 7.12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain> 306.20 ± 70.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>0.172 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain> 12.60 ± 3.20# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain> 267.40 ± 58.60# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>FB (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>1.804 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain> 23.74 ± 7.10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain> 301.60 ± 70.70 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>3.608 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain> 12.30 ± 3.40## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain> 173.20 ± 20.90## </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>IMI (mg/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain> 11.21 ± 3.12## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain> 168.53 ± 20.11## </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 10). <sup><italic>∗</italic></sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, as compared with control group. <sup>#</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <sup>##</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, as compared with CUMS group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>The contents of 5-HT, 5-HIAA, and 5-HIAA/5-HT ratio in hippocampus in each group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Dose </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>5-HT (ng/g wet tissue) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>5-HIAA (ng/g wet tissue) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>5-HIAA/5-HT </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain> 428.3 ± 171.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain> 376.3 ± 210.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain> 1.04 ± 0.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>CUMS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain> 213.7 ± 142.4∗∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain> 387.6 ± 146.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain> 1.62 ± 0.82∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>FA (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>0.086 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain> 262.5 ± 145.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain> 370.6 ± 107.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain> 1.58 ± 0.83 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>0.172 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain> 447.8 ± 236.7# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain> 436.8 ± 311.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain> 1.02 ± 0.46# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>FB (g/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>1.804 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain> 301.2 ± 146.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain> 378.7 ± 118.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain> 1.57 ± 0.79 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>3.608 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain> 468.2 ± 139.3## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain> 487.2 ± 83.2# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain> 0.97 ± 0.56# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>IMI (mg/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain> 479.5 ± 148.7## </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain> 509.3 ± 84.7# </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain> 1.01 ± 0.33# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 10). <sup><italic>∗</italic></sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <sup><italic>∗∗</italic></sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, as compared with control group. <sup>#</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <sup>##</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, as compared with CUMS group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
