<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1750-1172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4167147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25208612</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">119</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-014-0119-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Sengers syndrome: six novel AGK mutations in seven new families and review of the phenotypic and mutational spectrum of 29 patients </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Haghighi</surname><given-names>Alireza</given-names></name><address><email>haghighi@genetics.med.harvard.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haack</surname><given-names>Tobias B</given-names></name><address><email>tobias.haack@helmholtz-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Atiq</surname><given-names>Mehnaz</given-names></name><address><email>mehnaz.atiq@aku.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mottaghi</surname><given-names>Hassan</given-names></name><address><email>Mottaghih@mums.ac.ir</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haghighi-Kakhki</surname><given-names>Hamidreza</given-names></name><address><email>hamidreza_haghighik@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>Rani A</given-names></name><address><email>drraniabashir@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahting</surname><given-names>Uwe</given-names></name><address><email>Uwe.Ahting@helmholtz-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feichtinger</surname><given-names>René G</given-names></name><address><email>r.feichtinger@salk.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>Johannes A</given-names></name><address><email>H.Mayr@salk.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rötig</surname><given-names>Agnès</given-names></name><address><email>agnes.rotig@inserm.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lebre</surname><given-names>Anne-Sophie</given-names></name><address><email>aslebre@chu-reims.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klopstock</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><address><email>Thomas.Klopstock@med.uni-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dworschak</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><address><email>adworschak@ukaachen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pulido</surname><given-names>Nathan</given-names></name><address><email>nathanpulido@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff14"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>Mahmood A</given-names></name><address><email>MSaeed@kockw.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saleh-Gohari</surname><given-names>Nasrollah</given-names></name><address><email>salehgohari@yahoo.co.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff15"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holzerova</surname><given-names>Eliska</given-names></name><address><email>eliska.holzerova@helmholtz-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chinnery</surname><given-names>Patrick F</given-names></name><address><email>patrick.chinnery@newcastle.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff16"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Robert W</given-names></name><address><email>robert.taylor@newcastle.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Prokisch</surname><given-names>Holger</given-names></name><address><email>prokisch@helmholtz-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Genetics, Harvard Medical School, 77 Ave Louis Pasteur, Boston, MA 02115 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Medicine and the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, MA USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Institute of Human Genetics, Helmholtz Zentrum München, Neuherberg, München, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Institute of Human Genetics, Technische Universität München, Trogerstrasse 22, München, 81675 Germany </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Department of Pediatrics, Aga Khan University, Karachi, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Department of Pediatrics, Imam Reza Hospital, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label/>Faculty of Medicine, Mashhad Azad University, Mashhad, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label/>Department of Paediatrics and Neonatology, Ahmadi Hospital, Kuwait Oil Company, Al Ahmadi, Kuwait </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label/>Department of Paediatrics, Paracelsus Medical University, Salzburg, Austria </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label/>Inserm UMR 1163, Imagine Institute, Paris Descartes University, Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label/>Department of Genetics, Hôpital Necker-Enfants Malades, Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff12"><label/>Department of Neurology, Friedrich-Baur-Institute, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Munich, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff13"><label/>Department of Pediatric Cardiology, University Hospital, Aachen University of Technology, Aachen, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff14"><label/>Pediatric Department, Hospital Dr. Gustavo Fricke, Viña del Mar, Chile </aff><aff id="Aff15"><label/>Department of Genetics, Medical School, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff16"><label/>Wellcome Trust Centre for Mitochondrial Research, Institute of Genetic Medicine, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK </aff><aff id="Aff17"><label/>Wellcome Trust Centre for Mitochondrial Research, Institute of Neuroscience, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>119</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Haghighi et al.; licensee Biomedcentral Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Sengers syndrome is an autosomal recessive condition characterized by congenital cataract, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, skeletal myopathy and lactic acidosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the acylglycerol kinase (AGK) gene have been recently described as the cause of Sengers syndrome in nine families. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We investigated the clinical and molecular features of Sengers syndrome in seven new families; five families with the severe and two with the milder form. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis of AGK revealed compound heterozygous or homozygous predicted loss-of-function mutations in all affected individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A total of eight different disease alleles were identified, of which six were novel, homozygous c.523_524delAT (p.Ile175Tyrfs*2), c.424-1G &gt; A (splice site), c.409C &gt; T (p.Arg137*) and c.877 + 3G &gt; T (splice site), and compound heterozygous c.871C &gt; T (p.Gln291*) and c.1035dup (p.Ile346Tyrfs*39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>All patients displayed perinatal or early-onset cardiomyopathy and cataract, clinical features pathognomonic for Sengers syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Other common findings included blood lactic acidosis and tachydyspnoea while nystagmus, eosinophilia and cervical meningocele were documented in only either one or two cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Deficiency of the adenine nucleotide translocator was found in heart and skeletal muscle biopsies from two patients associated with respiratory chain complex I deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In contrast to previous findings, mitochondrial DNA content was normal in both tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>We compare our findings to those in 21 previously reported AGK mutation-positive Sengers patients, confirming that Sengers syndrome is a clinically recognisable disorder of mitochondrial energy metabolism. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Sengers syndrome</kwd><kwd>AGK</kwd><kwd>Acylglycerol Kinase</kwd><kwd>Mutation</kwd><kwd>Genotype-Phenotype Correlation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Sengers syndrome is a rare autosomal recessive condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It was first described by Sengers and colleagues in 1975 with the clinical features of congenital cataract, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, mitochondrial myopathy and lactic acidosis after exercise [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Two forms of this syndrome have been described, a severe neonatal form that causes infantile death and a more benign form with a longer survival into the fourth decade [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The longer surviving patients had normal developmental milestones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The cause of mortality in Sengers syndrome is heart failure as the result of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Van Ekeren et al. investigated 16 clinically-diagnosed patients with Sengers syndrome in order to describe the course of these two forms [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Although these authors did not observe any histopathologic distinction in muscle or heart samples between the two forms, Perry described 3 cases of neonatal Sengers with significant central nervous system involvement [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The cranial ultrasonography findings in the three siblings included cerebellar hypoplasia and increased echogenicity of the basal ganglia suggestive of calcification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Magnetic resonance imaging demonstrated hypoplasia of both the brainstem and inferior cerebellar vermis, impaired myelination of the cerebral hemispheres and brainstem, and cortical infarction [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These authors suggested that the neonatal form of Sengers syndrome should be described as a mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, because of involvement of the central nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, the genetic cause of the disease in this family has not been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Siriwardena et al. investigated two siblings with Sengers Syndrome and AGK mutations using magnetic resonance imaging and showed cortical infarction, however in a vascular pattern unlike metabolic strokes that do not respect any arterial distribution [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Recently, Mayr et al. investigated Caucasian Sengers patients from Germany, Italy, The Netherlands and Switzerland and, using whole exome sequencing, identified AGK as the disease-causing gene in Sengers syndrome [4]. AGK encodes a mitochondrial transmembrane enzyme, acylglycerol kinase, a multisubstrate lipid with a likely role in cardiolipin biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Acylglycerol kinase catalyzes the formation of phosphatidic acid and lysophosphatidic acid [7] that can participate in phospholipid synthesis or act as signaling molecules regulating a number of cell processes [7–9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Cardiolipin plays an important role in structural maintenance of mitochondria and regulating the permeability of the inner membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Abnormal mitochondrial morphology has been seen in conditions with cardiolipin impairment, like Sengers and Barth syndromes [10–12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Secondary to AGK mutations, a deficiency of the adenine nucleotide translocator and impairment of ATP synthesis has been reported and seems to play a central role in the pathomechanism of Sengers syndrome [4,13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We present the clinical features and molecular basis of Sengers syndrome in seven new families of different ethnic origin, documenting for the first time a molecular study of Sengers syndrome patients of non-Caucasian descent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Patients and families </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>We studied the members of seven families with Sengers syndrome in which patients were diagnosed based on the clinical features and mitochondrial histochemical and biochemical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Informed written consent for clinical and molecular investigation was obtained from all family members or their legal guardians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration. The study was approved by the ethics committee of the Technische Universität München. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All members of families underwent a comprehensive clinical investigation including cardiac, metabolic, neurological, endocrinological, ophthalmological and neuromuscular assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood samples were collected from all family members. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The causal mutation in Case 4 (Table 1) was identified by exome sequencing as described previously [14] and subsequently confirmed by Sanger sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In the other individuals, testing for DNA sequence variations in AGK was done by Sanger sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was amplified using intronic primers and the resulting PCR products were sequenced in both directions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences and PCR conditions are available upon request.Table 1Molecular and Clinical Findings in Patients with AGK Mutations  FEATURES  Sex/consan.  Mutation  Status  Onset of cardio-myopathy  Onset of cataract  Plasma lactic acidosis  Exercise intolerance  Motor develop. delay  Muscle weak.  Muscular hypotonia  Tachydys-pnea  OXPHOS defect  Other clinical features Case-1Male/+c.523_524delAT (p.Ile175Tyrfs*2)¥ Dead 7 m5 m1 m+Feeding difficulty++++Nystagmus, floppy infantCase-2A Male/- (Fm)c.424-1G&gt;A (splicing defect)¥ Dead 10 dBirthBirth+----+-Case-3A Female/- (Fm)c.424-1G&gt;A (splicing defect)¥ Dead 4 mBirthBirth+Feeding difficulty----EosinophiliaCase-4Female/- (Fm)c.409C&gt;T (p.Arg137*)¥ Dead 3 m+++IEsotropia, IUR, feeding problems, MMA elevation in urines (14 , N&gt;8), total and free carnitine elevation in blood, fatty infiltrations in heart biopsyCase-5Male/-c.409C&gt;T (p.Arg137*)¥ Dead 6 mBirthBirth+Feeding difficulty++++IEsotropia, nystagmus, floppy infantCase-6Male/- (Fm)c.871C&gt;T (p.Gln291*), c.1035dup (p.Ile346Tyrfs*39)Alive 3 mBirthBirth+-Mild retardationMildMild+ RSV pneumonia-Case-7Female/-c.297+2T&gt;C (p.Lys75Glnfs*12), c.841C&gt;T (p.Arg281*)Alive 10 yBirthBirth-++++-ICervical meningocele, ragged red fibers (15%), COX-deficient fibres (1-2%)Case-8Male/+c.877+3G&gt;T (splicing defect)¥ Alive 15 y+Birth-++---PC-1 [4]Male/-c.3G&gt;C (p.Met1?), c.517C&gt;T (p.Gln173*)Alive 36 y+3 m+++---Floppy infantPC-2 [4]Male/- (Fm)c.3G&gt;C (p.Met1?), c.672C&gt;A (p.Tyr224*)Alive 35 y+3 mOn exercise++-----PC-3B [4]Male/- (Fm)c.1131+5G&gt;A (splicing defect)¥ Dead 12 y+18 m-+-++-I, II+III, IV, V, PDHc-PC-4B [4]Female/- (Fm)c.1131+5G&gt;A (splicing defect)¥ Alive 10 y+5 m++----I, II+III, IV, V, PDHc-PC-5 [4]Female/+c.1131+5G&gt;A (splicing defect)¥ Alive 41 y+Birth++---VStrokePC-6 [4]Female/-c.221+1G&gt;A (splicing defect), c.1213C&gt;T (p.Gln405*)Alive 12 y+Birth+--+--I, II, III, IV, very high CS-PC-7 [4]Male/- (Fm)c.412C&gt;T (p.Arg138*), c.1137_1143del (p.Gly380Leufs*16)Dead 11 m+BirthOn exercise-Moderate retardation-+--Fatty infiltrations in muscle biopsyPC-8 [4]Female/-c.672C&gt;A (p.Tyr224*), c.870del (p.Gln291Argfs*8)Dead 10 m+4 m+-----I, II, III, IV, V, very high CS-PC-9 [4]Male/-c.101+?_222-?del (ND)¥ Dead 8 m+Birth+-----I, II, III, IV, V, very high CSAxial hypotonia, upper left limbs paresis, seizures, brain ventricles dilationPC-10 [4]Male/-c.306C&gt;T (p.Tyr102*), c.841C&gt;T (p.Arg281*)Dead 18 d+Birth+----+I, II+III, IV, V-PC-11 [16]Female/-c.297+2T&gt;C (p.Lys75Glnfs*12), c.1170T&gt;A (p.Tyr390*)Dead 18 y+&lt;1 year++I, III, IVFatigue, failure to thrive, recurrent headaches, osteopenia and premature ovarian failure, severe mtDNA depletion in skeletal musclePC-12 [16]Female/+c.1131+1G&gt;T (p.Ser350Glufs*19)¥ Dead 4 dBirth+++I, III, IVPulmonary hypertension, marked respiratorydistress, thrombocytopenia, severe mtDNA depletion in skeletal musclePC-13 [6]Female/+c.979A&gt;T (p.Lys327*)¥ Dead 5 mBirthBirth+Upper respiratory tract infectionPC-14 [6]Female/+c.979A&gt;T (p.Lys327*)¥ Dead 12 dBirthBirth+I, I+III, II+III, III, IV, high CSPC-15 [6]Male/+c.979A&gt;T (p.Lys327*)¥ Dead 2 dBirthBirthPC-16 [6]Male/+c.979A&gt;T (p.Lys327*)¥ Dead 18 dBirthBirthPC-17 [6]Male/+c.3G&gt;A (p.Met1?)¥ Dead 6 mBirthBirth+++Cerebellar non-hemorrhagic stroke, ventricular , growth delayfibrillationPC-18 [6]Male/+c.3G&gt;A (p.Met1?)¥ Alive 2 y2 mBirth----Cerebellar non-hemorrhagic stroke, ventricular, modest growth delayfibrillationPC-19 [18]Female/+c.424-3C&gt;G (p.Ala142Thrfs*4)¥ Alive 17 y-Birth------Urine organic acid profile: moderately elevated lactate, 3-hydroxyisovaleric, 3-methylglutaric and 3-methylglutaconic acidsPC-20 [18]Male/+c.424-3C&gt;G (p.Ala142Thrfs*4)¥ Alive 11 y-Birth------Urine organic acid profile showed moderately elevated lactate, 3-hydroxyisovaleric, 3-methylglutaric and 3-methylglutaconic acidsPC-21 [18]Male/+c.424-3C&gt;G (p.Ala142Thrfs*4)¥ Alive 7 y-Birth------Urine organic acid profile showed moderately elevated lactate, 3-hydroxyisovaleric, 3-methylglutaric and 3-methylglutaconic acids SUMMARY  17 M: 12 F/13 consan.  20 homozygous; 19 different mutations  17 †; 16 † &lt;1 y  25/29; 10 at birth  28/29 up to 18 m; 21 at birth  20/27  6/16; + 3 feeding difficulties  10/22  8/23  7/22  7/22  3 only I; 1 only V; 9 combined +: presence of condition, −: absence of condition, unknown when empty.I: complex I, II+III: succinate cytochrome c oxidoreductase, IV: cytochrome c oxidase, V: oligomycin-sensitive ATPase, CS: citrate synthase, OXPHOS: oxidative phosphorylation, PDHc: pyruvate dehydrogenase complex;Fm: familial, ND: not determined;d: day, m: month, y: year; ACases 2 and 3 are siblings; BPC-3 and PC-4 are siblings; ¥Homozygous mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The mtDNA content from 3 patient samples was measured in muscle or heart from three patients with samples available for testing according to published protocol [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis was performed from very small amount of tissue samples from 2 patients, therefore only ANT and respiratory chain complexes I and II were determined as described in [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Biochemical analysis of OXPHOS activity was done in 3 different research centers, where the muscle biopsies were available (case-4, 5, 7 [4]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Clinical investigation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Altogether, we report 8 new cases of Sengers syndrome with predicted loss-of-function mutations in all affected individuals with no hot-spot region in AGK gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Six patients displayed onset of cataract at birth, one in the first month of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Cardiomyopathy occurred at birth in 5 out of 8 cases and in two cases within the first 5 months of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>For one case, the onset of cardiomyopathy remained unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Five patients with severe form or Sengers syndrome died in the first year of life, last patient with severe form is alive with the age of 3 moths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Patients with milder form of disease survived the first decade of their life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Our data underline tachydyspnea and isolated Complex I deficiency as additional phenotypes of Sengers syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Consistently to previous findings, blood lactic acidosis was found as a common feature for all cases with severe form of disease, most with respiratory chain deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Other features like nystagmus, eosinophilia, cervical meningocele, exercise intolerance or motor developmental delay and muscle weakness differ case by case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Specific information are given in the case reports or in the overview Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Family-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The first proband (Case-1, Table 1) was a five months old male child that presented with coughing and respiratory difficulties for one week, reluctance to feed and excessive crying for a few hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>There was no associated fever, vomiting or history of drug intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>He was the first born at term to healthy consanguineous parents from Pakistan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>At birth, the child was diagnosed with bilateral cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Rubella and galactosemia were ruled out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>He underwent cataract surgery uneventfully during the first month of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>He had subsequent admissions for eye examinations under anesthesia and circumcision; both admissions were without complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The child was noticed to sweat and get tired during feeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>His physical growth was normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Motor milestones were delayed and the child was unable to hold his neck. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Family history was significant with neonatal deaths in two paternal uncles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>On admission, he had supraventricular tachycardia with a heart rate of 230 bpm with congestive cardiac failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The respiratory rate was 46/m with acidotic breathing pattern and blood pressure was 80/60 mmHg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The heart sounds were distant and there was no murmur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>He had moderate hepatomegaly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>His eyes were aphakic, pupils being irregular shaped, sluggishly reactive to light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>He also had generalized hypotonia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Electrocardiogram was consistent with supraventricular tachycardia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>This was aborted with cardioversion and a repeat electrocardiogram showed left ventricular hypertrophy and T wave inversion in limb and chest leads (Figure 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Arterial blood gases depicted severe metabolic acidosis (pH 6.9, pCO2 32.6 mmHg, pO2 98 mmHg, HCO3 6 meq/L) and anion gap was 29 meq/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Serum lactate level was 20 mmol/L (normal 0.67-2.67 mmol/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography was consistent with hypertrophic non-obstructive cardiomyopathy (Figure 1b) with a severe global systolic dysfunction (ejection fraction 15%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Moderate mitral and tricuspid valve regurgitation were present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The child was suspected to have Sengers syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A skeletal muscle biopsy taken from gastrocnemius muscle was stained with routine stains and examined under light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Abnormal muscle fibers were found with histiocytic infiltrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Special stains did not show ragged red fibers nor storage cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Cytochrome c oxidase histochemistry and electron microscopy were not available to study abnormal mitochondria.Figure 1 Electrocardiogram, echocardiogram and chest X-ray of a Sengers patient. a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>ECG of Case-1 showing left ventricular hypertrophy and T wave inversion in limb and chest leads. b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>2D echocardiogram of in parasternal long axis projection showing severe left ventricular hypertrophy in (Case-1). c. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Chest X-ray revealing significant cardiomegaly in (Case-3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Family-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The second proband (Case-2, Table 1) was a full term baby boy born to a 29 year old gravida-2 mother by vacuum extraction for fetal decelerations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>His birth weight was 3.28 kg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Apgar score was 5, 8, 8 at 1, 5, 10 minutes, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>There was cord round the neck tight and oligohydramnios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>He responded well to resuscitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The antibodies for toxoplasmosis were negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>A previous sibling (Case-3, Table 1) was a term girl with bilateral congenital cataract and congenital heart disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Her echo showed fenestrated atrial septal defect (ASD) and interventricular septal hypertrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Anticongestive medications were started for the neonate but she died at the age of 4 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>There was an episode of high lactate while the girl was in the neonatal intensive care unit, associated with diarrhea which self-recovered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Parents were non consanguineous, but they hailed from the same village in India. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>At birth, the baby was noted to be hypoperfused, tachypneic and with grade 3/6 pan-systolic murmur over the left sternal edge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Initial blood gas showed a mild metabolic acidosis, which normalized after a normal saline bolus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Chest X-ray showed gross cardiomegaly (Figure 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmology consultation revealed bilateral lamellar cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography (Figure 2) at 48 hours of life revealed moderate secundum ASD (5 mm), pulmonary arterial pressure 80% at the systemic level, moderate right ventricular hypertrophy and right atrial dilatation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The ejection fraction was 54%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>As per the advice of the cardiologist, he was started on oral sildenafil, furosemide and dopamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The tachypnea gradually improved and finally he could be maintained on full feeds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound evaluation of brain and abdomen were normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Repeat echocardiography after 72 hours showed hypertrophic left ventricle with ejection fraction 50% and improvement of pulmonary hypertension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Maintenance digoxin was started along with increasing doses of captopril. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Sildenafil and dopamine were stopped and furosemide and spironolactone were continued. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Basic metabolic work-up showed serum lactate of 14.5 mmol/L, which on repeat was 6 mmol/L and ammonia and blood gas levels were normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>At the age of 10 days, he was irritable, pale and desaturating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>He became bradycardic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Blood gas tests showed severe metabolic acidosis and chest X-ray revealed increasing cardiomegaly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Despite the resuscitative efforts, baby expired.Figure 2 Echocardiography of a Sengers patient. a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>M-Mode of LV in short axis showing dilated LV for age of (Case-3) at 6 days (LVEDD 2.04). b. moderate mitral valve regurgitation with left atrial contraction in systole. c. moderate tricuspid regurgitation with right atrial contraction envelope in systole. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Family-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The proband (Case-4, Table 1) was a girl, the second child from healthy non consanguineous Indian parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>They previously lost a first child at 3 days of life probably due to infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>She was born after an uneventful pregnancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Bilateral cataract was noticed at birth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>When she was 2.5 months old, her severe hypertrophic cardiomyopathy was detected after she collapsed during cataract surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The girl had growth retardation (weight 3.770 g/-1.5SD, head circumference 36 cm/-1.5SD), strabismus and feeding difficulties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>She presented hyperlactatemia and hyperlactaturia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Plasma glutamine, alanine, proline, and free and total carnitine levels were elevated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Methylmalonic acid was raised in urine (14 μmol/mmol creatinine, normal &lt; 8 μmol/mmol). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>An isolated complex I deficiency was found in endomyocardial biopsy, whereas cultured skin fibroblasts showed normal respiratory chain activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A heart biopsy revealed fatty infiltrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>She died at the age of 3 months from heart failure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Family-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The male patient (Case-5, Table 1) was born at term by vaginal delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The newborn was initially in a good condition with a normal Apgar score of 9-10-10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Later on, he started to present symptoms of heart failure with tachypnea and hepatomegaly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography showed profound concentric hypertrophy of the left ventricle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The cavum of the left ventricle was almost completely obstructed but left ventricular outflow tract was well developed and unobstructed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Anticongestive treatment with diuretics was started, but did not improve the condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>He also developed lactic acidosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Physical examination showed muscular hypotonia and dystrophic features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmologic examination showed bilateral cataract that was operated later on. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsy excluded Pompe disease, but showed low activity of mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In the further course, the child developed a mild form of necrotizing enterocolitis with intestinal bleeding and air collection in the portal vein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Antibiotic therapy was started while he was kept on parenteral nutrition for a couple of days that made him clinically more stable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, he was placed on ketogenic diet, riboflavin (40 mg/d) and coenzyme Q 10 (40 mg/d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In addition, propranolol was started because of heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>At the age of two months, the infant was discharged from hospital on parents’ request. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>He passed away three months later, at the age of five months. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Family-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The proband (Case-6, Table 1) was a 3 months boy infant, from Chile, who was admitted because of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) bronchiolitis and pneumonia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>He was born to healthy non-consanguineous parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>On chest radiography, his heart was enlarged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>He was diagnosed with bilateral cataract since birth too. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography revealed non-obstructive hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with poor left ventricular function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>His older brother died at the age of 15 months due to severe heart failure and cardiogenic shock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>He also had hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, bilateral cataract and lactic acidosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Autopsy pathology showed cytosolic granules in heart muscle and liver cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>He also had neurological developmental delay and mild hypotonia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Severe viral respiratory infection was reported in this patient as well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Family-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The patient (Case-7, Table 1) was a 10 year old girl, born to non-consanguineous healthy parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The pregnancy was complicated by early bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The heart abnormality was detected at the 19 week ultrasound scan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>She was born by vaginal delivery and required minimal resuscitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>On physical exam at birth, the absence of a red reflex led to diagnosis of cataract that was operated in infancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>As an infant she was also diagnosed with a cervical meningocele, noted at birth, and underwent a surgical operation within 6 months of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography at the 7 days of age, revealed a hypertensive hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>She walked at 18 months of age and had significant speech and language delay with only minimal vocalization at the age of 2 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>On physical examination at 2 years of age, all growth milestones (height, weight and head circumference) were below 4th centile, she had poor muscle mass and hypotonia but no overt dysmorphic features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>She had normal cognitive functions and later went to normal school. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>She had growth hormone deficiency that was treated by growth hormone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The abnormal clinical findings at the last visit, at the age of 10 years, included exercise intolerance, fatigue, hypotonia, and stable cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsy revealed an isolated complex I deficiency in muscle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Family-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The proband (Case-8, Table 1) was a 15 year old boy, the second child of healthy consanguineous parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Growth retardation, cataract, muscular hypotonia and moderate motor retardation were noted in infancy by the parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Rubella and galactosemia were ruled out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>On physical examination, at 2 years of age, he had bisferiens carotid pulse, grade 2–3/6 systolic murmur, normal S1 and single S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography revealed left and right ventricular outflow tract obstructions, significantly increased left ventricular mass index, biventricular diastolic dysfunction and mitral valve regurgitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Carnitine therapy was initiated for the patient but no clinical improvement was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>His younger brother had also had cataract, cardiomyopathy and metabolic disorder and died at the age of 3 months. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>AGK mutation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Sequencing analysis of AGK identified disease-causing mutation in all patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Molecular analysis of the genomic DNA from Family-1 identified a novel homozygous 2 bp deletion (c.523_524delAT) mutation in the proband, predicting a frameshift (p.Ile175Tyrfs*2) in the translated protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Both parents were confirmed to be heterozygous carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In Family-2, sequencing of their genomic DNA revealed a novel homozygous canonical splice site mutation c.424-1G &gt; A in the proband, affecting exon 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Both parents and a healthy sibling were heterozygous for this mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Molecular study in families 3 and 4 detected a homozygous nonsense mutation, c.409C &gt; T, predicting a premature termination codon at position 137 of AGK, p.Arg137*. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The parents, in both families, were heterozygous for this mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Genetic study of Family-5 identified novel loss-of-function compound heterozygous mutations, a nonsense variant c.871C &gt; T, (p.Gln291*), in exon 12, and a one-nucleotide insertion c.1035dup in exon 14 that is predicted to result in a frameshift (p.Ile346Tyrfs*39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The healthy parents were heterozygous for either of these two mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of the proband in Family-6, identified a heterozygous nonsense mutation c.841C &gt; T (p.Arg281*) in combination with a heterozygous canonical splice site mutation c.297 + 2 T &gt; C that has been shown to cause a shortened transcript with a premature termination codon (p.Lys75Glnfs*12) [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Molecular analysis of Family-7 revealed a homozygous mutation (c.877 + 3G &gt; T) that is likely to affect splicing of exon 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The results of genetic analysis are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 illustrates the localization of identified mutations in the AGK gene.Figure 3 Gene structure of AGK and localization of identified mutations. Boldface type indicates newly reported mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis was performed with the muscle biopsy sample of the patient from Family-4 and a heart biopsy sample of a previously published patient (PC-8, Table 1), diagnosed with combined respiratory chain deficiency [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against the adenine nucleotide translocator revealed a clear decrease in both the heart and the muscle sample (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Complex I was moderately decreased in muscle but severely decreased in the heart sample (Figure 4).Figure 4 Western blot analysis of heart and muscle samples. The blots were decorated with antibodies (all from Mitosciences/Abcam (Eugene, OR, USA)) against adenine nucleotide translocator (ANT), subunit NDUFS4 of complex I, and subunit SDHA of complex II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Intensities were quantified by the Image J software (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) and relative intensities were calculated for the patient sample in each tissue in relation to the two controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>P1stands for PC-8 and P2 stands for Case 5 in the Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Quantification of the mitochondrial DNA copy number </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The relative mitochondrial DNA content in the muscle biopsy of the patient from families 4 and 6 and the heart sample of the previously published patient PC-8 was analyzed by quantitative real time PCR (qRT-PCR) [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A high normal value of 1750 ± 390 copies of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) per nuclear genome (normal range 750-1610) was found in the muscle samples from case 5 and levels within the normal range for case 7 (130% of the mean from controls). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The relative mtDNA content in the heart sample was 4240 ± 730 copies of mtDNA per nuclear genome which is within a range of two controls (1042 and 5131). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Sengers syndrome is caused by mutations in the AGK gene [4], which is located on chromosome 7q34 and consists of 16 exons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>To date, only three studies have investigated families with Sengers syndrome and identified different types of loss-of-function mutations in AGK gene, including start codon mutations (compound heterozygous), nonsense (compound heterozygous), frameshift (compound heterozygous) and splice site mutations (homozygous and compound heterozygous) [4,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>An overview about the clinical, biochemical and genetic findings of all published and recently identified patients is summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>We investigated the clinical features and molecular basis of Sengers syndrome in seven new affected families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We have identified six novel predicted loss-of-function mutations in AGK; homozygous c.523_524delAT (p.Ile175Tyrfs*2), c.424-1G &gt; A (splice site), c.409C &gt; T (p.Arg137*) and c.877 + 3G &gt; T (splice site), and compound heterozygous c.871C &gt; T (p.Gln291*) and c.1035dup (p.Ile346Tyrfs*39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 provides an overview of the known and newly identified mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>To date, less than 10 families with neonatal Sengers syndrome have been reported [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The average survival of the severe form (with onset in the first month of life), in our and previously published cases, was 4.2 months, whereas Mayr et al. reported patients with the milder form of the disease who survived through their 5th decade of life (cases PC-5, PC-1 and PC-2, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Very early mortality (&lt;5 days of life) has also been reported (cases PC-12 and PC-15, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Calvo et al. described truncating AGK mutations in two patients with bilateral cataract, severe myopathy and combined complex I, III and IV deficiency [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The first patient (PC-11, Table 1) was born to unrelated parents and harbored compound heterozygous mutations; a splice site mutation c.297 + 2 T &gt; C (p.Lys75Glnfs*12) resulting in a shortened transcript, and a nonsense mutation c.1170 T &gt; A (p.Tyr390*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Her other clinical features included failure to thrive, fatigue, recurrent headaches, osteopenia and premature ovarian failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>She died at the age of 18 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The second patient (PC-12, Table 1), born to a consanguineous family, was homozygous for a splice site mutation, c.1131 + 1G &gt; T (p.Ser350Glufs*19), that causes a shortened transcript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The infant had severe lactic acidosis (10 –17 mmol/L, normal 0.7–2.0) (John Christodoulou, personal communication) and metabolic acidosis, and died at 4 days of age due to cardiorespiratory collapse [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Tachydyspnoea was a feature which was observed only in severe from of the disease (Table 1), and not in any of patients with the milder form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This feature seems to be correlated with poorer prognosis and survival (average ~ 2.8 months). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The unusual features in our patients were nystagmus (Case-1 and Case-5), eosinophilia (Case-3) and cervical meningocele (Case-7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In addition, esotropia was found in two patients (Case-4 and Case-5) with the c.409C &gt; T (p.Arg137*) mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We did not identify a hot-spot region within the AGK gene showing clustering of mutations; these were equally distributed over the whole gene sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>So far, all AGK mutations associated with Sengers syndrome are predicted to be loss-of-function variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>However, we noted that homozygous AGK nonsense mutations have always resulted in infantile (severe) form of the Sengers syndrome while all patients who survived the first decade harbor at least one splice site variant or a start codon mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In fact, two out of the three oldest patients with survival of &gt;35 years carry the c.3G &gt; C (p.Met1?) mutation in combination with two different stop codon mutations and the third one was homozygous for the splice mutation c.1131 + 5G &gt; A, frequently found in patients from The Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This observation may indicate some AGK activity through residual normal splicing or alternative start codon usage[17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Very recently, Aldahmesh et al. identified a splice site mutation in AGK causing isolated congenital cataract (recessive cataract 38) in a multiplex consanguineous family from Saudi Arabia, thereby extending the mild clinical spectrum associated with AGK mutations to a non-syndromic form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Urine organic acid profile showed moderately elevated lactate, 3-hydroxyisovaleric, 3-methylglutaric and 3-methylglutaconic acids (Fowzan Alkuraya, personal communication) and interestingly, cardiology evaluation of the affected family members revealed normal results (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The identified mutation, c.424-3C &gt; G, is predicted to lead to aberrant splicing and predicted premature truncation, p.Ala142Thrfs*4 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>It can be speculated therefore that a small proportion of the normally spliced transcript can still be formed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Although the role of AGK mutations in cataractogenesis is unclear, some authors have raised the hypothesis that an impairment of lenticular lipid composition may be of pathophysiological significance in the etiology [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In our and previously published cases with the severe form of Sengers syndrome, cataract was present at birth or detected shortly thereafter, whereas in milder form, it can remain undiagnosed for several months (18 months of age in PC-3, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Several patients (Case-7, Case-8, PC-3 and PC-18, Table 1) with a milder form of Sengers syndrome did not develop lactic acidosis, whereas in the severe form, none of the patients had normal levels of lactic acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Siriwardena et al. reported a Sengers patient with the start codon mutation, p.Met1?, who interestingly, at the age of 3 years, did not have skeletal myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>He was able to run and play without any limitation and his creatine phosphokinase levels were also normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>His skeletal muscles biopsy, at the age of 4 months, did not show presence of COX negative fibers [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>However, his sibling, obviously with the same AGK mutation, was affected with the severe form of the diseases and died at the age of 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>These observations suggest that myopathy can develop independent from lactic acidosis and that the absence of lactic acidosis favors a better prognosis with longer-term survival, even in patients with the same AGK mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>This observation resembles patients with Barth syndrome, which is known to show clinical variability found in siblings with identical TAZ genotype [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, these two mitochondrial disorders also seem to result in a decrease of complex I, which has been demonstrated by western blot analysis in Barth syndrome [21] and shown here in a heart and to milder extent a skeletal muscle sample (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Based on the finding of severe mtDNA depletion in skeletal muscle in two patients reported by Calvo and colleagues [16], Sengers syndrome is now also called cardiomyopathic mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome-10 (OMIM 212350). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In contrast to this published study, we did not find any indication for mtDNA depletion in muscle or heart from three patients with samples available for testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in the original publication of the clinical syndrome by Sengers and colleagues [1], the biochemical analysis of mitochondrial enzyme complex activities revealed normal results, which is incompatible with a severe loss of mtDNA copy number [1,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>To date, only nine patients with AGK mutations have been reported to have a combined respiratory chain deficiency indicating that mtDNA depletion is not a common feature of Sengers syndrome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Based on our findings, we can describe two distinct forms of Sengers syndrome, an infantile or severe form and a mild form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The infantile form of Sengers syndrome is caused by homozygous AGK nonsense mutations and is characterized by early onset (within the first few months of life) cardiomyopathy and lactic acidosis that causes death in infancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Some patients who carry at least one AGK splice site variant or a start codon mutation develop a milder form of Sengers syndrome and have a markedly better prognosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>These patients usually develop cardiomyopathy in later stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>They can survive even through their 5th decade of life and in the extreme case, they may only develop cataract. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Currently, no treatment is available for this fatal condition; therefore it is important to identify carriers in at-risk families in order to provide genetic counseling and prenatal diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>In summary, we have identified six novel AGK mutations causing Sengers syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Our findings, along with the other studies, indicate clinical heterogeneity in patients harboring AGK mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>However, interestingly, congenital or early-onset cataract is the common phenotypic finding in all patients, suggesting a role for AGK in the homeostasis of the human eye lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We also suggest that infants with cataract, even in the absence of cardiomyopathy, should be screened for Sengers syndrome or AGK mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>This study verifies the causative role of AGK in Sengers syndrome and expands the genotype-phenotype correlations of mutations in this gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Our results have important applications in genetic counseling and prenatal diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>AGK</term><def><p>Acylglycerol kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANT</term><def><p>Adenine nucleotide translocator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ASD</term><def><p>Atrial septal defect</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RSV</term><def><p>Respiratory syncytial virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mtDNA</term><def><p>Mitochondrial DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>AH and HP contributed as project leads across the whole project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>AH: Study design, literature search, data collection, data analysis, interpretation of results, figures, and writing the first draft of manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>TH: Sequencing, data analysis and interpretation of results, and contribution to the manuscript and figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>UA and EH: Sequencing, data analysis and interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>RGF and JAM: Protein and mtDNA analysis, interpretation of results, figures, and contribution to the manuscript and figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>MA, HM, HH-K, RAB, RGF, AR, A-SL, TK, AD, NP, MAS, NSG, PFC, RWT: patient recruitment and clinical examination, data collection, and contribution to the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>HP: Study design, data analysis, interpretation of results, figures, and contribution to the manuscript and figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed the manuscript for important intellectual content and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>This study was undertaken as part of GENE-ME (a research initiative for investigation of inherited diseases from the Middle-East), EU FP7 Mitochondrial European Educational Training project (MEET) and E-Rare project GENOMIT (01GM1207 for H.P. and FWF I 920-B13 for J.A.M). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In addition, T.K. and H.P. acknowledge a German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF, Bonn, Germany) grant to the German Network for Mitochondrial Disorders (mitoNET, 01GM1113A, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>PFC and RWT receive support from the Wellcome Trust Centre for Mitochondrial Research (096919Z/11/Z) and the UK NHS Highly Specialised “Rare Mitochondrial Disorders of Adults and Children” Service. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>1.SengersRCTrijbelsJMWillemsJLDanielsOStadhoudersAMCongenital cataract and mitochondrial myopathy of skeletal and heart muscle associated with lactic acidosis after exerciseJ Pediatr19758687388010.1016/S0022-3476(75)80217-4<?supplied-pmid 1168700?>1168700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>2.van EkerenGJStadhoudersAMSmeitinkJASengersRCA retrospective study of patients with the hereditary syndrome of congenital cataract, mitochondrial myopathy of heart and skeletal muscle and lactic acidosisEur J Pediatr199315225525910.1007/BF01956157<?supplied-pmid 8444256?>8444256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>3.SmeitinkJASengersRCTrijbelsJMRuitenbeekWDanielsOStadhoudersAMKock-JansenMJFatal neonatal cardiomyopathy associated with cataract and mitochondrial myopathyEur J Pediatr198914865665910.1007/BF00441527<?supplied-pmid 2744041?>2744041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>4.MayrJAHaackTBGrafEZimmermannFAWielandTHaberbergerBSuperti-FurgaAKirschnerJSteinmannBBaumgartnerMRBaumgartnerMRMoroniILamanteaEZevianiMRodenburgRJSmeitinkJStromTMMeitingerTSperlWProkischHLack of the mitochondrial protein acylglycerol kinase causes Sengers syndromeAm J Hum Genet20129031432010.1016/j.ajhg.2011.12.005<?supplied-pmid 22284826?>22284826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>5.PerryMSSladkyJTNeuroradiologic findings in Sengers syndromePediatr Neurol20083911311510.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.05.003<?supplied-pmid 18639755?>18639755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>6.SiriwardenaKMackayNLevandovskiyVBlaserSRaimanJKantorPFAckerleyCRobinsonBHSchulzeACameronJMMitochondrial citrate synthase crystals: novel finding in Sengers syndrome caused by acylglycerol kinase (AGK) mutationsMol Genet Metab2013108405010.1016/j.ymgme.2012.11.282<?supplied-pmid 23266196?>23266196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>7.BektasMPayneSGLiuHGoparajuSMilstienSSpiegelSA novel acylglycerol kinase that produces lysophosphatidic acid modulates cross talk with EGFR in prostate cancer cellsJ Cell Biol200516980181110.1083/jcb.200407123<?supplied-pmid 15939762?>15939762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>8.KalariSZhaoYSpannhakeEWBerdyshevEVNatarajanVRole of acylglycerol kinase in LPA-induced IL-8 secretion and transactivation of epidermal growth factor-receptor in human bronchial epithelial cellsAm J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol2009296L32833610.1152/ajplung.90431.2008<?supplied-pmid 19112101?>19112101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>9.WaggonerDWJohnsonLBMannPCMorrisVGuastellaJBajjaliehSMMuLK, a eukaryotic multi-substrate lipid kinaseJ Biol Chem2004279382283823510.1074/jbc.M405932200<?supplied-pmid 15252046?>15252046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>10.ClaypoolSMOktayYBoontheungPLooJAKoehlerCMCardiolipin defines the interactome of the major ADP/ATP carrier protein of the mitochondrial inner membraneJ Cell Biol200818293795010.1083/jcb.200801152<?supplied-pmid 18779372?>18779372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>11.JiangFRyanMTSchlameMZhaoMGuZKlingenbergMPfannerNGreenbergMLAbsence of cardiolipin in the crd1 null mutant results in decreased mitochondrial membrane potential and reduced mitochondrial functionJ Biol Chem2000275223872239410.1074/jbc.M909868199<?supplied-pmid 10777514?>10777514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>12.McKenzieMLazarouMThorburnDRRyanMTMitochondrial respiratory chain supercomplexes are destabilized in Barth Syndrome patientsJ Mol Biol200636146246910.1016/j.jmb.2006.06.057<?supplied-pmid 16857210?>16857210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>13.JordensEZPalmieriLHuizingMvan den HeuvelLPSengersRCDornerARuitenbeekWTrijbelsFJValssonJSigfussonGPalmieriFSmeitinkJAAdenine nucleotide translocator 1 deficiency associated with Sengers syndromeAnn Neurol200252959910.1002/ana.10214<?supplied-pmid 12112053?>12112053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>14.HaackTBHaberbergerBFrischEMWielandTIusoAGorzaMStreckerVGrafEMayrJAHerbergUHennermannJBKlopstockTKuhnKAAhtingUSperlWWilichowskiEHoffmannGFTesarovaMHansikovaHZemanJPleckoBZevianiMWittigIStromTMSchuelkeMFreisingerPMeitingerTProkischHMolecular diagnosis in mitochondrial complex I deficiency using exome sequencingJ Med Genet20124927728310.1136/jmedgenet-2012-100846<?supplied-pmid 22499348?>22499348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>15.Acham-RoschitzBPleckoBLindbichlerFBittnerRMacheCJSperlWMayrJAA novel mutation of the RRM2B gene in an infant with early fatal encephalomyopathy, central hypomyelination, and tubulopathyMol Genet Metab20099830030410.1016/j.ymgme.2009.06.012<?supplied-pmid 19616983?>19616983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>16.CalvoSEComptonAGHershmanSGLimSCLieberDSTuckerEJLaskowskiAGaroneCLiuSJaffeDBChristodoulouJFletcherJMBrunoDLGoldblattJDimauroSThorburnDRMoothaVKMolecular diagnosis of infantile mitochondrial disease with targeted next-generation sequencingScience translational medicine20124118ra11010.1126/scitranslmed.3003310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>17.KozakMContext effects and inefficient initiation at non-AUG codons in eucaryotic cell-free translation systemsMol Cell Biol1989950735080<?supplied-pmid 2601709?>2601709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>18.AldahmeshMAKhanAOMohamedJYAlghamdiMHAlkurayaFSIdentification of a truncation mutation of acylglycerol kinase (AGK) gene in a novel autosomal recessive cataract locusHum Mutat20123396096210.1002/humu.22071<?supplied-pmid 22415731?>22415731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>19.BorchmanDYappertMCLipids and the ocular lensJ Lipid Res2010512473248810.1194/jlr.R004119<?supplied-pmid 20407021?>20407021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>20.ClarkeSLBowronAGonzalezILGrovesSJNewbury-EcobRClaytonNMartinRPTsai-GoodmanBGarrattVAshworthMBowenVMMcCurdyKRDaminMKSpencerCTTothMJKelleyRIStewardCGBarth syndromeOrphanet J Rare Dis201382310.1186/1750-1172-8-23<?supplied-pmid 23398819?>23398819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>21.Karkucinska-WieckowskaATrubickaJWernerBKokoszynskaKPajdowskaMPronickiMCzarnowskaELebiedzinskaMSykut-CegielskaJZiolkowskaLJaronWDobrzanskaACiaraEWieckowskiMRPronickaELeft ventricular noncompaction (LVNC) and low mitochondrial membrane potential are specific for Barth syndromeJ Inherit Metab Dis20133692993710.1007/s10545-013-9584-4<?supplied-pmid 23361305?>23361305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
