<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4607270</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26178347</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1950</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-1950-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Stages of change of the readiness to quit smoking among a random sample of minority Arab -male smokers in Israel </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Daoud</surname><given-names>Nihaya</given-names></name><address><email>daoud@bgu.ac.il</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hayek</surname><given-names>Samah</given-names></name><address><email>ssamah_shaiek@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sheikh Muhammad</surname><given-names>Ahmad</given-names></name><address><email>ahmad48@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Saad</surname><given-names>Kathleen</given-names></name><address><email>kathleena@gertner.health.gov.il</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>Amira</given-names></name><address><email>osmana@email.sc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thrasher</surname><given-names>James F.</given-names></name><address><email>THRASHER@mailbox.sc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalter-Leibovici</surname><given-names>Ofra</given-names></name><address><email>ofral@gertner.health.gov.il</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Public Health, Faculty of Health Sciences, Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, P.O. Box 653, Beer Sheva, 84015 Israel </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>School of Public Health. University of Haifa, Haifa, Israel </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Cardiovascular Epidemiology Unit, Gertner Institute for Epidemiology and Health Policy Research, Sheba Medical Center, Ramat Gan, 52621 Israel </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Health Promotion, Education, and Behavior, Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, 800 Sumter Street, Columbia, SC 29208 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel-Aviv University, Tel-Aviv, Israel </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>672</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Daoud et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Despite advanced smoking prevention and cessation policies in many countries, the prevalence of cigarette smoking among indigenous and some ethnic minorities continues to be high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study examined the stages of change (SOC) of the readiness to quit smoking among Arab men in Israel shortly after new regulations of free-of-charge smoking cessation workshops and subsidized medications were introduced through primary health care clinics. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We conducted a countrywide study in Israel between 2012–2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Participants, 735 current smokers; 18–64 years old; were recruited from a stratified random sample and interviewed face-to-face using a structured questionnaire in Arabic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We used ordered regression to examine the contribution of socio-economic position (SEP), health status, psychosocial attributes, smoking-related factors, and physician advice to the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking (pre-contemplation, contemplation and preparation). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Of the current smokers, 61.8 % were at the pre-contemplation stage, 23.8 % were at the contemplation stage, and only 14.4 % were at the preparation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the multinomial analysis, factors significantly (P &lt; 0.05) contributing to contemplation stage compared to pre-contemplation stage included [odds ratio (OR), 95 % confidence interval (CI)]: chronic morbidity [0.52, (0.31-0.88)], social support [1.35, (1.07-1.70)], duration of smoking for 11–21 years [1.94, (1.07-3.50)], three or more previous attempts to quit [2.27, (1.26-4.01)], knowledge about smoking hazards [1.75, (1.29-2.35)], positive attitudes toward smoking prevention [1.44, (1.14-1.82)], and physician advice to quit smoking [1.88, (1.19-2.97)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The factors significantly (P &lt; 0.05) contributing to preparation stage compared to pre-contemplation stage were [OR, (95 % CI)]: chronic morbidity [0.36, (0.20-0.67)], anxiety [1.07, (1.01-1.13)], social support [1.34, (1.01-1.78)], duration of smoking 5 years or less [2.93, (1.14-7.52)], three or more previous attempts to quit [3.16, (1.60-6.26)], knowledge about smoking hazards [1.57, (1.10-2.21)], and positive attitudes toward smoking prevention [1.34, (1.00-1.82)]. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Most Arab men who currently smoke are in the pre-contemplation stage, indicating low readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>New policies of free-of-charge smoking-cessation group sessions and subsidized medications introduced through primary health care clinics in Israel may be less effective among Arab men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>For these policies to promote cessation more successfully, tailored interventions and campaigns may be needed to increase the readiness to quit smoking in this population, especially for those at the pre-contemplation stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Smoking remains a major global public health concern despite its decreasing prevalence in developed counties [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Smoking is the leading preventable cause of chronic morbidity and mortality [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>On average, the life expectancy of smokers is reduced by almost 10 years [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Smoking cessation can decrease the risk of smoking-related diseases and mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Smokers who stop smoking before the age of 35 can enjoy the same life expectancy as non-smokers [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Smokers who quit at the age of 60, 50, 40 and 30 can increase their life expectancy by 3, 6, 9 and 10 years, respectively [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For those who quit before the age of 50, the risk of myocardial infarction can be reduced by half one year after smoking cessation [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Smoking cessation can also reduce the cost of treating smoking-related diseases [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, although many smokers express interest in quitting, only 2-5 % succeed annually [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Behavioral and pharmacological interventions have been shown to be effective in smoking cessation [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The stages of change (SOC) theory has been used in many behavioral interventions to facilitate smoking cessation [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The SOC assumes that smoking cessation is a process of movement through five motivational stages [11, 12], each representing a different temporal and motivational aspect of behavioral change [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The first three out of five stages describe individuals’ readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These stages include: a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>pre-contemplation, when smokers have no intention to quit; b. contemplation, when smokers express an intention to quit smoking within the next 6 months; and c. preparation, when smokers plan to quit smoking within the next 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>When individuals quit smoking for 6 months, they are at the action stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>They are considered to be at the maintenance stage if they have been abstinent for 6 months to 5 years, and at the termination stage if they have been abstinent for more than 5 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A study by DiClemente and colleagues found that stage differences predict attempts to quit smoking and cessation success at 1- and 6-month follow-up [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Interventions tailored to an individual’s readiness to quit smoking based on SOC can be more effective in facilitating quitting success [14–17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Prochaska et al. [18]. suggested employing different strategies called “process of change” to promote behavioral change across different SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Rosen et al. [19]. conducted a meta-analysis of studies evaluating the process of change and found that cognitive processes such as “consciousness raising” were more effective among smokers at the pre-contemplation and contemplation stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Assessing the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking among smokers in health care service settings can help in planning more effective interventions for cessation [11, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, smoking cessation policies and interventions do not always consider the SOC of the readiness to quit in program planning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This is particularly important when there are different population groups who might be at different stages in their readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The World Health Organization (WHO) policy report on smoking cessation shows that many countries implement the MPOWER plan, which includes monitoring tobacco use, implementing prevention policies, protecting people from tobacco smoke, offering help to quit tobacco use, warning about the dangers of tobacco, enforcing bans on tobacco advertising, promotion and sponsorship, promoting policies to quit smoking, and raising taxes on tobacco [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>However, smoking cessation is a neglected area in the initial period of the Framework Convention on Tobacco Control (FCTC) adoption and implementation [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Despite the availability of nationwide tobacco control programs and policies in many countries [23], smoking cessation remains a challenge, particularly among some ethnic minorities [24–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>For example, the prevalence of smoking is higher among Aborigine peoples in Australia [28] and Canada [29], racial and ethnic minorities in the UK [30], and some ethnic minorities in the US [31], compared to the majority population groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Generally, few studies have been conducted on smoking cessation in ethnic minority populations [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus, it remains unclear as to why smoking cessation programs are less effective among minority groups [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>A study in a health care setting in the US showed that Black and Hispanic individuals were less likely to receive and use smoking cessation interventions [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Researchers argue that universal policies for smoking cessation can increase inequalities in smoking since such policies are less effective in minority groups [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Therefore, smoking cessation interventions need to be tailored to different population groups and include assessment of the SOC of the readiness to quit at baseline [27, 35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>This requires more research on disadvantaged and marginalized subgroups of society [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In Israel, despite implementation of the WHO MPOWER plan of tobacco control and multiple national programs and interventions, there are persistent inequalities in rates of smoking between population groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Of special concern is the very high prevalence of smoking among Arab minority men [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In all age groups, smoking prevalence is 1.5-2.2 times higher among Arab men compared to Jewish men [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In 2011, smoking prevalence was 43.8 % among Arab men compared to 23.7 % among their Jewish counterparts [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In addition to higher prevalence of smoking, Arab men smoke more frequently than Jewish men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>According to the Israeli Ministry of Health report (2011), among smokers, 30.9 % of Arab men smoke more than one cigarette pack a day compared to only 12.6 % of Jewish men [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Smoking has been attributed to increased incidence of lung cancer among Arab men [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>However, little is known about the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking among Arab men in Israel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Despite a higher prevalence of smoking, few studies have been conducted on smoking cessation and intention to quit among individuals in Arab countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>One study found high rates of smoking in Middle Eastern countries, ranging from 30 % to 60 % [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Between 1990 and 2009, cigarette consumption increased by 57 % in the Middle East and Africa but dropped by 26 % in Western Europe [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>High prevalence of smoking in the Mediterranean region had implications for smokers’ readiness to quit and might translate into a higher proportion of smokers being at the pre-contemplation stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we applied the SOC theory to assess the readiness to quit smoking and examined factors that might contribute to pre-contemplation, contemplation, and preparation in a random sample of Arab minority men in Israel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted shortly after new regulations of free-of-charge workshops and subsidized medications were introduced in primary health care clinics in 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the current study might provide baseline information needed to assess whether the new health policies of free-of-charge workshops and subsidized medications are effective in changing the SOC of the readiness to quit among Arab male smokers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We conducted a cross-sectional study between 2012 and 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The study included a nationwide stratified random sample of Arab men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Individuals were eligible if they were between 18 and 64 years of age, tobacco smokers, Arab citizens in Israel, and living in an Arab town of 5,000 or more inhabitants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The study participants were randomly selected from the Israeli population registry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The sample design took into account the Arab population distribution according to area of residence, locality size and socio-economic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Sixty-four Arab towns with 5,000 or more residents were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>For the purpose of creating the sample strata, the country was divided into three major regions in Israel: North, Center and South, containing 58 %, 30 % and 12 % of the Arab population, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Within each region, towns were stratified according to population size (5,000-9,999, 10,000-29,999, and 30,000 or more residents) and three ranks of socio-economic score of the locality according to the Central Bureau of Statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For each region, one town was sampled from each size and socio-economic specific stratum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The final sample consisted of 20 towns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The number of persons sampled and interviewed in each locality was proportional to the size of the entire population of the respective stratum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Information that identifies the men sampled from the population registry was received (first name, last name, ID and address) from the Ministry of Interior (approximately 15,000 men). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We prepared two random samples of Arab men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The size of each sample was at least three times the number of interviews for replacement of participants, to account for lack of identification or refusal to interview. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We used STATA software (version 13) for power calculation and sample size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This was based on several assumptions: 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of Arab men smokers at the pre-contemplation stage will be 50 % based on previous reports in this population [36] and on results about smokers at the pre-contemplation stage among Arab immigrants in Australia; [40] 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Based on the findings by Wewer et al., [41] there will be approximately a 10 % difference in the proportion of individuals at the pre-contemplation stage between the 18–24 and 45–64 age groups (58.4 % and 68.0 %, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The needed sample size is 964 at a significance level α of 5 % and 80 % power. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>This sample size also took into consideration 0.005 for Inter Cluster Correlation within towns, as this is a stratified sample [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the Ethics Review Board of the Faculty of Health Sciences at Ben-Gurion University of the Negev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Data were collected between September 2012 and September 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Men were contacted via telephone calls or home visits and screened for their tobacco smoking status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Men who met the eligibility criteria and agreed to participate in the study signed an informed consent form and were interviewed face-to-face in their home by trained Arab-speaking interviewers using a structured questionnaire in Arabic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Out of 1,620 men who were approached, 1,165 men met the eligibility criteria (current or past smokers) and 964 agreed to participate (response rate = 83 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Of those, 735 were current smokers and formed the study population for this paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The stages of change (SOC) of the readiness to quit smoking </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Was measured using the following questions: “Do you smoke?” Participants who replied positively were coded as current smokers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>They were then asked if they intend to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Response categories were “no, never” (pre-contemplation stage), “yes, thinking to quit within the next 6 month” (contemplation stage), and “yes, thinking to quit within the next month” (preparation stage). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic characteristics included age groups according to quintiles (18–25, 26–35, 36–45 and 46–64 years of age), and marital status (married or unmarried). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Socioeconomic position (SEP) was determined by three variables: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Education level: The highest educational institution the participant completed (“less than high school,” “high school” and “more than high school”). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Primary source of income: The main source of household income (from “work” or “social allowance and other”). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Employment status: The participant’s current employment status (“yes, full time employment” and “part-time work or unemployed”). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Health status included two variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Chronic disease: A yes / no question; if the participant was ever informed by a physician that he has a chronic disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Anxiety level was measured by the “State-Trait Anxiety Inventory” (STAI) [43, 44], a commonly used measure [45, 46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We used ten items from the original scale that assesses trait and state anxiety. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Examples of state anxiety items include: “I am tense”, “I am worried”, “I feel calm”, and “I feel secure”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Examples of trait anxiety items include: “I worry too much over something that really doesn’t matter”, “I am content”, and “I am a steady person”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Response categories include: 1. almost never, 2.sometimes, 3.often, and 4.almost always. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The codes of positively worded items were reversed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The ten items were summed to create a total score of anxiety (range 1–40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Higher scores indicate greater anxiety levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Cronbach’s alpha of the scale was 0.796, indicating high internal consistency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Psychological factors included two variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Stressful life events measures exposure to nine stressful events during the previous year (e.g., unemployment, major family problems) [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The list includes a modified version of the recent life events index [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="?"><plain>Respondents were asked: “For each situation, indicate whether it have happened to you or to close family members (i.e., spouse, children, parents, or close friends) in the last year: Did you or someone in your family 1) Get fired from work? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="?"><plain>2) Had a major financial crisis? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="?"><plain>3) Experienced death of a family member or a close relative? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="?"><plain>4) Get sick or injured? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="?"><plain>5) Experienced a change of job to lower skill one? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>6) Begin receiving income support or go on welfare? and 7) Experienced any other difficult life events in the last year?” The modified questions include: “During the past four years: 8) Did you or someone in your family get injured in events related to the Arab-Israeli conflict (e.g., a terror attack, Nakba day, protests)? and 9) Did you or someone in your family spend time in prison?” Responses categories were yes\no. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We summed the response scores across all items to create a count variable of stressful life events (range 0–9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Higher scores indicate higher levels of exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Social support was measured by a scale of six items assessing material, emotional and informational support [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The general question was: “To what extent do you have the following types of support?”; Examples for types of support: 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Someone who provides you with advice during difficult times; 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Someone who helps you materially, such as takes you to the doctor, etc.; and 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Someone you trust and talk to about your daily problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Response categories were: 1. never, 2. rarely, 3. sometimes, 4. frequently, and 5. always. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We calculated the mean scores for the answers (range 1–5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Higher scores indicate a higher level of social support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Internal consistency of the scale was high (Cronbach’s alpha = 0.87) in prior research among Arab populations in Israel [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In the current study Cronbach’s alpha was 0.91. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Smoking-related variables included direct questions regarding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Age at initiation of smoking was grouped into three categories: 15 years or less, 16–18 years, and 19 years or more. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These categories are closely related to the age quartiles of our study sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Duration of smoking was classified into four categories: 5 years or less, 6–10 years, 11–20 years, and 21 years or more. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Number of cigarettes smoked per day: Current smokers were asked: “on average, how many cigarettes per day do you smoke?” Response categories were “10 cigarettes or less”, “11-20 cigarettes”, “21-30 cigarettes”, and “31 cigarettes or more”. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Number of previous attempts to quit was measured by a direct question: “How many times did you try to quit smoking?” Answers were grouped into three categories: never, once or twice, three times or more. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Nicotine dependence level was measured by the FrangestÖm Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This measure includes six items: three yes/no items are scored 0 (no) and 1 (yes) and three multiple-choice items are scored from 0 to 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The items were summed to yield a total score of 0–10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Classification of dependence is as follows: 0–2 very low, 3–4 low, 5 moderate, 6–7 high, 8–10 very high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In the current study this variable was used as continuous variable, with higher scores indicating greater nicotine dependence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Knowledge about smoking hazards included the sum score of three yes/no questions: “Do you think smoking can harm your ability to do activities that you are used to do day by day?” “Do you think that smoking can harm organs within the body?” and “Do you think smoking can cause diseases?” The answers were summed into one score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This was a continuous variable in the current study, with higher scores indicating greater knowledge (range: 0–3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation were measured by the mean score of the level of agreement to three statements: “To what extent do you: 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="?"><plain>Support the anti-smoking law in the public places? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="?"><plain>Think that there is a need to enforce smoking prevention and treatment in the Arab society in Israel? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Think that smoking is a common habit among Arab men?” Response categories were: “strongly agree,” “agree,” “don’t agree,” and “don’t agree at all”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This was a continuous variable in the current study, with higher mean scores indicating greater levels of agreement (range 0–3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Smoking social environment included the number of smokers in the participant’s home in addition to himself (none, one, and two or more), parental smoking (yes/no), and indoor smoking (yes/no). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Physician advice to quit: An answer to a yes/no question assessing if the participant had ever been advised by his family physician to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Data analysis was conducted using SAS (Version 9.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Cary, NC: SAS Institute Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>We examined the univariate association between the independent variables and the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking (pre-contemplation, contemplation and preparation), using Chi-square test for categorical variables, and Kruskel-Wallis for the independent continuous variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Independent variables that were significantly (p &lt; 0.05) associated with the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking in the univariate analysis were included in ordered logistic regression analysis after the proportional odds assumption was tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Pre-contemplation was the reference category for the other two categories (contemplation and preparation). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The SOC of the readiness to quit smoking are presented in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Of the sample, 61.8 % were at the pre-contemplation stage, 23.8 % were at the contemplation and 14.4 % were at the preparation stage.Fig. 1Stages of change of the readiness to quit smoking among Arab men smokers in Israel </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The distribution of the study variables is presented in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The average age of the participants was 36.42 years (SD = 12.88) and 63.4 % were married. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Most participants (83.2 %) had high school education or less. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The primary source of income for 16.1 % of the participants was social allowance, and 26.7 % were unemployed or had a part time job. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>About 1 in 3 (30.9 %) men reported having a chronic disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The average score for anxiety was moderate (mean = 16.03, SD = 4.35) and the average score for stressful events was low (mean = 0.79, SD = 1.29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The mean social support score was moderate (mean = 3.6, SD = 0.97).Table 1Socio-demographic characteristics of current smokers (N = 735)Total sampleN%Age 18-2520427.83 26-3517824.28 36-4514920.33 46-6420227.56Marital status Unmarried26936.65 Married46563.35 Socio-economic position Education level Less than high school16322.39 High school44360.85 More than high school12216.76Primary source of income Social allowances/other11316.14 Work58783.86Employment status Unemployed or part time19526.71 Full time employment53573.29 Health status Chronic disease Yes22730.88 No50869.12Anxiety1 (mean (SD) range)73316.03 (4.35) 5-39 Psychosocial factors Stressful life events1 (mean (SD) range)7350.79 (1.29) 0-9Social support1 (mean (SD) range)7353.66 (0.97) 1-5 Smoking-related variables Age at smoking initiation ≤15 years old13318.29 16-18 years36550.21 ≥19 years old22931.50Duration of smoking ≥21 years23836.56 11-20 years15523.81 6-10 years13320.43 5 years or less12519.20Number of cigarettes per day ≥31 cigarettes7511.42 21-30 cigarettes17126.03 11-20 cigarettes26039.73 ≤10 cigarettes15022.83Number of previous attempts to quit Never43460.78 Once or twice15822.13 Three times or more12217.09Nicotine dependence score (FTND)1 (mean (SD) and range)6724.17 (2.61) 0-10Parents smoking Yes39645.30 No32854.70Number of smokers at home Two or more28539.80 One23032.12 None20128.07Smokes indoors Yes49267.58 No23632.42Knowledge about the smoking hazards1 (mean (SD) range)7352.45 (0.89) 0-3Attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation1 (mean (SD) range)7352.19 (1.03) 0-3Physician advice to quit smoking No44460.57 Yes28939.43 1For continuous variables, mean, standard deviation and range are presented </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Half of the participants (50.2 %) began smoking between 16 and 18 years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Long-term smoking was evident: 36.6 % had been smoking for more than 21 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>About 37.5 % smoked 21 cigarettes or more per day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Three fifths (60.8 %) never attempted to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The nicotine dependence score was moderate (mean = 4.17, SD = 2.61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of at least one parent who smoked was high (45.3 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Over two-thirds (71.9 %) stated that they live with one or more smokers at home and 67.6 % reported indoor smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The participants had a high mean score on the knowledge about smoking hazards (mean = 2.45, SD = 0.89), and a high mean score on positive attitudes towards smoking prevention (mean = 2.19, SD = 1.03). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>More than half (60.6 %) stated that their primary care physician did not advise them to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Results of the bivariate analysis are presented in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Marital status, education level, presence of a chronic disease, anxiety, and social support were significantly associated with the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A high proportion of the participants at the pre-contemplation stage (Table 2) were unmarried (65.8 %) (P = 0.039, X2 = 6.46, df = 2) and had a high school education (63.7 %) (P = 0.023, X2 = 11.3, df = 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In addition, they had medium anxiety levels (mean = 15.9, SD = 4.4) (p &lt; 0.001, KW = 14.17, df = 2) and a medium social support score (7.04 %) (P = 0.047, KW = 1.63, df = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>They were also less likely to have chronic disease(s) (66.3 %) (P &lt; 0.001, X2 = 14.56, df = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Age, primary source of income, employment status, and stressful life events were not significantly associated with the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking.Table 2Bivariate associations: stages of change to quit smoking by socio-demographic characteristics, socio-economic position, health status and psychological wellbeing (N = 735)Pre-contemplationContemplationPreparationP-value*N = 454N = 175N = 106n%n%n%Age0.058 18-2513666.673215.693617.65 26-3510760.114726.402413.48 X 2  = 12.18  36-459362.423724.831912.75 DF = 6  46-6411657.425929.202713.37Marital status0.039 Unmarried17765.805018.604215.60 X 2  = 6.46  Married27659.3612526.886413.76 DF = 2  Socio-economic position Education level0.023 Less than high school10161.974426.991811.04 X 2  = 11.33  High school28263.6610223.025913.32 DF = 4  More than high school6654.102722.132923.77Primary source of income0.263 Social allowance/ other7768.142522.12119.74 X 2  = 2.65  Work36061.3313923.688814.99 DF = 2 Employment status0.545 Unemployed or part time11458.464925.133216.41 X 2  = 1.20  Full time employment33562.6212623.557413.83 DF = 2  Health status Chronic disease No33766.34107629.966418.50&lt;0.001 Yes11751.54821.064212.60 X 2  = 14.56  DF = 2 Anxietya 45315.92 (4.40)17515.56 (4.21)10517.25 (4.21)&lt;0.001b  KW = 14.17  DF = 2  Psychosocial factors Stressful life eventsa 4540.76 (1.21)1750.81 (1.45)1060.88 (1.23)0.440b  KW = 1.63  DF = 2 Social support a 4547.04 (4.35)1746.65 (4.62)1067.80 (4.15)0.047b  KW = 6.11  DF = 2 *P value indicates the differences in the distribution of the variable of interest across the 3 levels of the stage of change aFor continuous variables, mean and standard deviation are presented bKruskal Wallis (KW) for these associations otherwise X 2 test </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We further examined the associations between each of the smoking-related factors and SOC of the readiness to quit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Table 3 shows that duration of smoking, previous attempts to quit smoking, number of smokers at home, smoking indoors, knowledge about smoking hazards, attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessations, and receiving physician advice to quit smoking were significantly associated with the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A high proportion of participants at the pre-contemplation stage had long-term (≥21 years; 67.8 %) or short-term (≤5 years; 67.2 %) duration of smoking (P = 0.025, X2 = 14.5, df = 6), never attempted to quit smoking (71.9 %) (P &lt; 0.001, X2 = 53.7, df = 4), had two or more smokers at home (66.3 %) (P = 0.032, X2 = 10.5, df = 4), and had smoked indoors (65.9 %) (P &lt; 0.001, X2 = 12.6, df = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In addition, those at the pre-contemplation stage had low scores on the knowledge about smoking hazards (mean = 2.30, SD = 0.99), held less positive attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation (mean = 2.01, SD = 1.11), and were less likely to receive physician advice to quit smoking (68.5 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The age at which individuals began smoking, the number of cigarettes smoked per day, the nicotine dependence scores, and parental smoking were not significantly associated with the SOC.Table 3Bivariate associations: Stages of change by smoking-related factors (N = 735)Pre-contemplationContemplationPreparationP-value*N = 454N = 175N = 106n%n%n%Age at smoking initiation ≤15 years old8664.662418.052317.290.367 16-18 years22762.198824.115013.70 X 2  = 4.29  ≥19 years old13659.396227.073113.54 DF = 4 Cigarettes per day0.247 ≥31 cigarettes3952.002128.001520.00 21-30 cigarettes11366.083621.052212.87 X 2  = 7.87  11-20 cigarettes15760.157227.593212.26 DF = 6  ≤10 cigarettes9664.003120.672315.33Duration of smoking0.025 ≥21 years14767.766226.052912.18 11-21 years8554.844227.102818.06 X 2  = 14.51  6-10 years8866.163123.311410.53 DF = 6  5 years or less8467.201713.602419.20Previous attempts to quit Never31271.898218.89409.22&lt;0.001 Once or twice8251.904629.113018.99 X 2  = 53.68  Three times or more4738.524335.253226.23 DF = 4 Nicotine dependence score (FTND) a 4144.24 (2.66)1634.24 (2.47)953.87 (2.60)0.421 b KW = 1.47DF = 2Parents smoking Yes24461.628521.466716.910.058 No20261.598826.833811.58 X 2  = 5.68  DF = 2 Number of smokers at home Two or more18966.326221.753411.930.032 One14663.485624.352812.17 X 2  = 10.52  None10853.735326.374019.90 DF = 4 Smokes indoors No12452.546728.394519.070.001 Yes32465.8510821.956012.20 X 2  = 12.56  DF = 2 Knowledge about smoking hazardsa 4542.30 (0.99)1752.66 (0.64)1062.71 (0.60)&lt;0.001b  KW = 25.35  DF = 2 Attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessationa 4542.01 (1.11)1752.49 (0.81)1062.50 (0.60)&lt;0.001 b  KW = 36.94  DF = 2 Physician advice to quit smoking&lt;0.001 No30468.478418.925612.61 X 2  = 21.39  Yes15051.909131.494816.61 DF = 2 *P- value indicates the differences in the distribution of the variable of interest across the 3 levels of the stage of change aFor continuous variables, mean and standard deviation are presented bKruskel Wallis for these associations otherwise X 2 test </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>In the ordered multivariable regression results (Table 4), presence of a chronic disease, a higher anxiety score, higher social support score, shorter duration of smoking, higher number of quitting attempts, higher knowledge score about smoking hazards, more positive attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation, and receiving physician advice to quit smoking were significantly (P &lt; 0.05) associated with the likelihood of being at a more advanced SOC of the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Conversely, number of years of education, marital status, and smoking indoors were not significantly associated with the SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The odds in favor of being at the contemplation stage versus the pre-contemplation stage for participants without a chronic disease was half that of participants with a chronic disease (OR = 0.52, 95 % CI = 0.31-0.88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The same directionality of the OR was found when we compared participants in the preparation stage versus the pre-contemplation stage: the odds of not having a chronic disease were a third of having a chronic disease (OR = 0.36, 95 % CI = 0.20-0.67). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>For a one unit increase in the anxiety score, the odds in favor of being at the contemplation stage versus the pre-contemplation stage were 0.97 (95 % CI = 0.92-1.02), whereas the OR in favor of being in the preparation stage versus the pre-contemplation stage was 1.07 (95 % CI = 1.01-1.13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Higher social support was associated with being in a more advanced stage in the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The OR associated with a one unit increment of social support in favor of being in the contemplation stage versus the pre-contemplation stage was 1.35 (95 % CI = 1.07-1.70), and the OR in favor of preparation stage versus pre-contemplation stage was 1.34 (95 % CI = 1.01-1.78). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Participants who had smoked for less than 21 years were more likely to be in a more advanced SOC than long-term smokers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Three or more attempts to quit smoking was the strongest contributing factor to being at a more advanced level in the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The odds in favor of being in the contemplation versus the pre-contemplation stage for those who had three or more attempts to quit smoking were 2.27 (95 % CI = 1.27-4.10) times greater than for those who had never attempted to quit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The same directionality was found among participants in the preparation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The odds in favor of being in the preparation versus pre-contemplation stage were 3.16 (95 % CI = 1.60-6.26) times as great as for those who had never attempted to quit smoking in the past. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Higher knowledge about smoking hazards was associated with higher SOC of the readiness to quit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>For a one unit increase in the knowledge about smoking hazards, the OR of advancement to the contemplation from the pre-contemplation stage was 1.75 (95 % CI = 1.29-2.35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The same directionality was found in the higher SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>For a one unit increase in the knowledge about smoking hazards, the OR for being in the preparation versus pre-contemplation stage was 1.57 (95 % CI = 1.10-2.21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In addition, more positive attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation were associated with higher readiness to quit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>A one unit increase in positive attitudes toward smoking prevention and cessation increased the OR of being in the contemplation versus pre-contemplation stage by 1.44 (95 % CI = 1.14-1.82). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The same directionality was found in the higher SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>A one unit increase in positive attitudes toward smoking prevention and cessation increased the odds of being in the preparation versus pre-contemplation stage by 1.34 (95 % CI = 1.00-1.82). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Receiving physician advice to quit contributed to participants’ advancement from pre-contemplation to contemplation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The OR of being in the contemplation versus pre-contemplation stage among those who received advice from a physician to quit smoking was 1.88 (95 % CI = 1.19-2.97) compared to participants who did not receive such advice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>However, receiving physician advice to quit smoking did not increase the likelihood that participants would be in the preparation stage, as this was not a significant association (OR = 1.63, 95 % CI = 0.93-2.77).Table 4Ordered logistic regression for factors contributing to the stages of change of the readiness to quit smoking (N = 735)Pre-contemplationContemplationPreparationN = 454N = 175N = 106P-valueReference categoriesOdds Ratio (95 % CI)Odds Ratio (95 % CI)Education level0.356 Less than high school111 High school0.97 (0.56-1.67)1.31 (0.63-2.72) More than high school0.81 (0.41-1.64)1.98 (0.86-4.57)Chronic disease0.002 Yes111 No0.52 (0.31-0.88)0.36 (0.20-0.67)Anxiety10.97 (0.92-1.02)1.07 (1.01-1.13)0.016Social support11.35 (1.07-1.70)1.34 (1.01-1.78)0.017Marital status0.623 Unmarried111 Married0.90 (0.48-1.67)0.70 (0.34-1.44)Duration of smoking0.025 ≥21 years111 11-21 years1.94 (1.07-3.50)2.48 (1.18-5.21) 6-10 years1.46 (0.71-2.99)1.35 (0.54-3.40) 5 years or less0.96 (0.41-2.27)2.93 (1.14-7.52)Previous attempts to quit0.007 Never11 Once or twice11.33 (0.81-2.20)1.76 (0.95-3.24) Three times or more2.27 (1.26-4.01)3.16 (1.60-6.26)Number of smokers at home0.210 Two or more111 One1.41 (0.84-2.38)1.30 (0.67-2.53) None1.41 (0.80-2.46)2.06 (1.05-4.04)Knowledge about smoking hazards11.75 (1.29-2.35)1.57 (1.10-2.21)&lt;0.001Positive Attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation11.44 (1.14-1.82)1.34 (1.00-1.82)0.004Smokes indoors0.309 Yes11 No11.21 (0.76-1.94)1.52 (0.88-2.65)Physician advice to quit smoking0.016 No111 Yes1.88 (1.19-2.97)1.63 (0.93-2.77) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The SOC theory has been used extensively to study smoking cessation [9, 35, 52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>However, research on smoking cessation in low-income and marginalized populations is scarce [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In particular, few studies have used SOC to examine readiness to quit smoking in Mediterranean countries, where smoking prevalence is increasing or has remained consistently high over time [1, 39, 53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Our findings regarding the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking among Arab minority men in Israel show that 62 % of the participants were at the pre-contemplation stage, 24 % at the contemplation stage, and 14 % at the preparation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate lower readiness to quit smoking compared to previous studies in the US and Europe, where 40-45 % of smokers were at the pre-contemplation, 35-40 % at the contemplation, and 20 % at the preparation stage [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In addition, our result regarding the percentage of individuals at the preparation stage was lower than what has been reported in Turkey (20 %) [54] and Iran (17 %) [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Compared to previous findings on minorities in other countries, our study found a higher proportion of smokers at the pre-contemplation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>For example, one study of Aboriginal peoples in Canada found that 39.6 % were at the pre-contemplation and 43.4 % were at the contemplation stage [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>A study among African Americans in the US found that 51 %, 28 % and 17 % were in the pre-contemplation, contemplation and preparation stages, respectively [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Higher prevalence of individuals in the pre-contemplation stage among Arabs in Israel compared to minorities in other countries might relate to the lack of tailored policies and interventions to help these individuals move to a more advanced SOC in the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that Israel’s advanced smoking cessation and prevention policies appear to be less effective among Arabs and highlight the importance of exploring factors that can help Arab men move to a more advanced SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Determining the characteristics of smokers in different SOC will provide valuable information that can be used to plan and implement tailored smoking cessation interventions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Previous research has identified different factors that relate to the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking, including demographic and socio-economic characteristics such as age, gender, marital status, SEP, education, and income [31, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In our study, results from the bivariate analysis showed that among the socio-demographic and socio-economic variables, marital status and education level were significantly associated with the SOC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>However, these associations became non-significant in the multivariate analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Other variables we examined, such as age, primary source of income and employment status, were not significant in the bivariate analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Lack of association between SEP and SOC might be explained by the higher prevalence of smoking among Arab men in Israel regardless of education level or SEP [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Results from previous studies on the association between demographic and SEP variables and the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking had mixed results, with some finding no association and others finding significant associations [13, 59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>For example, Vicler et al., [60] found that level of education, ethnicity, and race were important for the SOC, while another study that included results of five studies in the US did not find significant associations with demographic or SEP variables [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Similar to our results, Choi et al., [62] found that among smokers in Korea, age, education level, and income did not predict the SOC to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Gender was the only demographic variable that predicted being at the maintenance stage [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Our study did not include women since the prevalence of cigarette smoking among Arab women in Israel is very low (about 5 %) [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>A study in the Netherlands compared pre-contemplators with contemplators and preparators and found that the level of education, cultural background, and neighborhood conditions correlated with the intention to quit smoking [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>However, the study compared contemplators and preparators with former smokers [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we were interested in studying the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking among current smokers; therefore, our sample did not include past smokers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Future studies might want to compare the SOC in current and past smokers among Arab men, and longitudinal research is needed to assess the correlates of quitting behavior. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Although we did not find associations with demographic and socio-economic variables, our findings indicated significant associations between some smoking-related variables and the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>We found that a longer duration of smoking, higher number of previous attempts to quit, greater knowledge about smoking hazards, and positive attitudes towards smoking prevention and cessation contributed to advanced SOC (contemplation or preparation stages compared to pre-contemplation stage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with findings of a meta-analysis [61], and one cohort study on previous attempts to quit smoking [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Nicotine dependence did not contribute to advanced SOC in our study, perhaps due to the fact that we found unexpectedly low dependence levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>It might be that those with low dependence levels are less likely to attempt to quit, a result that was reported in a longitudinal study of low intensity smokers in Mexico [66], and in a study in Egypt [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>We did not find evidence that social smoking (parents smoking, indoor smoking and number of smokers in a household) contributed to the SOC of the readiness to quit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>We assumed that social smoking might be an important factor in the Arab collective society, where cigarettes are distributed during social events such as weddings and funerals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>It has previously been suggested that social pressure in Arab societies might contribute to low levels of smoking cessation [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>However, social norms have been identified as an important factor in quitting smoking [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>We found that higher social support contributed to a more advanced SOC of the readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>In addition, our finding that higher levels of anxiety contributed to being at the preparation stage, compared to the pre-contemplation, was unexpected but is important and should be investigated in future research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Our finding that having a chronic disease was related to a more advanced SOC of the readiness to quit is consistent with findings of two previous cohort studies indicating that, in addition to cigarette costs, health status is the most important reason for quitting smoking [65, 69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>A high proportion of Arab men “wait” until they develop a chronic disease before they are ready to quit smoking, which should set alarms for policy makers and health care providers to intervene before Arab men develop a chronic disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>In the current study, compared to the pre-contemplation stage, physician advice to quit smoking was associated with the contemplation stage, but not with the preparation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The OR of being at the contemplation stage for individuals who received physician advice to quit was almost twice as high as compared to those who did not receive such advice, but physician advice did not significantly increase the OR of being at the preparation stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>This is a very important finding since physician advice was previously found to be cost-effective and increased smoking cessation [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>However, 60 % of participants in our study reported that their family physician did not advise them to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>This may be related to a previous finding that prevalence of smoking among physicians is similar to the prevalence of smoking in the general population [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Therefore, more effort should be invested by sick funds to help physicians quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal research is needed to assess the long-term effects of physician interventions and their impact on smoking cessation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The strength of this study is that it is the first study that we know of that examined the SOC of the readiness to quit smoking among Arab men in Israel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The cross-sectional design of the study does not allow for causal inferences of the results, and therefore longitudinal research is recommended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>However, the study included, for the first time, a stratified random sample of Arab men who smoke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This enabled us to examine specific factors that relate to the context of these men, who have received less attention in previous research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A high proportion of Arab men in Israel who smoke are at the pre-contemplation stage, indicating low readiness to quit smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>This low readiness might indicate that policies of free-of-charge smoking-cessation technologies in primary health care clinics may be less effective for this minority group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Interventions aimed at increasing smoking cessation among Arab men need to consider the SOC of the readiness to quit and be tailored to fit the needs of Arab men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Generally, statewide smoking cessation programs have been less effective in minority groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Our study suggests that assessing the SOC might be an important step to designing smoking cessation interventions for ethnic minority groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Competing interest </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>ND initiated the study, led the all study aspects including the study design, data collection, and analysis, and prepared the first draft of the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>OK and KA were involved in the study design and preparation of the study sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>ASM coordinated the data collection, data entry and cleaning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>SH conducted the data analysis together with ND, AO and ASM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>JT, OK, KA, AO, ASM critically reviewed the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>All the authors participated in the study design, critically reviewed previous versions of the paper, and confirmed the final version. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by grant number R/152/10 of the Israel National Institution for Health Policy and Research (NIHP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Many thanks to Dr. Ilya NoviKov (PhD), and Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Angela Chetrit for their valuable help in the preparation of the study sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>We wish to thank all the Arab men who agreed to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title><bold>References</bold></title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>1.WHO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>WHO Report on the Global Tobacco Epidemic: Enforcing bans on tobacco advertising, promotion and sponsorship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>2.Zwar NA, Mendelsohn CP, Richmond RL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Supporting smoking cessation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>BMJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>2014;348. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>3.DollRPetoRWheatleyKGrayRSutherlandIMortality in relation to smoking: 40 years’ observations on male British doctorsBMJ199430990191110.1136/bmj.309.6959.901<?supplied-pmid 7755693?>7755693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>4.DollRPetoRBorehamJSutherlandIMortality in relation to smoking: 50 years’ observations on male British doctorsBMJ2004328151910.1136/bmj.38142.554479.AE<?supplied-pmid 15213107?>15213107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>5.NHS Centre for Reviews and DisseminationSmoking cessation: what the health service can doEffectiveness Matters1998314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>6.BrownRALarkinJCDavisRLCurrent concepts in the management of smoking cessation: a reviewThe American journal of managed care20006394401<?supplied-pmid 10977439?>10977439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>7.FioreMCHatsukamiDKBakerTBEffective Tobacco Dependence TreatmentJAMA20022881768177110.1001/jama.288.14.1768<?supplied-pmid 12365962?>12365962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>8.Stead LF, Lancaster T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Combined pharmacotherapy and behavioural interventions for smoking cessation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Cochrane Tobacco Addiction Group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>2012;10:1–93 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>9.Cahill K, Lancaster T, Green N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Stage-based interventions for smoking cessation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Cochrane Database Syst Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>2010;10:1–112. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>10.Riemsma R, Pattenden J, Bridle C, Sowden A, Mather L, Watt I, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Systematic review of the effectiveness of stage based interventions to promote smoking cessation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>BMJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>2003;326:1175–982. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>11.ProchaskaJDiClementeCStages and processes of self-change of smoking: toward an integrative model of changeJ Consult Clin Psychol19835139039510.1037/0022-006X.51.3.390<?supplied-pmid 6863699?>6863699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>12.ProchaskaJVeliceWMeasuring processes of change: applications to the cessation of smokingJ Consult Clin Psychol19885652052810.1037/0022-006X.56.4.520<?supplied-pmid 3198809?>3198809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>13.DiClementeCProchaskaJFairhurstSVelicerWVelasquezMRossiJThe process of smoking cessation: an analysis of precontemplation, contemplation, and preparation stages of changeJ Consult Clin Psychol19915929530410.1037/0022-006X.59.2.295<?supplied-pmid 2030191?>2030191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>14.DijkstraADe VriesHThe development of computer-generated tailored interventionsPatient Educ Couns19993619320310.1016/S0738-3991(98)00135-9<?supplied-pmid 10223023?>10223023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>15.KrebsPProchaskaJORossiJSA meta-analysis of computer-tailored interventions for health behavior changePrev Med20105121422110.1016/j.ypmed.2010.06.004<?supplied-pmid 20558196?>20558196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>16.VelicerWProchaskaJFavaJNormanGReddingCSmoking cessation and stress management: applications of the transtheoretical model of behavior changeHomeost Health Dis199838216233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>17.SharifiradGREslamiAACharkaziAMostafaviFShahnaziHThe effect of individual counseling, line follow-up, and free nicotine replacement therapy on smoking cessation in the samples of Iranian smokers: Examination of transtheoretical modelJ Res Med Sci20121711281136<?supplied-pmid 23853630?>23853630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>18.ProchaskaJOVelicerWFDiClementeCCFavaJMeasuring processes of change: applications to the cessation of smokingJ Consult Clin Psychol19885652052810.1037/0022-006X.56.4.520<?supplied-pmid 3198809?>3198809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="?"><plain>19.RosenCSIs the sequencing of change processes by stage consistent across health problems? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysisHealth Psychol20001959360410.1037/0278-6133.19.6.593<?supplied-pmid 11129363?>11129363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>20.SinclairHKSilcockJBondCMLennoxASWinfieldAJThe cost-effectiveness of intensive pharmaceutical intervention in assisting people to stop smokingInt J Pharm Pract1999710711210.1111/j.2042-7174.1999.tb00957.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>21.World Health Organization (WHO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Report on the Global Tobacco Epidemic, 2008: The MPOWER package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2008. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>22.McRobbieHRawMChanSResearch priorities for Article 14: demand reduction measures concerning tobacco dependence and cessationNicotine Tob Res20131580581610.1093/ntr/nts244<?supplied-pmid 23139406?>23139406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>23.Song Y, Zhao L, Palipudi KM, Asma S, Morton J, Talley B, Hsia J, Ramanandraibe N, Caixeta R, Fouad H, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Tracking MPOWER in 14 countries: results from the Global Adult Tobacco Survey, 2008–2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Glob Health Promot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>2013;0:1–14. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>24.Marley JV, Atkinson D, Kitaura T, Nelson C, Gray D, Metcalf S, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The Be Our Ally Beat Smoking (BOABS) study, a randomised controlled trial of an intensive smoking cessation intervention in a remote aboriginal Australian health care setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>BMC Public Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>2014;14:32. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>25.Liu JJ, Wabnitz C, Davidson E, Bhopal RS, White M, Johnson MR, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Smoking cessation interventions for ethnic minority groups: a systematic review of adapted interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Prev Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>2013;57:765–75. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>26.CarsonKVBrinnMPPetersMVealeAEstermanAJSmithBJInterventions for smoking cessation in Indigenous populationsCochrane Database Syst Rev20121CD009046<?supplied-pmid 22258998?>22258998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>27.CampbellSBohannaISwinbourneACadet-JamesYMcKeownDMcDermottRStages of change, smoking behaviour and readiness to quit in a large sample of Indigenous Australians living in eight remote north queensland communitiesInt J Environ Res Public Health2013101562157110.3390/ijerph10041562<?supplied-pmid 23591787?>23591787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>28.ThomasDPChanges in smoking intensity among Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people, 1994–2008Med J Aust201219750350610.5694/mja12.10558<?supplied-pmid 23121586?>23121586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>29.BaderPBoisclairDFerrenceREffects of tobacco taxation and pricing on smoking behavior in high risk populations: a knowledge synthesisInt J Environ Res Public Health201184118413910.3390/ijerph8114118<?supplied-pmid 22163198?>22163198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>30.Aspinall PJ, Mitton L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Smoking prevalence and the changing risk profiles in the UK ethnic and migrant minority populations: implications for stop smoking services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Public Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>2014;128:297–306. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>31.LariscyJTHummerRARathJMVillantiACHaywardMDValloneDMRace/ethnicity, nativity, and tobacco use among U.S. young adults: Results from a nationally representative surveyNicotine Tob Res2013151417142610.1093/ntr/nts344<?supplied-pmid 23348968?>23348968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>32.LawrenceDMitrouFZubrickSRGlobal research neglect of population-based approaches to smoking cessation: time for a more rigorous science of population health interventionsAddiction (Abingdon, England)20111061549155410.1111/j.1360-0443.2011.03451.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>33.CokkinidesVEHalpernMTBarbeauEMWardEThunMJRacial and ethnic disparities in smoking-cessation interventions: analysis of the 2005 National Health Interview SurveyAm J Prev Med20083440441210.1016/j.amepre.2008.02.003<?supplied-pmid 18407007?>18407007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="?"><plain>34.OgilvieDPetticrewMReducing social inequalities in smoking: can evidence inform policy? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>A pilot studyTob Control20041312913110.1136/tc.2003.003962<?supplied-pmid 15175527?>15175527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>35.ProchaskaJONorcrossJCDiclementeCCApplying the stages of changePsychother Aust2013191015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>36.Public Health Division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Report of the Minister of Health on Smoking in Israel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Jerusalem, Israel: Ministry of Health; 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>37.Tarabeia J, Green M, Barchana M, Baron-Epel O, Ifrah A, Fishler Y, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Increasing lung cancer incidence among Israeli Arab men reflects a change in the earlier paradox of low incidence and high smoking prevalence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Eur J Cancer Prev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>2008;17:291–6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>38.Khattab A, Javaid A, Iraqi G, Alzaabi A, Ben Kheder A, Koniski M-L, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Smoking habits in the Middle East and North Africa: results of the BREATHE study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Respir Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>2012;106(2):S16–24. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>39.EriksenMMackayJRossHThe Tobacco Atlas, 4th ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Atlanta, GAWorld Medical &amp; Health Policy20135274275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>40.Girgis S, Adily A, Velasco M, Garden F, Zwar N, Jalaludin B, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Smoking patterns and readiness to quit: a study of the Australian Arabic community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Aust Fam Physician. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>2009;38:154–61. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>41.WewersMEStillmanFAHartmanAMShoplandDRDistribution of daily smokers by stage of change: current population survey resultsPrev Med20033671072010.1016/S0091-7435(03)00044-6<?supplied-pmid 12744915?>12744915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>42.SlymenDJHovellMFCluster versus individual randomization in adolescent tobacco and alcohol studies: illustrations for design decisionsInt J Epidemiol19972676577110.1093/ije/26.4.765<?supplied-pmid 9279608?>9279608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>43.SpielbergerCDGorsuchRLLusheneRVaggPRJacobsGAManual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory1983Palo Alto, CAConsulting Psychologists Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>44.SpielbergerCDState-trait anxiety inventory: a comprehensive bibliography1989CAConsulting Psychologists Press Palo Alto </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>45.SpielbergerCDManual for the State–Trait Anxiety Inventory STAI (Form Y)Book Manual for the State–Trait Anxiety Inventory STAI (Form Y)1983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>46.SpielbergerCDState–Trait Anxiety Inventory: a comprehensive bibliographyBook State–Trait Anxiety Inventory: a comprehensive bibliography1989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>47.McDonoughPWaltersVGender and health: reassessing patterns and explanationsSoc Sci Med20015254755910.1016/S0277-9536(00)00159-3<?supplied-pmid 11206652?>11206652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>48.TurnerRJWheatonBLloydDAThe Epidemiology of Social StressAmerican Sociological Review19956010412510.2307/2096348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>49.KarlssonJSjostromLSullivanMSwedish obese subjects (SOS)-an intervention study of obesity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Measuring psychosocial factors and health by means of short-form questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Results from a method studyJ Clin Epidemiol19954881782310.1016/0895-4356(94)00196-W<?supplied-pmid 7769412?>7769412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>50.DaoudNSoskolneVManorOExamining cultural, psychosocial, community and behavioural factors in relationship to socioeconomic inequalities in limiting longstanding illness among the Arab minority in IsraelEpidemiol Community Health20096335135810.1136/jech.2008.080465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>51.HeathertonTFKozlowskiLTFreckerRCFagerstromKOThe Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision of the Fagerstrom Tolerance QuestionnaireBritish journal of addiction1991861119112710.1111/j.1360-0443.1991.tb01879.x<?supplied-pmid 1932883?>1932883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>52.SpencerLPagellFHallionMAdamsTApplying the transtheoretical model to tobacco cessation and prevention: a review of literatureAm J Health Promot20021777110.4278/0890-1171-17.1.7<?supplied-pmid 12271754?>12271754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>53.Khattab A, Javaid A, Iraqi G, Alzaabi A, Ben Kheder A, Koniski M-L, Shahrour N, Taright S, Idrees M, Polatli M, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Smoking habits in the Middle East and North Africa: results of the BREATHE study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Respir Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>2012;106:S16-S24. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>54.Yalçınkaya-AlkarÖKaranciAWhat are the differences in decisional balance and self-efficacy between Turkish smokers in different stages of change?Addictive behaviors20073283684910.1016/j.addbeh.2006.06.023<?supplied-pmid 16842929?>16842929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>55.CharkaziAShahnaziHGhourchaeiABMirkarimiKSmoking behaviors in Iranian male students: an application of transtheoretical modelJ Educ Health Promot201212210.4103/2277-9531.99954<?supplied-pmid 23555125?>23555125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>56.SchorlingJBThe stages of change of rural African-American smokersAmerican journal of preventive medicine199511170177<?supplied-pmid 7662396?>7662396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>57.SiahpushMHellerGSinghGLower levels of occupation, income and education are strongly associated with a longer smoking duration: Multivariate results from the 2001 Australian National Drug Strategy SurveyPublic Health20051191105111010.1016/j.puhe.2005.03.004<?supplied-pmid 16085150?>16085150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>58.Daoud N, Abu-Saad K, Kalter-Livovici O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="?"><plain>Will Arab men stop smoking? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Analysis of smoking cessation readiness according to the trans-theoretical model (the stages and processes of change): internal report National Institue of Health Policy and Research (NIHP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Israel: Tel Hashomer; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>59.SnowMGProchaskaJORossiJSStages of change for smoking cessation among former problem drinkers: A cross-sectional analysisJ Subst Abuse1992410711610.1016/0899-3289(92)90011-L<?supplied-pmid 1504636?>1504636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>60.VelicerWFFavaJLProchaskaJOAbramsDBEmmonsKMPierceJPDistribution of smokers by stage in three representative samplesPrev Med19952440141110.1006/pmed.1995.1065<?supplied-pmid 7479632?>7479632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>61.VelicerWFReddingCASunXProchaskaJODemographic variables, smoking variables, and outcome across five studiesHealth Psychol20072627828710.1037/0278-6133.26.3.278<?supplied-pmid 17500614?>17500614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>62.Choi JH, Chung KM, Park K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Psychosocial predictors of four health-promoting behaviors for cancer prevention using the stage of change of Transtheoretical Model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Psychooncology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>2013;22:2253–61. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>63.Baron-EpelOKeinan-BokerLWeinsteinRShohatTPersistent high rates of smoking among Israeli Arab males with concomitant decrease among JewsIMAJ201012732737<?supplied-pmid 21348400?>21348400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>64.DotingaASchrijversCTVoorhamAJMackenbachJPCorrelates of stages of change of smoking among inhabitants of deprived neighbourhoodsEur J Public Health20051515215910.1093/eurpub/cki112<?supplied-pmid 15941760?>15941760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>65.HylandALiQBauerJEGiovinoGAStegerCCummingsKMPredictors of cessation in a cohort of current and former smokers followed over 13 yearsNicotine Tobacco Research200463S36336910.1080/14622200412331320761<?supplied-pmid 15799599?>15799599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>66.SwayampakalaKThrasherJCarpenterMJShigematsuLMCupertioAPBergCJLevel of cigarette consumption and quit behavior in a population of low-intensity smokers: longitudinal results from the International Tobacco Control (ITC) survey in MexicoAddict Behav2013381958196510.1016/j.addbeh.2012.12.007<?supplied-pmid 23380491?>23380491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>67.BoulosDNKLoffredoCAEl SetouhyMAbdel-AzizFIsraelEMohamedMKNondaily, light daily, and moderate-to-heavy cigarette smokers in a rural area of Egypt: a population-based surveyNicotine Tob Res20091113413810.1093/ntr/ntp016<?supplied-pmid 19246629?>19246629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>68.MaziakWEissenbergTKlesgesRKeilUWardKAdapting smoking cessation interventions for developing countries: a model for the Middle EastIntl J Tuberc Lung Dis20048403413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>69.HymowitzNCummingsKMHylandALynnWRPechacekTFHartwellTDPredictors of smoking cessation in a cohort of adult smokers followed for five yearsTob Control19976Suppl 2S576210.1136/tc.6.suppl_2.S57<?supplied-pmid 9583654?>9583654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>70.SteadLFBuitragoDPreciadoNSanchezGHartmann-BoyceJLancasterTPhysician advice for smoking cessationCochrane Database Syst Rev20135Cd000165<?supplied-pmid 23728631?>23728631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
