<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4414469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25923325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-35084</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Females Choose Mates Based on Genetic Relatedness in a Small Dasyurid Marsupial, the Agile Antechinus (Antechinus agilis) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mate Choice and Multiple Mating in Antechinus</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parrott</surname><given-names>Marissa L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Simon J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Temple-Smith</surname><given-names>Peter D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selwood</surname><given-names>Lynne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Zoology, University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Biodiversity Conservation Division, NT Department of Natural Resources, Environment, the Arts and Sport, Palmerston, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Southern Clinical School, Monash University, Clayton, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Wildlife Conservation and Science, Zoos Victoria, Parkville, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zane</surname><given-names>Lorenzo</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Padova, ITALY</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MLP SJW PDT-S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: MLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: MLP SJW PDT-S LS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: MLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Supervised MLP's PhD research: SJW PDT-S LS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Edited the manuscript: SJW PDT-S LS </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>mparrott@zoo.org.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e0122381</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Parrott et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Parrott et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0122381.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Females in a variety of taxa mate with more than one male during a single oestrus and exhibit mate preferences for genetically compatible males, but the influence of female mate choice on siring success is not clearly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Whether females choose to mate with more than one male or endure forced copulations is also often unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Here, we examined the effects of genetic relatedness on female mate choice and siring success in a small semelparous carnivorous marsupial, the agile antechinus (Antechinus agilis), during two consecutive breeding seasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Experimental trials were conducted in captivity over periods of 72 hours using interconnected enclosures in which female antechinus could choose to access any of four separated males, but males were only able to access females that entered their quarters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Females had access to two genetically similar and two genetically dissimilar males simultaneously and all behavioural interactions were observed and scored from continuous video recordings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Genetic similarity between mates and paternity of young was determined by microsatellite analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Some females chose to enter and mate with more than one male during a single oestrus period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Although females investigated all males, they spent significantly more time visiting, and mated more times with, genetically dissimilar males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Males that were genetically dissimilar to the female sired 88% of subsequent offspring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Whilst males mated readily with most females, they rejected the advances of some receptive females, indicating a previously unexpected level of male mate choice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The results show that genetic relatedness between mates has a significant influence on mate choice, breeding and siring success in the agile antechinus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was funded by a Melbourne Research PhD Scholarship, grants from the Holsworth Wildlife Research Endowment and Winifred Violet Scott Estate, a Loftus-Hills Memorial Fund Award and David Hay Postgraduate Writing-up Award to M. Parrott. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>A female’s choice of mate can significantly affect her reproductive success [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In social systems that involve no paternal investment other than spermatozoa, females are expected to choose males that confer greater survival and future reproductive success to their offspring (reviewed in [1,2]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Females that are permitted to choose mates in captivity may produce greater quality offspring with improved survival, social dominance, larger home ranges, better nest sites and nests [3] and increased attractiveness as mates [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in the wild, a female’s choice of mate can lead to increased fitness and parasite resistance in offspring [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Females in a variety of taxa may choose males based on a number of criteria, including ‘good’ or compatible genes with a females own genotype, genes of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) that can offer a reliable olfactory indicator of male health, genetic diversity and quality ([2]), viability genes or genetic relatedness [6,7,8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>While viability genes are often expressed through secondary sexual characteristics, it is less clear how females assess the genetic relatedness or incompatibility of potential mates and how this affects the siring success of individual males [6,1,9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Such information is lacking for numerous species and the mechanisms for multiple mate selection and the effects of female mate preferences on siring success are still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Females mate with more than one male during a single oestrus in a range of species (e.g. common shrews, Sorex araneus [11]; Gunnison’s prairie dogs, Cynomys gunnisoni, [12]; agile antechinus, Antechinus agilis, [13,14]; feathertail gliders, Acrobates pygmaeus, [15], saltmarsh sparrows (Ammodramus caudacutus; [16]), grass snakes (Natrix natrix, [17]), eastern water skinks (Eulamprus quoyii; [18]), but it is often difficult to determine whether females choose to mate with more than one male or endure forced copulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Females that mate with a number of different males potentially face greater risk of injury or disease [19,20], but may benefit through increased reproductive output by ensuring adequate levels of sperm for fertilisation [21,22,18] and/or safeguarding against the possible incompatibility or sterility of some males [2,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Females may also rely on competition between spermatozoa from two or more males to fertilise ova and produce the highest quality young [24,25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Species with multiple mating strategies often produce litters that are sired by more than one male which may increase the success and survival of litters by increasing genetic variability [26] and heterozygosity [6,21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>This research investigated the effects of genetic relatedness between mates on female choice and the outcomes of multiple mating in the agile antechinus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This species is promiscuous [11,27,28] with multiple paternity occurring in 96%–98% of litters and an average of three to four sires per litter ([14], MLP unpub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Most males sire young in wild populations with 81% siring offspring in a year where the population was at parity and 100% siring offspring when the population was female biased (MLP unpub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Little is known about mate selection in antechinus, but the level of information available on other aspects of their reproduction makes them an ideal model species in which to examine the effects of female preference on multiple matings and siring success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Larger males sire a higher proportion of young in wild populations ([29], MLP unpub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>data), but captive studies have shown that females choose mates on other criteria, including scent and genetic relatedness, rather than on male size [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In wild situations, larger males may secure forced copulations, have increased stamina or travel greater distances to pursue females, or exclude smaller males from mating, and override any opportunity for female mate choice [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Sperm precedence, where the male that mates closest to ovulation during oestrous receptivity in females sires the highest proportion of young, also significantly influences paternity success [26,32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In this study, a series of captive mating trials was conducted in which receptive females were provided with a simultaneous choice of four males, but these males could not follow a female out of his enclosure and could not interact directly with other males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The combination of males within each trial was selected to provide each female with a range of potential mates that were of similar size, but varied in their degree of relatedness to her. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>This allowed us to analyse female and male mate choice behaviours and interactions, and test the following hypotheses: 1) that females prefer males that are genetically dissimilar to themselves; 2) that female agile antechinus choose to mate with more than one male; and 3) that genetically dissimilar males have a greater siring success than males that are more genetically similar to the female. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec003"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This research adhered to Animal Behaviour Society Guidelines for the use of animals and was carried out with ethics approval from the Animal Ethics Sub-Committee at the University of Melbourne (AEC 02181) and under Department of Sustainability and Environment Wildlife permits (10002396 and 10002889). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Animal maintenance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Agile antechinus were trapped in the Mt Disappointment State Forest, Victoria, in July 2003 (n = 28, 12 males and 16 females) and 2004 (n = 24, 12 males and 12 females) and maintained in captivity as described in Parrott et al. [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Due to extreme drought conditions during the study, animals were in poor condition (based on comparisons of weight with non-drought years, emaciated appearance and dull, rough fur) when collected [33], but all females used in this study survived and were successfully maintained in captivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>On completion of the mate selection experiments, males were released to their original points of capture, except for any that had reached their natural die-off period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Females remained in captivity until young were born and all were then released in their natal nest-boxes back to the wild at their original points of capture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Female choice equipment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Experimental enclosures constructed from 16 mm thick white melamine coated particle board (whiteboard panels, Laminex Industries, Tullamarine, Victoria, Australia; n = 3; Fig 1A) were designed with five compartments, one inner containing 2 females and 4 outer each housing a male, which were covered by clear perspex sheets to facilitate observation and video recording. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Pairs of females were used as females better adjust to captivity when housed socially (F Kraaijeveld-Smit pers comm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Food was provided in each compartment daily and water (supplemented with Pentavite) was available ad libitum [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All compartments were lined with white paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0122381.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Enclosures for female choice experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(a) Enclosure seen from above, showing the four male and one female compartments and furnishings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Four outer compartments, with external measurements 400 mm × 300 mm × 300 mm high, each housed a single male and the middle compartment, measuring 800 mm × 200 mm × 300 mm, housed two females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Each male compartment contained a stainless steel nest-box (130 mm × 130 mm × 130 mm) filled with cotton bedding, a cardboard tube, water bowl, feed tray and plastic climbing lattice on one wall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The female compartment contained a nest-tube with cotton bedding (200 mm long × 100 mm diameter) which had entrance/exit holes at each end, plus a water bowl, feed tray and lattice placed at each end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Holes (3 mm diameter) were drilled every 30 mm around the base and top of the four outer walls of the enclosures to allow air flow and in two lines near the base of the walls between the male and female compartments to facilitate movement of animal scents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In the centre of the wall separating each male compartment from the female compartment, a 70 mm × 70 mm gap was covered by a removable clear perspex ‘door’ which contained a 15 mm diameter hole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The size of the hole allowed the exclusion of the larger males which were unable to leave their own compartment in this sexually dimorphic species and allowed almost all females to move in and out of the male and female compartments uninhibited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Females were able to see and interact with males through the perspex and hole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Doors were recessed into a groove across the centre of a wooden ‘door step’ (60 mm × 70 mm × 20 mm high) with grooves on either side of the door to provide grip. (b) Video surveillance set-up showing the enclosure, video camera and video recorder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0122381.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A small black and white closed-circuit digital camera (1/4 B/W G type security surveillance camera, Jaycar, Silverwater, NSW, Australia) suspended above the centre of each enclosure was connected to a video recorder (V-W58H 6 head HiFi VCR, Toshiba, Mt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Waverley, Victoria, Australia; Fig 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Light cycles mimicked natural conditions with a dim red light (12 W dark room infrared globe, Philips, North Ryde, NSW, Australia) on during night hours to allow video recording and direct observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>An observer (MLP) was present in the room during all night hours, and most hours during the day, to record direct observations and ensure no animals became trapped or injured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Behaviours were observed via video output on a TV screen or from a distance to minimise disturbance to the animals and ensure animal movements were not influenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Any females that were seized and held through doors by males and appeared unable to free themselves after ~2 minutes were freed by the observer by gently prodding the male with a light, blunt instrument. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>This occurred only once when an observer was not present and the female freed herself after ~8 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>No females were injured or lost fur when seized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Ambient temperature was maintained at 21 ± 1°C, but temperature was approximately 2°C higher inside the enclosures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Between trials, enclosures were cleaned with detergent, water and 70% ethanol and allowed to air-dry to remove scents and other contaminating material that may have influenced behavioural interactions in the next trial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Female choice experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In 2003, eight trials using a total of 12 males and 16 females were performed, while in 2004, this was reduced to six trials using 12 males and 12 females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To determine the onset of mating receptivity and ovulation, urine from each female was examined daily to monitor numbers of cornified epithelial cells with ‘Day 0’ of the receptive period corresponding to the time of detection of the first high levels of cornified epithelial cells [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Females have a receptive period during which they mate, when numbers of cornified epithelial cell in their urine are high for up to 20 days before ovulation, and continuing after ovulation when such cell numbers start to decline [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, the most fertile receptive period when the percentage of normal embryos is high (60–100%) occurs 5–13 days before ovulation [13] due to declining fertilizing capacity of stored sperm outside that period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>All trials were conducted after day 3 of the receptive period and during the most fertile portion of the receptive period wherever possible (22/28 females; with 3 females paired on days 4–6 and 3 females paired after day 14 due to time constraints), and all were completed prior to ovulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Male urine was analysed prior to experiments to ensure all males were producing sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Females were provided with two males that were more genetically similar and two less genetically similar (dissimilar) to themselves (see below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Females in each pair were identified by black permanent marker on their tails with two thin stripes given to one female and two thick bands given to the other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>To remove any influence of male size on mate selection or male success and enable a more controlled examination of female preference for genetic relatedness, males in each trial were selected to be roughly of equal weight, with less than 3 g difference between them (mean ± SE, 2003: 31.8 ± 0.3 g; 2004: 37.7 ± 0.8 g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>No males were able to leave their compartments through size exclusion doors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Females chosen for this experiment were in their first breeding season and had not previously mated (mean weight ± SE, 2003: 20.1 ± 0.4 g; 2004: 18.9 ± 0.6 g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Females that attempted to enter areas and were observed to insert a head and torso, but could not enter due to the width of their pelvis (n = 3), were placed with males and observed at all times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>This occurred only once while an observer was not present one afternoon, but the female was introduced to the male compartment when she tried to enter again that night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>When females attempted to leave, they were removed from the male compartment by the experimenter (MLP), who was present at all times the female was in the compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in the mating behaviour or breeding success rates of these females compared with females that could enter and leave of their own accord (n = 25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Primiparous females were chosen for this experiment as few females survive to produce a litter in a second year, with no second-year females producing a litter during drought [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Each trial was conducted over 72 hours (three days) with constant video recording, providing around 1008 hours of video for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Males were allowed one day rest between trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Videos were analysed to determine for each female 1) the number of visits to each male door; 2) the time spent investigating each male; 3) which male compartments she entered; 4) the time spent in each male compartment; and 5) which males she mated with during the trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Timing of copulation and intromission were not analysed as mating pairs often moved in and out of nest boxes during copulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A visit involved the female stopping to look, sniff, chew or climb on male doors and doorsteps and did not include the female walking past doors without stopping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Female visits that lasted five seconds or longer were timed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Behaviours that included male/female and female/female agonistic encounters, scent marking, chasing and sexual positions [36,37] were counted as distinct bouts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Genetic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Prior to each experiment, animals were genotyped using seven microsatellite markers as described in Parrott et al. [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Relatedness between all members of the captive colony was determined using the GENEPOP 3.4 program to analyse allele frequencies and Kinship 1.3.1 to give a numerical score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Kinship values in relation to each female were used when choosing females and their four potential mates in this experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Mean (± SE) Kinship values were 0.14 ± 0.02 (median 0.12, range -0.07–0.38) for the two more genetically similar and -0.10 ± 0.01 (median -0.10, -0.31–0.09.) for the two more genetically dissimilar males compared to each female over both years and this difference was significant for each female (paired t-test t = -16.87, p &lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Female pairs in each experiment differed in genetic relatedness to each other and males differed in relatedness to each of the females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This allowed each female different choices of mates that were genetically dissimilar or similar to themselves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Pouch young born from matings during these experiments were genotyped at five microsatellite loci using DNA extracted from tail tip samples (&lt;1 mm of skin) taken at four weeks of age [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The paternity of each pouch young was allocated using the CERVUS 2.0 program with 100% confidence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Analysis of results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Males were divided into either the genetically similar (2 males/female) or genetically dissimilar (2 males/female) categories based on Kinship values described above for analyses of female choice and paternity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Efforts were made to reduce pseudoreplication in the dataset, though this was not always possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Comparisons between the measures of female behaviour directed toward similar verses dissimilar males and the reproductive outcomes were performed using either repeated measures ANOVA to correct for between-individual differences or chi-square tests (when the dependent variable was binary) using the statistical program SYSTAT [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Weights of individuals that produced offspring and those that did not were compared using t-tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec009"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec010"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Mate choice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec011"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Investigation by females </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>All but one female (27/28) visited the four male doors prior to focussing on a preferred male(s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>There was no significant difference in the number of times a female visited the door of the males that were more genetically similar or dissimilar to herself (F1,26 = 2.46, p = 0.13; Fig 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>However, females spent significantly more time investigating the doors of males that were genetically dissimilar to themselves (F1,26 = 11.05, p = 0.003; Fig 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Once interested in a particular male(s), females would chew, push and climb on doors of these males prior to gaining access. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Genetically dissimilar males attracted significantly more bouts of chewing, pushing and climbing behaviours than similar males (mean ± SE per female, Similar: 9.1 ± 1.7 times; Dissimilar: 16.2 ± 3.4 times; F1,26 = 6.50, p = 0.017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0122381.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The number of visits and time spent at male doors. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The mean (± SE) number of times female agile antechinus (n = 28) visited the doors of males that were more genetically similar and more dissimilar to themselves (left) and the mean (± SE) time (seconds) female agile antechinus (n = 28) spent visiting the doors of males that were more genetically similar and more dissimilar to themselves (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>An asterisk (*) indicates a significant difference from the other value (p = 0.003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0122381.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Females investigated males that were acting in an aggressive or vocal manner from a distance, returning to examine them after being chased from and/or grabbed through doors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in the number of chases/attacks from genetically similar or dissimilar males (mean ± SE per female, Similar: 9.8 ± 1.4; Dissimilar: 11.8 ± 2.0; F1,26 = 0.75, p = 0.39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Most females that were seized by males through doors were able to quickly free themselves (67%, n = 30 times), while others were released after observer intervention (33%, n = 15 times). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>No females attempted to enter compartments with males vocalising or acting in an aggressive manner (n = 0/28 females). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Entries to male compartments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Females entered into the compartments of both genetically similar and dissimilar males and there was no difference in the number of times they did so (Repeated measures ANOVA; F1,26 = 0.29, p = 0.60; Fig 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, females typically spent more than double the time in the enclosures of genetically dissimilar males (F1,26 = 4.38, p = 0.046; Fig 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Half the females (14/28) entered male compartments more than once with two females entering different male compartments a combined total of 41 and 32 times respectively (mean ± SD = 4.64 ± 9.45; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0122381.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The number of entries and time spent in male enclosures. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The mean (± SE) number of times female agile antechinus (n = 28) entered into the compartments of males that were more genetically similar and more dissimilar to themselves (left) and the mean (± SE) time (hours) female agile antechinus (n = 21) spent in the compartments of males that were more genetically similar and more dissimilar to themselves (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>An asterisk (*) indicates a significant difference from the other value (p = 0.046). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0122381.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone.0122381.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Overview of female visits, entries, matings and pouch young produced. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0122381.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0122381.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Number of females </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Additional data </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Entry into 1 male compartment </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>14/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Entry into &gt;1 male compartment </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>14/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Actively seeking mate and entered male nest box </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>21/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>7 females entered the male area, but fled from the male when approached. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>2 females were rejected by males despite attempts to gain male attention. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Mated with 1 male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>13/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>6/13 females produced young </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Mated with &gt;1 male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>6/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>5/6 females produced young </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Failed to mate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>9/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Produced pouch young </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>11/28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Total of 47 young produced (range 1–9 PY/litter; mean ± SE litter size 4.27 ± 0.79) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The number of females that entered into one, or more than one, male compartment, sought to mate with males, mated with single or multiple males and produced pouch young, including additional data on female behaviour and the number of young produced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec><sec id="sec013"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Genetic relatedness and mating behaviour </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Females actively sought males and entered into nest-boxes with males of their own accord (n = 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Females often mated with a male multiple times before leaving his compartment (n = 11 females), but it was not possible to score the exact number of matings during each visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Some females (n = 6) chose to enter and mate with more than one male, but most females mated with only one male (n = 13) and 9 females failed to mate (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Four females re-entered male compartments and mated with the same male up to 5 times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Some of these re-entries (n = 3 females) were sequential, while one was after mating with different males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Females were more likely to mate with one or both of the more genetically dissimilar males (17/28) than with one or both of the more genetically similar males (7/28; X2 = 7.29, df = 1, p = 0.007; Fig 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Females that mated with more than one male did not appear to trade up to more genetically dissimilar males with four females mating with the more genetically dissimilar male first, one mating with the more similar of their two males first, and one female mating with a similar male in between two more genetically dissimilar males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Some males in each year (2003: n = 2/12; 2004: n = 2/12) were disproportionately popular, regardless of genetic relatedness and were chosen by all females they encountered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0122381.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122381.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The number females that mated with genetically similar and dissimilar males and paternity of young produced. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The mean (± SE) number of females that mated with the more genetically similar and more dissimilar males (left), and the number of agile antechinus young sired by the more genetically similar and more dissimilar males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Asterisks (*) indicate significant differences in pairs of values (number of matings, p &lt;0.001; number of young, p &lt; 0.016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0122381.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Females did not appear to follow each other and entered into the same male compartment simultaneously in only three trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In two of those trials females pushed, chased and bit each other until one left from the males’ nest-boxes and compartments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Both females that were chased from a male compartment later re-entered the compartment and one stayed to mate with the male. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Female agonistic behaviour was observed only near males with low levels occurring during or following mating events, except in one instance where it also occurred near the female nest-tube and food trays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Females chose to mate with the same male in one trial only, with one of the females in that trial mating with 3 of the four males available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec014"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Male behavior </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>All males (n = 24) scent marked their compartments using urine and paracloacal and cutaneous sternal glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Scent marking behaviour and wet scent-marked areas were most often apparent near the door areas where females had scent-marked and on the upright climbing lattices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Males appeared to show interest in and accept most females regardless of whether the female showed passive or agonistic (hissing and biting) behaviours, but ignored the advances of others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Females were able to enter the compartments and nest-boxes of these males while the male was awake without any male reaction (n = 6 females). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Three of these females pushed and climbed over males and assumed mating positions, but did not elicit a response and left soon after. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Four females that were rejected by some males were accepted by others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Two females were rejected by all males, but the males in these trials mated with the other female present, showing that these males were interested in females and capable of mating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The two females ignored by all males were within their most fertile receptive period and were within the weight range of females mated by males, though were two of the lighter females that year (rejected females: 14.4 and 14.8 g; mean of all females in 2003 = 15.1 ± 0.22, range = 14–17 g). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec015"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Offspring production and genetic relatedness </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In 2003, 6 females gave birth to 28 young following this experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Samples were taken from 23 pouch young (5 young were lost before they were large enough to sample). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In 2004, 5 females gave birth to 19 young following these experiments, all of which were sampled (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Females that produced litters were mated in their most fertile period (n = 8) or towards the end their receptive period (n = 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Females that did not give birth were either in (n = 14), or at the beginning of their most fertile period (days 4–6; n = 3), and nine of those females failed to mate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in weight between females that produced young (16.4 ± 0.5 g) and did not produce young (15.6 ± 0.4 g; t = 1.30, p = 0.21), or in males that sired (26.2 ± 0.6 g) or did not sire young (27.4 ± 0.8 g; t = -1.19, p = 0.25). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Of the 19 females that were observed to have mated, offspring were produced by 5 of the 6 that had mated with more than one male and 6 of the 13 that had mated with only one male (X2 = 2.33, df = 1, p = 0.13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Of the 11 females that produced young, mean litter size was 4.66 ± 1.05 among females that mated to one male and 2.80 ± 0.73 among females that mated to more than one male (ANOVA; F1,9 = 1.94, p = 0.20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Of the 13 females that mated with only one male, offspring were produced by 6/11 that mated with a more dissimilar male and 0/2 that mated with a more similar male (X2 = 2.03, df = 1, p = 0.16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Multiple paternity was observed in 2/11 litters with two fathers in each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Of the four females that mated with both dissimilar and similar males and produced offspring, the dissimilar mates sired more young on average in two cases and the similar mate more young in the other two cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Overall, females were more likely to produce offspring with genetically dissimilar males (10/28) than similar males (2/28; X2 = 6.79, df = 1, p = 0.01) and produced, on average, more young with their pair of dissimilar males (1.32 ± 0.44) than similar males (0.19 ± 0.13; F1,54 = 6.24, p = 0.016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In total, 88% of young produced were sired by the genetically dissimilar males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Two males sired young in two litters, while nine males sired a litter with one female. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This study has shown for the first time that female agile antechinus actively seek, and are receptive to, matings with more than one male and that mate choice is an important strategy in the antechinus breeding system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Although females watched and interacted with all the males, they spent significantly more time investigating males that were genetically dissimilar to themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Females also mated and produced young with genetically dissimilar males significantly more times than with the genetically similar males. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Female agile antechinus in wild populations almost always produce litters that are sired by more than one male ([14], MLP unpub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Here, despite the availability of four males, the majority of females chose to be monandrous, often returning to mate with a single male multiple times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>This differs to the field data and may suggest that when constraints exerted by males are relieved, females avoid multiple matings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Females that mate with more than one male may hedge their bets against the possibility of a mate being sterile or incompatible [2,39], but females in this study chose males that were more genetically dissimilar to themselves and so avoided mating with males more likely to be genetically incompatible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In this study, genetic relatedness was determined using seven microsatellite markers, thus questions remain regarding the levels of relatedness between potential mates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Further research with additional markers and research into genes of the Major Histocompatibility Complex could be used to further clarify relationships in the future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Females may also mate with an available male and then ‘trade up’ by mating with a higher quality male if encountered [40,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Each trial in this experiment was run for 72 hours, so offered the opportunity for females to trade up to higher quality available males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>However, the majority of females in this experiment that mated with more than one male did so with a more dissimilar male first and showed the highest level of interest in their first mate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>As all males were simultaneously available, this may not be indicative of a wild situation where females may be expected to encounter new males at different times during their long receptive period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Last male sperm precedence operates in the agile antechinus [26,32], so females may be able to influence the paternity of their young by trading up to genetically superior males during their most fertile periods [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The small litter sizes produced in this study may have resulted in the decreased incidence of mixed paternity when compared with wild data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>However, all but one female that mated with more than one male produced young, while less than half the females that mated with one male produced a litter, suggesting that females that mate with multiple partners increase their reproductive success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Research has shown that female brown antechinus (Antechinus stuartii) that mate with multiple males during a single receptive period produce significantly more young than females allowed to mate with only one male [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A similar effect has been observed in European adders (Vipera berus), where females that mated with more than one male had fewer stillborn young [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In sand lizards, increased number of mates correlated with increased egg-hatching success and survival of young [45], while, female blue tits (Parus caeruleus) and tree swallows (Tachycineta bicolor) increase the heterozygosity and thus the potential fitness and reproductive success of their offspring through additional extra-pair matings [46,47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Conversely, females may avoid mating with multiple males to reduce the risk of parasite transmission, illness or injury sustained during mating [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Here, females avoided males that were particularly vocal or aggressive at their doors, regardless of the level of genetic dissimilarity between the pair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The relationships between female mate choice, male coercion and reproductive success are complex and warrant further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Males that were genetically dissimilar to females obtained more matings than genetically similar males and sired more young, as has been observed in a variety of taxa [6,1,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>However, compared with the number of matings obtained by males in each category, genetically dissimilar males sired a disproportionately higher number of young than genetically similar males per mating event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Previous research by Kraaijeveld-Smit et al. [32] suggested that spermatozoa from genetically dissimilar males may be more successful due to sperm competition [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Female agile antechinus store sperm in specialised isthmic crypts in their oviducts for up to 15 days [13,34,48] providing time and a suitable environment for sperm competition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Potentially, males that are genetically dissimilar to females are not only chosen pre-copulation, but their spermatozoa also compete more successfully post-copulation by cryptic female selection of sperm within the reproductive tract [40,49,50,51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>It is possible that part of the uterine mortality encountered in this species which progressively reduces viable embryos to 60% by the neurula stage [34] is due to matings between genetically similar individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In natural populations, larger males may also secure more matings and sire more young ([14], MLP unpub data), but ex situ research into female mate choice shows that female agile antechinus do not choose males based on size [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Regardless, the effect of male size on mate selection in this experiment was excluded as a confounding factor by selection of males of similar sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>There was no evidence of mate copying, as occurs in species including the guppy [52] and sage grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus; [53]) where females copy the preferences of other females, even changing from their original choice [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Although female antechinus entered the enclosures of the same males, two females chose to mate with the same male in only one of 14 trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>One male sired young in two litters, but all other sires produced one litter each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Due to the 72 hour time period of the trials, females had time to access all males, regardless of whether another female had chosen the male. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Female antechinus can determine the difference between scents from more and less genetically similar males and prefer chemosensory cues from genetically dissimilar males [31], suggesting that the process of mate choice in this experiment was influenced by these cues (see review in [54]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Although important, genetic relatedness between mates may be only one aspect of a set of mate preference criteria used by females, particularly in the wild. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Some males in this experiment were preferred by all females they encountered, regardless of the level of genetic relatedness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This occurred in both years, suggesting that it was not an anomaly and that certain traits possessed by some males that we were not able to identify in this study may override the importance of genetic relatedness. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Following this experiment, 47 young were born to 11 mothers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>This was fewer than expected and differs from wild populations in which all teats are generally occupied [55,56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>There are two likely reasons for this outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Firstly, animals used in this experiment were collected during severe drought conditions which significantly decreased weight, survival and litter sizes in the wild [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This probably also influenced fertility in the captive population used in this study, despite the availability of increased nutrition, because animals were collected less than one month prior to the breeding season and were in poor condition [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Secondly, most litters (8) were produced from matings in the most fertile period of receptivity, with the remaining three produced from matings late in the receptive period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>No young were produced from females paired on days 4–6 of their receptive period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This concurs with the findings of Selwood and McCallum [13] who showed that matings that occurred more than 14 days, or less than 5 days, from the spontaneous ovulation resulted in low numbers of normal fertile embryos and few young. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In antechinus and some other dasyurid marsupials oestrus is difficult to define [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Females may be receptive to mating at times when conception is unlikely (eg too early or late in respect to ovulation, or even during gestation) and the female may not be fertile [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Selwood and McCallum [13] demonstrated that for single inseminations, sperm survival time is finite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>For single inseminations outside that period ie 0 to 4 days before ovulation and 14–20 days before ovulation, the percentage of normal embryos is 0 to 58% and the averages for these periods are 44.5 and 27% respectively [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Thus, some females in this study mated outside their period of optimum fertility which is likely to have influenced their reproductive successs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Additionally, previous studies have shown that antechinus can have a lower breeding success in captivity than in the wild (e.g. [57]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Male mate choice has received less attention than mate choice by females, but may also be important [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Mate choice by males may occur when there is a female-bias in the operational sex ratio [59], when females show secondary sexual characteristics such as colour or ornamentation as seen in a variety of birds and fish [60,61,62], when there is a preference for novel over resident females [63], when female fertility is correlated with her body size [64] and/or choice may be based on genetic relatedness [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe the first case of male mate choice in a marsupial to our knowledge, with male antechinus appearing disinterested in some females and ignoring their efforts to gain attention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Males prefer novel females rather than familiar previously-mated females in green anole lizards (Anolis carolinensis; [64]), but familiarity with the female did not appear to influence male mate choice in the agile antechinus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Males re-mated with the same females if they stayed with them or re-entered the compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>This was unexpected as males have a relatively small and finite number of spermatozoa available for insemination [66] and may be expected to maximise the number of females inseminated to increase their siring success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Male mate choice also did not appear to be affected by his level of genetic relatedness to the female nor by her fertility status which can be an influence in some species [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>In oldfield mice (Peromyscus polionotus rhoads), males paired with preferred females had a greater siring success than those paired with non-preferred females based on compatibility of mates [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Here, females that were rejected by some males were accepted by others and successfully produced young, suggesting compatibility, rather than the fertility or attractiveness of the female, affected male choice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Female agonistic behaviour did not appear to deter males, a similar observation to that made by Shimmin et al. [37], and female body mass also did not appear to influence male choice or female reproductive success in this experiment with the lightest and heaviest females mating and no differences in weight between females that did and did not produce young. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The reason(s) for the preference by male agile antechinus of certain females over others is not clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The role of male mate choice and its effects on breeding success in the agile antechinus and other species warrants further examination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>This research has provided new and important insights into the effects of genetic relatedness and female mate choice on siring success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>It also provides new knowledge about the unusual mating system of the agile antechinus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Future studies of mate choice and its effects on reproductive success will shed light on the evolution of the mating system of the agile antechinus, which provides an interesting and useful paradigm for studies in other related species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We thank Michael Magrath for his assistance with statistics and the preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0122381.ref001"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>1 NeffBD, PitcherTE (2005) Genetic quality and sexual selection: an integrated framework for good genes and compatible genes. Molecular Ecology 14: 19–38. <?supplied-pmid 15643948?>15643948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref002"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>2 TregenzaT, WedellN (2000) Genetic compatibility, mate choice and patterns of parentage: invited review. Molecular Ecology 9: 1013–1027. <?supplied-pmid 10964221?>10964221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref003"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>3 DrickamerLC, GowatyPA, HolmesCM (2000) Free female mate choice in house mice affects reproductive success and offspring viability and performance. Animal Behaviour 59: 371–378. <?supplied-pmid 10675259?>10675259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref004"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>4 JonesTM, QuinnellRJ, BalmfordA (1998) Fisherian flies: benefits of female choice in a lekking sandfly Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B 265 1651–1657. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref005"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>5 ConsuegraS, Garcia de LeanizC (2008) MHC-mediated mate choice increases parasiteresistance in salmon. Proceeding of the Royal Society of London B. 275: 1397–1403. 10.1098/rspb.2008.0066 <?supplied-pmid 18364312?>18364312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref006"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>6 MaysHL, HillGE (2004) Choosing mates: good genes versus genes that are a good fit. Trends in Ecology and Evolution 19: 554–559. <?supplied-pmid 16701321?>16701321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref007"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>7 PuurtinenM, KetolaT, KotiahoJS (2009) The good-genes and compatible-genes benefits of mate choice. The American Naturalist 174: 741–752. 10.1086/606024 <?supplied-pmid 19772439?>19772439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref008"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>8 CharpentierMJE, CrawfordJC, BouletMN, DreaCM (2010) Message 'scent': lemurs detect the genetic relatedness and quality of conspecifics via olfactory cues. Animal Behaviour 80: 101–108. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref009"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>9 KempanearsB (2007) Mate choice and genetic quality: A review of the heterozygosity theory. Advances in the Study of Behavior 37: 189–278. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref010"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>10 MaysHL, AlbrechtT, LiuM, HillGE (2008) Female choice for genetic complementarity in birds: a review. Genetica. 34 147–158. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref011"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>11 StockleyP, SearleJB, MacdonaldDW, JonesCS (1993) Female multiple mating behaviour in the common shrew as a strategy to reduce inbreeding. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B 254: 173–179. <?supplied-pmid 8108451?>8108451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref012"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>12 HooglandJL (1998) Why do female Gunnison’s prairie dogs copulate with more than one male? Animal Behaviour 55: 351–359. <?supplied-pmid 9480703?>9480703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref013"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>13 SelwoodL, McCallumF (1987) Relationship between longevity of spermatozoa after insemination and the percentage of normal embryos in brown marsupial mice (Antechinus stuartii). Journal of Reproduction and Fertility 79: 495–503. <?supplied-pmid 3572881?>3572881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref014"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>14 Kraaijeveld-SmitFJL, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD (2002a) Multiple paternity in a field population of a small carnivorous marsupial, the agile antechinus, Antechinus agilis. Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology 52: 84–91. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref015"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>15 ParrottML, WardSJ, TaggartDA (2005) Multiple paternity and communal maternal care in the feathertail glider (Acrobates pygmaeus). Australian Journal of Zoology 53: 79–85. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref016"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>16 HillCE, GjerdumC, ElphickCS (2010) Extreme Levels of Multiple Mating Characterize the Mating System of the Saltmarsh Sparrow (Ammodramus Caudacutus). The Auk 127: 300–307. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref017"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>17 MeisterB, UrsenbacherS, BaurB (2012) Frequency of multiple paternity in the grass snake (Natrix natrix) Amphibia-Reptilia. 33: 308–312. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref018"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>18 NobleDWA, KeoghJS, WhitingMJ (2013) Multiple mating in a lizard increases fecundity but provides no evidence for genetic benefits. Behavioural Ecology 24: 1128–1137. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref019"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>19 ArnqvistG (1988) On multiple matings and female fitness: comments on Loman et al.. Oikos 54: 248–250. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref020"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>20 StockleyP (1997) Sexual conflict resulting from adaptation to sperm competition. Trends in Ecology and Evolution 12: 154–159. <?supplied-pmid 21238013?>21238013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref021"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>21 BrownJL (1997) A theory of mate choice based on heterozygosity. Behavioural Ecology 8: 60–65. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref022"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>22 JennionsMD (1997) Female promiscuity and genetic incompatibility. Trends in Ecology and Evolution 12: 251–253. <?supplied-pmid 21238060?>21238060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref023"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>23 LomanJ, MasdenT, HakanssonT (1988) Increased fitness from multiple matings, and genetic heterogeneity: a model of a possible mechanism. Oikos 52: 69–72. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref024"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>24 ParkerGA (1970) Sperm competition and its evolutionary consequences in the insects. Biological Reviews 45: 526–567. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref025"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>25 SlatyerRA, MautzBS, BackwellPRY, JennionsMD (2012) Estimating genetic benefits of polyandry from experimental studies: a meta-analysis. Biological Reviews 87: 1–33. 10.1111/j.1469-185X.2011.00182.x <?supplied-pmid 21545390?>21545390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref026"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>26 ShimminGA, TaggartDA, Temple-SmithPD (2000) Sperm competition and genetic diversity in the agile antechinus (Dasyuridae: Antechinus agilis). Journal of Zoology 252: 343–350. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref027"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>27 ScottMP, TanTN (1985) A radiotracer technique for the determination of male mating success in natural populations. Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology 17: 29–33. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref028"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>28 Lazenby-CohenKA, CockburnA (1988) Lek promiscuity in a semelparous mammal, Antechinus stuartii (Marsupialia, Dasyuridae). Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology 22: 195–202. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref029"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>29 Kraaijeveld-SmitFJL, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD (2003) Paternity success and the direction of sexual selection in a field population of a semelparous marsupial, Antechinus agilis. Molecular Ecology 12: 475–484. <?supplied-pmid 12535097?>12535097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref030"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>30 ParrottML, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD (2006) Genetic similarity, not male size, influences female mate choice in the agile antechinus (Antechinus agilis). Australian Journal of Zoology 54: 319–323. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref031"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>31 ParrottML, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD (2007a) Olfactory cues, genetic relatedness and female mate choice in the agile antechinus (Antechinus agilis). Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology 61: 1075–1079. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref032"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>32 Kraaijeveld-SmitFJL, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD, PaetkauD (2002b) Factors influencing paternity success in Antechinus agilis: last-male sperm precedence, timing of mating and genetic compatibility. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 15: 100–107. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref033"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>33 ParrottML, WardSJ, Temple-SmithPD, SelwoodL (2007b) Effects of drought on weight, survival and breeding success of agile antechinus (Antechinus agilis), dusky antechinus (A. swainsonii) and bush rats (Rattus fuscipes). Wildlife Research 34: 437–442. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref034"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>34 SelwoodL (1982) Brown antechinus, Antechinus stuartii: management of breeding colonies to obtain embryonic material and pouch young In: EvansDD, editor. The management of Australian mammals in captivity. Australia: Zoological Board of Victoria pp. 31–36. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref035"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>35 SelwoodL (1985) Synchronisation of oestrus, ovulation and birth in female Antechinus stuartii (Marsupialia: Dasuridae). Australian Mammalogy 8: 91–96. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref036"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>36 MarlowBJ (1961) Reproductive behaviour of the marsupial mouse, Antechinus flavipes (Waterhouse) (Marsupialia) and the development of the pouch young. Australian Journal of Zoology 9: 203–220. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref037"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>37 ShimminGA, TaggartDA, Temple-SmithPD (2002) Mating behaviour in the agile antechinus Antechinus agilis (Marsupialia: Dasyuridae). Journal of Zoology 258: 39–48. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref038"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>38 SYSTAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>(2004) SYSTAT for Windows, statistics, version 11 Illanois: SYSTAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref039"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="?"><plain>39 KellerL, ReeveHK (1995) Why do females mate with multiple males? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The sexually selected sperm hypothesis. Advances in the Study of Behaviour 24: 291–315. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref040"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="?"><plain>40 JennionsMD, PetrieM (2000) Why do females mate multiply? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>A review of the genetic benefits. Biological Reviews 75: 21–64. <?supplied-pmid 10740892?>10740892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref041"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>41 PitcherTE, NeffBD, RoddFH, RoweL (2003) Multiple mating and sequential mate choice in guppies: females trade up. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B. 270: 1623–1629. <?supplied-pmid 12908984?>12908984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref042"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>42 BirkheadT, MøllerA (1993) Female control of paternity. Trends in Ecology and Evolution 8: 100–104. 10.1016/0169-5347(93)90060-3 <?supplied-pmid 21236119?>21236119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref043"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>43 FisherDO, DoubleMC, BlombergMD, CockburnA (2006) Post-mating sexual selection increases lifetime fitness of polyandrous females in the wild. Nature 444: 89–92. <?supplied-pmid 17080089?>17080089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref044"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>44 MadsenT, ShineR, LomanJ, HakanssonT (1992) Why do female adders copulate so frequently? Nature 355: 440–441. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref045"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>45 OlssonM, GullbergA, TegelströmH, MadsenT, ShineR (1994) Can female adders multiply? Nature 369: 528. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref046"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>46 FoersterK, DelheyK, JohnsenA, LifjeldJT, KempenaersB (2003) Females increase offspring heterozygosity and fitness through extra-pair matings. Nature 425: 714–717. <?supplied-pmid 14562103?>14562103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref047"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>47 StapletonMK, OddmundK, LifjeldJT, RobertsonRJ (2007) Female tree swallows (Tachycineta bicolor) increase offspring heterozygosity through extrapair mating. Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology. 61: 1725–1733. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref048"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>48 ShimminGA, JonesM, TaggartDA, Temple-SmithPD (1999) Sperm transport and storage in the agile antechinus (Antechinus agilis). Biology of Reproduction 60: 1353–1359. <?supplied-pmid 10330092?>10330092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref049"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>49 ZehJA, ZehDW (1996) The evolution of polyandry I: intragenomic conflict and genetic incompatibility. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B 263: 1711–1717. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref050"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>50 ZehJA, ZehDW (1997) The evolution of polyandry II: post-copulatory defenses against genetic incompatibility. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B 264: 69–75. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref051"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="?"><plain>51 NordeideJT (2007) Is there more in ‘gamete quality’ than quality of the gametes? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>A review of effects of female mate choice and genetic compatibility on offspring quality. Aquaculture Research 38: 1–16. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref052"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>52 DugatkinLA, GodinJJ (1992) Reversal of Female Mate Choice by Copying in the Guppy (Poecilia reticulata) Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B. 249: 179–184. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref053"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>53 GibsonRM, BradburyJW, SandraL, VehrencampSL (1991) Mate choice in lekking sage grouse revisited: the roles of vocal display, female site fidelity, and copying. Behavioral Ecology. 2: 165–180. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref054"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>54 JohanssonBG, JonesTM (2007) The role of chemical signals in sexual selection. Biological Reviews of the Cambridge Philosophical Society 82: 265–289. <?supplied-pmid 17437561?>17437561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref055"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>55 WoolleyPA (1966) Reproduction in Antechinus spp., and other dasyurid marsupials. Symposia of the Zoological Society of London 15: 281–294. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref056"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>56 WoodDH (1970) An ecological study of Antechinus stuartii (Marsupialia) in a south-east Queensland rainforest. Australian Journal of Zoology 18: 185–207. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref057"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>57 AslinHJ (1982) Small dasyurid marsupials: their maintenance and breeding in captivity In: EvansDD, editor. The management of Australian mammals in captivity. Australia: Zoological Board of Victoria pp. 22–26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref058"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>58 EdwardDA, ChapmanT (2011) Review: The evolution and significance of male mate choice. Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution 26: 647–654.21890230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref059"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>59 KvarnemoC, AhnesjoI (1996) The dynamics of operational sex ratios and competition for mates. Trends in Ecology and Evolution 11: 404–408. <?supplied-pmid 21237898?>21237898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref060"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>60 HillGE (1993) Male mate choice and the evolution of female plumage colouration in the house finch. Evolution. 47: 1515–1525.28564892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref061"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>61 NolanPM, DobsonFS, NicolausM, KarelsTJ, McGrawKJ, JouventinP (2010) Mutual Mate Choice for Colorful Traits in King Penguins. Ethology. 116: 635–644. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref062"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>62 AmundsenT, ForsgrenE (2001) Male mate choice selects for female coloration in a fish. Evolution 98: 13155–13160. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref063"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>63 OrrellKS, JenssenTA (2002) Male mate choice by the lizard Anolis carolinensis: a preference for novel females. Animal Behaviour. 63: 1091–1102  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref064"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>64Orrell KS, Jenssen TA (2002) Male mate choice by the lizard Anolis carolinensis: a preference for novel females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Animal Behaviour: 1091–1102. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref065"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>65 RyanKK, LacyRC (2003) Monogamous male mice bias behaviour towards females according to very small differences in kinship. Animal Behaviour. 65: 379–384. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref066"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>66 TaggartDA, Temple-SmithPD (1990) Effects of breeding system and mating on total number and distribution of spermatozoa in the epididymis of the brown marsupial mouse, Antechinus stuartii. Journal of Reproduction and Fertility 88: 81–91. <?supplied-pmid 2313656?>2313656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref067"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>67 CraigAS, HermanLM, PackAA (2002) Male mate choice and male-male competition coexist in the humpback whale (Megaptera novaeangliae). Journal of Zoology 80: 745–755. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0122381.ref068"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>68 RyanKK, AltmannJ (2001) Selection for male choice based primarily on mate compatibility in the oldfield mouse, Peromyscus polionotus rhoadsi. Behavoural Ecology and Sociobiology. 50: 436–440. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
