<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4792959</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">ncomms10826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms10826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26964640</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A subunit of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex is required for interspecific gametophyte recognition in Arabidopsis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>Lena M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>Heike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>Nuno D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gagliardini</surname><given-names>Valeria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>Ueli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Plant and Microbial Biology and Zürich-Basel Plant Science Center, University of Zürich</institution>, Zollikerstrasse 107, 8008 Zürich, <country>Switzerland</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>grossnik@botinst.uzh.ch</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Present address: Boyce-Thompson Institute for Plant Research, 533 Tower Road, Ithaca, New York 14853, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="n2"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Present address: Carnegie Institution for Science, Department of Plant Biology, 260 Panama Street, Stanford, California 94305, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>10826</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>08</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>01</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016, Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Species-specific gamete recognition is a key premise to ensure reproductive success and the maintenance of species boundaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>During plant pollen tube (PT) reception, gametophyte interactions likely allow the species-specific recognition of signals from the PT (male gametophyte) by the embryo sac (female gametophyte), resulting in PT rupture, sperm release, and double fertilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This process is impaired in interspecific crosses between Arabidopsis thaliana and related species, leading to PT overgrowth and a failure to deliver the sperm cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Here we show that ARTUMES (ARU) specifically regulates the recognition of interspecific PTs in A. thaliana. ARU, identified in a genome-wide association study (GWAS), exclusively influences interspecific—but not intraspecific—gametophyte interactions. ARU encodes the OST3/6 subunit of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex conferring protein N-glycosylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that glycosylation patterns of cell surface proteins may represent an important mechanism of gametophyte recognition and thus speciation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Species-specific gamete recognition is needed to maintain species boundaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Here, Müller et al. show that ARTUMES regulates pollen tube recognition between different Arabidopsis species, representing the first gene known to exclusively influence inter- but not intraspecific gamete interaction in plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Species evolve and are maintained by a variety of hybridization barriers that prevent interspecific gene flow and thus the formation of potentially unviable or sterile hybrids1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>To date, the molecular basis of hybridization barriers is still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In plants, such barriers can either act before (pre-pollination barriers) or after pollination (post-pollination barriers). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Pre-pollination barriers can be spatial or temporal patterns preventing plants from being pollinated by pollen from a different species, whereas post-pollination barriers come into play only after an interspecific pollination event occurs and can be further divided into pre- and post-zygotic barriers2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The latter usually act at the genomic level (for example, incompatibilities leading to hybrid lethality or sterility), while pre-zygotic barriers prevent the formation of a zygote and usually rely on direct cell–cell communication between the male and female tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Most species pairs are isolated by a complex interplay of different types of isolation barriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Whereas barriers that prevent fertilization (both pre-pollination and pre-zygotic barriers) often represent the most important means to reduce interspecific gene flow, post-zygotic hybridization barriers appear to contribute less to reproductive isolation in many species pairs3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In plants, successful fertilization starts with the deposition of intraspecific (same-species) pollen (male gametophyte) onto the stigma of a gynoecium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The subsequent steps involve extensive communication between the male and female tissues, leading to pollen adherence, hydration, and the germination of a pollen tube (PT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Within its cytoplasm, the tip-growing PT transports the two sperm cells through the transmitting tract of the pistil to the embryo sac (female gametophyte), which is deeply embedded in the ovule, the precursor of seed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>During its journey, the PT is guided towards the embryo sacs by attractants secreted by female tissues4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>On arrival at the embryo sac, communication between the PT and the synergid cells of the female gametophyte is initiated (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The two synergid cells are located at the micropylar end of the embryo sac and possess a secretory region characterized by membrane invaginations and thickened cell wall structures5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This so-called filiform apparatus is the first point of contact between the male and female gametophytes, which communicate in preparation for penetration of the receptive synergid cell by the PT, PT rupture, sperm release, and double fertilization6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>While one sperm fuses with the egg cell to form the diploid zygote, the other fertilizes the homo-diploid central cell to produce the triploid endosperm, an embryo-nourishing tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The communication process between the male and female gametophytes leading to PT rupture and sperm cell discharge is known as PT reception, and its success or failure is under female gametophytic control6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, if a pollen grain originating from a different species (interspecific pollination) is placed on a plant's stigma, all the communication processes described above have the potential to act as pre-zygotic post-pollination barriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Several studies describe a species-preferential behaviour of molecular factors involved in pollen adherence to the stigma, PT growth, and PT guidance towards the ovules47891011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In interspecific crosses between closely related Ericaceae or Brassicaceae, respectively, hybridization barriers act at the stage of PT reception1213. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In such crosses, PTs are properly targeted to the female gametophyte but, upon arrival at the embryo sacs, interspecific PTs are not recognized and fail to arrest growth and discharge their sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Instead, they continue growing inside the embryo sacs (referred to as PT overgrowth) and cannot effect double fertilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we consider PT reception to be an integral part of the hybridization barrier in these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Interspecific PT overgrowth phenocopies the female gametophytic mutants feronia/sirène (fer/srn), lorelei (lre), nortia (nta), turan (tun), evan (evn), and Zea mays embryo sac 4 (ZmES4) RNAi-lines1314151617181920, which are defective in the reception of intraspecific PTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In addition, FER has been proposed to be involved in interspecific PT recognition13, and there is evidence that ZmES4 is sufficient to trigger PT growth arrest and rupture in a species-preferential manner20. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Despite the rapid advance in our understanding of the molecular basis of intraspecific PT reception21, the genetic basis of post-pollination hybridization barriers remains largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>All molecular factors that have so far been described to be involved in pre-zygotic species-discrimination, including species-preferential pollen adherence, PT guidance, growth, and reception, act primarily during intraspecific pollination and have additional species-preferential effects47891011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Here, we report the identification of the first gene required exclusively for inter- but not for intraspecific pollination, thus likely representing a specific component for the establishment of a hybridization barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>By making use of the striking natural variation of A. thaliana accessions in interspecific PT reception, we identified ARTUMES (ARU) as an indispensable factor for the recognition of interspecific A. lyrata PTs by A. thaliana embryo sacs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In contrast, aru mutants do not affect gametophytic communication in intraspecific A. thaliana crosses. ARU encodes the OST3/6 subunit of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex, which is known to regulate site- and substrate-specific N-glycosylation of proteins in yeast2223 and a similar substrate specificity has been reported for A. thaliana OST3/6 (ref. 24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Thus, a possible mechanism for the discrimination of inter- and intraspecific PTs may depend on the species-specific glycosylation of proteins on the surface of the synergid cells of the female gametophyte. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>PT overgrowth restricts gene flow between Arabidopsis species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Self-fertilizing A. thaliana and its outcrossing relative A. lyrata are separated by strong pre-pollination barriers due to their different mating systems1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In addition, they are isolated by post-pollination barriers based on direct male–female interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Although A. thaliana (Col-0) pollen germination is inhibited at the A. lyrata stigma, A. lyrata PTs are guided towards A. thaliana embryo sacs, but PT reception fails (Fig. 1c, as opposed to Fig. 1b showing successful PT reception, Supplementary Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Such unilateral incompatibility is similar to that observed in other crosses between self-compatible and self-incompatible species25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We also observed PT overgrowth in interspecific crosses between A. arenosa and A. lyrata (Supplementary Fig. 2), between which natural gene flow occurs26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This finding indicates that A. lyrata PT overgrowth in A. thaliana ovules does not only occur between species that do not interbreed in nature (A. thaliana × A. lyrata) but also between species that are only partially reproductively isolated and do interbreed (A. arenosa × A. lyrata). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Natural variation in interspecific PT reception </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To analyse interspecific hybridization barriers within the genus Arabidopsis, we assessed PT overgrowth in 86 A. thaliana accessions that were pollinated with A. lyrata pollen (Supplementary Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>PTs were visualized by staining callose in PT cell walls with aniline blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We scored the proportion of ovules that failed to recognize interspecific PTs—leading to PT overgrowth—in relation to the total number of ovules that attracted a PT in a silique (overgrowth per silique, OG/S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We found a striking variation in the ability to recognize interspecific PTs between different A. thaliana accessions, with OG/S ranging from about 10 to 90% (Fig. 1d, broad-sense heritability H2=0.7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Examples of accessions with extreme phenotypes are Lz-0 (10% OG/S, n=12 siliques) and Kz-9 (87.3% OG/S, n=10; Fig. 1e,f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>There is no obvious correlation between the geographical origin of the accessions and their phenotype (Supplementary Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To analyse whether the variation in the ability to recognize interspecific PTs is species-dependent, we pollinated a subset of A. thaliana accessions with low or high OG/S in crosses with A. lyrata (Lz-0, Kas-1, Ga-0, Lp2-6 and Col-0, Kz-1, Nd-1, respectively) also with pollen of A. halleri and A. arenosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Although OG/S in the accessions pollinated with A. lyrata or A. halleri pollen was highly comparable (Fig. 2a,b), the values were slightly lower for all accessions when pollinated by A. arenosa (Fig. 2c), indicating that A. thaliana recognizes A. arenosa PTs better than those of A. lyrata or A. halleri. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>However, accessions showing very low or high OG/S in crosses with A. lyrata, respectively, displayed a similar phenotype with A. halleri and A. arenosa as pollen donors, suggesting a common molecular PT reception mechanism for all three species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Thus, PT overgrowth is a hallmark of interspecific crosses with close Brassicaceae relatives and not a species-specific feature of A. thaliana and A. lyrata. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>To investigate whether intraspecific PT reception was affected in accessions with high OG/S (Col-0, Kz-1, Kz-9, Nd-1, Fei-0, and Sq-8), we crossed them with A. thaliana pollen (from both low and high OG/S accessions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific PT reception was normal in all the tested accessions (Supplementary Fig. 3), indicating that high OG/S frequencies result from a failure in the recognition of interspecific PTs only, and are not due to a general defect in PT reception. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>ARTUMES regulates inter- but not intraspecific PT reception </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To identify loci causing the variation in interspecific PT reception in A. thaliana, we used publicly available single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) data from the 86 accessions to perform a genome-wide association study (GWAS)27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To date, most GWAS in Arabidopsis have identified previously known candidate genes, with only a few studies identifying novel regulatory genes in the respective pathways2829. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Applying the GLM function implemented in TASSEL30, we identified a region on chromosome 1 containing 8 of the top 20 SNPs with the highest correlation to the OG/S trait (Fig. 3a and Supplementary Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>This 28-kb region (positions 22,814,316 to 22,842,689) contains six genes and one pseudogene (Fig. 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, calculation with mixed linear models that simultaneously correct for population structure and unequal genetic relatedness between individuals masked the peak, whereas it could be detected—although below the significance threshold—using a step-wise multi-locus mixed model (MLMM) specifically designed for mapping complex traits31 (Supplementary Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>With each step of MLMM, new peaks appear, consistent with a multigenic basis for interspecific PT reception. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>To narrow down the 28-kb candidate region to a single gene, we analysed OG/S in T-DNA insertion lines of three synergid-expressed genes32 in this region because the synergids control PT reception (At1g61780, At1g61790 and At1g61810; as well as At1g61795, for which no expression data was available; Supplementary Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In a homozygous T-DNA insertion allele disrupting the coding sequence of At1g61790 (Fig. 4a), an average of 84.3% (n=18 siliques) of ovules display A. lyrata PT overgrowth, significantly more than in the Col-0 wild-type control (58.7% OG/S, n=28, Student's t-test P&lt;0.001, Fig. 4b,d,e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We named the At1g61790 gene, which has previously been described as OST3/6 based on homology24, ARTUMES (ARU) after the Etruscan goddess of night, nature, and fertility33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The T-DNA allele was denoted aru-1. A second mutant allele, aru-2, carrying an EMS-induced premature stop-codon after aa residue 129 (ref. 34), also showed an increase in interspecific OG/S (96.1%, n=20, Fig. 4a,b,f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Likewise, aru-1 mutants pollinated with A. arenosa pollen showed significantly more ovules with PT overgrowth (67.6% OG/S, n=8) than the wild type (34.9% OG/S, n=12, Student's t-test P&lt;0.001, Supplementary Fig. 6), suggesting a common basis for interspecific PT recognition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In contrast, aru mutant ovules have no problem recognizing and receiving intraspecific PTs from A. thaliana (Fig. 4c,g), indicating that the PT reception pathway is fully functional within the species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To confirm that ARU function is required for interspecific PT recognition in the synergids, we expressed an ARU-GFP translational fusion protein under the control of the MYB98 and FERONIA promoters (pMYB98::ARU-GFP and pFER::ARU-GFP) in aru-1 mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>These promoters are highly active in synergids1335, and in ovules the strongest ARU-GFP signal was detected in these cells (Fig. 5a and Supplementary Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>ARU-GFP localized to perinuclear structures resembling the ER in synergids (Fig. 5a, inset), and co-localized with an ER-marker in transiently transformed onion epidermal cells (Supplementary Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with the previously reported ER-localization of ARU-GFP in infiltrated tobacco leaves24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Mutant aru-1 plants expressing a functional copy of ARU-GFP in their synergids displayed wild-type-like PT reception in interspecific crosses (Fig. 5b and Supplementary Fig. 7), indicating that ARU expression in synergid cells is sufficient to complement the aru mutant phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, the ARU-GFP translational fusion protein driven by the endogenous promoter (pARU::ARU-GFP) is highly expressed in wild-type synergids (Supplementary Fig. 7), suggesting an important role for ARU in these cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Functional complementation of the aru-1 mutant was also observed when ARU was driven by the endogenous promoter in a construct also containing 865 bp downstream sequence (pARU::ARU), although there was more line-to-line variability than when the pMYB98 promoter was used (Supplementary Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Since ARU is not fused to a fluorescent tag here, technical difficulties in measuring synergid specific expression of the transgene make it hard to explore this difference experimentally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, it is conceivable that additional regulatory sequences, up- or downstream of the ARU coding sequence that are present in the pARU::ARU construct but not in pMYB98::ARU-GFP or pFER::ARU-GFP, contributed to the observed phenotypic variability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>SNPs around ARTUMES correlate with phenotypic variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We assessed the correlation of amino acid differences in the ARU coding sequence in all accessions to determine whether differences in the protein sequence could explain the phenotypic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Within this population, we detected a total of 10 amino acid differences, four of which are significantly correlated to variation in OG/S (Pearson's correlation coefficient R, P&lt;0.05, Supplementary Data 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>However, differing residues had similar chemical properties, implying small, if any, differences in protein function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, differential expression levels could cause the observed phenotypic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we examined alignments of 1,000 bp up- and downstream sequence of ARU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We found 9 of 49 and 39 of 79 upstream and downstream SNPs, respectively, to be correlated with phenotypic variation (P&lt;0.05, Supplementary Data 1), suggesting that phenotypic variation could be due to differences in gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>To investigate this further, we used RNA extracts from pistils and ovules collected 2 days after emasculation from selected accessions (Lz-0, Kas-1, Ga-0 and Col-0, Nd-1, Fei-0, Kz-1, Kz-9) for quantitative real-time PCR and digital droplet PCR, respectively36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We found ARU mRNA levels differed between accessions (Supplementary Fig. 8), but they did not correlate with the OG/S phenotype among the selected set of accessions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Because we used RNA from whole pistils and ovules, we cannot exclude the possibility that ARU is differentially expressed in synergids only, where it is required and sufficient for interspecific PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In addition, post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression could play a role in mediating ARU protein levels. ARU has a 410 bp long 3′-UTR (3′-untranslated region)37 containing 17 SNPs that are correlated with the OG/S phenotype and might contribute to accession-specific differences in ARU protein levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the role of ARU in different accessions, we transformed high OG/S accessions (Fei-0, Kz-1, Kz-9) with pMYB98::ARU-GFP to ensure strong expression in synergid cells and assessed interspecific PT reception in these lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Of several independent transformants of all accessions, none showed a significant reduction of OG/S (Supplementary Fig. 8), which would be expected if low expression of ARU alone would be the cause of impaired interspecific PT reception in these accessions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the ARU allele (including 1,492 bp up- and 865 bp downstream sequence) from Ga-0 could not better complement the aru mutant—which is in the Col-0 background—than the Col-0 allele, as it would be expected if differences in ARU alone caused the phenotypic difference between Ga-0 and Col-0 (Supplementary Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Although these experiments could not establish a mechanistic link between variation in ARU and variation in OG/S, they are not inconsistent with the hypothesis that ARU is differentially regulated in A. thaliana accessions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Because ARU is likely only one of several factors involved in interspecific PT reception, we cannot rule out that crucial epistatic interactions with other factors were missing in the particular accessions we tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>At present, it is conceivable that population structure or co-segregating SNPs, which do not directly influence ARU expression or protein function, caused the GWAS peak on chromosome 1 and that ARU itself—although undoubtedly involved in interspecific PT reception—is not responsible for the observed natural variation among the 86 accessions tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>We consider co-segregating SNPs a highly unlikely explanation, however, because mutations disrupting other genes in the region identified by GWAS did not show a phenotype in interspecific crosses with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Signatures of selection at the ARTUMES locus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Genes involved in reproductive isolation and speciation are often subject to selective pressures driving rapid divergence38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>We tested ARU plus 1,000 bp up- and downstream sequence for signatures of positive selection by estimating Tajima's D39 for a set of 96 A. thaliana accessions40, including all accessions used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>A negative D is due to an excess of low frequency polymorphisms that can be caused by positive selection on the locus or by population expansion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Tajima's D was −2.07 for the 1,000 bp upstream of the translation start, −1.57 for the coding sequence and −1.58 for the 1,000 bp downstream of the ARU stop-codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>All values significantly deviate from the neutral model (P&lt;0.05), but do not fall into the 5% tail of the estimated genomic distribution of D in A. thaliana40 (cut-off value: −2.08). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Thus, although the 1,000 bp upstream region was very close to this cut-off, the observed negative values might be influenced by demographic factors that shaped the entire genome rather than selective pressure acting on the ARU locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In addition, we estimated Fay and Wu's H, another test statistic to detect positive selection41, which is not as sensitive to demographic factors as Tajima's D42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>All values for H were strongly negative (upstream region: −20.20, coding sequence: −21.79, downstream region: −20.73, P&lt;0.02), and fall into the very extreme tails of both an empirical and a simulated distribution of H calculated with 12 accessions, which represent a world-wide distribution and are a subset of the accessions used in this study42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Such strongly negative values for H indicate that positive selection may indeed have acted on each of the regions of the ARU locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The fact that D for the upstream region was very close to the 5% tail and the strongly negative values for H provide evidence for possible positive selection and indicate that ARU may have undergone a recent selective sweep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the lack of variation in ARU amino acid sequence and expression level but is difficult, although not impossible, to reconcile with the fact that we identified ARU in a GWAS for variation in the OG/S phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>As pointed out above, this may be due to epistatic interactions with additional factors involved in this complex process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, as in animal speciation genes, selective pressures appear to have contributed to shaping the genetic basis that underlies interspecific PT reception in A. thaliana. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Interspecific PT reception depends on protein N-glycosylation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>ARU encodes the OST3/6 subunit of the hetero-oligomeric plant oligosaccharyltransferase complex (OST), which catalyses the co- or posttranslational transfer of pre-assembled carbohydrate oligomers (Glc3Man9GlcNAc2) to asparagine (N) residues of polypeptides43. N-glycosylation affects the substrate protein's folding, targeting, and/or processing through the ER. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the N-linked glycan can be modified in the Golgi apparatus in a cell-type and species-specific manner, accounting for the functionality and binding specificity of the glycoprotein43. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The yeast OST consists of eight subunits and the homologues of OST3/6, Ost3p and Ost6p, differ in their protein substrate and site-specific glycosylation efficiency2223. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In plants, OST3/6 confers similar substrate specificity since in the A. thaliana ost3/6 (aru) mutant only a subset of glycoproteins is misglycosylated and therefore non-functional24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Among these are the pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP) receptor kinase EF-TU RECEPTOR (EFR), and KORRIGAN1, an endo-β-1,4-glucanase involved in cellulose biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In line with this, aru has previously been identified in an EMS-screen for cell wall mutants34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Some of the known members in the PT reception pathway, FER and NTA, have been implicated in the perception of cell wall perturbations, pathogen resistance, and innate immunity174445. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>After pollination with A. lyrata, fer heterozygous mutants show higher OG/S (74.9%) than wild-type segregants (61.2%, P&lt;0.01, Supplementary Fig. 9), suggesting that inter- and intraspecific PT reception both involve the FER pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Moreover, FER (a receptor-like kinase with an extracellular malectin-binding domain) and LRE (a glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored protein) are likely to be glycosylated131646 and could be substrates of ARU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>To test this, we analysed the expression and localization of fluorescent FER and LRE fusion proteins in aru ovules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>We included NTA, which itself does not contain any putative glycosylation sites but whose subcellular localization depends on FER signalling17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>All fusion proteins displayed a wild-type-like subcellular localization in the synergids of aru embryo sacs: FER-GFP and LRE-Citrine were observed at the micropylar end of the synergids, and NTA-GFP was re-localized there upon PT arrival (Supplementary Fig. 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that, in the absence of functional ARU, these proteins are properly targeted to their subcellular compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot rule out that the extracellular domain of FER is un- or misglycosylated at specific glycosylation sites in aru, which may allow the protein to recognize intra- but not interspecific PTs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The synergid has a specialized secretory region at its micropylar end, the filiform apparatus, which contains a large amount of secreted material and is believed to be the site of PT recognition6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>It is possible that even subtle differences in ARU protein levels could lead to the misglycosylation of target proteins, including FER, such that a few specific glycosylation sites remain unglycosylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Given the high secretory activity of the filiform apparatus, such small changes could have a large effect on PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Further work will be necessary to shed more light on the target proteins of ARU and to elucidate the role of specific glycosylated surface proteins in PT reception. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>A possible interpretation of our results is that FER, and/or yet unknown synergid (co-)receptors, bind putative ligands from intraspecific PTs both via specific interactions with carbohydrates on the receptor protein and via direct protein–protein interactions, a mechanism similar to the proposed ‘domain-specific model' in mammalian sperm-egg binding47 (Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Ligands from interspecific PTs might not be able to sufficiently interact via protein–protein contacts alone but could still be recognized to some extent via the carbohydrate moieties, explaining the partial A. lyrata PT reception success in Col-0 ovules (Fig. 6b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It is conceivable that in aru, and potentially also in A. thaliana accessions with a similar phenotype, changes in the glycosylation status of the receptor could completely abolish the ability to recognize and receive interspecific PTs (Fig. 6d), while ligands from A. thaliana PTs are still efficiently recognized via protein–protein interactions, leading to normal PT reception (Fig. 6c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The crosstalk between gametophytes constitutes a specific form of cell–cell communication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Cellular interactions are often mediated by specific binding of an extracellular ligand to a receptor, triggering downstream signalling cascades in the recipient cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Most extracellular ligands and receptors are heavily glycosylated48, which influences their binding specificities and conformation, such that already the absence of a single glycosylation motif can reduce or abolish a receptor's function and ligand-binding affinity4950. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that both protein–protein interactions and recognition mediated by carbohydrates may be crucial factors to ensure species-specific PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Thus, divergent evolution of receptor–ligand pairs, as well as of the factors controlling their glycosylation status, could establish new species barriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Deciphering the molecular basis of speciation in plants might enable us to overcome existing hybridization barriers, which could eventually be of great agronomic importance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Plant material and growth conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The A. thaliana accessions were part of the Nordborg collection for GWAS2740. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Amplified seed stocks were kindly donated by Ortrun Mittelsten Scheid (Gregor Mendel Institute, Vienna). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>After stratification (2 days at 4 °C), the seeds were allowed to germinate for 6 days on MS plates (22 °C, 16 h light, MS from Carolina Biological Supply). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Because some accessions require vernalization, all the seedlings were kept in a vernalization chamber for 5 weeks (4 °C, 16 h light) on MS plates before they were transferred to the soil (ED73, Universalerde). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The accessions were grouped into early- (four incomplete blocks A, B, C and D), mid-, and late flowering plants (three complete blocks A, B, C each) according to the flowering time27, and were grown in a greenhouse chamber (22 °C, 16 h light) in an incomplete randomized block design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>See Supplementary Table 1 for the assignment of accessions to the blocks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A. lyrata13, A. halleri (a gift from Marcus Koch, University of Heidelberg), and A. arenosa (donated by Matthias Helling, University of Zurich) plants were stratified for 10 days and grown in the same greenhouse chamber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Plants were vernalized to induce flowering (see above). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>SALK-lines were obtained from NASC: SALK_067271 (At1g61790, aru-1), SALK_137883C (At1g61780), SALK_052207C and SALK_026074C (At1g61795), SALK_104077 (At1g61810). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The EMS allele aru-2 (ref. 34) was a gift from Peter McCourt (University of Toronto). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The plants were grown as described before17. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Crosses and aniline blue staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Flowers were emasculated and the pistils were pollinated 2 days after emasculation (dae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Siliques were collected two days after pollination and fixed for aniline blue staining in 9:1 ethanol:acidic acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Aniline blue staining was performed as described previously17, and the samples were analysed with a Leica DM6000B microscope (Leica Microsystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For GWAS phenotyping, 9–20 siliques of a minimum of three individuals were analysed for each accession (Exceptions: Zdr-1: seven siliques, Got-7: four siliques from two individuals). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>GWAS analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Association mapping was conducted using the mean values of the proportions of ovules with PT overgrowth per silique (OG/S) as phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>An A. thaliana 250 K Affymetrix SNP genotyping data set27 was downloaded from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cynin.gmi.oeaw.ac.at/home/resources/atpolydb">https://cynin.gmi.oeaw.ac.at/home/resources/atpolydb</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>GWAS analyses were performed using a compressed mixed linear model, using population parameters previously determined5152, and a kinship matrix to account for family relatedness, in the R package GAPIT53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The mixed linear models were run with and without principal components as fixed effects to correct for population structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Multiple testing was controlled using the Bonferroni correction and false-discovery rate54. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>GWAS analyses were also run using a general linear model in the web-based interface TASSEL3.0 (ref. 30) and an accelerated mixed model with Box-Cox transformed phenotypes in GWAPP55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>MLMM analysis was conducted as previously described31. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Constructs for stable plant transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>For pMYB98/pFER::ARU-GFP the complete coding sequence of ARU without the stop-codon was amplified using gene-specific primers with attB-sites for Gateway cloning: 5′- GGGGACAAGTTTGTACAAAAAAGCAGGCTTCATGGCGCTCAAATCAAAACTCGTC -3′ and 5′- GGGGACCACTTTGTACAAGAAAGCTGGGTCACGCCAACTCGATGGCCAATACGGA -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We introduced the PCR-fragment into pDONR207, and subsequently into the destination vector (using the E. coli strain DH5-alpha F'Iq from New England Biolabs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The destination vector was a modification of the plant Gateway vector pMDC83, which contains the 2x35S-promotor before and GFP after the Gateway cassette56. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>For our purpose, we exchanged the original 2x35S-promoter with the promoters of FER13 and MYB98 (ref. 35) to express ARU specifically in synergid cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The MYB98 promoter was amplified from Col-0 with primers 5′- TTTAAGCTTATACACTCATTGTCCTTCG -3′ and 5′- CCCTCTAGATGTTTTGGAAAGGAGAAAAAA -3′, introducing a HindIII and XbaI restriction site, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The FER promoter was amplified from the pFER::FER-GFP construct13 using specific primers 5′- TTTGGTAAGCTTCGATTTAAGCGAG -3′ and 5′- TTTTCTAGACGATCAAGAGCACTTCTCCGGG -3′, which introduce HindIII and XbaI restriction sites as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The 2x35S-promoter was cut out of pMDC83 (ref. 56) with HindIII/XbaI (New England Biolabs), and the PCR fragments were introduced into the dephosphorylated vector backbone by ligation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>pDONR207 carrying the ARU coding sequence and the modified destination vector were combined in an LR reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The resulting vectors, pFER::ARU-GFP and pMYB98::ARU-GFP were transformed into Agrobacterium tumefaciens strain CV1310, and homozygous aru-1 plants were transformed by the floral dip method57. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The complementation assays were conducted in the T2 and T3 generations with plants homozygous for the complementation construct and the aru-1 mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>For experiments with pMYB98::ARU-GFP in accessions with high OG/S, the construct was transformed into Fei-0, Kz-1, and Kz-9, and OG/S was assessed in heterozygous plants (T1 generation). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>For the constructs with ARU under the control of its endogenous promoter, the ARU fragment (including 1,492 bp of upstream, ARU CDS, and 865 bp of downstream sequence) was amplified from Col-0 and Ga-0 genomic DNA using primers 5′- TTTTACTAGTAGGCAATTCCATCAGTTGTT -3′ and 5′- TTTTGGTACCGTTACTTCACTTTCTCGAGT -3′, introducing a SpeI and a KpnI restriction site, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The fragments were cloned into pMDC99 (ref. 56) using restriction-ligation and transformed into aru mutants (Col-0 background). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>pARU::ARU-GFP was cloned by amplification of a part of ARU coupled to GFP-tNOS from pFER::ARU-GFP with primers 5′- GCGTTAACGCTTTACCTCA -3′ (including the natural HpaI site in ARU) and 5′- TTTGGATCCAGTAACATAGATGACACCGCG -3′ (introducing a BamHI site after tNOS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This fragment was introduced by ligation into the pMDC99 vector carrying the genomic fragment of ARU (Col-0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>By cutting this vector with HpaI and BamHI, part of the ARU coding sequence and the downstream sequence were removed and replaced with the respective fragment of ARU coupled to GFP-tNOS, resulting in pARU(1,492 bp)::ARU-GFP, which was transformed into Col-0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>pLRE::LRE-Citrine was cloned with overlapping PCR fragments that were assembled using the Gibson cloning Master Mix from New England Biolabs according to the manufacturer's recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The 779-bp long promoter sequence with the predicted signal peptide from LRE16 was amplified with primers 5′- GTGCTGCAAGGCGATTAAGTCCGTGTGCTCTGTCTGCATT -3′ and 5′- CACAGCTCCACCTCCACCTCCAGGCCGGCCTATGGAACTTGAAGAGGAGAGAGA -3′, introducing an overhang complementary to the vector pMDC99 (ref. 56). Citrine was amplified from the transgenic line CS36962 (ordered from Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center, ABRC), using gene-specific primers with overhang primers for the signal peptide of LRE and overhang primers for the GPI-anchor of LRE: 5′- GGCCGGCCTGGAGGTGGAGGTGGAGCTGTGAGCAAGGGCGAGGAGCT -3′ and 5′- GGCCCCAGCGGCCGCAGCAGCACCAGCAGGATCCTTGTACAGCTCGTCCA -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The GPI-anchor of LRE was amplified with overhang primers for pMDC99: 5′- TGCTGGTGCTGCTGCGGCCGCTGGGGCCTCGGGTATGTCTTTTTGTTGTC -3′ and 5′- AGCTCCACCGCGGTGGCGGCCGCTCTAGAAGTCTCGCTTCTTCTTTTGT -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>pMDC99 was amplified with overhang primers for the LRE promoter and the GPI-anchor using primers: 5′- ACTTAATCGCCTTGCAGCAC -3′ and 5′- TCTAGAGCGGCCGCCACCGCGG -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>All the constructs were verified by sequencing. pFER::FER-GFP and pNTA::NTA-GFP were described previously1317. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>ARU-GFP subcellular localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We used the pFER::ARU-GFP construct for microprojectile bombardment of onion epidermal cells and co-localized it with the ER-marker pER-rk (mCherry) obtained from ABRC58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Biolistic bombardment of onion epidermis was performed as described17. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>For visualizing GFP expression in the synergids, flowers were emasculated and pistils were dissected 2 dae to ensure the development of mature, unfertilized embryo sacs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The tissue was mounted on slides in 1 M glycine, pH 9.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Images were captured on Leica Confocal Microscopes SP2 and SP5 (Leica Microsystems). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and reverse transcriptase PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>RNA from pistils (25 pistils, 2 dae), inflorescences, and ovules (extracted from 30 pistils, 2 dae) was extracted using the Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Pistil and inflorescence cDNA was reverse transcribed using Oligo-dT primers and Superscript II reverse transcriptase from Invitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Ovule cDNA was amplified using the Ovation Pico SL WTA system V2 from Nugen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcriptase PCR (RT–PCR) of ARU was done using primers 5′- CAATGTGCTTGTTCGAGTG -3′ and 5′- ATCCAGTCTTCCAGTTATCCA -3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>For quantitative RT and digital droplet PCR of ARU in A. thaliana accessions, the primers 5′- GTTTGTTACCAATGTGCTTGTTCG -3′ and 5′- TCCATATCCAGTCTTCCAGTTATCC -3′ were used and expression levels were normalized against UBIQUITIN C (UBC9, primers: 5′- ATGCTTGGAGTCCTGCTTGG -3′ and 5′- TGCCATTGAATTGAACCCTCTC -3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>For digital droplet PCR on ovule cDNA, the UBC9 assay was performed as an EvaGreen assay, whereas ARU transcripts were detected using a gene-specific probe (5′-FAM- TACTGCACAAAGGTTG -MGB-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The samples were analysed with the QX200 system from Bio-Rad. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Population genetic analyses and statistical tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Determination of ARU gene structure and UTRs is based on annotations in the ARAMEMNON database37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Sequences of ARU and 1,000 bp up- and downstream flanking regions were downloaded from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://signal.salk.edu/atg1001/3.0/gebrowser.php">http://signal.salk.edu/atg1001/3.0/gebrowser.php</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>For accessions for which no sequences or only sequences with missing data were available, we amplified the whole region from genomic DNA using primers 5′- TTTGCTATAGGCACATGTGT -3′ and 5′- GACCCGAAATTGTCAAATGA -3′, and sequenced the resulting PCR products of Bay-0, Fab-2, Fab-4, Omo-2-3, Knox-10, Kz-1, LL-0, Lz-0, Mr-0, Mrk-0, Zdr-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The upstream region was sequenced additionally from Got-7, Pu2-23, and Spr1-6 (primer 5′- TTTGCTATAGGCACATGTGT -3′ and 5′- CGGAGGTTAGGAATTTTGAGA -3′), and the downstream region from Got-7, Pu2-23, Kz-9, Mz-0, Pro-0, Van-0, and Var2-1 (primer 5′- CAATGTGCTTGTTCGAGTG -3′ and 5′- GACCCGAAATTGTCAAATGA -3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Tajima's D and Fay and Wu's H were calculated separately for the 1,000 bp up- and downstream as well as the coding sequence with the set of 96 accessions40 using DnaSP 5.10 (ref. 59). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Several accessions that had big indels in the up- and downstream regions were left out from the analysis (Mr-0, Got-7, Pu2-23, and Spr1-6 for the upstream, Var2-1, Nok-3, and Got-7 for the downstream region). A. lyrata was used as outgroup. P values against the null model were obtained by running 10,000 coalescent simulations and for Tajima's D, the 5% quantile was calculated using previously published estimates for D40. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Additional information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Müller, L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>M. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>A subunit of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex is required for interspecific gametophyte recognition in Arabidopsis. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Commun. 7:10826 doi: 10.1038/ncomms10826 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d33e18" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Figures 1-10, Supplementary Tables 1-2 and Supplementary References </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d33e24" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Correlation of SNPs (1000 bp downstream region) with OG/S phenotype of accessions </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-s2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We thank Sharon A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Kessler and Aurélien Boisson-Dernier for critically reading the manuscript and helpful discussions; and Karl J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Schmid and Dounia Saleh for their help and insight with population genetic analyses; Ortrun Mittelsten Scheid, Marcus Koch, Peter McCourt, and Matthias Helling for providing seeds; Daniela Guthörl, Arturo Bolanos, Christof Eichenberger, and Peter Kopf for general lab support; and Christian Frei and Karl Huwiler for greenhouse maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the University of Zürich, partial support for L.M.M. and H.L. through Research Modules of the SNF ProDoc Programs ‘Plant Science and Policy' and ‘Molecular Life Science', respectively, to U.G., and grants from the Swiss National Science Foundation and the European Research Council to U.G. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>LowryD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>B., ModliszewskiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>L., WrightK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>M., WuC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; WillisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>H. The strength and genetic basis of reproductive isolating barriers in flowering plants. Philos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Sci. 363, 3009–3021 (2008) .18579478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>RiesebergL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>H. &amp; BlackmanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>K. Speciation genes in plants. Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Bot. 106, 439–455 (2010) .20576737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>WidmerA., LexerC. &amp; CozzolinoS. Evolution of reproductive isolation in plants. Heredity 102, 31–38 (2009) .18648386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>OkudaS. . Defensin-like polypeptide LUREs are pollen tube attractants secreted from synergid cells. Nature 458, 357–361 (2009) .19295610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>HuangB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Q. &amp; RusselS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>D. Female germ unit: organization, isolation, and function. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Cytol. 140, 233–293 (1992) . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>KesslerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; GrossniklausU. She's the boss: signaling in pollen tube reception. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Biol. 14, 622–627 (2011) .21855398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>ZinklG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>M., ZwiebelB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>I., GrierD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>G. &amp; PreussD. Pollen-stigma adhesion in Arabidopsis: a species-specific interaction mediated by lipophilic molecules in the pollen exine. Development 126, 5431–5440 (1999) .10556067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>MartonM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>L., FastnerA., UeblerS. &amp; DresselhausT. Overcoming hybridization barriers by the secretion of the maize pollen tube attractant ZmEA1 from Arabidopsis ovules. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Biol. 22, 1194–1198 (2012) .22633810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>LausserA., KliwerI., SrilunchangK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>O. &amp; DresselhausT. Sporophytic control of pollen tube growth and guidance in maize. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Bot. 61, 673–682 (2010) .19926683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>KanaokaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>M. . Identification and characterization of TcCRP1, a pollen tube attractant from Torenia concolor. Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Bot. 108, 739–747 (2011) .21546430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>HigashiyamaT. . Species preferentiality of the pollen tube attractant derived from the synergid cell of Torenia fournieri. Plant Physiol. 142, 481–491 (2006) .16935992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>WilliamsE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>G., KaulV., RouseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; PalserB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>F. Overgrowth of pollen tubes in embryo sacs of Rhododendron following interspecific pollinations. Aust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Bot. 34, 413–423 (1986) . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Escobar-RestrepoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>M. . The FERONIA receptor-like kinase mediates male-female interactions during pollen tube reception. Science 317, 656–660 (2007) .17673660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>HuckN., MooreJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>M., FedererM. &amp; GrossniklausU. The Arabidopsis mutant feronia disrupts the female gametophytic control of pollen tube reception. Development 130, 2149–2159 (2003) .12668629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>RotmanN. . Female control of male gamete delivery during fertilization in Arabidopsis thaliana. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Biol. 13, 432–436 (2003) .12620194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>CapronA. . Maternal control of male-gamete delivery in Arabidopsis involves a putative GPI-anchored protein encoded by the LORELEI gene. Plant Cell 20, 3038–3049 (2008) .19028964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>KesslerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>A. . Conserved molecular components for pollen tube reception and fungal invasion. Science 330, 968–971 (2010) .21071669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>LindnerH. . TURAN and EVAN mediate pollen tube reception in the synergid cells but play distinct roles in the male gametophyte. PLoS Biol. 13, e1002139 (2015) .25919390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>LindnerH. . SNP-ratio mapping (SRM): identifying lethal alleles and mutations in complex genetic backgrounds by next-generation sequencing. Genetics 191, 1381–1386 (2012) .22649081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>AmienS. . Defensin-like ZmES4 mediates pollen tube burst in maize via opening of the potassium channel KZM1. PLoS Biol. 8, e1000388 (2010) .20532241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>QuL.-J., LiL., LanZ. &amp; DresselhausT. Peptide signalling during the pollen tube journey and double fertilization. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Bot. 66, 5139–5150 (2015) .26068467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>SchulzB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; AebiM. Analysis of glycosylation site occupancy reveals a role for Ost3p and Ost6p in site-specific N-glycosylation efficiency. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Proteomics 8, 357–364 (2009) .18854577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>SchwarzM., KnauerR. &amp; LehleL. Yeast oligosaccharyltransferase consists of two functionally distinct sub-complexes, specified by either the Ost3p or Ost6p subunit. FEBS Lett. 579, 6564–6568 (2005) .16297388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>FaridA. . Specialized roles of the conserved subunit OST3/6 of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex in innate immunity and tolerance to abiotic stresses. Plant Physiol. 162, 24–38 (2013) .23493405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>LewisD. &amp; CroweL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>K. Unilateral interspecific incompatibility in flowering plants. Heredity 12, 233–256 (1958) . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>SchmicklR. &amp; KochM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>A. Arabidopsis hybrid speciation processes. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>USA 108, 14192–14197 (2011) .21825128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>AtwellS. . Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in Arabidopsis thaliana inbred lines. Nature 465, 627–631 (2010) .20336072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>VersluesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>E., LaskyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>R., JuengerT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>E., LiuT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>W. &amp; KumarM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>N. Genome wide association mapping combined with reverse genetics identifies new effectors of low water potential-induced proline accumulation in Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Physiol. 164, 144–159 (2013) .24218491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>MeijonM., SatbhaiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>B., TsuchimatsuT. &amp; BuschW. Genome-wide association study using cellular traits identifies a new regulator of root development in Arabidopsis. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Genet. 46, 77–81 (2013) .24212884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>BradburyP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>J. . TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples. Bioinformatics 23, 2633–2635 (2007) .17586829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>SeguraV. . An efficient multi-locus mixed-model approach for genome-wide association studies in structured populations. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Genet. 44, 825–830 (2012) .22706313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>WuestS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>E. . Arabidopsis female gametophyte gene expression map reveals similarities between plant and animal gametes. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Biol. 20, 506–512 (2010) .20226671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>GerhardE. Über die Gottheiten der Etrusker Druckerei der Königlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften (1847) . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>AustinR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>S. . Next-generation mapping of Arabidopsis genes. Plant J. 67, 715–725 (2011) .21518053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>KasaharaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>D., PortereikoM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>F., Sandaklie-NikolovaL., RabigerD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>S. &amp; DrewsG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>N. MYB98 is required for pollen tube guidance and synergid cell differentiation in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 17, 2981–2992 (2005) .16214903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>HindsonB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>J. . High-throughput droplet digital PCR system for absolute quantitation of DNA copy number. Anal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Chem. 83, 8604–8610 (2011) .22035192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>SchwackeR. . ARAMEMNON, a novel database for Arabidopsis integral membrane proteins. Plant Physiol. 131, 16–26 (2003) .12529511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>SwansonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; VacquierV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>D. The rapid evolution of reproductive proteins. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Genet. 3, 137–144 (2002) .11836507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>TajimaF. Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism. Genetics 123, 585–595 (1989) .2513255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>NordborgM. . The pattern of polymorphism in Arabidopsis thaliana. PLoS Biol. 3, e196 (2005) .15907155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>FayJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; WuC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>I. Hitchhiking under positive Darwinian selection. Genetics 155, 1405–1413 (2000) .10880498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>SchmidK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>J., Ramos-OnsinsS., Ringys-BecksteinH., WeisshaarB. &amp; Mitchell-OldsT. A multilocus sequence survey in Arabidopsis thaliana reveals a genome-wide departure from a neutral model of DNA sequence polymorphism. Genetics 169, 1601–1615 (2005) .15654111 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>AebiM. N-linked protein glycosylation in the ER. Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Acta 1833, 2430–2437 (2013) .23583305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>KeinathN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>F. . PAMP (pathogen-associated molecular pattern)-induced changes in plasma membrane compartmentalization reveal novel components of plant immunity. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Chem. 285, 39140–39149 (2010) .20843791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>CheungA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Y. &amp; WuH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>M. THESEUS1, FERONIA and relatives: a family of cell wall-sensing receptor kinases? Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 14, 632–641 (2011) .21963060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>LindnerH., MüllerL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>M., Boisson-DernierA. &amp; GrossniklausU. CrRLK1L receptor-like kinases: not just another brick in the wall. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 15, 659–669 (2012) .22884521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>ClarkG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>F. Molecular models for mouse sperm-oocyte binding. Glycobiology 21, 3–5 (2011) .21188842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>ZielinskaD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>F., GnadF., SchroppK., WisniewskiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; MannM. Mapping N-glycosylation sites across seven evolutionarily distant species reveals a divergent substrate proteome despite a common core machinery. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Cell 46, 542–548 (2012) .22633491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>van der HoornR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>A. . Structure-function analysis of Cf-9, a receptor-like protein with extracytoplasmic leucine-rich repeats. Plant Cell 17, 1000–1015 (2005) .15722474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>HawekerH. . Pattern recognition receptors require N-glycosylation to mediate plant immunity. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Chem. 285, 4629–4636 (2010) .20007973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>ZhangZ. . Mixed linear model approach adapted for genome-wide association studies. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Genet. 42, 355–360 (2010) .20208535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>KangH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>M. . Variance component model to account for sample structure in genome-wide association studies. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Genet. 42, 348–354 (2010) .20208533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>LipkaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>E. . GAPIT: genome association and prediction integrated tool. Bioinformatics 28, 2397–2399 (2012) .22796960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>BenjaminiY. &amp; HochbergY. Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Statist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Soc. 57, 289–300 (1995) . </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>SerenU. . GWAPP: a web application for genome-wide association mapping in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 24, 4793–4805 (2012) .23277364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>CurtisM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>D. &amp; GrossniklausU. A Gateway cloning vector set for high-throughput functional analysis of genes in planta. Plant Physiol. 133, 462–469 (2003) .14555774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>CloughS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; BentA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>F. Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant J. 16, 735–743 (1998) .10069079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>NelsonB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>K., CaiX. &amp; NebenfuhrA. A multicolored set of in vivo organelle markers for co-localization studies in Arabidopsis and other plants. Plant J. 51, 1126–1136 (2007) .17666025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>RozasJ. &amp; RozasR. DnaSP, DNA sequence polymorphism: an interactive program for estimating population genetics parameters from DNA sequence data. Comput. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Biosci. 11, 621–625 (1995) .8808578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Author contributions U.G. initiated and supervised the project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>L.M.M. and U.G. conceived the experiments and wrote the manuscript; H.L. and N.D.P. critically read and commented on the manuscript; L.M.M., H.L., N.D.P., and V.G. performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>All the authors were involved in data analysis and interpretation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PT reception in interspecific crosses.</title><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>(a) Diagram of the female gametophyte with its cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>The synergids with their membrane-rich filiform apparatus are crucial for communication with the arriving PT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(b) Ovule with normal PT reception, visualized by callose staining of the PT cell walls with Aniline Blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>The PT stopped its growth and ruptured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Dashed line indicates outline of the ovule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>(c) Ovule with PT overgrowth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>The PT continues growing inside the female gametophyte. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Dashed line indicates outline of the ovule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>(d) Natural variation in the proportion of ovules with PT overgrowth per silique (OG/S) in 86 A. thaliana accessions that were pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>OG/S varies between 10% and more than 90%, depending on the genotype of the mother. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(e) A silique of Lz-0 pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Most of the ovules show normal PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Ovules with PT overgrowth are marked with an arrowhead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>(f) A silique of Kz-9 pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Most of the ovules display PT overgrowth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark ovules with normal PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Per accession and per pollen donor, 5–10 siliques were analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 50 μm (b and c), 250 μm (e and f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Natural variation in PT reception with different interspecific pollen donors.</title><p><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>(a) A subset of A. thaliana accessions pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Per accession, four to eight siliques were analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Box plots are ordered by the mean OG/S value and colour-coded to facilitate comparison with b and c. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>(b,c) The same subset pollinated with pollen from A. halleri (b) and A. arenosa (c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>The accessions show comparable OG/S with all three interspecific pollen donors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>GWAS identifies an associated region on chromosome 1.</title><p><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>(a) Manhattan plot showing a peak on chromosome 1 (grey box) with its highest correlated SNP showing significance at P&lt;0.1 (after Bonferroni correction; dotted line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>The peak corresponds to a 28 kb region spanning position 22,842,689–22,814,316 (magnified in the second panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>The eight SNPs that were identified to be among the 20 most highly correlated ones in the GWAS are annotated with their PERL identifiers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>(b) Genes and pseudogenes (grey) in the 28 kb region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Genes expressed in synergids are marked in red, genes without available expression data are in orange32. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><italic>ARTUMES</italic> mutants are impaired in interspecific PT reception.</title><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>(a) Genomic region of ARTUMES (At1g61790) with the two mutant alleles aru-1 and aru-2, and the surrounding polymorphisms identified by GWAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>(b) PT overgrowth of Col-0 wild-type (n=28 siliques) and aru mutant plants in interspecific crosses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Both aru mutant alleles show significantly higher proportions of ovules with PT overgrowth per silique (OG/S, Student's t-test ***P&lt;0.001; n=18 and 20 siliques, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>(c) PT overgrowth of aru-1 in inter- and intraspecific crosses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>The mutant is impaired in interspecific crosses with A. lyrata pollen (n=9 siliques), but not in intraspecific crosses with Col-0 (n=6) or self pollen (n=9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(d) A silique of Col-0 pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Ovules with normal PT reception (marked with asterisks) and with PT overgrowth are visible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>(e,f) aru-1 and aru-2 siliques pollinated with A. lyrata pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Both mutant alleles show high proportions of ovules with PT overgrowth in interspecific crosses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Ovules with normal PT reception are marked with asterisks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>(g) A silique of aru-1 pollinated with intraspecific Col-0 pollen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>All ovules display normal PT reception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 250 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Synergid-specific expression of <italic>ARTUMES</italic> complements the mutant phenotype.</title><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>(a) An ovule expressing pMYB98::ARU-GFP in the synergids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Inset: ARU-GFP localizes to perinuclear structures resembling the ER. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>(b) PT overgrowth in interspecific crosses using aru-1 (n=22 siliques), Col-0 (n=28), and three independent transformant lines of pMYB98::ARU-GFP in the aru-1 background as mother plants and A. lyrata as pollen donor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>All the three transformant lines complement the mutant phenotype (n=16, 22, and 27 siliques, respectively); line 2 shows even lower OG/S than the wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Significance levels in comparison with Col-0 (Student's t-test ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Potential mechanisms of interspecific PT reception and the role of glycosylation.</title><p><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>(a) In wild-type Col-0 synergid cells, a receptor is glycosylated by ARU and can bind putative signals from the A. thaliana PT with its carbohydrate moieties and via protein–protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>(b) A. lyrata PT signals might not be properly recognized by protein–protein contacts but partially by carbohydrate interactions, thus leading to PT overgrowth in some ovules and normal PT reception in others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>(c) In aru mutants, the synergid receptor is un- or misglycosylated; nevertheless, A. thaliana PTs can be efficiently received through protein–protein interactions of the receptor with the PT signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>(d) In aru mutants pollinated with A. lyrata pollen, PT reception is neither possible by carbohydrate, nor by protein–protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Therefore, almost all ovules show PT overgrowth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms10826-f6"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
