<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cancer Res. Clin. Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Cancer Research and Clinical Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0171-5216</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-1335</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4954838</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2199</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00432-016-2199-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article – Clinical Oncology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Impact of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis on advanced non-small cell lung cancer survival </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kanaji</surname><given-names>Nobuhiro</given-names></name><address><phone>+81-87-891-2145</phone><email>kanaji@med.kagawa-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadokoro</surname><given-names>Akira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>Nobuyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murota</surname><given-names>Makiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>Tomoya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>Takehiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Naoki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tojo</surname><given-names>Yasunori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>Shingo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hasui</surname><given-names>Yusuke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kadowaki</surname><given-names>Norimitsu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bandoh</surname><given-names>Shuji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Hematology, Rheumatology and Respiratory Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Kagawa University, 1750-1 Ikenobe, Miki-cho, Kita-gun, Kagawa, 761-0793 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Radiology, Faculty of Medicine, Kagawa University, Kagawa, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Respiratory Medicine, National Hospital Organization Takamatsu Medical Hospital, Kagawa, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Internal Medicine, Takamatsu Heiwa Hospital, Kagawa, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, Kagawa Prefectural Shirotori Hospital, Kagawa, Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>142</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Purpose </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The clinical features of patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and interstitial lung disease (ILD) have not fully been elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to investigate the clinical features of these patients, particularly with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Data on 218 patients with pathologically confirmed diagnoses of NSCLC who had been treated with chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy were retrospectively analyzed for progression-free survival (PFS), overall survival (OS), responses to first-line therapy, and incidence of acute exacerbations (AEs). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Fifty-three of the 218 patients were diagnosed with ILD, and 34 of them with IPF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The frequency of epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutation was significantly lower in ILD and IPF patients than in non-ILD patients (2 or 0 vs. 32 %, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Median PFS and OS were significantly shorter in both ILD and IPF patients than in non-ILD patients (118, 92, and 196 days for PFS, and 267, 223, and 539 days for OS, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Multivariate analysis showed that poor performance status, absence of EGFR mutation, and presence of IPF were poor prognostic factors for PFS and OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Disease control rate (DCR) was significantly lower in ILD and IPF patients than in non-ILD patients regardless of the presence of EGFR mutation (67 or 53 vs. 85 %, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The incidence of AEs of ILD was significantly higher during chemotherapy with docetaxel-containing regimens (seven of 38; 18.4 %). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Both IPF and ILD were associated with lower EGFR positivity, lower DCR, and shorter PFS and OS in advanced NSCLC patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Interstitial lung disease</kwd><kwd>Chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>Docetaxel</kwd><kwd>Acute exacerbation</kwd><kwd>Epidermal growth factor receptor</kwd><kwd>Advanced lung cancer</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Interstitial lung diseases (ILDs), also called interstitial lung abnormalities (ILA) or interstitial pneumonia (IP), are characterized by diffuse pulmonary interstitial abnormalities that often lead to fibrosis (Borchers et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Recent evidence has shown that preexisting ILD is associated with shorter survival in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) (Kinoshita et al. 2012; Nishino et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In a study of NSCLC patients receiving chemotherapy, 22 of whom had idiopathic interstitial pneumonia (IIP), IIP was found to be a significantly unfavorable factor for progression-free survival (PFS) (95.0 vs. 199.5 days) and overall survival (OS) (163.0 vs. 400.0 days) (Kinoshita et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In another study, NSCLC patients with high ILA scores according to computed tomography (CT) findings had shorter OS (n = 17, 7.2 months) than those without ILA (n = 103, 14.8 months) (Nishino et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), the commonest type of ILD (Borchers et al. 2011), is defined as a specific form of chronic, progressive fibrosing IP of unknown cause, occurring primarily in older adults, limited to the lungs, and associated with the histopathologic and/or radiologic patterns of usual interstitial pneumonia (UIP) (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>IPF was recently reported to be a poor prognostic factor in patients with surgically treated NSCLC (Goto et al. 2014; Lee et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Only one study has focused on the efficacy of chemotherapy in advanced NSCLC with IPF (Watanabe et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The authors reported that 21 patients with IPF had an overall response rate (RR), PFS, and OS of 42.9 %, 5.4, and 11.4 months, respectively (Watanabe et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>No published studies have compared the survival of IPF and non-ILD patients with advanced NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Because there is limited clinical information regarding advanced NSCLC patients with IPF, we retrospectively compared the efficacy of chemotherapy and survival in NSCLC patients with ILD or IPF with that in patients without ILD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, we investigated the incidence, risk factors, and outcome of acute exacerbations (AEs) after receiving chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kagawa University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Patients with pathologically confirmed advanced (stage IIIB or IV) NSCLC who presented to the Department of Internal Medicine, Kagawa University Hospital, between January 2007 and July 2015 were retrospectively identified, and relevant clinical and laboratory data were collected from their medical records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Patients who (1) had received definitive thoracic irradiation (usually more than 60 Gy), (2) had another concomitant active malignancy, or (3) had received only best supportive care were excluded, whereas those treated with chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) for epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) were included. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Classification of ILD and diagnosis of IPF and AE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The classification of ILD was made in accordance with the ATS/ERS/Japanese Respiratory Society/Latin American Thoracic Association Statement (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>UIP pattern was defined as having all the following four features: (1) subpleural, basal predominance; (2) reticular abnormality; (3) honeycombing with or without traction bronchiectasis; and (4) absence of features listed as inconsistent with UIP pattern (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>If honeycombing was absent, but other features met the criteria for UIP, the case was classified as possible UIP pattern (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The diagnosis of IPF was based on the following criteria: (1) UIP pattern on high-resolution computed tomography and (2) exclusion of other known causes of interstitial lung diseases (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>No patients in this study underwent surgical lung biopsy to diagnose IPF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>According to the sequential reading method, a board-certificated pulmonologist (N.K.) and a board-certificated radiologist (M.M.) independently reviewed all subjects’ CT scans and classified them into four categories: UIP pattern, possible UIP pattern, inconsistent with UIP pattern, and without ILD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Accordance of their classifications was considered a definite diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>When their classifications differed, two other board-certificated pulmonologists (T.T. and A.T.) carefully reviewed the scans independently; the diagnosis was considered definite if the classifications of three of the four readers were in accord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>When two readers agreed on one classification and the other two another, the case was discussed until all four readers agreed on a diagnosis (this procedure was required in two cases). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Diagnoses of AEs of ILD were made in accordance with criteria detailed in previous studies as follows: (1) worsening of dyspnea within 30 days; (2) new radiologic bilateral ground-glass abnormality and/or consolidation superimposed on a background of reticular shadows or honeycombing; (3) no evidence of pulmonary infection; and (4) exclusion of alternative causes, including left heart failure, pulmonary embolism, and acute lung injury of identifiable cause (Collard et al. 2007; Kinoshita et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>PFS was defined as the time between the start of chemotherapy or molecular targeted therapy and diagnosis of disease progression or death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>OS was defined as the time between the date of diagnosis and date of death from any cause. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>PFS and OS curves were constructed by the Kaplan–Meier method, and differences in survivals compared using the log-rank test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Fisher’s exact test and Student’s t test were used to analyze patient characteristics and the significance of the association of AE with ILD or IPF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Laboratory and pulmonary function data are presented as mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using Ekuseru-Toukei 2015 (Social Survey Research Information, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Patient selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In all, 285 patients with pathologically confirmed advanced (stage IIIB or IV) NSCLC were identified for this study, 29 of whom had received definitive thoracic irradiation, four had another concomitant active malignancy (malignant lymphoma, renal, gastric, or colon cancer), and 34 had received only best supportive care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Thus, 218 patients were included in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Samples were obtained by transbronchial biopsy (131 cases), percutaneous biopsy (71 cases including 31 pleural effusions), surgical resection (9 cases), and others such as biopsy at different departments (7 cases). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Classification of ILD and diagnosis of IPF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Relevant characteristics of patients treated with chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>ILD was identified in 53/218 patients (24.3 %): 35 were diagnosed as having UIP, 15 possible UIP, and three inconsistent with UIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>One patient had dermatomyositis-related UIP pattern, and the remaining 34 with UIP pattern were diagnosed as having IPF (15.6 % of 218 patients).Table 1Characteristics of patients treated with chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapyNon-ILD (n = 165)ILDAll ILD (n = 53) P (vs. non-ILD)IPF (n = 34) P (vs. non-ILD)Age, years (range)66 (30–91)71 (57–86)0.0002770 (57–86)0.0053Sex Male95 (58 %)51 (96 %)&lt;0.000134 (100 %)&lt;0.0001 Female70 (42 %)2 (4 %)0 (0 %)Smoking status Never56 (34 %)2 (4 %)&lt;0.00010 (0 %)&lt;0.0001 Ever109 (66 %)51 (96 %)34 (100 %) Pack-year, average523467PS 0–1134 (81 %)43 (81 %)1.000027 (79 %)0.8123 2–431 (19 %)10 (19 %)7 (21 %)Histology Adeno129 (78 %)21 (40 %)&lt;0.000112 (35 %)&lt;0.0001 Squamous22 (13 %)19 (36 %)0.000512 (35 %)0.0046 Adenosquamous122 Large121 Non-small1297Stage IIIB1460.585431.0000 IV1514731EGFR mutation Yes53 (32 %)1 (2 %)&lt;0.00010 (0 %)&lt;0.0001 No112 (68 %)52 (98 %)34 (100 %) ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, PS performance status, EGFR epidermal growth factor receptor </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Patients with ILD were significantly older than those without ILD and more often male and smokers (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The frequency of adenocarcinoma was lower, and that of squamous cell carcinoma was higher in patients with ILD than in those without it (40 vs. 78 % for adenocarcinoma, and 36 and 13 % for squamous cell carcinoma, respectively). EGFR mutation was detected in 53/112 non-ILD patients (32 %) and in only one of 53 ILD patients (2 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>These differences were more extreme in patients with IPF, all of whom were male smokers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Adenocarcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma histology each comprised 35 % of cases, and no EGFR mutations were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Average of percent vital capacity (%VC) is significantly lower in IPF than in non-ILD patients (76.4 % vs 89.1 %, respectively, P = 0.0115, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Responses to chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>First-line therapy was cytotoxic chemotherapy in 179/218 patients and EGFR-TKI in the remaining 39 (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Fewer than three cycles of first-line chemotherapy were received by 72 and 82 % of ILD and IPF patients, respectively, both percentages being significantly higher than for non-ILD patients (37 %, P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>RR evaluated by RECIST was 55, 37, and 31 % for non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Disease control rate (DCR) was 87, 71, and 53 % in non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>RR and DCR were significantly lower in ILD and IPF patients than in non-ILD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>When patients with EGFR mutation were excluded (n = 54), RR was 44, 35, and 31 % for non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>DCR was 85, 67, and 53 % for non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Although RR was not significantly different in subjects with EGFR wild type (WT), the DCR was significantly lower in ILD and IPF than in non-ILD patients.Table 2Response to first-line chemotherapy/molecular targeted therapyNon-ILD (n = 165)ILDAll ILD (n = 53) P (vs. non-ILD)IPF (n = 34) P (vs. non-ILD)Number of cycles of chemotherapy, average (range)5 (1–24)4 (1–34)0.11213 (1–12)0.0014Number of patients who received fewer than three cycles (%)61 (37 %)38 (72 %)&lt;0.000128 (82 %)&lt;0.0001All patients CR400 PR861910 SD51177 PD221515 NA222 Response rate55 %37 %0.036331 %0.0193 Disease control rate87 %71 %0.018053 %0.0001Patients without EGFR mutation CR200 PR461810 SD46177 PD161515 NA222 Response rate44 %35 %0.391031 %0.2278 Disease control rate85 %67 %0.030453 %0.0004 ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, CR complete response, PR partial response, SD stable disease, PD progressive disease, NA not assessed </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Shorter PFS and OS in patients with ILD or IPF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier survival curves for NSCLC patients who received chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy showed a significantly shorter median PFS (Fig. 1a, 118 vs. 196 days, P = 0.0007) and OS (Fig. 1b, 267 vs 539 days, P = 0.001) in ILD than in non-ILD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In patients with IPF, median PFS (92 days, P &lt; 0.0001) and OS (223 days, P = 0.0002) were even shorter (Fig. 2).Fig. 1Kaplan–Meier curves of (a) progression-free survival and (b) overall survival in advanced NSCLC patients with interstitial lung disease (ILD) who received chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapyFig. 2Kaplan–Meier curves of (a) progression-free survival and (b) overall survival in advanced NSCLC patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) who received chemotherapy and/or molecular targeted therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Univariate analysis by the log-rank test identified that male sex, smoking history, poor performance status (PS), non-adenocarcinoma histology, and EGFR-WT were associated with poor PFS and/or OS (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Multivariate analysis by Cox proportional hazards model showed that poor PS, absence of EGFR mutation, and presence of IPF were identified as poor prognostic factors for PFS and OS.Table 3Risk factors associated with PFS and OS n PFSOSMedian (days)Univariate analysisMultivariate analysisMedian (days)Univariate analysisMultivariate analysis P valueHR (95 % CI) P value P valueHR (95 % CI) P valueAgeOlder (≥75 years)561500.08271.33 (0.94–1.88)0.10823140.01451.46 (1.00–2.15)0.0528Younger (&lt;75 years)162186539Sex Female722280.04031.05 (0.67–1.67)0.82476380.00300.81 (0.48–1.36)0.4219 Male146149398Smoking status Never582370.04050.84 (0.52–1.33)0.45366100.02420.95 (0.57–1.61)0.8595 Ever160149430PS 0–1178202&lt;0.00010.35 (0.24–0.52)&lt;0.0001538&lt;0.00010.24 (0.16–0.36)&lt;0.0001 2–44079139Histology Adeno1501900.04301.02 (0.71–1.47)0.89545390.00091.00 (0.67–1.49)0.9929 Others68150283Stage IIIB201850.72030.78 (0.47–1.28)0.32464950.94070.90 (0.52–1.56)0.7136 IV198180471EGFR mutation Yes543040.00030.55 (0.37–0.82)0.00377710.00010.51 (0.33–0.81)0.0042 No164149360ILD IPF34920.000021.98 (1.26–3.11)0.00302230.00021.74 (1.03–2.92)0.0373 Non-ILD165196539 PFS progression-free survival, OS overall survival, HR hazard ratio, PS performance status, EGFR epidermal growth factor receptor, ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosisTable 4Associations between chemotherapeutic regimens and acute exacerbation of ILD and IPFILDIPF n AE (−)AE (+)Incidence (%) P value n AE (−)AE (+)Incidence (%) P valueDocetaxel Containing3831718.40.04722419520.80.0802 Not containing585535.2292813.4Pemetrexed Containing1513213.30.653187112.51.0000 Not containing817389.94540511.1Paclitaxel/nab-paclitaxel Containing121200.00.35335500.01.0000 Not containing84741011.94842612.5 ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, AE acute exacerbation </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Because EGFR mutation status is associated with survival and differs between non-ILD and ILD/IPF patients, PFS and OS were assessed in these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, PFS and OS were still shorter in ILD and IPF patients with EGFR-WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Median PFS was 180, 118, and 92 days for non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively (P = 0.0301 for non-ILD vs. ILD and P = 0.0018 for non-ILD vs. IPF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Median OS was 458, 258, and 223 days for non-ILD, ILD, and IPF patients, respectively (P = 0.0202 for non-ILD vs. ILD and P = 0.0126 for non-ILD vs. IPF). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Factors associated with AEs of ILD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>AEs were observed in 10/53 patients (18.9 %) with ILD (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Limited to patients with IPF, AEs developed in 6/34 patients (17.6 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>No factors associated with the occurrence of AE were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>However, the incidence of AEs differed between chemotherapeutic regimens (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The number of regimen types received by each patient was counted as shown by the following example: carboplatin plus pemetrexed plus bevacizumab followed by pemetrexed plus bevacizumab was classified as one regimen type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The same regimen administered to two patients was counted as two regimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In all, 96 regimens were administered to 53 patients with ILD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>When they contained docetaxel, the incidence of AEs was 18.4 % (7/38 regimens), which is significantly higher than for regimens without docetaxel (5.2 %, P = 0.0472). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In IPF patients, docetaxel-containing regimens resulted in a trend toward higher incidence of AEs (5/24 patients; 20.8 %), whereas only 1/29 regimens (3.4 %) without docetaxel led to AEs (P = 0.0802); this difference is not statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>No ILD patients received EGFR-TKI.Table 5Patient characteristics associated with acute exacerbations of ILD and IPFILDIPFAE (−) (n = 43)AE (+) (n = 10) P valueAE (−) (n = 28)AE (+) (n = 6) P valueAge Older (≥75 years)1350.2792930.6410 Younger (&lt;75 years)305193Sex Female110.3447001.0000 Male429286Smoking status Never110.3447001.0000 Ever429286PS 0–13670.37612340.5798 2–47352Histology Adeno1950.74111021.0000 Others245184Stage IIIB511.0000301.0000 IV389256EGFR mutation Yes010.1887001.0000 No439286LDH283 ± 127314 ± 1260.5208277 ± 114340 ± 1430.3829KL-6808 ± 608688 ± 3720.5435865 ± 664807 ± 4600.8625%VC81.8 ± 19.884.4 ± 18.50.742678.0 ± 18.071.6 ± 13.80.4691%FVC79.7 ± 20.280.6 ± 18.70.908578.1 ± 18.367.2 ± 13.80.2263 ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, AE acute exacerbation, PS performance status, EGFR epidermal growth factor receptor, LDH lactate dehydrogenase, VC vital capacity, FVC forced vital capacity </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Median PFS in patients with and without AE was 118 versus 124 days (P = 0.4244), and median OS was 142 versus 284 days (P = 0.1099). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Although these differences are not statistically significant, 6/10 patients died quickly after the onset of their AEs (Table 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>All patients who developed AEs were treated with corticosteroids, including methylprednisolone pulse therapy, and received no further chemotherapy.Table 6Outcomes of ten patients with acute exacerbations of ILDNo.Classification of ILDAssociated regimens (chemotherapeutic line)Cycles receivedOnset of AE (days from chemotherapy)Outcome of AESurvival (days from onset of AE)1Possible UIPPemetrexed (second)113Died162Inconsistent with UIPS-1 (third)126Died23Possible UIPCarboplatin and docetaxel (first)5150Died364IPFCarboplatin and docetaxel (first)115Died125IPFCarboplatin and pemetrexed (first)241Recovered816IPFCarboplatin and docetaxel (first)322Died47IPFDocetaxel (first)252Recovered808IPFDocetaxel (first)246Died49Possible UIPDocetaxel (second)228Recovered38510IPFDocetaxel (first)118Recovered108 ILD interstitial lung disease, UIP usual interstitial pneumonia, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, AE acute exacerbation </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The reasons for discontinuation of first-line chemotherapy within three cycles were investigated (Table 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, discontinuation because of adverse events occurred significantly more often in ILD and IPF than in non-ILD patients (42, 46, and 21 %, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Importantly, 6/16 adverse events that resulted in discontinuation of chemotherapy were AEs in ILD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In IPF patients, AEs comprise 6/13 adverse events.Table 7Reasons for discontinuation of first-line chemotherapy within three cyclesNon-ILD (n = 61)ILDAll ILD (n = 38) P (vs. non-ILD)IPF (n = 28) P (vs. non-ILD)PD21 (34 %)14 (37 %)0.831613 (46 %)0.3490Deterioration in PS12 (20 %)7 (18 %)1.00005 (18 %)1.0000Adverse events13 (21 %)16 (42 %)0.040313 (46 %)0.0234Acute exacerbation–66Others16 (26 %)4 (11 %)0.07351 (4 %)0.0100 Note Because numbers are shown as events, the total number may exceed patient numbers and the total percentage will exceed 100 % ILD interstitial lung disease, IPF idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, PD progressive disease, PS performance status </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we demonstrated that (1) characteristics of ILD/IPF patients differed significantly from those of non-ILD patients; in particular, no IPF patients had EGFR mutation-positive tumors; (2) the presence of either IPF or ILD was associated with shorter PFS and OS in patients with advanced NSCLC who received chemotherapy; (3) DCR was significantly lower in ILD and IPF patients than in non-ILD patients, even those with EGFR-WT; and (4) AEs of ILD occurred more frequently after docetaxel-containing regimens than after other regimens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The present study clearly demonstrated several differences in the characteristics of non-ILD and ILD/IPF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Most ILD and all 34 IPF patients were male smokers and had EGFR-WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>It is particularly interesting that no IPF patients had EGFR mutation-positive cancers, which has been shown for the first time although a previous study has reported a correlation between preexisting ILD and EGFR-WT adenocarcinoma (Fujimoto et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In that study, only one of 31 ILD patients with lung adenocarcinoma had an EGFR mutation; this patient had a non-UIP radiographic pattern (Fujimoto et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The current study extended this finding in that our one ILD patient with EGFR mutation also had a radiologic pattern inconsistent with UIP pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The frequency of squamous cell carcinoma was higher in IPF than in non-ILD patients (35 vs. 13 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In ILD patients, most tumors reportedly develop in the area affected by ILD (Fujimoto et al. 2013; Kanaji et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The current study provides evidence that carcinogenesis in IPF differs from that in non-ILD patients in that it is not associated with EGFR mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Consistent with previous studies (Borchers et al. 2011; Watanabe et al. 2013), IPF was the commonest type of ILD (34/53 patients; 64 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Even in patients with EGFR-WT, PFS and OS were significantly shorter in IPF than in non-ILD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that the presence of IPF predicts an extremely poor prognosis in patients with advanced NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Lower %VC (&lt;80 %) was also associated with shorter survivals (120 vs 196 days for PFS, P = 0.0043, and 266 vs 538 days for OS, P = 0.0023, respectively, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Shorter survival in lower %VC has been reported in patients with NSCLC and ILD who underwent surgical resection (Sato et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Another important finding of the current study is regarding response to chemotherapy/molecular targeted therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>RR and DCR in ILD/IPF patients were lower than that in non-ILD patients. EGFR mutation was not identified in any of the 34 IPF patients, whereas 32 % of non-ILD patients harbored EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Because the response to EGFR-TKI is much better in tumors with EGFR mutation than in EGFR-WT, the lower RR in IPF patients may be associated with the absence of EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the difference in RR was not significant for EGFR-WT patients; interestingly, however, a difference in DCR was observed, even in patients without EGFR mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>There are several possible mechanisms that could explain the lower DCR and shorter survival of ILD/IPF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>First, ILD/IPF patients may experience adverse events more frequently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Indeed, adverse events, including AEs, and PD were the main reasons for discontinuing first-line therapy within three cycles in patients with ILD/IPF, suggesting that AEs of ILD/IPF may have made an important contribution to the lower DCR and shorter survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, coexisting ILD is reportedly associated with a high risk of developing chemotherapy-induced ILD (Sakurada et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Chemotherapeutic strategies that do not induce AEs or deterioration of ILD are needed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Second, an altered drug delivery system may lead to the lower response and shorter survival of ILD/IPF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Histological features of the UIP pattern include marked pulmonary fibrosis and architectural distortion (Raghu et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Alveolar epithelial cell damage, dysregulation of fibroblasts, and vascular injury and aberrant angiogenesis related to vascular remodeling are key elements of lung fibrosis (Selman and Pardo 2006; Wémeau-Stervinou et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Destruction of normal vasculature would logically reduce the local delivery of chemotherapeutic agents to a tumor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Third, acquired drug resistance may result in lower DCR and shorter survival in ILD/IPF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In this regard, transforming growth factor (TGF)-β may have a role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Many cytokines and growth factors, including TGF-β, are reportedly associated with the development of ILD/IPF (Das et al. 2014; Kanaji et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>TGF-β concentrations are higher in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid obtained from IPF than from control patients (Khalil et al. 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>TGF-β is reportedly associated with chemoresistance in colon cancer (Li et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Additionally, TGF-β is a major regulator of epithelial–mesenchymal transition in the alveolar epithelia (Kasai et al. 2005; Miyazono 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In epithelial–mesenchymal transition, cancer cells seemingly acquire chemoresistance in lung and other types of cancers (Jiang et al. 2015; Li et al. 2014; Wang et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Thus, increased TGF-β in the lung’s microenvironment may be a causative factor for lower DCR and shorter survival in NSCLC patients with ILD/IPF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Regarding AEs of ILD, several studies have reported docetaxel-induced AE (Tamiya et al. 2012; Watanabe et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In 35 patients with NSCLC and IP treated with docetaxel monotherapy, the incidence of AEs of IP was 14.3 % (5/35 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Three of the five patients who developed AEs of IP died (Watanabe et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In another study, deterioration of ILD was observed in 7/27 patients (25.9 %) with NSCLC and preexisting ILD (Tamiya et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In contrast, 6/309 patients (1.9 %) without preexisting ILD reportedly developed it after receiving docetaxel (Tamiya et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In the current study, there was also a higher incidence of AEs of ILD/IPF after docetaxel-containing chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Of note, AEs also occurred in 3/15 patients with radiographic possible UIP pattern (20 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Several studies have reported that possible UIP pattern often corresponds with pathologically confirmed UIP (Sumikawa et al. 2014; Raghu et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Radiographic possible UIP pattern should be considered clinically similar to UIP when choosing treatment strategies for patients with advanced NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Administration schedule also affects the incidence of AEs (higher incidence in a weekly than in triweekly administration) (Chen et al. 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Anti-microtubule activity by taxanes itself seems not to be related in the development of AE because the incidence of AE in paclitaxel is different from that in docetaxel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Thus, factors other than anticancer activity might be associated with docetaxel-related AE although an actual mechanism has never been reported. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>No optimal chemotherapeutic regimen for patients with advanced NSCLC and underlying ILD has been established (Watanabe et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>A combination of carboplatin and weekly paclitaxel may be a treatment option for NSCLC with ILD (Minegishi et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Eighteen patients with ILD, including six with IPF, treated with carboplatin and paclitaxel achieved PFS and median survival time of 5.3 and 10.6 months, respectively (Minegishi et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Only one patient (5.6 %) with IPF developed an AE (after four cycles of chemotherapy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>However, in another study 4/15 patients with NSCLC and ILD who received carboplatin and paclitaxel developed grade 3 or higher pneumonitis (27 %) (Shukuya et al. 2010); this high incidence cannot be ignored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In a phase III trial, administration of albumin-bound paclitaxel (nab-paclitaxel) as first-line treatment in patients with advanced NSCLC without ILD was effective and resulted in a higher RR than conventional solvent-based paclitaxel (Socinski et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Currently, several clinical trials are assessing a combination of carboplatin and nab-paclitaxel for advanced NSCLC with ILD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Nintedanib is a multiple tyrosine kinase inhibitor, and INPULSIS-2 trial demonstrated that nintedanib reduced the time to first AE compared with placebo (Richeldi et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In addition, a combination of docetaxel and nintedanib showed a benefit on OS over docetaxel monotherapy as second-line treatment (Reck et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The addition of nintedanib to cytotoxic agents such as docetaxel may be more effective with fewer adverse events. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of ILD and IPF in this study was 24.3 and 15.6 %, respectively, and seems to be higher than in previous reports (7.3–14 %) (Kinoshita et al. 2012; Nishino et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>However, among 387 patients who received surgical resection, 65 (16.8 %) were confirmed as underlying IPF (Goto et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Location of the institution would greatly influence the prevalence of ILD and IPF as well as smoking status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The limitations of this study are as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>First, this was a retrospective, single-center study; a prospective, multicenter large study including both non-ILD and ILD patients is desirable to further investigate clinical differences in response to chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Second, all patients were Japanese: Some studies have shown ethnic differences in incidence of drug-induced lung injury and other pulmonary diseases (Azuma et al. 2008; Natsuizaka et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The incidence of AEs of ILD/IPF may vary between different ethnicities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This study showed, for the first time, that patients with advanced NSCLC and IPF have shorter PFS and OS and lower DCR than patients without ILD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Docetaxel-containing chemotherapeutic regimens were more frequently associated with AEs than other regimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Because survival after onset of AEs is usually short, more effective therapeutic strategies that do not induce AEs should be identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>No funding was received specifically for this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="conflict-interest"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. No funding was received specifically for this study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Human and animal rights</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kagawa University. All procedures performed in study involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional research committee and with the Declaration of Helsinki revised at the 64th WMA General Assembly in 2013 or comparable ethical standards.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Informed consent</title><p>Informed consent was not obtained from all individual participants because this study is retrospective and includes patients who already died. However, our institute presented the study design officially which provided the chance all people check it and reject the participation in this study. This procedure was also approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kagawa University.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>AzumaAHagiwaraKKudohSBasis of acute exacerbation of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in Japanese patientsAm J Respir Crit Care Med20081771397139810.1164/ajrccm.177.12.1397a<?supplied-pmid 18522953?>18522953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>BorchersATChangCKeenCLGershwinMEIdiopathic pulmonary fibrosis-an epidemiological and pathological reviewClin Rev Allergy Immunol20114011713410.1007/s12016-010-8211-5<?supplied-pmid 20838937?>20838937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>ChenYMShihJFPerngRPTsaiCMWhang-PengJA randomized trial of different docetaxel schedules in non-small cell lung cancer patients who failed previous platinum-based chemotherapyChest20061291031103810.1378/chest.129.4.1031<?supplied-pmid 16608954?>16608954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>CollardHRMooreBBFlahertyKRBrownKKKanerRJKingTEJrLaskyJALoydJENothIOlmanMARaghuGRomanJRyuJHZismanDAHunninghakeGWColbyTVEganJJHansellDMJohkohTKaminskiNKimDSKondohYLynchDAMüller-QuernheimJMyersJLNicholsonAGSelmanMToewsGBWellsAUMartinezFJIdiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis Clinical Research Network InvestigatorsAcute exacerbations of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosisAm J Respir Crit Care Med200717663664310.1164/rccm.200703-463PP<?supplied-pmid 17585107?>17585107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>DasSKumarMNegiVPattnaikBPrakashYSAgrawalAGhoshBMicroRNA-326 regulates profibrotic functions of transforming growth factor-β in pulmonary fibrosisAm J Respir Cell Mol Biol20145088289210.1165/rcmb.2013-0195OC<?supplied-pmid 24279830?>24279830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>FujimotoDTomiiKOtoshiTKawamuraTTamaiKTakeshitaJTanakaKMatsumotoTMondenKNagataKOtsukaKNakagawaAHataATachikawaROtsukaKHamakawaHKatakamiNTakahashiYImaiYPreexisting interstitial lung disease is inversely correlated to tumor epidermal growth factor receptor mutation in patients with lung adenocarcinomaLung Cancer20138015916410.1016/j.lungcan.2013.01.017<?supplied-pmid 23419507?>23419507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>GotoTMaeshimaAOyamadaYKatoRIdiopathic pulmonary fibrosis as a prognostic factor in non-small cell lung cancerInt J Clin Oncol20141926627310.1007/s10147-013-0566-1<?supplied-pmid 23660786?>23660786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>JiangXWangJZhangKTangSRenCChenYThe role of CD29-ILK-Akt signaling-mediated epithelial-mesenchymal transition of liver epithelial cells and chemoresistance and radioresistance in hepatocellular carcinoma cellsMed Oncol20153214110.1007/s12032-015-0595-x<?supplied-pmid 25805567?>25805567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>KanajiNBasmaHNelsonAFaridMSatoTNakanishiMWangXMichalskiJLiYGunjiYFeghali-BostwickCLiuXRennardSIFibroblasts that resist cigarette smoke-induced senescence acquire profibrotic phenotypesAm J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol2014307L364L37310.1152/ajplung.00041.2014<?supplied-pmid 25015975?>25015975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>KanajiNOkudaMDobashiHKamedaTTadokoroAWakiyaRKadowakiNBandohSSquamous cell lung cancer associated with systemic sclerosisJ Clin Med Res2015789690010.14740/jocmr2313w<?supplied-pmid 26491504?>26491504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>KasaiHAllenJTMasonRMKamimuraTZhangZTGF-beta1 induces human alveolar epithelial to mesenchymal cell transition (EMT)Respir Res200565610.1186/1465-9921-6-56<?supplied-pmid 15946381?>15946381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>KhalilNParekhTVO’ConnorRAntmanNKepronWYehaulaeshetTXuYDGoldLIRegulation of the effects of TGF-beta 1 by activation of latent TGF-beta 1 and differential expression of TGF-beta receptors (T beta R-I and T beta R-II) in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosisThorax20015690791510.1136/thorax.56.12.907<?supplied-pmid 11713352?>11713352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>KinoshitaTAzumaKSasadaTOkamotoMHattoriSImamuraYYamadaKTajiriMYoshidaTZaizenYKawaharaAFujimotoKHoshinoTChemotherapy for non-small cell lung cancer complicated by idiopathic interstitial pneumoniaOncol Lett20124477482<?supplied-pmid 23741246?>23741246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>LeeTParkJYLeeHYChoYJYoonHILeeJHJheonSLeeCTParkJSLung cancer in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: clinical characteristics and impact on survivalRespir Med20141081549155510.1016/j.rmed.2014.07.020<?supplied-pmid 25175479?>25175479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>LiJWangYSongYFuZYuWmiR-27a regulates cisplatin resistance and metastasis by targeting RKIP in human lung adenocarcinoma cellsMol Cancer20141319310.1186/1476-4598-13-193<?supplied-pmid 25128483?>25128483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>LiJLiuHYuJYuHChemoresistance to doxorubicin induces epithelial-mesenchymal transition via upregulation of transforming growth factor β signaling in HCT116 colon cancer cellsMol Med Rep201512192198<?supplied-pmid 25684678?>25684678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>MinegishiYSudohJKuribayasiHMizutaniHSeikeMAzumaAYoshimuraAKudohSGemmaAThe safety and efficacy of weekly paclitaxel in combination with carboplatin for advanced non-small cell lung cancer with idiopathic interstitial pneumoniasLung Cancer201171707410.1016/j.lungcan.2010.04.014<?supplied-pmid 20493578?>20493578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>MiyazonoKTransforming growth factor-beta signaling in epithelial-mesenchymal transition and progression of cancerProc Jpn Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci20098531432310.2183/pjab.85.314<?supplied-pmid 19838011?>19838011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>NatsuizakaMChibaHKuronumaKOtsukaMKudoKMoriMBandoMSugiyamaYTakahashiHEpidemiologic survey of Japanese patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis and investigation of ethnic differencesAm J Respir Crit Care Med201419077377910.1164/rccm.201403-0566OC<?supplied-pmid 25162152?>25162152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>NishinoMCardarellaSDahlbergSEArakiTLydonCJackmanDMRabinMSHatabuHJohnsonBEInterstitial lung abnormalities in treatment-naïve advanced non-small-cell lung cancer patients are associated with shorter survivalEur J Radiol201584998100410.1016/j.ejrad.2015.01.021<?supplied-pmid 25726730?>25726730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>RaghuGCollardHREganJJMartinezFJBehrJBrownKKColbyTVCordierJFFlahertyKRLaskyJALynchDARyuJHSwigrisJJWellsAUAncocheaJBourosDCarvalhoCCostabelUEbinaMHansellDMJohkohTKimDSKingTEJrKondohYMyersJMüllerNLNicholsonAGRicheldiLSelmanMDuddenRFGrissBSProtzkoSLSchünemannHJATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Committee on Idiopathic Pulmonary FibrosisAn official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT statement: idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: evidence-based guidelines for diagnosis and managementAm J Respir Crit Care Med201118378882410.1164/rccm.2009-040GL<?supplied-pmid 21471066?>21471066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>RaghuGLynchDGodwinJDWebbRColbyTVLeslieKOBehrJBrownKKEganJJFlahertyKRMartinezFJWellsAUShaoLZhouHPedersenPSSoodRMontgomeryABO’RiordanTGDiagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis with high-resolution CT in patients with little or no radiological evidence of honeycombing: secondary analysis of a randomised, controlled trialLancet Respir Med2014227728410.1016/S2213-2600(14)70011-6<?supplied-pmid 24717624?>24717624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>ReckMKaiserRMellemgaardADouillardJYOrlovSKrzakowskiMvon PawelJGottfriedMBondarenkoILiaoMGannCNBarruecoJGaschler-MarkefskiBNovelloSLUME-Lung 1 Study GroupDocetaxel plus nintedanib versus docetaxel plus placebo in patients with previously treated non-small-cell lung cancer (LUME-Lung 1): a phase 3, double-blind, randomised controlled trialLancet Oncol20141514315510.1016/S1470-2045(13)70586-2<?supplied-pmid 24411639?>24411639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>RicheldiLdu BoisRMRaghuGAzumaABrownKKCostabelUCottinVFlahertyKRHansellDMInoueYKimDSKolbMNicholsonAGNoblePWSelmanMTaniguchiHBrunMLe MaulfFGirardMStowasserSSchlenker-HercegRDisseBCollardHRINPULSIS Trial InvestigatorsEfficacy and safety of nintedanib in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosisN Engl J Med20143702071208210.1056/NEJMoa1402584<?supplied-pmid 24836310?>24836310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>SakuradaTKakiuchiSTajimaSHorinouchiYOkadaNNishisakoHNakamuraTTeraokaKKawazoeKYanagawaHNishiokaYMinakuchiKIshizawaKCharacteristics of and risk factors for interstitial lung disease induced by chemotherapy for lung cancerAnn Pharmacother20154939840410.1177/1060028014566446<?supplied-pmid 25565405?>25565405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>SatoTWatanabeAKondoHKanzakiMOkuboKYokoiKMatsumotoKMarutsukaTShinoharaHTeramukaiSKishiKEbinaMSugiyamaYMeinoshinODateHJapanese Association for Chest SurgeryLong-term results and predictors of survival after surgical resection of patients with lung cancer and interstitial lung diseasesJ Thorac Cardiovasc Surg2015149646910.1016/j.jtcvs.2014.08.086<?supplied-pmid 25439777?>25439777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>SelmanMPardoARole of epithelial cells in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: from innocent targets to serial killersProc Am Thorac Soc2006336437210.1513/pats.200601-003TK<?supplied-pmid 16738202?>16738202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>ShukuyaTIshiwataTHaraMMurakiKShibayamaRKoyamaRTakahashiKCarboplatin plus weekly paclitaxel treatment in non-small cell lung cancer patients with interstitial lung diseaseAnticancer Res20103043574361<?supplied-pmid 21036764?>21036764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>SocinskiMABondarenkoIKarasevaNAMakhsonAMVynnychenkoIOkamotoIHonJKHirshVBharPZhangHIglesiasJLRenschlerMFWeekly nab-paclitaxel in combination with carboplatin versus solvent-based paclitaxel plus carboplatin as first-line therapy in patients with advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: final results of a phase III trialJ Clin Oncol2012302055206210.1200/JCO.2011.39.5848<?supplied-pmid 22547591?>22547591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>SumikawaHJohkohTFujimotoKArakawaHColbyTVFukuokaJTaniguchiHKondohYKataokaKOguraTBabaTIchikadoKGyobuTYanagawaMHondaOTomiyamaNPathologically proved nonspecific interstitial pneumonia: CT pattern analysis as compared with usual interstitial pneumonia CT patternRadiology201427254955610.1148/radiol.14130853<?supplied-pmid 24661246?>24661246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>TamiyaANaitoTMiuraSMoriiSTsuyaANakamuraYKairaKMurakamiHTakahashiTYamamotoNEndoMInterstitial lung disease associated with docetaxel in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancerAnticancer Res20123211031106<?supplied-pmid 22399640?>22399640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>WangHSunQWuYWangLZhouCMaWZhangYWangSZhangSGranzyme M expressed by tumor cells promotes chemoresistance and EMT in vitro and metastasis in vivo associated with STAT3 activationOncotarget201565818583110.18632/oncotarget.3461<?supplied-pmid 25788270?>25788270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>WatanabeNTaniguchiHKondohYKimuraTKataokaKNishiyamaOKondoMHasegawaYEfficacy of chemotherapy for advanced non-small cell lung cancer with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosisRespiration20138532633110.1159/000342046<?supplied-pmid 23171837?>23171837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>WatanabeNNihoSKiritaKUmemuraSMatsumotoSYohKOhmatsuHGotoKSecond-line docetaxel for patients with platinum-refractory advanced non-small cell lung cancer and interstitial pneumoniaCancer Chemother Pharmacol201576697410.1007/s00280-015-2775-y<?supplied-pmid 25976217?>25976217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Wémeau-StervinouLPerezTMurphyCPolgeASWallaertBLung capillary blood volume and membrane diffusion in idiopathic interstitial pneumoniaRespir Med201210656457010.1016/j.rmed.2011.12.011<?supplied-pmid 22221584?>22221584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
