<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4552872</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26317984</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-46388</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Unimodal Model for Double Observer Distance Sampling Surveys </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Unimodal Model for Double Observer Distance Sampling Surveys</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Earl F.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>Aaron M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<addr-line>Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Anchorage, Alaska, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>Aaron W.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Missouri Kansas City, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: EFB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: EFB AMC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: EFB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: EFB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: EFB AMC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>earl.becker@alaska.gov</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e0136403</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Becker, Christ</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Becker, Christ</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0136403.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Distance sampling is a widely used method to estimate animal population size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Most distance sampling models utilize a monotonically decreasing detection function such as a half-normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Recent advances in distance sampling modeling allow for the incorporation of covariates into the distance model, and the elimination of the assumption of perfect detection at some fixed distance (usually the transect line) with the use of double-observer models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The assumption of full observer independence in the double-observer model is problematic, but can be addressed by using the point independence assumption which assumes there is one distance, the apex of the detection function, where the 2 observers are assumed independent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Aerially collected distance sampling data can have a unimodal shape and have been successfully modeled with a gamma detection function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Covariates in gamma detection models cause the apex of detection to shift depending upon covariate levels, making this model incompatible with the point independence assumption when using double-observer data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This paper reports a unimodal detection model based on a two-piece normal distribution that allows covariates, has only one apex, and is consistent with the point independence assumption when double-observer data are utilized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>An aerial line-transect survey of black bears in Alaska illustrate how this method can be applied. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding was provided by the Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Federal Aid in Wildlife Restoration Funds.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="18"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Animal population size is an important parameter for many wildlife and ecological problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Distance sampling is a widely used method to estimate animal population size [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Conventional distance sampling (CDS) models animal detection as function of the perpendicular distance between the animal and transect to obtain a population estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In most applications, there are additional variables that affect an animal’s detection probability [2–4] and these variables can be used for modeling animal detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>When appreciable variation in animal detection is present, multiple covariate distance sampling (MCDS) models are superior to CDS models if the appropriate covariates are measured [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>CDS and MCDS models make the important assumption that animal detection is perfect at the apex of detection, usually on the transect line (distance = 0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>If this assumption is true, Burnham et al. [6] show that CDS models under mild assumptions are robust to biases associated with unmodeled heterogeneity, a condition Burnham et al. [7] labeled “pooling robust”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>By extension, MCDS models would also be pooling robust if the assumption of perfect detection at the apex were true. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In many cases the perfect detection assumption is unrealistic or suspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In such cases the collection of double-observer data can be used to remove this assumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Double-observer data consists of 2 observers trying to detect animals independently of one another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>When one observer detects an animal, it is essentially “marked” for the other observer to either detect (recapture) or miss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The incorporation of double-observer data into distance modeling (Mark-Recapture Distance Sampling models, MRDS models) eliminates the assumption of perfect detection at a distance associated with the detection apex and allows this parameter to be estimated [8–11] and even vary due to other variables [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The initial MRDS models [8–11] assume independent animal sightings between the observers over all distances, which Borchers et al. [12] call the “full independence” (FI) assumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>While there are several ways to estimate MRDS models under this assumption, a common method is to use a Huggins type [13] mark-recapture model with distance as a covariate [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The property of “pooling-robustness” does not hold for MRDS models [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Like mark-recapture models, unmodeled heterogeneity in MRDS models is a source of bias [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Covariates can reduce the unmodeled heterogeneity but are unlikely to account for all the sources of heterogeneity [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Laake [16] analyzed distance data on a known population of 150 wooden stakes, the best CDS estimate was 81% (121) of the true value, while the MRDS model using the FI assumption was 80% (120) of the true value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Additionally, analysis of crabeater seal (Lobodon carcinophaga) [12,14] and feral horse (Equus caballus) [15] datasets with a MRDS model using the FI assumption resulted in estimates that were considerably lower than those obtained with MCDS models that assume perfect detection on the transect line (the location of maximum detection for these data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>These results do not follow the expected pattern of MRDS population estimates being larger than CDS and MCDS estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These results can be caused by statistical dependence in the data, even though the 2 observers collected the data independently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The dependence can easily be a function of distance or animal activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Increased distance to the animal will cause more and more animals to be missed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>If at far distances only the most visible animals are detected then they may be more likely to be detected by both observers since they are more visible than the average animal at that distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This occurs because missing variables explaining detection have not been accounted for; this is unmodeled heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In the above case, an animal standing on a ridge top with no ground cover or vegetation in the background (sky-lined), would be very visible at far distances to both observers; the inadequate modeling of the sighting conditions would cause unmodeled heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The effect of vegetation obstruction may increase with distance, resulting in the situation described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Laake et al. [15] document a divergence in detection probabilities over distance obtained from a MCDS model and the mark-recapture probabilities in a feral horse dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The higher mark-recapture probabilities at far distances are consistent with unmodeled heterogeneity causing some dependency in the sighting data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Laake et al. [15] state: “it is important to understand that independence is not solely achieved by the observers being unaware of each other.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>There are several ways to deal with this dependence issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Buckland et al. [17] used a limited independence model that simultaneously modeled the distance data, the mark-recapture data and the dependence between the 2 observers as a function of distance as well as other covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Conn et al. [18] modeled observer detections as arising from a probit-Bernoulli model with the correlation between the observers being a function of distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Laake [16] presented a less restrictive independence assumption that only assumed independence of observer observations at the distance associated with the apex of detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Borchers et al. [12] denoted these as “point independence” (PI) assumption models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>MRDS models that use a point independence assumption fit a MCDS model and use a Mark-recapture model to estimate maximum detection at the MCDS detection apex, this is then used to adjust the height of the MCDS model [12,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Borchers et al. [12] document the mathematical details of a MRDS model under the PI assumption. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Line transect surveys are an excellent tool for obtaining population estimates for large geographic areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In terrestrial study areas, aircraft are often used to fly transects over large study areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Assuming perfect detection at some distance from a fast-moving aircraft is unrealistic and requires the use of a MRDS model to estimate animal detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Due to costs, both observers are usually on the same aircraft which makes it more likely that unmodeled heterogeneity of the sighting conditions will occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions a MRDS model using the PI assumption will be less biased than one that relies on the FI assumption [12, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Large terrestrial study areas often contain mountainous terrain over which it is unsafe to fly straight-line transects; however, these areas can safely be flown using contour transects [19–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>For contour transects, distance is measured as the closest distance between the transect and the sighted animal using GPS locations [19–21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Becker and Quang [20] encountered unimodal detection data of brown bears sighted from transects flown with small fixed-wing aircraft. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The main reason for this unimodal detection shape is that detection is degraded close to the aircraft due to less time available for searching caused by the plane’s speed and fewer sighting angles around vegetative obstructions, whereas at moderate distances the increased sighting angles and viewing time improve detection despite the negative effect of increased distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A more detailed explanation is available on pages 209 and 220 of Becker and Quang [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>They used a unimodal detection function coupled with double-count data modeled under the FI assumption to obtain a population estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>They also modeled the scale parameter as a function of covariates similar to Marques and Buckland [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In the gamma detection model, the addition of covariates results in a different detection apex for each covariate level [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The gamma detection function when coupled with double-count data is inconsistent with a MRDS model utilizing the PI assumption, since the covariates cause multiple apexes at various distances and under the PI assumption only 1 distance is assumed to have point independence [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this paper is to implement a MRDS model for unimodal detection data that does not require independent observations over all distances between the 2 observers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Our solution will involve developing a new detection model that will allow us to implement Borchers et al. [12] MRDS model with the PI assumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We propose a new detection model that has a unimodal shape with only one detection apex, even when multiple covariates are used to model detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a unimodal model for the double-observer (mark-recapture) data will be presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A MRDS model using the PI assumption allows for less biased and more realistic population estimates from line transect data which have a unimodal detection shape and avoids the unrealistic assumption of perfect detection [12,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>If there is no unmodeled heterogeneity then the population estimates are unbiased [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>As an example, these models will be applied to double-observer, aerial line transect survey of black bears (Ursus americanus). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Borchers et al. [12] partition the likelihood for MRDS data into 4 components: a distance component (Ly|z(θ_y|z)), a mark-recapture component (Lω(θ_ω)), a binomial component (Ln•(Nc,θ_,ϕ_z_)), and a covariate component (Lz(ϕz,θ_)) Using their partial likelihood approach, estimates of θ_,(θ_={θ_,y|zθ_ω}) can be obtained from (Ly|z(θ_y|z)), (Lω(θ_ω)), and a Horvitz-Thompson like estimator is used to obtain the population estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Our focus is on aerial surveys which often have blind strip of width (w b), we use the notation of Borchers et al. [12] with the lower limit denoted by w b throughout this paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec003"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Distance Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Assume random transect placement and truncation of the distance data at w. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Let y represent the closest distance between the transect and the sighted animal, z_ represent a vector of covariates that affect the detection probability, and i index the sighted animal (i = 1,2,…n). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Define p•(yi,z_i) as the probability that an animal at distance y i with covariate vector z_i is detected by at least one observer in the (w b,w) strip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Denote the pdf of y as π(y)=1(w−wb). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Borchers et al. [12] give the general form of the distance likelihood as: Ly|z(θ_y|z)=∏i=1np•(yi,z_i)π(y)p•(z_i),(1) where p•(z_i)=∫wbwp•(yi,z_i)π(y)dy,(2) is the probability that at least one observer detects animal i. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Our interest is to develop a MRDS model that is consistent with the PI assumption of independent sighting data between observers only at some distance y = y*. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>This requires a unimodal detection function that also allows the use of detection covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The two-piece normal distribution [22], also known as a split-normal distribution, is a simple distribution that meets this requirement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The two-piece normal distribution is essentially 2 half-normal distributions that share a common mode (μ) but have different variances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Using the terminology of Marques and Buckland [4] the key function is: p•(yi,z_i)={exp[−((yi−μ)2σ1i)2]for wb≤yi&lt;μexp[−((yi−μ)2σ2i)2]foryi≥μ,(3) where μ denotes the mode of the detection distribution and μ = y* under the PI assumption. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Assuming the covariates, z_i, affect detection via the scale parameters (σ 1i,σ 2i) [4], σ1i=exp(β0+∑k1βk1z_k1i+∑k2I(wb≤yi&lt;μ)βk2z_k2i),and(4) σ2i=exp(β0+∑k1βk1z_k1i+∑k3I(yi≥μ)βk3z_k3i).(5) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The covariates that affect the scale of both half-normal curves are modeled by the ∑k1βk1z_k1i terms, the covariates that affect only σ 1i are modeled by the ∑k2βk2z_k2i terms, and the covariates that affect only σ 2i are modeled by the ∑k3βk3z_k3i terms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The total number of covariates in the model is k, (k = k 1+k 2+k 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The I( ) notation is a standard indicator function that is 1 when the condition in the parentheses is true and 0 otherwise, the purpose of this notation is to make explicit which scale parameters are being modelled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>MCDS parameter estimates are obtained by maximizing the log-likelihood equation: ly|z(θ_^y|z)=∑i=1n[ln(p•(yi,z_i))+ln(π(y))−ln(p•(z_i))]=∑i=1n[−(yi−μ^2[I(wb≤yi&lt;μ^)σ^1i+I(yi≥μ^)σ^2i])2]−∑i=1nln(∫y=wbμ^exp[−(yi−μ^2σ^1i)2]dy)−∑i=1nln(∫y=μ^wexp[−(yi−μ^2σ^2i)2]dy)•(6) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Numerical methods for maximizing Eq (6) above require initial starting values for the parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We follow Ramsey et al. [23] to obtain initial starting values for the β^k's, and use the apex of a kernel estimator [24] for the initial starting value of μ^. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Double-Observer Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Our focus is the implementation of a point independence MRDS model, which will utilize the results of a two-piece normal distance model in order to obtain a population estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Following Borchers et al. [12] the mark-recapture likelihood is: Lω(θ_ω)=∏i=1nPr(ωi|yi,z_)p•(yi,z_i).(7) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Here ω i denotes the encounter history of the i th animal (ω i ∈ {(1,0),(01),(1,1)}); the first number in the history indexes whether the animal was seen by the 1st observer (0 = no, 1 = yes) and the second number indexes whether the animal was seen by the 2nd observer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Borchers et al. [12] denote the degree of dependence between the 2 observers as δ(y,z_), σ 12 as the covariance between the 2 observers’ detection probabilities that is induced by excluding covariates u_ from the model, and pj(y,z_)=Eu[pj(y,z_,u_)] for observer j, j = 1, 2; δ(y,z_)=1+(σ12(y,z_)p1(y,z_)p2(y,z_)),(8) σ12(y,z_)=Covu_[p1(y,z_,u_),p2(y,z_,u_)].(9) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The calculation of p•(yi,z_i) requires knowledge of δ(yi,z_i) which cannot be obtained from the capture history [12], p•(yi,z_i)=p1(yi,z_i)+p2(yi,z_i)−p1(yi,z_i)p2(yi,z_i)δ(yi,z_i).(10) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>They show that using conditional probabilities under the PI assumption allows for the estimation of p•(yi,z_i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Without making any independence assumptions: p•c(yi,z_i)=p1|2(yi,z_i)+p2|1(yi,z_i)−p1|2(yi,z_i)p2|1(yi,z_i),(11) p•c(yi,z_i)=p•(yi,z_i)δ(yi,z_i).(12) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Assuming point independence (PI) at y*, we assume δ(y*,z_i)=1, so p•c(y*,z_i)=p•(y*,z_i)δ(y*i,z_i)=p•(y*,z_i).(13) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Their approach to fitting a point independence MRDS model requires a logistic model that contains different observers (1 and 2), and other possible covariates to obtain estimates of p^1|2(yi,z_i), and p^2|1(yi,z_i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A linear form of distance (y) was a potential explanatory variable in their logistic models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In addition to the linear form of distance as a potential covariate, we also wanted to consider other forms that could mimic the general shape of the two-piece normal detection model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We used a polynomial spline [25] on the distance variable as a possible covariate to accomplish this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We placed no restrictions on the apex location of the spline fit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Depending upon the nature of the unmodeled heterogeneity and other variables being considered in the model, distance may not be an important covariate [15] or have a unimodal shape. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Our MRDS model uses a two-piece normal detection function to model the distance data, so we assume point independence at the detection apex y*=μ^ and obtain p^1|2(μ^i,z_i), and p^2|1(μ^,z_i) from our logistic model to calculate p^•(μ^,z_i), p^•(μ^,z_i)=p^1|2(μ^,z_i)+p^2|1(μ^,z_i)−p^1|2(μ^,z_i)p^2|1(μ^,z_i).(14) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Population Estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Following Borchers et al. [12], let N c be the number of animals in the covered region, which is estimated by using a Horvitz-Thompson like estimator: N^c=∑i=1nsiπ^i,(15) where s i denotes the size of the i th animal group, and π^i denotes the estimated inclusion probability of the i th group and is estimated by: π^i=p^•(μ^,z_i)p^•(z_i)(16) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>[12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The p^•(μ^,z_i) term is calculated from the mark-recapture data (Eq (14)) and the p^•(z_i) term is calculated from the distance data (Eq (2)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Transects were randomly placed so inferences about animal density and population size can be made for the entire study area. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Laake and Borchers [14] have shown that averaging the p^•(μ^,z_i)’s over the observed covariates is also valid and can be used to calculate the estimated inclusion probability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We denote this average as p^•(μ^), and followed equation 6.50 of Laake and Borchers [14]: p^•(μ^)=∑i=1np^•(μ^,z_i)E^(p^•(z_i))∑i=1n1E^(p^•(z_i)),(17) where: E^(p^•(z_i))=∫wbwp^•(y,z_i)π(y)dy.(18) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The estimated inclusion probabilities are now calculated by: π^i=p^•(μ^)p^•(z_i).(19) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The variance can be obtained following Borchers et al. [12] or by using a transect-based bootstrap method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We used the lowest AIC [1] to determine the best MCDS model and the best logistic model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Marques and Buckland [4] report that estimators based on estimated Horvitz-Thompson inclusion probabilities can have substantial bias if many of the estimated inclusion probabilities are small. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Marques and Buckland [5] recommend restricting model selection to models whose estimated inclusion probabilities are all greater than 0.1 and less than 5% of them are below 0.2; we excluded models that did not meet these criteria from our AIC selection process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Assessing the fit of the MCDS model includes a Goodness-of-Fit test [1], q-q plots, and a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Model fit for the logistic model and the MRDS model follow Borchers et al. [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Application to a South-Central Alaska Black Bear Population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Data collection involved aerial observation of black bears (Ursus americanus), for which no agency field permit or approval was required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>All Federal Aviation Administration regulations were followed in collecting the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>No lands were accessed in the data collection, nor were any endangered or protected species sampled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>No animals were handled during the survey, so no IACUC permit (a permit that is required to ensure the humane treatment and handling of captured animals) was required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In the spring of 2007, an aerial line transect survey for black bears was conducted in the 21,398 km2 Skwetna study area in South-Central Alaska. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This area is bordered on the south by the Chakachamna Lake, Chakachamna River and Cook Inlet; on the east by the Susitna and Yentna rivers; and on the north and west by the spine of the Alaska Range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Elevation ranged from 0 to 6,196 meters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Prominent habitats consisted of: birch and mixed birch-spruce forests, and muskegs at lower elevations; mixtures of grasslands and alder on the lower mountain slopes; alpine habitat at intermediate elevations; and rocky terrain with variable snow cover and glaciers at higher elevations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The survey was conducted between 10–25 May, a period after black bear den emergence and prior to full leaf-out of the birch forest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>A total of 470 30-km long transects were flown by 5 small tandem-seat aircraft that contained 2 observers: the pilot and a backseat observer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>No black bears were encountered above 1,067 meters and terrain above this elevation was not considered black bear habitat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The 14,895 km2 of black bear habitat were sampled by 441 of the 470 flown transects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Roughly half of the bear habitat was too mountainous for straight-line transects and required contour transects [19–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Straight-line transects were hinged in the middle with a random angle between 30 and 330 degrees, and this facilitated efficient sampling of irregular shaped subareas that were suitable for “straight-line” transects (Fig 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Bear searches were restricted to one-side of the transect to facilitate the collection of double-count data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Searches along contour transects were conducted on the uphill side, while a random side was used for straight-line transects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Other than using hinged straight-line transects, survey methodology follows the details given in Becker and Quang [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Possible covariates included: bear activity (bedded, sitting, standing, moving), group size, percent cover within 10 m of the bear, percent snow cover within 10 m of the bear, plane speed, search distance, and transect type (straight, contour). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Percent cover and percent snow covariates were divided by 20, and air speed was divided by 100 to increase numerical efficiency of the optimizer used to obtain maximum likelihood estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Search distance represented how far out the observers were searching at the time the bear was detected and was measured by overflying that location and obtaining a GPS location, from which a distance to the transect was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The covariate Bin.lnSD350 represents the search distance covariate which was truncated at w, transformed to the natural log scale, and binned to into 9 classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The truncation and binning was done to minimize the correlation between this covariate and distance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The Skwetna study area of South-Central Alaska that was used in a 2007 aerial distance sampling survey of black bears. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The study area is enclosed by the red border and Cook Inlet to the southeast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Red-shaded areas within the study area denote locations that were above 1,067 m in elevation that were classified as non-black bear habitat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Yellow triangles denote the location of detected black bear groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The blue lines denote the actual flown transects, with contour transects flown in mountainous terrain and straight transects that contain a midpoint hinge being flown in the lower-elevation, flat terrain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A total of 260 black bear groups were detected from these transects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The distance data was truncated at 350 m (w = 350), in addition there was a 22 m blind spot underneath the plane, so π(y)=1(350−22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Within this 22–350 m strip, a total of 235 bear groups were detected, so 9.6% of the data were trimmed off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The distance data for these detections exhibited a unimodal distribution and were modeled using a two-piece normal detection function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The R-code [26] used to obtain the parameter estimates, standard errors, confidence intervals, graphs, and fit diagnostics are listed in appendix 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Standard errors and confidence intervals were based on Borchers et al. [12] variance formula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Based on AIC, the best MCDS model (Fig 2) included covariates for transect type (Fig 3) and percent cover (Fig 4) which affect both scale parameters (σ 1i,σ 2i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The Bin.lnSD350 covariate was included in modeling the σ 2i scale parameter (Fig 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The mode (μ^) was estimated to be 102.61 meters (se = 1.013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>This analysis ignored observer type (pilot or backseat observer) which resulted in a detection model for the survey plane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Parameter estimates and standard errors are given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A Goodness of Fit test for the MCDS model using 15 bins resulted in a Chi-sq. statistic of 7.742, df = 8, p = 0.459. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (p = 0.843) and a q-q plot (Fig 6) revealed no abnormalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these results indicate that the two-piece normal detection model provided an adequate fit to the data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Two-piece normal detection model for black bears in Skwetna study area of South-Central Alaska. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The detection curve is for averaged covariate values of binned search distance, percent cover, and transect type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The vertical line at 102.6 m depicts μ^. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The histogram is of the observed black bear group detection distances. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The effect of transect type on average covariate detection of black bears in the Skwetna study area of South-Central Alaska. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The effect of vegetative cover on average covariate detection of black bears in the Skwetna study area of South-Central Alaska. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The effect of binned search distance on average covariate detection of black bears in the Skwetna study area of South-Central Alaska. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Q-q plot of the multiple covariate distance model fit. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone.0136403.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Coefficients and standard errors for the best fitting multiple covariate distance sampling model using a two-piece normal detection model. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The parameter notation Bin.lnSD denotes the 9 binned values of the natural log of truncated search distance (SD), for which ln(350) m was substituted for ln(SD) if the SD value was beyond 350 m (w). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0136403.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0136403.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Parameter </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Coefficient </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>SE </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Intercept </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>3.5549 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>0.0644 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>I(y&gt; μ^) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>-2.5125 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>0.6103 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>I(y&gt; μ^) Bin.lnSD350 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>0.4526 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>0.0060 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Transect (Flat) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>0.5199 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>0.0358 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Percent Cover </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>-0.0944 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>0.0044 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>ln(μ^) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>4.6309 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>0.0128 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The Double-Observer model was fit using the R-package mrds [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In addition to the fixed observer effect, the covariates that were considered in the MCDS model for this data were also considered here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Based on AIC [28] (AIC = 3064.3), the best Double-Observer model included a 4th order polynomial spline of distance, percent cover, air speed, bear activity of bedded/sitting, and observer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Parameter estimates are given in Table 2 and a graph of the average covariate values are given in Figs 7 and 8 for the pilot and backseat observer models respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>A Goodness of Fit test resulted in a Chi-sq. value of 14.776, df = 11, p = 0.193. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>At 102.61 m (μ^), the model resulted in an estimate of 0.926 (se = 0.038) for p^•(μ^). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Logistic model of detection probabilities of the pilot given the backseat observer detected a black bear. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The solid line denotes the conditional detection probability for the average values of the distance, percent cover, observer, air speed, and bedded/sitting bear covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The circles represent the model estimated conditional probabilities for each bear, based on their observed covariates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Logistic model of detection probabilities of the backseat observer given the pilot detected a black bear. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The solid line denotes the conditional detection probability for the average values of the distance, percent cover, observer, air speed, and bedded/sitting bear covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The circles represent the model estimated conditional probabilities for each bear, based on their observed covariates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone.0136403.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Coefficients and standard errors for the best fitting double observer model which included a quadratic spline over distance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The 4-bs(distance, degree = 4) parameters denote the 4 parameters of the 4th order polynomial spline of distance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0136403.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0136403.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Parameter </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Coefficient </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>SE </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Intercept </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>2.2843 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>1.6794 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>bs(distance, degree = 4)1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>9.1280 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>3.2812 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>bs(distance, degree = 4)2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>-2.4780 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>2.7692 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>bs(distance, degree = 4)3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>5.7301 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>3.5575 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>bs(distance, degree = 4)4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>0.8770 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>1.6418 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Observer (backseat) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>-1.1690 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>0.2024 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Percent Cover </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>-0.3819 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>0.1356 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Air Speed </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>-2.8225 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>1.5882 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Bedded/Sitting </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>-0.5289 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>0.2960 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The estimated inclusion probabilities from our best MRDS model ranged from 0.137 to 0.790, with a median value of 0.555 (Fig 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Only 2.98% of the estimated probabilities were below 0.2, and all were within the limits suggested by Marques and Buckland [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Our MRDS model resulted in a population estimate of 2,377.0 black bears (se = 185.29, CV = 7.80%) and a 95% confidence interval of (1990.9, 2838.1) in the study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Converting to density (bears/1000 km2) results in a point estimate of 159.58 (se = 12.44) with a 95% confidence interval of (133.7, 190.5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0136403.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136403.g009</object-id><label>Fig 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Boxplot of the estimated Horvitz-Thompson inclusion probabilities. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0136403.g009"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec007"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In our best MRDS model of the black bear dataset, distance was an important covariate and was fit using a 4th degree polynomial spline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Our model did not restrict the apex locations of the MCDS and MRDS models to be the same. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The apexes, 102.6 and 110.8 m respectively, differed by 8.2 meters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The main reasons the apexes were not restricted to be the same were: 1) distance may not be included in the best MRDS model, 2) computational complexity, and 3) if distance were in the MRDS model, unmodeled heterogeneity in the mark-resight data may cause the 2 apex locations to differ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In our black bear example, the difference in the estimates of p^•(μ^) is negligible between these apex locations (0.926 and 0.928 respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Besides goodness of fit tests to assess model fit, we also required the estimated inclusion probabilities obtained from the model to meet the recommendations of Marques and Buckland [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This additional criterion ensures that the population estimate is not being driven by a few observations with very low estimated inclusion probabilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>An analogous situation exists for traditional Horvitz-Thompson estimators [29] (where the inclusion probabilities for the observations are known, not estimated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The inclusion probabilities are contained in the denominator for both the point estimate and the variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>If very small inclusion probabilities are encountered then the variance becomes very large and the point estimate is driven by these few probabilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>In traditional sampling, care is taken to avoid small inclusion probabilities, and optimal sample designs have the inclusion probabilities proportional to size [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The recommendation of Marques and Buckland [5] formalizes the avoidance of this problem with their criteria of no estimated inclusion probabilities lower than 0.1, and less than 5% falling in the 0.1 to 0.2 range. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Our black bear example illustrates the utility of distance sampling to make inferences over large study areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Areas of management interest are often so large that aerial distance sampling is one of the few logistically feasible options. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Double-count modeling is needed since the assumption of perfect detection at the detection apex would not be tenable without supporting data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Our double count model indicates that perfect detection at the apex may be reasonable for some black bear sightings but not for all sightings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with our expectations that black bears are not perfectly detectable at some apex distance from fast-moving aircraft over various covariate conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>A MCDS estimate that assumes perfect detection at the apex would generate a population estimate of 2,220.6 bears while a MRDS model assuming full independence would estimate 1,716.6 bears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>These estimates are 7.4% and 27.8% lower than our reported estimate of 2,377.0 black bears. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Very few options exist for modeling distance sampling data that exhibit a unimodal form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The gamma detection model developed by Becker and Quang [20] allows for covariates and has proven to be a useful model with aerially collected distance sampling data if the assumption of perfect detection at the apex is reasonable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>To determine if that assumption is reasonable, double-observer data must be collected [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>If the analysis of the double-count data indicates a MRDS model is required, the use of the gamma detection function to model the distance data could be problematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Using a gamma detection function in a MRDS model with PI would require a single apex location for the distance model, so no covariates could be used; thus a CDS model using a gamma detection function would model the distance data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>When appreciable variation in animal detection exists, as in the black bear example, the inability of the CDS model to incorporate covariates would result in an inferior estimate (AIC = 3111.5 versus 3064.3 for our model) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Neilson et al. [30] used a non-monotonic, non-parametric Gaussian kernel estimator to model aerially collected distance data on golden eagles (Aquila chrysaetos) with a MRDS model that used the PI assumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Their nonparametric detection model is more flexible than a unimodal detection model, but does not allow for covariates in the distance portion of the MRDS model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this paper is to model unimodal distance datasets with a MRDS model that addresses unmodeled heterogeneity in the mark-resight data and allows for the use of covariates in modeling animal detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>There are several approaches that could be modified to provide a solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The limited independence model 17] is one possible solution; the logistic detection function may have to be modified to adequately model the unimodal aerial distance data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The probit-Bernoulli model [18] is another possible solution; it would need to be modified to model observer dependence as a function of distance from the detection apex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>This model may allow for multiple detection apexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>We choose to take the approach of Borchers et al. [12] to solve this problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>We used the two-piece normal detection function with covariates in a MRDS model with the PI assumption obtain a population estimate from our aerially collected bear data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>This approach provided a good fit to our unimodal detection data, avoids the unrealistic assumption of perfect detection at the apex, avoids the FI assumption that has caused biases in many MRDS datasets, and allows for the use of covariates in the MCDS model to obtain a potentially superior model [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Researchers with unimodal detection data should consider the two-piece normal detection model for MRDS models and MCDS models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec008"><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0136403.s001"><label>S1 File</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>BlackBear.MRDS.data.csv. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>A csv file containing the black bear distance data that was analyzed in the manuscript; this file is required by PlosOneMRDSAnalysis.txt. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>(CSV) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0136403.s001.csv"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0136403.s002"><label>S2 File</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>SkwetnaTranData350.csv. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>A csv file containing the transect area information; this file is required by SkwetnaBlackBearAnalysis.txt. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>(CSV) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0136403.s002.csv"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0136403.s003"><label>S1 Text</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>PlosOneMRDSAnalysis.txt. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>A R script file that will replicate the results found in this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>(TXT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0136403.s003.txt"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0136403.s004"><label>S2 Text</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Two.Piece.Normal.txt. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>A R file containing all the R-functions written to fit a MRDS model that uses a two-piece normal detection model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>These functions are required by the SkwetnaBlackBearAnalysis.txt file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>(TXT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0136403.s004.txt"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Rebecca Strauch, Alaska Department of Fish and Game, provided invaluable GIS support for this project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>David Miller, University of St. Andrews, made the mrds R-code [24–25] available for us to obtain variance estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Steve Buckland, University of St. Andrews, provided invaluable encouragement and insights on modeling dependence in MRDS models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Jeff Laake, National Marine Mammal Laboratory, patiently answered numerous questions, and provided numerous insights into MRDS models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Louise Burt and David Miller, both at the University of St. Andrews, provided invaluable assistance in using and understanding the mrds R-package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>We thank the pilots: J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>DeCreft, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Filkill, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Greenblat, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Litzen, and H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>McMahan, for their expert and safe survey flying. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>We also thank the backseat observers: L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Gustavsen, T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Peltier, and H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Reynolds for their untiring efforts in collecting the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Alaska Department of Fish and Game and the Federal Aid in Wildlife Restoration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>We thank Paul Conn and another anonymous referee for their constructive reviews that has greatly improved this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The R-code [25] used in this analysis is included in the appendix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The two-piece normal detection model is planned to be incorporated into the mrds R-package [26–27] in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0136403.ref001"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>1 BucklandST, AndersonDR, BurnhamKP, LaakeJL, BorchersDL, ThomasL. Introduction to distance sampling New York: Oxford University Press; 2001. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref002"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>2 DrummerTD, McDonaldLL. Size bias in line-transect sampling. Biometrics. 1987 3;43(1):13–21. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref003"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>3 QuangPX, BeckerEF. Line transect sampling under varying conditions with applications to aerial surveys. Ecology. 1996 6;77(4):1297–1302. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref004"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>4 MarquesFFC, BucklandST. Incorporating covariates into standard line transect analyses. Biometrics. 2003 12;59(4):924–935. <?supplied-pmid 14969471?>14969471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref005"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>5 MarquesFCC, BucklandST. Covariate models for the detection function In: BucklandST, AndersonDR, BurnhamKP, LaakeJL, BorchersDL, ThomasL, editors. Advanced Distance Sampling. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2004 pp. 31–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref006"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>6 BurnhamKP, BucklandST, LaakeJL, BorchersDL, MarquesTA, BishopJRN, et al Further topics in distance sampling In: BucklandST, AndersonDR, BurnhamKP, LaakeJL, BorchersDL, ThomasL, editors. Advanced Distance Sampling. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2004 pp. 307–392. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref007"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>7 BurnhamKP, AndersonDR, LaakeJL. Estimation of density from line transect sampling of biological populations. Wildlife Monographs. 1980;72:1–202. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref008"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>8 Alpizar-JaraR, PollockKH. A combination of line transect and capture-recapture sampling model for multiple observers in aerial surveys. Environ Ecol Stat. 1998 12;3(4):311–327. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref009"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>9 ManlyBFJ, McDonaldLL, GarnerGW. Maximum likelihood estimation for the double-count method with independent observers. J Agric Biol Environ Stat. 1996 6;1(2):170–189. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref010"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>10 QuangPX, BeckerEF. Combining line transect and double count sampling techniques for aerial surveys. J Agric Biol Environ Stat. 1997 6;2(2):230–242. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref011"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>11 BorchersDL, ZucchiniW, FewsterRM. Mark-recapture models for line transect surveys. Biometrics. 1998 12;54(4):1207–1220. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref012"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>12 BorchersDL, LaakeJL, SouthwellC, PaxtonCGM. Accommodating unmodeled heterogeneity in double-observer distance sampling surveys. Biometrics. 2006 6;62(2):372–378. <?supplied-pmid 16918901?>16918901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref013"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>13 HugginsRM. On the statistical analysis of capture experiments. Biometrika. 1989 3;76(1):133–140. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref014"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>14 LaakeJL, BorchersDL. Methods for incomplete detection at distance zero In: BucklandST, AndersonDR, BurnhamKP, LaakeJL, BorchersDL, ThomasL, editors. Advanced Distance Sampling. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2004 pp. 108–189. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref015"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>15 LaakeJ, DawsonMJ, HoneJ, Visibility bias in aerial survey: mark-recapture, line-transect or both? Wildlife Research. 2008 1;35(4):299–309. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref016"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>16 LaakeJL. Distance sampling with independent observers: reducing bias from heterogeneity by weakening the conditional independence assumption In: GarnerGW, AmstrupSC, LaakeJL, ManlyBFJ, McDonaldLL, RobertsonDG, editors. Marine mammal survey and assessment methods. Rotterdam: Balkema Press; 1999 pp. 137–148. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref017"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>17 BucklandST, LaakeJL, BorchersDL. Double-observer line transect methods: levels of independence. Biometrics. 2010 3;66(1):169–177. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1541-0420.2009.01239.x">10.1111/j.1541-0420.2009.01239.x</ext-link> <?supplied-pmid 19432793?>19432793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref018"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>18 ConnPB, LaakeJL, JohnsonDS. A hierarchical modeling framework for multiple observer transect surveys. PLoS One. 2012 8 8;7(8):e42294 doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0042294">10.1371/journal.pone.0042294</ext-link> <?supplied-pmid 22905121?>22905121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref019"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>19 QuangPX, BeckerEF. Aerial line transect sampling of contour transects using double-count and covariate data In: GarnerGW, AmstrupSC, LaakeJL, ManlyBFJ, McDonaldLL, RobertsonDG, editors. Marine mammal survey and assessment methods. Rotterdam: Balkema Press; 1999 pp. 87–97. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref020"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>20 BeckerEF, QuangPX. A gamma-shaped detection function for line-transect surveys with mark-recapture and covariate data. J Agric Biol Environ Stat. 2009 6;14(2):207–223. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref021"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>21 HibyL, KrishnaMB. Line transect sampling from a curved path. Biometrics. 2001 9;57(3):727–731. <?supplied-pmid 11550921?>11550921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref022"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>22 JohnsonNL, KotzS, BalakrishnanN. Continuous Univariate Distributions, Volume 1 New York: John Wiley and Sons; 1994. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref023"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>23 RamseyFL, WildmanV, EngbringJ. Covariate adjustments to effective area in variable-area wildlife surveys. Biometrics. 1987 3;43(1):1–11. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref024"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>24 VenablesWN, RipleyBD. Modern applied statistics with S-PLUS New York: Springer-Verlag; 1997. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref025"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>25 HastieTJ. Generalized additive models In: ChambersJM, HastieTJ, editors. Statistical Models. New York: Chapman and Hall; 1997 pp. 249–307. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref026"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>26 R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing Vienna: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref027"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>27Laake JL, Borchers DL, Thomas LJ, Miller DL, Bishop J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Mark-recapture distance sampling (mrds); 2015 Jul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Software: mrds [Internet]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/mrds/index.html">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/mrds/index.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref028"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>28 AkaikeH. Prediction and entrophy In: AtkinsonAC, FinbergSE, editors. A celebration of statistics. Berlin: Springer-Verlag; 1985 pp. 1–24. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref029"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>29 ThompsonSK. Sampling, 2nd ed. New York: John Wiley and sons; 2002. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0136403.ref030"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>30 NielsonRM, McmanusL, RintzT, McDonaldLL, MurphyRK, HoweWH, et al Monitoring abundance of Golden Eagles in the Western United States. J Wildl Manage. 2014 5;78(4):721–730. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
