<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4294342</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25426549</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Downregulated MTAP expression in myxofibrosarcoma: A characterization of inactivating mechanisms, tumor suppressive function, and therapeutic relevance </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Chien-Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Fu-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>Hsing-Jien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Li-Tzong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jun-Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Jen-Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9"><sup>9</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Shih Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10"><sup>10</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yu-Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11"><sup>11</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Shau-Hsuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12"><sup>12</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Hsuan-Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10"><sup>10</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Pathology, Chi-Mei Medical Center, Tainan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Biotechnology, Southern Taiwan University of Science and Technology, Tainan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> National Institute of Cancer Research National Health Research Institutes, Tainan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Institute of Clinical Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A5"><sup>5</sup> Departments of Radiation Oncology, Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital and Chang Gung University College of Medicine, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A6"><sup>6</sup> Institute of Molecular and Genomic Medicine, National Health Research Institutes, Tainan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A7"><sup>7</sup> Department of Internal Medicine and Cancer Center, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A8"><sup>8</sup> Orthopedic Surgery, Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital and Chang Gung University College of Medicine, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A9"><sup>9</sup> Department of Anatomic Pathology, E-Da Hospital, Kaohsiung, Tawian</aff><aff id="A10"><sup>10</sup> Department of Pathology, Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital and Chang Gung University College of Medicine, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A11"><sup>11</sup> Institute of Biosignal Transduction, National Cheng Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A12"><sup>12</sup> Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Oncology, Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital and Chang Gung University College of Medicine, Kaohsiung, Taiwan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Hsuan-Ying Huang, <email>a120600310@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>11428</fpage><lpage>11441</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2014 Li et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Myxofibrosarcomas are genetically complex and involve recurrently deleted chromosome 9p, for which we characterized the pathogenically relevant target(s) using genomic profiling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In 12 of the 15 samples, we detected complete or partial losses of 9p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The only aggressiveness-associated, differentially lost region was 9p21.3, spanning the potential inactivated methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) that exhibited homozygous (4/15) or hemizygous (3/15) deletions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In independent samples, MTAP gene status was assessed using quantitative- and methylation-specific PCR assays, and immunoexpression was evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We applied MTAP reexpression or knockdown to elucidate the functional roles of MTAP and the therapeutic potential of L-alanosine in MTAP-preserved and MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcoma cell lines and xenografts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>MTAP protein deficiency (37%) was associated with MTAP gene inactivation (P &lt; 0.001) by homozygous deletion or promoter methylation, and independently portended unfavorable metastasis-free survival (P = 0.0318) and disease-specific survival (P = 0.014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Among the MTAP-deficient cases, the homozygous deletion of MTAP predicted adverse outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In MTAP-deficient cells, MTAP reexpression inhibited cell migration and invasion, proliferation, and anchorage-independent colony formation and downregulated cyclin D1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This approach also attenuated the tube-forming abilities of human umbilical venous endothelial cells, attributable to the transcriptional repression of MMP-9, and abrogated the susceptibility to L-alanosine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The inhibiting effects of MTAP expression on tumor growth, angiogenesis, and the induction of apoptosis by L-alanosine were validated using MTAP-reexpressing xenografts and reverted using RNA interference in MTAP-preserved cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, homozygous deletion primarily accounts for the adverse prognostic impact of MTAP deficiency and confers the biological aggressiveness and susceptibility to L-alanosine in myxofibrosarcomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>myxofibrosarcoma</kwd><kwd>MTAP</kwd><kwd>homozygous deletion</kwd><kwd>methylation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Myxofibrosarcoma is characterized by the multinodular growth of spindle to polygonal sarcoma cells within variably myxoid stroma containing long curvilinear vessels [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Clinically, increased tumor grades and stages are frequently observed in myxofibrosarcomas after local recurrence, and may cause metastatic diseases [1–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, histological evaluation is insufficiently satisfactory to predict aggressiveness of individual cases, indicating the need to elucidate the pathogenesis of myxofibrosarcoma [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Genetically, complex karyotypic changes are characteristic of myxofibrosarcomas [4, 5] and a recent large-scale genomic study indicated that a nonrandom loss of chromosome 9, and particularly 9p, occurs in myxofibrosarcomas [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>By using ultrahigh-resolution array comparative genomic hybridization (aCGH), we previously profiled the global copy-number alterations (CNAs) in myxofibrosarcoma specimens and cell lines and characterized SKP2 on 5p and CDK6 and MET on 7q as amplified oncogenes of pathogenic relevance [6–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Regarding DNA losses, chromosome 9p was the most frequently lost chromosomal arm in myxofibrosarcomas [5], prompting the search for potential tumor suppressor gene(s) underlying this selection pressure for the loss of 9p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>We characterized methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) on 9p21.3 because whether the tumor-suppressive role of this polyamine metabolism-regulating enzyme is independent from the frequently co-deleted CDKN2A and CDKN2B genes still remains debated [9–12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In this study, MTAP protein deficiency in myxofibrosarcomas was associated with a poor prognosis and inactivated MTAP gene, caused by either homozygous deletion or promoter methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Functionally, MTAP deficiency yielded increased aggression in myxofibrosarcoma cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>By restricting the adenosine monophosphate (AMP) supply [13, 14], L-alanosine induced prominent apoptosis in the MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcoma cells and derived xenografts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Collectively, the mechanistic and clinical evidence reinforces MTAP as a functional tumor suppressor gene exhibiting prognostic and therapeutic relevance in myxofibrosarcomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2_1"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Genomic profiling revealed recurrent 9p loss </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Chromosomal imbalances of varying degrees were detected in all samples subjected to aCGH profiling, indicating more recurrent deletions than gains, and exhibiting characteristically high genomic complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>According to filter criteria, Nexus software revealed recurrent DNA gains in 211 chromosomal regions spanning 4577 genes in all of the genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, 235 chromosomal regions were nonrandomly lost, involving 7871 named genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In the long arm of chromosome 9, the copy number alterations were predominantly of DNA gains, except for the 9q34 region that exhibited DNA losses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the complete or partial losses of 9p were detected in 12 of the 15 samples, and five major deletion cores on 9p, recurrent in ≥ 20% of samples tested, were interspersed with short stretches of DNA gains (Figures 1A, B, Supplementary Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Within the 9p22.2-p21.1 deletion core, the sole differentially deleted, aggressiveness-associated region on 9p was narrowed down to 9p21.3 (P = 0.0454). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>This result indicated the implication of 9p21.3 in the myxofibrosarcoma progression, in which MTAP and CDKN2A/CDKN2B were homozygously deleted in 4 and 4 samples and hemizygously deleted in 3 and 3 samples, respectively (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>MTAP homozygous deletion in myxofibrosarcoma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>(A) Referring to chromosome 9 cytoband, genomic profiling exhibits near arm-level losses of 9p clustered in five major deletion cores (top). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Within the middle deletion core (9p22.2-p21.1), homozygous deletions frequently involves the aggressiveness-associated 9p21.3 region as delineated by the rectangle (middle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>At higher magnification, the genomic locus of MTAP gene in the 9p21.3 region is illustrated (bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Frequency plots of the CNAs are expressed in blue (gain) or red (loss). (B) The close-up view of representative myxofibrosarcoma cell line (NMFH-2) and tissue (MFS96b) samples shows the homozygous deletion of the MTAP gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Intratumoral nonneoplastic cells in MFS96b account for the less prominent loss of MTAP copies. (C) Upper: A Grade 1 myxofibrosarcoma stained with hematoxylin-eosin (left) shows diffused MTAP expression (middle) and a preserved MTAP gene, shown as the red curve in a quantitative DNA-PCR (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Lower: A Grade 3 myxofibrosarcoma stained with hematoxylin-eosin (left) shows MTAP-deficient sarcoma cells (middle) and the nondetectable MTAP gene (right). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Associations of MTAP immunoexpression with clinicopathological and gene statuses in primary myxofibrosarcomas </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The MTAP immunostain of 87 independent primary myxofibrosarcomas (Figure 1C) demonstrated an aberrant MTAP deficiency in 32 cases (37%). MTAP gene dosage was successfully determined in 79 cases, 20 of which (25.3%) exhibited homozygous deletion at an MTAP/PFKL ratio of &lt; 0.2 (Table 1, Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Because 13 of the 29 MTAP protein-deficient tumors were not homozygously deleted at the MTAP gene (Table 1), methylation-specific PCR was adopted to examine whether promoter hypermethylation alternatively caused protein loss, and 10 of these 13 cases were hypermethylated at the MTAP promoter (Table 1, Figure S1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>MTAP protein deficiency was strongly related to inactivated MTAP genes (P &lt; 0.001, Table 1), either by homozygous deletion or promoter methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Regarding the status of MTAP protein expression and promoter methylation, no significant difference was detected in the clincopathological features, including the tumor grading and staging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>By contrast, MTAP homozygous deletion was significantly correlated with high histological grades (P = 0.006, Figure 1C, Table 1) and a high mitotic rate (P = 0.011, Figure S1B), and marginally correlated with advanced clinical stages (P = 0.097). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Associations of clinicopathological features with MTAP immunoexpression and gene status in primary myxofibrosarcomas </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>MTAP Expression (n=87) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>p-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>MTAP Gene (n=79) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>p-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Deficient </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Positive </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>HD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Non-HD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Sex </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>0.936 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain> Male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain> Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Age </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>0.854 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain> &lt;60 years </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain> ≥60 years </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Location </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>0.799 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>0.908 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain> Extremity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain> Axial </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Tumor necrosis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>0.483 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>0.115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain> &lt;10% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain> &gt;=10% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>FNCLCC grade </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>0.534 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>0.006* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain> grade 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain> grade 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain> grade 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>AJCC stage </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>0.763 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>0.097 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain> Stage 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain> Stage 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain> Stage 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Tumor size&amp; </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>7.314±6.528 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>6.347±3.701 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>0.633 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>6.600 4.808 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>7.311 5.551 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>0.612 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Mitotic rate&amp; </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>12.81±13.143 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>10.33±1.695 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>0.585 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>8.780±9.180 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>19.050±15.408 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>0.011* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>MTAP gene status </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain> Aberration (HD, PM) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>26 (16,10) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>4 (4,0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain> No aberration (no HD or PM detected) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>46 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>HD: homozygous deletion, PM: promoter methylation, </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fn id="tfn-001"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>:Statistically significant, </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tfn-002"><label>&amp;</label><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>:t-test, </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Survival analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Univariate correlations of the clinical outcome with various clinicopathological, immunohistochemical, and molecular parameters are shown in Table S3 and Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>MTAP protein deficiency was a significant adverse prognosticator of an adverse DSS (P = 0.0195, Figure 2A) and was marginally predictive of a short MFS (P = 0.0572, Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Regarding various mechanisms regulating MTAP expression, MTAP-homozygously deleted myxofibrosarcomas behaved aggressively and exhibited significantly shorter DSS (P = 0.0129, Figure 2C) and MFS (P = 0.0150, Figure 2D) values than did the cases lacking homozygous deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Among the nonhomozygously deleted cases, no difference in prognosis was observed between the MTAP-expressing and MTAP-hypermethylated cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Compared with the homozygously deleted cases, the MTAP-deficient tumors caused by methylation exhibited a trend toward more favorable outcomes (P = 0.0735, Figure 2C; P = 0.0881, Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>These results suggested variable implications of distinct inactivating mechanisms in MTAP-deficient tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In the multivariate analysis (Table S4), MTAP protein deficiency was the single independent prognosticator of an inferior DSS (P = 0.0140, hazard ratio = 4.020) and, along with high histological grades, could predict inferior MFS (P = 0.0318, hazard ratio = 2.527). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>MTAP protein deficiency predicts adverse disease-specific </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>(A) and metastasis-free survival (B) rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Myxofibrosarcomas involving homozygously deleted MTAP genes yield significantly poor outcomes for both survival endpoints (C, D) and MTAP-expressing and MTAP-methylated cases did not differ prognostically. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Tumor suppressive functions of MTAP in myxofibrosarcoma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Because of physical proximity, MTAP inactivation by deletion in 9p21.3 was generally considered a bystander event concomitant with deletions of CDKN2A/B [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Until recently, scholars have started noticing the tumor-suppressive attributes of MTAP that may independently inhibit carcinogenesis [9, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>We first characterized myxofibrosarcoma cell lines regarding their MTAP gene status and endogenous protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the aCGH findings, homozygous deletion in OH931 and NMFH-2 cells was confirmed using real-time PCR quantification without a detectable MTAP DNA copy (Figures 3A, S2A), reflective of the absence of MTAP protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Endogenously expressing MTAP, the NMFH-1 cells were neither homozygously deleted at the MTAP gene nor methylated at its promoter (Figure 3A, S1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we applied MATP-bearing vectors and shMTAP to decipher how inactivated MTAP modulates myxofibrosarcoma phenotypes regarding various cancer hallmarks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The stably transfected and knockdown clones were validated using western blots (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In the NMFH-1 cells, the silencing of the MTAP transcript with 2 stable clones of shMTAP was determined using real-time quantitation (Figure S2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In vitro growth-inhibiting function of MTAP linked to downregulated cyclin D1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>(A) Compared with reference CCD966SK fibroblasts, the OH931 and NMFH-2 cell lines were homozygously deleted at the MTAP gene; no DNA copy was detected using real-time PCR (left) and the western blots exhibited no MTAP expression (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Although the MTAP gene dosage was slightly decreased, a western blotting assay revealed MTAP-expressing NMFH-1 cells. (B) Stable exogenous MTAP reexpression was achieved in the OH931 (left) and NMFH-2 (middle) myxofibrosarcoma cell lines, and the western blots exhibited the expected bands using anti-MTAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Two clones of shMTAP stably downregulated MTAP expression in NMFH-1 cells exhibiting decreased protein abundance (right), compared with the non-targeting shLacZ controls. (C) The BrdU readout, indicating the level of proliferative activity, was significantly reduced in stable MTAP-transfected NMFH-2 cells (left), but increased in MTAP-silenced NMFH-1 cells (right), compared with the corresponding controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Depending on the MTAP expression status, only the expression level of cyclin D1 in western blots was consistently altered as expected among the MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 cells and 2 MTAP-knockdown clones of the NMFH-1 cells. (D) Compared with the empty controls (left), the MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 transfectants (middle) formed fewer colonies on soft agar, as expressed in the histogram (bottom). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>MTAP expression inhibited cell proliferation and colony formation of myxofibrosarcoma primarily through the downregulation of cyclin D1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>To elucidate the potential MTAP-associated antitumor function, we compared the BrdU readout of myxofibrosarcoma cells engineered to manifest various MTAP expression levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In the MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 myxofibrosarcoma transfectants, the readout indicative of cell proliferation significantly reduced, whereas shMTAP effectively promoted cell proliferation in the NMFH-1 cells exhibiting endogenous MTAP (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>By using an ECIS assay, we measured NMFH-2 cells for real-time cell proliferation, revealing a significantly slow cell growth rate in MTAP-reexpressing transfectants (Figure S2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>These observations supported that MTAP may dampen the proliferation of myxofibrosarcoma, prompting investigating whether MTAP expression modulates cell cycle regulators and inhibits colony formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>We performed western blotting to evaluate alterations in the G1- and G1/S-associated cyclins and cyclin-dependent kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Among these, only cyclin D1 expression was consistently downregulated in both MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 cells and shLac-transfected NMFH-1 cells (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>However, the trend in alterations in cyclin E and CDK2 expression varied between exogenous expression and RNA interference approaches as well as between 2 shMTAP clones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In the flow cytometric analysis, MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 cells exhibited significant cell cycle arrest in the G1 phase and concomitant low percentages of cells in the S and G2 phases (Figure S2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In a soft-agar assay, significantly small and few cell colonies were observed in MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 transfectants, substantiating the inhibition of MTAP in anchorage-independent growth (Figure 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>These findings imply that cyclin D1 represents the predominant cell cycle regulator associated with the antiproliferative role of MTAP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>MTAP expression inhibited cell migration and invasion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The results of wound-healing assays indicated significantly rapid wound closure in both NMFH-2 cells transfected with an empty vector and NMFH-1 cells silenced against endogenous MTAP (Figure S3A,C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>According to matrigel invasion assays, the 2 conditions also yielded significantly increased invading tumor cells (Figure S3B), indicating enhanced metastatic propensity by MTAP deficiency in myxofibrosarcomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>MTAP expression conferred antiangiogenic function </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Recently, we reported that aberrant loss of argininosuccinate synthetase (ASS1) caused by promoter methylation may contribute to the enhanced angiogenesis in myxofibrosarcomas [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Because MTAP is linked to polyamine metabolism and adenine and methionine salvage [16, 17], examining whether MTAP inactivation promotes angiogenesis by perturbing the metabolic balance of sarcoma cells is conceivable, similar to the scenario involved in deregulated ASS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Under various experimental conditions used to manipulate MTAP expression, 3 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines were assessed for the formation of HUVEC tubes incubated with corresponding conditioned media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Using HUVEC assays, the angiogenic capability significantly decreased to 55% and 60% in the MTAP-reexpressing OH931 and NMFH-2 transfectants, respectively, but significantly increased up to 2~3-fold in the MTAP-silenced NMFH-1 cells (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Because of increased angiogenesis in the MTAP-deficient state, we used an RT-PCR expression array to explore the potential mediators relevant to MTAP-regulated angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Lacking upregulated genes in this angiogenesis-associated panel, MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 cells showed significantly reduced mRNA expression of 6 candidates (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Of these, CXCL-9, CXCL-10, and MMP-9 proteins were concomitantly downregulated using western blots in both NMFH-2 and OH931 MTAP-reexpressing cell lines, the conditioned media of which also consistently demonstrated decreased MMP-9 protein concentration using ELISA (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Real-time RT-PCR showed decreased expression of MMP-9 mRNA in both MTAP-reexpressing myxofibrosarcoma cell lines (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In the MTAP-silenced NMFH-1 cells used for cross-validation, MMP-9 was the only molecule that exhibited upregulated mRNA and protein expression (Figure 4B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The luciferase activity of MMP-9 promoter significantly reduced in the MTAP-reexpressing OH931 and NMFH-2 cells (Figure 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>These data demonstrated that MTAP deficiency enhanced the transcriptional upregulation of MMP-9 to promote angiogenesis in myxofibrosarcomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>MTAP governs tumor angiogenesis by the transcriptional repression of MMP-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>(A) The well-formed HUVEC tubes decrease when exposed to conditioned media from MTAP-reexpressing transfectants of NMFH-2 and OH931 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Conversely, MTAP knockdown promoted angiogenesis in both shMTAP-transduced clones of the NMFH-1 cells (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The relative level of angiogenic tube-forming activity is expressed in the histograms (right). (B) Of the differentially expressed genes identified from the RT-PCR expression array, western blotting validation for both MTAP-reexpressing transfectants exhibited correspondingly decreased protein expression of CXCL-9, CXCL-10, and MMP-9 (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The MMP-9 protein concentration secreted into the conditioned media was significantly reduced in MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 and OH931 cell lines (middle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Only the level of MMP-9 protein expression was significantly upregulated in the cross-validation of MTAP-silenced NMFH-1 cells (right). (C) As a representative potential downstream mediator of MTAP, the MMP-9 mRNA expression levels were significantly downregulated in the MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 and OH931 cells (left) but elevated by MTAP knockdown using quantitative RT-PCR (right). (D) Luciferase activity of MMP-9 promoter construct was significantly lower in the NMFH-2 and OH931 cells transfected with the MTAP-expressing vector than in the empty controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and the results are expressed as mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_8"><title><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>MTAP reexpression inhibited growth of xenografted tumors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The in vivo inhibitory effect of MTAP on tumor growth was analyzed in NMFH-2 xenografts exhibiting ectopic MTAP reexpression versus empty controls (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The xenografts reexpressing MTAP exhibited a significantly small average tumor volume from Day 7 until sacrifice on Day 30, on which the excised specimens were evidently larger and heavier in the controls than were those in the MTAP-reexpressing group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The control xenografts exhibited more high-grade pleomorphic cells in a fibromyxoid matrix and a higher mitotic rate (P &lt; 0.001) compared with the MTAP-reexpressing xenografts primarily composed of low-grade spindle cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemically, MTAP-reexpressing xenografts exhibited a significantly reduced labeling of cyclin D1, cyclin E, and Ki-67, as well as decreased intratumoral vessels stained with the CD31 endothelial marker, substantiating the antiproliferative and antiangiogenic attributes of MTAP in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In vivo tumor suppressive function of MTAP and the inhibition of L-alanosine in MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcoma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>(A) The average tumor volume of the empty vector-transfected NMFH-2 xenografts was significantly larger than that of the MTAP-reexpressing counterparts (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>On Day 30, the excised xenografts were grossly larger and heavier in the control group than in the MTAP-reexpressing group (middle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Histologically, control xenografts (upper panel) comprise MTAP-deficient high-grade pleomorphic sarcoma cells that exhibit frequent mitotic figures, the increased expression of cyclin D1, cyclin E, Ki-67, and MMP-9, and an increased microvascular density based on CD31 staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>However, contrasting results were observed in the MTAP-reexpressing group (lower panel), which exhibited low-grade MTAP-expressing spindle cells (right). (B) L-alanosine effectively attenuated the viability of MTAP-deficient NMFH-2 and OH931 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines, and MTAP-expressing NMFH-1 cells were relatively resistant to L-alanosine, demonstrating &gt;50% viable sarcoma cells, even at 100 μM (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Unlike the sensitivity in the parent lines and empty controls, MTAP reexpression caused decreased susceptibility to L-alanosine in the OH931 (middle) and NMFH-2 (right) cells. (C) The average tumor volume was significantly larger in the PBS-treated group than in the groups treated with 25 μM and 50 μM of L-alanosine (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>On Day 42, the excised xenografts remained macroscopically larger and heavier in the control group, exhibiting no dose-dependent difference between the groups treated with 25 μM and 50 μM of L-alanosine (middle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the high-grade pleomorphic histology in the control xenografts lacking apparent apoptosis, the L-alanosine-treated group exhibited increased numbers of fibrohyaline collagen fibers and TUNEL-labeled apoptotic cells (right). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_9"><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>MTAP protein deficiency was associated with increases of proliferative index, microvessel density, and MMP-9 expression level in primary myxofibrosarcomas </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In a subset common cohort of 40 primary myxofibrosarcomas yielding informative scoring results (Table S6, Figure S4), we further corroborated the in vitro findings in clinical samples that MTAP protein deficiency was highly associated with increased Ki-67 labeling index (p &lt; 0.001), microvessel density (p = 0.002) assessed by CD31 staining [18], and MMP-9 expression levels (p &lt; 0.001) evaluated by H-score method [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_10"><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>L-alanosine inhibited MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcoma cells and xenografts by inducing apoptosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Because L-alanosine can completely abrogate AMP supply in MTAP-deficient cells, we investigated whether L-alanosine can effectively inhibit this aggressive subset of myxofibrosarcomas by targeting the methionine de novo pathway [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>All myxofibrosarcoma cell lines were incubated with indicated doses of L-alanosine for 72 h; this attenuated the cell viability in only the MTAP-deficient parent NMFH-2 and OH931 cells yielding IC50 values of approximately 1 μM and 5 μM, respectively, but not in the MTAP-expressing NMFH-1 cells (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry demonstrated a significantly increased sub-G1 population in both L-alanosine-treated OH931 and NMFH-2 cells, and the induction of apoptosis, particularly prominent in the NMFH-2 cells, was validated using annexin V/propidium iodide staining assays (Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Stable MTAP-reexpressing OH931 and NMFH-2 cells were employed to explore how MTAP expression affected the susceptibility of myxofibrosarcoma cells to L-alanosine (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This approach significantly reverted the attenuated cell viability caused by L-alanosine, indicating that its antitumor selectivity was attributable to the MTAP deficiency in myxofibrosarcoma cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the in vivo efficacy of L-alanosine in NMFH-2 xenografts (Figure 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>From Day 25 posttreatment until Day 42 at sacrifice, significantly smaller tumor volumes were observed in both groups treated with L-alanosine at 25 μM or 50 μM, compared with the PBS controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>However, no dose-dependent therapeutic effect was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The control xenografts exhibited high-grade pleomorphic histology characterized by frequent atypical mitoses, whereas the L-alanosine-treated specimens exhibited quiescent or apoptotic-appearing cells in a fibromyxoid backdrop containing increased hyaline collagenous fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In the L-alanosine-treated xenografts, significantly increased TUNEL-labeled apoptotic cells were observed (P &lt; 0.001), substantiating the in vivo apoptosis-inducing effect of L-alanosine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Myxofibrosarcoma is a common, and genetically complex sarcoma of histological and biological heterogeneity, and its therapeutic mainstay is conducting radical surgery to achieve clear margins [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The lack of effective molecular markers and standardized chemoradiotherapeutic regimen(s) dictates an unfavorable prognosis in primary advanced and recurrent myxofibrosarcomas [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>By integrating various methodologies, we identified the clinical, biological, and therapeutic relevance of MTAP deficiency, which was observed in 37% of primary myxofibrosarcomas, strongly linked to homozygous deletion or promoter methylation, and independently predictive of adverse survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>However, no inactivating mechanism was detected in the 3 MTAP-deficient cases, suggesting that MTAP downregulation was caused by alternative molecular defects such as small deletions of 5′ regions [20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, homozygous deletion of MTAP gene was detected in four cases interpreted as MTAP-expressing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This conflicting finding was most likely attributable to the existence of intratumoral heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Whatever whole-block or tissue microarray sections, the MTAP-positive tumor cells only ranged from 10% to 20% at most, which might not be isolated in the process of laser capture microdissection and therefore result in an underestimated gene ratio skewed toward homozygous deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Compared with the equally indolent MTAP-hypermethylated and MTAP-expressing myxofibrosarcomas, MTAP-homozygously deleted tumors were often high-grade and clinically aggressive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>This variation in the prognostic effect of MTAP gene abrogation between distinct mechanisms in myxofibrosarcoma progression was concordant with our previous findings regarding GISTs [22], indicating the probable random occurrence of MTAP promoter methylation in the early phase of myxofibrosarcoma tumorigenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>However, MTAP homozygous deletion represents a relatively late genetic event in the tumor progression, which may confer survival advantage to aggressive subclones of myxofibrosarcoma cells and thereby culminate in negative prognostic impact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>MTAP depletion is not uncommon in human malignancies and is primarily attributable to homozygous deletions spanning 9p21.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>MTAP deficiency may occur without the loss of adjoining CDKN2A in non-small cell lung cancers and gliomas [13, 14, 23–26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Instead of genomic losses, promoter hypermethylation represents the preponderant inactivating mechanism in MTAP-deficient hepatocellular carcinomas [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Functionally, MTAP reexpression in MTAP-deleted breast cancer cells may inhibit anchorage-independent growth and in vivo tumorigenicity [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Although mice heterozygous for germline MTAP mutations did not fully recapitulate the genetic events in clinical specimens, they were prone to developing T-cell lymphomas; however, homozygous inactivation was embryonically lethal in the MTAP-knockout murine model [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Because of these conflicting findings, whether the loss of MTAP activity is pathogenically relevant remains debated [9, 11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Given the clinical relevance of MTAP deficiency in myxofibrosarcomas, we characterized the biology of MTAP expression to clarify its functional effects on cancer hallmark-related phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The antiproliferative function of MTAP by the downregulation of cyclin D1 was validated using both MTAP knockdown in MTAP-expressing NMFH-1 cells and MTAP-reexpression in MTAP-deficient NMFH-2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Regarding the latter condition, the growth-inhibiting attribute of MTAP was reinforced by the reduced proliferation evidenced in the ECIS measurements, few colonies in the soft-agar assays, and low-grade histology of the corresponding xenografted specimens exhibiting an underexpression of Ki-67 and cyclin D1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>We also corroborated the suppressive role of MTAP in metastasis, which is the leading cause of sarcoma-associated mortality and critically involves the regulation of cell motility and transgression through an extracellular matrix [2, 27, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>In MTAP-reexpressing NMFH-2 cells, delayed closure in wound-healing assays and decreased invading cells through matrix-coated wells were measured and cross-validated by the reverse results of MTAP-silenced NMFH-1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Clinically, the independent effect of MTAP deficiency on adverse MFS in myxofibrosarcomas was reflective of these MTAP-associated antimigratory and antiinvasive functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>In MTAP-reexpressing and shLacZ-transduced myxofibrosarcoma cells, angiogenic capability was significantly impaired, as indicated by reduced levels of HUVEC-derived tube formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these findings corroborated endogenous MTAP as a functional suppressor that governs myxofibrosarcoma pathogenesis by inhibiting tumor proliferation, metastasis, and angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In the luciferase reporter assay, the antiangiogenic effect of MTAP was determined to primarily link to the transcriptional repression of MMP-9, ultimately attenuating mRNA and protein expression in the myxofibrosarcoma cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>In the MTAP-deficient xenografts and myxofibrosarcoma specimens, MMP-9 overexpression was present in the tumor cells and extracellular stroma and associated with increased microvessel density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>These exemplified the oncogenic role of MMP-9 in myxofibrosarcoma pathogenesis and corresponded with previous reports on its associations with aggressiveness in various cancer types [15, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Kiroviski reported that MTAP knockdown upregulated MMP-9 expression through the accumulation of 5′-deoxy-5′-methylthioadenosine in hepatocellular carcinomas [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>However, they neither elucidated the mechanistic link between MTAP deficiency and MMP-9 nor characterized the functional effect of this perturbed regulatory chain on angiogenesis and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Because MTAP is not a transcriptional factor, it is conceivable to hypothesize that MTAP deficiency indirectly transactivates an MMP-9 promoter, causing resultant aggressive phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Recently, we reported that the antiangiogenic function of ASS1, a rate-limiting enzyme converting citrulline into arginine in the urea cycle, was also attributable to the inhibition of ASS1 on MMP-9 expression in myxofibrosarcomas [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Evidently, aberrant losses of both MTAP in methionine salvage and ASS1 in arginine metabolism may upregulate ornithine decarboxylase (ODC) and subsequently induce overproduction of putrescine and other polyamines [17, 30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>This alteration is one of the first processes involved in proliferating cells preceding nucleic acid and protein syntheses and recently has been reported to promote tumor development and progression involving multiple cancer hallmarks [16, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>For instance, ODC transformants were reported to increase secreted MMP-2 in vitro to enhance matrix degradation [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Analogously, MMP-9 overexpression in the ASS1-deficient and MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcomas is likely mediated by overexpressed ODC, which converges growth-promoting signals to orchestrate transcriptional regulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The disabled methionine salvage in MTAP-inactivated myxofibrosarcomas renders this aggressive tumor subset a tumor-specific metabolic feature for use in L-alanosine therapy, which targets adenylosuccinate synthetase to abolish de novo AMP synthesis from IMP [13, 14, 30]. In vitro and in vivo, the growth inhibition of MTAP-deficient tumors by L-alanosine was partially ascribed to the induction of apoptosis, which was evidenced by increased Annexin-V and TUNEL labeling in myxofibrosarcomas and reported to be mitochondria-dependent in mantle cell lymphomas [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>In addition, we demonstrated that myxofibrosarcomas fundamentally depended on MTAP deficiency regarding their susceptibility to L-alanosine, which effectively inhibited the MTAP-deficient cell lines and derived xenografts and was well-tolerated by the mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Since several antimetabolites targeting purine synthesis are available and additional drugs are in development [32–34], the findings of this study suggest that MTAP-deficient myxofibrosarcomas may benefit from the chemoselective targeting of the defects in methionine-adenine recycling and AMP synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>In summary, MTAP deficiency in myxofibrosarcomas, and particularly that caused by homozygous deletion, negatively affects prognosis. In vitro and in vivo, MTAP may act as a tumor suppressor, serving antiangiogenic, antiproliferative, and antimigratory or antiinvasive functions, and its deficiency represents a potential therapeutic target of myxofibrosarcomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4_1"><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Analysis of aCGH </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Twelve fresh tumor specimens and 3 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines (OH931, NMFH-1, and NMFH-2) underwent oligonucleotide-based aCGH profiling (NimbleGen), as previously detailed [7, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The raw data from the aCGH profiling were log2-transformed and output into Nexus software (BioDiscovery). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>To delineate the breakpoints in the genome-wide array probes, the gains and losses in the critical regions of the CNAs were defined as log2 ratios of ≥ +0.20 and ≤ −0.20, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The amplification and homozygous deletion were defined as log2 ratios of ≥ +0.50 or ≤ −0.50, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>To unravel causal genes exhibiting copy number-driven deregulated expression, the common regions of alteration were filtered to identify consecutive makers, and their proportions were ^ 20% in the tumor and cell line samples analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Tumor materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>An institutional review board (97-2190A3) approved the retrieval of myxofibrosarcomas resected with curative intent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Those undergoing neoadjuvant radiation, chemotherapy or aCGH profiling were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Table 1 lists the 87 independent primary formalin-fixed myxofibrosarcomas successfully analyzed for MTAP gene dosage, promoter methylation, and immunoexpression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Tissue microarray sections were antigen-retrieved, incubated with antibodies targeting MTAP (1:100, Proteintech), Ki-67 (1:200, abcam), MMP-9 (1:50, Epitomics), and CD31 (1:50, BD Pharmingen), and detected using the ChemMate EnVision kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The cutoff value of &lt; 10% cytoplasmic reactivity to define aberrant MTAP loss was previously described [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The scoring criteria of determining the levels of intratumoral microvessel density [18] and MMP-9 expression by H-score method [19] were as previously reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Whole sections of xenografted specimens were stained with MTAP (1:50, Proteintech), cyclin D1 (1:100, Epitomics), cyclin E (1:20, Abcam), Ki-67 (1:200, abcam), MMP-9 (1:50, Epitomics), CD31 (1:50, BD Pharmingen), and TUNEL (Roche) for labeling apoptotic cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>MTAP dosage quantification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>As described in Supplementary Method-S1, real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed on MTAP exon 8 in duplicate for each case to detect the MTAP gene dosage. PIK3R1 (5q13.1) was the reference gene that exhibited no detectable CNAs in the aCGH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Standard curves were constructed using serial dilutions of human genomic DNA (Clontech). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>For each specimen, approximately 3000 tumor cells were microdissected using the Veritas LCM machine (Arcturus) to extract genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The MTAP/PIK3R1 ratio &lt; 0.2 was considered a homozygous deletion, assuming that the normal tissue contamination and intratumoral heterogeneity accounted for &lt; 20% of the experimental deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Regarding the 3 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines, homozygous deletion was determined when no MTAP gene copy was detected but PIK3R1 was amplifiable, i.e. the MTAP/PIK3R1 ratio approximating zero. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Methylation-specific PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted from formalin-fixed tissue, bisulfite-converted, and PCR-amplified with primers targeting methylated and unmethylated promoters of MTAP gene, as previously described [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Cell culture, transfection, and RNA interference </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The culture conditions of the OH931, NMFH-1, and NMFH-2 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines, CCD966SK dermal fibroblasts, and human umbilical venous endothelial cells (HUVECs, H-UV001) were previously described [15] and were authenticated using short tandem-repeat fingerprinting in December, 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Regarding the MTAP reexpression in MTAP-deleted OH931 and NMFH-2 cells, a full-length pMTAP-DDK-Myc expression plasmid and empty pCMV6 vector were purchased from Origene and validated using sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>In a 24-well plate, 105 cells from OH931 or NMFH-2 myxofibrosarcoma cell lines were seeded and incubated with lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogene) for 4 h at 37°C to transfect various plasmids (1.5 μg), then cultured for a further 24 h at 37°C, and lysed with Passive Lysis Buffer (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Cells stably expressing MTAP or DDK-Myc tags alone were selected using neomycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The transfected cells were analyzed for exogenous MTAP expression using western blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the MMP-9 promoter activity, an empty pGL vector and pG-MMP-9-promoter were cotransfected with a pCMV6 control or a pMTAP-DDK-Myc vector into myxofibrosarcoma cells [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>After 48 h, the cells underwent luciferase assays by using a dual luciferase assay kit (Promega) and normalized for the transfection efficiency of pRL vector. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>To silence the endogenous MTAP expression in NMFH-1 cells, lentiviral vectors were obtained from the Taiwan National RNAi Core Facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Viruses were produced by transfecting HEK293 cells with the control pLKO.1-shLacZ (TRCN0000072223: 5′-TGTTCGCATTAT CCGAACCAT-3′) and pLKO.1-shMTAP (TRCN0000005883: 5′-CCTGAATGATTTAGACAAC-3′ and TRCN0000005885: 5′-CCTTCTATGATGGAAGTCA-3′) using Lipofectamine 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>For viral infection, 3 × 106 NMFH-1 cells were incubated with 8 mL of lentivirus in the presence of polybrene, followed by puromycin selection to produce stable clones of lentivirus-transduced cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Quantification of transcripts of MTAP and angiogenesis-associated genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>As detailed in Method-S2, real-time reverse-transcription PCR (RT-PCR) was performed using the ABI StepOnePlus™ System to measure MTAP mRNA abundance in all myxofibrosarcoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>To explore antiangiogenic mediators of MTAP, an RT-PCR expression array (PAHS-024, SABioscience) was profiled for NMFH-2 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Those genes differentially expressed between MTAP-reexpressing and empty conditions were identified based on P &lt; 0.001, &gt; 5-fold changes, and Ct values % 30 for both tested and housekeeping genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>These candidates were further screened in all myxofibrosarcoma cell lines using western blots to assay molecules exhibiting corresponding protein alterations under varying MTAP reexpression or knockdown experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Western blots </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>To visualize protein expression alterations, Method-S3 details the western blots, sources of primary antibodies against MTAP, G1- and G1/S transition-associated cell cycle regulators, and RT-PCR expression array-selected angiogenesis-associated mediators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The proteins consistently downregulated or upregulated by MTAP reexpression in MTAP-deficient OH931 and NMFH-2 cells were reappraised in endogenously MTAP-expressing NMFH-1 cells transduced with shMTAP or shLacZ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>After the aforementioned cross-validations were conducted, the identified molecule(s) exhibiting the same trend in changes in protein abundance, as modulated by the MTAP expression level, underwent ELISA to quantify their concentration in corresponding conditioned media, as detailed in Method-S4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_10"><title><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Pharmacological assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Parent OH931, NMFH-2, and NMFH-1 cells, as well as the MTAP- or empty vector-transfected OH931 and NMFH-2 cells, were treated with a vehicle control using 0.9% phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) or L-alanosine (Santa Cruz Biotech) at indicated doses for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_11"><title><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Functional assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>To elucidate the functional alterations associated with MTAP reexpression, MTAP knockdown, and L-alanosine treatment, various cancer phenotypes were evaluated using cell viability, bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU), electric cell-substrate impedance sensing (ECIS), cell cycle kinetics, soft-agar, HUVEC tube formation, and wound-healing, invasion, and apoptosis assays in Methods-S5-S11. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_12"><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Animal xenografts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The animal use committee approved the protocol 103101401. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>To elucidate the in vivo function of MTAP reexpression, 4 × 106 NMFH-2 myxofibrosarcoma cells transfected with the MTAP-expressing plasmid or empty vector (n = 8 each) were inoculated into the flanks of 16 severe combined immunodeficient (SCID) mice (BioLasco) and allowed to grow until 30 d after cell implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>To analyze the in vivo therapeutic effect of L-alanosine, 4 × 106 parent NMFH-2 cells were inoculated into 24 SCID mice, which were allowed to grow until 10 d postinjection (Day 0), and then randomized into 3 groups (n = 8 each) receiving 25 μM or 50 μM of L-alanosine, or PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The treatment was continued for 6 wk and the mice were euthanized 42 d posttreatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The tumor volume was calculated using the formula: V=π/6 × length (mm) × width (mm)2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_13"><title><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The associations and comparisons among various parameters were evaluated using chi-square, Student t, or Mann-Whitney U test as appropriate to assess the MTAP gene status and MTAP immunoexpression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Follow-up data were available for 83 patients, and the median follow-up time was 30.6 mo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>The endpoints were metastasis-free survival (MFS) and disease-specific survival (DSS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Univariate survival analyses were compared using a log-rank test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>A multivariate model was performed using a Cox regression, including parameters with univariate P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>For cell line and xenograft samples, a Student's t-test was used to analyze the functional and pharmacological assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY METHODS, TABLES AND FIGURES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-05-11428-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1735" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Dr. Bridge and Dr. Ogose for providing myxofibrosarcoma cells, and the Chang Gung genomic core laboratory (CMRPG880251) and tissue bank (CLRPG8B0033) for their assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>GRANT SUPPORTS </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the National Science Council (96-2320-B-182A-008-MY3 &amp; 102-2628-B-182A-002-MY3, H-Y Huang; 99-2320-B-384-001-MY2, C-F Li; NSC 98-2314-B-182A-100-MY3, F-M Fang), Ministry of Health and Welfare (MOHW103-TD-M-111-102001 to C-F Li and H-J Kung) and Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (CMRPG8C0981, XMRPG890061, H-Y Huang) of Taiwan. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Disclosure </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>1MentzelTCalonjeEWaddenCCamplejohnRSBehamASmithMAFletcherCDMyxofibrosarcoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Clinicopathologic analysis of 75 cases with emphasis on the low-grade variantAm J Surg Pathol1996203914058604805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>2SanfilippoRMiceliRGrossoFFioreMPumaEPennacchioliEBarisellaMSangalliCMarianiLCasaliPGGronchiAMyxofibrosarcoma: prognostic factors and survival in a series of patients treated at a single institutionAnnals of surgical oncology201118720520878245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>3HuangHYLalPQinJBrennanMFAntonescuCRLow-grade myxofibrosarcoma: a clinicopathologic analysis of 49 cases treated at a single institution with simultaneous assessment of the efficacy of 3-tier and 4-tier grading systemsHum Pathol2004356122115138937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>4WillemsSMDebiec-RychterMSzuhaiKHogendoornPCSciotRLocal recurrence of myxofibrosarcoma is associated with increase in tumour grade and cytogenetic aberrations, suggesting a multistep tumour progression modelMod Pathol2006194071616415793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>5BarretinaJTaylorBSBanerjiSRamosAHLagos-QuintanaMDecarolisPLShahKSocciNDWeirBAHoAChiangDYRevaBSubtype-specific genomic alterations define new targets for soft-tissue sarcoma therapyNat Genet2010427152120601955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>6LeeJCLiCFFangFMWangJWJengYMYuSCLinYTWuJMTsaiJWLiSHHuangHYPrognostic implication of MET overexpression in myxofibrosarcomas: an integrative array comparative genomic hybridization, real-time quantitative PCR, immunoblotting, and immunohistochemical analysisMod Pathol20102313799220639860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>7LiCFWangJMKangHYHuangCKWangJWFangFMWangYHWuWRLiSHYuSCLeeJCLanJCharacterization of gene amplification-driven SKP2 overexpression in myxofibrosarcoma: potential implications in tumor progression and therapeuticsClin Cancer Res201218159861022322669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>8TsaiJWLiCFKaoYCWangJWFangFMWangYHWuWRWuLCHsingCHLiSHYuSCLanJRecurrent amplification at 7q21.2 Targets CDK6 gene in primary myxofibrosarcomas and identifies CDK6 overexpression as an independent adverse prognosticatorAnnals of surgical oncology20121927162522476749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>9ChristopherSADiegelmanPPorterCWKrugerWDMethylthioadenosine phosphorylase, a gene frequently codeleted with p16(cdkN2a/ARF), acts as a tumor suppressor in a breast cancer cell lineCancer Res20026266394412438261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>10KadariyaYTangBWangLAl-SaleemTHayakawaKSlifkerMJKrugerWDGermline Mutations in Mtap Cooperate with Myc to Accelerate Tumorigenesis in MicePLoS One20138e6763523840755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>11KadariyaYYinBTangBShintonSAQuinlivanEPHuaXKlein-SzantoAAl-SaleemTIBassingCHHardyRRKrugerWDMice heterozygous for germ-line mutations in methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) die prematurely of T-cell lymphomaCancer Res2009695961919567676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>12TangBLiYNKrugerWDDefects in methylthioadenosine phosphorylase are associated with but not responsible for methionine-dependent tumor cell growthCancer Res2000605543711034100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>13BatovaADiccianniMBNoboriTVuTYuJBridgemanLYuALFrequent deletion in the methylthioadenosine phosphorylase gene in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia: strategies for enzyme-targeted therapyBlood1996883083908874207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>14IlleiPBRuschVWZakowskiMFLadanyiMHomozygous deletion of CDKN2A and codeletion of the methylthioadenosine phosphorylase gene in the majority of pleural mesotheliomasClin Cancer Res2003921081312796375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>15HuangHYWuWRWangYHWangJWFangFMTsaiJWLiSHHungHCYuSCLanJShiueYLHsingCHASS1 as a novel tumor suppressor gene in myxofibrosarcomas: aberrant loss via epigenetic DNA methylation confers aggressive phenotypes, negative prognostic impact, and therapeutic relevanceClin Cancer Res20131928617223549872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>16CavuotoPFenechMFA review of methionine dependency and the role of methionine restriction in cancer growth control and life-span extensionCancer Treat Rev2012387263622342103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>17PeggAERegulation of ornithine decarboxylaseJ Biol Chem2006281145293216459331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>18GaspariniGWeidnerNBevilacquaPMalutaSDalla PalmaPCaffoOBarbareschiMBoracchiPMarubiniEPozzaFTumor microvessel density, p53 expression, tumor size, and peritumoral lymphatic vessel invasion are relevant prognostic markers in node-negative breast carcinomaJ Clin Oncol199412454667509851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>19Budwit-NovotnyDAMcCartyKSCoxEBSoperJTMutchDGCreasmanWTFlowersJLMcCartyKSJrImmunohistochemical analyses of estrogen receptor in endometrial adenocarcinoma using a monoclonal antibodyCancer Res1986465419253756890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>20BehrmannIWallnerSKomyodWHeinrichPCSchuiererMBuettnerRBosserhoffAKCharacterization of methylthioadenosin phosphorylase (MTAP) expression in malignant melanomaAm J Pathol20031636839012875987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>21HellerbrandCMuhlbauerMWallnerSSchuiererMBehrmannIBatailleFWeissTScholmerichJBosserhoffAKPromoter-hypermethylation is causing functional relevant downregulation of methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) expression in hepatocellular carcinomaCarcinogenesis200627647216081515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>22HuangHYLiSHYuSCChouFFTzengCCHuTHUenYHTianYFWangYHFangFMHuangWWWeiYCHomozygous deletion of MTAP gene as a poor prognosticator in gastrointestinal stromal tumorsClin Cancer Res20091569637219887491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>23CrespoITaoHNietoABRebeloODominguesPVitalALPatino MdelCBarbosaMLopesMCOliveiraCROrfaoATaberneroMDAmplified and homozygously deleted genes in glioblastoma: impact on gene expression levelsPLoS One20127e4608823029397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>24MarceSBalagueOColomoLMartinezAHollerSVillamorNBoschFOttGRosenwaldALeoniLEstellerMFragaMFLack of methylthioadenosine phosphorylase expression in mantle cell lymphoma is associated with shorter survival: implications for a potential targeted therapyClin Cancer Res20061237546116778103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>25OlopadeOIJenkinsRBRansomDTMalikKPomykalaHNoboriTCowanJMRowleyJDDiazMOMolecular analysis of deletions of the short arm of chromosome 9 in human gliomasCancer Res199252252391568221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>26SchmidMMalickiDNoboriTRosenbachMDCampbellKCarsonDACarreraCJHomozygous deletions of methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) are more frequent than p16INK4A (CDKN2) homozygous deletions in primary non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLC)Oncogene1998172669759840931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>27HuangHYLiCFFangFMTsaiJWLiSHLeeYTWeiHMPrognostic implication of ezrin overexpression in myxofibrosarcomasAnnals of surgical oncology2010173212920585869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>28OverallCMKleifeldOTumour microenvironment - opinion: validating matrix metalloproteinases as drug targets and anti-targets for cancer therapyNat Rev Cancer200662273916498445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>29KirovskiGStevensAPCzechBDettmerKWeissTSWildPHartmannABosserhoffAKOefnerPJ-HellerbrandCDown-regulation of methylthioadenosine phosphorylase (MTAP) induces progression of hepatocellular carcinoma via accumulation of 5′-deoxy-5′-methylthioadenosine (MTA)Am J Pathol201117811455221356366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>30AuvinenMCell transformation, invasion, and angiogenesis: a regulatory role for ornithine decarboxylase and polyamines?J Natl Cancer Inst19978953379106637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>31HolttaEPohjanpeltoPPolyamine dependence of Chinese hamster ovary cells in serum-free culture is due to deficient arginase activityBiochim Biophys Acta198272132177159597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>32LubinMLubinASelective killing of tumors deficient in methylthioadenosine phosphorylase: a novel strategyPLoS One20094e573519478948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>33BasuILockerJCasseraMBBelbinTJMerinoEFDongXHemeonIEvansGBGuhaCSchrammVLGrowth and metastases of human lung cancer are inhibited in mouse xenografts by a transition state analogue of 5′-methylthioadenosine phosphorylaseJ Biol Chem201128649021121135097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>34TangBTestaJRKrugerWDIncreasing the therapeutic index of 5-fluorouracil and 6-thioguanine by targeting loss of MTAP in tumor cellsCancer Biol Ther20121310829022825330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>35LinLFChuangCHLiCFLiaoCCChengCPChengTLShenMRTsengJTChangWCLeeWHWangJMZBRK1 acts as a metastatic suppressor by directly regulating MMP9 in cervical cancerCancer Res20097019220119996286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
