<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4022742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24830368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-00644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097628</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA processing</subject><subject>RNA transport</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Stem Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematopoietic Stem Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Fate Determination</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subject>Gene Function</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Thoc1 Encoded Ribonucleoprotein Is Required for Myeloid Progenitor Cell Homeostasis in the Adult Mouse </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Thoc1</italic> Is Required for Myelopoiesis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pitzonka</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ullas</surname><given-names>Sumana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chinnam</surname><given-names>Meenalakshmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Povinelli</surname><given-names>Benjamin J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Daniel T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Appenheimer</surname><given-names>Michelle M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Sharon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics, Roswell Park Cancer Institute, Buffalo, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Immunology, Roswell Park Cancer Institute, Buffalo, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Palazzo</surname><given-names>Alexander F.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Toronto, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>david.goodrich@roswellpark.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: LP SU DWG MJN SE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: LP SU MC BJP DTF MG MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: LP SU BJP DTF DWG MJN SE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MA MG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: LP SU MJN SE DWG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Current address: Department of Allergy and Immunology, Boston Children’s Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e97628</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Pitzonka et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pitzonka et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Co-transcriptionally assembled ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complexes are critical for RNA processing and nuclear export. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>RNPs have been hypothesized to contribute to the regulation of coordinated gene expression, and defects in RNP biogenesis contribute to genome instability and disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Despite the large number of RNPs and the importance of the molecular processes they mediate, the requirements for individual RNP complexes in mammalian development and tissue homeostasis are not well characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>THO is an evolutionarily conserved, nuclear RNP complex that physically links nascent transcripts with the nuclear export apparatus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>THO is essential for early mouse embryonic development, limiting characterization of the requirements for THO in adult tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>To address this shortcoming, a mouse strain has been generated allowing inducible deletion of the Thoc1 gene which encodes an essential protein subunit of THO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow reconstitution was used to generate mice in which Thoc1 deletion could be induced specifically in the hematopoietic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We find that granulocyte macrophage progenitors have a cell autonomous requirement for Thoc1 to maintain cell growth and viability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Lymphoid lineages are not detectably affected by Thoc1 loss under the homeostatic conditions tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Myeloid lineages may be more sensitive to Thoc1 loss due to their relatively high rate of proliferation and turnover. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Financial support was provided by the Roswell Park Alliance Foundation (B.J.P., M.G., M.J.N., D.W.G.), the National Blood Foundation (B.J.P., M.G., M.J.N.), University at Buffalo Mark Diamond Fund grant SU 11-14 (L.P.), and Public Health Service grants CA125665 (D.W.G.), CA79765 (S.S.E.) and AI082039 (S.S.E.) from the National Institutes of Health. Institutional core facilities utilized in this work were supported by National Cancer Institute grant P30 CA016056. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The co-transcriptional packaging of nascent RNA transcripts into RNP complexes is important for transcription, RNA processing, and RNA export from the nucleus [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>RNP complexes are composed of multiple protein and RNA subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>They are heterogeneous and dynamic, differing in composition depending on the transcript and the stage of the transcript’s life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Potential combinatorial permutations are vast enough to facilitate unique RNP processing pathways for different subsets of transcripts [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These observations have inspired the hypothesis that co- and post-transcriptional RNP mediated mechanisms support the elaboration of coordinated gene expression [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Loss of RNP function can also compromise genome integrity directly by inducing promiscuous formation of R-loops, a three-strand nucleic acid structure composed of an RNA∶DNA hybrid formed during transcription plus a displaced DNA strand [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>R-loops lead to DNA strand breaks by multiple mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>While the importance of RNP mediated mechanisms for gene expression and genome integrity is increasingly appreciated, the contribution of individual RNP complexes to normal growth and development in mammals is not well characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Identifying these contributions will further the understanding of how defects in RNP mediated processes lead to disease [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>THO is an RNP complex that assembles on nascent RNA in a RNA cap, splicing, and ATP-dependent manner [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>It recruits RNA export factors to form larger complexes like TREX that facilitate interaction with and activation of the nuclear export apparatus [9]–[11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>THO, therefore, physically links transcription with nuclear export [12]–[16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition to defects in nuclear export, THO deficiency affects other steps in transcription that depend on proper RNP biogenesis including transcriptional elongation [17]–[19], transcription-associated recombination [20]–[22], and transcript 3′ end formation [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>THO is conserved from yeast to man. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In metazoa, THO is composed of six proteins in equal stoichiometry encoded by the THOC1, THOC2, THOC5, THOC6, THOC7, and Tex1 genes [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The yeast THO orthologue contains four proteins encoded by the THO2, HPR1, MFT1, and THP2 genes [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Loss of any one of these yeast proteins causes disassembly of the complex, loss of function, and the same set of deficiency phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, given its widespread role in RNA processing and transport [20], THO is not essential for yeast viability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Deletion of Thoc1 or Thoc5 in mice yields an embryonic lethal phenotype [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Since THO is required for early embryonic development, testing the requirements for THO in maintaining homeostasis in adult tissues has been limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To overcome this limitation, a floxed mouse allele has been generated allowing inducible deletion of the Thoc1 [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Using this allele, widespread Thoc1 deletion has been observed to cause cell type specific effects such as disruption of stem cell homeostasis in small intestine but not the related mucosa of the large intestine [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This suggests Thoc1 deficiency has context dependent effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Here the effects of Thoc1 deletion on hematopoiesis are examined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Mice, Tamoxifen Treatment, and Tissue Harvest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>All animal work was approved by the Roswell Park Cancer Institute Animal Care and Use Committee according to AAALAC standards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The generation and genotyping of the Rosa26CreERT2 and floxed Thoc1 alleles were described previously [26], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Widespread Thoc1 deletion was performed as previously described [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Mice successfully reconstituted with Thoc1f/fRosa26CreERT2/+ test or Rosa26CreERT2/+ control bone marrow were treated with five daily injections of 2 mg tamoxifen in corn oil at 9 to 10 weeks post transplantation via intraperitoneal injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Following tamoxifen administration, mice were euthanized by CO2 inhalation and tissues collected as previously described [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Tissue was either snap frozen for later extraction of RNA and protein or fixed and embedded to generate tissue sections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Blood Cell Counts, Blood Smears, and Bone Marrow Smears </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>20–50 µl of peripheral blood was collected retro-orbitally into EDTA containing tubes and complete blood counts performed using an MS4-5 Automated Hematology Cell Counter (Melet Schloesing Labratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The total numbers of white blood cells, red blood cells, and platelets, as well as the percent of lymphocytes, neutrophils, monocytes, eosinophils, and basophils within the white blood cell population were counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood smears were prepared from retro-orbital bleeds, fixed in methanol, and stained with Wright-Giemsa stain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow was extracted from the right femur, cleaned of muscle and fat tissue, and was halved length wise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Sable hair (3/O) brush and 5% BSA in 1X PBS was used to brush bone marrow cells on to microscope slides and the slides were then fixed in methanol and stained with Wright-Giemsa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For each time point, individual mice were used so that blood was not collected from the same mouse more than once. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Bone Marrow Reconstitution and Flow Cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow chimeric mice were generated as described [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Briefly, Rosa26CreERT2/+ and Thoc1f/fRosa26CreERT2/+ 8-week old mice on the C57BL/6 background (expressing CD45.2) were sacrificed and their bone marrow transplanted into sub-lethally irradiated, age and sex-matched B6.SJL-Ptprc a/BoyAiTac mice that express CD45.1 (Taconic laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow was extracted from both femurs and tibias by flushing with sterile PBS using a 27 gauge needle and stored on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>1×106 bone marrow cells in 200 µl PBS were transplanted into recipient mice via tail vein injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Prior to transplantation, recipient mice were irradiated twice at a 3 hour interval with 5 Gy over the course of 2.4 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All irradiated recipient mice were maintained on the antibiotics sulfamethoxaole and trimethoprim (Bactrim(R), Hi-Tech Pharmacal, Amityville, NY) administered orally via in the drinking water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow reconstitution in recipient mice was monitored by immunophenotyping of peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Retro-orbital blood was collected in EDTA tubes at 4 and 9 weeks post transplantation, red blood cells lysed with ACK lysis buffer (150 µM NH4Cl, 9.9 mM KHCO3, 120 µM EDTA), and the CD45.1 and CD45.2 markers immunostained with 0.5 mg/ml PE conjugated antibody (BD Pharmingen, #550802) and 0.2 mg/ml FITC-conjugated antibody (BD Pharmingen #560695). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Samples were analyzed on an LSR II Flow Cytometer (BD Life Sciences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The ratio of CD45.2 to CD45.1 positive cells from at least 50,000 events estimates the extent of bone marrow reconstitution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Immunophenotyping of different cell lineages in the bone marrow, peripheral blood, lymph node, and spleen was performed similarly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow samples were treated with ACK lysis buffer as above and 5×106 remaining bone marrow cells re-suspended in 100 µl staining buffer (.5% FBS in PBS) with 1 µl of the appropriate antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For analysis of peripheral blood, serum was collected and double lysed in ACK lysis buffer before staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Spleen cells were obtained by physical dissociation, filtering, and ACK lysis before staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Lymph node cells were obtained similarly without ACK lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After incubation on ice, cells were washed with staining buffer and resuspended in staining buffer plus DAPI prior to flow cytometry analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Samples, along with unstained or DAPI only stained cells were analyzed on a LSRII flow cytometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Data was analyzed with Flowjo v9.5 software (TreeStar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Live singlets were gated on DAPI- as well as side scatter and forward scatter singlets in order to eliminate false positive events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Cells were analyzed for markers that can be used to identify distinct hematopoietic stem/progenitor cell populations including Lin (CD4, CD8, B220, Ter-119, Gr-1, CD11b), Sca-1 (D7), C-kit (C2B8), CD150 (mshad), CD105 (Mu7/18), and CD16/32 (93). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>All antibodies were obtained from eBioscience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The antigens and the corresponding progenitor populations they define are listed in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>For analysis of the cell cycle, cells were stained with the cell surface markers above and then fixed 10 minutes at room temperature with 2% paraformaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed with 0.5% saponin, 3.0% FBS in PBS and resuspended with 20 µg/ml Hoescht 33343 (Sigma Aldrich) for 30 minutes at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>After washing and resuspension in PBS, cells were analyzed by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Cell cycle phases were determined by DNA content as measured by Hoechst 33343 staining intensity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Flowjo software v10.0 (TreeStar) was used for cell cycle analysis of flow data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Colony Formation Assays and In vitro Assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>40,000 viable bone marrow cells per recipient mouse were washed with 1x PBS and re-suspended in 200 µL sterile 1X PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The cells were added to 4 mL of methylcellulose-based medium with recombinant cytokines and EPO for mouse cells (Methocult GF #M3434, StemCell Technologies, Vancouver, BC) containing Pen/Strep (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The bone marrow methylcellulose media mixture was plated and incubated at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Total numbers of colonies were counted on day 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For isolation of pre-granulocyte-macrophage progenitor (pre-GMP) and granulocyte-macrophage progenitor (GMP) populations, bone marrow was harvested and pooled from a total of seven mice each with the Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 genotype in two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow cells were lineage depleted by incubating with the following rat anti mouse lineage antibodies: CD4 (clone GK1.5), CD8a (53-6.7), B220 (RA3-6B2), Gr-1 (RB6-8C5), Mac-1 (M1/70), Ter119 (Ter-119). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>After 15 minutes of incubation on ice, cells were washed and incubated for an additional 15 minutes on ice with anti-rat antibody magnetic beads (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Unbound lineage-negative cells were harvested and stained for the aforementioned GMP markers using rat anti-mouse Sca-1 (D7), c-kit (2B8), CD150 (mShad), CD105 (MJ7/18), and CD16/32 (93) (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic definitions of pre-GMP and GMP populations were based on those described in Pronk, et al. [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Sorted GMPs were cultured in serum-free StemSpan medium (Stem Cell Technologies) with 25 ng/ml recombinant mouse SCF, FLT-3 and GM-CSF (Peprotech). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Tamoxifen (2 µM) or ethanol vehicle was added to the cultures on day 0 and day 1, and then washed out on day 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>On day 4, cells where harvested and stained with antibodies directed against the mature granulocyte/macrophage markers Gr-1 and Mac-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Cells were then washed and resuspended in binding buffer with Annexin V according to manufacturer’s recommendations (eBioscience). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>After washing, cells were resuspended with DAPI to discriminate between live and dead cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>GMPs were defined as cells negative for Gr-1 and Mac-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Widespread Thoc1 Deletion in Adult Mice Affects Hematopoiesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>A floxed allele of Thoc1 in which loxP sites flank exons 6–7 was previously created (Thoc1F), and Cre mediated deletion creates the equivalent of a null allele [26]. Thoc1F alleles were bred into mice containing a transgene expressing the Cre recombinase-estrogen receptor fusion protein (Rosa26CreERT2) to allow widespread, tamoxifen inducible Thoc1 gene deletion in adult mice [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Untreated and thus undeleted Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 mice were viable and did not exhibit phenotypes distinguishable from wild type mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Nine to twelve week old Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 test mice or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 control mice were administered tamoxifen daily for 5 days to drive widespread Cre mediated Thoc1 gene deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>As previously described, tamoxifen treatment caused decreased stem/progenitor cell proliferation and viability in the small intestinal crypt [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This defect compromised the structural integrity of the small intestine (Fig. 1A) causing death beginning at 11 days from the start of tamoxifen treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The small intestine has one of the highest rates of cell turnover during homeostasis, suggesting rapidly proliferating cell types are particularly susceptible to Thoc1 deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This prompted us to explore whether Thoc1 loss had effects on the hematopoietic system, another tissue characterized by rapid cell turnover. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0097628-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097628.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Widespread Thoc1 deletion affects hematopoiesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A) The small intestine from Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1+/+) mice was dissected six days from to the start of tamoxifen treatment, tissue sections were stained with H&amp;E, and representative images are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The asterisk identifies a typical normal small intestinal crypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The plus sign identifies a degenerating, hypocellular crypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Scale bars represent 200 microns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>B) Bone marrow (BM), spleen, and thymus tissue was isolated from Thoc1F/F (red) or Thoc1+/+ (blue) mice 5 days after the start of tamoxifen treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>RNA was extracted, and the fraction of remaining wild type Thoc1 RNA quantitated by real time RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse, and the data are normalized to one of the control mice for each tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.05) are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>C) Protein extracted from thymus (1–4) or spleen (5–8) of Thoc1F/F (red) or Thoc1+/+ (blue) mice 6 days from the start of tamoxifen treatment was analyzed for Thoc1 protein by western blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Each lane represents an individual mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Actin serves as the loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>D) Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (red) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (blue) mice were treated with tamoxifen, peripheral blood was isolated, and white blood cells (WBC) were counted at the indicated times from the start of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse of the indicated genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>E) Peripheral red blood cells (RBC) from mice in D) were counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>F) Peripheral blood platelets from mice in D) were counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>G) The percentage of neutrophils among total peripheral white blood cells from mice in D) was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.01) are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>H) The percentage of lymphocytes among total peripheral white blood cells was counted as in G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>I) Peripheral blood was collected from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1+/+) mice, and Giemsa stained blood smears were examined under light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Representative images are shown with neutrophils highlighted by arrows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>J) Bone marrow brush smears from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1+/+) mice were stained with Wright Giemsa and imaged under light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Representative images are shown with neutrophils typical of each sample highlighted by arrows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The scale bar represents 50 microns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0097628.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Wild-type Thoc1 RNA levels were significantly reduced in the bone marrow, spleen, and thymus of tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 test mice (Fig. 1B) indicating induced deletion of floxed Thoc1 alleles was efficient in these tissues. Thoc1 protein levels were also generally reduced (Fig. 1C), but the effects in individual mice were variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Despite Thoc1 deficiency in these hematopoietic tissues, the number of white blood cells, red blood cells and platelets in peripheral blood was not significantly different from control mice for the time points measured (Fig. 1D–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The relative proportion of neutrophils was significantly increased whereas the fraction of lymphocytes declined in tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 test mice compared to tamoxifen treated Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 control mice (Fig. 1G,H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The relative increase in neutrophils was confirmed by examination of peripheral blood smears (Fig. 1I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Brush smears suggested that the bone marrow from Thoc1 deficient test mice was abnormal (Fig. 1J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>For example, bone marrow neutrophils from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 mice appeared smaller with more condensed nuclei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These observations suggested that Thoc1 deficiency affects hematopoiesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Because widespread Thoc1 deficiency affected the small intestine, however, non-cell autonomous effects might influence the hematopoietic phenotype observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In particular, loss of small intestine structural integrity would be expected to cause inflammatory and immune responses that may influence mobilization of neutrophils from the bone marrow into the peripheral blood [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Effects of Thoc1 Deletion in Bone Marrow Reconstituted Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>To overcome the potential bias of non-cell autonomous effects, we reconstituted irradiated wild type mice with bone marrow from untreated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Since untreated mice retain Thoc1, bone marrow from both genotypes was expected to successfully reconstitute irradiated host mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Indeed, nine weeks after irradiation and reconstitution more than 85% of white blood cells in the peripheral blood of host CD45.1 expressing mice were derived from the CD45.2 expressing donor bone marrow, on average (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Reconstituted mice were treated with tamoxifen and RNA or protein extracts prepared 10 days after the start of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>As expected, tamoxifen treatment significantly reduced Thoc1 RNA levels in the bone marrow of Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 reconstituted mice relative to Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 control mice (Fig. 2B, t-test P = 0.003). Thoc1 protein levels were reduced in secondary hematopoietic organs like the thymus and spleen (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Consistent with prior studies [25], Thoc5 protein levels also declined in Thoc1 deficient tissues (Fig. 2C), suggesting the entire THO complex becomes unstable when one subunit is missing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The small intestine of reconstituted mice was not detectably affected by tamoxifen treatment (Fig. 2D), as expected, since floxed Thoc1 alleles are now present only in the hematopoietic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Thus tamoxifen treatment of mice reconstituted with Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 bone marrow caused Thoc1 deletion specifically in the hematopoietic system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0097628-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097628.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Thoc1 deficiency in the bone marrow causes a decline in myeloid cells, but not lymphocytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A) CD45.1 wild type mice were irradiated and transplanted with bone marrow from Cd45.2 Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (Thoc1+/+) mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>9 weeks later, CD45.1 and CD45.2 positive peripheral white blood cells were counted by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The percentage of CD45.1 (host, blue) and CD45.2 (donor, red) cells is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse with bars representing the mean and standard error. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>B) Mice in A) were treated with tamoxifen and bone marrow isolated 10 days later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>RNA was extracted and Thoc1 RNA levels measured by real time RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (+/+) mouse, and the data are normalized to one of the control mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The difference in Thoc1 RNA levels between genotypes is significant (t-test P = 0.003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>C) Protein was extracted from the thymus (1–6) and spleen (7–9) of tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (red) and Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (blue) mice in B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Extracts were analyzed for the indicated proteins with actin serving as a loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>D) The small intestine was harvested from mice in B) and tissue sections stained with H&amp;E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Representative images from mice of the indicated genotype are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Scale bars represent 200 microns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>E) Peripheral blood was isolated from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (+/+) mice in B) and the percentage of the indicated cell types counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse with bars representing the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (t-test P&lt;0.02) are noted by *. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>F) Spleen cells were isolated from the tamoxifen treated mice in B) and the percentage of the indicated cell types counted as in E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (t-test P&lt;0.01) are noted by ∧. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>F) Lymph node cells were isolated from the tamoxifen treated mice in B) and the percentage of the indicated cell types counted as in E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0097628.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood, spleen, and lymph node tissues isolated from tamoxifen treated, reconstituted mice were analyzed for various hematopoietic cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The relative proportion of CD11b+Gr−1+ neutrophils was significantly decreased in each of these tissues (Fig. 2E–G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The decrease in peripheral blood neutrophils was in contrast to the increase observed upon global Thoc1 deletion, confirming the influence of non-cell autonomous effects on hematopoiesis under inflammatory conditions associated with small intestinal damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant decrease in CD11b+GR−1negative monocytes was also observed in the spleen (Fig. 2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Significant changes in the proportion of CD4+ cells, CD8+ cells, or B220+ B cells were not observed within the tissues examined, other than a modest increase in peripheral blood B cells (Fig. 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The consistent decrease in neutrophils in tamoxifen treated mice reconstituted with Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 bone marrow suggests that the myeloid lineage is sensitive to Thoc1 deficiency under the conditions tested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Myelopoiesis was assessed in tamoxifen treated reconstituted mice by examining the bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The number of viable bone marrow cells recovered from treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 mice was significantly lower than the number recovered from treated Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 control mice (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Further, viable bone marrow cells recovered from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 mice were less able to form colonies upon in vitro culture in methylcellulose (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Thus, the number and proliferative potential of bone marrow progenitors is reduced upon Thoc1 loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Since cells of the granulocyte and macrophage lineages normally make up the majority of bone marrow cells, this data was an initial indicator that granulocyte-macrophage progenitors (GMPs) may be affected by Thoc1 deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Lineage specific markers were used to quantitate the number of myeloid progenitor cells in the bone marrow to test this possibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The number and proportion of Pre-GMP and GMP cells was significantly reduced in Thoc1 deficient bone marrow (Fig. 3C,D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Pre-megakaryocyte erythroid progenitor (Pre-MegE) cells were also reduced in Thoc1 deficient bone marrow, but this did not significantly affect the number of erythroid-committed-progenitor cells (Pre-CFU-E) at the time points examined (Fig. 3C,D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0097628-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097628.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Myeloid progenitor cells are affected by Thoc1 deficiency. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>A) Bone marrow was recovered from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 (F/F) or Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 (+/+) mice and the number of viable cells counted by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse with bars representing the genotype mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Differences between genotypes are significant (t-test P = 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>B) An equal number of viable bone marrow cells isolated in A) were cultured in methylcellulose to assess colony forming potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Each data point shows the number of colonies generated with samples from a different mouse with bars representing the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Differences between genotypes are significant (t-test P = 0.0006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>C) Pre-granulocyte macrophage progenitors (Pre-GMP), granulocyte macrophage progenitors (GMP), pre-megakaryocyte erythroid progenitors (Pre-MegE), and erythroid progenitors (Pre-CFU-E) were counted in the bone marrow from A) using immunophenotyping and flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Each data point is from a different mouse with bars representing the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (t-test P&lt;0.01) between genotypes are noted by *. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>D) Data from C) is plotted as a percentage of total viable bone marrow cells analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (t-test P&lt;0.02) between genotypes are noted by *. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>E) A schematic outlining a simplified view of hematopoiesis highlighting the bifurcation of multi-potent progenitor cells (MPP) cells into common lymphoid progenitor cells (CLP) or common myeloid progenitor cells (CMP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>HSC indicates hematopoietic stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>F) HSC and MPP cells from bone marrow in A) were counted as in C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Results from the different genotypes are not significantly different (t-test P&gt;0.18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>G) Data from E) is plotted as a percentage of total viable bone marrow cells analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (t-test P&lt;0.05) between genotypes are marked by *. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0097628.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The myeloid and lymphocyte lineages bifurcate when multi-potent progenitor cells (MPP) differentiate into a common myeloid or a common lymphoid progenitor cell (Fig. 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We have examined whether CD150+ hematopoietic stem cells (HSC) and CD150− MPP cells that precede the myeloid/lymphoid bifurcation are affected by Thoc1 loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The number of HSC or MPP cells was similar in tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 and Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 mice (Fig. 3F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The relative proportion of hematopoietic stem cells increased significantly (Fig. 3G), presumably due to the significant loss of myeloid progenitors noted above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Loss of myeloid progenitors likely explains the reduced number of neutrophils and monocytes observed in secondary hematopoietic tissues like the spleen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>These observations confirm that the myeloid lineage is preferentially and adversely affected by Thoc1 deficiency under the conditions tested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The decrease in myeloid progenitor cells could be due to an inability to proliferate, a loss in viability, or a change in the kinetics of myeloid differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The cell cycle phase distribution of pre-GMP/GMP cells from tamoxifen treated Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 mice showed a significant increase in G0/G1 cells and a concomitant decrease in the proportion of cells in S or G2/M compared to similarly treated Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 mice (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>However, similar changes were also observed in the cell cycle distribution of HSCs and MPPs (Fig. 4B,C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>While these changes are consistent with results from the colony formation assay and suggest Thoc1 deficiency causes decreased cell proliferation, they do not account for the preferential loss of pre-GMP/GMP cells observed upon Thoc1 loss in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Further, since all bone marrow cells lose Thoc1 subsequent to tamoxifen treatment, we cannot exclude the possibility that non-cell autonomous effects contribute to the loss of pre-GMP/GMP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>To address these issues, we isolated pre-GMP/GMPs from the bone marrow of Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 and Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 mice and treated them with tamoxifen ex vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Tamoxifen treatment caused an increase in the percentage of apoptotic Thoc1F/F:Rosa26CreERT2 pre-GMP/GMPs, as indicated by annexin V staining, compared to similarly treated Thoc1+/+:Rosa26CreERT2 cells (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Increased annexin V staining was accompanied by efficient deletion of the floxed Thoc1 alleles (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Hence pre-GMP/GMPs have a cell autonomous requirement for Thoc1 to maintain cell viability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0097628-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097628.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Effects of Thoc1 deficiency on myeloid progenitor cell cycle and apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>A) The cell cycle phase distribution of bone marrow GMPs from tamoxifen treated mice of the indicated genotype was measured by Hoechst 33343 staining and flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The graph shows the mean and standard error for 7 different mice of each genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark statistically significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>B) The cell cycle distribution of HSC cells from tamoxifen treated mice was determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark statistically significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>C) The cell cycle distribution of MPP cells from tamoxifen treated mice was determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark statistically significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>D) The graph shows the percentage of in vitro cultured GMPs of the indicated genotype that stain positive for the apoptotic marker Annexin V and negative for DAPI subsequent to tamoxifen treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The data show the mean and standard error for a total of 7 different mice for each genotype analyzed in 2 independent pools of samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark statistically significant differences between genotypes (t-test P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>E) GMPs in D) were monitored for Cre mediated deletion of the floxed Thoc1 allele by PCR and agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>GMPs of the indicated genotype were treated with increasing doses of tamoxifen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The upper panel shows results from PCR using primers specific for the wild type or unrecombined floxed Thoc1 alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The lower panel shows results using primers specific for the Cre deleted floxed Thoc1 allele. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0097628.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The data presented indicate that Thoc1 deficiency can have both cell autonomous and non-cell autonomous effects on hematopoiesis in the adult mouse, and the effects observed are dependent on cell lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The myeloid lineage clearly has a cell autonomous requirement for Thoc1 as demonstrated by reduced neutrophil numbers in the peripheral blood, spleen, and lymph nodes following hematopoietic-specific Thoc1 deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Both granulocyte-macrophage progenitors and megakaryocyte-erythroid progenitors are reduced in the bone marrow, and granulocyte-macrophage progenitors require Thoc1 to maintain cell viability when cultured in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Whole body Thoc1 deficiency, however, increases neutrophils numbers in the peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This is likely a non-cell autonomous consequence of increased neutrophil mobilization that is triggered by bacterial infections resulting from loss of epithelial integrity in the gut. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the myeloid lineage, lymphocytes are not significantly affected by Thoc1 loss under the conditions tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Lymphocyte numbers in the peripheral blood, spleen, and lymph nodes remain similar to wild type control mice retaining Thoc1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The only significant difference noted is an increase in the relative percentage of B cells in peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>While this increase in B cells highlights the different effects of Thoc1 deficiency on myeloid and lymphoid lineages, the cause is unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that Thoc1 deficiency alters the rate of class switch recombination. Thoc1 deficiency can cause increased accumulation of R-loops, and R-loops are an intermediate in class switch recombination [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Increased R-loop formation in Thoc1 deficient B-cells may increase class-switch recombination and the generation of plasma cells migrating to the peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>As expected based on the differential effects on the myeloid and lymphoid lineages, the number of HSC and MPP cells which precede myeloid/lymphoid commitment are also largely unaffected by Thoc1 loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>While lymphocytes are minimally affected, it is tempting to speculate that Thoc1 loss may have non-cell autonomous effects on adaptive immunity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Adaptive immunity during an antigenic challenge may be compromised indirectly by adverse effects of Thoc1 deficiency on myeloid-derived dendritic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that Thoc1 loss would affect lymphocytes if examined over longer periods of time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Our results are generally consistent with those observed after inducible deletion of Thoc5, another component of the THO complex [25], [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Deleting Thoc5 has deleterious effects on the gut and myeloid lineages of the hematopoietic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In contrast to our observations, deleting Thoc5 reduces red blood cell and platelet counts in the peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This difference may be explained by the distinct expression pattern of Cre transgenes used in the studies, the known side-effects of interferon treatment on hematopoiesis, the time course of the experiments, or distinct functions for the Thoc1 and Thoc5 encoded proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>This latter possibility seems unlikely in light of the observation that Thoc5 protein levels decline in Thoc1 knockout tissue and vice versa [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>This suggests that THO complex subunits become unstable when the complex does not assemble normally [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Lineage dependent effects of THO complex deficiency have now been observed in multiple biological contexts [25], [27], [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The biological basis for the specificity of these effects is not currently understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation is that the THO complex regulates a subset of transcripts important for the cell types affected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>For example, the THO complex may regulate a subset of transcripts uniquely important for the differentiation, proliferation or viability of myeloid cells thus rendering myeloid cells uniquely sensitive to Thoc1 loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this hypothesis, Thoc5 deficient myeloid cells show defects in the expression of some genes that potentially influence myeloid differentiation [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Gene expression profiling of other THO deficient cell types has detected changes in different subsets of transcripts [21], [35], [37], [38], suggesting the transcripts regulated by THO vary by cell type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>How THO selects transcripts for regulation is unknown, but elucidation of these mechanisms will be required to validate this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, THO may regulate a large number of gene transcripts in most cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation data from yeast indicates that the THO complex regulates the transcripts for most actively transcribed genes [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>If this extends to mammalian cells, Thoc1 deficiency would be expected to cause a general decline in the efficiency of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>In this case, differential effects of THO deficiency on individual transcripts is expected to be modest, as is typically observed [21], [32], [35], [37], [38], and highly expressed genes would likely show the greatest defects [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Widespread defects in gene transcription may also account for the accumulation of R-loops and DNA damage that is observed in THO deficient cells [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In this scenario, cell types that turn over rapidly would be expected to suffer the most from Thoc1 loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Rapid cell turnover requires high levels of gene expression to meet the demands of cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Further, rapidly proliferating cells replicate their DNA frequently, making them particularly susceptible to DNA damage that is generated when replication forks collide with R-loops [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Indeed one characteristic shared by the cell types acutely sensitive to Thoc1 loss is their relatively rapid turnover. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The epithelium of the small intestine completely turns over every 3–5 days in the mouse [39], while 1×109 neutrophils are produced per kilogram per day in humans [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>This alternative hypothesis predicts that Thoc1 loss would also affect lymphocytes if examined under conditions like adaptive immunity where transcriptional programs drive robust lymphocyte proliferation and production of effector molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>More study is required to test these different and mutually exclusive hypotheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The role that RNP complexes play in supporting coordinated gene expression programs is increasingly appreciated [3], [4], but the requirements for individual complexes in normal development and homeostasis have not been explored extensively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The results described here demonstrate that myeloid progenitor cells have a cell intrinsic requirement for the Thoc1 encoded protein, an essential component of the THO RNP complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The effects of Thoc1 deficiency in the hematopoietic system are lineage dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>While we cannot exclude the possibility that resistant lineages like lymphocytes would be affected by Thoc1 loss under different conditions, these observations indicate Thoc1 and THO complex deficiency have context dependent effects on hematopoiesis in the adult mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Context dependent effects have also been observed in other tissues like the intestine [27], [33], suggesting this may be a general theme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Elucidation of the mechanisms underlying these context dependent effects will inform our understanding of how RNP complexes contribute to normal development, tissue homeostasis, and disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0097628.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0097628.s001.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0097628-Luna1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>1 LunaR, GaillardH, Gonzalez-AguileraC, AguileraA (2008) Biogenesis of mRNPs: integrating different processes in the eukaryotic nucleus. Chromosoma 117: 319–331.18427828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Glisovic1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>2 GlisovicT, BachorikJL, YongJ, DreyfussG (2008) RNA-binding proteins and post-transcriptional gene regulation. FEBS Lett 582: 1977–1986.18342629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Moore1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>3 MooreMJ (2005) From Birth to Death: The Complex Lives of Eukaryotic mRNAs. Science 309: 1514–1518.16141059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Keene1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>4 KeeneJD (2007) RNA regulons: coordination of post-transcriptional events. Nature Reviews Genetics 8: 533–543. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Aguilera1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>5 AguileraA, Gomez-GonzalezB (2008) Genome instability: a mechanistic view of its causes and consequences. Nat Rev Genet 9: 204–217.18227811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Cooper1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>6 CooperTA, WanL, DreyfussG (2009) RNA and disease. Cell 136: 777–793.19239895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Cheng1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>7 ChengH, DufuK, LeeC-S, HsuJL, DiasA, et al (2006) Human mRNA Export Machinery Recruited to the 5′ End of mRNA. Cell 127: 1389–1400.17190602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Dufu1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>8 DufuK, LivingstoneMJ, SeebacherJ, GygiSP, WilsonSA, et al (2010) ATP is required for interactions between UAP56 and two conserved mRNA export proteins, Aly and CIP29, to assemble the TREX complex. Genes &amp; Development 24: 2043–2053.20844015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Viphakone1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>9 ViphakoneN, HautbergueGM, WalshM, ChangCT, HollandA, et al (2012) TREX exposes the RNA-binding domain of Nxf1 to enable mRNA export. Nat Commun 3: 1006.22893130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Gwizdek1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>10 GwizdekC, IglesiasN, RodriguezMS, Ossareh-NazariB, HobeikaM, et al (2006) Ubiquitin-associated domain of Mex67 synchronizes recruitment of the mRNA export machinery with transcription. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 103: 16376–16381.17056718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Schneiter1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>11 SchneiterR, GuerraCE, LamplM, GoggG, KohlweinSD, et al (1999) The Saccharomyces cerevisiae hyperrecombination mutant hpr1Delta is synthetically lethal with two conditional alleles of the acetyl coenzyme A carboxylase gene and causes a defect in nuclear export of polyadenylated RNA. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 19: 3415–3422.10207065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Luna2"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>12 LunaR, RondonAG, AguileraA (2012) New clues to understand the role of THO and other functionally related factors in mRNP biogenesis. Biochim Biophys Acta 1819: 514–520.22207203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Chavez1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>13 ChavezS, BeilharzT, RondonAG, Erdjument-BromageH, TempstP, et al (2000) A protein complex containing Tho2, Hpr1, Mft1 and a novel protein, Thp2, connects transcription elongation with mitotic recombination in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. EMBO Journal 19: 5824–5834.11060033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Rehwinkel1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>14 RehwinkelJ, HeroldA, GariK, KocherT, RodeM, et al (2004) Genome-wide analysis of mRNAs regulated by the THO complex in Drosophila melanogaster. Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology 11: 558–566. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Strasser1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>15 StrasserK, MasudaS, MasonP, PfannstielJ, OppizziM, et al (2002) TREX is a conserved complex coupling transcription with messenger RNA export. Nature 417: 304–308.11979277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Furumizu1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>16 FurumizuC, TsukayaH, KomedaY (2011) Characterization of EMU, the Arabidopsis homolog of the yeast THO complex member HPR1. Rna 16: 1809–1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Huertas1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>17 HuertasP, AguileraA (2003) Cotranscriptionally formed DNA: RNA hybrids mediate transcription elongation impairment and transcription-associated recombination. Molecular Cell 12: 711–721.14527416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Voynov1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>18 VoynovV, VerstrepenKJ, JansenA, RunnerVM, BuratowskiS, et al (2006) Genes with internal repeats require the THO complex for transcription. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 103: 14423–14428.16983072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Li1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>19 LiY, WangX, ZhangX, GoodrichDW (2005) Human hHpr1/p84/Thoc1 Regulates Transcriptional Elongation and Physically Links RNA Polymerase II and RNA Processing Factors. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 25: 4023–4033.15870275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-GomezGonzalez1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>20 Gomez-GonzalezB, Garcia-RubioM, BermejoR, GaillardH, ShirahigeK, et al (2011) Genome-wide function of THO/TREX in active genes prevents R-loop-dependent replication obstacles. Embo J 30: 3106–3119.21701562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-DominguezSanchez1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>21 Dominguez-SanchezMS, BarrosoS, Gomez-GonzalezB, LunaR, AguileraA (2011) Genome instability and transcription elongation impairment in human cells depleted of THO/TREX. PLoS Genet 7: e1002386.22144908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Wellinger1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>22 WellingerRE, PradoF, AguileraA (2006) Replication fork progression is impaired by transcription in hyperrecombinant yeast cells lacking a functional THO complex. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 26: 3327–3334.16581804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Saguez1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>23 SaguezC, SchmidM, OlesenJR, GhazyMA, QuX, et al (2008) Nuclear mRNA surveillance in THO/sub2 mutants is triggered by inefficient polyadenylation. Mol Cell 31: 91–103.18614048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>24 WangX, ChangY, LiY, ZhangX, GoodrichDW (2006) Thoc1/Hpr1/p84 is essential for early embryonic development in the mouse. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 26: 4362–4367.16705185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Mancini1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>25 ManciniA, Niemann-SeydeSC, PankowR, El BounkariO, Klebba-FarberS, et al (2010) THOC5/FMIP, an mRNA export TREX complex protein, is essential for hematopoietic primitive cell survival in vivo. BMC Biol 8: 1.20051105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>26 WangX, LiY, ZhangX, GoodrichDW (2007) An allelic series for studying the mouse Thoc1 gene. Genesis 45: 32–37.17211872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Pitzonka1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>27 PitzonkaL, WangX, UllasS, WolffDW, WangY, et al (2013) The THO Ribonucleoprotein Complex Is Required for Stem Cell Homeostasis in the Adult Mouse Small Intestine. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 33: 3505–3514.23816884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Ventura1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>28 VenturaA, KirschDG, McLaughlinME, TuvesonDA, GrimmJ, et al (2007) Restoration of p53 function leads to tumour regression in vivo. Nature 445: 661–665.17251932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Fisher1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>29 FisherDT, ChenQ, SkitzkiJJ, MuhitchJB, ZhouL, et al (2011) IL-6 trans-signaling licenses mouse and human tumor microvascular gateways for trafficking of cytotoxic T cells. Journal of Clinical Investigation 121: 3846–3859.21926464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Pronk1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>30 PronkCJ, RossiDJ, ManssonR, AttemaJL, NorddahlGL, et al (2007) Elucidation of the phenotypic, functional, and molecular topography of a myeloerythroid progenitor cell hierarchy. Cell Stem Cell 1: 428–442.18371379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Aguilera2"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>31 AguileraA, Garcia-MuseT (2012) R loops: from transcription byproducts to threats to genome stability. Molecular Cell 46: 115–124.22541554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Tran1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>32 TranDD, SaranS, Dittrich-BreiholzO, WilliamsonAJ, Klebba-FarberS, et al (2013) Transcriptional regulation of immediate-early gene response by THOC5, a member of mRNA export complex, contributes to the M-CSF-induced macrophage differentiation. Cell Death Dis 4: e879.24157873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Saran1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>33 SaranS, TranDD, Klebba-FarberS, Moran-LosadaP, WiehlmannL, et al (2013) THOC5, a member of the mRNA export complex, contributes to processing of a subset of wingless/integrated (Wnt) target mRNAs and integrity of the gut epithelial barrier. BMC Cell Biol 14: 51.24267292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Song1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>34 SongF, FanC, WangX, GoodrichDW (2013) The Thoc1 Encoded Ribonucleoprotein Is a Substrate for the NEDD4-1 E3 Ubiquitin Protein Ligase. PLoS ONE 8: e57995.23460917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Wang3"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>35 WangX, ChinnamM, WangJ, WangY, ZhangX, et al (2009) Thoc1 Deficiency Compromises Gene Expression Necessary for Normal Testis Development in the Mouse. Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology 29: 2794–2803.19307311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Li2"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>36 LiY, LinAW, ZhangX, WangY, WangX, et al (2007) Cancer cells and normal cells differ in their requirements for Thoc1. Cancer Research 67: 6657–6664.17638875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Guria1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>37 GuriaA, TranDD, RamachandranS, KochA, El BounkariO, et al (2011) Identification of mRNAs that are spliced but not exported to the cytoplasm in the absence of THOC5 in mouse embryo fibroblasts. RNA 17: 1048–1056.21525145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Wang4"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>38 WangL, MiaoYL, ZhengX, LackfordB, ZhouB, et al (2013) The THO complex regulates pluripotency gene mRNA export and controls embryonic stem cell self-renewal and somatic cell reprogramming. Cell Stem Cell 13: 676–690.24315442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Barker1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>39 BarkerN, van EsJH, KuipersJ, KujalaP, van den BornM, et al (2007) Identification of stem cells in small intestine and colon by marker gene Lgr5. Nature 449: 1003–1007.17934449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0097628-Dancey1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>40 DanceyJT, DeubelbeissKA, HarkerLA, FinchCA (1976) Neutrophil kinetics in man. Journal of Clinical Investigation 58: 705–715.956397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
