<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4010498</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24798083</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-47937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Blood Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>White Blood Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Monocytes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fibrosis</subject><subj-group><subject>Cystic Fibrosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Dominance</subject><subj-group><subject>Autosomal Recessive Traits</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Human Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Burkholderia</subject><subj-group><subject>Burkholderia Cepacia Complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Genetics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ Stimulates Autophagy-Mediated Clearance of Burkholderia cenocepacia in Human Cystic Fibrosis Macrophages </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Autophagy Clearance of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cenocepacia</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assani</surname><given-names>Kaivon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tazi</surname><given-names>Mia F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>Amal O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>Benjamin T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Center for Microbial Pathogenesis, The Research Institute at Nationwide Children’s Hospital, Columbus, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Microbial Infection and Immunity and the Department of Internal Medicine, The Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Section of Pediatric Pulmonology, Nationwide Children’s Hospital, Columbus, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gulbins</surname><given-names>Erich</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Duisburg-Essen, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Benjamin.Kopp@NationwideChildrens.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KA AOA BTK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: KA MFT BTK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: KA MFT AOA BTK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AOA BTK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: KA BTK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e96681</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Assani et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Assani et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Burkholderia cenocepacia is a virulent pathogen that causes significant morbidity and mortality in patients with cystic fibrosis (CF), survives intracellularly in macrophages, and uniquely causes systemic infections in CF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Autophagy is a physiologic process that involves engulfing non-functional organelles and proteins and delivering them for lysosomal degradation, but also plays a role in eliminating intracellular pathogens, including B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Autophagy is defective in CF but can be stimulated in murine CF models leading to increased clearance of B. cenocepacia, but little is known about autophagy stimulation in human CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ activates macrophages and increases antigen presentation while also inducing autophagy in macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We therefore, hypothesized that treatment with IFN-γ would increase autophagy and macrophage activation in patients with CF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood monocyte derived macrophages (MDMs) were obtained from CF and non-CF donors and subsequently infected with B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Basal serum levels of IFN-γ were similar between CF and non-CF patients, however after B. cenocepacia infection there is deficient IFN-γ production in CF MDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ treated CF MDMs demonstrate increased co-localization with the autophagy molecule p62, increased autophagosome formation, and increased trafficking to lysosomes compared to untreated CF MDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy confirmed IFN-γ promotes double membrane vacuole formation around bacteria in CF MDMs, while only single membrane vacuoles form in untreated CF cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Bacterial burden is significantly reduced in autophagy stimulated CF MDMs, comparable to non-CF levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>IL-1β production is decreased in CF MDMs after IFN-γ treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Together, these results demonstrate that IFN-γ promotes autophagy-mediated clearance of B. cenocepacia in human CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by funds provided by the Public Health Preparedness for Infectious Diseases program (phpid.osu.edu) (BK, AA) and Nationwide Children’s Hospital institutional funds (BK). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Cystic fibrosis (CF) is an inherited, life-limiting disease that causes multi-organ dysfunction characterized by progressive respiratory infections with inspissated mucous [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Patients with CF can be infected by a variety of pathogens, including the rapidly transmissible Burkholderia cenocepacia [3]–[6]. B. cenocepacia is a unique CF pathogen that causes either a distinct clinical phenotype of systemic fatal septicemia or hastened chronic respiratory deterioration with diminished long term survival [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Therapeutic options are severely limited due to multi-drug resistance and near universal exclusion from lung transplant eligibility due to poor post-transplant survival in chronically infected patients [9]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Macrophages are a first-line defense against pathogens including B. cenocepacia. The vital role of macrophages in CF pathogen interactions, in addition to airway epithelial cells, has been highlighted by several groups [14]–[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Bacteria survive in CF macrophages despite successful phagocytosis due to links between CF transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) dysfunction and impaired phagolysosomal killing [17], [20], [21]. B. cenocepacia is also specifically able to evade degradation in CF macrophages leading to severe and persistent inflammation [19], [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Additionally, in model systems B. cenocepacia replicates inside of macrophages prior to dissemination [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In conjunction with macrophage defects, CF leads to deficient autophagy through inflammatory mediated cross-linking of the essential beclin-1 autophagy initiator interactome [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Autophagy is a physiologic process that normally augments innate responses to intraphagosomal pathogens and may relate to macrophage clearance defects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Deficient autophagy prevents destruction of engulfed B. cenocepacia in murine CF macrophages [22], [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulation by rapamycin reduces murine CF bacterial burden and inflammation [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulation with rapamycin also enhances clearance of other major CF pathogens such as Pseudomonas aeruginosa [27] and Staphylococcus aureus [28], but autophagy has not been studied in human CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Restoration of functional autophagy with an anti-inflammatory peptide, IDR-1018, decreases inflammation in CF cells [29], and may globally alleviate CF symptoms by releasing sequestered essential autophagy molecules, such as the autophagy adaptor molecule P62/SQSTM1 (p62)[30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Relief of sequestered autophagy molecules enabled protein aggregate clearance and improved CFTR trafficking, lending benefits of autophagy-stimulated pathogen clearance [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Although rapamycin was effective in murine CF studies, systemic side effects of rapamycin in CF [31] and increased development of interstitial lung disease [32] prevent clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Additionally, autophagy stimulation by immununologics, such as rapamycin, raises questions how this would affect other microorganisms in the lungs of CF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, IFN-γ has been shown to increase macrophage clearance of apoptotic cells in chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) [33], and is used prophylactically in CGD patients to prevent acquisition of severe infections such as Burkholderia species [34], [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>CGD, the only other known clinical disease commonly affected by Burkholderia species, also has known phagocytic killing defects [36], [37] and was recently shown to have deficient autophagic responses to B. cenocepacia [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, IFN-γ treatment enhances the autophagy response in macrophages derived from non-CGD patients resulting in clearance of pathogens that evade typical phagocytic degradation [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ therapy is well tolerated in CGD patients who have altered immune functions and polymicrobial infections similar to CF [34], [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Although a trial of inhaled IFN-γ in CF patients with mild to moderate disease did not prove effective in altering lung function [41], IFN-γ has never been studied systemically in CF, or specifically in B. cenocepacia infected patients, who may require more than local lung treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that due to known defects in CF macrophage autophagy, IFN-γ will reduce B. cenocepacia burden in human CF macrophages through more effective killing and enhanced autophagy that degrade B. cenocepacia in nascent vacuoles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Bacterial Strains and Culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Burkholderia cenocepacia strain k56-2 is a clinical isolate of the ET12 lineage originally isolated from a CF patient’s sputum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The strain was tagged dsRED and grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) broth at 37°C overnight with high amplitude shaking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The B. cenocepacia MHK1 strain is derived from k56-2 and has a mutation in an antibiotic efflux pump that confers gentamicin sensitivity, but does not alter the trafficking of the mutant in macrophages [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>For colony forming unit (CFU) analysis, 50 µg/ml gentamicin (Invitrogen, 3564) was added for 0.5 hours as described previously [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>To enumerate intracellular bacteria, infected macrophages were lysed with ice-cold PBS (Invitrogen, 14190) at designated times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Extracellular bacteria were enumerated directly from cell supernatants during macrophage viability assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Recovered bacteria were quantified by plating serial dilutions on LB agar plates and counting colonies using the Acolyte Colony Counter, 5710/SYN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Human Monocyte-Derived Macrophages (MDMs) –Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Human subjects underwent written informed consent for blood donation at the Nationwide Children’s Hospital as approved by the Institutional Review Board of Nationwide Children’s Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Written consent from legal guardians of minors was obtained as well as written assent from minors aged 9 to 17 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Blood was drawn in heparinized tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria included history of B. cepacia complex culture positivity, chronic immunosuppression, CFTR modulator use, and history of transplantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Chronic azithromycin was the only immunomodulatory medicine taken by some subjects during the study period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were isolated from 27 CF and 27 non-CF healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Monocytes were separated using a Ficol gradient via Lymphocyte Separation Medium (Corning, 25-072-CV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Isolated monocytes were re-suspended in RPMI (Gibco, 22400-089) and 10% human AB serum (Lonza, 14-490E) to a concentration of 2×106 cells/mL and incubated for 5 days at 37°C to derive macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were then infected with B. cenocepacia strain k56-2 at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) ranging from 2–10 over the stated times. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ (eBioscience, 14-8319-80) was used at a concentration of 200 ηg/ml based upon effectiveness in trial experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Rapamycin (LC laboratories, AY-22989) was added to the cells at a concentration of 25 µg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Treatments were added 1 hour post infection and the cells were allowed to incubate for 2, 4, and 24hours before obtaining results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Two mM 3-methyladenine (3MA, M9281) and 10 nM Bafilomycin (Sigma-Aldrich, B1793) were added one hour prior to infection in inhibitor experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Macrophage supernatants were removed post treatment and the cells were washed twice with phosphate buffered saline (PBS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The cells were lysed in lysis buffer and primed with a protease inhibitor (Roche Applied Science, 10-519-978-001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Then, 30 ug of protein was separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Membranes were immunoblotted for LC3 (Sigma-Aldrich, L8918), p62 (Sigma-Aldrich, P0067), beclin-1 (Abcam, ab51031), actin (Abcam, ab8226-100), IFNGR1 (Abcam, ab61179), IFNGRbeta (Abcam, ab84524), and calreticulin (Stressgen, #SPA-600). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Protein bands were detected with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies visualized using enhanced chemiluminescent (ECL) reagents (Life Sciences, RPN2106). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>MDM culture supernatants were clarified and stored at −20°C until assayed for cytokine content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>MDMs were infected for 4 and 24 hours with k56-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The quantification of IL-1β, IFN-γ, and IL-10 in supernatants was determined by sandwich ELISA following the manufacturer’s protocol (R&amp;D system Inc, DY285) as previously described [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxicity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>MDMs were infected with k56-2 for 4 and 24hours and the culture supernatants were collected and centrifuged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Histone-associated DNA fragments were detected using a cytotoxicity detection photometric assay kit according to the manufacturer’s protocol (Roche Applied Science, 11 644 793 001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in at least triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Additionally, macrophage viability was assessed via naphthol staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>MDMs were plated in 24-well plates, infected for 1 h, then treated for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed and treated with 1% Cetavlon in 0.1 M citric acid with 0.05% Napthol blue black (Sigma-Aldrich), pH 2.2, for 15 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Stained nuclei were enumerated on a haemacytometer using phase-contrast microscopy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Confocal Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Confocal microscopy sample were analyzed with an Olympus FV10i Spectral Confocal microscope. Two million MDMs were cultured on 12 mm glass cover slips in 24-well tissue culture plates and infected synchronously with k56-2 at an MOI of 2 or 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were stained with the nucleic acid dye 4′,6′-diamino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) blue for imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>LC3 stained green with a cleaved LC3 antibody detection (Abgent, AP1805a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Lysosomes were stained green with Lysotracker Green (Invitrogen, L7526). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>p62 was detected with a green fluorescent ligand (BD Bioscience, 610832). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>At least one hundred macrophages were scored for each condition with scoring verified by independent study members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in at least triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Transmission Electron Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>TEM Images were obtained using a FEI Technai G2 Spirit transmission electron microscope (FEI, USA), Macrofire (Optronics) digital camera and AMT image capture Software with assistance from the Campus Microscopy and Imaging Facility (CMIF) at The Ohio State University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>MDMs were isolated and infected with k56-2 at an MOI of 10 for 1 hour prior to 24 hour experimental treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured on Permanox (Lab-Tek) chamber slides and fixed with 2.5% gluteraldehyde in 0.1 M phosphate buffer with 0.1 M sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Slides were post fixed with 1% osmium tetroxide in phosphate buffer then en bloc stained with 2% uranyl acetate in 10% ethanol, dehydrated in a graded series of ethanols and embedded in Eponate 12 epoxy resin (Ted Pella Inc., USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Ultrathin sections were cut on a Leica EM UC6 ultra microtome (Leica microsystems, Germany), collected on copper grids, and then stained with lead citrate and uranyl acetate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism software (version 6.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was determined with a two-tailed p&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Mann-Whitney was used for non-parametric measurements, and ANOVA was used where appropriate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Patient Demographics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Subject demographics are described in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>CF and non-CF subjects were similar in terms of ethnicity (100% Caucasian) and mean age (30.4±11.5 years vs. 33.5±9.2 years, p = 0.53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Subjects with CF had a mean forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) % predicted of 57.1%, indicative of moderately severe lung function at the time of sampling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>81% of CF patients had chronic respiratory cultures positive for P. aeruginosa, and 48% had methicillin resistant S. aureus (MRSA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Importantly, 48% of subjects were on chronic azithromycin prophylaxis, and this treatment was not noted to influence the experiments below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Azithromycin has been show to block autophagy in CF macrophages in vitro [44], but CF Patient Registry data does not support an increased risk of mycobacterial infections for those on chronic azithromycin as proposed in the study by Renna and colleagues[45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Cell cultures in our experiments were not further treated with azithromycin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0096681-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Patient Demographics. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0096681-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0096681.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>non CF patients (n = 27) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>CF patients (n = 27) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Mean age (years ± st. dev.) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>33.5±9.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>30.4±11.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>30% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>59% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Caucasian </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>100% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>100% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Mean FEV1 (% predicted) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>N/A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>57.1±21.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Pseudomonas colonization </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>N/A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>81% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>MRSA colonization </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>N/A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>48% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ Production is Reduced in CF PBMCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ effectively stimulates autophagic responses in macrophages [46], [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, CF cells insufficiently produce IFN-γ in response to another pathogen, P. aeruginosa [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>To determine if IFN-γ is differentially produced in CF in response to B. cenocepacia, IFN-γ was measured in the serum of CF and non-CF subjects prior to macrophage isolation and in PBMC culture supernatants with and without 24 hour B. cenocepacia infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Mean serum levels of IFN-γ were non-significantly lower in CF versus non-CF subjects (56.6±6.6 vs. 78.9±10.4, p = 0.08, Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Infected non-CF PBMC supernatants displayed significantly higher IFN-γ levels compared to uninfected, whereas there was no change in IFN-γ production between uninfected and infected CF PBMCs (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Uninfected CF and non-CF PBMC IFN-γ levels were both slightly higher than serum levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in IFN-γ production between CF patients on azithromycin therapy and those not (figure S1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Additionally, there was no difference in IFN-γ receptor expression during infection between IFN-γ treated and non-treated MDMs as measured by immunoblotting (Figures 1C, 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with studies from P. aeruginosa [48], suggesting a defective host CF IFN-γ response to multiple pathogens in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ is deficiently produced in CF PBMCs in response to B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>1A) IFN-γ levels from the serum of 14 non-CF and 14 CF patients at the time of blood donation, p = 0.056, n = 14 subjects for each condition, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>1B) IFN-γ production from PBMC 24 hour cell supernatants from CF and non-CF patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>NT represents uninfected cells, and k56 were infected with B. cenocepacia k56-2. n = 8 subjects for NT and 10 subjects k56, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>1C) Immunoblot for IFN-receptor 1 from cell lysates of MDMs infected with k56-2+/− treatment with IFN-γ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>1D) Immunoblot for IFN-receptor β from cell lysates of MDMs infected with k56-2+/− treatment with IFN-γ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ Increases B. cenocepacia Co-localization with p62 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>p62 is an essential intracellular protein that targets cargo for autophagy as well as regulates signaling pathways involved in cell survival and/or death [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This docking molecule is required for targeting B. cenocepacia to autophagosomes in a murine model[26], however its mechanism of action in human cells infected with B. cenocepacia is unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Using confocal microscopy, we investigated how p62 targets B. cenocepacia in human CF macrophages by examining MDMs for co-localization of bacteria with p62 after a 24 hour infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>MDMs were stimulated with rapamycin or IFN-γ for the duration of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Untreated CF macrophages demonstrated significantly less median co-localization with p62 compared to non-CF macrophages (16.8% (10.1–19.1) vs. 37.0% (34.9–40.0), p = 0.016, Figures 2A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ or rapamycin treatment significantly increased median bacterial co-localization with p62 in CF human MDMs (CF IFN-γ 32.7% (25.2–33.4), p = 0.006, CF rapamycin 26.3% (22.4–47.4), p = 0.008, Figures 2A,B) nearing non-CF levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>p62 levels detected by western blotting are increased in uninfected and infected CF MDMs compared to non-CF MDMs (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four hour IFN-γ treatment of non-CF and CF MDMs resulted in a decrement in p62 accumulation (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>To ensure that initiation of the beclin-1 interactome was not influencing p62 expression, beclin-1 was measured via immunoblotting and confocal microscopy after 24 hour infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in beclin-1 levels between CF and non CF MDMs (Figure 2C, confocal not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Altogether, this data suggested that p62 is either sequestered or inefficiently utilized by human CF MDMs, and IFN-γ can alleviate this undesirable phenotype in CF cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ increases B. cenocepacia co-localization with p62 and decreases p62 accumulation in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>2A) Confocal microscopy for non-CF and CF macrophages infected with m-RFP expressing k56-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>IFN-y or rapamycin treatment was administered after 1 hour of infection for a 24 hour treatment period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>p62 is stained green, and macrophage nuclei are stained blue with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Co-localization of bacteria with p62 is noted in yellow in the bottom panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>2B) The percentage of bacterial co-localization with p62 was scored for over 100 macrophages per condition, n = 5 subjects per condition, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>2C) Immunoblot for non-CF and CF macrophages demonstrating p62 accumulation in CF with reduction during IFN-y therapy, representative of 5 subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Immunoblot of beclin-1 levels for non-CF and CF macrophages from cell lysates of control (NT) and MDMs infected with k56-2+/− treatment with IFN-γ, n = 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Autophagic Flux is Enhanced by IFN-γ in CF MDMs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Autophagic flux is deficient in CF cells [25], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Microtubule-associated proteins 1A/1B light chain 3A (LC3) can be monitored to assess autophagosome formation and flux. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>During the autophagic process, cytosolic LC3 (LC3-I) is conjugated to phosphatidylethanolamine to form LC3-II, which is then recruited to the autophagosomal membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We analyzed LC3 concentrations by immunoblotting to monitor the conversion of LC3-I to LC3-II, as well as depletion/accumulation of the proteins to assist in determination of turnover of proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>During basal, uninfected conditions (NT), CF macrophages demonstrated persistence of increased LC3-1 over 24 hours compared to non CF as evidence by high proportion of LC31 relative to total LC3 (Figures 3A, 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Infection with k56-2 leads to persistently elevated LC3-1 levels in CF by 24 hours compared to non CF, but to a lesser extent than basal conditions (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>LC31 levels are seen to decrease in CF similar to non CF levels by 24 hours with the use of either IFN-γ or rapamycin (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Specific autophagy inhibitors were used to monitor treatment effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The addition of bafilomycin to inhibit autophagolysosomal fusion via inhibiting vacuolar H+ ATPase (V-ATPase) caused an increase in LC3-1 in CF at 4 and 24 hours (Figures 3A,3B), reversing the effects of IFN-γ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The addition of 3-methyladenine (3-MA) to block autophagosome formation via inhibiting type III Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinases had a similar, but lesser effect in CF on LC3 conversion compared to bafilomycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Combining data from 4 and 24 hour time points suggests a deficit in autophagic flux in CF macrophages, with enhancement through autophagy stimulators such as IFN-γ that are increasing autophagosome formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Autophagic flux is decreased in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>3A) Representative immunoblot of 4 hour treatment protein lysates for LC3-1 and LC3-2 from non-CF and CF macrophages, with corresponding summed band densitometries normalized to loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>All lanes are marked with a “+” if the corresponding treatments were added: B. cenocepacia infection (k56-2), autophagy stimulators (IFN-y, Rapamycin) and autophagy inhibitors (Bafilomycin, 3-MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Inhibitors were added one hour prior to infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulators were added one hour after infection for a total of 4 hours of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Data is representative of 3 independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>3B) Representative immunoblot of 24 hour treatment protein lysates for LC3-1 and LC3-2 from non-CF and CF macrophages with corresponding summed band densitometries normalized to loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>All lanes are marked with a “+” if the corresponding treatments were added: B. cenocepacia infection (k56-2), autophagy stimulators (IFN-y, Rapamycin) and autophagy inhibitors (Bafilomycin, 3-MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Inhibitors were added one hour prior to infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulators were added one hour after infection for a total of 24 hours of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Data is representative of 3 independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Autophagy Stimulation Increases Bacterial Clearance in CF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>B. cenocepacia infection causes increased bacterial burden in human and murine CF cells, indicating an innate defect in clearing the pathogen in CF [19], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Persistent bacterial loads can lead to systemic involvement and/or heightened inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Because autophagy regulates pathogen clearance, we stimulated autophagy in MDMs with IFN-y or rapamycin for 4 and 24 hours and assessed bacterial clearance by confocal microscopy and CFU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four hours is an expected clinical dosing regimen of IFN-γ, and 4 hours was chosen to ensure sufficient autophagosome formation, as murine studies have shown that even in wild type macrophages B. cenocepacia requires at least 2 hours to traffic to autophagosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>There is no difference in bacterial counts at 2 hours (figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>At 4 hours of treatment, there were significantly higher bacterial counts in both autophagy-stimulated and unstimulated CF macrophages compared to non-CF macrophages (Figures 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>However, CF macrophages treated with IFN-γ for 4 hours had a higher proportion of bacterial co-localized with autophagosomes as marked by LC3 compared to untreated CF macrophages (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A 24 hour treatment of IFN-γ or rapamycin markedly reduced bacterial counts in the CF macrophages compared to untreated CF macrophages (Figures 4B, 4C, 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>These reductions mirror bacterial levels in non-CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in bacterial counts between CF patients on azithromycin therapy and those not (Supplemental Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>24 hour extracellular bacterial counts were not reduced (Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>There is a sustained increase in the co-localization of bacteria with LC3 after 24 hours of autophagy stimulation in CF macrophages compared to untreated CF macrophages (p = 0.02, Figures 4B, 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy confirmed these confocal findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Untreated non-CF macrophages contained double membrane vacuoles surrounding B. cenocepacia, indicative of autophagosome formation (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Untreated CF macrophages displayed only single membrane bound vacuoles (5C), but when stimulated with IFN-γ, CF macrophages displayed double membrane vacuoles similar to the non-CF (5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests autophagosome formation is stimulated upon IFN-γ treatment in the CF MDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Additionally, IFN-γ had no direct effects on bacterial growth when added to bacteria in media devoid of MDMs, with no difference in bacterial growth over 24 hours between media with k56-2 alone, and media with k56-2 plus IFN-γ (Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In summation, these results indicate that IFN-γ effectively stimulates early autophagic targeting of B. cenocepacia to autophagosomes, thus allowing enhanced clearance after 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ increases autophagosome formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>4A) Confocal microscopy for non-CF and CF macrophages infected with m-RFP expressing k56-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>IFN-y treatment was administered after 1 hour of infection for a 4 hour treatment period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>LC3 is stained green, and macrophage nuclei are stained blue with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Co-localization of bacteria with LC3 is noted in yellow in the bottom panel as noted by white arrows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>4B) 24 hour IFN-γ and rapamycin treatments similar to 4A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>4C) Summary of scored bacteria per 100 macrophages from individual subjects for the confocal microscopy experiments from 4B, n = 17 subjects, with 2 replicates per subject, unpaired t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>4D) The percentage of bacterial co-localization with LC3 was scored for over 100 macrophages per condition from 4B, n = 17 subjects, with 2 replicates per subject, unpaired t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>4E) CFU counts for non-CF and CF macrophages infected with MHK1 for 24 hours (n = 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ stimulates double-membrane autophagosome formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>5A) Electron microscopy of non-CF macrophage infected with k56-2 only for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>White arrow indicates double membrane formation indicative of autophagosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>5B) EM of non-CF macrophage treated with IFN-γ for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>5C) EM of CF macrophage infected with k56-2 only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Black arrow indicates single membrane vacuole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>5D) EM of CF macrophage treated with IFN-γ for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>White arrow indicates double membrane formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Pictures are marked with 500 nm marker. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Lysosome Targeting is Increased in Autophagy Stimulated CF MDMs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Rapamycin increases lysosomal degradation of B. cenocepacia in CF murine macrophages by promoting phagosome-lysosome fusion via autophagy [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Human CF macrophages also demonstrate decreased co-localization of B. cenocepacia with lysosomes[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We examined the extent to which IFN-γ enhances autophagosome fusion with lysosomes by infecting human MDMs with B. cenocepacia for 1 hour and then treating with IFN-γ for 2 and 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>We then scored co-localization of a fluorescent lysotracker with bacteria using confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>After 2 hours of infection, untreated CF macrophages exhibited very little co-localization of bacteria with lysosomes (11.5±3.2%, Figures 6A, B) compared to non-CF macrophages (29.9±8.5%, Figures 6A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>However, CF macrophages treated with IFN-γ demonstrate increased lysosomal co-localization of bacteria (26.5±.5%, p&lt;0.0001, Figures 6A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>After 24 hours of IFN-γ therapy CF macrophages demonstrated a sustained lysosomal co-localization of remaining bacteria, similar to what was observed in non-CF macrophages (34.8±5.4% vs. 37.0±9.5%, p = 0.5, Figures 6C, D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Untreated CF macrophages have significantly less lysosomal co-localization compared to treated CF macrophages at 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>(25.1±9.4%, p = 0.038, Figures 6C, D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Together, the results demonstrate delayed lysosomal targeting of B. cenocepacia in CF MDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Combined with prior results, IFN-γ treatment increases autophagosome formation in CF macrophages, enhancing lysosomal targeting of B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Lysosomal co-localization is increased with IFN-γ in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>6A) Confocal microscopy for non-CF and CF macrophages infected with k56-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Macrophages were labeled with green lysotracker and bacterial co-localization to lysosomes was measured after a 2 hour infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Macrophage nuclei are stained blue with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Co-localization of bacteria with lysotracker is noted in yellow by white arrows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>6B) Quantitative scoring of % bacterial co-localization with lysosomes from 6A, n = 8 subjects, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>6C) 24 hour k56-2 infection with lysotracker staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>6D) Bacterial co-localization with lysotracker quantitative scoring for 5C, n = 8 subjects, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>IL-1β Production is Decreased with Autophagy Stimulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>CF macrophages excessively produce the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-1β in response to B. cenocepacia infection [19], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Human bronchial epithelial cells do not produce IL-1β in response to B. cenocepacia [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>During B. cenocepacia infection pyrin inflammasome activation results in IL-1β release from mononuclear cells [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we measured IL-1β production in human CF macrophages after autophagy stimulation as a primary source of excess inflammatory cytokine production during infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>MDMs were infected with B. cenocepacia and treated with IFN-γ or rapamycin for 4 and 24 hours and cell supernatants were examined by ELISA for IL-1β production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>After 4 hours of autophagy stimulation, IL-1β levels were similar between treated and untreated CF macrophages, but CF macrophages had significantly more IL-1β than non-CF macrophages (p = 0.0012, Figure 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>However, in CF macrophages treated with IFN-γ, IL-1β levels diminished by 24 hours of treatment (p = 0.045), while untreated CF macrophages infected with B. cenocepacia perpetuate elevated IL-1β production (Figure 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in IL-1β production between CF patients on azithromycin therapy and those not (figure S1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>IL-10 was also measured as it can directly impair IFN-γ signaling pathways and its production can correlate with inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>There was no difference in IL-10 production in 24 hour supernatants between uninfected, infected, and IFN-γ treated CF and non-CF macrophages (Figure 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate autophagy induction plays a role in reducing IL-1β production in macrophage responses to B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>IL-1β is decreased with IFN-γ treatment in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>IL-1β levels in macrophage supernatants after infection with k56-2 and either a 4 hour treatment with IFN-γ or a control diluent (7A) or a 24 hour IFN-γ treatment (7B), n = 7 subjects, Mann-Whitney analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>7C) IL-10 levels in macrophage supernatants after infection with k56-2 and a 24 hour treatment with IFN-γ or a control diluent, n = 7 subjects, Mann-Whitney analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Significant differences are noted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3h"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Cell Death is Decreased by IFN-γ Treatment during B. cenocepacia Infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>B. cenocepacia promotes increased cell death in human CF macrophages [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Autophagy has an interconnected role with apoptosis and necrosis in the regulation of cell death [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>We examined MDMs for LDH release at 4 and 24 hours after infection to assess cell death as a result of autophagy stimulation in CF macrophages infected with B. cenocepacia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>After 4 hours of infection IFN-γ treated CF MDMs trended towards higher cell death compared to untreated CF MDMs (Figure 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>All CF macrophages had higher cell death than non-CF macrophages (Figure 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>After 24 of infection CF macrophages remained with slightly higher cell death than non-CF, except for IFN-γ treated CF MDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>There was also no difference among autophagy stimulated CF macrophages compared to un-stimulated CF macrophages (Figures 8B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Macrophage viability was additionally assessed at 24 hours of infection via a naphthol blue/black assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>At 24 hours there was no difference in macrophage viability between CF and non CF macrophage (Figure 8C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Macrophage viability was not decreased with IFN-γ treatment (Figure 8c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Taken together, this data suggests that autophagic clearance of B. cenocepacia in CF macrophages decreases cell death in a human model after IFN-γ treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0096681-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096681.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Cell death is decreased with autophagy stimulation in CF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Percent LDH release from MDM supernatants treated with autophagy stimulators IFN-γ or Rapamycin for 4 hours (8A) or 24 hours (8B), n = at least 6 subjects per condition, Mann-Whitney testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>8c) Percent of macrophages deemed viable per naphthol staining after a 24 hour infection, n = 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0096681.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The discovery of new therapeutic classes or novel utilization of existing therapeutics is imperative for CF patients infected with B. cenocepacia due to its devastating impact on morbidity and mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Here, we demonstrate the effectiveness of autophagy stimulation as a therapeutic class, specifically IFN-γ in clearing B. cenocepacia from human CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>This is a crucial finding considering the mounting evidence for CFTR dysfunction in monocyte-pathogen interactions in CF[54], as well as the ability of B. cenocepacia to replicate within macrophages [24], [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>By improving the clearance of B. cenocepacia from macrophages, we can minimize the chances of overwhelming bacteremia as well as reduce continued pro-inflammatory signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Our work is aligned well with a recent study from Al-Khodor and colleagues in CGD macrophages [38], and importantly demonstrates the effectiveness of a post infection therapeutic intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulation also holds the promise of clearing other pathogens in CF besides B. cenocepacia [27], [28], [56], as well as facilitating CFTR trafficking [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ has numerous signaling effects in the body including host defense, autoimmunity, inflammatory responses, and is a major activator of macrophages [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we found deficient production of IFN-γ with adequate receptor expression in CF PBMCs in response to B. cenocepacia compared to non-CF PBMCs, suggesting a natural defect in CF macrophage priming/pathogen response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>This was in contrast to our previous work with the J2315 strain [19], however our previous study may have been affected by the different strain as well as negligible baseline IFN-γ from pure macrophage cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ has been previously studied in CF as an inhalational therapy in patients without Burkholderia infections, demonstrating no significant effects on lung function, sputum bacterial density, or inflammatory sputum markers [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>However, in that study only 2 of the 48 treated patients had detected serum IFN-γ levels, and they did not measure lower airway IFN-γ levels to monitor deposition efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the effective aerosol deposition of IFN-γ is low in several non-CF studies, which questions the efficacy of the aforementioned CF study as alveolar macrophages would not be affected by upper airway deposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>A 2004 study of aerosolized IFN-γ in TB patients demonstrated greater upper airway deposition of IFN-γ than lower airway, with a mean lower airway deposition of only 35.8 µg of a 500 ug dose [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Recent studies in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis demonstrated only 65% lower airway deposition using a Philips Respironics I-neb [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Based on the sputum density of CF patients it is reasonable to assume that nebulized concentrations of IFN-γ would be even lower in CF patients’ lower airways, necessitating systemic IFN-γ use in situations such as B. cenocepacia septicemia or worsening patient progression until improved aerosol deposition can be achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Prior studies in CF murine models of P. aeruginosa infection effectively utilized IFN-γ as a systemic therapy [60], and patients with CGD inject IFN-γ subcutaneously to prevent infections with species including Burkholderia [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Known side effects of IFN-γ administration are fever, headaches, myalgias, fatigue, irritability, and flulike syndromes, but overall it has been safely used in CGD [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The effects of IFN-γ on the total CF microbiome still remain to be characterized, but on individual pathogens such as B. cenocepacia and P. aeruginosa, there is a demonstrable benefit on bacterial clearance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Autophagy stimulation is also known to reduce inflammasome mediated IL-1β production [62] and attenuates hyperinflammatory responses from CF cells [29] independent of B. cenocepacia. We demonstrated that IFN-γ was effective in reducing the exaggerated IL-1β production that is observed in response to B. cenocepacia in CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>This result was not unexpected given the possibility of inflammasome dependent IFN-γ signaling [63], as well as the observed reduction in bacteria with IFN-γ treatment in the CF macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Therefore, our results suggest the reductions in IL-1β are likely due to both the reduced burden observed and dampened inflammasome activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>IL-10 was unchanged with treatment, but was not significantly different between CF and non CF prior to treatment, and therefore not likely to be reduced with IFN-γ therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Importantly, IL-10 was not significantly overproduced in response to therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>In addition to reductions in bacteria and inflammatory cytokines, autophagy stimulation was effective in increasing autophagosome formation and trafficking of B. cenocepacia to lysosomes. B. cenocepacia-containing vacuoles have been shown to have prolonged arrest phases [64], and the ability to correctly utilize otherwise sequestered autophagic machinery may be key in overcoming this delay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy confirmed the presence of single membrane vacuoles containing B. cenocepacia in untreated CF macrophages that were effectively converted to double membrane autophagosomes upon IFN-γ stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>This process was marked by decreased p62 accumulation and decreased LC3-I accumulation, suggesting effective autophagic flux, allowing for early autophagolysosomal fusion and subsequent bacterial clearance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>This study is limited by the use of a single pathogen model, which was necessary to accurately follow B. cenocepacia trafficking as well as cytokine production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Future studies will examine multi-pathogen models to examine more closely effects on pathogen interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Further work is also needed in vivo to determine the benefits in human subjects. B. cenocepacia also possesses several quorum sensing systems that may affect its activity in humans and during a 24 hour infection model [65]–[67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>This will be important to consider in future multi-pathogen studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we tried to overcome inherent human subject differences in cell signaling and baseline medications through the use of multiple subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we did not see differences in B. cenocepacia clearance by CF patients chronically on azithromycin, but samples did not receive further supplementation with azithromycin during any of the experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In summary, CF macrophages have a deficient IFN-γ response to B. cenocepacia, ineffective utilization of the autophagy cargo molecule p62, decreased autophagosome formation, and delayed lysosomal uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ treatment increased autophagy mediated clearance of B. cenocepacia in human CF macrophages via increased autophagosome formation and lysosomal trafficking, and was associated with decreased inflammatory cytokine production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The use of IFN-γ or autophagy stimulating drugs is promising for treating life-threatening or chronic infections from B. cenocepacia in patients with CF, but further study is needed to determine their efficacy outside of cell culture models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0096681.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Chronic azithromycin use has no effect on CF MDMs. S1A) Serum (n = 7) and infected PBMC (k56, n = 5) IFN-γ levels from CF and non-CF patients separated by patients with (+azithromycin) and without chronic azithromycin prophylaxis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>S1B) Summary of scored bacteria per 100 macrophages from individual subjects for the confocal microscopy experiments from 4B and separated by patients with (+azithromycin) and without chronic azithromycin prophylaxis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>S1C) IL-1β levels in macrophage supernatants after infection with k56-2 and either a 24 hour treatment with IFN-γ or a control diluent and separated by patients with (+azithromycin) and without chronic azithromycin prophylaxis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0096681.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0096681.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>No difference in 2 hour or supernatant CFUs. CFU counts for non-CF and CF macrophages infected with MHK1 for 2 (n = 3) and 24 hour supernatants (n = 3) with or without IFN-γ treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0096681.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0096681.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ has no effect on bacterial growth in media devoid of MDMs. Optical density (OD) of bacteria cultured in LB broth alone (k56-2) versus LB + IFN-γ (IFN-γ) was compared over 24 hours during normal growth conditions at 37° with high amplitude shaking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Inset shows negligible difference at 24 hours in OD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0096681.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Thank you to Richard Montione from the CMIF at The Ohio State University for aiding with TEM processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Thank you to Anwari Akhter and Kyle Caution for editing and experimental input. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Thanks to Don Hayes Jr. for his editorial comments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Dr. Miguel Valvano kindly donated the MHK strain. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0096681-Grasemann1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>1 GrasemannH, RatjenF (2013) Early lung disease in cystic fibrosis. Lancet Respir Med 1: 148–157.24429095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Kreda1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>2 KredaSM, DavisCW, RoseMC (2012) CFTR, mucins, and mucus obstruction in cystic fibrosis. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med 2: a009589.22951447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Govan1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>3 GovanJR, BrownPH, MaddisonJ, DohertyCJ, NelsonJW, et al (1993) Evidence for transmission of Pseudomonas cepacia by social contact in cystic fibrosis. Lancet 342: 15–19.7686239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Sun1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>4 SunL, JiangRZ, SteinbachS, HolmesA, CampanelliC, et al (1995) The emergence of a highly transmissible lineage of cbl+ Pseudomonas (Burkholderia) cepacia causing CF centre epidemics in North America and Britain. Nat Med 1: 661–666.7585148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Walsh1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>5 WalshNM, CasanoAA, MananganLP, Sinkowitz-CochranRL, JarvisWR (2002) Risk factors for Burkholderia cepacia complex colonization and infection among patients with cystic fibrosis. J Pediatr 141: 512–517.12378190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Drevinek1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>6 DrevinekP, MahenthiralingamE (2010) Burkholderia cenocepacia in cystic fibrosis: epidemiology and molecular mechanisms of virulence. Clin Microbiol Infect 16: 821–830.20880411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Jones1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>7 JonesAM, DoddME, GovanJR, BarcusV, DohertyCJ, et al (2004) Burkholderia cenocepacia and Burkholderia multivorans: influence on survival in cystic fibrosis. Thorax 59: 948–951.15516469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Isles1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>8 IslesA, MacluskyI, CoreyM, GoldR, ProberC, et al (1984) Pseudomonas cepacia infection in cystic fibrosis: an emerging problem. J Pediatr 104: 206–210.6420530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Alexander1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>9 AlexanderBD, PetzoldEW, RellerLB, PalmerSM, DavisRD, et al (2008) Survival after lung transplantation of cystic fibrosis patients infected with Burkholderia cepacia complex. Am J Transplant 8: 1025–1030.18318775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-DeSoyza1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>10 De SoyzaA, MeacheryG, HesterKL, NicholsonA, ParryG, et al (2010) Lung transplantation for patients with cystic fibrosis and Burkholderia cepacia complex infection: a single-center experience. J Heart Lung Transplant 29: 1395–1404.20810293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Egan1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>11 EganTM, DetterbeckFC, MillMR, BleiweisMS, ArisR, et al (2002) Long term results of lung transplantation for cystic fibrosis. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg 22: 602–609.12297180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Murray1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>12 MurrayS, CharbeneauJ, MarshallBC, LiPumaJJ (2008) Impact of burkholderia infection on lung transplantation in cystic fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 178: 363–371.18535253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Olland1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>13 OllandA, FalcozPE, KesslerR, MassardG (2011) Should cystic fibrosis patients infected with Burkholderia cepacia complex be listed for lung transplantation? Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg 13: 631–634.21920934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Brennan1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>14 BrennanS, SlyPD, GangellCL, SturgesN, WinfieldK, et al (2009) Alveolar macrophages and CC chemokines are increased in children with cystic fibrosis. Eur Respir J 34: 655–661.19386685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Bruscia1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>15 BrusciaEM, ZhangPX, FerreiraE, CaputoC, EmersonJW, et al (2009) Macrophages directly contribute to the exaggerated inflammatory response in cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator−/− mice. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol 40: 295–304.18776130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Bruscia2"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>16 BrusciaEM, ZhangPX, SatohA, CaputoC, MedzhitovR, et al (2011) Abnormal trafficking and degradation of TLR4 underlie the elevated inflammatory response in cystic fibrosis. J Immunol 186: 6990–6998.21593379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-DelPorto1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>17 Del PortoP, CifaniN, GuarnieriS, Di DomenicoEG, MariggioMA, et al (2011) Dysfunctional CFTR alters the bactericidal activity of human macrophages against Pseudomonas aeruginosa. PLoS One 6: e19970.21625641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Hartl1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>18 HartlD, GaggarA, BrusciaE, HectorA, MarcosV, et al (2012) Innate immunity in cystic fibrosis lung disease. J Cyst Fibros 11: 363–382.22917571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Kopp1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>19 KoppBT, AbdulrahmanBA, KhweekAA, KumarSB, AkhterA, et al (2012) Exaggerated inflammatory responses mediated by Burkholderia cenocepacia in human macrophages derived from Cystic fibrosis patients. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 424: 221–227.22728038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Vandivier1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>20 VandivierRW, RichensTR, HorstmannSA, deCathelineauAM, GhoshM, et al (2009) Dysfunctional cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator inhibits phagocytosis of apoptotic cells with proinflammatory consequences. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 297: L677–686.19633071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Di1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>21 DiA, BrownME, DeriyLV, LiC, SzetoFL, et al (2006) CFTR regulates phagosome acidification in macrophages and alters bactericidal activity. Nat Cell Biol 8: 933–944.16921366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Abdulrahman1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>22 AbdulrahmanBA, KhweekAA, AkhterA, CautionK, KotrangeS, et al (2011) Autophagy stimulation by rapamycin suppresses lung inflammation and infection by Burkholderia cenocepacia in a model of cystic fibrosis. Autophagy 7: 1359–1370.21997369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Kotrange1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>23 KotrangeS, KoppB, AkhterA, AbdelazizD, Abu KhweekA, et al (2011) Burkholderia cenocepacia O polysaccharide chain contributes to caspase-1-dependent IL-1beta production in macrophages. J Leukoc Biol 89: 481–488.21178113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Vergunst1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>24 VergunstAC, MeijerAH, RenshawSA, O’CallaghanD (2010) Burkholderia cenocepacia creates an intramacrophage replication niche in zebrafish embryos, followed by bacterial dissemination and establishment of systemic infection. Infect Immun 78: 1495–1508.20086083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Luciani1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>25 LucianiA, VillellaVR, EspositoS, Brunetti-PierriN, MedinaD, et al (2010) Defective CFTR induces aggresome formation and lung inflammation in cystic fibrosis through ROS-mediated autophagy inhibition. Nat Cell Biol 12: 863–875.20711182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Abdulrahman2"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>26 AbdulrahmanBA, KhweekAA, AkhterA, CautionK, TaziM, et al (2013) Depletion of the ubiquitin-binding adaptor molecule SQSTM1/p62 from macrophages harboring cftr DeltaF508 mutation improves the delivery of Burkholderia cenocepacia to the autophagic machinery. J Biol Chem 288: 2049–2058.23148214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Yuan1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>27 YuanK, HuangC, FoxJ, LaturnusD, CarlsonE, et al (2012) Autophagy plays an essential role in the clearance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa by alveolar macrophages. J Cell Sci 125: 507–515.22302984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Schnaith1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>28 SchnaithA, KashkarH, LeggioSA, AddicksK, KronkeM, et al (2007) Staphylococcus aureus subvert autophagy for induction of caspase-independent host cell death. J Biol Chem 282: 2695–2706.17135247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Mayer1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>29 MayerML, BlohmkeCJ, FalsafiR, FjellCD, MaderaL, et al (2013) Rescue of Dysfunctional Autophagy Attenuates Hyperinflammatory Responses from Cystic Fibrosis Cells. J Immunol 190: 1227–1238.23264659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Luciani2"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>30 LucianiA, VillellaVR, EspositoS, GavinaM, RussoI, et al (2012) Targeting autophagy as a novel strategy for facilitating the therapeutic action of potentiators on DeltaF508 cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator. Autophagy 8: 1657–1672.22874563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Hardinger1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>31 HardingerKL, CorneliusLA, TrulockEP3rd, BrennanDC (2002) Sirolimus-induced leukocytoclastic vasculitis. Transplantation 74: 739–743.12352895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Chhajed1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>32 ChhajedPN, DickenmannM, BubendorfL, MayrM, SteigerJ, et al (2006) Patterns of pulmonary complications associated with sirolimus. Respiration 73: 367–374.16127266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-FernandezBoyanapalli1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>33 Fernandez-BoyanapalliR, McPhillipsKA, FraschSC, JanssenWJ, DinauerMC, et al (2010) Impaired phagocytosis of apoptotic cells by macrophages in chronic granulomatous disease is reversed by IFN-gamma in a nitric oxide-dependent manner. J Immunol 185: 4030–4041.20805415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>34 A controlled trial of interferon gamma to prevent infection in chronic granulomatous disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The International Chronic Granulomatous Disease Cooperative Study Group. N Engl J Med 324: 509–516.1846940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Errante1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>35 ErrantePR, FrazaoJB, Condino-NetoA (2008) The use of interferon-gamma therapy in chronic granulomatous disease. Recent Pat Antiinfect Drug Discov 3: 225–230.18991804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-McPhail1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>36 McPhailLC, DeChateletLR, ShirleyPS, WilfertC, JohnstonRBJr, et al (1977) Deficiency of NADPH oxidase activity in chronic granulomatous disease. J Pediatr 90: 213–217.12254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Sanmun1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>37 SanmunD, WitaspE, JitkaewS, TyurinaYY, KaganVE, et al (2009) Involvement of a functional NADPH oxidase in neutrophils and macrophages during programmed cell clearance: implications for chronic granulomatous disease. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol 297: C621–631.19570889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-AlKhodor1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>38 Al-KhodorS, Marshall-BattyK, NairV, DingL, GreenbergDE, et al (2014) Burkholderia cenocepacia J2315 escapes to the cytosol and actively subverts autophagy in human macrophages. Cell Microbiol 16: 378–395.24119232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Gutierrez1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>39 GutierrezMG, MasterSS, SinghSB, TaylorGA, ColomboMI, et al (2004) Autophagy is a defense mechanism inhibiting BCG and Mycobacterium tuberculosis survival in infected macrophages. Cell 119: 753–766.15607973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Holland1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>40 HollandSM (2010) Chronic granulomatous disease. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol 38: 3–10.19504359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Moss1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>41 MossRB, Mayer-HamblettN, WagenerJ, DainesC, HaleK, et al (2005) Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-escalating study of aerosolized interferon gamma-1b in patients with mild to moderate cystic fibrosis lung disease. Pediatr Pulmonol 39: 209–218.15573395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Hamad1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>42 HamadMA, SkeldonAM, ValvanoMA (2010) Construction of aminoglycoside-sensitive Burkholderia cenocepacia strains for use in studies of intracellular bacteria with the gentamicin protection assay. Appl Environ Microbiol 76: 3170–3176.20348312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Akhter1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>43 AkhterA, GavrilinMA, FrantzL, WashingtonS, DittyC, et al (2009) Caspase-7 activation by the Nlrc4/Ipaf inflammasome restricts Legionella pneumophila infection. PLoS Pathog 5: e1000361.19343209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Renna1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>44 RennaM, SchaffnerC, BrownK, ShangS, TamayoMH, et al (2011) Azithromycin blocks autophagy and may predispose cystic fibrosis patients to mycobacterial infection. J Clin Invest 121: 3554–3563.21804191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Binder1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>45 BinderAM, AdjemianJ, OlivierKN, PrevotsDR (2013) Epidemiology of nontuberculous mycobacterial infections and associated chronic macrolide use among persons with cystic fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 188: 807–812.23927602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-AlZeer1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>46 Al-ZeerMA, Al-YounesHM, LausterD, Abu LubadM, MeyerTF (2013) Autophagy restricts Chlamydia trachomatis growth in human macrophages via IFNG-inducible guanylate binding proteins. Autophagy 9: 50–62.23086406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Matsuzawa1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>47 MatsuzawaT, KimBH, ShenoyAR, KamitaniS, MiyakeM, et al (2012) IFN-gamma elicits macrophage autophagy via the p38 MAPK signaling pathway. J Immunol 189: 813–818.22675202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Moser1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>48 MoserC, KjaergaardS, PresslerT, KharazmiA, KochC, et al (2000) The immune response to chronic Pseudomonas aeruginosa lung infection in cystic fibrosis patients is predominantly of the Th2 type. APMIS 108: 329–335.10937769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Komatsu1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>49 KomatsuM, KageyamaS, IchimuraY (2012) p62/SQSTM1/A170: physiology and pathology. Pharmacol Res 66: 457–462.22841931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-McKeon1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>50 McKeonS, McCleanS, CallaghanM (2010) Macrophage responses to CF pathogens: JNK MAP kinase signaling by Burkholderia cepacia complex lipopolysaccharide. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol 60: 36–43.20602636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Gillette1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>51 GilletteDD, ShahPA, CremerT, GavrilinMA, BeseckerBY, et al (2013) Analysis of human bronchial epithelial cell proinflammatory response to Burkholderia cenocepacia infection: inability to secrete il-1beta. J Biol Chem 288: 3691–3695.23269671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Gavrilin1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>52 GavrilinMA, AbdelazizDH, MostafaM, AbdulrahmanBA, GrandhiJ, et al (2012) Activation of the Pyrin Inflammasome by Intracellular Burkholderia cenocepacia. J Immunol 188: 3469–3477.22368275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Jain1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>53 JainMV, PaczullaAM, KlonischT, DimgbaFN, RaoSB, et al (2013) Interconnections between apoptotic, autophagic and necrotic pathways: implications for cancer therapy development. J Cell Mol Med 17: 12–29.23301705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-VandeWeertvanLeeuwen1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>54 Van de Weert-van LeeuwenPB, Van MeegenMA, SpeirsJJ, PalsDJ, RooijakkersSH, et al (2013) Optimal complement-mediated phagocytosis of Pseudomonas aeruginosa by monocytes is cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator-dependent. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol 49: 463–470.23617438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Sajjan1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>55 SajjanSU, CarmodyLA, GonzalezCF, LiPumaJJ (2008) A type IV secretion system contributes to intracellular survival and replication of Burkholderia cenocepacia. Infect Immun 76: 5447–5455.18824538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Junkins1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>56 JunkinsRD, ShenA, RosenK, McCormickC, LinTJ (2013) Autophagy enhances bacterial clearance during P. aeruginosa lung infection. PLoS One 8: e72263.24015228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Farrar1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>57 FarrarMA, SchreiberRD (1993) The molecular cell biology of interferon-gamma and its receptor. Annu Rev Immunol 11: 571–611.8476573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Condos1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>58 CondosR, HullFP, SchlugerNW, RomWN, SmaldoneGC (2004) Regional deposition of aerosolized interferon-gamma in pulmonary tuberculosis. Chest 125: 2146–2155.15189935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Diaz1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>59 DiazKT, SkariaS, HarrisK, SolomitaM, LauS, et al (2012) Delivery and safety of inhaled interferon-gamma in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. J Aerosol Med Pulm Drug Deliv 25: 79–87.22360317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Johansen1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>60 JohansenHK, HougenHP, RygaardJ, HoibyN (1996) Interferon-gamma (IFN-gamma) treatment decreases the inflammatory response in chronic Pseudomonas aeruginosa pneumonia in rats. Clin Exp Immunol 103: 212–218.8565302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Marciano1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>61 MarcianoBE, WesleyR, De CarloES, AndersonVL, BarnhartLA, et al (2004) Long-term interferon-gamma therapy for patients with chronic granulomatous disease. Clin Infect Dis 39: 692–699.15356785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Shi1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>62 ShiCS, ShenderovK, HuangNN, KabatJ, Abu-AsabM, et al (2012) Activation of autophagy by inflammatory signals limits IL-1beta production by targeting ubiquitinated inflammasomes for destruction. Nat Immunol 13: 255–263.22286270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Mitchell1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>63 MitchellAJ, YauB, McQuillanJA, BallHJ, TooLK, et al (2012) Inflammasome-dependent IFN-gamma drives pathogenesis in Streptococcus pneumoniae meningitis. J Immunol 189: 4970–4980.23071286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Lamothe1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>64 LamotheJ, ValvanoMA (2008) Burkholderia cenocepacia-induced delay of acidification and phagolysosomal fusion in cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR)-defective macrophages. Microbiology 154: 3825–3834.19047750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Subramoni1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>65 SubramoniS, SokolPA (2012) Quorum sensing systems influence Burkholderia cenocepacia virulence. Future Microbiol 7: 1373–1387.23231487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-Aubert1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>66 AubertDF, O’GradyEP, HamadMA, SokolPA, ValvanoMA (2013) The Burkholderia cenocepacia sensor kinase hybrid AtsR is a global regulator modulating quorum-sensing signalling. Environ Microbiol 15: 372–385.22830644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0096681-OGrady1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>67 O’GradyEP, ViteriDF, SokolPA (2012) A unique regulator contributes to quorum sensing and virulence in Burkholderia cenocepacia. PLoS One 7: e37611.22624054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
