<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4349710</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-1514-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The humanistic, economic and societal burden of Herpes Zoster in Europe: a critical review </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gater</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><address><email>adam.gater@adelphivalues.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uhart</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name><address><email>muhart@spmsd.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCool</surname><given-names>Rachael</given-names></name><address><email>rachael.mccool@adelphivalues.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Préaud</surname><given-names>Emmanuelle</given-names></name><address><email>epreaud@spmsd.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Adelphi Values, Adelphi Mill, Grimshaw Lane, Bollington, Cheshire SK10 5JB UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Sanofi Pasteur MSD, 162 avenue Jean Jaurès, Lyon, France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>193</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Gater et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Herpes zoster (HZ) or “shingles” is common in persons aged 50 years or over. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>HZ is characterised by a painful dermatological rash which typically resolves in approximately one month. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Persistent pain for months or years after rash onset, however, is a common complication of HZ; referred to as post-herpetic neuralgia (PHN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Both HZ and PHN have a significant impact on patients’ lives, with considerable implications for healthcare systems and wider society. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present review is to provide comprehensive documentation and critical appraisal of published data concerning the humanistic, economic and societal burden of HZ in Europe. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Systematic literature searches were conducted in Medline, EMBASE, PsycINFO, EconLit, HEED and CRD databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Searches were conducted in July 2014 and restricted to articles published in the past 20 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Articles were selected for full review by two independent researchers in accordance with predefined eligibility criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>From a review of 1619 abstracts, 53 eligible articles, were identified which reported data concerning healthcare resource use (n = 38), direct costs (n = 20), indirect costs (n = 16), total costs (n = 10) and impact on health-related quality of life (HRQoL) (n = 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Findings highlight that PHN is associated with greater impairments in HRQoL and higher costs of management than HZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>For both HZ and PHN, pain severity is a significant predictor of impact on individuals, healthcare systems and society. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>While the incidence of HZ and PHN increase with age, age does not appear to be a key driver of overall costs for HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Specifically, while direct costs (e.g. GP, specialists, medications, hospitalisations) tend to be higher for older patients, indirect costs (e.g. work time missed) are higher for younger patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Available evidence highlights that HZ and PHN result in significant humanistic and economic burden for patients, healthcare systems and wider societies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>A tendency to focus upon healthcare resource use and the direct costs of management at the expense of other impacts (e.g. informal caregivers and formal social care) may result in an underestimation of the true burden of HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Herpes zoster (HZ), also known as shingles, is caused by the reactivation of the varicella zoster virus (VZV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Primary infection with VZV usually occurs during childhood, manifesting as chickenpox, after which the virus lies dormant [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The great majority (95%) [2] of the population hosts VZV and approximately one in four persons will develop HZ in their lifetime through reactivation, leading to an estimated 1.7 million episodes in Europe annually [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>VZV reactivation is primarily related to an age-related decline in VZV-specific immunity; it is well documented that the incidence of HZ increases with age, with the majority of cases occurring in patients over 50 years of age [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>HZ is characterized by a painful dermatomal rash, which most commonly presents on the trunk and lumbar regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>HZ, however, may present along any nerve including the ophthalmic division of the trigeminal nerve where it can affect the eye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Herpes Zoster Ophthalmicus (HZO) occurs in 10-20% of all HZ cases and in some cases can lead to ocular complications [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The dermatological rash and pain associated with HZ typically resolves within one month of presentation [4]; however, long-term complications can arise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Post-herpetic neuralgia (PHN) is the most common and debilitating complication of HZ, occurring in approximately 10-20% of all sufferers [6-8] and as many as 50% of those aged 85 years and over [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>PHN is a neuropathic syndrome manifesting as on-going pain along the nerves in the area of the prior HZ rash and typically involves one or more of the following: spontaneous aching or burning; paroxysmal shooting pains; allodynia, and hyperalgesia [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>There is no consensus regarding the definition of PHN; however, PHN is often defined as pain persisting for 90 days from HZ rash onset [4,6,10,11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>While HZ is an acute experience that typically resolves within one month, in the majority of sufferers, PHN persists for at least 6 months with some patients experiencing PHN for years [12-15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>As expected given the relationship to HZ, the incidence of PHN increases markedly with age [16-18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The incidence of PHN is also linked to the severity of pain experienced during the prior HZ episode (among other predictors such as the severity of the dermatomal rash and prodromal symptoms) [19], with those patients experiencing the highest levels of pain during HZ presentation being most at risk of developing PHN [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As conditions primarily affecting older persons, many patients with HZ and PHN may already experience significant deficits in health status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Findings from a number of articles indicate that the pain and resulting discomfort associated with HZ and PHN can have a substantial negative and widespread impact on patients’ health-related quality of life (HRQoL) and patients’ ability to engage in activities of daily living [7,20-25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In addition to the burden encountered by the individual with HZ, the condition is also associated with considerable economic burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For example, considerable costs to healthcare systems [26-31] arise from the care provision for HZ and PHN patients, including visits to primary care (general practitioner) and outpatient secondary/tertiary care (specialist pain clinics and ophthalmologists), inpatient visits (hospitalisations) and prescription costs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, HZ and PHN are also associated with significant indirect costs, primarily in terms of loss of productivity for younger patients [7,21,23,24,28,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Finally, as conditions occurring in retired and older patients, HZ and PHN can also have significant consequences for the caregivers of patients including partners, relatives, and friends of people with the conditions [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Such details, however, may often go unreported and are not often communicated in the research literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Evidence for the efficacy of a VZV vaccine in the prevention of HZ and PHN episodes and attenuation of the severity of HZ and PHN episodes and associated impact has been documented in recent years [11,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In order to understand the value of preventative strategies, a complete understanding of the impact of HZ and PHN is required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>While a significant body of literature has sought to determine the impact of HZ and PHN on patients, healthcare systems and wider society within EU countries, to date, no comprehensive review of these studies has been conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The aim of this review, therefore, is to provide a comprehensive and holistic overview of the humanistic, economic and societal burden of HZ and PHN in Europe as reported within the published peer-reviewed literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Published peer-reviewed articles were identified via systematic searches conducted in the following biomedical and economic databases: EMBASE, Medline, PsycINFO, EconLit, Health Economic Evaluations Database (HEED) and the Centre for Reviews and Dissemination databases at the University of York. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Searches and reviews were conducted in accordance with the Cochrane systematic review guidelines [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A range of disease-related, economic, societal and HRQoL-related keywords was utilized to capture the humanistic, economic and societal burden of HZ and PHN (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Searches were conducted in July 2014 and were restricted to articles published in the last 20 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Although data relating to the EU was the primary focus of this review, no limits regarding study country or article language were implemented during the search stage (so to not exclude potentially relevant articles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Instead, articles focused on the EU were prioritized as part of the article selection process.Table 1Search terms  Databases searched  Disease search terms  Economic, humanistic and societal burden search terms  • Medline “Herpes Zoster” OR “Shingles” OR “Post-herpetic Neuralgia” OR “Post herpetic Neuralgia” OR “Postherpetic Neuralgia” OR “PHN”“Burden” OR “Humanistic” OR “quality of life” OR “QOL” OR “HRQOL” OR “cost” OR “economic” OR “resource” OR “society” OR “societal” OR “family” OR “relatives” OR “Caregiver” OR “care$” OR “activities of daily living” OR “ADLS” OR “daily activities” OR “cost of illness” OR “autonomy” OR “hospitalisation” OR “hospitalization” • Embase  • PscyINFO  • EconLit.  • Health Economic Evaluations Database (HEED)  • Centre for Reviews and Dissemination databases:     - Database of Abstracts of Reviews of Effects (DARE),     - Health Technology Assessment (HTA)     - NHS Economic Evaluation Database (NHS EED)  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In accordance with Cochrane review guidelines [35], all abstracts were reviewed by two researchers independently according to formal inclusion/exclusion criteria (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>For inclusion in the review, abstracts were required present information specific to adult patients in the EU and to contain information pertaining to the key search terms (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In instances were aforementioned details were not clear from the abstract, full text articles were obtained to confirm whether the article should be included/excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Real world data, observational studies, effectiveness studies, qualitative studies, economic evaluations and cost studies were all considered relevant for review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The final list of abstracts and articles for full in-depth review was agreed following consensus between the authors.Table 2 Study Inclusion/exclusion criteria  Inclusion criteria  Exclusion criteria  Country setting  Present data from a country in the EU or EU in general  Only present data from a non-EU country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>No data specific to the EU.  Population  Adults with HZ or PHN  Children  Focus mainly on chicken pox  Immunodepressed patients only (e.g. HIV patients)  Studies that contain information on key search terms (inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>QoL, burden, productivity)  Studies that do NOT contain information on key search terms  Study design  Real world data, observational studies, effectiveness, qualitative research and cost studies  Clinical trials of efficacy and safety of treatments presenting QoL data as secondary endpoint only  Clinical trials of Zostavax  Focus mainly on epidemiological evidence (e.g. incidence, prevalence etc.)  Publication type  For conference abstracts, exclusion if manuscript corresponding to this abstract and presenting equivalent information is already published  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Data extraction tables were developed to accurately record information from the articles chosen for review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Of importance was information related to the study aims, design and outcomes of interest, sample characteristics, country of study, resource use data, cost data (direct and indirect) and any patient-reported impacts of HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>All referenced costs are provided in Euros and have been adjusted to the same price year (2015) based on annual average rate of change (%) in the Harmonised Index of Consumer Prices [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Search results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 provides an overview of the article selection process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A total of 1619 titles and abstracts were reviewed against the inclusion/exclusion criteria, resulting in 78 EU based articles for full text review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>A further 25 articles were excluded following full text review, leaving a total of 53 studies to be included in this review.Figure 1 Overview of study selection for review.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Overview of selected articles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A summary of the 53 articles selected for inclusion in the review (including study countries, population, data presented) is provided in Table 3.Table 3 Overview of included studies  Author and year  Country perspective  Population  Healthcare utilisation  Economic data  HRQoL  HZ  HZ and PHN  PHN1  PHN3  PHN Other/Undefined  Direct costs  Indirect costs  Total costs Annemans et al. (2010) [26]Belgium✓X✓✓X✓✓✓✓XBayas et al. (2011) [37]Spain CataloniaX✓XXX✓✓XXXBerrut, G. and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Baptiste (2013) [38]France✓XXXX✓XXXXBlein, C., et al. (2013) [39]France✓XXXX✓XXXXBilcke et al. (2012) [40]BelgiumX✓X✓X✓✓✓XXBouhassira et al. (2012) [15]France✓✓X✓XXXXX✓Bresse, X., et al. (2013) [41]France✓XX✓X✓XXXXBricout, H., et al. (2013) [42]Italy✓XXXXXX✓X✓Bricout, H., et al. (2013) [42]Italy✓XX✓X✓XXX✓Brisson et al. (2003) [43]England &amp; WalesX✓XX✓✓✓✓✓XCastro-Lopes, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>M., et al. (2013) [44]PortugalXXXX✓✓XXX✓Cebrian-Cuenca et al. (2011) [27]Spain, Valencia✓X✓✓X✓✓✓✓XChidiac et al. (2001) [21]France✓✓XX✓✓XXX✓De Juanes et al. (2011) [45]Spain MadridX✓XX✓✓✓XXXDi Legami et al. (2007) [46]Italy – Piemonte✓XXX✓✓✓XXXEdmunds et al. (2001) [47]England and WalesX✓✓XX✓✓XXXFranco, E., et al. (2013) [48]Italy✓XX✓X✓XXX✓Garcia-Doval et al. (2010) [49]Spain✓XXX✓✓XXXXGater, A., et al. (2014) [50]UK✓XXXX✓XXX✓Gauthier et al. (2009) [28]UK✓X✓✓X✓✓XX✓Gialloreti et al. (2010) [29]Italy✓X✓✓X✓✓✓✓XGil et al. (2004) [51]Spain✓XXXX✓✓XXXGil et al. (2009) [52]Spain✓XXXX✓✓XXXGil-Prieto et al. (2011) [53]Spain✓XXXX✓✓XXXGil-Prieto, R., et al. (2014) [54]Spain✓XXXX✓XXXXGonzalez et al. (2010) [55]France✓XXXX✓XXXXLionis et al. (2011) [56]Greece✓X✓XXXXXX✓Loncar, Z., et al. (2013) [57]Croatia✓XXXX✓XXX✓Lukas et al. (2012) [58]Germany, Spain, Portugal, the Netherlands, Belgium, Sweden and Switzerland✓✓X✓XXX✓X✓Mesquita, M. and F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Froes (2013) [59]Portugal✓XXXX✓XXXXMick et al. (2010) [30]FranceX✓X✓X✓✓✓✓XMoore et al. (2010) [60]UKX✓✓✓XXX✓XXMorant-Talamante, N., et al. (2013) [61]Spain✓XXXX✓XXXXMordarski et al. (2009) [62]PolandXXXX✓XXXX✓Nilsson, J., et al. (2013) [63]SwedenX✓XXXXX✓✓XPierik et al. (2012) [64]Holland/the Netherlands✓XXXX✓XXXXRabaud, C., et al. (2013) [65]France✓X✓✓X✓XXX✓Rehm et al. (2010) [66]14 European countries (countries not specified)XX✓XXXXXX✓Schiffner-Rohe et al. (2011) [67]Germany✓X✓XX✓✓X✓XScott et al. (2003) [68]UK✓XX✓XXXXX✓Scott et al. (2006) [7]UKX✓X✓XXX✓✓✓Serpell, M., et al. (2014) [14]UKXXX✓X✓XXX✓Sicras-Mainar et al. (2012) [69]Spain✓✓XX✓✓✓✓✓XSouliotis, K., et al. (2013) [70]GreeceX✓XXXX✓✓XXStudahl, M., et al. (2013) [71]Sweden✓XXXX✓XXXXSzucs (2011) [72]Switzerland✓XX✓✓X✓✓✓XUltsch et al. (2011) [73]Germany✓XX✓X✓XXXXUltsch et al. (2012) [31]Germany✓XX✓X✓✓✓✓XVan Hoek et al. (2009) [74]England and Wales✓XX✓X✓✓XXXVan Seventer et al. (2006) [25]France, Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Spain, UKXXX✓X✓XXX✓Volpi et al. (2007) [75]Italy✓XXXXXXXX✓Volpi et al. (2008) [76]Italy✓✓X✓✓XXXX✓Weinke et al. (2010) [77]Germany✓XX✓XXX✓X✓✓ and x indicate the presence/absence of evidence, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The references selected for review presented data from 14 European countries with the majority (n = 39, 73.6%) of articles providing data from the ‘Big 5’ EU countries (UK; Spain; France; Germany &amp; Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Of the included references, 39 reported data specifically attributed to HZ patients and 35 reported data specifically attributed to PHN patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Data attributed to a combined HZ and PHN population was included in 15 references. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The references eligible for inclusion in the study were all published between 2000 and 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Data presented in reviewed references was categorized as follows: 1) Healthcare utilisation in terms of rates of medical visits, hospitalisations and medication prescribed, 2) Direct costs corresponding to the management of HZ/PHN, 3) Indirect costs, 4) Total costs and 5) Health related quality of life and humanistic burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Of note, some references contained data pertaining to multiple categories. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Healthcare utilisation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Information regarding healthcare resource was included in 38 of the identified references (as summarized in Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Data indicated that HZ and PHN are associated with considerable healthcare utilisation, with increased resource use associated with increasing age and the presence of PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Data concerning healthcare utilisation was presented in terms of rates of medical visits (including GP and specialist visits), hospitalisations (including duration of stay), use of medications and additional diagnostic/laboratory procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Medical visits </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The majority of patients presenting with HZ will consult their GP at least once [43,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Reflecting the chronic nature of PHN, higher rates of medical visits (GP and specialist visits) have been reported in PHN patients compared to HZ patients [14,21,27,29,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>For example, reports from a study in Italy indicated that patients over the age of 50 with HZ made approximately 1.9 visits to their GP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the reported number of visits among patients with PHN was 11.9 and 12.0 (PHN-1 month and PHN 3-months definitions, respectively) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The proportion of patients referred to specialists (74% PHN versus 18% HZ) and the number of specialist visits per case (3.5 and 3.9 for PHN-1 month and PHN 3-months vs 0.2 for HZ) were also higher for PHN patients compared to HZ patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>More frequent specialist visits have also been reported among patients with HZO compared to those with HZ [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The average annual incidence of herpes zoster GP-consultations has been reported to increase with age from 32.8/10,000 among those aged &lt;60 years, to 93.1 and 113.2/10,000 among those aged 60–64 years and ≥65 years respectively [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the average number of specialist visits was also higher in patients over the age of 50 compared to those over the age of 14 [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Hospitalisations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The rates of hospitalisations due to HZ and/or PHN reported in the literature (generally derived from national or insurance databases of hospital admissions) suggest that increased rates of hospitalisation are also associated with increasing age [55,71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>More frequent hospitalisations have also been observed among patients with PHN when compared to patients with HZ across studies in Italy [29], Belgium [40], France [55], Germany [73], Spain [37,45,49,51,52,61]. and Portugal [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>There are also reports of a greater rate of hospitalisations among female HZ patients compared to male HZ patients at across all age groups [71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The average length of inpatient stay for PHN (10.2 ± 8.6 days) has been reported to be higher than those associated with HZ (7.8 ± 5.4 days) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The average duration of stay in hospital among HZ patients also appears to be influenced by age [47,74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>For example, analysis of Hospital Episode Statistics (2002–2005) from England indicates the average length of stay among HZ/PHN patients aged 60–64 is 9.3 days whereas those aged 85–90 is 22.3 days [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Comparisons between HZ and HZO patients over 50 years of age also indicate longer hospital stays in patients with HZO (9.8 vs 7.8 days) [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Medication use </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>It is reported that up to 100% of PHN patients and 83.2% of patients with HZ receive medication for their condition across all ages [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Polypharmacy is common among HZ patients with HZ patients reported to be taking at least 4 different medications on average and PHN patients reported to be taking 5 medications [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This could potentially have wider implications as polypharmacy is known to be a major cause of drug interactions and issues with treatment adherence and safety [78]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The types of medication used has been reported to vary depending on the population being considered (HZ or PHN) [14,21,29,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Indeed, current treatment of HZ aims to relieve pain, to limit the spread and duration of the dermatomal lesions and (when started within 72 hours of rash onset) to prevent or alleviate complications associated with HZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>By contrast, for PHN, the focus of medications is to alleviate pain [79,80]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The amount of available information regarding medication use in EU countries was somewhat limited; however available evidence from the literature suggests that, despite the availability of European Guidelines for the management of HZ [80,81], medication prescribing practices (for the treatment of PHN in particular) are not consistent across countries [14,21,25,29,44,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>An observational study of PHN patients over the age of 50 conducted in France, Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Spain and the UK (n = 84), for example, reported that neuropathic pain medications (89%), analgesics (64%) and anticonvulsants (52%) were most commonly prescribed for the treatment of PHN [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, a study conducted in the UK reported that antidepressants were most commonly prescribed for PHN followed by level 1 and 2 analgesics (59.2%, 55.3% and 50% respectively) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Similarly, studies in Italy and Portugal have reported that anticonvulsants to be the most commonly prescribed treatment for PHN, followed by opioid analgesics [29,44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Where reported, medication usage for the treatment of HZ was consistent across studies; with antivirals (typically taken for 7 days) the most commonly prescribed treatment [14,21,29,42,50,71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Of note, despite the widespread use of pharmacological therapies for the management of HZ and PHN, reports from patients indicate dissatisfaction with treatments, particularly in regards to perceived efficacy [14,50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Diagnostic/laboratory procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Details of additional investigations among patients with HZ and PHN were reported from studies in France, Italy, Spain and the UK [14,21,27,29,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Additional investigations reported included blood and urine tests, assessments of inflammation (e.g. erythrocyte sedimentation rate, C-reactive protein level), ophthalmological/ontological examinations, radiology, X-ray, electrocardiograms and ultrasound. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Further diagnostic or laboratory examinations were reported in 28.0% of incident cases of HZ among an Italian sample of immunocompetent individuals, with the mean number of procedures and examinations reported to be 2.6 per case [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>By comparison, rates of additional investigations reported in France, Spain and the UK were lower [14,21,27,50], with evidence suggesting that rates of additional investigations were higher in those with PHN (10–12.5% compared to HZ (4.4-9%) [14,21,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Additional investigations are also more likely among those patients with HZO compared to HZ [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Direct costs of management </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Direct costs of the management of HZ and PHN patients were reported in 20 studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The reviewed articles presented data from Spain [27,37,45,51-53,69], the UK [7,28,43,47,74], France [30], Italy [29,46], Germany [31,67], Belgium [26,40], Greece [70] and Switzerland [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Outpatient costs (including medical visits, diagnostic tests and medications), hospitalization and inpatient costs were identified in the literature as key contributors to the overall cost burden of HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Outpatient costs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Studies in Belgium [26], Germany [31,67], Italy [29] and the UK [28] have consistently reported higher outpatient management costs (including medical visits, diagnostic tests and medications) among patients who go on to develop PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>For example, mean direct costs of outpatient management have been reported as €107.98 per HZ episode and €406.04 and €485.51 per PHN episode (1- and 3-month definition respectively) [28]a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In addition, costs for outpatient management of HZ and PHN have been reported to increase markedly with pain severity [26,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>For example, outpatient costs among HZ patients ranging from €85.89 (no pain) to €178.32 (severe pain) per case have been reported in the UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Reported differences are more pronounced among PHN patients with costs per case ranging from €237.90/284.80 (PHN1/PHN3) among patients with mild pain to €741.91/878.88 (PHN1/PHN3) among patients with severe pain [28]a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Key differences in the attribution of outpatient costs for HZ and PHN have been reported for Italy; for patients that did not develop PHN, the majority of the cost of management has been reported to be due to the cost of medication (83%) whereas for patients that develop PHN a greater proportion of cost was attributed to diagnostic and investigative procedures [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Other studies, however, indicate costs of diagnostic procedures to be the smallest contributor to outpatient costs among patients with HZ and PHN (PHN-1 and PHN-3) [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>While the average cost of outpatient management per case is higher for patients with PHN than for patients with HZ, when considering overall burden of disease at a country level, the overall cost of disease is higher for HZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This is primarily a result of the higher incidence rates of HZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>These differences were highlighted by one study which investigated the annual cost of HZ and PHN to healthcare providers located in England and Wales [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Based on an estimated 260,995 episodes of HZ occurring annually, with 14% of cases developing PHN, an estimated €76.39 milliona is spent on the management of HZ (including PHN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Of this, €52.32 million was attributable to HZ (€22.47 m due to hospitalisation, €19.26 m due to prescription medications and €9.63 m due to GP consultations) and €24.07 million to PHN1 (cost breakdown not provided). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Similar findings are reported in Germany where statutory health insurance bills have been estimated at €115.5 m; €93.5 m attributed to HZ treatment and €22 m attributed to treatment of PHN [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Hospitalisation and inpatient costs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Hospitalisation costs contribute significantly to the overall direct cost of managing HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Rates of hospitalisation and duration of stay were found to be higher for PHN than for HZ, and to increase with increasing age, translating into higher inpatient costs for patients that develop PHN (Table 4) [18,24,33,70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Note that data on hospitalisations and inpatient costs was primarily extracted from a range of national and insurance databases in each country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>No studies identified provided a breakdown of the cost elements that are included in a ‘hospital stay’.Table 4 Mean cost per hospitalised case of HZ/PHN, by country  Country  HZ/PHN  HZ (without PHN)  PHN Belgium [40]-€5,982 (€798-31,689)-(all ages)France [41]-€2,774.28 (50+years)€3,731.09 (50+years)Germany [31]-€4,189.74 (50+years)€4,279.68 (50+years)€3,282.64 (all ages)€4,112.03 (all ages)Italy [29]-€3,188.16 ± €1,614.99 (50+years)€3,451.38 ± €3,248.43 (50+years)Spain [37,45,52,53]€3,366.4 -4,505.6€5,019.84 (aged 40–49)€5,108.04 (aged 50–59)(all ages)€4,495.68 – 5,139.54 (aged 50–59)€4,732.56 (aged 60–69)€4,210.92 – 4,782.96 (aged 60–69)€4,478.04 (70+)€4,062.24 – 4,556.16 (aged 70+) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Indirect costs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Indirect costs considered in the EU literature were mainly related to costs associated with sick leave (absenteeism). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Seventeen articles reported data on sick leave due to HZ and PHN and the costs that this incurs [7,26,27,29-31,40,42,58,60,63,69,70,72,73,77,82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Absenteeism due to HZ and PHN is a significant cost driver, with increased costs found to be associated with the presence of PHN [29,31,72] and increased levels of pain experienced [26,72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Up to 65% of employed patients report work absence due to their disease [77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Costs associated with absenteeism varied across EU countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In France, these costs accounted for up to 30% of the costs of management of HZ from the societal perspective and up to 10% of the costs of management for PHN in patients aged 50 years and over [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In Germany, the mean annual cost of sick leave due to HZ was €1,504 per patient (increasing to €1,826 for patients over the age of 50), with patients missing an average of 12.5 days from work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The costs associated with PHN were found to be higher at €7,183 (€7.590 for patients over 50) with patients missing an average of 2 months from work [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The average costs associated with absenteeism were found to be lower in Italy and Switzerland than those reported for Germany [29,72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Average costs for patients over the age of 50 in Italy were €684 per case of HZ and €978 per case of PHN [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In Switzerland, reported costs of sick leave per case for patients with varying levels of pain were as follows: mild pain (HZ €335; PHN 381), moderate pain (HZ €421; PHN €1,018), severe pain (HZ €1,837; PHN €2,443)b [72]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In Spain, the findings from an observational study [27] of 130 HZ patients aged 19–45 (median age of 63.5 yrs) who were observed for 1 year suggest that an average of 4.3 hours of work were missed per patient at a cost of €52.98. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This study also found that a total of 6 work hours were lost by carers across the study sample of 130, resulting in a total loss of €86.31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The cost and time implications of time taken off work by carers were also considered in two further studies that were conducted in Belgium and the UK respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The study conducted in Belgium found that 14/184 patients reported that someone else could not go to work due to their illness for between 0.5-10days, resulting in an average loss of €52 per case due to carer absenteeism [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>For the study conducted in the UK, among 70 HZ patients, a total of 52 work days were lost by their carers [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>However as the majority of the reviewed studies usually do not report the cost burden associated with time lost by carers this cost is likely to be underestimated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Total costs of management </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>A total of 10 studies reported the total cost per case of HZ and/or PHN in EU countries, taking into account both direct costs (including medical visits, medications and hospitalisations) and indirect costs (including time missed from work). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Table 5 presents the average cost per case in each country based on the data that was detailed in the reviewed literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Overall, higher costs were consistently associated with the presence of PHN and increased levels of pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Of note, whilst HZ and PHN are associated with higher costs to healthcare providers in elderly populations, costs to society in terms of time missed for work tends to be lower, so the total costs overall are similar across age groups [60].Table 5 Mean total cost of management per HZ or PHN case  Country  Population age  Cost per case  HZ  PHN1*  PHN3^ Belgium [26]Aged ≥50€118 (no pain)€156.94 (mild pain)€329.22 (mild pain)€1,150.50 (severe pain)€1,085.60 (severe pain)€2,037.86 (severe pain)France [30]Aged ≥50€419.87 (271–586)€672.76 (451–968)-Germany [31]Aged ≥50€388.30 (354–425)-€1,427.80 (1,002-1,917)Germany [67]Aged ≥50€729.57€ 2,167.89Italy [29]Aged ≥50€888.06-€1,66.65Spain [27]Aged &gt;14 Overall: €446.04 (SD 508.58)€647.82 (SD 684.4)€968.78 (SD 803.58) 50-59: €282.06 (SD 273.15) 60-69:€510.52 (SD 512.73) &gt;70: €422.91 (SD 388.66)Spain [69]Aged &gt;30€460.95€1,956.15-Sweden [63]All ages€902.88 (HZ and PHN)Switzerland [72]Aged ≥50€394.46 (no pain)-€381.15 (no pain)€1,835.57 (severe pain)€2,442.99 (severe pain)UK [7]Not specified€793.60 (31–6,394)--(all ages) Aged +65: €788.48*PHN defined as pain persisting for one month following resolution of HZ rash.^PHN defined as pain persisting for three months following resolution of HZ rash. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The total annual cost (direct and indirect costs) of HZ and PHN on a country level basis was only available for the UK [43], France [30], Germany [31], Italy [29] and Sweden [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Two studies presented data separately for the cost of HZ and PHN and patients over the age of 50 [29,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Further details are provided in Figure 2.Figure 2 Estimated total cost burden associated with HZ and PHN considering outpatient, hospitalisation and indirect costs.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Humanistic burden and impact on quality of life </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>A total of 21 EU studies [7,14,15,21,25,28,42,44,48,50,56-58,62,65,66,68,75-77] reported data on the humanistic burden associated with HZ and PHN, with the significant negative impact of HZ and PHN on patients’ HRQOL consistently reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Of note, pain experienced due to the disease was found to interfere with many aspects of patient’s daily life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Greater interference was associated with increased levels of pain [25,83] and the presence of PHN was associated with a greater impact on most domains of HRQoL [14,50,58,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Patients also reported consequences for their family and social circle when suffering from HZ or PHN [58,77,84]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Pain and interference with daily activities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Reports within the reviewed literature indicate that patients with HZ and PHN experience moderate-severe pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Ratings of average and worst pain reported in the literature are higher among PHN patients compared to HZ patients [14,41,50,58,77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>A number of the reviewed articles provided data from the Zoster Brief Pain Inventory (ZBPI) and the Modified Brief Pain Short Form (mBPI-SF)c – derivative measures of the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) which require patients to rate the level of interference they experience on a scale of 0–10 (‘does not interfere’ – ‘completely interferes’), across seven health status domain; general activity, mood, walking ability, normal work, social relations, sleep and enjoyment of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Table 6 presents the mean scores for patients with HZ and PHN from five studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In general, reports of pain interference on all seven health status domains were greater among patients experiencing PHN compared to patients with HZ [14,50,58,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>HZ and PHN patients reported sleep to be the aspect of their daily lives most affected by pain (4.5-4.9 and 6.3-6.5 mean scores respectively), while walking ability was the least affected in HZ patients (1.7-4.0 mean score) and enjoyment of life was least affected in PHN patients (3.8-5.2 mean score) [14,15,50,58,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Increased levels of pain are reported to be associated with increased levels of interference [25,83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Levels of pain interference, however, do not appear to be associated with age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Lukas et al. [58] presented pain interference data separately for six European countries included in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>While differences in the level of interference observed varied from country to country, the domains of health status most affected was largely consistent.Table 6 Level of pain interference across seven health state domains as assessed by the ZBPI (or similar instrument)  Health state domains  HZ (mean scores)  PHN (mean scores)  General activity 3.8-4.43.1-5.7 Mood 3.4-4.53.4-5.9 Walking ability 1.7-4.01.7-5.8 Normal work 3.3-4.42.9-6.1 Social relations 2.1-3.52.1-5.4 Sleep 4.5-4.96.3-6.5 Enjoyment of life 3.6-4.03.8-5.2Data from Bouhassira 2012 [15], Gater 2014 [50], Lukas 2012 [58], Serpell 2014 [14], Weinke 2010 [77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Impact on general health-related quality of life </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>A number of studies have included generic HRQoL measures such as the SF-12 [15,83], SF-36 [14,21,50], EQ-5D [7,14,25,50] and Short Italian Questionnaire (SIQ) [75,76] to assess HRQoL in HZ and PHN patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Generally, HRQoL has found to be inversely associated with levels of reported pain [14,25,50,83] and the poorest HRQoL has been observed for patients with PHN [14,21,50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Consideration of HRQoL scores from normative populations indicates an inverse relationship between age and HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>As a condition mainly inflicting the elderly, therefore, HRQoL is already considerably compromised in HZ and PHN patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, recent research indicates that both HZ and PHN patients demonstrate statistically significant and clinically relevant deficits in HRQoL when scores for validated measures of HRQoL (e.g. SF-36 and EQ-5D) among these populations are compared to those from aged-matched normative samples (Figures 3 and 4) [14,50].Figure 3 Comparison of SF-36 domain and component scores for HZ patients compared to age-matched norms [ 50 ]. No *s p≥0.05, *p&lt;0.05; **p&gt;0.01; ***p &lt;0.001. † = clinically meaningful PF=Physical functioning, R-P=Role-physical, BP=Bodily pain, GH=General health, V=Vitality, SF=Social functioning, R-E=Role-emotional, MH=Mental health, PCS=Physical component summary, MCS=Mental component summary. Note: Data collected on initial presentation of HZ to healthcare professional and then again 7-14 days later (follow-up).Figure 4 Comparison of SF-36 domain and component scores for PHN patients compared to age-matched norms [ 14 ]. No *s p≥0.05, *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01; ***p &lt;0.001. † = clinically meaningful PF=Physical functioning, R-P=Role-physical, BP=Bodily pain, GH=General health, V=Vitality, SF=Social functioning, R-E=Role-emotional, MH=Mental health, PCS=Physical component summary, MCS=Mental component summary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Impact on mood and mental well-being </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Data presented across studies demonstrates that patients experience a negative impact on their mood and mental well-being, with patients reporting stress, anxiety and depressive symptoms [14,15,50,56,58,76,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Across studies, a range of instruments have been used to assess the impact of HZ and PHN on mood, including the Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale (HADS) [7,15], 10,47 Short Italian Questionnaire (SIQ) [75,76], the Short Anxiety Screening Test (SAST) [56] and bespoke questions [58,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Up to 29% of patients with HZ reported feelings of moderate anxiety or depression, rising to 43% in patients with PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Further, a larger percentage of PHN patients reported extreme anxiety or depression (11% vs. 5%) [58,77], evidencing that mood and mental well-being issues are greater for PHN patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The majority of patients reported experiencing stress some of the time (up to 78% for HZ and 91% for PHN) or most of the time (up to 19% HZ and 41% PHN) [58,77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Impact on family and social relations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Up to 50% of patients with HZ and 81% of patients with PHN reported consequences for their family members and social circle [58,77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Despite the high proportion of patients reporting impacts on their social and family lives, only three studies assessed this issue beyond comparing scores on social dimensions of instruments such as the ZBPI or SF-36 [58,77,84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In one study in particular, one fifth of the respondents felt isolated from their family and friends while suffering from HZ or PHN, with 19% and 27% of patients respectively reporting reduced communication during their illness [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Of note, impacts were not limited to the patient themselves, with findings from a qualitative focus group of patient’s relatives demonstrating that relatives were worried and stressed by the impact of HZ on the patients [84]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The aim of this article was to provide a holistic overview of the published literature concerning the humanistic, economic and societal burden of HZ and PHN in Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The reviewed evidence highlights the significant burden of HZ and PHN for patients, healthcare systems and wider society. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>A number of key findings are noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the direct costs of managing HZ represent a significant proportion of the total costs associated with the disease, with higher costs associated with the presence of PHN and with greater pain severity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Secondly, absenteeism was identified as a significant cost driver (albeit in a small number of studies), with up to 65% of employed patients reporting work absence due to their disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Lastly, research suggests that age, pain severity and the presence of PHN are the key drivers of burden to patients, healthcare systems and society. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In Europe the percentage of people aged 65 years or over is projected to increase from 17.1% (84.6million) in 2008 to 30.0% (151.5 million) in 2060 [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>This demographic shift is likely to have a profound influence on the incidence of HZ and PHN and may contribute to increased concern among European healthcare authorities; particularly if economic crisis and healthcare budget constrains persist in the long term. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Findings from this review indicate that the direct costs of HZ and PHN management are greater for older patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In addition, older adults typically have lower HRQoL than younger adults (deficits which are more pronounced with the presence of HZ and PHN) and may be less able to complete activities of daily living and self-care unassisted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The potential implications of an aging population to wider society, therefore, are wide reaching. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Limitations of the current literature and potential gaps that provide opportunities for future research </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>A number of limitations concerning the currently available body of evidence were identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Inconsistencies in data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>There is currently no consensus regarding the definition of PHN and a lack of consistency in the definition of PHN employed in studies was evident throughout the review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This presents a number of challenges when attempting to accurately understand the burden of HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For example, it has been demonstrated that the prevalence of PHN varies dramatically depending on the point at which HZ-related pain becomes classified as PHN (PHN1 or PHN3) [86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Accurately attributing costs to HZ and PHN and determining the overall cost burden of the conditions, therefore, is difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Similarly, cost per case may vary dramatically depending on the definition employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For this reason, PHN definitions employed in the referenced studies have been highlighted throughout this review and should be considered when interpreting the findings from individual studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, there is a lack of consistency in the use of International Classification of Diseases (ICD) codes used to identify PHN patients in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>As a result, there may be a significant proportion of PHN patients who have not been considered in these studies; consequently decreasing confidence in the accuracy of estimates regarding the burden of PHN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>A lack of consistency in the ways in which data had been collected provides further difficulties in interpreting and comparing the available data across studies, with databases, patient records and patient surveys all utilized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>For example, rates of resource use were derived from a range of sources including: analysis of patient records or an observed sample, patient responses to surveys and national and insurance databases, with each of these methods having their own limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The use of databases is a valuable way of gathering data at a national level, however it assumes information is recorded consistently and accurately across databases and that the database has adequate and representative population coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Analysis of patient records assumes information is accurately recorded by GPs, who have a myriad of demands on their time, and analysis of patient’s responses assumes accuracy in their recall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Of note, the incidence of hospitalisations were largely based on rates derived from databases in different countries, or rates recorded in observed samples, thus inaccuracies may occur when these data are extrapolated to the country population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Variation in reports of healthcare resource use, indirect costs and humanistic burden are also likely to have resulted from inconsistency in the time frame that different studies considered relevant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>With respect to the literature on economic burden, it is understood that costs are likely to vary between countries in terms of the cost of medical resources, medical visits and prescribed medications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Currently these differences are not reflected in the published literature and in some cases, the cost of treating a case of HZ or PHN were calculated inconsistently, with some studies presenting the cost per treated case while others presented the average across all patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>As such there was a wide variation between studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Only one study provided costs (per treated case) for the different types of medications used to treat HZ or PHN [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Similarly, no studies provided breakdown or clarification of cost elements included in a ‘hospital stay’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Great caution, therefore, should be taken in comparing and interpreting the available data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Furthermore this highlights an unmet need for data that clearly distinguishes between HZ and PHN and also for ‘per treated case’ data for a wide range of EU countries. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>A further notable limitation was that data were not available for all EU countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Despite comprehensive database searches, in which no restrictions on country of interest or language of publication were implemented, cost burden data for the majority of Eastern European countries was not identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The majority of studies, instead, focus primarily on the UK, Spain, France, Italy, Belgium and Germany. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Gaps in evidence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>A number of evidence gaps were identified, some of which provide opportunities for future research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>A key gap identified in the available evidence pool relates to how indirect costs are assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>While a number of EU studies presented data on the time missed from work and associated costs, data on productivity while at work and associated costs is lacking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Studies in the US and Canada, however, report that presenteeism could account for up to 75% of the cost burden associated with work loss [87] and that an average of 46 hours were lost (per employed patient) due to presenteeism [88]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In Europe, decisions regarding access and reimbursement of medical interventions are predominately driven by considerations of cost-effectiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Consideration of the impact of conditions as reported by patients themselves, however, provides important information regarding unmet need and the efficacy of medical interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>A number of studies assessing aspects of humanistic burden associated with HZ and PHN were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>However, there are number of notable limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the impact of HZ and PHN was generally assessed using disease specific questionnaires (such as the ZBPI) or ‘bespoke’ questions which have not been tested or validated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>There was only limited use of generic HRQoL instruments in the EU studies conducted to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, data from such instruments are valuable for quantifying burden with reference to the normative population and patients with other diseases – data that is important for contextualizing the relative burden associated with HZ and PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The available evidence does not typically look beyond the pain which accompanies or persists beyond the rash and the omission of other factors that can impact on patients’ quality of life (e.g. fatigue, stomach upsets, allodynia, and numbness). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>This should be addressed, preferably through a combination of quantitative and qualitative research, the latter of which was notably lacking in the literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Finally, the lack of literature relating to the wider societal burden potentially caused by HZ and PHN (particularly with respect to the impact on caregivers and the broader implications of HZ and PHN on provision of formal and informal social care) may be considered a critical gap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>To date burden among informal caregivers has rarely been considered, and only in terms of time lost from work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Significantly, this omits the potential impacts of providing informal care to patients that may not have resulted in time lost from work (e.g. negative impact on the health and well-being of caregivers). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, consideration of healthcare resource use and the economic burden of HZ and PHN has typically focussed on impacts within the healthcare system; the broader implications of HZ and PHN are rarely appreciated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>For example, the functional deficits observed among HZ and PHN patients that may lead to a loss of autonomy and increased reliance on formal paid care have not been estimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Beyond some evidence of direct and indirect costs related to the disease, the potential impact of HZ and PHN on the social care system remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec25" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>This literature review highlights the burden faced by patients, healthcare systems and society due to HZ and PHN in Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>While the incidence of HZ and PHN increases with age, the total cost per case of HZ and PHN management is not necessarily age-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Pain severity was associated with increased costs for both HZ and PHN, and, as a chronic condition, costs were higher for patients experiencing PHN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>No study fully addressed the humanistic and economic burden of HZ and PHN to patients, their families and society as a whole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Based on the reviewed evidence and an assessment of the gaps in the evidence base, it is likely that the true burden of HZ and PHN is underestimated in the Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Further research is required to build a holistic understanding of the impact of HZ and PHN to patients, healthcare systems and society. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec26"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Endnotes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>a*Costs originally reported in 2006 GBP sterling (£), converted to euros (€) using the following conversion rate £1 = €1.18. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>b*Costs originally reported in 2006 Swiss francs (CHF), converted to euros (€) using the following conversion rate 1CHF = €0.81. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>cAlthough 2 studies do not report a specific instrument, items reported appear to be derived from the ZBPI (38, 55). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>AG and RM are/were employees of Adelphi Values, a health outcomes agency commissioned by Sanofi Pasteur MSD, to conduct, analyse and communicate findings from this research on their behalf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>MU and EP are employees of Sanofi Pasteur MSD, a provider of a herpes zoster vaccine approved in the European Union. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The authors have no other competing interests to declare. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>AG and EP designed the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>RA and AG conducted the literature searches, determined eligibility of studies for inclusion in the review and were responsible for primary data extraction and analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>EP and MU contributed to the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>AG, EP and MU drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank Florence Baron-Papillon and Nathalie Largeron, employees of Sanofi Pasteur MSD (Lyon, France), for their support in the preliminary searches and their critical review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>They would also like to thank Jessica Costello (Adelphi Values) for assistance in data extraction of non-English articles included in this review, and Sophi Tatlock and Adam Moore (Adelphi Values) for editorial support during the development of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>1.OpsteltenWEekhofJNevenAKVerheijTTreatment of herpes zosterCan Fam Phys Med Fam Can20085433737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>2.SenguptaNBooyRSchmittHJPeltolaHVan-DammePSchumacherRFVaricella vaccination in Europe: are we ready for a universal childhood programme?Eur J Pediatr20081671475510.1007/s00431-007-0424-0<?supplied-pmid 17334784?>17334784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>3.PinchinatSCebrián-CuencaAMBricoutHJohnsonRWSimilar herpes zoster incidence across Europe: results from a systematic literature reviewBMC Infect Dis201313111010.1186/1471-2334-13-17023280237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>4.SchmaderKGnannJWJrWatsonCPThe epidemiological, clinical, and pathological rationale for the herpes zoster vaccineJ Infect Dis2008197Suppl 2S2071510.1086/522152<?supplied-pmid 18419399?>18419399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>5.LancasterTSilagyCGraySPrimary care management of acute herpes zoster: systematic review of evidence from randomized controlled trialsBr J Gen Pract1995453903945<?supplied-pmid 7779475?>7779475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>6.DworkinRSchmanderKThe epidemiology and natural history of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia20012AmsterdamElsevier </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>7.ScottFTJohnsonRWLeedham-GreenMDaviesEEdmundsWJBreuerJThe burden of Herpes Zoster: a prospective population based studyVaccine200624913081410.1016/j.vaccine.2005.09.026<?supplied-pmid 16352376?>16352376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>8.JohnsonRWRiceASPain following herpes zoster: the influence of changing population characteristics and medical developmentsPain20071281–23510.1016/j.pain.2006.10.024<?supplied-pmid 17161531?>17161531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>9.JohnsonRWWasnerGSaddierPBaronRPostherpetic neuralgia: epidemiology, pathophysiology and managementExpert Rev Neurother200771115819510.1586/14737175.7.11.1581<?supplied-pmid 17997705?>17997705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>10.BowsherDThe management of postherpetic neuralgiaPostgrad Med J199773864623910.1136/pgmj.73.864.623<?supplied-pmid 9497970?>9497970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>11.OxmanMNLevinMJJohnsonGRSchmaderKEStrausSEGelbLDA vaccine to prevent herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia in older adultsN Engl J Med20053522222718410.1056/NEJMoa051016<?supplied-pmid 15930418?>15930418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>12.HelgasonSPeturssonGGudmundssonSSigurdssonJAPrevalence of postherpetic neuralgia after a first episode of herpes zoster: prospective study with long term follow upBMJ20003217264794610.1136/bmj.321.7264.794<?supplied-pmid 11009518?>11009518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>13.KostRGStrausSEPostherpetic neuralgia–pathogenesis, treatment, and preventionN Engl J Med19963351324210.1056/NEJM199607043350107<?supplied-pmid 8637540?>8637540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>14.SerpellMGaterACarrollSAbetz-WebbLMannanAJohnsonRBurden of post-herpetic neuralgia in a sample of UK residents aged 50 years or older: Findings from the zoster quality of life (ZQOL) studyHealth Qual Life Outcomes20141219210.1186/1477-7525-12-92<?supplied-pmid 24920439?>24920439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>15.BouhassiraDChassanyOGaillatJHanslikTLaunayOMannCPatient perspective on herpes zoster and its complications: an observational prospective study in patients aged over 50 years in general practicePain20121532342910.1016/j.pain.2011.10.026<?supplied-pmid 22138256?>22138256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>16.ChooPWGalilKDonahueJGWalkerAMSpiegelmanDPlattRRisk factors for postherpetic neuralgiaArch Intern Med19971571112172410.1001/archinte.1997.00440320117011<?supplied-pmid 9183233?>9183233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>17.CoenPGScottFLeedham-GreenMNiaTJamilAJohnsonRWPredicting and preventing post-herpetic neuralgia: are current risk factors useful in clinical practice?Eur J Pain200610869570010.1016/j.ejpain.2005.11.002<?supplied-pmid 16427792?>16427792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>18.OpsteltenWMauritzJWde WitNJvan WijckAJStalmanWAvan EssenGAHerpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia: incidence and risk indicators using a general practice research databaseFam Pract2002195471510.1093/fampra/19.5.471<?supplied-pmid 12356697?>12356697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>19.OpsteltenWZuithoffNPvan EssenGAvan LoonAMvan WijckAJKalkmanCJPredicting postherpetic neuralgia in elderly primary care patients with herpes zoster: prospective prognostic studyPain2007132Suppl 1S52910.1016/j.pain.2007.02.004<?supplied-pmid 17379412?>17379412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>20.SchmaderKESloaneRPieperCCoplanPMNikasASaddierPThe impact of acute herpes zoster pain and discomfort on functional status and quality of life in older adultsClin J Pain2007236490610.1097/AJP.0b013e318065b6c9<?supplied-pmid 17575488?>17575488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>21.ChidiacCBruxelleJDauresJPHoang-XuanTMorelPLeplegeACharacteristics of patients with herpes zoster on presentation to practitioners in FranceClin Infect Dis: Offic Publ Infect Dis Soc Am200133162910.1086/320884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>22.DroletMBrissonMSchmaderKELevinMJJohnsonROxmanMNThe impact of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia on health-related quality of life: a prospective studyCMAJ: Can Med Assoc J = J Assoc Med Can2010182161731610.1503/cmaj.091711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>23.KatzJCooperEMWaltherRRSweeneyEWDworkinRHAcute pain in herpes zoster and its impact on health-related quality of lifeClin Infect Dis: Offic Publ Infect Dis Soc Am2004393342810.1086/421942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>24.OsterGHardingGDukesEEdelsbergJClearyPDPain, medication use, and health-related quality of life in older persons with postherpetic neuralgia: results from a population-based surveyJ Pain2005663566310.1016/j.jpain.2005.01.359<?supplied-pmid 15943957?>15943957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>25.van SeventerRSadoskyALuceroMDukesEA cross-sectional survey of health state impairment and treatment patterns in patients with postherpetic neuralgiaAge Ageing2006352132710.1093/ageing/afj048<?supplied-pmid 16431855?>16431855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>26.AnnemansLBresseXGobboCPapageorgiouMHealth economic evaluation of a vaccine for the prevention of herpes zoster (shingles) and post-herpetic neuralgia in adults in BelgiumJ Med Econ20101335375110.3111/13696998.2010.502854<?supplied-pmid 20707768?>20707768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>27.Cebrián-CuencaADíez-DomingoJSan-Martín-RodríguezMPuig-BarberáJNavarro-PérezJEpidemiology and cost of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia among patients treated in primary care centres in the Valencian Community of SpainBMC Infect Dis201111130210.1186/1471-2334-11-302<?supplied-pmid 22044665?>22044665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>28.GauthierABreuerJCarringtonDMartinMRemyVEpidemiology and cost of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia in the United KingdomEpidemiol Infect20091371384710.1017/S0950268808000678<?supplied-pmid 18466661?>18466661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>29.GialloretiLEMeritoMPezzottiPNaldiLGattiABeillatMEpidemiology and economic burden of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia in Italy: a retrospective, population-based studyBMC Infect Dis20101023010.1186/1471-2334-10-230<?supplied-pmid 20682044?>20682044 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>30.MickGGallaisJLSimonFPinchinatSBlochKBeillatM[Burden of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia: Incidence, proportion, and associated costs in the French population aged 50 or over]Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique201058639340110.1016/j.respe.2010.06.166<?supplied-pmid 21094001?>21094001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>31.UltschBKosterIReinholdTSiedlerAKrauseGIcksAEpidemiology and cost of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia in GermanyEur J Health Econ: HEPAC: Health Econ Prev Care201214610152610.1007/s10198-012-0452-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>32.RothbergMBVirapongseASmithKJCost-effectiveness of a vaccine to prevent herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia in older adultsClin Infect Dis: Offic Publ Infect Dis Soc Am200744101280810.1086/514342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>33.SchmaderKELevinMJGnannJWJrMcNeilSAVesikariTBettsRFEfficacy, safety, and tolerability of herpes zoster vaccine in persons aged 50–59 yearsClin Infect Dis2012547922810.1093/cid/cir970<?supplied-pmid 22291101?>22291101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>34.Collaboration TC: Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0 [updated March 2011]: Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane-handbook.org">www.cochrane-handbook.org</ext-link>; 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>35.Higgins JPTGSCochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0 [updated March 2011]2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>36.EurostatHarmonised Index of Consumer Prices2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>37.BayasJGilRLlupiáADíezCConesaAArizaCHospitalizaciones por herpes zoster y neuralgia postherpética en Cataluña, 1998–2003Vacunas2011124122810.1016/S1576-9887(11)70019-X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>38.BerrutGBaptisteCOphthalmic herpes zoster, a complication with a poor prognosis, is now a vaccine-preventable diseaseEur Geriatr Med20134S11610.1016/j.eurger.2013.07.381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>39.BleinCGavazziGPaccalinMBaptisteCVainchtockAEvaluation of the herpes zoster impact as comorbidity factor in 5 pathologies French hospital care among adults aged 50 and olderValue Health: J Int Soc Pharmacoeconomics Outcomes Res2013167A50310.1016/j.jval.2013.08.1151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>40.BilckeJOgunjimiBMaraisCde SmetFCallensMCallaertKThe health and economic burden of chickenpox and herpes zoster in BelgiumEpidemiol Infect201214011209610910.1017/S0950268811002640<?supplied-pmid 22230041?>22230041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>41.BresseXAnnemansLPreaudEBlochKDuruGGauthierAVaccination against herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia in France: a cost-effectiveness analysisExpert Rev Pharmacoeconomics Outcomes Res201313339340610.1586/erp.13.19 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>42.BricoutHPerinettiEMarchettiniPRagniPZottiCGabuttiGDescription of herpes zoster patients aged over 50 years in Italy-A GP based multi center prospective observational studyEur Geriatr Med20134S116710.1016/j.eurger.2013.07.383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>43.BrissonMEdmundsWJVaricella vaccination in England and Wales: cost-utility analysisArch Dis Child20038810862910.1136/adc.88.10.862<?supplied-pmid 14500303?>14500303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>44.Castro-LopesJMMenezesJMendoncaLCosta-PereiraAAzevedoLThe impact of post-herpetic neuralgia: a prospective multicentre study on pain and health related quality of lifeEur Geriatr Med20134S7910.1016/j.eurger.2013.07.260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>45.de JuanesJArrazolaPGarcía de CodesAArizaCGilRSan MartínMHospitalizaciones por herpes zoster y neuralgia postherpética en la Comunidad de Madrid, 1998–2003Vacunas20111241293510.1016/S1576-9887(11)70020-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>46.Di LegamiVGianinoMMCiofi degli AttiMMassariMMigliardiATombaGSEpidemiology and costs of herpes zoster: background data to estimate the impact of vaccinationVaccine20072543759860410.1016/j.vaccine.2007.07.049<?supplied-pmid 17889410?>17889410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>47.EdmundsWJBrissonMRoseJDThe epidemiology of herpes zoster and potential cost-effectiveness of vaccination in England and WalesVaccine20011923–2430769010.1016/S0264-410X(01)00044-5<?supplied-pmid 11312002?>11312002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>48.FrancoEPerinettiEMarchettiniPRagniPZottiCGabuttiGProportion of post herpetic neuralgia among patients with herpes zoster in Italy-A multicenter prospective observational studyEur Geriatr Med20134S115610.1016/j.eurger.2013.07.379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>49.García-DovalIPérez-ZafrillaBDescalzoMÁRosellóRHernándezMVGómez-ReinoJJIncidence and risk of hospitalisation due to shingles and chickenpox in patients with rheumatic diseases treated with TNF antagonistsAnn Rheum Dis201069101751510.1136/ard.2009.125658<?supplied-pmid 20551153?>20551153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>50.GaterAAbetz-WebbLCarrollSMannanASerpellMJohnsonRBurden of herpes zoster in the UK: findings from the zoster quality of life (ZQOL) studyBMC Infect Dis201414140210.1186/1471-2334-14-402<?supplied-pmid 25038799?>25038799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>51.GilASan-MartinMCarrascoPGonzalezAEpidemiology of severe varicella-zoster virus infection in SpainVaccine20042229–3039475110.1016/j.vaccine.2004.04.004<?supplied-pmid 15364443?>15364443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>52.GilAGilRAlvaroASan MartinMGonzalezABurden of herpes zoster requiring hospitalization in Spain during a seven-year period (1998–2004)BMC Infect Dis200995510.1186/1471-2334-9-55<?supplied-pmid 19422687?>19422687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>53.Gil-PrietoRSan-MartínMÁlvaro-MecaAGonzález-LópezAGil de MiguelAHerpes zoster hospitalizations of patients with chronic illnesses in Spain, 1998–2004Vacunas20111239510110.1016/S1576-9887(11)70013-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>54.Gil-PrietoRWalterSGonzalez-EscaladaAGarcia-GarciaLMarin-GarciaPGil-de-MiguelADifferent vaccination strategies in spain and its impact on severe varicella and zosterVaccine20143222778310.1016/j.vaccine.2013.11.008<?supplied-pmid 24275483?>24275483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>55.Gonzalez ChiappeSSarazinMTurbelinCLasserreAPelatCBonmarinIHerpes zoster: Burden of disease in FranceVaccine201028507933810.1016/j.vaccine.2010.09.074<?supplied-pmid 20946861?>20946861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>56.LionisCDVardavasCISymvoulakisEKPapadakakiMGAnastasiouFSAntonopoulouMDMeasuring the burden of herpes zoster and post herpetic neuralgia within primary care in rural Crete, GreeceBMC Fam Pract201112113610.1186/1471-2296-12-136<?supplied-pmid 22145678?>22145678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>57.LoncarZMestrovicAHBilicMTaksicIMickovicVQuality of pain in herpes zoster patients Kvaliteta boli kod pacijenata oboljelih od herpes zosteraColl Antropol201337252730<?supplied-pmid 23941000?>23941000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>58.LukasKEdteABertrandIThe impact of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia on quality of life: patient-reported outcomes in six European countriesZeitschr Gesundheitswissenschaften = J Public Health201220444151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>59.MesquitaMFroesFHospital admissions for Herpes Zoster in Portugal between 2000 and 2010 Internamentos hospitalares por Herpes Zoster em Portugal entre 2000 e 2010Acta Med Port20132655316<?supplied-pmid 24192092?>24192092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>60.MooreLRemyVMartinMBeillatMMcGuireAA health economic model for evaluating a vaccine for the prevention of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia in the UKCost Effect Resour Allocation: C/E20108710.1186/1478-7547-8-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>61.Morant-TalamanteNDiez-DomingoJMartinez-UbedaSPuig-BarberaJAleman-SanchezSPerez-BrevaLHerpes zoster surveillance using electronic databases in the Valencian Community (Spain)BMC Infect Dis201313146310.1186/1471-2334-13-463<?supplied-pmid 24094135?>24094135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>62.MordarskiSLysenkoLGerberHZietekMGredesTDominiakMThe effect of treatment with fentanyl patches on pain relief and improvement in overall daily functioning in patients with postherpetic neuralgiaJ Physiol Pharmacol200960suppl 8315<?supplied-pmid 20400789?>20400789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>63.NilssonJCasselTLindquistLBurden of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia in SwedenValue Health2013167A34710.1016/j.jval.2013.08.147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>64.PierikJGGumbsPDFortanierSAVan SteenwijkPCPostmaMJEpidemiological characteristics and societal burden of varicella zoster virus in the NetherlandsBMC Infect Dis20121211010.1186/1471-2334-12-110<?supplied-pmid 22574722?>22574722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>65.RabaudCRogeauxOLaunayOStradyCMannCChassanyOEarly antiviral treatment fails to completely prevent herpes-related painMed Mal Infect20134311–12461610.1016/j.medmal.2013.07.012<?supplied-pmid 24262914?>24262914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="?"><plain>66.RehmSBinderABaronRPost-herpetic neuralgia: 5% lidocaine medicated plaster, pregabalin, or a combination of both? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>A randomized, open, clinical effectiveness studyCurr Med Res Opin201026716071910.1185/03007995.2010.483675<?supplied-pmid 20429825?>20429825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>67.Schiffner-RoheJKösterIBeillatMLilieHSchubertIResource consumption and health care costs of herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia in GermanyGesundheitsökonomie Qualitätsmanagement201116042162310.1055/s-0029-1245896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>68.ScottFTLeedham-GreenMEBarrett-MuirWYHawramiKGallagherWJJohnsonRA study of shingles and the development of postherpetic neuralgia in East LondonJ Med Virol200370Suppl 1S243010.1002/jmv.10316<?supplied-pmid 12627483?>12627483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>69.Sicras-MainarANavarro-ArtiedaRIbáñez-NollaJPerez-RoncoJ[Incidence, resource use and costs associated with postherpetic neuralgia: a population-based retrospective study]Rev Neurol201255844961<?supplied-pmid 23055426?>23055426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>70.SouliotisKLionisCPapadakakiMPapageorgiouMTsiaousiIBersimisSThe economic burden of herpes zoster on patients visiting primary care settings in Greece-Results from a multicentre study in CreteEur Geriatr Med20134S117810.1016/j.eurger.2013.07.386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>71.StudahlMPetzoldMCasselTDisease burden of herpes zoster in Sweden - predominance in the elderly and in women - a register based studyBMC Infect Dis201313158610.1186/1471-2334-13-586<?supplied-pmid 24330510?>24330510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>72.SzucsTDKressigRWPapageorgiouMKempfWMichelJPFendlAEconomic evaluation of a vaccine for the prevention of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia in older adults in SwitzerlandHum Vaccine2011777495610.4161/hv.7.7.15573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>73.UltschBSiedlerARieckTReinholdTKrauseGWichmannOHerpes zoster in Germany: quantifying the burden of diseaseBMC Infect Dis20111117310.1186/1471-2334-11-173<?supplied-pmid 21679419?>21679419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>74.van HoekAJGayNMelegaroAOpsteltenWEdmundsWJEstimating the cost-effectiveness of vaccination against herpes zoster in England and WalesVaccine200927914546710.1016/j.vaccine.2008.12.024<?supplied-pmid 19135492?>19135492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>75.VolpiAGattiASerafiniGCostaBSuligoiBPicaFClinical and psychosocial correlates of acute pain in herpes zosterJ Clin Virol: Offic Publ Pan Am Soc Clin Virol2007384275910.1016/j.jcv.2007.01.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>76.VolpiAGattiAPicaFBellinoSMarsellaLTSabatoAFClinical and psychosocial correlates of post-herpetic neuralgiaJ Med Virol200880916465210.1002/jmv.21254<?supplied-pmid 18649332?>18649332 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>77.WeinkeTEdteASchmittSLukasKImpact of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia on patients’ quality of life: a patient-reported outcomes surveyZeitschr Gesundheitswissenschaften = J Public Health201018436774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>78.Organization WHActive ageing: a policy framework2002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>79.GalluzziKEManagement strategies for herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgiaJ Am Osteopath Assoc20071073 Suppl 1S813<?supplied-pmid 17488885?>17488885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>80.WhitleyRJVolpiAMcKendrickMWijckAOaklanderALManagement of herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgia now and in the futureJ Clin Virol: Offic Publ Pan Am Soc Clin Virol201048Suppl 1S20810.1016/S1386-6532(10)70005-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>81.VolpiAGrossGHercogovaJJohnsonRWCurrent management of herpes zoster: the European viewAm J Clin Dermatol2005653172510.2165/00128071-200506050-00005<?supplied-pmid 16252931?>16252931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>82.BrissonMPellissierJMCamdenSQuachCDe WalsPThe potential cost-effectiveness of vaccination against herpes zoster and post-herpetic neuralgiaHum Vaccine2008432384510.4161/hv.4.3.5686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>83.PickeringGLeplegeAHerpes zoster pain, postherpetic neuralgia, and quality of life in the elderlyPain Pract: Offic J World Inst Pain201111439740210.1111/j.1533-2500.2010.00432.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>84.MortensenGLPerceptions of herpes zoster and attitudes towards zoster vaccination among 50-65-year-old DanesDan Med Bull20115812A4345<?supplied-pmid 22142574?>22142574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>85.Eurostat: Ageing Charaterises the Demographic Perspectives of the European Societies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Statistics in Focus Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/en/web/products-statistics-in-focus/-/KS-SF-10-001">http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/en/web/products-statistics-in-focus/-/KS-SF-10-001</ext-link> 2008. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>86.YawnBPPost-shingles neuralgia by any definition is painful, but is it PHN?Mayo Clin Proc Mayo Clin201186121141210.4065/mcp.2011.0724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>87.SinghalPKMakinCPellissierJSyLWhiteRSaddierPWork and productivity loss related to herpes zosterJ Med Econ20111456394510.3111/13696998.2011.607482<?supplied-pmid 21838599?>21838599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>88.DroletMLevinMJSchmaderKEJohnsonROxmanMNPatrickDEmployment related productivity loss associated with herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia: a 6-month prospective studyVaccine2012301220475010.1016/j.vaccine.2012.01.045<?supplied-pmid 22285632?>22285632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
