<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oxid Med Cell Longev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oxid Med Cell Longev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OMCL</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1942-0900</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1942-0994</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4417603</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/638416</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Role of the Lipoperoxidation Product 4-Hydroxynonenal in the Pathogenesis of Severe Malaria Anemia and Malaria Immunodepression </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>Evelin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arese</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Skorokhod</surname><given-names>Oleksii A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Oncology, University of Torino, Via Santena 5 Bis, 10126 Torino, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Evelin Schwarzer: <email>evelin.schwarzer@unito.it</email> and </corresp><corresp id="cor2">*Oleksii A. Skorokhod: <email>oskorokh@unito.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Thomas Kietzmann </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>2015</volume><elocation-id>638416</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 Evelin Schwarzer et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress plays an important role in the pathogenesis of falciparum malaria, a disease still claiming close to 1 million deaths and 200 million new cases per year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Most frequent complications are severe anemia, cerebral malaria, and immunodepression, the latter being constantly present in all forms of malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Complications are associated with oxidative stress and lipoperoxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Its final product 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE), a stable yet very reactive and diffusible molecule, forms covalent conjugates with proteins, DNA, and phospholipids and modulates important cell functions at very low concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Since oxidative stress plays important roles in the pathogenesis of severe malaria, it appears important to explore the role of 4-HNE in two important malaria complications such as malaria anemia and malaria immunodepression where oxidative stress is considered to be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In this review we will summarize data about 4-HNE chemistry, its biologically relevant chemical properties, and its role as regulator of physiologic processes and as pathogenic factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We will review studies documenting the role of 4-HNE in severe malaria with emphasis on malaria anemia and immunodepression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Data from other diseases qualify 4-HNE both as oxidative stress marker and as pathomechanistically important molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Further studies are needed to establish 4-HNE as accepted pathogenic factor in severe malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In malaria pathophysiology, oxidative stress plays an important role in many fatal endpoints of the disease [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Imbalance in redox metabolism may be important under two aspects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>On the one hand, prooxidative reactions are important in the host response to combat malaria infection in a controlled manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Some protective mechanisms against malaria, such as glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase- (G6PD-) deficiency [3, 4] and hemoglobinopathies, were proposed to be connected with oxidative stress (reviewed in [1, 2]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Reactive nitrogen species were claimed to have a protective role against blood-stage malaria [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, such protective role has been denied in other studies [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, excess oxidative stress is harmful for the host and may contribute to malaria complications with potentially fatal outcome, such as severe malaria anemia and immunodepression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Indications for excess lipoperoxidation have been shown in malaria, where plasma lipid peroxides are increased [7] and red blood cells (RBCs) displayed increased lipid peroxidation and decreased antioxidative defense [8, 9] in clinical malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Cellular dysfunctions following excess oxidative stress are frequently mediated by lipoperoxidation products of nonenzymatic degradation of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Lipid peroxidation progresses by free radical chain reactions with lipid hydroperoxides as immediate unstable products that decompose to a series of very reactive products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Among these products, hydroxyaldehydes like 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE) are particularly important because they reach relatively high concentrations, are more stable as radicals, and are able to diffuse inside or even outside the cell to reach distant targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Target molecules, with which 4-HNE forms covalent conjugates, are proteins, DNA, and phospholipids [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Thus, 4-HNE can be considered the final mediator and marker of oxidative stress in cells and whole organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The role of 4-HNE in malaria pathogenesis was recently considered, and the malaria anemia is under special focus, since 4-HNE was shown to play a pathomechanistic role in this potentially deadly complication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>4-HNE Chemistry (Generation, Biologically Relevant Properties, and Metabolism) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>4-HNE is the final product of two sequential processes: first the generation of the hydroperoxide omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) during lipid peroxidation and second the carbon-chain break of the peroxidized PUFA together with the introduction of a hydroxyl group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Only omega-6 PUFAs, such as the essential fatty acids linoleic acid and arachidonic acid, play a role in 4-HNE generation (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Lipid peroxidation is a powerful nonenzymatic chain reaction that continuously provides free lipid radicals for further peroxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>PUFAs are attacked by free radicals regardless of whether the fatty acid is in free form (e.g., in the circulation, noncovalently bound to albumin) or esterified in phospholipids in the cellular membranes [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Thanks to their unpaired electron, free radicals are highly reactive compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>One of the most reactive representatives of oxygen radicals is the hydroxyl radical (•OH) that is able to initiate the peroxidation process by hydrogen abstraction from a C-atom positioned between two conjugated double bonds in PUFAs (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Similarly, iron (Fe2+/Fe3+) can act as a catalyst for this step and produce additional hydroxyl radicals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The result of hydrogen abstraction is a PUFA radical which binds molecular oxygen, becoming highly reactive peroxide that propagates the peroxidation chain reaction by “stealing” hydrogen from a further PUFA to become a PUFA hydroperoxide (PUFA-OOH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The newly formed PUFA radical may continue the peroxidation chain reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Similar to free iron, iron-containing heme is a highly efficient catalyst and accelerates substantially the lipoperoxidation process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The peroxidized PUFA rearranges the hydroperoxy group within the molecule (Hock rearrangement [13]), and the bond between carbons 9 and 10 of the fatty acid chain is destabilized and breaks up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The so-called Hock cleavage splits the peroxidized PUFA molecule between the C11 and C12 carbon atoms (in case of arachidonic acid) and the rearranged peroxy-group and releases the aldehyde nonenal and the oxidized residual 11-C fatty acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Nonenal consists of the last 9 carbons of the omega-6 fatty acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A further peroxidation with hydrogen abstraction and oxygen binding occurs at position 4 and the resulting 4-hydroperoxynonenal is finally reduced to 4-HNE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>All reactions may run efficiently without enzyme catalysis and are enhanced by heme. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>4-HNE is a 9 C-atom long aldehyde with a double bond between the carbon atoms C2 and C3 conjugated to the head aldehyde group (C1) and a hydroxyl group at the C4 position (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>While the aldehyde group is hydrophilic, the nonpolar carbon chain from C5 to C9 is hydrophobic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This explains the preferential enrichment of the molecule in lipid-rich structures like membranes as well as the capacity to cross the cell membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Thus, 4-HNE produced in a cell is enriched intracellularly but is not confined to the cell of origin but is found also extracellularly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>4-HNE was described to interfere with membrane fluidity and phospholipid asymmetry [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The molecule is highly reactive due to two reactive sites, the C3 carbon atom and the aldehyde group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>First, the conjugated system of C=C double bond and C=O carbonyl group plus the hydroxyl group makes the C3 atom more electropositive and thus susceptible to nucleophilic attacks, which allow the formation of Michael adducts with cysteine, histidine, and lysine residues, and less frequently with arginine residues of polypeptide chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Second, the aldehyde group may react with free amino group of lysine residues forming so-called Schiff bases frequently seen in lipoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Due to the presence of the two reactive sites in 4-HNE mentioned before, high concentrations of 4-HNE can also cross-link two peptide chains (reviewed in [16]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Further, 4-HNE was described to form adducts with purine bases in DNA (4-HNE-deoxyguanosine). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>This modification may play a role in tumor pathogenesis [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The second nonprotein targets of 4-HNE-conjugation are phosphatidylethanolamine and phosphatidylserine that react with their free amino groups forming Michael adducts and Schiff bases [19–21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Also vitamin C (ascorbic acid) and pyridoxamine, the precursor of vitamin B6, are targets for 4-HNE-conjugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Ascorbylation is assumed to play a role in the elimination of 4-HNE from the body [22, 23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In parallel, unconjugated 4-HNE is metabolized for detoxification and better excretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The main enzymes involved in 4-HNE metabolism are glutathione-S-transferase (GSTA4-4, EC 2.5.1.18) that catalyzes the synthesis of the 4-HNE-GSH adducts, aldehyde reductase (EC 1.1.1.21) that oxidizes 4-HNE to hydroxynonenoic acid (HNA), and alcohol dehydrogenase (EC 1.1.1.1) that reduces 4-HNE to 1,4-dihydroxynonene (DHN) [24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Proteins modified by 4-HNE are degraded by the proteasome in the cell cytosol but accumulate in case of high oxidative stress and may contribute to functional losses [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>4-HNE Role in Health and Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Cellular Targets of 4-HNE and Its Potential Functional Importance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of 4-HNE detectable in human serum under nonpathological conditions are 0.05–0.15 micromoles per liter, increasing with age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Kidney tubular cells, hepatocytes, and monocytes revealed higher tissue concentrations (between 1 and 100 micromoles per liter) varying by tissue type and organism condition (for review see [10, 27]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Although it seems unlikely that overall concentration may reach 100 micromoles per liter in organs, it is plausible that such levels may build up locally near peroxidized membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>4-HNE was calculated to reach 4 millimoles per liter in microsomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Due to cumulative effect in the membrane, 4-HNE may attack critical target proteins in or near the lipid bilayer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, monocytes where the enzyme NADPH-oxidase produces oxygen radicals directed against extracellular and intracellular microbes during the oxidative burst reaction may contain 40 micromoles per liter or higher 4-HNE concentrations [28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>At low concentration, 4-HNE is considered an efficient signaling molecule, whilst under oxidative stress the metabolism of 4-HNE may be saturated and modifications of biomolecules may elicit pathological effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Protein modifications represent the main known mechanism by which 4-HNE influences physiological and pathological processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A high and increasing number of 4-HNE target proteins have been identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The binding sites of 4-HNE to the protein chain were determined by mass spectrometry for about half of the proteins functionally modified by 4-HNE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The functional annotation of the structurally and/or functionally modified proteins covers a wide spectrum including enzymes in energy metabolism, protein kinases and phospholipases involved in cellular signaling, enzymes involved in intracellular proteolysis by the proteasome, extracellular matrix metalloproteinases, membrane receptors for neurotransmitter and growth factors, membrane ion transporter and carriers in the plasma membrane, some plasma proteins, cytoskeletal proteins, heat-shock proteins, and proteins involved in translation [10, 27, 30–35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Regulation of Physiological Processes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The cellular increase of 4-HNE in response to oxidative stress can potently activate stress response mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Nontoxic levels of 4-HNE have been described to modify (i) signal transduction regulating the de novo synthesis of detoxifying enzymes (e.g., via transcription factor Nrf2 and the transcription-enhancer antioxidant response element ARE); (ii) cell proliferation (e.g., via c-Jun N-terminal kinase JNK); (iii) apoptosis and cell cycle regulation (e.g., via p53); (iv) differentiation (e.g., via mitogen-activated protein kinase MAPK and growth factor receptors); (v) inflammatory response; (vi) expression of the cellular adhesion molecules ICAM-1, VCAM-1, and E-selectin (e.g., via transcription factors p38 and NF-kappaB); and (vii) protein turnover (via proteasome activity) [10, 11, 36–38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Modification of these pathways may be associated with survival mechanisms of cells or tissues under stress condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Association of 4-HNE with Pathologies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Uncontrolled or excessive production of 4-HNE could interfere with basal cellular signaling and play a role in the pathogenesis of several diseases accompanied by oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In 39 different human diseases increased steady-state levels of 4-HNE have been either reported in the affected organ or generalized in the blood plasma or both [10, 39] which suggests a pathogenic role of the aldehyde in the disease pattern and progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>It is now accepted that 4-HNE plays a role in inflammation-related cell signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Importantly, inflammation represents the main driving force in progression of most chronic diseases, in acute inflammatory diseases and in some anemias, as renal anemia [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>4-HNE Production in Malaria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>4-HNE has received little attention by malariologists as yet, although elevated levels of free, unconjugated 4-HNE had been described in RBCs of P. vinckei-infected mice as early as 1988 [41]; one study reported the growth inhibition of in vitro cultured parasites by 4-HNE [42], and the general presence of oxidative stress in malaria was detected long ago [43–46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec4.1"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>4-HNE from the Parasite </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>During its development the malaria parasite digests the major part of host RBC hemoglobin and polymerizes the undigested and prooxidant heme to HZ (hemozoin, malaria pigment) in close contact with the membrane of the digestive vacuole of the parasite [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Similar to free heme, isolated HZ catalyzes in vitro the peroxidation of PUFAs with subsequent degradation to 4-HNE and other products (Figures 1 and 2 and [48]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The onset of hemoglobin degradation and HZ formation at young trophozoite stage coincided with a significantly enhanced formation of 4-HNE and 4-HNE-membrane protein conjugates in parasitized RBCs, compared to nonparasitized control RBCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The progressive HZ generation during parasite growth was accompanied by the increase of 4-HNE conjugates up to 15-fold higher levels in HZ-rich schizonts compared to young HZ-free ring-forms (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The conjugates can be detected and quantified by flow cytometry or fluorescence microscopy after recognition by specific antibodies [11, 49, 50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>4-HNE conjugates are not confined to 4-HNE-producing cells but were also found in nonparasitized RBCs (npRBCs) cytoadherent to trophozoites (see Figure 4) [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>4-HNE from the Residual Body </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The synthetic beta-hematin core of natural HZ (nHZ) is able to catalyze in vitro the PUFA peroxidation with formation of 4-HNE and hydroxy-fatty acids such as hydroxylated arachidonic acid (hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid, HETE) or hydroxylated linoleic acid (hydroxyoctadecadienoic acid, HODE) (Figure 2, [48]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>At the end of the 48 h parasite growth cycle in the RBC, the daughter parasites leave the RBC to infect fresh RBCs (schizogony). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In parallel the residual body (RB) or nHZ, that is, the membrane-enveloped, HZ-containing digestive vacuole, is expelled into the bloodstream. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The RBs collected from culture supernatant contained 50 micromoles per liter of free 4-HNE (Figure 3, [52]), which was released and transferred to adjacent cells in an in vitro erythropoiesis model (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Hence, RBs represent an additional source of 4-HNE in pathology [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>4-HNE from Human Phagocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>RBs released into plasma bind preferentially host fibrinogen and to a lesser extent immunoglobulins (IgGs) and complement factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Fibrinogen was constantly present at 10–100,000 fibrinogen molecules per residual body and was stably bound to nHZ collected from plasma-cultured parasites [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Surface-binding changes the conformation of fibrinogen and makes it recognizable by Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) on monocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>RBs coated with fibrinogen become excellent ligands for TLR4 and were responsible for the rapid 100-fold stronger production of reactive oxygen species by human monocytes [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Close contact of HZ with the cell membrane, together with extensive oxidative burst during HZ phagocytosis, resulted in fast and persistent 6-fold increase of lipid peroxides in RB-fed monocytes compared to the transient 2-fold increase after RBC phagocytosis [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>4-HNE was significantly increased at 2 h after feeding monocytes with HZ and peaked at 5 h attaining 50-fold levels compared to unfed controls and was still almost 15-fold the control levels after 12 h [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The long-lasting generation of 4-HNE (Figure 3) is caused by a persisting lipoperoxidation catalyzed by HZ after its uptake into the lysosome of the monocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The generation of 4-HNE in HZ-fed monocytes is followed by a significant increase of 4-HNE conjugate formation with membrane proteins [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In summary, HZ can be considered to be source and shuttle for 4-HNE in malaria and 4-HNE is likely one molecular mediator of the HZ effects (reviewed in [55, 56]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>4-HNE Effect on Immune Response and Malaria Anemia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>HZ or RB has been described to interfere with several immune processes that might play a role in malaria and contribute to the lack of sterile immunity as well as in complicated forms of malaria [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>As described above, HZ acts as catalyst and shuttle for 4-HNE in malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Thus, a series of HZ effects were recapitulated by exogenously added 4-HNE, and molecular targets for 4-HNE listed above were modified by 4-HNE in HZ-fed cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The roles of 4-HNE on the pathophysiologically relevant processes are listed below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec5.1"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>5.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis, Oxidative Burst, and MHC Class II Expression: Protein Kinase C (PKC) Involvement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis and oxidative burst are first-line defense mechanisms against the blood-stage malaria parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>After avid phagocytosis of HZ and a violent oxidative burst elicited by mature parasites and released RB, both phagocytosis and burst are switched off after approximately 6–12 h from initial phagocytosis and remain inactive during the observation period of 3 days [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Phagocytes do not die and do not show signs of apoptosis [54, 57] that could explain the inactivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In malaria disease large proportions of resident macrophages and circulating monocytes and neutrophils contain massive amounts of HZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>When fed with HZ in vitro, the precursors of macrophages, the monocytes, lose their capacity to upregulate the antigen presenting MHC class II in response to interferon-gamma suggesting that HZ loading may contribute to the impairment of the immune response and derangement of antigen presentation previously reported in falciparum malaria [56, 58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Protein kinase C (PKC), the common regulator protein that coordinates phagocytosis, burst, and antigen presentation, was shown to be inactivated by 4-HNE-conjugation in vitro, and HZ-fed monocytes exhibited a high level of 4-HNE-conjugated PKC [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The kinetics of 4-HNE production and conjugate formation after HZ phagocytosis fit with the quick loss of active membrane-associated PKC and the subsequent disappearing responsiveness of cytosolic PKC to activators in HZ-fed monocytes [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Thus, we consider 4-HNE to be a molecular mediator in the HZ-provoked modulation of immune responses such as inhibition of oxidative burst, phagocytosis, and antigen presentation by MHC class II. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Comparison of transcriptional changes elicited by synthetic HZ and 4-HNE in murine macrophages suggests that both are involved in the modulation of inflammatory responses, transcription factor NF-kappaB-dependent signal transduction, and extracellular matrix degradation [60] further confirming 4-HNE as an immune-modulating factor of interest in malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>5.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Dendritic Cell Differentiation and Maturation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Enhanced 4-HNE production and formation of membrane protein-4-HNE conjugates were observed in HZ-fed monocytes in their differentiation towards DC [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Functionally, phagocytosis of HZ-containing parasites or HZ by itself (HZ is here synonymous with RBs), as well as 4-HNE and/or HETE generated and carried by HZ, inhibited the differentiation and maturation of DC [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In particular, 4-HNE significantly inhibited the expression of CD83, the functionally important marker for mature DCs, mimicking the effect of HZ or HETE [56, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Moreover, 4-HNE dose dependently inhibited the expression of CD83 in differentiating DCs [52] and 4-HNE added at reasonably low doses significantly inhibited the protein expression of MHC classes I and II, CD1a, and accessory molecules, which can modulate the ability of immune cells to develop or perform their functions [61], such as CD40, CD54, and CD83 [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 4-HNE modified the responsiveness of GM-CSF receptor, the crucial growth factor for dendritic cell differentiation in vitro [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Similar to phagocytosis of HZ, the addition of 4-HNE resulted in increased expression of the nuclear receptor PPAR-gamma (peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma) in the immune cells [36, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>After activation (e.g., by HETE) PPAR-gamma moves into the nucleus where it regulates immune cell functions [62] and functionally suppresses the transcription factor NF-kappaB [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>NF-kappaB controls proinflammatory immune responses [64], DC differentiation, DC maturation, and CD83 expression related to the latter process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>5.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Cell Cycle Control and Membrane Receptor Expression in Erythropoiesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Dyserythropoiesis (defective production of RBC) is an important determinant of severe malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Erythropoiesis prominently occurs in the bone marrow erythroblastic islands, microenvironmental niches in which erythroid progenitors proliferate, differentiate, and finally expel their nucleus at the end of the maturation process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>An island is formed by a central macrophage surrounded by developing and differentiating erythroid cells from early stages through reticulocytes [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Marrow macrophages and erythroid precursors have been shown to contain HZ in malaria patients [66, 67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>4-HNE, the production of which is enhanced by HZ, was first shown to interfere with erythropoiesis in an in vitro model of the initial stages of erythroid development in the bone marrow [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Both supplemented free 4-HNE and 4-HNE contained in HZ supernatants inhibited erythroid cell colony growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Application of advanced cell culture protocols allows the complete differentiation of umbilical cord blood-derived erythroid stem cells to fully mature enucleated RBCs and to analyze biochemical parameters crucial for this proliferation-dependent differentiation program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Erythroid stem cells incubated with 4-HNE displayed sustained high levels of 4-HNE-protein conjugate on their surface [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Human phagocytes either HZ-laden or cocultured with HZ were able to shed 4-HNE that diffused to the surrounding erythroid cells and was detected on the surface of those cells as 4-HNE-protein conjugate (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>4-HNE inhibits the erythroid cell proliferation during the whole period of erythropoiesis, involving the molecular regulators of the cell cycle, a series of controlled events that take place in a cell leading to its division [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Both natural HZ and 4-HNE treatment of erythroid cells results in (i) increased regulatory proteins: p53 (tumor suppressor protein 53) and p21 (cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1); (ii) unbalanced phosphorylation of the retinoblastoma protein Rb; (iii) decreased levels of cyclins A and D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Importantly, neither HZ nor 4-HNE added at reasonable concentrations induced programmed cell death (apoptosis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Further, low micromolar 4-HNE delays the differentiation marker expression: the functionally important membrane receptors for transferrin (TfR1, CD71), stem cell factor c-kit (CD117), interleukin-3 (CD123), and erythropoietin (EpoR) as well as the stem cell marker CD34, and the RBC markers glycophorin A and hemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>GATA-1, the master transcription factor that controls the differentiation processes in erythropoiesis, was less expressed in HZ- and 4-HNE-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The impaired cell cycle and reduced receptor expression decreased the total cell yield and specifically the yield of differentiated erythroid cells [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>These results reconfirm the inhibitory role of HZ, identify 4-HNE as HZ-generated inhibitory molecule for proliferation and differentiation, and describe molecular targets of 4-HNE in erythroid progenitors possibly involved in the inhibition of erythropoiesis in malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>5.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>RBC Membrane Proteins and Phagocytosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Excessive loss of npRBC, in addition to impaired erythropoiesis, is considered to be cause for malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Parasitized RBCs generate 4-HNE that conjugates with membrane skeleton proteins such as spectrin and actin and the integral membrane protein band 3 [51, 70] that contributes to anchoring the cytoskeleton to the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>4-HNE-conjugation is not confined to the parasitized RBCs but 4-HNE is transferred and binds to adjacent npRBCs as shown in Figure 4 where the central trophozoite-infected RBC is surrounded by npRBCs [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The differential labeling of pRBCs and npRBCs with a nuclear fluorescent probe (e.g., ethidium bromide) allows the separate analysis by flow cytometry of membrane protein-4-HNE conjugates in both cell cohorts [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Similar to npRBCs, protein-4-HNE conjugates are detectable in 4-HNE-treated RBCs causing loss in deformability and increased phagocytosis [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As decreased deformability and increased phagocytosis add to RBC elimination in the spleen, 4-HNE is suggested to be instrumental for the removal of large numbers of npRBCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.5"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>5.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Cytoskeleton Modifications and Impairment of Chemotactic Motility and Transendothelial Migration of Monocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Immune cell motility is an important physiological process, relatively poorly studied in malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Recently it was shown that nHZ phagocytosis by human primary monocytes impaired their chemotactic motility toward MCP-1, TNF, and FMLP and their diapedesis across a confluent endothelial cell layer toward MCP-1 [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>No inhibition was detected in control latex-fed or unfed monocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Microscopic analysis has shown that the polarization defect in nHZ-fed monocytes was due to irregular actin polymerization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Similar to nHZ phagocytosis, the exposure of monocytes to in vivo-compatible 4-HNE concentrations inhibited cell motility in both the presence and the absence of chemotactic stimuli, suggesting the impairment of cytoskeleton dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Consequently, 4-HNE conjugates with the cytoskeleton proteins β-actin and coronin-1A were identified in nHZ-fed monocytes and localized in domains of protein-protein interactions involved in cytoskeleton reorganization and cell motility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The molecular and functional modifications of actin and coronin by nHZ/4-HNE may also explain impaired phagocytosis, another motility-dependent process previously described in nHZ-fed monocytes [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This study indicates that impaired monocyte motility may contribute to the immune depression and the frequent occurrence of secondary infections observed in malaria patients [71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Figure 6 summarizes molecules and processes of potential relevance for malaria pathology that were structurally or functionally modified by 4-HNE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>4-HNE in Clinical Malaria and in Malaria Anemia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In vitro and clinical data strongly indicate that oxidative stress plays important roles in falciparum malaria, notably in the pathogenesis of severe anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>However, oxidative modifications of the RBC membrane by 4-HNE, which may mechanistically clarify the pathogenesis of clinical malaria as described above, have not been tested for their clinical significance until recent times. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Two important clinical trials, performed from 2005 to 2011 in malaria endemic regions of Mozambique [9] and Kenya [51], have shown that increased 4-HNE generation is occurring in clinical malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Small cohorts with mild to severe anemia have been studied to see whether a correlation between 4-HNE-conjugation and anemia was present. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec6.1"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>6.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Elevated 4-HNE Conjugates in Clinical Malaria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress markers including 4-HNE conjugates in RBC membranes and advanced oxidation protein products (AOPP) were longitudinally assessed in a large cohort of nonimmune Mozambican newborns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The study was performed in the period from 2.5 to 24 months of age, and additionally at the first clinical malaria episode and in convalescence, and included analysis of association with the malaria incidence rate until 2 years of age [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>A large data base for control values and values in clinical malaria of the same cohort of very young children allows defining the influence of clinical disease on 4-HNE generation: (i) 4-HNE conjugates significantly increased by approximately 75% in parasitized and nonparasitized RBCs during clinical malaria; (ii) 4-HNE conjugates correlated with plasma but not with RBC oxidative stress markers during clinical malaria; (iii) in contrast to plasma oxidative stress markers, 4-HNE conjugates remained significantly elevated in convalescence after clearing of malaria parasites from peripheral blood in comparison to the healthy state before clinical malaria; and (iv) high levels of 4-HNE conjugates in individual healthy children were predictive of increased malaria incidence rates until 2 years of age [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Above data underscore the clinical significance of 4-HNE in malaria immunology and the potential role of 4-HNE for impaired immune functions of phagocytes as described in Sections 5.1 and 5.2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>6.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Role of 4-HNE in Malaria Anemia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>As outlined before, 4-HNE demonstrated a strong inhibitory effect on ex vivo erythropoiesis of human erythroid stem cells, also contributing to enhanced phagocytosis of RBCs in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Both erythropoiesis inhibition and enhanced phagocytosis of npRBCs were shown to contribute to severe malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>First indications for the clinical relevance of 4-HNE as a molecular pathogenic factor for malaria anemia come from studies in Mozambique and Kenya mentioned before [9, 51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Elevated or increasing 4-HNE conjugate levels in convalescence were associated with sustained anemia or aggravated anemia during convalescence (Figure 7, [5]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Children with severe malaria anemia had significantly higher percentages of 4-HNE-conjugate-positive npRBCs compared to children with uncomplicated malaria [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, 4-HNE is suggested to play a role in the phagocytic removal of npRBCs, one hallmark of severe malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Of note, field studies have shown that another blood oxidative stress marker, the advanced oxidative protein products (AOPP), has been shown to be predictive of malaria anemia [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This data, together with the correlation between AOPP and 4-HNE conjugates level on RBC established in clinical malaria [9], will strengthen the role of increased 4-HNE levels as part of systemic oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Results of studies summarized in this review indicate that 4-HNE is a highly active molecule produced by the malaria parasite and by the host immune system in response to infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In ex vivo cell cultures 4-HNE was found to impair several immune functions of phagocytic cells that certainly contribute to malaria pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Similarly, 4-HNE was found to impair the development of mature RBCs and to enhance their elimination by the spleen leading to anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Clinically, malaria disease is accompanied by elevated 4-HNE levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Clinical studies indicate that 4-HNE is involved in the pathogenesis of malaria anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>However, despite abundant evidence from current research, further clinical studies are necessary to better establish this promising molecule as an accepted pathogenic factor in severe malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Funding by the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013; EVIMALAR Grant no. 242095) is gratefully acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Evelin Schwarzer was supported by the Grant PRIN 2010-11 (SKINFLAM) from MIUR (the Italian Ministry of Education, Universities and Research). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>1PercárioS.MoreiraD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>R.GomesB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Q.Oxidative stress in MalariaInternational Journal of Molecular Sciences20121312163461637210.3390/ijms1312163462-s2.0-8487168300623208374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>2BeckerK.TilleyL.VennerstromJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>L.RobertsD.RogersonS.GinsburgH.Oxidative stress in malaria parasite-infected erythrocytes: host-parasite interactionsInternational Journal for Parasitology200434216318910.1016/j.ijpara.2003.09.0112-s2.0-124231694115037104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3LuzzattoL.UsangaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A.ReddyS.Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficient red cells: resistance to infection by malarial parasitesScience1969164388183984210.1126/science.164.3881.8392-s2.0-00146809154889647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>4CappadoroM.GiribaldiG.O'BrienE.Early phagocytosis of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD)-deficient erythrocytes parasitized by Plasmodium falciparum may explain malaria protection in G6PD deficiencyBlood1998927252725342-s2.0-00321890189746794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>5KunJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>F.MordmüllerB.PerkinsD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>J.Nitric oxide synthase 2(Lambaréné) (G-954C), increased nitric oxide production, and protection against malariaThe Journal of Infectious Diseases2001184333033610.1086/3220372-s2.0-003542616111443559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>6TaylorA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>M.DayN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>J.SinhD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>T.Reactive nitrogen intermediates and outcome in severe adult malariaTransactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene199892217017510.1016/S0035-9203(98)90733-72-s2.0-00319178219764323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>7DasB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>S.ThurnhamD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>I.PatnaikJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>K.DasD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>B.SatpathyR.BoseT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>K.Increased plasma lipid peroxidation in riboflavin-deficient, malaria-infected childrenThe American Journal of Clinical Nutrition19905158598632-s2.0-00252681922185624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>8DasB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>S.NandaN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>K.Evidence for erythrocyte lipid pepoxidation in acute falciparum malariaTransactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene1999931586210.1016/S0035-9203(99)90180-32-s2.0-003301442910492792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>9AguilarR.MarroccoT.SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>A.Blood oxidative stress markers and Plasmodium falciparum malaria in non-immune African childrenBritish Journal of Haematology2014164343845010.1111/bjh.126362-s2.0-8489246162124422726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>10PoliG.SchaurR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>J.SiemsW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>G.LeonarduzziG.4-Hydroxynonenal: a membrane lipid oxidation product of medicinal interestMedicinal Research Reviews200828456963110.1002/med.201172-s2.0-4524912466318058921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>11SchaurR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>J.Basic aspects of the biochemical reactivity of 4-hydroxynonenalMolecular Aspects of Medicine2003244-514915910.1016/s0098-2997(03)00009-82-s2.0-004317250912892992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>12GardnerH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>W.Oxygen radical chemistry of polyunsaturated fatty acidsFree Radical Biology and Medicine198971658610.1016/0891-5849(89)90102-02-s2.0-00243547752666279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>13WangZ.Hock rearrangementComprehensive Organic Name Reactions and Reagents2010New York, NY, USAJohn Wiley &amp; Sons10.1002/9780470638859.conrr321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>14SubramaniamR.RoedigerF.JordanB.The lipid peroxidation product, 4-hydroxy-2-trans-nonenal, alters the conformation of cortical synaptosomal membrane proteinsJournal of Neurochemistry1997693116111692-s2.0-00307466219282939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>15CastegnaA.LauderbackC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>M.Mohmmad-AbdulH.ButterfieldD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>A.Modulation of phospholipid asymmetry in synaptosomal membranes by the lipid peroxidation products, 4-hydroxynonenal and acrolein: implications for Alzheimer's diseaseBrain Research200410041-219319710.1016/j.brainres.2004.01.0362-s2.0-164234149215033435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>16UchidaK.4-hydroxy-2-nonenal: a product and mediator of oxidative stressProgress in Lipid Research200342431834310.1016/s0163-7827(03)00014-62-s2.0-003741128212689622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>17WinterC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>K.SegallH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>J.HaddonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>F.Formation of cyclic adducts of deoxyguanosine with the aldehydes trans-4-hydroxy-2-hexenal and trans-4-hydroxy-2-nonenal in vitroCancer Research19864611568256862-s2.0-00230090073756915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>18ChungF.-L.ChenH.-J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>C.GuttenplanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>B.NishikawaA.HardG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>C.2,3-epoxy-4-hydroxynonanal as a potential tumor-initiating agent of lipid peroxidationCarcinogenesis199314102073207710.1093/carcin/14.10.20732-s2.0-00273650958222056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>19GuichardantM.Taibi-TroncheP.FayL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>B.LagardeM.Covalent modifications of aminophospholipids by 4-hydroxynonenalFree Radical Biology and Medicine19982591049105610.1016/S0891-5849(98)00149-X2-s2.0-00324038899870558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>20GuichardantM.Bernoud-HubacN.ChantegrelB.DeshayesC.LagardeM.Aldehydes from n-6 fatty acid peroxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Effects on aminophospholipidsProstaglandins Leukotrienes and Essential Fatty Acids2002672-314714910.1054/plef.2002.04122-s2.0-0036693955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>21BacotS.Bernoud-HubacN.BaddasN.Covalent binding of hydroxy-alkenals 4-HDDE, 4-HHE, and 4-HNE to ethanolamine phospholipid subclassesJournal of Lipid Research200344591792610.1194/jlr.M200450-JLR2002-s2.0-014210585512588949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>22SowellJ.FreiB.StevensJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>F.Vitamin C conjugates of genotoxic lipid peroxidation products: structural characterization and detection in human plasmaProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200410152179641796910.1073/pnas.04084331022-s2.0-1114422652515608056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>23AmarnathV.AmarnathK.AmarnathK.DaviesS.RobertsL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>J.IIPyridoxamine: an extremely potent scavenger of 1,4-dicarbonylsChemical Research in Toxicology200417341041510.1021/tx03005352-s2.0-164231712415025512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>24SiemsW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>G.ZollnerH.GruneT.EsterbauerH.Metabolic fate of 4-hydroxynonenal in hepatocytes: 1,4-dihydroxynonene is not the main productJournal of Lipid Research19973836126222-s2.0-00309861629101442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>25EsterbauerH.ZollnerH.LangJ.Metabolism of the lipid peroxidation product 4-hydroxynonenal by isolated hepatocytes and by liver cytosolic fractionsBiochemical Journal198522823633732-s2.0-00218467503160340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>26SiemsW.GruneT.Intracellular metabolism of 4-hydroxynonenalMolecular Aspects of Medicine2003244-516717510.1016/S0098-2997(03)00011-62-s2.0-004217029612892994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>27EsterbauerH.SchaurR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>J.ZollnerH.Chemistry and Biochemistry of 4-hydroxynonenal, malonaldehyde and related aldehydesFree Radical Biology and Medicine19911118112810.1016/0891-5849(91)90192-62-s2.0-00258149801937131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>28SchwarzerE.MüllerO.AreseP.SiemsW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>G.GruneT.Increased levels of 4-hydroxynonenal in human monocytes fed with malarial pigment hemozoin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>A possible clue for hemozoin toxicityFEBS Letters19963882-311912210.1016/0014-5793(96)00523-62-s2.0-00305914368690068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>29WitzG.LawrieN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>J.AmorusoM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>A.GoldsteinB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>D.Inhibition by reactive aldehydes of superoxide anion radical production from stimulated polymorphonuclear leukocytes and pulmonary alveolar macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Effects on cellular sulfhydryl groups and NADPH oxidase activityBiochemical Pharmacology198736572172610.1016/0006-2952(87)90725-82-s2.0-00231006623030333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>30WagnerT.MullallyJ.FitzpatrickF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>A.Reactive lipid species from cyclooxygenase-2 inactivate tumor suppressor LKB1/S TK11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Cyclopentenone prostaglandins and 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal covalently modify and inhibit the AMP-kinase kinase that modulates cellular energy homeostasis and protein translationThe Journal of Biological Chemistry20062812598260416311241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>31EchtayK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>S.EstevesT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>C.PakayJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>L.A signalling role for 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal in regulation of mitochondrial uncouplingEMBO Journal200322164103411010.1093/emboj/cdg4122-s2.0-004146500912912909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>32AndringaK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>K.UdohU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>S.LandarA.BaileyS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>M.Proteomic analysis of 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE) modified proteins in liver mitochondria from chronic ethanol-fed ratsRedox Biology201421038104710.1016/j.redox.2014.09.00625454745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>33PerryE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>A.CastellaniR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>J.MoreiraP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>I.Neurofilaments are the major neuronal target of hydroxynonenal-mediated protein cross-linksFree Radical Research2013476-750751010.3109/10715762.2013.7942652-s2.0-8487887536123566300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>34KhatoonF.MoinuddinAlamK.AliA.Physicochemical and immunological studies on 4-hydroxynonenal modified HSA: implications of protein damage by lipid peroxidation products in the etiopathogenesis of SLEHuman Immunology201273111132113910.1016/j.humimm.2012.08.0112-s2.0-8486789112022917540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>35SmathersR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>L.FritzK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>S.GalliganJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>J.Characterization of 4-HNE modified L-FABP reveals alterations in structural and functional dynamicsPLoS ONE201276e3845910.1371/journal.pone.00384592-s2.0-84862017251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>36PizzimentiS.LauroraS.BriatoreF.FerrettiC.DianzaniM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>U.BarreraG.Synergistic effect of 4-hydroxynonenal and PPAR ligands in controlling human leukemic cell growth and differentiationFree Radical Biology and Medicine200232323324510.1016/s0891-5849(01)00798-52-s2.0-003646888311827749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>37IshiiT.ItohK.RuizE.Role of Nrf2 in the regulation of CD36 and stress protein expression in murine macrophages: activation by oxidatively modified LDL and 4-hydroxynonenalCirculation Research200494560961610.1161/01.res.0000119171.44657.452-s2.0-164239653714752028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>38MinekuraH.KumagaiT.KawamotoY.NaraF.UchidaK.4-Hydroxy-2-nonenal is a powerful endogenous inhibitor of endothelial responseBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications2001282255756110.1006/bbrc.2001.45862-s2.0-003480609111401496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>39GruneT.MichelP.SitteN.Increased levels of 4-hydroxynonenal modified proteins in plasma of children with autoimmune diseasesFree Radical Biology and Medicine199723335736010.1016/s0891-5849(96)00586-22-s2.0-00309537279214570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>40SiemsW.CarluccioF.RadenkovicS.GruneT.HamplH.Oxidative stress in renal anemia of hemodialysis patients is mitigated by epoetin treatmentKidney and Blood Pressure Research2006285-629530110.1159/0000901842-s2.0-3364497333416534224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>41BuffintonG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>D.HuntN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>H.CowdenW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>B.ClarkI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>A.Detection of short-chain carbonyl products of lipid peroxidation from malaria-parasite (Plasmodium vinckei)-infected red blood cells exposed to oxidative stressBiochemical Journal1988249163682-s2.0-00237043183342016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>42ClarkI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>A.ButcherG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>A.BuffintonG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>D.HuntN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>H.CowdenW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>B.Toxicity of certain products of lipid peroxidation to the human malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum Biochemical Pharmacology198736454354610.1016/0006-2952(87)90364-92-s2.0-00231096983548730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>43DasB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>S.PatnaikJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>K.MohantyS.Plasma antioxidants and lipid peroxidation products in falciparum malariaThe American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene19934967207252-s2.0-00277162678279640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>44Delmas-BeauvieuxM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>C.PeuchantE.DumonM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>F.ReceveurM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>C.Le BrasM.ClercM.Relationship between red blood cell antioxidant enzymatic system status and lipoperoxidation during the acute phase of malariaClinical Biochemistry199528216316910.1016/0009-9120(94)00071-32-s2.0-00289395577628075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>45ErelO.VuralH.AksoyN.AslanG.UlukanligilM.Oxidative stress of platelets and thrombocytopenia in patients with vivax malariaClinical Biochemistry200134434134410.1016/s0009-9120(01)00221-111440737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>46Tiyong IfoueS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>H.Teugwa MoforC.GouadoI.TetoG.AsonganyiT.Amvam ZolloP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>H.Evaluation of oxidative stress and antioxidant status of pregnant women suffering from malaria in CameroonIndian Journal of Clinical Biochemistry200924328829310.1007/s12291-009-0054-62-s2.0-7034926985723105851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>47KapishnikovS.WeinerA.ShimoniE.Oriented nucleation of hemozoin at the digestive vacuole membrane in Plasmodium falciparum Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America201210928111881119310.1073/pnas.11181201092-s2.0-8486391066822745164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>48MillerC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>M.CarneyC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>K.SchrimpeA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>C.WrightD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>W. β-hematin (hemozoin) mediated decompostion of polyunsaturated fatty acids to 4-hydroxy-2-nonenalInorganic Chemistry20054472134213610.1021/ic048821i2-s2.0-1624437982315792445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>49SpickettC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>M.The lipid peroxidation product 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal: advances in chemistry and analysisRedox Biology20131114515210.1016/j.redox.2013.01.0072-s2.0-8487888410024024147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>50WaegG.DimsityG.EsterbauerH.Monoclonal antibodies for detection of 4-hydroxynonenal modified proteinsFree Radical Research199625214915910.3109/107157696091499202-s2.0-00299061888885333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>51UyogaS.SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>A.OpiyoM.Transfer of 4-hydroxynonenal from parasitized to non-parasitized erythrocytes in rosettes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Proposed role in severe malaria anemiaBritish Journal of Haematology2012157111612410.1111/j.1365-2141.2011.09015.x2-s2.0-8485829854722352722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>52SkorokhodO.SchwarzerE.GruneT.AreseP.Role of 4-hydroxynonenal in the hemozoin-mediated inhibition of differentiation of human monocytes to dendritic cells induced by GM-CSF/IL-4BioFactors2005241–428328910.1002/biof.55202401332-s2.0-2864444160916403989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>53BarreraV.SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>A.BaciD.GremoG.AreseP.SchwarzerE.Host fibrinogen stably bound to hemozoin rapidly activates monocytes via TLR-4 and CD11b/CD18-integrin: a new paradigm of hemozoin actionBlood2011117215674568210.1182/blood-2010-10-3124132-s2.0-7995761005621460246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>54SchwarzerE.TurriniF.UlliersD.GiribaldiG.GinsburgH.AreseP.Impairment of macrophage functions after ingestion of Plasmodium falciparum-infected erythrocytes or isolated malarial pigmentJournal of Experimental Medicine199217641033104110.1084/jem.176.4.10332-s2.0-00266630501402649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>55TybergheinA.DeroostK.SchwarzerE.AreseP.Van den SteenP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>E.Immunopathological effects of malaria pigment or hemozoin and other crystalsBioFactors2014401597810.1002/biof.11192-s2.0-8489410367523907956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>56SchwarzerE.SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>A.BarreraV.AreseP.Hemozoin and the human monocyte—a brief review of their interactionsParassitologia2008501-21431452-s2.0-5614909103118693582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>57SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>A.AlessioM.MordmüllerB.AreseP.SchwarzerE.Hemozoin (malarial pigment) inhibits differentiation and maturation of human monocyte-derived dendritic cells: a peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ-mediated effectThe Journal of Immunology200417364066407410.4049/jimmunol.173.6.40662-s2.0-464422008315356156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>58UrbanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>C.MwangiT.RossA.Peripheral blood dendritic cells in children with acute Plasmodium falciparum malariaBlood20019892859286110.1182/blood.v98.9.28592-s2.0-003552578611675362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>59SchwarzerE.TurriniF.GiribaldiG.CappadoroM.AreseP.Phagocytosis of P. falciparum malarial pigment hemozoin by human monocytes inactivates monocyte protein kinase CBiochimica et Biophysica Acta—Molecular Basis of Disease199311811515410.1016/0925-4439(93)90089-j2-s2.0-0027534915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>60SchrimpeA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>C.WrightD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>W.Comparative analysis of gene expression changes mediated by individual constituents of hemozoinChemical Research in Toxicology200922343344510.1021/tx80027522-s2.0-6594911109019191707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>61BenedictS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>H.CoolK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>M.DotsonA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>L.ChanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>A.Immune accessory proteinsEncyclopedia of Life Sciences2007John Wiley &amp; Sons<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/9780470015902.a0000923.pub2/full">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/9780470015902.a0000923.pub2/full</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>62RicoteM.HuangJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>T.WelchJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>S.GlassC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>K.The peroxisome proliferator-activated receptorγ (PPARγ) as a regulator of monocyte/macrophage functionJournal of Leukocyte Biology19996657337392-s2.0-003273785810577502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>63ZhangX.YoungH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>A.PPAR and immune system —what do we know?International Immunopharmacology2002281029104410.1016/s1567-5769(02)00057-72-s2.0-003599320712349941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>64GilmoreT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>D.Introduction to NF-κB: players, pathways, perspectivesOncogene200625516680668410.1038/sj.onc.12099542-s2.0-3375046623017072321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>65ChasisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>A.MohandasN.Erythroblastic islands: niches for erythropoiesisBlood2008112347047810.1182/blood-2008-03-0778832-s2.0-5094908931118650462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>66Casals-PascualC.KaiO.CheungJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>P.Suppression of erythropoiesis in malarial anemia is associated with hemozoin in vitro and in vivoBlood200610882569257710.1182/blood-2006-05-0186972-s2.0-3375062641216804108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>67AguilarR.MoraledaC.AchtmanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>H.Severity of anaemia is associated with bone marrow haemozoin in children exposed to Plasmodium falciparum British Journal of Haematology2014164687788710.1111/bjh.127162-s2.0-8489671575024386973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>68GiribaldiG.UlliersD.SchwarzerE.RobertsI.PiacibelloW.AreseP.Hemozoin- and 4-hydroxynonenal-mediated inhibition of erythropoiesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Possible role in malarial dyserythropoiesis and anemiaHaematologica20048944924932-s2.0-294269984915075084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>69SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>A.CaioneL.MarroccoT.Inhibition of erythropoiesis in malaria anemia: Role of hemozoin and hemozoin-generated 4-hydroxynonenalBlood2010116204328433710.1182/blood-2010-03-2727812-s2.0-7854928604220686121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>70MéndezD.HernáezM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>L.KamaliA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>N.DiezA.PuyetA.BautistaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>M.Differential carbonylation of cytoskeletal proteins in blood group O erythrocytes: potential role in protection against severe malariaInfection, Genetics and Evolution20121281780178710.1016/j.meegid.2012.06.0132-s2.0-84865858920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>71SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>A.BarreraV.HellerR.Malarial pigment hemozoin impairs chemotactic motility and transendothelial migration of monocytes via 4-hydroxynonenalFree Radical Biology and Medicine20147521022110.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2014.07.00425017964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>72ZhangG.SkorokhodO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>A.KhooS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>K.Plasma advanced oxidative protein products are associated with anti-oxidative stress pathway genes and malaria in a longitudinal cohortMalaria Journal201413, article 13410.1186/1475-2875-13-134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Omega-6 PUFAs are the source of 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>The formation of 4-HNE from arachidonic acid by lipid peroxidation, chain break, and hydroxylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>In malaria, it was shown that the heme core of hemozoin (HZ, malaria pigment) could catalyze the lipoperoxidation of PUFAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Resulting hydroperoxides are chemically unstable: they (i) are reduced to the hydroxy-fatty acid such as hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid (HETE) from arachidonic (note, HETEs are bioactive PPAR-γ (peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma) ligands) or (ii) are decomposed to 4-HNE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>C1 and C3 are 4-HNE reactive sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Biologically relevant properties of 4-HNE are listed in blue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>4-HNE source in malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>4-HNE transfer from parasitized to nonparasitized RBCs in rosettes in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Micrographs of 4-HNE-positive parasitized RBCs and nonparasitized RBCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>This result was originally published in British Journal of Haematology, Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>(Uyoga et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>2012, © John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>4-HNE conjugates on the cell surface of erythroid cells cocultivated with residual body (RB or natural HZ) visible as green fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>This research was originally published in Blood (Skorokhod et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>2010, supplemental materials© the American Society of Hematology). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Proteins and processes of potential relevance for malaria pathology structurally or functionally modified by 4-HNE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Association of 4-HNE conjugate levels on RBCs with sustained moderate anemia during convalescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Children presenting with Hb &lt; 100 g/L at their first acute malaria episode were grouped according to their capacity to recover from anemia by increasing Hb levels during convalescence or to worsen their state by decreasing or sustained low Hb levels during convalescence (1 month after acute malaria episode). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>4-HNE binding to the RBCs of children was assessed as MFI at acute and convalescence states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Mean MFI-values ± SE during convalescence are plotted for the groups with increasing Hb (+35, 3 ± 6,5%; N = 34) and decreasing Hb (−15, 4 ± 6,0%; N = 8) (a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>The change in 4-HNE conjugate levels in the RBC membrane during recovery from malaria disease is shown (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>The mean ± SE of the ratio of 4-HNE conjugates measured during convalescence and at acute state is plotted for the increasing (+38,5 ± 9,2%; N = 22) and decreasing (−26,8 ± 6, 2%; N = 4) Hb groups, respectively (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>The significance of differences between groups is indicated by ∗ when P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>MFI, mean fluorescence intensity; Hb, hemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>This result was originally published in British Journal of Haematology, Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>(Aguilar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>2014, © John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OMCL2015-638416.007"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
