<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4051664</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24915573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-51278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Digestive System</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastrointestinal Tract</subject><subj-group><subject>Small Intestine</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunopathology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immune Response</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastroenterology and Hepatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Celiac Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal Administration of Poly I:C Causes an Enteropathy That Is Exacerbated by Administration of Oral Dietary Antigen </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Intraluminal Poly I:C Causes Gluten Enteropathy</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>Romina E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jury</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bondar</surname><given-names>Constanza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Verdu</surname><given-names>Elena F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Chirdo</surname><given-names>Fernando G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratorio de Investigación en el Sistema Inmune- LISIN, Departamento de Ciencias Biológicas, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Universidad Nacional de La Plata, La Plata, Argentina</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Division of Gastroenterology, Farncombe Family Digestive Health Institute, McMaster University, Hamilton, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>Simon Patrick</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>fchirdo@biol.unlp.edu.ar</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: E.F.V. receives grant support from Nestle Research Center, Switzerland, unrelated to this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The remaining authors have declared that no competing interest exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors' adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RA EV FGC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: RA JJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: RA EV FGC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: RA EV FGC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e99236</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Araya et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Araya et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Systemic administration of polyinosinic:polycytidylic acid (poly I:C), mimics virally-induced activation of TLR3 signalling causing acute small intestine damage, but whether and how mucosal administration of poly I:C causes enteropathy is less clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Our aim was to investigate the inflammatory pathways elicited after intraluminal administration of poly I:C and determine acute and delayed consequences of this locally induced immune activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C induced rapid mucosal immune activation in C57BL/6 mice involving IFNβ and the CXCL10/CXCR3 axis, that may drive inflammation towards a Th1 profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C also caused enteropathy and gut dysfunction in gliadin-sensitive NOD-DQ8 mice, and this was prolonged by concomitant oral administration of gliadin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that small intestine pathology can be induced in mice by intraluminal administration of poly I:C and that this is exacerbated by subsequent oral delivery of a relevant dietary antigen. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by a grant to F.Ch. from CONICET PIP 719 and a CIHR grant to E.F.V. (MOP-123282). R.E.A. received a travel grant from Canadian Association of Gastroenterology (CAG) – Latin American Student Research Opportunity. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Detection of components of microorganisms by a complex system of pattern recognition receptors leads to immune host defense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In the gut, home to 1013–1014 resident bacteria, but also fungi and viruses, the immune mechanisms elicited have a critical role in tissue homeostasis[1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>However, uncontrolled activation of these pathways may lead to pathology, as demonstrated in studies using intraperitoneal (ip) administration of double stranded RNA (dsRNA) that induces overactivation of TLR3 signalling [2], [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Polyinosinic:polycytidylic acid (poly I:C) is a synthetic analogue of dsRNA used to mimic the intermediates of replication present in cells infected with RNA viruses and some DNA viruses [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In addition to TLR3, dsRNA sensors include two cytoplasmic receptors, retinoic acid-inducible gene I (RIG-I) and melanoma differentiation-associated gene 5 (MDA5) [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>NFκB and IRF3/7 are the dominant nuclear factors involved in the control of the expression of inflammatory cytokines and chemokines and Type I IFN, respectively, upon activation by dsRNA[8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>McAllister C. et al.5 showed that signaling pathways activated through dsRNA sensors and particularly, TLR3/TRIF/caspase 8, drive intestinal pathology but also host protection during viral infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>However, the role of locally induced, rather than systemic pathways in these models, remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>More importantly there is a scarcity of models directly relevant to small intestinal induction of pathology and gut dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Epidemiological studies support the association of enteric infections with the subsequent development of inflammatory or functional gastrointestinal disease [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Viral infections, in particular enterovirus such as rotavirus, have been suggested to increase the incidence of celiac disease (CD), a permanent intolerance to gluten that occurs in genetically susceptible people [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Case reports have also suggested the association of enteric infections with CD onset [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Currently, the underlying mechanisms that support this association are poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, it is well known that innate immune activation generates a rapid and strong anti-viral response, which essentially involves the production of Type I IFNs and other components of the inflammatory response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The link among enterovirus infection and CD raises the hypothesis that Type I IFNs may be involved in loss of tolerance to gluten through the ability to promote inflammation and an strong Th1 response [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In this work, we aimed to mimic the local intestinal immune response as triggered by enteric viral infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We used intraluminal administration of poly I:C to wild type mice and evaluated the immediate in vivo immune and pathological mechanisms triggered at the small intestinal mucosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We also investigated the potential influence of this initial immune activation on long lasting gut functional responses to administration of a relevant dietary antigen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>For this, we used NOD-DQ8 mice, a model that allows in vivo evaluation of functional and immune responses to gliadin, the storage protein in cereals [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Animal models rarely recapitulate the full spectrum of human complex diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Moreover, human diseases often express different clinical phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Thus the usefulness of animal models resides in mimicking certain aspects of disease pathogenesis in order to generate hypotheses to be tested in clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In this work, we used two animal models to investigate two different questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>First, the effect of oral poly I:C in the early stages of the mucosal innate immune response, and second the influence of the administration of a specific dietary antigen in preconditioned mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>We observed that luminal administration of poly I:C activated the innate immune response and caused acute enteropathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Administration of gliadin to gliadin-sensitive mice previously treated with poly I:C, prolonged gliadin-induced gut dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We propose a mucosally-driven model of enteropathy by poly I:C in which post inflammatory mechanisms of gastrointestinal disease can be investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Eight-week female C57BL/6J mice were purchased to the Animal Care Facility of the Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences of the University of Buenos Aires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Mice were housed in plastic cages and fed ad libitum with balanced food and water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>They were maintained on a 12h light/darkness cycle and acclimatized to the surrounding conditions for 1 week before the experimental procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Transgenic mice that express HLA-DQ8 in an endogenous MHC class II-deficient background were backcrossed to NOD mice for 10 generations and intercrossed to produce congenic NOD AB° DQ8 mice [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Eight- to 10-wk-old male mice were used for experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Mice were weaned and maintained on a low-fat (4.4%), gluten-free diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The original breeding pairs of NOD-DQ8 mice were kindly provided by Dr. Chella David and Dr. Joseph Murray from Mayo Clinic, Rochester, USA, and subsequently bred in specific pathogen-free conditions at McMaster University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All the studies were performed in accordance with international protocols for laboratory animal care (Canadian Council on Animal Care). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Experiments were conducted with approval from the McMaster University Animal Care Committee and the National University of La Plata Ethic Committee. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C treatment and oral gavage </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Mice were kept on the gluten free diet at the time of the surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C (Sigma-Aldrich) or PBS was intraluminally administrated throughout an intestinal microsurgery that allows inject the stimuli directly in the lumen of small intestine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Mice were anaesthetized with Ketamine 80 mg/kg of weight and Xilacine 10 mg/kg of weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Once mice were asleep, 30μg/g of weight of poly I:C solution in PBS were injected in the lumen of small intestine, 2 cm after the stomach, to avoid the enzymatic degradation of the poly I:C (mainly because of nuclease activity from pancreatic enzymes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Control mice receipted only PBS in the lumen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>After the surgery, a fluid replacement was done and mice were strictly monitored until they were able to walk around the cage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>A group of mice was sacrificed after 3h or 12h post-treatment with poly I:C or PBS, and samples of blood and small intestine were collected for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Other group of mice was orally gavaged with 5 mg of α-gliadin/time, three times a week during 2 weeks, starting at 24h post-surgery. α-Gliadin (by Sigma-Aldrich) was dissolved in endotoxin-free acetic acid 0.02 M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Control mice were gavaged with the acetic acid solution only (Gluten-free diet mice). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All solutions were controlled and endotoxin free preparations were determined using E-TOXATE endotoxin kit (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Mice were weighed three times a week during the 2 weeks, after the oral gavage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Histologic evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Cross-sections of the proximal small intestine were fixed in 10% formalin, embedded in paraffin, and stained with H&amp;E staining for histological evaluation by using a Nikon Eclipse Ti fluorescence microscope with X-Cites Series 120 Q light source. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Images were taken with Nikon Digital Sight DS Ri1 camera using Nis-Elements software and measurements were performed using Image J software properly calibrated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Two sections of the proximal small intestine were evaluated for evidence of inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>At least thirty villus-to-crypt ratios were measured for each mouse in a blinded fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Intraepithelial lymphocytes (IELs) per 30 enterocytes in ten randomly chosen villus tips were counted according to the previously described methods and expressed as IEL/100 enterocytes [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Histological scores were obtained from the small intestinal sections stained with H&amp;E, following the Park-Chiu criteria[18]: 0, normal mucosa; 1, subepithelial space at villus tips; 2, extension of subepithelial space with moderate lifting; 3, massive lifting down sides of villi, some denuded tips; 4, denuded villi, dilated capillaries; 5, disintegration of lamina propria; 6, Crypt layer injury; 7, transmucosal infarction; 8, transmural infarction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Ussing chambers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Two sections of proximal small intestine from each NOD-DQ8 mouse were used for Ussing chamber experiments as described previously [15], [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>A 3–4-cm piece of small intestine was collected (3 cm from the stomach), cut into two sections, and placed in Krebs buffer aerated with 95% O2 and 5% CO2 (pH 7.3–7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Each segment of intestine was cut open along the mesenteric border to form a flat sheet and mounted into an Ussing chamber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The chamber exposed 0.7 cm2 of tissue surface area to 8 ml of circulating oxygenated Krebs buffer containing 10 mM glucose (serosal side) and 10 mM mannitol (mucosal side) maintained at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Net active ion transport across the epithelium was measured via a short circuit current (Isc, mA) injected across the tissue under voltage-clamp conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Tissue conductance (the passive permeability to ions) was calculated using Ohm's law. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Baseline Isc (mA/cm2) and conductance (mS/cm2) were recorded at equilibrium, 20 min after mounting small intestine sections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Cytokine analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The presence of proinflammatory cytokines in serum from NOD-DQ8 mice was determined using a Cytometric Bead Array Inflammation kit (BD Biosciences) and analyzed using BD FACSarray Bioanalyzer System (BD Biosciences). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Real Time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Small Intestinal samples from C57BL/6 and NOD-DQ8 mice were stored in RNA later in-80°C freezer until be used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Tissues were disrupted and RNA extraction was performed using RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>cDNA synthesis was performed from isolated RNA samples (2-5µg), using iScript Reverse Transcription Supermix (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Real Time PCR reaction was performed with SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix (Bio-Rad) using the adequate forward and reverse primers and the iQ5 thermocycler with fluorescence detection (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Reactions were run in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The Real Time PCR protocol was: Cycle 1 (1X) 95°C for 10min; Cycle2 (40X) 60°C for 1min and 95° for 15sec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Primers were synthesized as it was previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are provided in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The geometric mean of housekeeping gene HPRT was used as an internal control to normalize the variability in expression levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>All results were expressed as a fold increase of PBS and PIC treatment versus the mean of PBS treatment in every time point (2−ΔΔCt method). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0099236-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Primers used for quantitative PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0099236-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0099236.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Gene </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>HPRT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>CAATGCAAACTTTGCTTTCC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>CAAATCCAACAAAGTCTGGC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>MDA5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>CGATCCGAATGATTGATGCA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>AGTTGGTCATTGCAACTGCT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>RIG-I </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>CAGACAGATCCGAGACACTA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>TGCAAGACCTTTGGCCAGTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>TLR3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>GAAGATGATGCAGTCTTTCCA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>CCTGTATCATATTCTACTCCTTGC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>IFNβ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>AATGGAAAGATCAACCTCAC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>AAGGCAGTGTAACTCTTCTG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>CXCL10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>ATAGGGAAGCTTGAAATCATCC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>TTCATCGTGGCAATGATCTC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>CXCR3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>TGTAGTTGGGCTAGCTCGAACTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>ACCTGGATATATGCTGAGCTGTCA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>TNFα </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>CTCCCTCTCATCAGTTCTATGG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>TTGAGAAGATGATCTGAGTGTG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>IL-15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>CATCCATCTCGTGCTACTTGTGTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>CATCTATCCAGTTGGCCTCTGTTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>MCP1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>CTACAAGAGGATCACCAGCAG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>TTCTGATCTCATTTGGTTCCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>CXCL2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>AAGATACTGAACAAAGGCAAGG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>TTCTTTCTCTTTGGTTCTTCCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>IL-1β </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>CGTTCCCATTAGACAACTGC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>CTCATGGAGAATATCACTTGTTGG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>IL-18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>GATCAAAGTGCCAGTGAACC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>GATCTTGTTCTTACAGGAGAGG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>IL-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>CATGTTCTCTGGGAAATCGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>TATATCCAGTTTGGTAGCATCC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>IFNγ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>CTGAGACAATGAACGCTACAC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>TTTCTTCCACATCTATGCCAC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Bax </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>TGCTACAGGGTTTCATCCAG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>ATTGCTGTCCAGTTCATCTC </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Bcl2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>GATCTCTGGTTGGGATTCCT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>ACAACTTGCAATGAATCGGG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Small intestinal sections from PBS- and PIC-treated mice were deparaffinized and an immunofluorescence protocol was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Antigenicity recovery was performed using Antigen Retrieval AR-10 Solution (BioGenex). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>After blocking with 2% goat serum, goat anti-IL-15 IgG antibody (R&amp;D) was added in a concentration of 2 µg/ml for 1h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Alexa488 donkey anti-goat antibody (Molecular Probes) in a concentration of 10 µg/ml was added for 1h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were stained with propidium iodide at 1 µg/ml for 15 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Images were obtained and analyzed in a TCS SP5 Confocal Microscope combined with Leica LAS AF software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was performed with GraphPad Prism software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>For more than two treatment groups, an ANOVA with a Bonferroni post hoc test for multiple comparisons was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>When two groups were compared, an unpaired t test was used; p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Data are displayed as mean ±SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C induces histological changes in the small intestinal mucosa </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>We first evaluated the capacity of poly I:C delivered at the mucosal site to induce enteropathy in wild type mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal administration of poly I:C to C57BL/6 mice produced severe enteropathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>At 12h post poly I:C, we observed shortening and widening of villi, edema, and increased cell infiltration in the lamina propria (LP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Using H&amp;E staining edema, dilated capillaries and interstitial spaces were observed in intestinal villi ( Figure 1A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, V/C ratios were decreased, while the number of IELs and global histological score increased compared to PBS-treated mice ( Figure 1B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>At 72h post poly I:C, there was partial recovery of villus-to-crypt (V/C) ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>In contrast to control mice, morphometric parameters remained altered in poly I:C-treated mice ( Figure 1C ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>As expected, the surgical procedure altered intestinal histology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, this change was transient, and control mice exhibited a faster recovery after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We also tested whether molecular weight of poly I:Cs influenced inflammation and mucosal damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We did not detect significant differences among the tested poly I:Cs (Figure S1), and therefore the remaining experiments were carried out using the commonly used commercial poly I:C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C induces enteropathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Representative H&amp;E stained sections of proximal small intestine of C57BL/6 mice after 12hs and 72hs of intraluminal administration of poly I:C or PBS (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Morphological analysis of small intestine from C57BL/6 mice: villus-to-crypt (V/C) ratio, number of IELs and histological score after 12h (B) and 72h (C) (Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory mediators and receptors MDA5, RIGI and TLR3 are induced by intraluminal poly I:C in small intestine </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>We next explored the signaling pathways induced by intraluminal poly I:C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>For this we analyzed the kinetics of expression of inflammatory mediators and three receptors for poly I:C in a time-course experiment using C57BL/6 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In the small intestine, there was a rapid and strong increment of IFNβ 2h after treatment, while CXCL10 and TNFα peaked 4h after intraluminal administration of poly I:C ( Figure 2A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Analysis of expression of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-18, IL-1β, IL-15 and IFNγ,chemokines such as MCP1 and CXCL2, and anti- and pro-apoptotic molecules Bcl-2 and Bax, respectively, did not show any differences between groups (data not shown).Since recognition of poly I:C is mediated by TLR3, MDA5 and RIGI and their expressions are modulated by poly I:C, we evaluated whether the expression of these receptors were induced in the small intestine of treated mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The time course experiment showed that MDA5, RIGI and TLR3 mRNA were similarly upregulated in small intestine by intraluminal injection of poly I:C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Expression of the three receptors peaked 6h post-treatment ( Figure 2B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we analyzed the protein expression of IL-15, obtaining no relevant differences among poly I:C and PBS treatments after 12h (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C generates a proinflammatory response and the induction of MDA5, RIG-I and TLR3 mRNA expression in small intestine. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Real Time-PCR analysis of small intestinal samples from C57BL/6 mice after intraluminal administration of poly I:C or PBS was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Plots shows mRNA expression after 2 to 12h of poly I:C (black dots) or PBS (empty dots) treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>IFNβ, CXCL10, and TNFα mRNA expression (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>MDA5, RIG-I, and TLR3 mRNA expression (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>All values were normalized with the housekeeping mRNA expression (HPRT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Results were expressed as fold increase of PBS and poly I:C treatment versus the mean of PBS treatment in every time point (2-ΔΔCt method). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001, poly I:C treated mice versus PBS control in the same time point. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory response induced by intraluminal poly I:C in the small intestine of NOD-DQ8 mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The NOD-DQ8 mouse represents one useful model of gluten sensitivity [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the model has particular phenotypes given by the DQ8 restriction and the NOD background [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Thus, prior to gliadin antigen administration, we first examined in detail the immune responses to poly I:C in NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Indeed, poly I:C caused severe mucosal damage in NOD-DQ8 mice characterized by cell infiltration of the LP, edema and shortening of villi at 12h post-treatment ( Figure 3A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Morphometric parameters revealed marked reduction in the V/C ratio in poly I:C treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Also, IELs numbers and histological scores were higher in poly I:C-treated mice than in control NOD-DQ8 mice ( Figure 3B ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal administration of poly I:C induces enteropathy in NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Representative H&amp;E-stained sections of the proximal small intestine in PBS and poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice at 12h post-treatment (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Morphological analysis of small intestine from NOD-DQ8 mice: villus-to-crypt (V/C) ratio, number of IELs and histological score after 12h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01 (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We found that IFNβ mRNA expression was increased in the small intestinal mucosa of NOD-DQ8 mice at 3h post-poly I:C compared to controls ( Figure 4 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>A 40-fold increment in CXCL10 mRNA was observed at 3 h in poly I:C-treated mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>At 12 hours, CXCL10 levels remained higher in poly I:C-treated mice than in controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The cytoplasmic pattern recognition receptors for poly I:C, MDA5 and RIG-I, were also induced in the small mucosa of poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Expression of both receptors was increased at 3h, but was higher at 12 h after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The upregulation of these receptors was observed later than in C57BL/6 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>At 3h and 12h post-Poly I:C injection we did not observe differences in TLR3 expression when compared to PBS controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory mediators elicited by intraluminal poly I:C were also evaluated in peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Concentration of TNFα, IL-6 and MCP1 was significantly higher 3h after intraluminal administration of poly I:C than in controls ( Figure 5 ), while IL-10, IL-12p70 and IFNγ did not show changes in poly I:C-stimulated mice versus PBS controls (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Altogether these results suggest a systemic pro-inflammatory state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C generates a proinflammatory response and induces RIG-I and MDA5 mRNA expression in the small intestine from NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Real Time-PCR analysis of the IFNβ, CXCL10, TLR3, MDA5, and RIG-I mRNA expression at 3 and 12 h post-treatment with poly I:C (black bar) or PBS (white bar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>All values were normalized to the housekeeping mRNA expression (HPRT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>All results were expressed as a fold increase of PBS and poly I:C treatment versus the mean of PBS treatment in every time point (2−ΔΔCt). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, poly I:C-treated mice versus PBS control in the same time point. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Increased serum levels of TNFα, MCP-1, and IL-6 after intraluminal poly I:C administration. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>TNFα, MCP-1, and IL-6 concentration was assessed in serum after 3h of poly I:C or PBS treatment, using a cytometric bead array inflammation kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The dotted line represents the limit of detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Intraluminal poly I:C and oral dietary antigen induce prolonged enteropathy in NOD-DQ8 mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Once we had determined the local and systemic immune responses of NOD-DQ8 mice to mucosally-administered poly I:C, we evaluated whether this was potentiated or prolonged by oral administration of relevant dietary antigen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>NOD-DQ8 mice were treated with poly I:C and fed gliadin or a gluten-free chow, starting 24h later, three times a week during two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Small intestinal sections and blood samples were collected after two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>A gluten-free chow did not affect the level of enteropathy in NOD-DQ8 mice induced by intraluminal poly I:C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>H&amp;E staining showed subepithelial edema and moderate lifting of villi in poly I:C-treated mice with or without gliadin ( Figure 6A ).Histological parameters revealed that both groups had an altered V/C ratio, but similar IELs counts, 2 weeks after poly I:C administration ( Figure 6B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>However, persistent morphological changes in the small intestinal mucosa were only observed in poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice that were subsequently challenged with gliadin, indicating maintenance of intestinal damage by oral antigen administration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Gliadin induces histological damage in intraluminal poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Representative H&amp;E-stained sections of the proximal small intestine from PBS and poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice on a gluten free diet (GFD) or orally gavaged with gliadin during 2 weeks (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Morphological analysis of small intestine from NOD-DQ8 mice treated with poly I:C or PBS under a gluten free diet (GFD) or gavaged with gliadin during 2 weeks: V/C ratio, number of IELs and histological score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4-5 mice per group, Unpaired t test, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001 (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>We also evaluated intestinal barrier function by Ussing chamber technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Oral gavage of gliadin for two weeks was associated with increased transepithelial conductance in poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This change was not observed in poly I:C-treated mice fed a gluten free chow or in control mice ( Figure 7A ).The evaluation of isotopic flux of 51Cr-EDTA showed increased paracellular permeability two weeks after poly I:C treatment regardless of the diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>However the percentage increase was higher in mice receiving gliadin gavages than in those on gluten-free chow (mean value for each treatment: PBS-GFD: 0.095%, poly I:C-GFD: 0.22%, PBS-gliadin: 0,17%, poly I:C-Gliadin: 0,56% Hot/h/cm2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The levels of the proinflammatory cytokines IL-12p70 and TNFα were increased in peripheral blood of mice gavaged with gliadin after 2 weeks compared with those on gluten free chow, even in the absence of poly I:C treatment ( Figure 7B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>However no differences were observed in MCP-1, IL-6 and IFNγ cytokine production in any of groups (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Gliadin gavages also induced an increment in the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 in serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, poly I:C treatment abolished the production of IL-10 induced by gliadin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Therefore, orally delivered gliadin in poly I:C treated mice produced a substantial imbalance in the IL-12p70/IL-10 ratio, suggesting a long lasting proinflammatory milieu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Serum levels of IL-12p70 and IL-10 were below the limit of detection in mice on gluten-free chow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that local inflammatory and functional processes in the small intestine induced by intraluminal poly I:C predispose to stronger functional impairment and inflammatory response to a relevant orally-administered dietary antigen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0099236-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099236.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Gliadin induces barrier dysfunction and proinflammatory cytokines in poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>After 24h of the final gavage, sections of small intestine were mounted in Ussing chambers and tissue conductance (mS/cm2) and isotopic flux (% Hot/h/cm2) were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Each dot represents an individual mouse and is a mean of 2 independent tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  3-4 mice per group, Two way ANOVA and Bonferroni post-test, *P&lt;0.05 (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Analysis of IL-12p70, TNFα and IL-10 in serum samples from poly I:C or PBS-treated mice on a gluten-free diet (GFD) or gavaged with gliadin for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>IL-12p70/IL-10 ratio was determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Serum concentration of cytokines was determined by a cytometric bead array inflammation kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The dotted line represents the limit of detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Stats: N =  4-5 mice per group, Two way ANOVA and Bonferroni post-test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01 gliadin versus GFD mice; #P&lt;0.05 poly I:C versus PBS in Gliadin-gavaged mice (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099236.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>We showed that induction of local small intestinal inflammation can be elicited by intraluminal administration of poly I:C to both wild type and gliadin-sensitive NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>We determined that the severe enteropathy induced by intraluminal poly I:C, predisposed to functional impairment of small intestine in NOD-DQ8 mice receiving the dietary antigen, gliadin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>During viral enteric infections, intermediates of replication, such as dsRNA, are produced in infected cells [6] and trigger a rapid inflammatory cascade, which involves the activation of TLR3 and RNA helicases such as RIG-I and MDA5 [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C is a synthetic analogue commonly used to mimic the effects of dsRNA which causes intestinal pathology when injected parentally [2], [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The marked villus shortening and increased enterocyte apoptosis observed after parenteral poly I:C has been suggested to be caused by TLR3/TRIF/Caspase 8 activation[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>We used instead intraluminal administration of poly I:C and demonstrated it produced severe intestinal pathology, as assessed by reduced V/C ratio, increased IELs counts and increased global histological scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Induction of dsRNA sensors TLR3, MDA5 and RIG-I was transient, peaked at 6h and returned to basal levels at 12h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>In previous models using parenteral poly I:C administration, mucosal damage seemed to be specific for TLR3 activation[3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The underlying mechanisms proposed for intestinal damage include NK cells [2] and CD8αα+ IELs with critical participation of IL-15 [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>A recent study however has proposed that, neither NK cells, IELs or IL-15 are involved in the induction of intestinal pathology [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Using intraluminal poly I:C, we found a strong and early increase of IFNβ mRNA levels in the small intestine of C57BL/6 mice 2h post-treatment, indicating a mucosal specific poly I:C-signaling activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>TNFα, a cytokine commonly involved in the early inflammatory response, was also transiently upregulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, a 60-fold increase in CXCL10 expression was observed 4h after intraluminal poly I:C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>CXCL10 has previously been shown to be upregulated by poly I:C in different experimental strategies[23], and it may play a crucial role in the development of small intestine pathology since it is a major chemo-attractant for Th1 CXCR3+ cells into inflamed tissues [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The mRNA expression of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-15, IL-18, IL-1β and IFNγ, chemokines such as MCP1 and CXCL2 and anti- and pro-apoptotic molecules as Bcl-2 and Bax respectively, were analyzed, but no changes were observed (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the report by McAllister C. et al. [5] using a parenteral poly I:C model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Since poly I:C triggers a cascade of inflammatory reactions involving different signaling pathways some of the effects after poly I:C administration may also have diverse origins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The observation that transglutaminase 2 (TG2) is activated in small intestine by intraperitoneal poly I:C administration highlights that different players may contribute to additional dysregulation of gut homeostasis[26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Upregulation of TG2 has also been related to NFkB pathway, driving an amplification loop of inflammation and damage at the small intestinal mucosa[27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Overall our results suggest that intraluminal poly I:C induces rapid mucosal immune activation involving IFNβ, and the CXCL10/CXCR3 axis that may drive inflammation towards a Th1 profile. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Understanding the early and delayed consequences of immune activation by enteric viral infections, or dsRNA, has important implications for post-infectious inflammatory and functional consequences [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Thus our second aim was to determine whether a single intraluminal administration of poly I:C influenced subsequent responses to gliadin, a dietary antigen that causes CD in genetically susceptible people, but which may be involved in gut functional abnormalities in a subgroup of patients with irritable bowel syndrome (non celiac gluten sensitivity) [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>For this we used NOD-DQ8 mice, which lack all endogenous class II molecules and express the human HLA-DQ8 gene involved in CD [16], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Previous studies using this model have shown that gliadin sensitization results in barrier dysfunction and moderate enteropathy [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice developed mucosal damage characterized by higher histological score than in control mice, cell infiltration in LP, reduction of V/C ratio, increased IEL counts, and upregulation of IFNβ and CXCL10 mRNA in intestinal mucosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>This was also accompanied by higher levels of TNFα, IL-6 and MCP1 in peripheral blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>After poly I:C administration, one group of NOD-DQ8 mice was subjected to oral gliadin challenges while another was fed a gluten free chow. 51Cr-EDTA flux studies indicated increased paracellular permeability in poly I:C-treated mice after two weeks regardless of the dietary treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Poly I:C also induced alterations in V/C ratio compared to control mice in both gliadin challenged and gluten free mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>However, only poly I:C-treated mice receiving gliadin presented higher global histological scores, demonstrating severe changes in the mucosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>More importantly, increased transepithelial conductance was only observed in poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice that were subsequently challenged with gliadin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, after two weeks of gliadin ingestion, NOD-DQ8 mice showed increased levels of the proinflammatory cytokines IL-12p70 and TNFα in peripheral blood, compared with those on gluten-free chow, indicating a causal link to gliadin challenges and not to poly I:C treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Moreover, IL-10 induction by gliadin, a feature observed in -DQ8 mouse models of gluten sensitivity before [15], [30], [31], was inhibited in previously poly I:C-treated mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>An imbalance in the IL-12p70/IL-10 ratio was observed in gliadin challenged and poly I:C-treated NOD-DQ8 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The inflammatory effects elicited by IL-12p70 and TNFα have been shown to have direct effects on barrier function and intestinal damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The correct assembly of tight junction components is critical to preserve barrier integrity and TNFα is recognised as one of the main mediators associated with inflammation in Crohn's disease and CD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>TNFα signalling activates myosin light chain kinase (MLCK) and tight junction remodelling leading to loss of barrier function [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that gliadin peptides can also increase permeability by innate mechanisms amplifying the circuit of mucosal damage [34], [35], [36], [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We did not observe changes in IL-15 expression associated with this model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>IL-15 expression has a complex post-transcriptional control which is particularly important to maintain an adequate balance of the immune response in gut. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, IL-15 expression has been shown to be modulated by p31-43 gliadin peptide, which triggers different innate responses in Caco-2 cells as well as in human duodenum [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Though we did not specifically work with p31-43, we have performed significant characterization of the NOD-DQ8 model [15].Given the NOD background of mice this model is not specifically IL-15 driven. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Thus, neither mRNA nor protein IL-15 determinations in this particular model are useful markers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, intraluminal poly I:C induced a severe but transitory damage in the small intestinal mucosa in both wild-type and NOD-DQ8 mice.The combination of poly I:C and subsequent gliadin feeding in the genetically susceptible mouse strain NOD-DQ8, led to a proinflammatory synergistic effect and impairment of gut barrier function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Our results raise the intriguing hypothesis thattype I IFNs constitute an important contributor to the loss of tolerance to dietary antigens such as gluten, after a viral infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>This may be particularly important in genetically susceptible hosts, by promoting inflammation as well as a biased Th1 response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that this may provide a mechanistic explanation for the clinical link between enteric infections and post-inflammatory and functional disorders [11], [12], [39], [40], [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0099236.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Different molecular weight poly I:Cs cause enteropathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Analysis of different molecular weight poly I:Cs by ethidium bromide-stained agarose gel electrophoresis, commercial poly I:C (PICs) (Sigma-Aldrich), PICL (LMW-PIC) and PICH (HMW-PIC) (Invivogen) (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Morphological analysis performed in C57BL/6 mice intraluminally treated with PICs, PICL or PICH in a time-course experiment (from 12 up to 72hs) (B): V/C ratio vs. time (i); V/C ratio at 72h post-treatment with different poly I:Cs or PBS (ii); Histological score at 12h and 72h after different poly I:Cs treatments (iii). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(Stats: N =  4 mice per group, Unpaired t test, *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0099236.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The original breeding pairs of NOD-DQ8 mice were kindly provided by Dr. Chella David and Dr. Joseph Murray from Mayo Clinic, Rochester, USA. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0099236-Honda1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>1 HondaK, TakedaK (2009) Regulatory mechanisms of immune responses to intestinal bacteria. Mucosal Immunology 2: 187–196.19262502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Garside1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>2 GarsideP, FelsteinMV, GreenEA, MowatAM (1991) The role of interferon alpha/beta in the induction of intestinal pathology in mice. Immunology 74: 279–283.1748474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>3 ZhouR, WeiH, SunC, ZhangJ, TianZ (2007) NKG2D recognition mediates TLR3 signaling-induced breakdown of epithelial homeostasis in the small intestine of mice. PNAS 104: 7512–7515.17463084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Zhou2"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>4 ZhouR, WeiH, SunR, TianZ (2007) Recognition of double-stranded RNA by TLR3 induces severe small intestinal injury in mice. The Journal of Immunology 178: 4548–4556.17372013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-McAllister1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>5 McAllisterCS, LakhdariO, Pineton de ChambrunG, GareauMG, BroquetA, et al (2013) TLR3, TRIF, and Caspase 8 Determine Double-Stranded RNA-Induced Epithelial Cell Death and Survival In Vivo. The Journal of Immunology 190: 418–427.23209324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Weber1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>6 WeberF, WagnerV, RasmussenSB, HartmannR, PaludanSR (2006) Double-Stranded RNA Is Produced by Positive-Strand RNA Viruses and DNA Viruses but Not in Detectable Amounts by Negative-Strand RNA Viruses. Journal of Virology 80: 5059–5064.16641297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Broquet1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>7 BroquetAH, HirataY, McAllisterCS, KagnoffMF (2011) RIG-I/MDA5/MAVS Are Required To Signal a Protective IFN Response in Rotavirus-Infected Intestinal Epithelium. The Journal of Immunology 186: 1618–1626.21187438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Iwamura1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>8 IwamuraT, YoneyamaM, YamaguchiK, SuharaW, MoriW, et al (2001) Induction of IRF-3/-7 kinase and NF-κB in response to double-stranded RNA and virus infection: common and unique pathways. Genes to Cells 6: 375–388.11318879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Marshall1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>9 MarshallJK, ThabaneM, BorgaonkarMR, JamesC (2007) Postinfectious Irritable Bowel Syndrome After a Food-Borne Outbreak of Acute Gastroenteritis Attributed to a Viral Pathogen. Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology 5: 457–460.17289440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Verdu1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>10 VerduEF (2012) Editorial: Differences in Intestinal Microbial Composition in Children With IBS-What Does It All Mean? American Journal of Gastroenterology 107: 1752–1754.23160293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Stene1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>11 SteneLC, HoneymanMC, HoffenbergEJ, HaasJE, SokolRJ, et al (2006) Rotavirus Infection Frequency and Risk of Celiac Disease Autoimmunity in Early Childhood: A Longitudinal Study. American Journal of Gastroenterology 101: 2333–2340.17032199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Troncone1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>12Troncone R, Auricchio S (2007) Rotavirus and Celiac Disease: Clues to the Pathogenesis and Perspectives on Prevention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Journal of Pediatric Gastroenterology and Nutrition 44: 527-528 510.1097/MPG.1090b1013e31804ca31800ec. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Verdu2"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>13 VerduEF, MauroM, BourgeoisJ, ArmstrongD (2007) Clinical onset of celiac disease after an episode of Campylobacter jejuni enteritis. Canada Journal of Gastroenterology 21: 453–455. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Sollid1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>14 SollidLM, JabriB (2013) Triggers and drivers of autoimmunity: lessons from coeliac disease. Nature Reviews Immunology 13: 294–302. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Galipeau1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>15Galipeau HJ, Rulli NE, Jury J, Huang X, Araya R, et al. (2011) Sensitization to Gliadin Induces Moderate Enteropathy and Insulitis in Nonobese Diabetic-DQ8 Mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The Journal of Immunology. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Marietta1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>16 MariettaE, BlackK, CamilleriM, KrauseP, RogersRSIII, et al (2004) A new model for dermatitis herpetiformis that uses HLA-DQ8 transgenic NOD mice. The Journal of Clinical Investigation 114: 1090–1097.15489956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Biagi1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>17 BiagiF, LuinettiO, CampanellaJ, KlersyC, ZambelliC, et al (2004) Intraepithelial lymphocytes in the villous tip: do they indicate potential coeliac disease? Journal of Clinical Pathology 57: 835–839.15280404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Quaedackers1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>18 QuaedackersJSLT, BeukRJ, BennetL, CharltonA, oude EgbrinkMG, et al (2000) An evaluation of methods for grading histologic injury following ischemia/reperfusion of the small bowel. Transplantation Proceedings 32: 1307–1310.10995960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Verdu3"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>19 VerduEF, HuangX, NatividadJ, LuJ, BlennerhassettPA, et al (2008) Gliadin-dependent neuromuscular and epithelial secretory responses in gluten-sensitive HLA-DQ8 transgenic mice. American Journal of Physiology - Gastrointestinal and Liver Physiology 294: G217–G225.18006603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-deKauwe1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>20 de KauweA, ChenZ, AndersonRP, KeechCL, PriceJD, et al (2009) Resistance to coeliac disease in humanized HLADR3 DQ2 transgenic mice expressing specific anti-gliadin CD4+ T cells. The Journal of Immunology 182: 7440–7450.19494267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Bustin1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>21 BustinSA, BenesV, GarsonJA, HellemansJ, HuggettJ, et al (2009) The MIQE Guidelines: Minimum Information for Publication of Quantitative Real-Time PCR Experiments. Clinical Chemistry 55: 611–622.19246619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Suwanai1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>22 SuwanaiH, WilcoxMA, MathisD, BenoistC (2010) A defective Il15 allele underlies the deficiency in natural killer cell activity in nonobese diabetic mice. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 107: 9305–9310. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-stvik1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>23Østvik AE, Granlund Av, Bugge M, Nilsen NJ, Torp SH, et al. (2013) Enhanced Expression of CXCL10 in Inflammatory Bowel Disease: Potential Role of Mucosal Toll-like Receptor 3 Stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases 19: 265–274 210.1002/ibd.23034. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Groom1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>24 GroomJR, LusterAD (2011) CXCR3 in T cell function. Experimental Cell Research 317: 620–631.21376175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Bondar1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>25 BondarC, ArayaRE, GuzmanL, RuaEC, ChopitaN, et al (2014) Role of CXCR3/CXCL10 Axis in Immune Cell Recruitment into the Small Intestine in Celiac Disease. PLoS ONE 9: e89068.24586509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Siegel1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>26 SiegelM, StrnadP, WattsRE, ChoiK, JabriB, et al (2008) Extracellular Transglutaminase 2 Is Catalytically Inactive, but Is Transiently Activated upon Tissue Injury. PLoS ONE 3: e1861.18365016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Bayardo1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>27 BayardoM, PunziF, BondarC, ChopitaN, ChirdoF (2012) Transglutaminase 2 expression is enhanced synergistically by interferon-γ and tumour necrosis factor-α in human small intestine. Clinical &amp; Experimental Immunology 168: 95–104.22385244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Verdu4"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>28 VerduEF, ArmstrongD, MurrayJA (2009) Between Celiac Disease and Irritable Bowel Syndrome: The "No Man's Land" of Gluten Sensitivity. American Journal of Gastroenterology 104: 1587–1594.19455131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Rajagopalan1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>29 RajagopalanG, KudvaYC, FlavellRA, DavidCS (2003) Accelerated Diabetes in Rat Insulin Promoter-Tumor Necrosis Factor-α Transgenic Nonobese Diabetic Mice Lacking Major Histocompatibility Class II Molecules. Diabetes 52: 342–347.12540606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Natividad1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>30 NatividadJM, HuangX, SlackE, JuryJ, SanzY, et al (2009) Host Responses to Intestinal Microbial Antigens in Gluten-Sensitive Mice. PLoS ONE 4: e6472.19649259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Black1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>31 BlackKE, MurrayJA, DavidCS (2002) HLA-DQ Determines the Response to Exogenous Wheat Proteins: A Model of Gluten Sensitivity in Transgenic Knockout Mice. The Journal of Immunology 169: 5595–5600.12421937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Turner1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>32 TurnerJR (2009) Intestinal mucosal barrier function in health and disease. Nature Reviews Immunology 9: 799–809. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Kolodziej1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>33 KolodziejLE, LodolceJP, ChangJE, SchneiderJR, GrimmWA, et al (2011) TNFAIP3 Maintains Intestinal Barrier Function and Supports Epithelial Cell Tight Junctions. PLoS ONE 6: e26352.22031828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Clemente1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>34 ClementeMG, De VirgiliisS, KangJS, MacatagneyR, MusuMP, et al (2003) Early effects of gliadin on enterocyte intracellular signalling involved in intestinal barrier function. Gut 52: 218–223.12524403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Heyman1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>35 HeymanM, AbedJ, LebretonC, Cerf-BensussanN (2012) Intestinal permeability in coeliac disease: insight into mechanisms and relevance to pathogenesis. Gut 61: 1355–1364.21890812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Nanayakkara1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>36 NanayakkaraM, LaniaG, MaglioM, DiscepoloV, SarnoM, et al (2013) An undigested gliadin peptide activates innate immunity and proliferative signaling in enterocytes: the role in celiac disease. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition 98: 1123–1135.23966426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-DePaolo1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>37 DePaoloRW, AbadieV, TangF, Fehlner-PeachH, HallJA, et al (2011) Co-adjuvant effects of retinoic acid and IL-15 induce inflammatory immunity to dietary antigens. Nature 471: 220–224.21307853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Barone1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>38 BaroneMV, ZanziD, MaglioM, NanayakkaraM, SantagataS, et al (2011) Gliadin-Mediated Proliferation and Innate Immune Activation in Celiac Disease Are Due to Alterations in Vesicular Trafficking. PLoS ONE 6: e17039.21364874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Marshall2"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>39 MarshallJK, ThabaneM, GargAX, ClarkWF, MoayyediP, et al (2010) Eight year prognosis of postinfectious irritable bowel syndrome following waterborne bacterial dysentery. Gut 59: 605–611.20427395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Marshall3"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>40 MarshallJK, ThabaneM, GargAX, ClarkWF, SalvadoriM, et al (2006) Incidence and Epidemiology of Irritable Bowel Syndrome After a Large Waterborne Outbreak of Bacterial Dysentery. Gastroenterology 131: 445–450.16890598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0099236-Garg1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>41 GargAX, MarshallJ, SalvadoriM, Thiessen-PhilbrookHR, MacnabJ, et al (2006) A gradient of acute gastroenteritis was characterized, to assess risk of long-term health sequelae after drinking bacterial-contaminated water. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 59: 421–428.16549265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
