<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?ManuscriptPrefix new?><?iso-abbr Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.?><?submitter-system ukmss?><?submitter-userid 7725?><?submitter-authority WT?><?submitter-login s_radford?><?submitter-name Sheena E Radford?><?domain wtpa?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9107784</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">8602</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Opin Struct Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Current opinion in structural biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0959-440X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1879-033X</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4499843</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25710390</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbi.2015.02.001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">ems62612</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Force-induced remodelling of proteins and their complexes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>Sheena E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brockwell</surname><given-names>David J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Astbury Centre for Structural Molecular Biology, University of Leeds, Leeds LS2 9JT, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>School of Molecular and Cellular Biology, University of Leeds, Leeds LS2 9JT, UK
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Corresponding authors: Radford, Sheena E (<email>S.E.Radford@leeds.ac.uk</email>) and Brockwell, David J (<email>D.J.Brockwell@leeds.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Force can drive conformational changes in proteins, as well as modulate their stability and the affinity of their complexes, allowing a mechanical input to be converted into a biochemical output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>These properties have been utilised by nature and force is now recognised to be widely used at the cellular level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The effects of force on the biophysical properties of biological systems can be large and varied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>As these effects are only apparent in the presence of force, studies on the same proteins using traditional ensemble biophysical methods can yield apparently conflicting results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Where appropriate, therefore, force measurements should be integrated with other experimental approaches to understand the physiological context of the system under study. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P2"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The first mechanical unfolding experiment was carried out almost 20 years ago and since this time great strides have been made in understanding the relationship of mechanical stability to the structure of proteins/protein complexes and their thermodynamic or kinetic stability (see [1] and [2]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This knowledge is important because the mechanical perturbation of bio-molecular conformation affects the stability of bio-molecules, their affinity for ligands and binding partners and even their catalytic efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>As these parameters control many of the basic processes that occur in cells, force has been implicated in processes as diverse as catalysis, signal transduction, protein degradation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Importantly, even the relatively small forces that are encountered in vivo can result in large changes to structure and/or affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the application of force in vivo can alter biological activity in a manner that cannot be recapitulated in the absence of force in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In the last few years our knowledge of the effects of force in biology, gained using single-molecule experimental and theoretical approaches, has allowed the effects of force to be delineated for relatively simple systems in vitro, as well as more complex systems found in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In this review, we briefly describe the single molecule force techniques utilised to probe bio-molecular interactions and the underlying theories and models used to interpret the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>By reference to the recent literature, we then focus on the main topic of this review: progress in unravelling the roles of mechanical force in cellular systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Measuring and analysing the effects of force on bio-molecules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P3"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>To analyse and understand the effects of force at the molecular level it is necessary to manipulate single bio-molecules or perturb their environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This review discusses three commonly used techniques that achieve this feat: atomic force microscopy (AFM), optical or magnetic tweezers and patch clamping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>As summarised in Figure 1 each method has its own optimal force and distance resolutions and experimental limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The application of AFM to force measurements (sometimes called force spectroscopy or dynamic force spectroscopy, DFS) has gained widespread use in biology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is able to measure single molecule stretching and rupture forces directly with subnanometer distance and picoNewton force resolution [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This technique is typically used to measure relatively high forces in biological terms (pN — nN) at relatively high extension rates (10–10000 nm s−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>However, both limitations have been addressed by the use of uncoated [4] and nano-engineered cantilevers [5•], pushing the lower force threshold to the subpicoNewton level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Tweezers use either light (laser tweezers/optical traps) or magnetic fields (magnetic tweezers) as the force transducer [6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Laser tweezers have been used to study processive motors, such as myosin [8], kinesin [9] and ClpX [10,11], while magnetic tweezers are applied most often to torque-generating proteins such as those that interact with DNA [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Both techniques are now being applied to study mechanical unfolding, with optical trapping technology able to study multiple folding/unfolding cycles of a single protein over many seconds [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>On-cell patch-clamp is an electrophysiological technique that is especially powerful for the study of single ion channels on intact cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>By attaching a micropipette to the cell membrane, the current created by a single ion channel can be recorded [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>For force studies, patch clamp offers the opportunity to assess the role of the lipid environment on membrane proteins by changing membrane tension or modulating lipid identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The utility of these techniques can also be enhanced by combining them with other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For example, the combination of force and fluorescence spectroscopy provides a powerful tool to gain information simultaneously on single molecule forces and conformational changes (including complex formation) induced by force [15,16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P4"><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>For most interactions, force acts to decrease the stability of the folded or bound state of a protein or complex relative to the unfolded or dissociated state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The effect of force can be thought of as a mechanical lever that tilts the underlying energy landscape with a magnitude that increases with distance from the native (or bound) state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Thus, in addition to stabilising the unfolded state, force also reduces the free energy barrier to unfolding (or unbinding). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>As these experiments are usually carried out far-from-equilibrium at a variety of extension rates, it is necessary to calculate the parameters that describe the unperturbed energy landscape (koff and xβ, see Figure 2) so that the results from different experiments can be compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In order to reveal kinetic parameters for the reactions of interest a dynamic force spectrum is measured by performing single molecule force spectroscopy at different loading rates [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>A plot of most likely rupture force versus force loading rate can be fitted to different analytical models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In the Bell–Evans model (Figure 2 left), it is assumed that the energy barrier is so deep that its position does not change, but the height of the escape barrier is lowered by the applied force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The most probable rupture force is then proportional to the natural logarithm of the loading rate [17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>A modification of the Bell–Evans model by applying Kramer’s diffusion theory was later proposed (Figure 2 middle) to avoid this assumption [19,20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Both models above ignore the possibility of reversible bond formation during the force spectroscopy, and have been challenged by the Friddle-De Yoreo model (Figure 2 right) [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In this recently developed model, it is assumed that at relatively low loading rates, there is another shallow barrier for rebinding; while at higher loading rates, this secondary barrier increases so that the probability of rebinding is reduced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="?"><plain>How do proteins and complexes respond to force? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P5"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>As can be inferred from the macroscopic world, the application of force usually decreases the lifetime of a non-covalent interaction (whether a single hydrogen bond or the multitude of interactions that stabilise the folded conformation of a protein or a bio-molecular complex). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Bonds that show an exponential decrease in lifetime with increased force as described in the Bell model [17–18] and its more sophisticated variants [19–21] are known as ‘slip bonds’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In this case force acts as a denaturant by diminishing barriers to unfolding/unbinding to the extent that the protein unfolds/unbinds at some characteristic force or timescale due to thermal fluctuations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Application of even the relatively small forces that are usually applied to single complexes in vivo (&lt;40 pN [22,23]) reduces the lifetimes of proteins and their complexes exponentially, allowing the dissociation of high affinity interactions to take place on a physiologically relevant timescale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This is exemplified by recent work from Tolar and colleagues [24••] who investigated the role of force in the early steps of the humoral immune response that culminates in the generation of high affinity antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Antibody generation is initiated by the binding of B cell receptors (BCRs) to a specific antigen on the surface of antigen presenting cells (APCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>B cells were found to actively pull out finger-like protrusions from APCs before internalising both lipid and antigen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The authors were able to show that BCR:antigen complexes with higher affinities and, therefore, longer lifetimes under force (measured by DFS experiments using the AFM) showed a greater internalisation of antigen-containing membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>As the lifetime of the force transduction network is longer-lived for cognate BCR:antigen interactions relative to low affinity non-cognate complexes, application of force allows selection of high affinity antibodies over a physiologically relevant timescale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P6"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>If the unfolding pathways in the presence and absence of force are identical (i.e. there is no force-induced remodelling) then the force-induced off rates, when extrapolated to zero applied force, should be identical to the intrinsic thermally-induced unfolding/unbinding rate, as found for the unbinding of antibody: antigen complexes [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>This parity is thought to arise due to the presence of a mechanically strong clamp between the complementarity determining region in the antibody domains and the point of force application that prevents any force-induced remodelling of the complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>However, force effects can still be induced in antibody:antigen complexes by immobilising bivalent antibodies onto surfaces displaying epitopes at regular, but non-ideal, intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The strain introduced into immobilised antibodies decreases complex affinity to such an extent that, when imaged by fast scan AFM, IgGs display bipedal stochastic ‘walking’ [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The Fab variant of the same IgG immobilised onto the same surface, by contrast, remained stationary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Force can thus act allosterically to alter complex affinity markedly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Recent work on the Ca2+-activated actin-binding protein, gelsolin [27] has demonstrated that the effects of force can also be quite subtle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>For this protein, application of a force as low as 10 pN was found to increase the binding affinity of gelsolin for Ca2+ more than five-fold, suggesting that gelsolin may be activated at lower [Ca2+] than previously recognised when subjected to tensile forces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Introduction of strain into an enzyme (via tethering the N- and C-termini to a DNA spring) can also alter enzyme activity [28,29], opening the door to force-modulated catalysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>As the strength of covalent bonds is also reduced under force (see [30–32]), it is not surprising that chemo-mechanical effects have been observed for reactions of small molecules [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For example, Fernandez and colleagues have shown, using AFM force measurements, that the catalytic rate of thioredoxin is force sensitive [33] and that this AFM technique can be used to probe catalytic mechanisms [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Larger remodelling events </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P7"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>At a longer length-scale force can induce conformational re-arrangements leading to allosteric activation or inhibition of a protein or protein complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>One notable case is titin which, in addition to its structural role, can act as a strain sensor, triggering muscle adaptation upon detection of mechanical strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>At physiologically relevant forces, low enough to maintain titin’s structural domains in the folded state (&lt;50 pN), the C-terminal kinase domain unfolds via a multistep pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Early in the unfolding process the C-terminal tail of the kinase domain unravels from the remainder of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Extension in this way activates the kinase by both allowing access of ATP to its binding site (which in the absence of force is occluded by the C-terminus) and by triggering autophosphorylation of a tyrosine residue that inhibits activity [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Force is also integral to outside-in and inside-out signal transduction between cells and their surroundings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane proteins such as integrins are vital to this network, linking the extra-cellular matrix with the actin cytoskeleton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Many adaptor proteins are involved in this signal transduction pathway, with filamin playing a central role [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>At the molecular level, filamin complex formation is driven by a β-strand augmentation of the 21st immunoglobulin-like domain of filamin A (FLNa21) by the β-integrin tail (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Under no force, FLNa21 cannot bind to integrin due to occlusion of the binding site by the N-terminal β-strand of the preceding filamin domain (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Rognoni et al. [37] investigated the mechanical behaviour of the auto-inhibited state and showed that the force-dependent gating characteristics of filamin allow for a cellular response to surprisingly low forces (the affinity for the C-terminal tail peptides of different interaction partners is increased up to seventeen fold upon increasing applied force from to 2 to 5 pN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The same authors then showed that switching between the auto-inhibited and activated state is enabled by cis–trans isomerisation of a proline residue in the force sensing domain (FLNa20), weakening the stability of the auto-inhibited state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Whilst cis–trans isomerisation does result in bond lengthening, the authors suggest that force induced unfolding accelerates this isomerisation, rather than force driving isomerisation per se [38•]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Local unfolding prevents global unfolding or unbinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P8"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In addition to direct signal transduction, mechanical deformation can also prolong bond lifetime (i.e. maintenance of native structure or complex) by reducing the level of force acting upon it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Such mechanisms have been postulated for the all-β proteins tensacin and Mel-CAM [39,40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Given the relative strengths of α- and β-structures (see later) it may be expected that more sensitive safety latches could be achieved using the former, mechanically weaker, secondary structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This is indeed the case for myomesin, a tandemly-arrayed dimeric multi-modular protein found in the M-band of the muscle sarcomere which has an unusual α-helical linker separating each Ig domain [41,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The α-helical segments were found to unfold at a much lower force than the Ig domains (24 and 83 pN, respectively [43]) and underwent folding/unfolding transitions at low loading rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These helices, therefore, act as fast and reversible latches to ensure the structural integrity of the M-band. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P9"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Partial unfolding of one binding partner can also increase complex lifetime by decreasing the force being loaded onto it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For example, bacterial pili are long proteinaceous structures emanating from bacterial outer membranes that are used for a variety of functions including host colonisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>As this process may involve hydrodynamic shear forces, all of the non-covalent linkages connecting the host to the bacterium must be able to survive force-loading for effective colonisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In type I pili, this is achieved by donor strand exchange between inherently mechanically strong Ig-like domains (Figure 3b) and the unwinding of the helical quaternary structure of the pilus at low force [44–46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Type IV pili, involved in the pathogenicity of Neisseria gonorrheae and Pseudomonas aeruginosa, have a different quaternary structure, precluding such a mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Instead, under force, these pili lengthen via a conformational re-arrangement and also display ‘nanospring’ behaviour (displacement proportional to force) with a spring constant of 2 pN nm−1 [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Similar (though indirect results) have recently been reported for the effects of inhibitor binding on the mechanical strength of domains 1 and 2 of CD4 (the primary receptor for gp120 on the surface HIV-1) [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that HIV infectivity would be expected to increase with increasing length of the ‘tether’ connecting the virus to the cell, which has previously been observed [49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="?"><plain>Can the unfolding behaviour of proteins be predicted? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P10"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>As discussed above, different types of secondary structure behave differently under force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The relationship between structure and mechanical strength was studied in great detail soon after the emergence of force spectroscopy and a wide variety of protein structures have been unfolded by force methods (both experimentally and by simulations) since 1997 [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>These studies have shown that α-helical proteins are mechanically weak, β-sheet proteins are mechanically strong, while proteins with mixed topologies display varied responses [51–54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The difference in mechanical strength between proteins containing different secondary structural elements is thought to arise as a consequence of the localised nature of force application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In such a model, the height of the rate limiting transition state for unfolding is governed by the strength of interactions between amino-acids which bear the loaded force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The array of non-covalent interactions between adjacent β-strands in β-sheet proteins provides more stability against local mechanical deformation than the hydrophobic contacts between helices which can unfold in a stepwise, sequential manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This difference appears to have been exploited by nature, as while both types of protein are used in mechano-transduction pathways, their roles are quite distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The low mechanical strength of α-helical proteins is utilised to facilitate unfolding, allowing exposure of novel binding sites for proteins that either strengthen these complexes or trigger a signalling event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>For example, α-catenin (Figure 3c) and talin (Figure 3d) are all α-proteins which cross link cadherins to actomyosin or integrins to actin, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Each, therefore has a key role in mechano-sensing (at cell–cell adhesions and focal adhesions, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Using magnetic tweezers and AFM, talin was found to unfold at ~40 pN [16], whereas α-catenin unfolded in three steps: a reversible step at around 5 pN and two non-equilibrium steps at 10–15 pN [55•]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The outcome for both proteins is similar in that the initial unfolding events expose cryptic binding sites for vinculin (Figure 3c,d), a protein that stabilises adhesions, converting force to a biochemical signal. β-sheet proteins, by contrast, are employed if the non-covalent complex is required to resist breakage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>As described for filamin above, many such interactions are mediated by β-strand augmentation or complementation [56], whereby a single β-stranded peptide binds to the β-sheet of its partner, forming a mechanically long-lived complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Such interactions are observed for filamin:integrin, type I bacterial pili (Figure 3b) [57], and interactions between proteins that span the periplasm of Gram negative bacteria (Figure 3e) [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Our understanding of the mechanical stability of small, topologically simple domains has also led to the ability to design protein-based hydrogels, with dramatically improved flexibility and toughness [59•]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P11"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>While protein topology governs the molecular response to extension to a large degree, the stability of the mechanical interface (the parts of a protein that resist the applied extension) can also affect protein mechanical strength and the degree of co-operativity upon unfolding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>For example, molecular dynamics simulations demonstrated that protein L (a protein that is expressed on the outer cell wall of some bacteria but has no known mechanical function) unfolds by the shearing of two mechanical subdomains with an interface between neighbouring anti-parallel N- and C-terminal β-strands [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Increasing the hydrophobic contacts (or inter-digitation of side-chains) across this interface increased the mechanical strength of protein L from 134 to 206 pN [61]. In vitro unfolding studies on simple protein polymers have also shown that the mechanical strength of a protein depends on the direction of force application relative to the topology of the secondary structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A protein may thus be able to resist mechanical deformation when force is applied in one geometry, but be weak when force is applied in another direction (similar to pulling apart Velcro). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The anisotropic response of proteins and their complexes to force has now been demonstrated many times [62–73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>These effects, which to a large part were delineated using engineered model poly-proteins unfolded by AFM in vitro, have led to the realisation that proteins and their complexes may exploit different unfolding pathways in the presence and absence of force, leading to force-catalysed or force-triggered phenomena in vivo [36,73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>For example, we have shown that mechanical perturbation remodels the interface of an exceedingly stable complex (Kd = 10−14 M, koff = 1.8 × 10−6 s−1) formed between the bacterial antibiotic nuclease colicin E9 and its inhibitor, immunity protein 9 (Im9) so that dissociation occurs at a surprisingly low force (&lt;20 pN) [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Examination of the N-terminal sequence of E9 (through which force or remodelling is applied or carried out in vivo) showed that this region docks against the remainder of the globular domain with little side-chain inter-digitation (see Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>As described for protein L, this is ideal for transmitting mechanical signals to the binding interface at low force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Remodelling increases the off-rate a million-fold relative to that expected for a slip bond, allowing Im9 release and E9 activation at a biologically relevant rate upon binding to a competing organism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The effects of force on proteins are varied </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P12"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>As the properties of proteins and their complexes can differ in the absence and presence of mechanical deformation, these effects must be accounted for when force is thought to be present in a cellular context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>This is illustrated in the investigation of adhesion junction assembly. In vivo experiments have shown that intercellular adhesion junctions are linked to the actin cytoskeleton via an E-cadherin:β-catenin:αEcatenin complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>This allows force transduction across cells, giving shape and driving morphogenetic changes during development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>By contrast with in vivo experiments, this complex was found to bind to actin too weakly to allow mechano-transduction in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As this complex presumably forms under tension in vivo, Buckley et al. [74••] investigated the effect of force by sequentially forming and breaking the interaction between E-cadherin:β-catenin:αEcatenin and an actin filament suspended between two optically trapped beads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Instead of a decrease in lifetime, as would be expected from a slip bond, the lifetime of the E-cadherin:β-catenin:αEcatenin:actin complex was found to increase under increasing force before decreasing like a slip bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This type of interaction, called a ‘catch-bond’ [75], is reminiscent of a molecular-scale finger trap toy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Catch bonds are observed in several protein complexes that have evolved to withstand hydrodynamic shear forces such as the interactions that mediate the immobilisation of uropathogenic E. coli to bladder epithelial cells [76]) and leukocyte rolling on the extracellular surface of endothelial cells of blood vessels [77,78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>At the macroscopic level, a widely-accepted explanation of this phenomenon is that, under force, the proteins undergo topological rearrangements, transitioning from low to high affinity states [74••]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Manibog et al. [79] investigated Ca2+-dependent catch-bond formation between pairs of cadherins using both molecular dynamics simulations and AFM force spectroscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>These investigations revealed that cadherins exhibit decreased conformational flexibility in the presence Ca2+. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Application of force pulled these rigidified dimers into register, forming long lived, de novo hydrogen bonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The same underlying mechanism (the de novo formation of force-induced interactions) was also recently proposed by applying a theoretical approach to analyse ligand–receptor protein complexes (selectin and integrin receptors) [80]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P13"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In addition to slip bonds and catch bonds, other more complex behaviour can be observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Springer and colleagues [81] used laser tweezers to study the forced unbinding behaviour of the A1 domain of von Willibrand Factor from glycoprotein 1b α subunit (GPIbα) present on the surface of platelets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Two dissociation pathways were observed and while both behaved as slip bonds, each predominated at different force loading rates, with the more force resistant pathway being followed at higher loading rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The authors termed such behaviour as a ‘flex bond’ and suggested that the second state may take part in the early events in platelet interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>As described above, under mechanical extension of the N-terminus, the high affinity E9:Im9 complex dissociates at a low force (short lifetime) due to remodelling of the binding interface [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>If this remodelling is prevented by locking the N-terminus to the rest of protein (via a disulfide bond between residues 20 and 66, Figure 4), the force required to unbind the complex increases from 34 to 102 pN at a force loading rate of 2980 pN s−1, yielding an off rate extrapolated to zero force that is identical to that measured by ensemble methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that the E9:Im9 complex demonstrates behaviour akin to a trip wire: in solution E9:Im9 is stable with a dissociation rate of 10−6 s−1 (which can only be measured in AFM experiments by introducing specific cross-linking). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Upon binding to a competing bacterium, remodelling of the E9:Im9 interface converts a complex that is very stable in the absence of force to a labile one, leading to colicin activation and cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We term such interactions ‘trip bonds’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>For colicin function, a trip bond meets the seemingly mutually exclusive requirements of providing long term protection to the host, yet permiting the facile dissociation of immunity protein that is required for cell invasion of bacterial competitors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Membrane proteins as mechanosensors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P14"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As expected from their location at the cell boundary, membrane proteins are also used as force sensors for both signal transduction and homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In principle, a mechanical signal may drive conformational changes by altering the lipid bilayer (by changes in curvature stress, bilayer thinning and lipid composition [82]), by direct mechanical activation, by gating of intra- or extra-cellular domains, or by a mixture of all three. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Gating is exemplified by ankyrin repeat sequences found in cytoplasmic domains of transient receptor potential (TRP) channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>These proteins were found, using AFM [83], to behave as nano-scale Hookean springs and are thus candidates for gating tethers for mechanoreceptors in sensory hair cells as well as in Drosophila bristles [84–86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The yeast transmembrane Wsc1 cell surface sensor displays similar nano-spring behaviour whose stiffness is sensitive to growth conditions [87]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P15"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>While single molecule force experiments have been used to investigate the extension of soluble nano-springs and the mechanical stability of membrane proteins [88,89], other techniques are required to test the ‘force-from-lipid’ principle [90]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Patch clamp methods can measure the effect of lipid composition and tension (by changing the pressure applied to the patch) on the activity or one or more channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In many ways patch clamping can be regarded as the first single molecule technique and was used in the early 1990s to show that the bacterial membrane channel protein, MscL, switched between closed and open states upon application of tension when reconstituted into synthetic liposomes [91]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Later work has shown, as expected, that liposome composition affects the electrophysiological properties of this protein and MscS, another mechanosensitive bacterial membrane protein [92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>By sensing membrane tension, MscL acts as a safety valve, allowing passage of solutes into bacteria when they encounter a hypo-osmolar environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The activity of TRAAK and TREK1 K+ channels has also been reported to be modulated by membrane tension [93,94] and composition [94], demonstrating that eukaryotic organisms also utilise these force sensors to modulate or control biological function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS,CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="S9"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Conclusions and perspectives </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P16"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The ability to manipulate single proteins and their complexes has led to an understanding of the effects of force on ‘bond’ lifetime. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>These studies, performed in vitro on either simple model proteins or minimal ‘in vivo’ models, have revealed a rich response of proteins and their complexes to mechanical deformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These effects are diverse in nature and can be large in magnitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Thus it is vital to integrate force data with those derived from traditional ensemble methods to fully understand systems in a cellular context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To do this, the force applied to proteins in vivo must be quantified for the system under study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Currently it remains challenging to use standard force probes in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Progress, however, is being made in quantifying force in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Force spectrum microscopy, has revealed that the activity of cellular motors is the dominant cause of force fluctuations in vivo and that the magnitude of the fluctuation can be related to the physiological status of the cell [95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Direct readout of applied forces in vivo has been achieved using two related, but distinct, fluorescence techniques that utilise the ability of Förster resonance energy transfer methods to report on changes in distance induced in a biosensor of known mechanical strength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Gratifyingly, these studies have shown that the forces applied in extracellular adhesion, in Notch signalling and across vinculin in focal adhesions are similar to those being measured in vitro (~12, 40 and 2.5 pN, respectively) [23,96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The ability to calibrate the force-induced effects observed for a particular system in vitro to the precise force levels applied to the same system in vivo is very powerful and will yield insight into the rich and varied effects of force in nature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="S10"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank the Brockwell and Radford laboratories for helpful discussions and comments on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge the BBSRC (BB/G019452/1, DJB and SER) and the ERC ((FP7/2007-2013)/ERC grant agreement no. 32240 (YC, SER and DJB) for funding. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P17"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P18"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Nothing declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References and recommended reading</title><p>Papers of particular interest, published within the period of review, have been highlighted as:</p><p>• of special interest</p><p>•• of outstanding interest</p><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>1CramptonNBrockwellDJUnravelling the design principles for single protein mechanical strengthCurr Opin Struct Biol20102050851720542682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>2WoodsideMTBlockSMReconstructing folding energy landscapes by single-molecule force spectroscopyAnn Rev Biophys2014431939<?supplied-pmid 24895850?>24895850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>3HinterdorferPDufreneYFDetection and localization of single molecular recognition events using atomic force microscopyNat Methods2006334735516628204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>4ChurnsideABSullanRMNguyenDMCaseSOBullMSKingGMPerkinsTTRoutine and timely subpicoNewton force stability and precision for biological applications of atomic force microscopyNano Lett2012123557356122694769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>5 •BullMSSullanRMLiHPerkinsTTImproved single molecule force spectroscopy using micromachined cantileversACS Nano201484984499524670198Force spectroscopy using the AFM is limited by instrument stability and force sensitivity precluding the measurement of small forces over long periods of time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>This paper obviates these limitations by minimising the gold coating on the back of a short cantilever and reducing the spring constant by removing the central portion of the cantilever using a focussed ion beam ‘machining’ approach. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>6PerkinsTTAngstrom-precision optical traps and applicationsAnn Rev Biophys20144327930224773015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>7De VlaminckIDekkerCRecent advances in magnetic tweezersAnn Rev Biophys20124145347222443989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>8SellersJRVeigelCDirect observation of the myosin-Va power stroke and its reversalNat Struct Mol Biol20101759059520418880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>9ClancyBEBehnke-ParksWMAndreassonJORosenfeldSSBlockSMA universal pathway for kinesin steppingNat Struct Mol Biol2011181020102721841789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>10MaillardRAChistolGSenMRighiniMTanJKaiserCMHodgesCMartinABustamanteCClpX(P) generates mechanical force to unfold and translocate its protein substratesCell201114545946921529717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>11Aubin-TamM-EOlivaresAOSauerRTBakerTALangMJSingle-molecule protein unfolding and translocation by an ATP-fueled proteolytic machineCell201114525726721496645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>12KlaueDKobbeDKemmerichFKozikowskaAPuchtaHSeidelRFork sensing and strand switching control antagonistic activities of RecQ helicasesNat Commun20134202423771268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>13StiglerJZieglerFGiesekeAGebhardtJCRiefMThe complex folding network of single calmodulin moleculesScience201133451251622034433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>14AndersenOSKoeppeREMolecular determinants of channel functionPhysiol Rev199272S89S1581279736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>15ZhouRSchlierfMHaTForce fluorescence spectroscopy at the single-molecule levelMethods Enzymol201047540542620627166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>16del RioAPerez-JimenezRLiuRCRoca-CusachsPFernandezJMSheetzMPStretching single talin rod molecules activates vinculin bindingScience200932363864119179532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>17EvansERitchieKDynamic strength of molecular adhesion bondsBiophys J199772154115559083660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>18EvansEProbing the relation between force — lifetime — and chemistry in single molecular bondsAnn Rev Biophys Biomol Struct20013010512811340054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>19HummerGSzaboAKinetics from nonequilibrium single-molecule pulling experimentsBiophys J20038551512829459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>20DudkoOKHummerGSzaboATheory, analysis, and interpretation of single-molecule force spectroscopy experimentsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2008105157551576018852468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>21FriddleRWNoyADe YoreoJJInterpreting the widespread nonlinear force spectra of intermolecular bondsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2012109135731357822869712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>22SmithDETansSJSmithSBGrimesSAndersonDLBustamanteCThe bacteriophage phi 29 portal motor can package DNA against a large internal forceNature200141374875211607035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>23WangXHaTDefining single molecular forces required to activate integrin and notch signalingScience201334099199423704575 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="?"><plain>24 ••NatkanskiELeeW-YMistryBCasalAMolloyJETolarPB cells use mechanical energy to discriminate antigen affinitiesScience20133401587159023686338Given the slow dissociation rates of most high affinity interactions, how are B-cells that express antibodies with high affinity for specific antigens selected on a physiologically relevant timescale? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Natkanski and colleagues show that, during internalisation, sufficient force is applied onto antigen:antibody complexes so that only high affinity interactions survive. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>25SchwesingerFRosRStrunzTAnselmettiDGuntherodtHJHoneggerAJermutusLTiefenauerLPluckthunAUnbinding forces of single antibody-antigen complexes correlate with their thermal dissociation ratesProc Natl Acad Sci USA2000979972997710963664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>26PreinerJKoderaNTangJEbnerABrameshuberMBlaasDGelbmannNGruberHJAndoTHinterdorferPIgGs are made for walking on bacterial and viral surfacesNat Commun20145439425008037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>27LvCGaoXLiWXueBQinMBurtnickLDZhouHCaoYRobinsonRCWangWSingle-molecule force spectroscopy reveals force-enhanced binding of calcium ions by gelsolinNat Commun20145462325100107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>28ChoiBZocchiGMimicking cAMP-dependent allosteric control of protein kinase a through mechanical tensionJ Am Chem Soc20061288541854816802820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>29TsengC-YZocchiGMechanical control of renilla luciferaseJ Am Chem Soc2013135118791188623863076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>30BustamanteCChemlaYRFordeNRIzhakyDMechanical processes in biochemistryAnn Rev Biochem20047370574815189157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>31BeyerMKClausen-SchaumannHMechanochemistry: the mechanical activation of covalent bondsChem Rev20051052921294816092823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>32YangQ-ZHuangZKucharskiTJKhvostichenkoDChenJBoulatovRA molecular force probeNat Nanotechnol2009430230619421215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>33WiitaAPPerez-JimenezRWaltherKAGraeterFBerneBJHolmgrenASanchez-RuizJMFernandezJMProbing the chemistry of thioredoxin catalysis with forceNature200745012412717972886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>34Perez-JimenezRIngles-PrietoAZhaoZ-MSanchez-RomeroIAlegre-CebolladaJKosuriPGarcia-ManyesSKappockTJTanokuraMHolmgrenASingle-molecule paleoenzymology probes the chemistry of resurrected enzymesNat Struct Mol Biol20111859259621460845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>35PuchnerEMAlexandrovichAKhoALHensenUSchaferLVBrandmeierBGraterFGrubmullerHGaubHEGautelMMechanoenzymatics of titin kinaseProc Natl Acad Sci USA2008105133851339018765796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>36EhrlicherAJNakamuraFHartwigJHWeitzDAStosselTPMechanical strain in actin networks regulates FilGAP and integrin binding to filamin ANature201147826026321926999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>37RognoniLStiglerJPelzBYlaenneJRiefMDynamic force sensing of filamin revealed in single-molecule experimentsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2012109196791968423150587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>38 •RognoniLMoestTZoldakGRiefMForce-dependent isomerization kinetics of a highly conserved proline switch modulates the mechanosensing region of filaminProc Natl Acad Sci USA20141115568557324706888A detailed study that uses optical tweezers to investigate the mechanism of filamin A mechanosensing at the molecular level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The authors build on previous work [37] to show that integrin binding on one domain of filamin is gated by the conformation of the prior filamin domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The affinity between the filamin pair complex is toggled by cis-trans proline isomerization which is triggered by force induced unfolding. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>39OberhauserAFMarszalekPEEricksonHPFernandezJMThe molecular elasticity of the extracellular matrix protein tenascinNature19983931811859603523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>40CarlPKwokCHMandersonGSpeicherDWDischerDEForced unfolding modulated by disulfide bonds in the Ig domains of a cell adhesion moleculeProc Natl Acad Sci USA2001981565157011171991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>41PinotsisNChatziefthimiouSDBerkemeierFBeuronFMavridisIMKonarevPVSvergunDIMorrisERiefMWilmannsMSuperhelical architecture of the myosin filament-linking protein myomesin with unusual elastic propertiesPLoS Biol201210e100126122347812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>42PinotsisNLangeSPerriardJ-CSvergunDIWilmannsMMolecular basis of the C-terminal tail-to-tail assembly of the sarcomeric filament protein myomesinEMBO J20082725326418059477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>43BerkemeierFBertzMXiaoSPinotsisNWilmannsMGraeterFRiefMFast-folding alpha-helices as reversible strain absorbers in the muscle protein myomesinProc Natl Acad Sci USA2011108141391414421825161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>44ForeroMYakovenkoOSokurenkoEVThomasWEVogelVUncoiling mechanics of Escherichia coli type I fimbriae are optimized for catch bondsPLoS Biol2006415091516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>45MillerEGarciaTHultgrenSOberhauserAFThe mechanical properties of E. coli type 1 pili measured by atomic force microscopy techniquesBiophys J2006913848385616950852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>46LugmaierRASchedinSKuehnerFBenoitMDynamic restacking of Escherichia coli P-piliEur Biophys J20083711112017554533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>47BeaussartABakerAEKuchmaSLEl-Kirat-ChatelSO’TooleGADufreneYFNanoscale adhesion forces of Pseudomonas aeruginosa type IV piliACS Nano20148107231073325286300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>48Perez-JimenezRAlonso-CaballeroABerkovichRFrancoDChenM-WRichardPBadillaCLFernandezJMProbing the effect of force on HIV-1 receptor CD4ACS Nano20148103131032025299596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>49FreemanMMSeamanMSRits-VollochSHongXKaoC-YHoDDChenBCrystal structure of HIV-1 primary receptor CD4 in complex with a potent antiviral antibodyStructure2010181632164121134642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>50RiefMGautelMOesterheltFFernandezJMGaubHEReversible unfolding of individual titin immunoglobulin domains by AFMScience1997276110911129148804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>51LuHSchultenKSteered molecular dynamics simulations of force-induced protein domain unfoldingProteins19993545346310382673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>52PaciEKarplusMUnfolding proteins by external forces and temperature: the importance of topology and energeticsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2000976521652610823892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>53KlimovDKThirumalaiDNative topology determines force-induced unfolding pathways in globular proteinsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2000977254725910860990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>54HoffmannTTychKMHughesMLBrockwellDJDouganLTowards design principles for determining the mechanical stability of proteinsPhys Chem Chem Phys201315157671578023989058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>55 •YaoMQiuWLiuREfremovAKCongPSeddikiRPayreMLimCTLadouxBMegeR-MForce-dependent conformational switch of alpha-catenin controls vinculin bindingNat Commun20145452525077739Magnetic tweezers are used to investigate the mechanical strength of α-catenin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>As expected for an all α-helical protein, α-catenin unfolds at low force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Addition of vinculin prevents refolding, allowing the authors to show that force-remodelling of α-catenin triggers high affinity vinculin binding, stabilising α-catenin in its open conformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>56RemautHWaksmanGProtein–protein interaction through beta-strand additionTrends Biochem Sci20063143644416828554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>57WaksmanGHultgrenSJStructural biology of the chaperone-usher pathway of pilus biogenesisNat Rev Microbiol2009776577419820722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>58ShultisDDPurdyMDBanchsCNWienerMCOuter membrane active transport: structure of the BtuB: TonB complexScience20063121396139916741124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>59 •FangJMehlichAKogaNHuangJKogaRGaoXHuCJinCRiefMKastJForced protein unfolding leads to highly elastic and tough protein hydrogelsNat Commun20134297424352111The development of a highly elastic and tough protein hydrogel is reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The hydrogel is composed of chains of mechanically weak ferredoxin-like folds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>This is an elegant demonstration of how understanding the mechanical strength of single protein molecules can be applied to other scientific disciplines. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>60BrockwellDJBeddardGSPaciEWestDKOlmstedPDSmithDARadfordSEMechanically unfolding the small, topologically simple protein LBiophys J20058950651915863479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R61"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>61SadlerDPPetrikETaniguchiYPullenJRKawakamiMRadfordSEBrockwellDJIdentification of a mechanical rheostat in the hydrophobic core of protein LJ Mol Biol200939323724819683005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R62"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>62BrockwellDJPaciEZinoberRCBeddardGSOlmstedPDSmithDAPerhamRNRadfordSEPulling geometry defines the mechanical resistance of a beta-sheet proteinNat Struct Biol20031073173712923573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R63"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>63Carrion-VazquezMLiHBLuHMarszalekPEOberhauserAFFernandezJMThe mechanical stability of ubiquitin is linkage dependentNat Struct Biol20031073874312923571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R64"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>64DietzHBerkemeierFBertzMRiefMAnisotropic deformation response of single protein moleculesProc Natl Acad Sci USA2006103127241272816908850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R65"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>65JagannathanBElmsPJBustamanteCMarquseeSDirect observation of a force-induced switch in the anisotropic mechanical unfolding pathway of a proteinProc Natl Acad Sci USA2012109178201782522949695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R66"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>66LiYDLamourGGsponerJZhengPLiHThe molecular mechanism underlying mechanical anisotropy of the protein GB1Biophys J20121032361236823283235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R67"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>67LeeWZengXRotoloKYangMSchofieldCJBennettVYangWMarszalekPEMechanical anisotropy of ankyrin repeatsBiophys J20121021118112622404934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R68"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>68JunkerJPRiefMEvidence for a broad transition-state ensemble in calmodulin folding from single-molecule force spectroscopyAngew Chem Int Ed Engl2010493306330920352635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R69"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>69GaoXQinMYinPLiangJWangJCaoYWangWSingle-molecule experiments reveal the flexibility of a Per-ARNT-Sim domain and the kinetic partitioning in the unfolding pathway under forceBiophys J20121022149215722824279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R70"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>70PopaIBerkovichRAlegre-CebolladaJBadillaCLRivas-PardoJATaniguchiYKawakamiMFernandezJMNanomechanics of HaloTag tethersJ Am Chem Soc2013135127621277123909704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R71"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>71ZhengPChouC-CGuoYWangYLiHSingle molecule force spectroscopy reveals the molecular mechanical anisotropy of the FeS4 metal center in rubredoxinJ Am Chem Soc2013135177831779224171546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R72"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>72BertzMWilmannsMRiefMThe titin–telethonin complex is a directed, superstable molecular bond in the muscle Z-diskProc Natl Acad Sci USA2009106133071331019622741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R73"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>73FarranceOEHannEKaminskaRHousdenNGDerringtonSRKleanthousCRadfordSEBrockwellDJA force-activated trip switch triggers rapid dissociation of a colicin from its immunity proteinPLoS Biol201311e100148923431269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R74"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>74 ••BuckleyCDTanJAndersonKLHaneinDVolkmannNWeisWINelsonWJDunnARCell adhesion: the minimal cadherin–catenin complex binds to actin filaments under forceScience2014346125421125359979A very clear example of the sometimes surprising effects that force exerts on non-covalent complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The authors use laser tweezers to investigate the effects of load on the binding of a minimal cadherin-catenin complex to actin and show, by contrast to ‘traditional’ biochemical experiments, that stable catch bonds are formed under load. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R75"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>75DemboMTorneyDCSaxmanKHammerDThe reaction-limited kinetics of membrane-to-surface adhesion and detachmentProc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci198823455832901109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R76"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>76ThomasWETrintchinaEForeroMVogelVSokurenkoEVBacterial adhesion to target cells enhanced by shear forceCell200210991392312110187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R77"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>77MarshallBTLongMPiperJWYagoTMcEverRPZhuCDirect observation of catch bonds involving cell-adhesion moleculesNature200342319019312736689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R78"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>78LouJYagoTKlopockiAGMehtaPChenWZarnitsynaVIBovinNVZhuCMcEverRPFlow-enhanced adhesion regulated by a selectin interdomain hingeJ Cell Biol20061741107111717000883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R79"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>79ManibogKLiHRakshitSSivasankarSResolving the molecular mechanism of cadherin catch bond formationNat Commun20145394124887573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R80"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>80ChakrabartiSHinczewskiMThirumalaiDPlasticity of hydrogen bond networks regulates mechanochemistry of cell adhesion complexesProc Natl Acad Sci USA20141119048905324927549 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R81"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>81KimJZhangCZZhangXHSpringerTAA mechanically stabilized receptor–ligand flex-bond important in the vasculatureNature201046699299520725043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R82"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>82HongHDTammLKElastic coupling of integral membrane protein stability to lipid bilayer forcesProc Natl Acad Sci USA20041014065407014990786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R83"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>83LeeGAbdiKJiangYMichaelyPBennettVMarszalekPENanospring behaviour of ankyrin repeatsNature200644024624916415852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R84"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>84HowardJBechstedtSHypothesis: a helix of ankyrin repeats of the NOMPIC-TRP ion channel is the gating spring of mechanoreceptorsCurr Biol200414R224R22615043829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R85"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>85CoreyDPGarcia-AnoverosJHoltJRKwanKYLinSYVollrathMAAmalfitanoACheungELDerflerBHDugganATRPA1 is a candidate for the mechanosensitive transduction channel of vertebrate hair cellsNature200443272373015483558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R86"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>86SotomayorMCoreyDPSchultenKIn search of the hair-cell gating spring: elastic properties of ankyrin and cadherin repeatsStructure20051366968215837205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R87"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>87DupresVAlsteensDWilkSHansenBHeinischJJDufreneYFThe yeast Wsc1 cell surface sensor behaves like a nanospring in vivoNat Chem Biol2009585786219767735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R88"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>88MullerDJAFM: a nanotool in membrane biologyBiochemistry2008477986799818616288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R89"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>89KesslerMGottschalkKEJanovjakHMullerDJGaubHEBacteriorhodopsin folds into the membrane against an external forceJ Mol Biol200635764465416434052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R90"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>90AnishkinALoukinSHTengJKungCFeeling the hidden mechanical forces in lipid bilayer is an original senseProc Natl Acad Sci USA20141117898790524850861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R91"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>91SukharevSIBlountPMartinacBBlattnerFRKungCA large-conductance mechanosensitive channel in E. coli encoded by MscL aloneNature19943682652687511799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R92"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>92NomuraTCranfieldCGDeplazesEOwenDMMacmillanABattleARConstantineMSokabeMMartinacBDifferential effects of lipids and lyso-lipids on the mechanosensitivity of the mechanosensitive channels MscL and MscSProc Natl Acad Sci USA20121098770877522586095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R93"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>93BerrierCPozzaADe lavaletteADLChardonnetSMesneauAJaxelCLe MaireMGhaziAThe purified mechanosensitive channel TREK-1 is directly sensitive to membrane tensionJ Biol Chem2013288273072731423897808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R94"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>94BrohawnSGSuZMacKinnonRMechanosensitivity is mediated directly by the lipid membrane in TRAAK and TREK1 K+ channelsProc Natl Acad Sci USA20141113614361924550493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R95"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>95GuoMEhrlicherAJJensenMHRenzMMooreJRGoldmanRDLippincott-SchwartzJMackintoshFCWeitzDAProbing the stochastic, motor-driven properties of the cytoplasm using force spectrum microscopyCell201415882283225126787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R96"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>96GrashoffCHoffmanBDBrennerMDZhouRParsonsMYangMTMcLeanMASligarSGChenCSHaTMeasuring mechanical tension across vinculin reveals regulation of focal adhesion dynamicsNature201046626326620613844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R97"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>97PettersenEFGoddardTDHuangCCCouchGSGreenblattDMMengECFerrinTEUCSF chimera — a visualization system for exploratory research and analysisJ Comput Chem2004251605161215264254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R98"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>98LadYKiemaTJiangPPentikaeinenOTColesCHCampbellIDCalderwoodDAYlaenneJStructure of three tandem filamin domains reveals auto-inhibition of ligand bindingEMBO J2007263993400417690686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R99"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>99KiemaTLadYJiangPJOxleyCLBaldassarreMWegenerKLCampbellIDYlanneJCalderwoodDAThe molecular basis of filamin binding to integrins and competition with talinMol Cell20062133734716455489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R100"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>100Le TrongIAprikianPKiddBAForero-SheltonMTchesnokovaVRajagopalPRodriguezVInterlandiGKlevitRVogelVStructural basis for mechanical force regulation of the adhesin FimH via finger trap-like beta sheet twistingCell201014164565520478255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R101"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>101RangarajanESIzardTDimer asymmetry defines alpha-catenin interactionsNat Struct Mol Biol20132018819323292143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R102"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>102RangarajanESIzardTThe cytoskeletal protein alpha-catenin unfurls upon binding to vinculinJ Biol Chem2012287184921849922493458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R103"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>103FillinghamIGingrasARPapagrigoriouEPatelBEmsleyJCritchleyDRRobertsGCKBarsukovILA vinculin binding domain from the talin rod unfolds to form a complex with the vinculin headStructure200513657415642262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Experimental set-up and comparison of the key parameters, features and limitations of (left) atomic force microscopy (AFM), (middle) optical tweezers and (right) on-cell patch clamping. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="emss-62612-f0001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Models used to interpret DFS data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The assumed energy landscape and the resultant theoretical force versus loading rate relationship (insets) are shown above each model where F(v) is the most probable rupture force at a loading rate v, kB is Boltzmann’s constant, T is temperature, xβ indicates the location of the energy barrier, and koff is the off rate constant at zero force. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In Dudko-Hummer-Szabo model (centre), ks is the harmonic force constant scaled by kBT and S(t) is the rupture probability as a function of the time t. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In Friddle-De Yoreo model (right), feq indicates the force at which the dissociation and association are in equilibrium, and koff(feq) is the off rate constant at feq. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="emss-62612-f0002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The structures of force-resistant and force-sensitive protein complexes. (a) in the absence of force, the N-terminal strand of FLNa20 (green, left) occludes the binding site for the integrin β-cytoplasmic tail (grey, right) on FLNa21 (red). (b) The bacterial Fim pilus is assembled by a donor strand complementation mechanism, whereby the Immunoglobulin-like fold of one domain (FimG in this case, red) missing the C-terminal β-strand is completed by the binding of an N-terminal extension of the subsequent Ig-like domain (FimF, grey). (c) and (d) upon mechanical extension, the cryptic vinculin binding sites (VBS, blue) within α-catenin ((c), red) and talin ((d), red) become accessible, triggering vinculin binding to the VBS (green and blue in the inset structures, respectively). (e) the complex formed between the C-terminal domain of TonB (red), tethered to the inner membrane of Gram negative bacteria and the TonB box (grey) of the outer membrane protein BtuB, that together span the periplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Structures drawn using UCSF Chimera [97] and PDB files:2J3S [98], 2BRQ [99], 2GSK [58], 3JWN [100], 4IGG [101], 4EHP [102], 1XWX (note that this is a theoretical model) [103] and 1 U6H [103]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="emss-62612-f0003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The highly avid E9:Im9 complex is a force-sensitive trip bond [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>(a) When extended between residue 3 of E9 (green) and 81 of Im9 (pink), the complex dissociates at low force with a short lifetime (12.5 ms under 20 pN force) due to force-induced remodelling of the binding interface which is connected directly to the N-terminus of E9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>(See left hand inset showing simplified topology diagram for the complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Yellow filled circles designate pulling points). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Interface remodelling can be prevented by introducing a disulfide cross-link (between residues 20 and 66, highlighted in blue and blue circles in the structure and topology diagrams, respectively), diverting the force propagation network away from regions proximal to the interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>This results in a mechanically strong, long lived complex (3.9 hours under 20 pN force), with a dissociation rate constant identical to that measured by ensemble methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>If a disulphide bond is introduced between residues 31 and 122 of E9 (red and red circles in the structure and topology diagrams, respectively), remodelling is not prevented, and the complex behaves identically to the wild-type (WT) protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>(b) Dynamic force spectrum of the wild-type complex (black circles), E9 cross-linked between residues 20–66 (blue closed circles) and 31–122 (red circles). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="emss-62612-f0004"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
