<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Nutr Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Nutr Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JNS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Nutritional Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2048-6790</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4791522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/jns.2015.42</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2048679015000427</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00042</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Addition of a dairy fraction rich in milk fat globule membrane to ahigh-saturated fat meal reduces the postprandial insulinaemic and inflammatory response in overweight and obese adults </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Elieke Demmer <italic>et al</italic>.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Addition of a dairy fraction rich in milk fat
globule membrane to a high-saturated fat meal reduces the postprandial insulinaemic and
inflammatory response in overweight and obese adults</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Demmer</surname><given-names>Elieke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Loan</surname><given-names>Marta D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>Tara S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gertz</surname><given-names>Erik R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>J. Bruce</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smilowitz</surname><given-names>Jennifer T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zivkovic</surname><given-names>Angela M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Nutrition</addr-line>,
<institution>University of California Davis</institution>, <addr-line>Davis,
CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>USDA/ARS Western Human Nutrition Research
Center</institution>, <addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Foods for Health Institute, University of
California</institution>, <addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Food Science &amp;
Technology</addr-line>, <institution>University of California</institution>,
<addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> A. M. Zivkovic, email
<email>amzivkovic@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e14</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits
unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S2048679015000427a.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="normal"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Meals high in SFA, particularly palmitate, are associated with postprandial inflammation and insulin resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Milk fat globule membrane (MFGM) has anti-inflammatory properties that may attenuate the negative effects of SFA-rich meals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Our objective was to examine the postprandial metabolic and inflammatory response to a high-fat meal composed of palm oil (PO) compared with PO with an added dairy fraction rich in MFGM (PO+MFGM) in overweight and obese men and women (n 36) in a randomised, double-blinded, cross-over trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Participants consumed two isoenergetic high-fat meals composed of a smoothie enriched with PO with v. without a cream-derived complex milk lipid fraction ( dairy fraction rich in MFGM) separated by a washout of 1–2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Serum cytokines, adhesion molecules, cortisol and markers of inflammation were measured at fasting, and at 1, 3 and 6 h postprandially. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Glucose, insulin and lipid profiles were analysed in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Consumption of the PO + MFGM v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>PO meal resulted in lower total cholesterol (P = 0·021), LDL-cholesterol (P = 0·046), soluble intracellular adhesion molecule (P = 0·005) and insulin (P = 0·005) incremental AUC, and increased IL-10 (P = 0·013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Individuals with high baseline C-reactive protein (CRP) concentrations (≥3 mg/l, n 17) had higher (P = 0·030) insulin at 1 h after the PO meal than individuals with CRP concentrations &lt;3 mg/l (n 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The addition of MFGM attenuated this difference between CRP groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM attenuated the negative effects of a high-SFA meal by reducing postprandial cholesterol, inflammatory markers and insulin response in overweight and obese individuals, particularly in those with elevated CRP. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Key words</title><kwd>Milk fat globule membrane</kwd><kwd>Postprandial inflammation</kwd><kwd>Saturated fat</kwd><kwd>Insulin</kwd><kwd>C-reactive protein</kwd><kwd>CVD</kwd><kwd>Cytokines</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><kwd-group kwd-group-type="abbreviations"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>CRP, C-reactive protein</kwd><kwd>iAUC, incremental AUC</kwd><kwd>MetS, metabolic syndrome</kwd><kwd>MFGM, milk fat globule membrane</kwd><kwd>PO, palm oil</kwd><kwd>sICAM, soluble intracellular adhesion molecule</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="54"/><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The postprandial state has been highlighted as an important transitory period when significant vascular damage can occur and has recently been implicated in the causal processes of CVD( 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Postprandial inflammatory and lipaemic responses are pronounced in individuals with obesity, the metabolic syndrome (MetS) and type 2 diabetes( 2 – 5 ), in part because the magnitude of the postprandial inflammatory response is correlated with insulin resistance( 6 , 7 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Current literature suggests that the inflammation of the postprandial state adds to the already pro-inflammatory environment in individuals with obesity-induced metabolic disease, intensifying the overall systemic inflammation that underlies metabolic dysfunction( 8 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Given the rise in overweight and obesity worldwide( 9 ), potential nutritional interventions that can limit the postprandial inflammatory response would be of great public health benefit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The postprandial inflammatory response is influenced by the fat content and composition of the test meal( 10 – 13 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that SFA induce inflammation postprandially( 8 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Palmitic acid in particular appears to be detrimental. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The consumption of palmitic acid acutely increases the insulin response compared with oleic acid and n-3 fatty acids( 14 ) and this was shown to be related to the adverse effects of palmitate on both β-cell function and insulin sensitivity in the postprandial state( 15 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Palmitate, either as an isolated fatty acid or as part of a high-SFA meal, increases inflammatory markers in the postprandial state( 16 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Palm oil (PO) is enriched in palmitate and has been used widely in the food industry as a substitute for trans-fatty acids, which are known to have deleterious effects on CVD risk( 17 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Milk fat globule membrane (MFGM) fractions have previously been reported to reduce inflammation in in vitro and animal models( 18 – 21 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>MFGM, a protein–lipid complex originating from the apical surface of mammary epithelial cells, surrounds the fat globules in milk and is found in dairy products at varying levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Specific proteins and lipids of MFGM are associated with health-promoting bioactive functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For example, one major MFGM-associated protein, lactadherin, was reported to bind and neutralise viruses, reduce intestinal inflammation, improve intestinal permeability, and repair intestinal epithelium( 20 , 22 – 24 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>MFGM-derived polar lipids were reported to have bactericidal properties, bind enterotoxigenic pathogens and reduce intestinal inflammation( 19 , 23 , 25 – 27 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition to functions attributed to its individual components, MFGM as a complex also reduced inflammation in vitro, in animals and clinically( 18 , 21 , 28 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, it is not known whether the addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM to meals high in saturated fat would blunt the postprandial inflammatory response in human subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study was to determine the postprandial inflammatory effect of a high-saturated fat meal using PO with and without the addition of MFGM in overweight and obese adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We hypothesised that consuming a high-fat PO + MFGM meal would result in lower pro-inflammatory serum markers compared with the isoenergetic PO meal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materialsandmethods" id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec1-1" sec-type="subjects"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A total of seventeen adult men and nineteen adult women (total of thirty-six participants) were recruited from the Davis and greater Sacramento areas of California to participate in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>To qualify, individuals had to be between 18 and 65 years of age, and either be overweight according to their BMI (25–29·9 kg/m2) plus have two or more MetS traits according to the definition of the American Heart Association or simply be obese according to their BMI (30–39·9 kg/m2) and have any number of MetS traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The MetS is defined by having three or more of the following traits: waist circumference &gt;40 inches (&gt;102 cm) for men and 35 inches (&gt;89 cm) inches for women; fasting plasma TAG ≥ 150 mg/dl (≥ 1·70 mmol/l); fasting plasma HDL-cholesterol &lt;40 mg/dl (&lt;1·04 mmol/l) for men and &lt;50 mg/dl (&lt;1·30 mmol/l) for women; blood pressure ≥130/85 mmHg; and fasting glucose ≥100 mg/dl (≥5·56 mmol/l)( 29 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Individuals were excluded from participation for the following reasons: diagnosis of immune-related diseases, gastrointestinal disorders, cancer, type 2 diabetes, eating disorder, allergies to the provided study foods, poor vein accessibility according to the research phlebotomist, or a body-weight change greater than 10 % over the past 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Individuals were excluded from participation if they used the following: weight loss medications; daily non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID); anti-inflammatory supplements; corticoid steroids; tobacco; change in hormonal birth control regimen with the past 6 months; initiation of statins in past 3 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Because of possible confounding effects on inflammatory outcomes, dietary exclusion criteria were as follows: &gt;1 serving of fish/week; &gt;14 g fibre/1000 kcal (4184 kJ) per d; &lt;16:1 of total dietary n-6:n-3 ratio; &gt;1 % of daily energy as trans-fats; and a vegetarian diet pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>If individuals had initiated an exercise programme within the past 6 months, planned to become pregnant within the next 6 months, or were already pregnant or lactating, they were not enrolled in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>To determine enrolment eligibility, questionnaires were administered regarding health history, diet and medication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>An online FFQ was used to assess dietary intake and a fasting blood sample was drawn for the analysis of blood lipids and glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Additional anthropometric measurements were taken during the screening visit to determine MetS traits (weight, height, and waist circumference). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This study was approved from an ethical standpoint by the Institutional Review Board of the University of California, Davis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was given in writing by all study participants prior to starting the study protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The study was registered at clinicaltrials.gov under NCT01811329. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Two isoenergetic test meals were consumed by the participants in a randomised, double-blinded, two-way cross-over design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>A high-fat PO meal was compared against a high-fat PO meal with the addition of MFGM (PO + MFGM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Participants were assigned to test meal order using a random number generator which randomly returned either a 0 or 1, with a 0 being assigned to PO first followed by PO + MFGM second, and a 1 being assigned to PO + MFGM first followed by PO second. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Test meals were consumed in random order on different test days separated by a washout phase of minimally 1 week and maximally 2 weeks to avoid any carry-over effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After each washout, participants consumed the alternate test meal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>To limit confounding effects, the consumption of anti-inflammatory supplements, alcohol or NSAID was not permitted for 72 h before each test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>At 24 h prior to the test day, vigorous exercise was prohibited to avoid increasing inflammatory markers and conversely consumption of seafood was not allowed to avoid a suppression of inflammatory markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To ensure compliance, participants filled out a 1-d food record for the 24 h prior to each test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The dietary records were analysed using the Nutrition Data System for Research (NDSR; University of Minnesota). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Participants arrived at the Western Human Nutrition Research Center after a 10–12 h fast on each test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The 24 h diet record was collected and participants were asked to complete a modified gastrointestinal questionnaire( 30 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>A fasted blood sample was drawn via venepuncture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Blood pressure, heart rate, weight and waist circumference were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The dietary test meal was then consumed completely within 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Postprandial blood draws were conducted at 1, 3 and 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>These time points were determined based on previous postprandial clinical trials observing a peak in pro-inflammatory cytokine concentrations around 3–6 h after consuming a high-fat meal( 6 , 31 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Consumption of any food other than the test meal was not permitted, but bottled water was offered throughout the test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Participants were offered the option to stay at the research facility or leave between blood draws via car to limit physical activity and had to return 15 min before their scheduled blood draw to allow for a 10 min rest period prior to each blood draw. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Dietary challenges </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The two test meals were made up of a bagel with strawberry preserves along with either a PO or PO + MFGM smoothie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In each instance the smoothie consisted of deionised water, cream of tartar, PO shortening, and raspberry sorbet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the PO + MFGM smoothie contained BPC50, a cream-derived complex milk lipid fraction powder (β serum concentrate) that is a proprietary product supplied by Fonterra Co-operative Group Ltd (New Zealand)( 32 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>BPC50 is comprised of the following (% w/w): 52 % protein of which 13·2 % is membrane-derived protein, 6·6 % lactose and 36·2 % total fat (22·5 % TAG and 13·7 % phospholipids), 0·63 % gangliosides (GD3), and 5·2 % ash( 33 – 35 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The six highest abundant MFGM-derived proteins reported in BPC50 include: fatty acid-binding protein, butyrophilin, lactadherin, adipophilin, xanthine oxidase and mucin( 35 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The PO smoothie contained whey protein isolate to match the protein content found in the BPC50 product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>For ingredient details, see Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Participants were instructed to eat the entire meal, rinse their cup with water, and drink the rinse-water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Each test meal provided 40 % of the participant's total daily energy intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Energy intake was determined by using the National Academy of Sciences equation from the Institute of Medicine Dietary Reference Intake( 36 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To determine each participant's physical activity level the Baecke Physical Activity questionnaire was used( 37 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The two isoenergetic test meals were constructed to vary less than 0·2 % in macronutrients and provided about 55 % fat, about 30 % carbohydrates, and about 15 % protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Each test meal provided between 49 and 87 g of fat depending on each individual's energy intake, 61–107 g of carbohydrates, and 31–55 g of protein (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Test meal nutrient composition was estimated using NDSR (University of Minnesota). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The addition of MFGM (ranging from 53·2 to 93·1 g depending on each individual's energy intake) replaced 31 % of the fat of each participant's meal (34 % of the total energy). Table 1.Nutrient composition of test meals†(Mean values and standard deviations)PO mealPO + MFGM mealMean sd Mean sd Energy (kcal)1088·1189·31088·1189·2Energy (kJ)4552·4791·84552·7791·7Total carbohydrate g82·714·483·214·5 % total energy30·40·030·60·0Total protein g42·57·4437·5 % total energy15·60·015·80·0Total fat g67·311·767·511·7 % total energy55·60·055·80·0Total SFA g32·65·734·66·0 % total energy27·00·028·60·0Total MUFA g24·64·322·73·9 % total energy20·30·018·80·0Total PUFA* g6·91·26·11·1 % total energy5·70·05·10·0SFA 4 : 0 (butyric acid) (%)000·20·0SFA 6 : 0 (caproic acid) (%)000·20·0SFA 8 : 0 (caprylic acid) (%)000·20·0SFA 10 : 0 (capric acid) (%)*000·50·1SFA 12 : 0 (lauric acid) (%)*0·10·00·80·1SFA 14 : 0 (myristic acid) (%)*0·70·12·50·4SFA 16 : 0 (palmitic acid) (%)*28·7524·84·3SFA 18 : 0 (stearic acid) (%)*2·90·54·70·8MUFA 16 : 1 (palmitoleic acid) (%)*0·20·00·50·1MUFA 18 : 1 (oleic acid) (%)*24·34·222·23·9PUFA 18 : 2 (linoleic acid) (%)6·61·15·10·9PUFA 18 : 3 (linolenic acid) (%)0·30·10·50·1PO, palm oil; PO + MFGM, palm oil + milk fat globule membrane.*Significant difference between the two meals (P &lt; 0·05).†Comparison of the dietary challenges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Nutrient composition obtained using the Nutrition Data System for Research (NDSR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Test meals were based on each individual's total energy expenditure; thus values shown are average of all test meals (n 36). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-4"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Blood analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Whole blood was drawn at baseline, and at 1, 3 and 6 h after the meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Serum tubes were allowed to clot at room temperature for 30 min, and then centrifuged at 1300 g at 4°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>EDTA-whole blood tubes were kept on ice during and after blood collection and were centrifuged within 30 min of collection at 1300 g at 4°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation, the serum and plasma tubes were kept on ice during aliquoting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, plasma and serum aliquots were directly frozen at –70°C until analysed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-5"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory markers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Serum samples from all four time points were analysed for cytokine concentrations (IL-10, IL-1β, IL-2, IL-4, IL-6, IL-8, TNFα, monocyte chemotactic protein-1), as well as the vascular injury molecules C-reactive protein (CRP), serum amyloid A, soluble intracellular adhesion molecule (sICAM) and soluble vascular adhesion molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Plasma was used to measure IL-18 concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>A commercially available Multi Spot ELISA kit was used to quantify the concentrations of these markers (SECTOR Imager 2400; Meso Scale Discovery). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The protocol was followed as recommended by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Briefly, pre-coated plates with capture antibodies were incubated with 25–50 µl of serum or plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>After washing the plates a labelled detection antibody was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Upon electrochemical stimulation the bound detection antibodies emit light, which is measured by the plate reader to quantify the amount of each protein of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-6"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Cortisol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Serum cortisol was measured at all times points using the DetectX Cortisol Enzyme Immunoassay kit (Arbor Assays). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Briefly, a cortisol–peroxidase conjugate and a monoclonal cortisol antibody were added to a pre-coated ninety-six-well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Upon incubation, serum samples were added to each well and allowed to bind with the cortisol–peroxidase conjugate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The total amount of cortisol present in each sample was then calculated based on the absorbance detected by the reader. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-7"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Metabolic parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>At each time point plasma glucose, insulin, and a lipid panel including TAG, total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL:LDL ratio, and non-HDL-cholesterol were assessed by standard clinical techniques in the clinical laboratory of University of California Medical Center (Sacramento, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-8"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Clinical characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Body weight, height, waist circumference, blood pressure and heart rate were measured on each test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Body weight was measured with a calibrated scale (6002 Wheelchair Scale; Scale-tronix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Waist circumference was measured in the standing position with measurements midway between the lateral lower rib margin and the ileac crest (QM2000 Measure Mate; QuickMedical). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Height was measured with a wall-mounted stadiometer (Ayrton Stadiometer Model S100; Ayrton Corporation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Blood pressure and resting heart rate were taken in the upright seated position using the appropriately sized cuff (Carescape V100 with Critikon Dura-cuf for either adults or large adults; GE Medical Instruments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Total fat mass and lean mass were assessed using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (Lunar Prodigy instrument; GE Medical Instruments). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-9"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The sample size was calculated based on the primary outcome marker IL-6 using the means and standard deviations from a similar human study with overweight men at risk for developing the MetS( 31 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>To ensure 95 % confidence of the results and 80 % power the sample size calculation indicated that thirty-six participants would be needed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were conducted on SPSS version 20.0 software for Macintosh (SPSS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered significant at P &lt; 0·05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Normality was established visually and numerically using histograms, Q–Q plots and the Shapiro–Wilk test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Data were transformed as needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>When concentrations for markers were below the lower limit of detection (LLOD) (IL-10; 23 % and IL-6; 9 %) for &lt;25 % of the samples, the value was calculated as the LLOD divided by 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>When concentrations for markers were below the LLOD for &gt;25 % of the samples, the data were excluded from statistical analyses (IL-1β and IL-4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Cases with values more than three box lengths from the 75th percentile or 25th percentile were deemed outliers and removed from all analyses; this only applied to sICAM where two subjects were excluded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>To determine if dietary differences existed between test meal composition and baseline analyte concentrations a paired t test was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>A mixed linear model was performed with treatment and time as fixed factors, participants as the random effect and treatment × time as the interaction term. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>If time was significant, multiple-comparison post hoc analysis with Bonferroni correction was carried out to compare the concentrations at 0–1 h, 0–3 h, 0–6 h, 1–3 h, 1–6 h, and 3–6 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The incremental AUC (iAUC, area above baseline) and decremental (area below baseline) using the conventional trapezoid method were used to compare postprandial responses between test meals( 38 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The iAUC was chosen over the total AUC because it reflects the postprandial rise of these metabolite concentrations above the non-zero fasting value( 39 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>iAUC between test meals were compared by one-way ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>To determine if pre-existing clinical conditions affected the inflammatory responses to the test meals, secondary analyses were conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Participants were coded as having high or low CRP levels based on their baseline levels prior to receiving either test meal treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>High CRP was defined as a concentration ≥3 mg/l (n 17), low CRP was defined as &lt;3 mg/l (n 19)( 40 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics of each CRP group can be found in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>ANCOVA was used to identify statistically significant differences in postprandial inflammatory markers between test meals using CRP as the covariate variable. Table 2.Participant baseline characteristics*(Mean values and standard deviations)All participantsLow CRP‡High CRP‡Mean sd MetS criteria†Mean sd Mean sd Age (years)42·914·042·413·643·614·9Weight (kg)92·912·293·511·992·212·8Height (m)1·70·11·70·11·70·1BMI (kg/m2)31·72·631·92·631·52·5Total body fat (%)36·77·834·28·339·56·3 Total body fat, male (%)§31·06·228·54·335·56·8 Total body fat, female (%)§41·94·942·15·141·75·0Android fat (g)3262·9799·940·56·746·14·2 Android fat, male (g)3370·8934·137·25·745·23·3 Android fat, female (g)3166·3669·045·05·346·74·7Gynoid fat (g)5353·31452·036·98·639·57·0 Gynoid fat, male (g)4829·21325·831·25·033·55·3 Gynoid fat, female (g)5822·11430·244·85·742·75·6WC (inches)39·33·238·82·939·93·4 WC, male (inches)41·13·1&gt;4040·22·942·82·9 WC, female (inches)37·72·2&gt;3536·91·638·22·4WC (cm)99·88·198·67·4101·38·6 WC, male (cm)104·47·9&gt;102102·17·4108·77·4 WC, female (cm)95·85·6&gt;8993·74·197·06·1Systolic BP (mmHg)123·913·6≥130123·19·5124·817·4Diastolic BP (mmHg)75·010·3≥8576·09·273·911·6HDL-cholesterol mg/dl48·314·148·414·248·214·4 mmol/l1·250·371·250·371·250·37 HDL-cholesterol, male  mg/dl43·211·7&lt;4042·513·744·57·8  mmol/l1·120·30&lt;1·041·100·351·150·20 HDL-cholesterol, female  mg/dl52·914·7&lt;5056·510·950·316·9  mmol/l1·370·38&lt;1·301·460·281·300·44Fasting glucose mg/dl91·07·4≥10092·07·889·97·1 mmol/l5·060·41≥5·565·110·434·990·39Fasting TAG mg/dl122·557·8≥150106·041·1140·968·7 mmol/l1·380·65≥1·701·200·461·590·78MetS, metabolic syndrome; CRP, C-reactive protein; WC, waist circumference; BP, blood pressure.*Measurements taken at screening visit (n 36).†MetS as defined by the American Heart Association.‡Low baseline CRP n 19; high baseline CRP n 17.§Male n 17, female n 19. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Participant characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>After screening 207 participants, thirty-eight were enrolled to start the study (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Thirty-six participants completed both postprandial test days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The two participants who did not finish the trial were disqualified due to scheduling difficulties and the initiation of medication that could confound the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Each participant was randomly assigned to one test meal and after a 1- to 2-week washout period, they were crossed-over to the alternate test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The majority of the study population was Caucasian (67 %) or Hispanic (28 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Out of the total thirty-six participants, six were overweight with two MetS traits, three were overweight with three or more MetS traits, twenty-one were obese with zero to two MetS traits, and six were obese with three MetS traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The baseline characteristics of the participants are shown in Table 2. Fig. 1.Enrolment and follow-up of participants in the randomised cross-over trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>PO, palm oil; PO + MFGM, palm oil + milk fat globule membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Dietary challenge </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Participants consumed two test meals, a high-fat PO test meal and a high-fat PO + MFGM test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The meals (Table 1) were isoenergetic and comparable for macronutrient composition, not varying by more than 0·2% for carbohydrates, protein or fat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The total weight of SFA and MUFA did not differ between the PO v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>PO + MFGM test meals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, the PO meal contained a significantly higher total amount of PUFA compared with the PO + MFGM test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The relative abundance of 18 : 2n-6 was not significantly different between the two test meals; however, since 18 : 2n-6 is the predominant PUFA in the two meals, and since the PO meal had higher total PUFA, the PO meal had a higher total amount of 18 : 2n-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The relative abundances of specific SFA and MUFA were significantly different: the PO + MFGM meal had more 10 : 0, 12 : 0, 14 : 0, 18 : 0 and 18 : 1n-9 whereas the PO meal had more 16 : 0 and 16 : 1n-7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>These differences in relative abundances of fatty acids are reflective of the composition of PO, which is enriched in palmitate (16 : 0), and MFGM, which is enriched in medium-chain SFA characteristic of dairy fat. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Metabolic parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>There was a time × treatment interaction for total cholesterol (P = 0·04), HDL-cholesterol (P = 0·01), TAG (P &lt; 0·0005), non-HDL-cholesterol (P = 0·04) and insulin (P &lt; 0·0005) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Among these lipid makers, the greater change in total cholesterol was observed in response to the PO test meal; there was a 5 % increase from 0 to 1 h as well as from 0 to 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>HDL-cholesterol increased from 0 to 1 h by 4 % and decreased from 1 to 3 h by 4 % in response to the PO test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In response to the PO + MFGM test meal, TAG concentration increased by 104 % from 0 to 3 h and non-HDL-cholesterol concentration increased by 22 % from 0 to 1 h. Table 3.Concentrations of metabolic markers with significant interaction effects(Mean values and standard deviations)Time point0 h1 h3 h6 hMean sd Mean sd Mean sd Mean sd Time × treatment: PTotal cholesterol (mg/dl)0·04 PO meal194·938·5204·2*40·8201·4*39·9203·9*39·6 PO + MFGM meal198·737·6199·737·6207·137·4203·735·8Total cholesterol (mmol/l)0·04 PO meal5·051·005·29*1·065·22*1·035·28*1·03 PO + MFGM meal5·150·975·170·975·360·975·280·93HDL-cholesterol (mg/dl)0·01 PO meal49·614·551·6*15·349·3†15·349·9†15·3 PO + MFGM meal50·214·050·614·550·414·549·714·4HDL-cholesterol (mmol/l)0·01 PO meal1·280·371·34*0·401·28†0·401·29†0·40 PO + MFGM meal1·300·361·310·381·300·371·290·37TAG (mg/dl)&lt;0·0005 PO meal126·656·5182·9*77·9223·9*†114·4209·6*‡82·9 PO + MFGM meal130·170·6174·958·2265·1119·8210·4111·8TAG (mmol/l)&lt;0·0005 PO meal1·430·642·07*0·882·53*†1·292·37*‡0·94 PO + MFGM meal1·470·801·980·663·001·352·381·26Non-HDL-cholesterol (mg/dl)0·04 PO meal145·435·3152·6*36·5152·2*36·3154·0*37·2 PO + MFGM meal148·534·9180·5166·6157·034·5154·033·8Non-HDL-cholesterol (mmol/l)0·04 PO meal3·770·913·95*0·953·94*0·943·99*0·96 PO + MFGM meal3·850·904·674·324·070·893·990·88Insulin (μIU/ml)&lt;0·0005 PO meal14·06·181·7*69·334·4*†28·6Not measured PO + MFGM meal16·410·654·846·139·625·9Not measuredInsulin (pmol/l)&lt;0·0005 PO meal100·744·1586·4*497·4246·5*†205·5Not measured PO + MFGM meal117·575·9392·9330·4283·8186·0Not measuredPO, palm oil; PO + MFGM, palm oil + milk fat globule membrane.*Significantly different from 0 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05).†Significantly different from 1 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05).‡Significantly different from 3 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The total concentration of each analyte over the 6 h postprandial time was calculated as the iAUC and compared between test meals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The addition of MFGM to the test meal resulted in significantly lower concentrations of total cholesterol (P = 0·02 with all subjects included, P = 0·04 with two outliers removed), LDL-cholesterol (P = 0·046) and a significantly higher concentration of TAG (P = 0·025) when compared with the PO meal alone (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>When total insulin concentration was compared over the 6 h postprandial period (i.e. the iAUC of insulin from 0 to 6 h) the addition of MFGM resulted in a significantly lower exposure to insulin (P = 0·005) (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Neither insulin nor glucose concentrations at baseline differed between the two test meals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>There were no effects of treatment on insulin and glucose concentrations in the postprandial period; however, there was a rapid increase in insulin concentration from 0 to 1 h (P &lt; 0·0005) that was complemented by a decrease in glucose (P &lt; 0·0005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>From 1 to 3 h there was an increase back to baseline levels for glucose (P = 0·003) and a corresponding decrease in insulin concentrations (P &lt; 0·0005) although still greater than the 0 h value (P &lt; 0·0005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The increase in insulin concentration was dampened from 0 to 1 h by more than 50 % when MFGM was added to the test meal, resulting in a 482 % increase v. a 234 % increase for PO v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>PO + MFGM, respectively (time × treatment effect, P &lt; 0·0005). Fig. 2.Postprandial serum insulin concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Serum insulin concentrations over the 6 h postprandial period after a high-fat mixed meal containing palm oil (PO) v. palm oil + milk fat globule membrane (PO + MFGM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Data are incremental AUC (iAUC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Values are means, with standard deviations represented by vertical bars. * The addition of MFGM resulted in a significant decrease of insulin concentration (P = 0·005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>To examine if there was a difference between participants who had high v. low baseline CRP concentrations, additional secondary analyses were conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Participants with baseline CRP concentration ≥3 mg/l (coded as ‘high’) had significantly higher insulin concentrations at 1 h after consuming the PO meal (P = 0·03). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The addition of MFGM to the meal suppressed the insulin response in the high CRP group, thus removing any significant difference between the high and low CRP groups (Fig. 3). Fig. 3.Insulin concentrations in high (––) v. low (––) baseline C-reactive protein (CRP) groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(a) There was a significant difference between the high and low baseline CRP groups at the 1 h time point (P = 0·03) after consuming the palm oil meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(b) When the palm oil + milk fat globule membrane meal was consumed there was no difference between the high and low baseline CRP groups for insulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Values are means, with standard deviations represented by vertical bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>To convert insulin to pmol/l, multiply by 6·945. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory markers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The two cytokines IL-1β and IL-4 fell below the detection limit for 70 and 95 % of samples, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Consequently, these markers were not included in the statistical analyses reported here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Similar results for IL-1β and IL-4 have been observed in previous studies( 41 , 42 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Baseline concentrations of all markers related to inflammation were comparable between the two treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>When analysed as iAUC, IL-10 was significantly higher (P = 0·013) and sICAM was significantly lower in response to the PO + MFGM test meal (P = 0·005 for all) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>An interaction effect between time and treatment was observed for IL-10 (P = 0·03), IL-8 (P = 0·04) and sICAM (P = 0·02) (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Over time IL-10 gradually, but not significantly, declined on the PO treatment whereas on the PO + MFGM treatment IL-10 increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>There was a significant decrease in IL-8 from 0–3 h and 1–3 h and a significant increase in concentration from the 3–6 h time points (P &lt; 0·05 for all) following the PO meal, but IL-8 was unchanged after the PO + MFGM meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Concentrations for sICAM significantly increased from 0–1 h, 0–6 h, and 3–6 h and significantly decreased between the 1–3 h time points (P &lt; 0·05 for all) after consumption of the PO meal and, like IL-8, was unchanged after the PO + MFGM challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>There was no treatment effect observed for any of the other inflammatory markers, but a significant change over time was observed for IL-6, IL-8, TNFα, CRP, serum amyloid A, sICAM, soluble vascular adhesion molecule and cortisol (P &lt; 0·05 for all) (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>There was no time or treatment effect for monocyte chemotactic protein-1. Fig. 4.Postprandial serum concentrations of IL-10 (a) and soluble intracellular adhesion molecule (sICAM) (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Serum IL-10 and sICAM concentrations over the 6 h postprandial period after a high-fat mixed meal containing palm oil (PO) v. palm oil + milk fat globule membrane (PO + MFGM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Data are incremental AUC (iAUC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Values are means, with standard deviations represented by vertical bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>(a) * The addition of MFGM resulted in a significant increase of anti-inflammatory IL-10 (P = 0·011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(b) * The addition of MFGM resulted in a significant decrease of sICAM concentration (P = 0·013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The sICAM graph and data exclude two subjects who were deemed outliers with values more than three box lengths away from the 75th or 25th percentile. Table 4.Concentrations of measured inflammatory markers at each time point(Mean values and standard deviations)Time point0 h1 h3 h6 hMean sd Mean sd Mean sd Mean sd Time × treatment: PIL-10 (pg/ml) PO meal0·561·350·541·340·541·200·511·300·03 PO + MFGM meal0·491·150·521·160·521·090·571·10IL-6 (pg/ml) PO meal0·741·070·59*0·860·61*1·080·76†‡1·140·48 PO + MFGM meal0·721·350·591·230·540·950·761·36IL-8 (pg/ml) PO11·243·0610·51*3·309·63*3·1110·962·910·04 PO + MFGM11·113·2811·323·2310·722·6610·83·30TNFα (pg/ml) PO meal2·490·702·360·562·290·622·360·640·13 PO + MFGM meal2·340·662·360·642·270·612·220·66IL-18 (pg/ml) PO meal145·4891·64148·4475·95162·38109·73150·9573·050·59 PO + MFGM meal154·2583·16152·1973·41155·3878·06160·0372·09MCP-1 (pg/ml) PO meal345·7593·66343·23104·24336·7294·82330·8182·090·26 PO + MFGM meal352·1684·36358·6190·41320·46102·57335·0597·92CRP (mg/l) PO meal4·424·694·394·234·424·434·64†4·640·8 PO + MFGM meal4·374·295·165·565·115·545·205·38SAA (mg/l) PO meal3·933·484·043·583·81†3·224·12‡3·710·91 PO + MFGM meal11·8530·7912·7632·7612·2031·6812·8233·37sICAM-1 (mg/l) PO meal0·970·501·06*0·531·00†0·501·04*‡0·530·02 PO + MFGM meal0·960·510·970·500·950·500·970·51sVCAM-1 (mg/l) PO meal1·550·851·65*0·861·58†0·861·62‡0·860·13 PO + MFGM meal1·490·831·510·841·460·821·520·85Cortisol (μg/l) PO meal1139751820859967108659595703305*†457081653937*†‡5773520·76 PO + MFGM meal1083979698219933085619060780686476281613297366507PO, palm oil; PO + MFGM, palm oil + milk fat globule membrane; MCP-1, monocyte chemoattractant protein-1; CRP, C-reactive protein; SAA, serum amyloid A; sICAM, soluble intracellular adhesion molecule; sVCAM, soluble vascular adhesion molecule.*Significantly different from 0 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05).†Significantly different from 1 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05).‡Significantly different from 3 h when both treatments analysed together (P &lt; 0·05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Secondary analysis using baseline CRP as a covariate revealed a statistically significant difference for IL-6 at each time point (P &lt; 0·05 for each time point) between participants with high v. low baseline CRP concentrations after consuming the PO test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>After consuming the PO + MFGM test meal, this difference was no longer significant, suggesting that MFGM may attenuate the postprandial inflammatory response in individuals with high CRP levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Cortisol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Analysis of serum cortisol revealed no time × treatment interaction effect or a treatment effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>There was a significant decrease in cortisol concentration for all time points (P &lt; 0·05 for all time points) over the course of each test day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Decreases throughout the day, from baseline to 1 h, 1–3 h, and 3–6 h were as follows: 15, 33 and 43 %, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>This observed decrease throughout the day is consistent with diurnal patterns of cortisol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This study was designed to determine if the addition of MFGM to a high-fat meal containing plant-based saturated fat influences postprandial inflammation in overweight and obese individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that adding a dairy fraction rich in MFGM to a high-fat meal may lower CVD risk by reducing postprandial insulin, total cholesterol and LDL-cholesterol as well as sICAM concentrations while increasing the concentration of anti-inflammatory IL-10. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Compared with PO, consumption of the PO + MFGM test meal resulted in a significantly higher concentration of IL-10 at 6 h postprandial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>IL-10 is an anti-inflammatory cytokine which has been recognised for its atheroprotective effects( 43 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that the addition of MFGM to a high-SFA meal improves postprandial inflammation in an overweight and obese population already in a chronically inflamed state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge we are the first to examine the postprandial effect on IL-10 after a high-fat dietary challenge with and without MFGM in human subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Cellular adhesion molecules, such as sICAM, are key players in the early events of atherosclerosis development( 44 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The consumption of the PO + MFGM test meal resulted in a significantly lower concentration of sICAM over the postprandial period when compared with PO alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In large prospective studies of both healthy individuals and patients with CVD, concentrations of sICAM were positively associated with future incidents of CVD( 45 – 47 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>In our study the total amount of sICAM over the 6 h postprandial period in response to PO + MFGM was significantly lower by 95 % compared with PO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM attenuates the atherogenic milieu triggered by the PO meal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the difference in sICAM between the PO v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>PO + MFGM treatments could stem from the difference in the fatty acid composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The PO + MFGM meal was higher in short- and medium-chained SFA and lower in 18 : 2n-6 and 18 : 1n-9 compared with the PO meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Chen et al.( 48 ) showed that when human retinal vascular endothelial cells were treated with linoleic acid (18 : 2n-6) it resulted in increased ICAM expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The MFGM preparation used is composed of complex lipids including sphingolipids, as well as bioactive proteins, which may also play roles in the observed anti-inflammatory effects( 49 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>When analysing the insulin iAUC over the 6 h postprandial period, the total insulin concentration was significantly lower in response to the PO + MFGM compared with the PO test meal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge there have not been any prior clinical trials examining the effect of MFGM consumption on the insulin response in human subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>One study investigated the postprandial effect of adding a dairy product rich in sphingolipids, a lipid constituent of MFGM, to a high-fat breakfast meal and found no significant difference in postprandial insulin concentrations( 50 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Branched-chain amino acids may promote insulin secretion( 51 , 52 ); thus the effect of MFGM on insulin may be related to its amino acid composition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The secondary analysis based on baseline CRP concentrations revealed that participants who were in an inflamed state (CRP ≥ 3 mg/l) in the fasted condition had significantly higher insulin concentrations after consuming the PO meal compared with those who had normal baseline CRP concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>However, the addition of MFGM to the high-fat test meal completely removed this difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>These results suggest an interaction between diet and phenotype, whereby consumption of MFGM by chronically inflamed individuals normalised responses to a high-fat meal to closely resemble that of a metabolically healthy profile. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Research has shown that cortisol peaks in the morning( 53 ), which was reflected in the present study, and decreases over the course of the day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Elevated levels of cortisol inhibit the synthesis of pro-inflammatory cytokines( 54 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>We hypothesised that this potential inhibition may explain the observed initial decrease in the pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-6, IL-8, TNFα) from baseline (blood draw schedule between 08·00 and 09·00 hours) to the 3 h blood draw (scheduled between 11·00 and 12·00 hours). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>However, none of the correlations was significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In summary, the addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM reduced the iAUC in postprandial insulin, total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol and sICAM responses over the 6 h postprandial period, and increased the production of the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM also attenuated the increases in insulin at 1 h in individuals with elevated fasting CRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Results from this study suggest that the addition of a dairy fraction rich in MFGM attenuates the negative metabolic and inflammatory effects of a high-fat meal rich in saturated fat, specifically palmitate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the study participants for their time and efforts to comply with the study requirements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Fonterra Co-operative Group Ltd (New Zealand) for supplying the BCP50 product for use in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The authors thank the Western Human Nutrition Research Center kitchen personnel, Dustin Burnett, Sara Dowling and Julie Edwards; phlebotomist, Jerome Crawford; physiologist, Mary Gustafson; and molecular biologist, Pieter Oort for their dedication to the project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The US Department of Agriculture is an equal opportunity employer and provider. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Z., J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>S., J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>G. and M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>L. designed the research; E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>D., N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>R., T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>R. and E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>G. conducted the research; E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>D. analysed the data; and E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>D., A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Z., J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>S. and M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>L. wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>D. had primary responsibility for the final content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>L., A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Z. and J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>S. have received research funding from the National Dairy Council; A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Z. received a stipend from the National Dairy Council to present a talk at a symposium in 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The founding sponsors had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of the data; in the writing of the manuscript, and in the decision to publish the results. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec4"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2048679015000427sup001"><p>For supplementary material accompanying this paper visit http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/jns.2015.42.</p><media xlink:href="S2048679015000427sup.zip" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" orientation="portrait" id="d36e3558" position="anchor"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>click here to view supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="reflist1"><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>1.BurdgeGC &amp; CalderPC (2005) Plasma cytokine response during the postprandial period: a potential causal process in vascular disease? Br J Nutr 93, 3–9.15705218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref2"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>2.El KhouryD, HwallaN, FrochotV,  (2010) Postprandial metabolic and hormonal responses of obese dyslipidemic subjects with metabolic syndrome to test meals, rich in carbohydrate, fat or protein. Atherosclerosis 210, 307–313.20031131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref3"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>3.BlackburnP, DesprésJ-P, LamarcheB,  (2006) Postprandial variations of plasma inflammatory markers in abdominally obese men. Obesity (Silver Spring) 14, 1747–1754.17062804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref4"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>4.RectorRS, LindenMa, ZhangJQ,  (2009) Predicting postprandial lipemia in healthy adults and in at-risk individuals with components of the cardiometabolic syndrome. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich) 11, 663–671.19878381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref5"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>5.TushuizenME, PouwelsPJ, BontempsS,  (2010) Postprandial lipid and apolipoprotein responses following three consecutive meals associate with liver fat content in type 2 diabetes and the metabolic syndrome. Atherosclerosis 211, 308–314.20227695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref6"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>6.NappoF, EspositoK, CioffiM,  (2002) Postprandial endothelial activation in healthy subjects and in type 2 diabetic patients: role of fat and carbohydrate meals. J Am Coll Cardiol 39, 1145–1150.11923038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref7"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>7.EspositoK, CiotolaM, SassoFC,  (2007) Effect of a single high-fat meal on endothelial function in patients with the metabolic syndrome: role of tumor necrosis factor-α. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis 17, 274–279.17134952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref8"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>8.MargiorisAN (2009) Fatty acids and postprandial inflammation. Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care 12, 129–137.19202384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref9"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>9.NgM, FlemingT, RobinsonM,  (2014) Global, regional, and national prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adults during 1980–2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013. Lancet 384, 766–781.24880830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref10"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>10.DeopurkarR, GhanimH, FriedmanJ,  (2010) Differential effects of cream, glucose, and orange juice on inflammation, endotoxin, and the expression of Toll-like receptor-4 and suppressor of cytokine signaling-3. Diabetes Care 33, 991–997.20067961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref11"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>11.AryaF, EggerS, ColquhounD,  (2010) Differences in postprandial inflammatory responses to a ‘modern’ v. traditional meat meal: a preliminary study. Br J Nutr 104, 724–728.20377925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref12"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>12.ErridgeC, AttinaT, SpickettCM,  (2007) A high-fat meal induces low-grade endotoxemia: evidence of a novel mechanism of postprandial inflammation. Am J Clin Nutr 86, 1286–1292.17991637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref13"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>13.GhanimH, AbuayshehS, SiaCL,  (2009) Increase in plasma endotoxin concentrations and the expression of Toll-like receptors and suppressor of cytokine signaling-3 in mononuclear cells after a high-fat, high-carbohydrate meal: implications for insulin resistance. Diabetes Care 32, 2281–2287.19755625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref14"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>14.ShahM, Adams-HuetB, BrinkleyL,  (2007) Lipid, glycemic, and insulin responses to meals rich in saturated, cis-monounsaturated, and polyunsaturated (n-3 and n-6) fatty acids in subjects with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care 30, 2993–2998.17804680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref15"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>15.BermudezB, Ortega-GomezA, VarelaLM,  (2014) Clustering effects on postprandial insulin secretion and sensitivity in response to meals with different fatty acid compositions. Food Funct 5, 1374–1380.24752559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref16"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>16.TengKT, ChangCY, ChangLF,  (2014) Modulation of obesity-induced inflammation by dietary fats: mechanisms and clinical evidence. Nutr J 13, 12.24476102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref17"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>17.HayesKC &amp; PronczukA (2010) Replacing trans fat: the argument for palm oil with a cautionary note on interesterification. J Am Coll Nutr 29, 3 Suppl., 253S–284S.20823487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref18"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>18.DalbethN, GraceyE, PoolB,  (2010) Identification of dairy fractions with anti-inflammatory properties in models of acute gout. Ann Rheum Dis 69, 766–769.19713204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref19"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>19.ParkEJ, SuhM, ThomsonB,  (2007) Dietary ganglioside inhibits acute inflammatory signals in intestinal mucosa and blood induced by systemic inflammation of Escherichia coli lipopolysaccharide. Shock 28, 112–117.17510604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref20"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>20.AzizMM, IshiharaS, MishimaY,  (2009) MFG-E8 attenuates intestinal inflammation in murine experimental colitis by modulating osteopontin-dependent alphavbeta3 integrin signaling. J Immunol 182, 7222–7232.19454719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref21"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>21.SnowDR, WardRE, OlsenA,  (2011) Membrane-rich milk fat diet provides protection against gastrointestinal leakiness in mice treated with lipopolysaccharide. J Dairy Sci 94, 2201–2212.21524510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref22"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>22.BuHF, ZuoXL, WangX,  (2007) Milk fat globule-EGF factor 8/lactadherin plays a crucial role in maintenance and repair of murine intestinal epithelium. J Clin Invest 117, 3673–3683.18008006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref23"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>23.SpitsbergVL (2005) Invited review: Bovine milk fat globule membrane as a potential nutraceutical. J Dairy Sci 88, 2289–2294.15956291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref24"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>24.AndersenM, GraversenH, FedosovS,  (2000) Functional analyses of two cellular binding domains of bovine lactadherin. Biochemistry 39, 6200–6206.10821695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref25"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>25.El AlwaniM, WuBX, ObeidLM,  (2006) Bioactive sphingolipids in the modulation of the inflammatory response. Pharmacol Ther 112, 171–183.16759708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref26"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>26.DialEJ, ZayatM, Lopez-StoreyM,  (2008) Oral phosphatidylcholine preserves the gastrointestinal mucosal barrier during LPS-induced inflammation. Shock 30, 729–733.18496240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref27"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>27.Sanchez-JuanesF, AlonsoJ, ZancadaL,  (2009) Glycosphingolipids from bovine milk and milk fat globule membranes: a comparative study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Adhesion to enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli strains. Biol Chem 390, 31–40.18937626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref28"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>28.DalbethN &amp; PalmanoK (2011) Effects of dairy intake on hyperuricemia and gout. Curr Rheumatol Rep 13, 132–137.21188562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref29"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>29.GrundySM, CleemanJI, DanielsSR,  (2006) Diagnosis and management of the metabolic syndrome: an American Heart Association/National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute scientific statement. Curr Opin Cardiol 21, 1–6.16355022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref30"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>30.PedersenA, SandstromB &amp; AmelsvoortJ (1997) The effect of ingestion of inulin on blood lipids and gastrointestinal symptoms in healthy females. Br J Nutr 78, 215–222.9301412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref31"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>31.MassonCJ &amp; MensinkRP (2011) Exchanging saturated fatty acids for (n-6) polyunsaturated fatty acids in a mixed meal may decrease postprandial lipemia and markers of inflammation and endothelial activity in overweight men. 141, 816–821. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref32"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>32.FongB, NorrisC &amp; McJarrowP (2011) Liquid chromatography–high-resolution electrostatic ion-trap mass spectrometric analysis of GD3 ganglioside in dairy products. Int Dairy J 21, 42–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref33"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>33.MacKenzieA, VyssotskiM &amp; NekrasovE (2009) Quantitative analysis of dairy phospholipids by 31P NMR. J Am Oil Chem Soc 86, 757–763. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref34"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>34.GuanJ, MacGibbonA, FongB,  (2015) Long term supplementation with β serum concentrate (BSC), a complex of milk lipids, during post-natal brain development improves memory in rats. Nutrients 7, 4526–4541.26056919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref35"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>35.FongB &amp; NorrisC (2009) Quantification of milk fat globule membrane proteins using selected reaction monitoring mass spectrometry. J Agric Food Chem 57, 6021–6028.19537729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref36"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>36.National Research Council (2005) Dietary Reference Intakes for Energy, Carbohydrate, Fiber, Fat, Fatty Acids, Cholesterol, Protein, and Amino Acids (Macronutrients). Washington, DC: National Academies Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref37"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>37.BaeckeJA, BuremaJ &amp; FrijtersJE (1982) A short questionnaire for the measurement of habitual physical activity in epidemiological studies. Am J Clin Nutr 36, 936–942.7137077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref38"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>38.MatthewsJN, AltmanDG, CampbellMJ,  (1990) Analysis of serial measurements in medical research. BMJ 300, 230–235.2106931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref39"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>39.CarstensenM, ThomsenC &amp; HermansenK (2003) Incremental area under response curve more accurately describes the triglyceride response to an oral fat load in both healthy and type 2 diabetic subjects. Metabolism 52, 1034–1037.12898469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref40"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>40.PearsonTA (2003) Markers of inflammation and cardiovascular disease: application to clinical and public health practice: a statement for healthcare professionals from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the American Heart Association. Circulation 107, 499–511.12551878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref41"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>41.KleinerG, MarcuzziA, ZaninV,  (2013) Cytokine levels in the serum of healthy subjects. Mediators Inflamm 2013, 434010.23533306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref42"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>42.Rosenberg-HassonY, HansmannL, LiedtkeM,  (2014) Effects of serum and plasma matrices on multiplex immunoassays. Immunol Res 58, 224–233.24522699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref43"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>43.HanX &amp; BoisvertWA (2012) The role of IL-10 in atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>In Atherogenesis, pp. 361–384 [ S Parthasarathy , editor]. http://cdn.intechopen.com/pdfs-wm/25913.pdf (accessed January 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref44"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>44.BlankenbergS, BarbauxS &amp; TiretL (2003) Adhesion molecules and atherosclerosis. Atherosclerosis 170, 191–203.14612198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref45"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>45.RidkerPM, HennekensCH, Roitman-JohnsonB,  (1998) Plasma concentration of soluble intercellular adhesion molecule 1 and risks of future myocardial infarction in apparently healthy men. Lancet 351, 88–92.9439492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref46"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>46.RidkerP, HennekensC, BuringJ,  (2000) C-reactive protein and other markers of inflammation in the prediction of cardiovascular disease in women. New Engl J Med 342, 836–843.10733371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref47"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>47.TanneD, HaimM, BoykoV,  (2002) Soluble intercellular adhesion molecule-1 and risk of future ischemic stroke: a nested case–control study from the Bezafibrate Infarction Prevention (BIP) Study cohort. Stroke 33, 2182–2186.12215584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref48"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>48.ChenW, JumpDB, GrantMB,  (2003) Dyslipidemia, but not hyperglycemia, induces inflammatory adhesion molecules in human retinal vascular endothelial cells. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 44, 5016–5022.14578429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref49"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>49.ContariniG &amp; PovoloM (2013) Phospholipids in milk fat: composition, biological and technological significance, and analytical strategies. Int J Mol Sci 14, 2808–2831.23434649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref50"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>50.OhlssonL, BurlingH, DuanR-D,  (2010) Effects of a sphingolipid-enriched dairy formulation on postprandial lipid concentrations. Eur J Clin Nutr 64, 1344–1349.20808331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref51"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>51.RietmanA, SchwarzJ, ToméD,  (2014) High dietary protein intake, reducing or eliciting insulin resistance? Eur J Clin Nutr 68, 973–979.24986822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref52"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>52.DuganCE &amp; FernandezML (2014) Effects of dairy on metabolic syndrome parameters: a review. Yale J Biol Med 87, 135–147.24910559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref53"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>53.Van CauterE &amp; AschoffJ (1989) Endocrine and other biological rhythms In Endocrinology, 3rd ed., pp. 2658–2705 [ LJ DeGroot , editor]. Philadelphia, PA: Saunders. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref54"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>54.Swolin-EideD &amp; OhlssonC (1998) Effects of cortisol on the expression of interleukin-6 and interleukin-1β in human osteoblast-like cells. J Endocrinol 156, 107–114.9496240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
