<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JMIR Ment Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JMIR Ment Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMH</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JMIR Mental Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2368-7959</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4947190</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">v3i3e30</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27370327</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/mental.5966</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Exploring the Use of Information and Communication Technology by People With Mood Disorder: A Systematic Review and Metasynthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Byron</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Donna</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fulford</surname><given-names>Hamish</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4249-5657</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McSwiggan</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7168-0750</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>Thilo</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2082-5117</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>MacGillivray</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><address><institution>School of Nursing and Health Sciences</institution><institution>Centre for Health and Related Research</institution><institution>University of Dundee</institution><addr-line>Airlie Place</addr-line><addr-line>Dundee,</addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country><phone>44 01382388534</phone><fax>44 01382388533</fax><email>s.a.macgillivray@dundee.ac.uk</email></address><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1933-6431</contrib-id></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Nursing and Health Sciences</institution><institution>University of Dundee</institution><addr-line>Dundee</addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Social Dimensions of Health Institute (SDHI)</institution><institution>Universities of Dundee and St Andrews</institution><addr-line>Dundee</addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>School of Nursing and Health Sciences</institution><institution>Centre for Health and Related Research</institution><institution>University of Dundee</institution><addr-line>Dundee</addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding Author: Stephen MacGillivray
<email>s.a.macgillivray@dundee.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e30</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©Hamish Fulford, Linda McSwiggan, Thilo Kroll, Stephen MacGillivray. Originally published in JMIR Mental Health (http://mental.jmir.org), 01.07.2016.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in JMIR Mental Health, is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mental.jmir.org/,">http://mental.jmir.org/,</ext-link> as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mental.jmir.org/2016/3/e30/"/><abstract><sec sec-type="background"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>There is a growing body of evidence relating to how information and communication technology (ICT) can be used to support people with physical health conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Less is known regarding mental health, and in particular, mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>To conduct a metasynthesis of all qualitative studies exploring the use of ICTs by people with mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Searches were run in eight electronic databases using a systematic search strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Qualitative and mixed-method studies published in English between 2007 and 2014 were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Thematic synthesis was used to interpret and synthesis the results of the included studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Thirty-four studies were included in the synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The methodological design of the studies was qualitative or mixed-methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>A global assessment of study quality identified 22 studies as strong and 12 weak with most having a typology of findings either at topical or thematic survey levels of data transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A typology of ICT use by people with mood disorder was created as a result of synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The systematic review and metasynthesis clearly identified a gap in the research literature as no studies were identified, which specifically researched how people with mood disorder use mobile ICT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Further qualitative research is recommended to understand the meaning this type of technology holds for people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Such research might provide valuable information on how people use mobile technology in their lives in general and also, more specifically, how they are being used to help with their mood disorders. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>information and communication technology</kwd><kwd>ICTs</kwd><kwd>mood disorder</kwd><kwd>metasynthesis</kwd><kwd>self-management</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Mood disorder is a diagnostic category containing, among others, diagnoses such as major depression and bipolar depression [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>For some, having a mood disorder can be a lifelong problem and the need to support people with such long-term conditions is a major challenge facing health care providers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In order to effectively manage their health and wellbeing, people with a mood disorders may have to master a range of skills and make lifestyle changes, either independently or with the support of others, such as family, friends, third sector services, and mental health and social care professionals [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In mental health care systems designed primarily to treat acute episodes of care, the rise in long-term conditions has threatened the sustainability of services and ultimately failed to meet the needs of patients with ongoing care management and the delivery of psychosocial interventions [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Developments in information and communication technology (ICT) (such as the use of the Internet or computer technology and electronic systems) have begun to provide new ways for people to manage their health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>ICT interventions have become affordable, accessible, and versatile such as through the use of Web-based self-help resources [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Psychological interventions have been effectively delivered through ICTs [5] while having the ability to reach rural areas within diverse populations and settings [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>ICTs are increasingly being used for direct patient care [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>eHealth is the umbrella term used for a broad range of health informatics applications that facilitate the management and delivery of health-related care, including the dissemination of health-related information, storage, and exchange of clinical data, interprofessional communication, computer-based support, patient-provider interaction, education, health service management, health communities, and telemedicine, among other functions [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In mental health care, eHealth technologies can facilitate the delivery of a wide range of effective treatments for a variety of clinical problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>They have widened the choices available to patients for selecting an approach best suited to manage their long-term condition [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Such choices include: computerized cognitive behavioral therapy (cCBT) [9]; computerized bibliotherapy, and Web-based self-help resources/patient information websites [10]; online counselling [11]; patient forums, blogs, social media/social networking sites (SNSs) [12], and online self-management groups [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>More recently, a shift has occurred toward making technologies more portable or mobile, evidenced by the recent rise in smartphone and tablet ownership and usage [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Consequently, mHealth has become important for the delivery of health and health services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Improvements in reliability and broadband coverage means greater and faster Internet access for these mobile technologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As a result, mobile devices have changed the way that consumers manage their health and engage with the health care system [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Evidence suggests that mHealth can facilitate the provision of effective interventions and support the self-management of long-term conditions [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Self-management is an interactive, dynamic, and daily set of activities by which people manage their long-term condition through overlapping skills, tasks, and processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>[16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, despite its growing popularity over the last decade, systematic research on the use of mHealth as a means of improving health outcomes remains scarce [17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Many mHealth development studies to date, mostly outcome studies and randomized control trials (RCT), have failed to include patients or end users in a meaningful way or considered them only in limited ways in the design process [5,14,19-22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This oversight has contributed to technology redundancy and abandonment rates [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Qualitative research that provides a more in-depth understanding of users’ views and experiences of how eHealth and mHealth affects their lives [23,24] is of vital importance if we are to understand how people use or benefit from technology and what drives them to engage, or not, with these technologies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>With the fast accumulation of qualitative studies in practice disciplines that specifically reflect experiences and subjective perspectives there is a need to bring together evidence from these studies [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We therefore conducted a systematic review in order to collect and synthesize all qualitative evidence exploring the use of ICTs and/or mobile information and communication technologies (mICTs) by people with mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We sought to answer the following review questions: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="?"><plain>Why do people with mood disorders use (m)ICTs? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="?"><plain>What are (m)ICTs being used for by people with mood disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="?"><plain>What are the perceived benefits and challenges of using (m)ICTs by people with mood disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="?"><plain>In what ways are (m)ICTs being used for self-management by people with mood disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="?"><plain>What role, if any, do (m)ICTs play in terms of social relationships for people with mood disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Rationale </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>A protocol for the review was published in PROSPERO (ID=CRD42014008841). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The systematic review and metasynthesis drew on methods proposed by Sandelowski and Barroso [26], Thomas and Harden [27], and Barnett-Page and Thomas [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Qualitative research synthesis is an approach developed to make use of this proliferation of qualitative findings driven from the growth of empirical research and evidence-based practice in the 1990s [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Search Strategy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Due to potential difficulties in finding qualitative research [27], a sensitive systematic search strategy was created to maximize the likelihood of finding all relevant studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The strategy consisted of two search strings combining thesaurus terms, free-text terms, and broad-based terms: one for ICTs/mICTs and one for qualitative methods (See Textbox 1 for an example of a search). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Initially there were also terms for mood disorders, however, the pilot searches identified the inclusion of this string as being too specific limiting the aggregative capabilities of the search strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The systematic review would therefore categorize and catalogue all qualitative health research related to ICTs with mood disorder being the category focused upon for synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><boxed-text id="box1" position="float"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Example search of Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(MH “World Wide Web Applications+”) (MH “Computers, Hand-Held”) (MH “Macintosh Microcomputers”) (MH “Multimedia”) OR (MH “Social Media”) (MH “Telemedicine+”) OR (MH “Telepsychiatry”) OR (MH “Telehealth+”) (MH “Computers, Portable+”) (MH “Computer Input Devices+”)OR TI App OR TX Mobile phone*OR TX Mobile Internet OR TX Sony OR TX HTC OR TX Nokia OR TX Samsung OR TX Wireless OR TI 5G OR TI 4G OR TI 3G OR TX Touch screen OR TX Context-aware system* OR TX Cel* Phone* OR TX User-centered design OR TX Mobile app* OR TX Internet treatment OR TX Virtual realit* OR TX Internet delivered OR TX Mobile technolog* OR TX Electronic health OR TX Mobile health OR TX iPad* OR TI Apple OR TX mHealth OR TX eHealth OR TX Android OR TX Blackberry OR TX Windows mobile* OR TX Windows phone* OR TX Smartphone* OR TX iPhone* OR TI Mobile* </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>(MH “Phenomenological Research”) OR (MH “Observational Methods+”) OR (MH “Patient Attitudes”) OR (MH “Ethnographic Research”) OR (MH “Constant Comparative Method”) OR (MH “Purposive Sample”) OR (MH “Qualitative Studies+”) OR (MH “Focus Groups”) OR TX Theoretical sample OR TX Qualitative research OR TX Theoretical saturation OR TX Mixed methodolog* </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>1 AND 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Limit 3 to published 2007-2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></boxed-text><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Searches were run in eight electronic databases: Medline, Embase, Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health, the psychological literature database, Applied Social Sciences Index and Abstracts, British Nursing Index, Social Sciences Citation Index, and Cochrane Library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The results from each database were exported into Endnote X7 where duplicates were removed electronically and manually. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The title and abstracts of the remaining articles were exported into a Microsoft Word document and numbered ready for screening. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Additionally, to optimize qualitative article retrieval the following methods were used: footnote searching; citation searching; journal run; area scanning; and author searching. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In addition, experts and key authors were contacted to identify unpublished and ongoing studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Due to research on the mobile aspect of ICTs being an emerging field, it was envisaged that grey literature might be a valuable source of primary data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Grey literature covers a wide range of material including: reports, government publications, fact sheets, newsletters, conference proceedings, policy documents, and protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We therefore searched the following sources for grey literature: The New York Academy of Medicine’s Grey Literature report and Open Grey and Grey Source Index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The Journal of Medical Internet Research and Biomedcentral Psychiatry were hand searched from 2007 to present day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Eligibility and Screening </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>One reviewer screened all of the titles and abstracts for inclusion in accordance with the following inclusion criteria: study used widely accepted qualitative methods to elicit in-depth experiences with findings appearing well supported by raw data (eg, participant quotes); study sample included people with mood disorders; study sample included the use of (m)ICTs; time period of 2007 to 2014 (2007 saw the release of the first ‘smartphone’, ie, Apple’s iPhone); and English language. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To optimize the validity of the search a systematic sampling strategy was adopted, whereby 10% of results were coscreened (HF &amp; SM/LM) to facilitate consistency of approach [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>All questionable citations from the full search results were discussed in order to reach consensus on disposal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Full texts were retrieved for those publications that were deemed to meet inclusion criteria and those that could not be adequately assessed for inclusion with the information provided in the abstract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Two authors independently assessed the full texts for inclusion and then met to discuss their decisions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Where they could not come to a consensus, a third author was consulted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Quality Appraisal </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>There is a lack of agreement about the approach to quality appraisal in qualitative research [26,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Therefore, due to the scarcity of data on the topic being studied, papers were not excluded based on quality, instead all papers were included and their quality appraised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A global assessment of study quality was undertaken assessing studies as being either strong or weak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Strong studies would likely include elements of respondent validation, triangulation of data, transparency, reflexivity, clear descriptions of methodology, methods of data collection, analysis, and an overall fit in regards to the research questions and the design of the project [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Reports were both individually and comparatively appraised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A typology designed by Sandelowski and Barroso [32] for classifying findings was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Rather than comparing differences in quality between studies the typology was used to identify the level of data transformation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Synthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The synthesis stage used thematic synthesis, an approach that combines elements of meta-ethnography and grounded theory providing the opportunity to synthesis methodologically heterogeneous studies [27,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The thematic synthesis followed a three-step process described in Textbox 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><boxed-text id="box2" position="float"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Thematic synthesis steps. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Step 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Free sentence-by-sentence coding: the verbatim findings of each selected study were entered into NVivo 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Codes were developed initially free from hierarchical structure but as the translation of concepts developed from one study to another new codes were either added to existing ones or new codes created. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Step2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Organization of free codes in hierarchical order under a range of descriptive themes: free codes were organized into related areas to create descriptive themes; then similarities and differences between codes were studied, facilitating the organization of the codes into related groups and the formation of a hierarchical tree structure of descriptive themes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Step 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Development of analytical themes: descriptive themes were analyzed and then organized into more abstract analytical themes, producing a synthesis that went beyond the data in the original studies and addressed the research questions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></boxed-text><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>In order to keep the synthesis as close to the data as possible the research questions were initially set to one side facilitating an inductive process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Codes were applied as part of an iterative process with constant comparison with other codes (Step 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This process was repeated for all the codes until higher order categories were constructed and all codes accounted for (Step 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The review questions were then brought to the fore and used as a framework to guide the analytical process, which focused and transformed the descriptive themes into the final synthesis (Step 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The categorization process was examined by the reviewing team where, through discussion, changes, and adaptions were made where necessary until consensus was reached and no further changes were required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The reviewing team scrutinized the synthesis at an analytical level through a cyclical process until a final synthesis was achieved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Search findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The search identified 12,926 titles; 67 publications were retrieved in full (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The methodological designs of the studies were qualitative or mixed-methods using focus groups, interviews, or forum/message boards as the methods for generating data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Studies originated mainly from Europe, the United States, or Australia and New Zealand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Only one paper was identified from the systematic review of qualitative papers and therefore, synthesis of mICTs and mood disorders was not possible due to lack of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>However, the review mapped and categorized all qualitative papers in the domain of health and ICT research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This facilitated methodological development in order to find a solution regarding how to use imperfect data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Rather than lose the potentially valuable qualitative data of relevance to the project, the 67 full-text papers were rescreened. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The aggregative and sensitive systematic search strategy offered a flexible approach toward the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This provided the researchers with the ability to use the existing data to explore how people with mood disorders used ICTs ‘of relevance’ to mobile technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This would include, but not be limited to, ICTs such as websites, online therapy, online support groups, forums, blogs, and so on, essentially, ICTs that could be accessed from mICTs but were not necessarily made explicit within the text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Thirty-four studies were included in the synthesis after the full-text articles had been rescreened; a summary of their results can be found in Multimedia Appendix 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The results of the appraisal process are shown in Table 1 with 22 studies identified as being strong and 12 weak, with most having a typology of findings either at the topical or thematic survey levels of data transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Therefore, with over a third of the studies being weak in quality, the appraised strength of the studies weighed upon, in a measured manner, our interpretation of the study findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The synthesis created three analytical themes and a number of respective analytical subthemes to describe people’s use of ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This is presented as a typology of findings (Textbox 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The research questions were then used as a template, explicating the typology of findings to understand how the descriptive themes interrelated with their analytical themes, thus helping to answer the questions asked of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The results are presented below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Appraisal of qualitative papers in metasynthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="623" cellpadding="7" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="10" span="1"/><col width="83" span="1"/><col width="183" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Global assessment of study quality </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Weak </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>12 (35) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Strong </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>22 (65) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Typology of findings </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>No findings </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>4 (12) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Topical survey </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>11 (32) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Thematic survey </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>14 (41) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Conceptual thematic description </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>5 (15) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Interpretive explanation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>0 (0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Total </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>34 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><boxed-text id="box3" position="float"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Typology of findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Movement and change </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Change processes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Engagement </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Motivational aspects of use </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Recovery </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Taking action </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Values </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Providing a source of community </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Communication </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Intrapersonal effects </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Safe places </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Sharing </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Social aspects </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The person and technology </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Acceptance of technology </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Design features </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Functionality </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Personal time </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Safety </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Technical mastery </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Technical issues </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Usability </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></boxed-text><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="figure1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>PRISMA diagram of screened articles of relevance to mood disorders and mICT . </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mental_v3i3e30_fig1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="?"><plain>Why do People With Mood Disorders use (Mobile) Information and Communication Technologies? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Considerable overlap was found in terms of why people used ICTs and the perceived benefits this technology gave them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Two studies [33,34] provided data regarding motivation to use ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>For those involved in Internet-based treatment, the interactive nature of ICTs appeared to increase their motivation to engage with treatment and, in so doing, possibly help in their recovery [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Three studies showed how users of ICTs liked the option of being able to choose where to use technology (ie, at work or in the convenience of their own homes) [35-37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Having easy access to information from around the world, at any time in the day, through use of the Internet was regarded as useful in comparison to using books [37,38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The use of websites to support relatives of people with depression appeared to decrease feelings of stigma in both by enabling people to draw strength from talking more openly about their situation [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Young people were concerned about feelings of embarrassment if other people realized they had depression increasing a sense of helplessness [38-40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Fear of being judged by others due to having a mental health issue was a particular problem faced by some young users of ICTs and it became a specific reason for using the technology [39,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Fear of school peers finding out and potential links to bullying opted users to engage with ICTs in the privacy of their own homes [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>People who felt shame due to experiencing emotional problems would put a lot of effort into hiding their symptoms so having a website where people could discuss their emotional problems anonymously was considered a good thing and often would be the first time sharing their experiences [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The use of websites to support relatives of people with depression appeared to decrease feelings of stigma and support their mental health [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Using Web-based assessment tools appeared to facilitate dialogue between patients and clinicians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>For instance, patients felt it was easier to talk to their general practitioner as they had thought about things beforehand and would be more confident in receiving a diagnosis [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Of significant importance to using ICTs was the concept of privacy [37,42-44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs were considered, by some, as providing the most private way to seek help for psychological issues [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>ICTs appeared to provide people with options regarding how they used technology with choice over temporal, location, treatment, privacy, and disclosure aspects of their care needs [33,38,39,41,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The credibility of ICTs appeared an important factor when deciding upon usage [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>For example, having testimonials from other users displayed on Web pages regarding credibility, and knowledge that the ICT was designed on research appeared to raise confidence in technology [35,46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>ICTs were also regarded as cost-effective solutions to access-to-care problems faced by people living in remote localities, by both patients and health professionals [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Participants reported being aware of long waiting times for specialist health services and, with the alternative being expensive private treatment, the low cost nature of ICTs made them attractive [34,37,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Modifying aspects of ICTs with a user-centered design appeared to facilitate use to some extent by reducing technical challenges and helped people feel more competent and autonomous [48,49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="?"><plain>What are (Mobile) Information and Communication Technologies Being Used for by People With Mood Disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The use and view of ICTs as a resource appeared to be an important factor in people’s lives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>ICTs could open up access to information, support, and treatment in a highly accessible, interactive, and instant way [37,38,42,50,51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The Internet was also considered empowering [45] and provided a resource for learning [46,48,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Holding certain values appeared to suggest people were going to commit to using and completing therapeutic work via ICTs more than others, for example, having a sense of what one should, or should not do, appeared to influence some people’s commitment to complete Web-based programs regardless of how tedious or frustrating they were [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>ICTs appeared to be used as a resource for people to communicate and exchange information and stories with others [38,43,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>They appeared to facilitate disclosure of personal information regarding people’s mental health [40], indicating a need by people to talk about their issues [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="?"><plain>What are the Perceived Benefits and Challenges of Using (Mobile) Information and Communication Technologies by People With Mood Disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>There was significant overlap in terms of why people use ICTs and the benefits provided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>As these benefits have already been identified and discussed in the previous two sections, this section focuses on the challenges of using technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Certain forms of technology and their functionalities produced usage difficulties [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>That is, people were put off using ICTs if software was slow, had broken hyperlinks, was unnecessarily complex or impersonal, and if use required additional software [47,50,54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For some people, there were concerns regarding the safety of using ICTs for treatment purposes due to queries regarding the levels of confidentiality the technology could provide [47,52,55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Being able to use ICTs anonymously appeared to be an important aspect in managing confidentiality and a factor when assessing the appropriateness of using a Web-based intervention [37,40,43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Indeed, there were people who preferred not to share personal information unless it was face-to-face due to the importance they placed on confidentiality [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Some people made a conscious decision not to use ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Reasons included having no interest in certain forms of technology, not being technologically savvy, and being too unwell to use technology (for example, reduced energy and motivation due to an acute depressive phase) [38,41,56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>There were also practical reasons for not using ICTs, such as, having no need to use it, not identifying with content, inhibitive cost, or having no Internet connection [42,48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Users needed to believe and trust in the ICTs they were using [48,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>There were concerns regarding information reliability and quality on the Internet, and doubts as to whether people had the ability to discriminate trustworthy information themselves [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Of note, was the generally limited mention of negative outcomes in the reviewed studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="?"><plain>In What Ways are (Mobile) Information and Communication Technologies Being Used for Self-Management Purposes by People With Mood Disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The use of ICTs appeared to support people to acquire relevant knowledge in regards to their mood problems providing a sense of recognition in situations that might be difficult to accept or unfamiliar, thus helping them feel supported [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>ICTs were used, by some, to acquire information about treatment, diseases, drug information, and the experiences of others [44,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Some people read information specifically targeted toward health professionals as they deemed it to be the most comprehensive and up-to-date sources of information [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Seeing relevance in material appeared to be a factor in the process of acquiring new self-knowledge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This was achieved through learning together by reflecting and restructuring new knowledge to suit one’s own needs [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>ICTs appeared to be being used for help-seeking through the acquirement of self-help information, the development of skills, and also as a means to seek help through online support groups and forums [38,40,45,57,58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Sitting down at a computer at regular times working on a self-help programs appeared to be of benefit; people reported experiencing an empowering effect, a change of perspective, increased personal agency, and a way of keeping new learning at the forefront of their minds [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>A programs to help monitor depression (on a mobile phone) appeared to hold potential as a motivational tool to support people to look after themselves [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Self-help books were viewed as having a number of disadvantages such as being hard to read, noninteractive, and difficult to engage with; where available, people preferred Web-based versions [50,59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>ICTs appeared to provide people with informational support and the ability to delve as deeply as they wished into certain topics, such as medication management, counselling services, negative thinking, and poor concentration [40,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The Internet appeared to be considered a key component in providing greater access to health information by patients and receiving benefits from engaging in self-help [34,40,45,46,52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>ICTs appeared to help provide a sense of control in people’s lives by providing them with the opportunity to find information about where to find help, assisted them with understanding when to seek help, and what support was available to them [38,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>They helped prepare for meetings with health professionals, thus making treatment more collaborative [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Support from online forums was flexible and inexpensive [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Maintaining contact with friends and family was also feasible through diverse Web-based platforms [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Receiving support through ICTs appeared to be of benefit by people with mood disorders [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>People required support in maintaining relationships and dealing with broken relationships while recovering from a mood disorder [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Methods of support, in preference to telephone calls or home visits by professionals, included the use of emails due to their unintrusive nature [49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>People also appeared to benefit from support from friends, family members, and significant others to encourage and help them persist with using ICTs for their recovery [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs potentially offered a means to lessen stigma toward mental health and encourage acceptance of conditions such as Bipolar Disorder [35,37,52,61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs supported people to feel validated and empowered increasing feelings of confidence and self-worth [36,46,57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Learning time management techniques facilitated people to organize their time better helping them meet deadlines and prepare for exams [35,48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Time was required to be set aside to use ICTs and having personal time in a private space was appreciated [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>People taking responsibility for their treatment, had a sense of determination, curiosity, and attributed success to their own endeavors appeared to benefit more from treatment delivered through ICTs [53,62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>People were able to use ICTs to contact health professionals and source health information for themselves, which appeared to help them manage their own problems moving from a position of passivity to one of activity [34,38,53,62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Being aware of one’s motivational levels and having responsibility for maintaining motivation to use interventions delivered through ICTs appeared helpful [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Holding certain values would help people to complete Web-based programs and others found their own way of working with material to face and overcome challenges and seeing difficulties as potentially valuable lessons to be learned [53,62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>People’s awareness sometimes appeared to change when using ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>For instance, becoming aware of holding high expectations toward technology and feeling disappointment if programs did not meet all their needs fostered a sense of consideration to revisit and work with material to see if it would be of benefit [62,63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs held the potential to help people become more aware of their negative thinking habits, promoting reflection, and challenging of thoughts moving people in a more positive direction toward self-acceptance [34,37,50,64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Participant feedback in the design process of ICTs potentially influenced the goals of particular programs centering on raising awareness regarding the importance of managing depressive symptoms among their users [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The use of ICTs to access information and seek other people’s opinions through online forums for example offered different viewpoints and helped people understand more about the difficulties they faced [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="?"><plain>What Role, if any, do (Mobile) Information and Communication Technologies Play in Terms of Social Relationships for People With Mood Disorders? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Using ICTs for social support appeared to be of benefit to people and one of the predominant reasons for using the technology on a daily basis [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Meeting similar people in virtual environments created a sense of acknowledgement and recognition decreasing feelings of social isolation, loneliness, and alienation [37,48,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>People could use ICTs as an opportunity for sharing their feelings, emotions, and personal stories [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The exchange of experiences and knowledge in a supportive environment appeared to help people; narrate their experiences, gain a sense of community, share tips, and provide a sense of comfort, strength, and hope in people [37,42-45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Using ICTs made some users less inhibited, in terms of the personal information they shared, because they felt more secure about privacy being maintained and, therefore, found ICTs less discomforting than face-to-face interactions [37,38,40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>ICTs provided people with the capacity to use online social networks in order to communicate with people experiencing similar issues, to ask advice or discuss certain topics in a convenient and accessible manner [37,38,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>ICTs also provided people with the opportunity to receive and give peer support [37,44,50,66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Peer support appeared to help people engage with Web-based interventions, overcome procrastination and motivational issues, and helped them to understand their own problems in a way that gave potential for behavior change [44,50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The aim of the study was to conduct a metasynthesis of all qualitative studies exploring the use of ICTs by people with mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The resultant metasynthesis created an analytical typology of findings and a descriptively themed framework, which conceptualized how people with mood disorder use and relate to their ICTs, and in so doing, answered the specific review questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The metasynthesis identified that people with mood disorders use ICTs in similar ways and face similar technological paradoxes as other users [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>However, the metasynthesis developed the understanding further, suggesting a continuum of use, in this instance, by people with mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>How ICTs of relevance to mobile technology are used and harnessed by this particular client group are discussed below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Our metasynthesis identified the factors influencing why people with mood disorders chose to use ICTs such as affordability, accessibility, and versatility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>These factors align closely with previous studies on the delivery of health-related products evidenced through increasing Web-based self-help resources [4], effective delivery of psychological interventions [68], and their ability to reach rural areas within diverse populations and settings [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The body of eHealth research is expanding with studies across different patient groups, using different technologies/interventions, and focusing on different outcomes [69-73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>In their interpretive review of the literature on consumer eHealth, Hordern et al [74] identified five broad usage themes: (1) peer-to-peer online support groups and health-related virtual communities, (2) self-management/self-monitoring applications, (3) decision aids, (4) the personal health record, and (5) Internet use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The results of our metasynthesis reflected these uses but also highlight a number of intrinsic factors affecting people’s use of ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>People were motivated to use ICTs to aid recovery, associated with the convenience afforded to them through using the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The privacy and choice of communication methods of ICTs were seen as facilitative and credible options often wrapped-up in cost-effective and user-center designed products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Seen as a resource, ICT use was empowering, facilitating people to self-care or self-manage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The Internet was considered a key component in providing greater access to health information by patients and for them to receive benefits from engaging in self-help [34,40,45,46,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>ICTs helped provide a sense of control in people’s lives by providing them with the opportunity to access information to help themselves, bettered their understanding about when to seek help, and increased awareness of what help was available [38,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>They facilitated people to prepare for meetings with their health professionals making treatment more collaborative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Receiving support through ICTs was seen to be of benefit by people with mood disorders [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>ICTs potentially facilitated people to take the first step in managing their recovery after years of deliberation [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>ICTs supported people to stay in contact with health professionals involved in their care and establish therapeutic relationships despite being separated by distance [38,47,49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>People were able to use ICTs to contact health professionals and source health information for themselves in order to manage their problems by converting intentions into actions [34,38,53,62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>People who took responsibility for their treatment, had a sense of determination, curiosity, and attributed success to their own endeavors appeared to benefit more from treatment delivered through ICTs [53,62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>ICTs that were stimulating to use and interacted well with peoples' senses and cognitive abilities enhanced engagement [46]; this was deemed vital in the context of online depression therapy [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>With engagement came an enhanced sense of personal agency from interacting with ICTs and the completion of Web-based activities offered a sense of empowerment [37,46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The functionality of ICTs was an important factor in their adoption and use [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>For example, having functions to compare information from day-to-day to week-to-week, track information, format content, use Web-based diaries, forums, bookmarks, blogs, messages, control privacy settings, invitation functions, e-reminders, and options to reply directly to clinicians were important usage features [37,42-44,49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>ICTs with increased usability were desirable [38,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>For example, having a user-interface that could be personally controlled, with an array of images, colors, information, and music options, could help engage the user [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In addition, being able to use ICTs in different locations (such as, work, home, or on public transport) appeared important factors when assessing usability by the user [37,42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>When designing ICTs and Web-based interventions importance was placed upon managing depressive symptoms in order to support people, through evidence-based interventions, with their practical and interpersonal issues caused by their conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>[50,65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs supported users to work on solving problems through taking a structured approach using manageable steps [46,57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>If people focused on achieving manageable goals then it provided them with a sense of completion [50,53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs supported people to cognitively restructure, facilitating them to rethink stressful situations that challenged their negative thought patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Web-based programs also facilitated behavioral changes by breaking negative cycles of inactivity, self-incrimination, and withdrawal, which lead to secondary benefits as people become closer to those around them [34,35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Peer support accessed through ICTs helped people to feel more positive and understand themselves better leading to behavior change and the confidence to negotiate changes in treatment [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Accessing Web-based medication information through ICT use prompted some people to request additional drug information from their prescriber regarding risks and benefits of antidepressants and conversely, made others change the dose of drug or discontinue the prescription without seeking professional guidance first [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Having a sense of curiosity toward ICTs and a will to learn self-management techniques and, if an improvement in their health was noticed through using ICTs, then they were more likely to persist with an intervention [48,53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>ICTs supported people to stay in contact with health professionals involved in their care and to establish therapeutic relationships despite being separated by distance [38,47,49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>However, ICTs can be viewed to have paradoxical elements to them; social and economic paradoxes, which challenged people in their social and individual lives [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The findings of our metasynthesis indicate that usage difficulties were a key factor in reducing people’s motivation to use ICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>This aligns well with the findings of others, including Bessel et al [75] who identified that computer-based interventions have limitations, such as the reliance on users having access to computers at scheduled times and restricted and unreliable Internet access in remote and rural areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Safety was a key concern raised from the synthesis with the concept of confidentiality and data security being paramount. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>This is clearly associated with the disadvantages of ICTs such as software errors, unreliable information, problems with privacy and unreliability, lack of regulation, social isolation, and in some forms of technology, the loss of vocal intonation and nonverbal communication [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Internet-delivered treatment programs such as open access websites are characterized by poor adherence with an average dropout rate of 31% [76,77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>There are many advantages for patients when using ICTs, such as being able to get in contact with health professionals quickly and easily, a reduction in travel and waiting times for face-to-face appointments, convenience, and affordability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>The technology provides a medium for communication between health professionals and patients where information about the patients’ disease, treatment, and therapeutic interventions can be discussed [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>This is of particular importance for those with long-term conditions and our metasynthesis reinforces this point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>In contrast to other forms of patient contact, ICTs provide the opportunity for asynchronous communication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>eHealth holds the potential to enable patients to better manage their long-term health conditions through the use of technology [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Our metasynthesis identified that people used ICTs to acquire relevant knowledge in regards to their mental health issues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>This can be linked to an increasing trend in society to adopt self-service models of interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>There have been promising results for using computers to deliver self-management programs to patients with long-term conditions in health-supported settings showing potential for changing health behavior and improving clinical outcomes [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Since 2005, interest in the Internet as a vehicle to disseminate interventions designed to treat and prevent mental disorders, including those targeted at depression, has been increasing [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Passive psychoeducational information might be an effective intervention for depression when employed with reminders and involving minimal information [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>In their systematic review, Griffiths et al [11] identified that the Internet was highly effective and facilitative when used to deliver mental health interventions with or without practitioner guidance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Web-based CBT has also been shown to provide small benefits when used to help manage chronic pain [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>However, in a recent meta-analysis of computerized cognitive behavioral therapy (cCBT) by So et al [9] only short-term reductions in symptoms were noted, long-term follow-up and functional improvement were not significant and there was a recommendation that the clinical usefulness of cCBT should be reconsidered downward in terms of methodological validity and practical implementation [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Therefore, further research is required to help understand peoples’ self-service approach to accessing Web-based health information and their acceptability and use of Web-based therapeutic interventions [80]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Outcome data from RCTs and meta-analyses have identified the cost-effectiveness and clinical efficacy of mental health programs delivered via ICTs with comparable effect sizes to face-to-face treatment [14,81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Web-based interventions have also highlighted positive effects on patient empowerment and self-efficacy including people with physical health conditions such as cancer [82,83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Our metasynthesis suggests similar outcomes for people with mood disorder and that ICTs can provide opportunities for help seeking and support for such people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Yet, evidence points to the variable quality of information and apps available on the Internet [7,84-87]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>There appear to be numerous health-related websites with limited availability of help, containing information that can be difficult to read and incomplete [85,86]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Our metasynthesis identified that people with mood disorder were using ICTs to give and receive social support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>This corresponds with evidence from SNS use and associated indices of psychological well-being relating to a persons’ sense of self-worth, self-esteem, satisfaction with life, and other psychological development measures [88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>The metasynthesis identified that people with mood disorder where using social networks in a similar way as suggested by Cohen [89] by providing platforms to give and receive social support in the form of informational support, instrumental support, and emotional support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>The metasynthesis highlighted how ICTs facilitate people with mood disorder to communicate with others, corresponding to previous work undertaken regarding Web-based disinhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Suler [90] suggests that a number of factors can loosen psychological barriers allowing for inhibition to become reduced when on the Internet: invisibility, dissociative anonymity, synchronicity, dissociative imagination, solipsistic introjections, and minimizing authority. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>People use social networking sites (SNSs) for their sociability function to maintain relationships with on and offline friends over varying distances [91] attending to extended social networks and relationships [92,93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Before the development of popular Web-based SNSs such as Facebook, Skinner and Zack [94] had already identified that barriers to communication were being overcome through using the Internet and as a result people were getting help in ways convenient to them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Of particular importance was the lack of qualitative research being undertaken in this field as evidenced by only one paper retrieved specifically reporting on mICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>To date, patients or end uses have not been sufficiently included in the design of software applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The same applies to the selection of relevant and appropriate outcome measures in effectiveness studies such as RCTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>These omissions have contributed to redundancy and the abandonment of technology. n fact, there has been a presumption that those designing technology and undertaking research already know what the user wants in terms of software and hardware. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Designers have, jumped ahead, and designed apps and websites, without first talking to end users about how they use and fit technology into both their existing lives and what would help them manage their lives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Qualitative research, which provides a more in-depth understanding of users’ views and experiences is of vital importance if we are to understand how people use or benefit from technology and what drives them to engage, or not, with these technologies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Recommendations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Research: research relating to how people with mood disorder used ICTs was lacking and in particular, their use of mICTs, not as participants in research studies, but as ubiquitous technology in their everyday lives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Qualitative research is required to help understand how mICTs fit into people’s lives both in general but also more specifically in relation to their mood disorders. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Practice: clinical practice could be supported through understanding how people with mood disorder use mICTs to look after themselves providing clinicians with valuable information to help harness peoples’ mICTs for use in their recovery and inform the future design of technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Strengths and Limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>The review relied exclusively upon English language publications, which may not adequately reflect the user experiences and perceptions that were gathered in non-English speaking contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Another issue may relate to the quality of primary data sources and the quality of existing quality appraisal tools for metasyntheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>The researcher’s stance was clearly set out in the study providing rationales for the choice of methodology and methods used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Transparency was achieved by clearly detailing the synthesis process and checks and balances were used to ensure rigor throughout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>The study originally set out to synthesis all qualitative articles regarding people with mood disorder and mICT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, as only one article met the original inclusion criteria for mobile technology a synthesis of this material was not possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>However, our novel approach toward the search and retrieval of data allowed us to catalogue all qualitative data related to health and ICTs including data of relevance to mICTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>This process provided us with the opportunity to restructure our inclusion criteria and make use of the data that would have otherwise been neglected in other systematic reviews and metasyntheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The metasynthesis of people with mood disorders and their use of ICTs has provided a tentative understanding into their uses, challenges, and gratifications spanning the intrapersonal, interpersonal, and through into wider society. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The typology of findings and analytical framework highlights the connections and interrelationships between analytical themes and subcategories; the intrinsic and extrinsic nature of use and the embedded characteristics of the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Our metasynthesis has identified that people can use ICTs in novel ways to help them manage their lives and health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>People use ICTs to support motivation, for their convenience, to help decrease feelings of stigma, their facilitative capabilities, enhance privacy, credibility, and cost effectiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>ICTs support people to access the Internet to get what they need in a way that fits into their lives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>ICTs are a resource for communication and promote user engagement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>However, they are not without issue, with particular challenges of trust and confidentially requiring to be negotiated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>That being said, when the challenges are navigated successfully, people are able access opportunities to manage their mood disorder by acquiring relevant knowledge, engage in help-seeking behavior, receive support, gain a sense of control, learn time management techniques, take responsibility, and increase their awareness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>ICTs also allow access to Web-based social networks where sharing with others can facilitate social support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Our typology of findings creates an empirical basis to help guide and harness the potential of (m)ICTs to support self-management, facilitate collaborative, person-centered care, and support the person actively recover from their mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Importantly, our metasynthesis has highlighted a gap in the evidence base, as no research has focused specifically on mICT use by people with mood disorder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Authors' Contributions: H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Fulford undertook the metasynthesis and manuscript preparation with principal supervision from S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>MacGillivray and additional supervision from L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>McSwiggan and T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Kroll. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Conflicts of Interest: None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="app1"><title>Multimedia Appendix 1</title><p>Summary of results</p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="d36e1476" position="anchor"><media xlink:href="mental_v3i3e30_app1.pdf"/></fig></SecTag></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="abb1">cCBT</term><def><p>computerized cognitive behavioral therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb2">BD</term><def><p>bipolar disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb3">GP</term><def><p>general practitioner</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb4">mICTs</term><def><p>mobile information and communication technologies</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb5">ICTs</term><def><p>information and communication technologies</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb6">RCT</term><def><p>randomized control trials</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb7">SNS</term><def><p>social networking site</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>1PowerMThe Wiley-Blackwell Handbook of Mood Disorders2013Chichester, UKWiley-Blackwell </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref2"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>2HouleJGascon-DepatieMBélanger-DumontierGCardinalCDepression self-management support: a systematic reviewPatient Educ Couns20139127127910.1016/j.pec.2013.01.0122341483123414831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref3"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>3SolomonMRInformation technology to support self-management in chronic care: a systematic reviewDisease Management &amp; Health Outcomes20081639140110.2165/0115677-200816060-00004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref4"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>4Van'tHECuijpersPSteinDJSelf-help and Internet-guided interventions in depression and anxiety disorders: a systematic review of meta-analysesCNS Spectr2009214Suppl 334401923812819238128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref5"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>5LyKHCarlbringPAnderssonGBehavioral activation-based guided self-help treatment administered through a smartphone application: study protocol for a randomized controlled trialTrials20121362<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1745-6215-13-62"/>10.1186/1745-6215-13-622260730222607302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref6"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>6RichardsDRichardsonTComputer-based psychological treatments for depression: a systematic review and meta-analysisClin Psychol Rev20123232934210.1016/j.cpr.2012.02.0042246651022466510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref7"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>7Eland-deKPvanOHVergouwe-MeijerABruijnzeel-KoomenCRosWA systematic review of the effects of e-health on chronically ill patientsJ Clin Nurs2011202997301010.1111/j.1365-2702.2011.03743.x2170780721707807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref8"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>8PagliariCSloanDGregorPSullivanFDetmerDKahanJPOortwijnWMacGillivraySWhat is eHealth (4): a scoping exercise to map the fieldJ Med Internet Res20057e9<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2005/1/e9/"/>10.2196/jmir.7.1.e91582948115829481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref9"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>9SoMYamaguchiSHashimotoSSadoMFurukawaTAMcCronePIs computerised CBT really helpful for adult depression?-A meta-analytic re-evaluation of CCBT for adult depression in terms of clinical implementation and methodological validityBMC Psychiatry201313113<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/13/113"/>10.1186/1471-244X-13-1132358734723587347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref10"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>10DölemeyerRTietjenAKerstingAWagnerBInternet-based interventions for eating disorders in adults: a systematic reviewBMC Psychiatry201313207<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/13/207"/>10.1186/1471-244X-13-2072391962523919625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref11"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>11GriffithsKMFarrerLChristensenHThe efficacy of internet interventions for depression and anxiety disorders: a review of randomised controlled trialsMed J Aust2010192SupplS4S112052870720528707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref12"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>12PulmanATwitter as a tool for delivering improved quality of life for people with chronic conditionsJournal of Nursing &amp; Healthcare of Chronic Illnesses20091324525210.1111/j.1752-9824.2009.01027.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref13"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>13CooperAUsing social networks to help patients self-careNurs Times201310922242356034323560343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref14"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>14HarrisonVProudfootJWeePPParkerGPavlovicDHManicavasagarVMobile mental health: review of the emerging field and proof of concept studyJ Ment Health20112050952410.3109/09638237.2011.6087462198823021988230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref15"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>15NilsenWKumarSSharAVaroquiersCWileyTRileyWTPavelMAtienzaAAAdvancing the science of mHealthJ Health Commun2012Suppl 151010.1080/10810730.2012.6773942254859322548593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref16"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>16Schulman-GreenDJaserSMartinFAlonzoAGreyMMcCorkleRRedekerNSReynoldsNWhittemoreRProcesses of self-management in chronic illnessJ Nurs Scholarsh201244136144<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/22551013"/>10.1111/j.1547-5069.2012.01444.x2255101322551013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref17"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>17FiordelliMDivianiNSchulzPJMapping mHealth research: a decade of evolutionJ Med Internet Res201315e95<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2013/5/e95/"/>10.2196/jmir.24302369760023697600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref18"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>18DennisonLMorrisonLConwayGYardleyLOpportunities and challenges for smartphone applications in supporting health behavior change: qualitative studyJ Med Internet Res201315e86<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2013/4/e86/"/>10.2196/jmir.25832359861423598614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref19"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>19WhittakerRMerrySDoreyEMaddisonRA development and evaluation process for mHealth interventions: examples from New ZealandJ Health Commun2012Suppl 1112110.1080/10810730.2011.6491032254859422548594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref20"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>20WattsSMackenzieAThomasCGriskaitisAMewtonLWilliamsAAndrewsGCBT for depression: a pilot RCT comparing mobile phone vs. computerBMC Psychiatry20131349<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/13/49"/>10.1186/1471-244X-13-492339130423391304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref21"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>21BurnsMNBegaleMDuffecyJGergleDKarrCJGiangrandeEMohrDCHarnessing context sensing to develop a mobile intervention for depressionJ Med Internet Res201113e55<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2011/3/e55/"/>10.2196/jmir.18382184083721840837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref22"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>22Ben-ZeevDKaiserSMBrennerCJBegaleMDuffecyJMohrDCDevelopment and usability testing of FOCUS: a smartphone system for self-management of schizophreniaPsychiatr Rehabil J201336289296<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/24015913"/>10.1037/prj00000192401591324015913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref23"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>23McCurdieTTanevaSCasselmanMYeungMMcDanielCHoWCafazzoJmHealth consumer apps: the case for user-centered designBiomed Instrum Technol2012Suppl495610.2345/0899-8205-46.s2.492303977723039777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref24"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>24De Vito DabbsAMyersBAMc CurryKRDunbar-JacobJHawkinsRPBegeyADewMAUser-centered design and interactive health technologies for patientsComput Inform Nurs200927175183<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/19411947"/>10.1097/NCN.0b013e31819f7c7c1941194719411947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref25"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>25SandelowskiMDochertySEmdenCQualitative metasynthesis: issues and techniquesRes Nurs Health19972036537110.1002/(SICI)1098-240X(199708)20:4&lt;365::AID-NUR9&gt;3.0.CO;2-E9256882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref26"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>26SandelowskiMBarrosoJHandbook for Synthesizing Qualitative Research2007New YorkSpringer Pub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Co </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref27"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>27ThomasJHardenAMethods for the thematic synthesis of qualitative research in systematic reviewsBMC Med Res Methodol2008845<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2288/8/45"/>10.1186/1471-2288-8-451861681818616818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref28"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>28Barnett-PageEThomasJMethods for the synthesis of qualitative research: a critical reviewBMC Med Res Methodol2009959<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bmcmedresmethodol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2288-9-59"/>10.1186/1471-2288-9-591967115219671152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref29"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>29Finfgeld-ConnettDGeneralizability and transferability of meta-synthesis research findingsJ Adv Nurs20106624625410.1111/j.1365-2648.2009.05250.x2042340720423407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref30"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>30LincolnYGubaEgNaturalistic Inquiry1985Beverly Hills, CASage Publications </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref31"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>31MorrisJOliverTKrollTMacgillivraySThe importance of psychological and social factors in influencing the uptake and maintenance of physical activity after stroke: a structured review of the empirical literatureStroke Res Treat20122012195249<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2012/195249"/>10.1155/2012/1952492191873021918730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref32"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>32SandelowskiMBarrosoJClassifying the findings in qualitative studiesQual Health Res2003139059231450295714502957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref33"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>33DrakeGCsipkeEWykesTAssessing your mood online: acceptability and use of MoodscopePsychol Med20134314551464<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0033291712002280"/>10.1017/S00332917120022802314912023149120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref34"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>34LillevollKRWilhelmsenMKolstrupNHøifødtRSWaterlooKEisemannMRisørMBPatients' experiences of helpfulness in guided internet-based treatment for depression: qualitative study of integrated therapeutic dimensionsJ Med Internet Res201315e126<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2013/6/e126/"/>10.2196/jmir.25312378676323786763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref35"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>35BradleyKLRobinsonLMBrannenCLAdolescent help-seeking for psychological distress, depression, and anxiety using an Internet programInternational Journal of Mental Health Promotion201214233410.1080/14623730.2012.665337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref36"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>36ParkerGOrmanJExamining the utility of the Black Dog Institute's online Mood Assessment Program in clinical practiceAustralas Psychiatry201220495210.1177/10398562114324642235767622357676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref37"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>37StjernswärdSOstmanMIlluminating user experience of a website for the relatives of persons with depressionInt J Soc Psychiatry20115737538610.1177/00207640093583882023389520233895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref38"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>38FogelJNehmadEDepression information on the Internet for Asian AmericansJournal of CyberTherapy and Rehabilitation20092243251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref39"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>39FlemingTMDixonRSMerrySN‘It’s mean!’ The views of young people alienated from mainstream education on depression, help seeking and computerised therapyAdvances in Mental Health20141019520310.5172/jamh.2011.10.2.195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref40"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>40HorganAMcCarthyGSweeneyJAn evaluation of an online peer support forum for university students with depressive symptomsArch Psychiatr Nurs201327848910.1016/j.apnu.2012.12.0052354051823540518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref41"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>41CheekCBridgmanHFlemingTCummingsEEllisLLucassenMFShepherdMSkinnerTViews of young people in rural Australia on SPARX, a fantasy world developed for New Zealand youth with depressionJMIR Serious Games20142e3<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://games.jmir.org/2014/1/e3/"/>10.2196/games.31832565911625659116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref42"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>42ProudfootJParkerGHadziPDManicavasagarVAdlerEWhittonACommunity attitudes to the appropriation of mobile phones for monitoring and managing depression, anxiety, and stressJ Med Internet Res201012e64<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2010/5/e64/"/>10.2196/jmir.14752116917421169174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref43"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>43StjernswärdSÖstmanMLöwgrenJOnline self-help tools for the relatives of persons with depression -- a feasibility studyScand J Caring Sci201226708010.1111/j.1471-6712.2011.00905.x2169282421692824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref44"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>44TakahashiYUchidaCMiyakiKSakaiMShimboTNakayamaTPotential benefits and harms of a peer support social network service on the internet for people with depressive tendencies: qualitative content analysis and social network analysisJ Med Internet Res200911e29<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2009/3/e29/"/>10.2196/jmir.11421963297919632979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref45"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>45Pohjanoksa-MäntyläMSaariJKNärhiUKarjalainenAPylkkänenKAiraksinenMSBellJSHow and why do people with depression access and utilize online drug information: a qualitative studyJ Affect Disord200911433333910.1016/j.jad.2008.06.0241869176518691765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref46"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>46PurvesDGDuttonJAn exploration of the therapeutic process while using computerised cognitive behaviour therapyCounselling and Psychotherapy Research20131330831610.1080/14733145.2012.761259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref47"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>47SwintonJJRobinsonWDBischoffRJTelehealth and rural depression: physician and patient perspectivesFam Syst Health20092717218210.1037/a00160141963045819630458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref48"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>48WilhelmsenMLillevollKRisørMBHøifødtRJohansenMWaterlooKEisemannMKolstrupNMotivation to persist with internet-based cognitive behavioural treatment using blended care: a qualitative studyBMC Psychiatry201313296<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/13/296"/>10.1186/1471-244X-13-2962419967224199672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref49"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>49WatkinsDCSmithLCKerberKKueblerJHimleJAEmail reminders as a self-management tool in depression: a needs assessment to determine patients' interests and preferencesJ Telemed Telecare20111737838110.1258/jtt.2011.1101052193389521933895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref50"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="?"><plain>50ToddNJJonesSHLobbanFAWhat do service users with bipolar disorder want from a web-based self-management intervention? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>A qualitative focus group studyClin Psychol Psychother20132053154310.1002/cpp.18042271516122715161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref51"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>51PagliariCBurtonCMcKinstryBSzentatotaiADavidDSerranoBAFerriniLAlbertiniSCastroJCEstevezSWoltersMPsychosocial implications of avatar use in supporting therapy for depressionStud Health Technol Inform20121813293332295488222954882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref52"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>52BarnesESimpsonSGriffithsEHoodKCraddockNSmithDJDeveloping an online psychoeducation package for bipolar disorderJ Ment Health201120213110.3109/09638237.2010.5255652127182321271823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref53"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>53DonkinLGlozierNMotivators and motivations to persist with online psychological interventions: a qualitative study of treatment completersJ Med Internet Res201214e91<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2012/3/e91/"/>10.2196/jmir.21002274358122743581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref54"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>54KurkiMHätönenHKoivunenMAnttilaMVälimäkiMIntegration of computer and Internet-based programmes into psychiatric out-patient care of adolescents with depressionInform Health Soc Care2013389310310.3109/17538157.2012.7106882295814222958142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref55"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>55WhitehillJMBrockmanLNMorenoMA“Just talk to me”: communicating with college students about depression disclosures on FacebookJ Adolesc Health201352122127<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/23260845"/>10.1016/j.jadohealth.2012.09.0152326084523260845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref56"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>56NicholasJProudfootJParkerGGillisIBurckhardtRManicavasagarVSmithMThe ins and outs of an online bipolar education program: a study of program attritionJ Med Internet Res201012e57<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2010/5/e57/"/>10.2196/jmir.14502116916921169169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref57"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>57RichardsDTimulakLClient-identified helpful and hindering events in therapist-delivered vs. self-administered online cognitive-behavioural treatments for depression in college studentsCounselling Psychology Quarterly20122525126210.1080/09515070.2012.703129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref58"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>58ClarkeJnSargentCChildhood depression: parents talk with one another on the ‘netSocial Work in Mental Health2010851052510.1080/15332985.2010.481997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref59"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>59MeyerDOnline self-help: developing a student-focused website for depressionCounselling and Psychotherapy Research2007715115610.1080/14733140701566357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref60"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>60VayredaAAntakiCSocial support and unsolicited advice in a bipolar disorder online forumQual Health Res20091993194210.1177/10497323093389521955640019556400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref61"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>61DanaherBGMilgromJSeeleyJRStuartSSchembriCTylerMSEricksenJLesterWGemmillAWLewinsohnPWeb-based interventions for postpartum depression: formative research and design of the MomMoodBooster programJMIR Res Protoc20121e18<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.researchprotocols.org/2012/2/e18/"/>10.2196/resprot.23292361227423612274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref62"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>62BendelinNHesserHDahlJCarlbringPNelsonKZAnderssonGExperiences of guided Internet-based cognitive-behavioural treatment for depression: a qualitative studyBMC Psychiatry201111107<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/11/107"/>10.1186/1471-244X-11-1072171852321718523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref63"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>63IloabachieCWellsCGoodwinBBaldwinMVanderplough-BoothKGladstoneTMurrayMFogelJVan VoorheesBWAdolescent and parent experiences with a primary care/Internet-based depression prevention intervention (CATCH-IT)Gen Hosp Psychiatry20113354355510.1016/j.genhosppsych.2011.08.0042195844721958447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref64"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>64TreanorAAbrarAHarrisKMorrisECarsonJUsing digital technologies in community mental healthSocial Work and Social Sciences Review2012149510710.1921/095352211X623236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref65"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>65BaeJWolpinSKimELeeSYoonSAnKDevelopment of a user-centered health information service system for depressive symptom managementNurs Health Sci20091118519310.1111/j.1442-2018.2009.00454.x1951970719519707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref66"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>66SobowaleKZhouANVan VoorheesBWStewartSTsangAIpPFabrizioCWongKLChimDAdaptation of an internet-based depression prevention intervention for Chinese adolescents: from “CATCH-IT” to “grasp the opportunity”Int J Adolesc Med Health20132512713710.1515/ijamh-2013-00202361253123612531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref67"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>67JarvenpaaSLLangKRManaging the paradoxes of mobile technologyInformation Systems Management20052272310.1201/1078.10580530/45520.22.4.20050901/90026.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref68"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>68AnderssonGCuijpersPInternet-based and other computerized psychological treatments for adult depression: a meta-analysisCogn Behav Ther20093819620510.1080/165060709033189602018369520183695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref69"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>69WilliamsVPriceJHardingeMTarassenkoLFarmerAUsing a mobile health application to support self-management in COPD: a qualitative studyBr J Gen Pract201464e392e400<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bjgp.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=24982491"/>10.3399/bjgp14X6804732498249124982491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref70"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>70WatsonAPatienceLPisanoUHeaneyDOC-044 Introduction of an inflammatory bowel disease smart phone ‘app’: a qualitative studyGut201564Suppl 1A2310.1136/gutjnl-2015-309861.44 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref71"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>71WakelinKStreetAFAn online expressive writing group for people affected by cancer: a virtual third placeAustralian Social Work20156819821110.1080/0312407X.2014.991336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref72"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>72SchnallRBakkenSRojasMTraversJCarballo-DieguezAmHealth technology as a persuasive tool for treatment, care and management of persons living with HIVAIDS Behav2015Suppl 2818910.1007/s10461-014-0984-82557283025572830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref73"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>73EmmeCRydahl-HansenSOstergaardBSchouLSvarreJAPhanarethKHow virtual admission affects coping - telemedicine for patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseJ Clin Nurs2014231445145810.1111/jocn.124442437267624372676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref74"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>74HordernAGeorgiouAWhettonSPrgometMConsumer e-health: an overview of research evidence and implications for future policyHIM J2011406142171255621712556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref75"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="?"><plain>75BessellTLMcDonaldSSilagyCAAndersonJNHillerJESansomLNDo Internet interventions for consumers cause more harm than good? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>A systematic reviewHealth Expect2002528371190653911906539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref76"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>76MelvilleKMCaseyLMKavanaghDJDropout from Internet-based treatment for psychological disordersBr J Clin Psychol201049Pt 445547110.1348/014466509X4721381979980419799804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref77"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>77ChristensenHGriffithsKMFarrerLAdherence in internet interventions for anxiety and depressionJ Med Internet Res200911e13<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2009/2/e13/"/>10.2196/jmir.11941940346619403466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref78"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>78McDermottMSWhileAEMaximizing the healthcare environment: a systematic review exploring the potential of computer technology to promote self-management of chronic illness in healthcare settingsPatient Educ Couns201392132210.1016/j.pec.2013.02.0142356642723566427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref79"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>79MaceaDDGajosKDaglia CalilYAFregniFThe efficacy of Web-based cognitive behavioral interventions for chronic pain: a systematic review and meta-analysisJ Pain20101191792910.1016/j.jpain.2010.06.0052065069120650691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref80"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>80KaltenthalerESutcliffePParryGBeverleyCReesAFerriterMThe acceptability to patients of computerized cognitive behaviour therapy for depression: a systematic reviewPsychol Med2008381521153010.1017/S00332917070026071820596418205964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref81"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>81BarakAHenLBoniel-NissimMShapiraNA comprehensive review and a meta-analysis of the effectiveness of Internet-based psychotherapeutic interventionsJournal of Technology in Human Services20082610916010.1080/15228830802094429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref82"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>82SamoochaDBruinvelsDJElbersNAAnemaJRvan der BeekAJEffectiveness of web-based interventions on patient empowerment: a systematic review and meta-analysisJ Med Internet Res201012e23<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2010/2/e23/"/>10.2196/jmir.12862058100120581001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref83"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>83KuijpersWGroenWGAaronsonNKvan HartenWHA systematic review of web-based interventions for patient empowerment and physical activity in chronic diseases: relevance for cancer survivorsJ Med Internet Res201315e37<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmir.org/2013/2/e37/"/>10.2196/jmir.22812342568523425685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref84"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>84HoganNMKerinMJSmart phone apps: smart patients, steer clearPatient Educ Couns20128936036110.1016/j.pec.2012.07.0162289798322897983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref85"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>85BarnesCHarveyRWildeAHadzi-PavlovicDWilhelmKMitchellPBReview of the quality of information on bipolar disorder on the InternetAust NZ J Psychiatry20094393494510.1080/00048670903179137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref86"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>86MooreDAyersSA review of postnatal mental health websites: help for healthcare professionals and patientsArch Womens Ment Health20111444345210.1007/s00737-011-0245-z2210982722109827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref87"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>87PandeyAHasanSDubeyDSarangiSSmartphone apps as a source of cancer information: changing trends in health information-seeking behaviorJ Cancer Educ20132813814210.1007/s13187-012-0446-92327523923275239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref88"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>88SteinfieldCEllisonNBLampeCSocial capital, self-esteem, and use of online social network sites: a longitudinal analysisJournal of Applied Developmental Psychology2008112943444510.1016/j.appdev.2008.07.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref89"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>89CohenSSocial relationships and healthAm Psychol20045967668410.1037/0003-066X.59.8.6761555482115554821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref90"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>90SulerJThe online disinhibition effectCyberpsychol Behav2004732132610.1089/10949310412912951525783215257832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref91"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>91Quan-HaaseAYoungALUses and gratifications of social media: a comparison of Facebook and instant messagingBulletin of Science, Technology &amp; Society20103035036110.1177/0270467610380009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref92"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>92EllisonNSteinfieldCLampeCThe benefits of Facebook “friends:” social capital and college students' use of online social network sitesJournal of Computer Mediated Communication2007121143116810.1111/j.1083-6101.2007.00367.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref93"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>93LampeCEllisonNSteinfieldCA face(book) in the crowd: social searching vs. social browsing2006Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative WorkNovember 4-8, 2006Banff, Alberta, CanandaAssociation for Computing Machinery16017010.1145/1180875.1180901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref94"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>94SkinnerACounseling and the InternetAmerican Behavioral Scientist20044843444610.1177/0002764204270280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
