<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cartilage</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cartilage</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CAR</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cartilage</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1947-6035</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1947-6043</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4749753</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1947603515607963</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1947603515607963</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Evaluating Joint Morbidity after Chondral Harvest for Autologous Chondrocyte Implantation (ACI) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><subtitle>A Study of ACI-Treated Ankles and Hips with a Knee Chondral Harvest</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>Helen S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1947603515607963">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1947603515607963">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1947603515607963"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>James B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1947603515607963">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1947603515607963">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>Jane C. E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1947603515607963">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1947603515607963">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Sally</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1947603515607963">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1947603515607963">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1947603515607963"><label>1</label>Centre for Spinal Studies, Robert Jones and Agnes Orthopaedic Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, Oswestry, Shropshire, UK</aff><aff id="aff2-1947603515607963"><label>2</label>ISTM, Keele University, Keele, Staffordshire, UK</aff><aff id="aff3-1947603515607963"><label>3</label>Institute of Orthopaedics, Robert Jones and Agnes Hunt Orthopaedic Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, Oswestry, Shropshire, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1947603515607963">Helen S. McCarthy, Centre for Spinal Studies, Robert Jones and Agnes Orthopaedic Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, ARC/TORCH Building, Gobowen, Oswestry, Shropshire, SY10 7AG, UK. Email: <email>helen.mccarthy@rjah.nhs.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2015</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits any use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="section1-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>To establish if harvesting cartilage to source chondrocytes for autologous chondrocyte implantation (ACI) results in donor site morbidity. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="section2-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Twenty-three patients underwent ACI for chondral defects of either the ankle or the hip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This involved cartilage harvest from the knee (stage I), chondrocyte expansion in the laboratory and implantation surgery (stage II) into the affected joint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Prior to chondral harvest, no patient had sought treatment for their knee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Lysholm knee scores were completed prior to chondral harvest and annually post-ACI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Histological analyses of the donor site were performed at 12.3 ± 1.5 months for 3 additional patients who had previously had ACI of the knee. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="section3-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The median preoperative Lysholm score was 100, with no significant differences observed at either 13.7±1.7 months or 4.8±1.8 years postharvest (median Lysholm scores 91.7 and 87.5, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Patients whose cartilage was harvested from the central or medial trochlea had a significantly higher median Lysholm score at latest follow-up (97.9 and 93.4, respectively), compared with those taken from the intercondylar notch (median Lysholm score 66.7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The mean International Cartilage Repair Society (ICRS) II histological score for the biopsies taken from the donor site of 3 additional knee ACI patients was 117 ± 10 (maximum score 140). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="section4-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This study suggests that the chondral harvest site in ACI is not associated with significant joint morbidity, at least up to 5 years postharvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, one should carefully consider the location for chondral harvest as this has been shown to affect knee function in the longer term. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>autologous chondrocyte implantation</kwd><kwd>cartilage repair</kwd><kwd>donor-site morbidity</kwd><kwd>osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>histology</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="section5-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Chondral and osteochondral lesions in the hyaline cartilage of an articulating joint often require surgical intervention due to the limited ability of cartilage self-repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Many techniques to restore articular cartilage and joint function have been established over the years, including mosaicplasty, osteochondral autograft transport system (OATS) and autologous chondrocyte implantation (ACI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Mosaicplasty and OATS involve obtaining cylindrical osteochondral grafts of varying sizes from the lesser loaded areas of the articular surface of the donor joint and implanting them into the recipient osteochondral lesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Traditionally, mosaicplasty requires multiple small osteochondral grafts (typically 3-8 mm),1-3 whereas OATS usually requires one single large defect-sized graft (typically ~10 mm)4 and either procedure can be performed in a single operation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>ACI on the other hand is a 2-stage procedure, requiring a chondral harvest of macroscopically healthy cartilage, also from a lesser loaded area of the joint (stage I) and subsequent chondrocyte isolation, culture, and proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The resulting cells are then implanted into the defect (stage II) approximately 3 to 4 weeks later,5 beneath either a periosteal or collagen membrane such as ChondroGide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Originally developed to treat chondral lesions in the knee,5 ACI has since been adapted for the treatment of chondral defects in other joints such as the ankle6-9 and less commonly, the hip.10-13 While encouraging results in terms of cartilage growth and improvement of joint function in the treated joint have been reported, little has been published on the potential morbidity caused by harvesting healthy tissue from the joint in ACI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>What has been described regarding donor site morbidity in the literature to date predominantly relates to osteochondral harvest for mosaicplasty3 or OATS,4,14 which has obvious differences in potential issues for donor site morbidity than solely a chondral harvest due to the depth and size of the harvest taken. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Donor site morbidity is an understandable concern as the integrity of the healthy, intact hyaline cartilage is violated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In this study, we aimed to assess the effect of chondral harvest on knee function by looking at a small population of patients who had ACI treatment of either the ankle or the hip but with a chondral harvest obtained from the knee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>This group of patients therefore provide a unique opportunity to assess the effect of controlled chondral injury on knee function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We have also analyzed the repair tissue formed at the donor site from 3 additional patients who previously underwent ACI for the knee. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="section6-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Method and Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="section7-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Ankle and Hip ACI patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="section8-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Patients and Surgical Technique </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Between 1998 and 2009, 23 patients (16 males, 7 females; mean age 38.4 ± 10.1 years, range 17.2-61.3 years) underwent ACI treatment for chondral defects of the ankle (n = 19) and hip (n = 4), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The average defect size treated was 2.1 ± 1.6 cm2 (range, 0.5-7.8 cm2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>ACI surgery involved chondrocyte harvest at the knee (stage I) from the ispilateral side in 21 patients and the contralateral side for 1 ankle and 1 hip patient, followed by chondrocyte implantation surgery (stage II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Chondral harvest was performed arthroscopically through standard anterolateral and anteromedial portals under tourniquet control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Specimens of cartilage (mean weight 271.9 ± 97.6 mg, range 103-520 mg) were taken using a 5-mm gouge from a region of the knee with low weightbearing status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The biopsy site locations were recorded and the biopsy material was transported to our on-site Good Manufacturing Practice (GMP) standard “Oscell” cell manufacturing facility for chondrocyte culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Ten samples were taken from the central trochlea (mean age 36.0 ± 14.0 years, range 17.2-61.3 years), 2 from the lateral trochlea (mean age 44.6 ± 1.6 years, range 43.5-45.8 years), 6 from the medial trochlea (mean age 40.7 ± 5.6 years, range 31.9-47.2 years), and 5 from the intercondylar notch (mean age 38.0 ± 6.1 years, range 28.3-44.3 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>A mean yield of 5.2 × 105 ± 1.3 × 105 (range 3 × 105 to 8 × 105) chondrocytes were obtained from the harvest biopsy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Following cell culture, a mean of 4.9 × 106 ± 1.9 × 106 chondrocytes (range 1.3 × 106 to 8 × 106) were implanted into the treatment site approximately 3 weeks later under either a periosteal (n = 20) or ChondroGide (n = 3) patch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>One ankle patient required a follow-up knee arthroscopy 1.4 years postharvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Patients in this study have been investigated as part of an ethically approved project (REACT 09/H1203/90, granted by West Midlands National Research Ethics Service). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Prior to chondral harvest, no patient had sought treatment for their knee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Modified Lysholm scores, a measure of knee function,15 were completed preoperatively and at yearly intervals post–cell implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Lysholm scores were categorized as excellent (95-100), good (84-94), fair (65-83), or poor (≤64).16 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="section9-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>A post hoc power analysis demonstrated a power of 0.8, at a significance level of 5% (P = 0.05) to identify a Lysholm score difference of 13 points,19 indicating that this study would require a paired sample of at least 10 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Data were tested for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk normality test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Nonparametric paired data (Lysholm scores) were analyzed for statistical differences with the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Nonparametric unpaired data were analyzed for statistical differences using the Mann-Whitney U test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Correlations were tested for using a Spearman’s rank correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Statistical differences between grouped frequency data of the Lysholm score parameters were tested for using a chi-square test of independence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A P value of &lt;0.05 was deemed significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using the software program Analyse-it Software Ltd, Leeds, UK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="section10-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Additional Donor Site Study from 3 Knee ACI Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="section11-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Histology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Three additional patients, who had received ACI treatment for chondral defects in their knees, underwent a follow-up arthroscopy at 12.3 ± 1.5 months, with full informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The donor site was examined and core biopsies of the repair tissue formed were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>These were snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen–cooled hexane prior to sectioning and 7-µm thick cryosections were collected onto poly-l-lysine–coated slides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Sections were stained with either hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) or toluidine blue (TB) and viewed with bright light microscopy to assess the general morphology and proteoglycan content of the repair tissue, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Sections were also viewed under polarised light to determine collagen fibril orientation to distinguish between hyaline cartilage and fibrocartilage morphologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Sections were scored using both the International Cartilage Repair Society (ICRS) II17 (maximum score 140) and the OsScore18 (maximum score 10) scoring systems, where a higher score for either systems represents a better quality of repair tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="section12-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In addition, immunohistochemistry for collagen types I and II was undertaken; for this cryosections were incubated with hyaluronidase prior to fixing in 4% formaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against collagen type I (1:500, clone I-8H5, MP Biomedicals, Cambridge, UK) or type II (1:10, clone CIIC1, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, IA, USA) were incubated for 60 minutes prior to the secondary goat anti-mouse biotinylated antibody for 60 minuntes (Vectastain Elite ABC kit, Vector Laboratories, Peterborough, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Adjacent sections were stained with an isotype-matched murine IgG1 (Dako, Cambridge, UK) as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Nonspecific binding and endogenous peroxidase activity were blocked using normal goat serum in 3% bovine serum albumin and 0.3% hydrogen peroxide in methanol, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Sections were washed 3 times with phosphate buffered saline between steps and all steps were performed at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Labelling was enhanced with streptavidin-peroxidase (Vectastain Elite ABC kit, Vector Laboratories, Peterborough, UK) and visualized with diaminobenzadine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="section13-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="section14-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Ankle and Hip ACI patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>At a mean of 5.1 ± 8.5 days preoperatively (range 0-31 days), the median Lysholm score for all patients was 100 (interquartile range [IQR] 8.7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Median Lysholm scores at the first annual review (13.7 ± 1.7 months postharvest, range 12-18.3 months) and at 4.8 ± 1.8 years postharvest (range 1.2-7.8, termed “latest follow-up” from here on) were 91.7 (IQR 12.5) and 87.5 (IQR 22.2), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Neither the first annual review nor the latest follow-up scores resulted in significantly different scores to the preoperative scores (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The majority of patients were classified as having either an excellent or good Lysholm score at all 3 time points (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>At latest follow-up, the median Lysholm score of the opposite knee was 100 (IQR 5.3) and significantly higher than the harvest knee (P = 0.0046). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Women had a greater change in median score from the preoperative score compared with men at both the first annual follow-up (median change −4.2 and 0, respectively) and the latest follow-up (median change −16.7 and 0, respectively), but neither was significant, either between the time points or between the sexes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Box and whisker plots displaying (A) Lysholm scores for the following time points: preoperative, 13.7 ± 1.7 months postharvest (first annual review), and at 4.8 ± 1.8 years postharvest (latest follow-up) and (B) median difference in Lysholm scores at the first annual review and latest follow-up compared with preoperative scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Lysholm scores at the first annual review (median 91.7) and at latest follow-up (median 87.5) were not significantly different to preoperative scores and neither was the difference in Lysholm score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The box and the horizontal line represent the interquartile range (IQR) and the median, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Outliers are represented as a small triangle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-fig1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table1-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Classification of Lysholm Scores Preoperatively, at First Annual Review, and Latest Follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-table1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Excellent (95-100), % </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Good (84-94), % </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Fair (65-83), % </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Poor (≤64), % </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Preoperatively </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>First annual review </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Latest follow-up </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>At the first annual review, Lysholm scores had decreased from preoperative scores in 44% of patients, increased in 25%, and remained the same in 31% of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The median change in Lysholm score from preoperative to first annual review was 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>By the latest follow-up, Lysholm scores had decreased from preoperative scores in 56% of patients, increased in 13%, and remained the same in 31% of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The median change in Lysholm score from preoperative to latest follow-up was −4.2 (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>From the Lysholm score, a significantly increased occurrence of pain was reported by patients at the latest follow-up compared with preoperatively (P = 0.05, Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In addition, significantly more catching and locking sensations were reported by patients at both the first annual review and latest follow-up (P = 0.004 and P = 0.019, respectively, Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Only 3 patients reported swelling of their knee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>One patient reported a constantly swollen knee at the first annual review, but no swelling 6.3 years postharvest at latest follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Two patients reported swelling only on severe exertion at 7.8 and 6.1 years follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Histograms depicting the 7 different scoring parameters of the modified Lysholm score13 and the percentage of patients within each category preoperatively (dark gray bar), at the first annual review (light gray bar), and the latest follow-up (white bar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A significantly higher occurrence of pain was reported by patients at the latest follow-up compared with preoperatively (P = 0.05) and significantly more catching and locking sensations were reported at both the first annual review and latest follow-up (P = 0.004 and P = 0.019, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-fig2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The influence of the location of the chondral harvest was considered; there was no significant difference between the mean ages of each harvest location group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The preoperative Lysholm score for harvests obtained from the central trochlea was 97.6 and 100 for both the medial trochlea and the intercondylar notch (Fig. 3A), with no significant differences in scores between the different harvest locations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>At the first annual review, median Lysholm scores were lower, but not significantly, than preoperative scores for all regions; 87.5, 95.8, and 91.7 for the central trochlea, medial trochlea, and intercondylar notch, respectively (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>By the latest follow-up, Lysholm scores for the central trochlea had returned to preoperative levels (median 97.9, mean follow-up 5.5 ± 0.9 years, range 4-6.5 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Lysholm scores for the medial trochlea group at the latest follow-up were maintained at 93.4 with a mean follow-up of 4.9 ± 1.6 years (range 3.4-7.8 years), while for the intercondylar notch group, the median Lysholm score was 66.7 with a mean follow up of 2.9 ± 2.1 years (range 1.2-6.1 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>These were significantly lower than for both the central and medial trochlea groups (P = 0.01 and P = 0.02, respectively, Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The 2 patients who had a chondral harvest from the lateral trochlea, had preoperative Lysholm scores of 87.5 and 100, first annual review scores of 70.8 and 100, and latest follow-up scores of 79.2 and 75. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Box and whisker plots comparing Lysholm scores for different donor sites preoperatively (A), at first annual review (B), and at latest follow-up (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Lysholm scores were not significantly different from each other preoperatively or at first annual review, but at the latest follow-up, the Lysholm score of patients who had chondral harvest from the intercondylar notch, had significantly lower scores than patients with harvests taken from the central trochlea (**P = 0.01) and the medial trochlea (*P = 0.02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Actual Lysholm scores for the lateral condyle at the 3 time points are represented as small crosses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The box and the horizontal line represent the interquartile range (IQR) and the median, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Outliers are represented as a small triangle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-fig3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>There was no significant relationship between the site of chondral harvest and the weight of harvest taken (P = 0.33) or the Lysholm score at either first annual review or latest follow-up (P = 0.996 and P = 0.148, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Patient’s age at ACI was also found not to correlate with either the preoperative or latest follow-up Lysholm scores (P = 0.59 and P = 0.12, respectively), nor were there any significant differences in either the first annual review or follow-up Lysholm scores between the sexes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>One patient in the series required a further knee arthroscopy 1.4 years postharvest after complaining of clicking and grinding behind the patella and reporting a Lysholm score of 68. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>At the stage I arthroscopy, this patient was noted by the surgeon to have a small grade III chondral defect on the trochlea; at this follow-up arthroscopy this defect was observed to be larger and was subsequently debrided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The chondral harvest site on the lateral trochlea was found to have healed with a good level of fill and with good integration with the surrounding native articular cartilage, but had a softer consistency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>There were also some fronds present here, which were debrided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Five years postarthroscopy, this patient now reports a Lysholm score of 91. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="section15-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Additional Donor Site Study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>All 3 donor sites of the patients who underwent a follow-up arthroscopy after ACI of the knee, were seen by the surgeon to be well healed with smooth, white cartilage that appeared to be well integrated into the surrounding native hyaline cartilage (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The core biopsies obtained were full depth (Fig. 5A) with generally good matrix metachromasia (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Under polarized light, 1 biopsy was observed to be hyaline cartilage and the other 2 biopsies were a mixture of both hyaline cartilage and fibrocartilage, the hyaline cartilage being at the base of the biopsy in both cases and well integrated into both the underlying subchondral bone and the upper fibrocartilaginous portion (Fig. 5C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>All 3 biopsies had moderately good surface architecture (Fig. 5E) and generally good cell morphology with most cells being rounded and of a chondrocytic appearance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The mean ICRS II and OsScore histological scores for the biopsies taken from the donor site were 116.8 ± 10 and 8.7 ± 0.8, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical staining for collagen type I was detected throughout the full depth of the biopsies (Fig. 5F), whereas collagen type II was predominantly restricted to the hyaline portions of the biopsies, but could also be detected to a lesser amount in the fibrocartilaginous portions adjacent to and above this (Fig. 5G). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Representative arthroscopic image of the donor site in a patient 11 months post–cell implantation for autologous chondrocyte implantation (ACI) of the knee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The white portion in the center of the image (black arrow) is the repaired cartilage in the center of the trochlea, observed to be smooth and well integrated into the surrounding cartilage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-fig4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5-1947603515607963" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Representative histological images of a full depth repair tissue biopsy from the donor site in a patient 11 months post–cell implantation for autologous chondrocyte implantation (ACI) of the knee, stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) (A) and toluidine blue (TB) (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Histological analysis of the repair cartilage demonstrated good matrix metachromasia (B) and good integration into the subchondral bone (C, higher powered image of dashed-line box region in A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Polarized light revealed a mixture of hyaline cartilage and fibrocartilage (D, polarized image of C, f = fibrocartilage, h = hyaline cartilage, b = bone) also well integrated with each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>All biopsies demonstrated a good surface (E, higher power image of the solid line box region in A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry of sections demonstrate the widespread presence of type I collagen (F) but more restricted type II collagen in the lower region (G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Scale bars represent 500 µm (A, B, F, G) and 250 µm (C-E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1947603515607963-fig5"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section16-1947603515607963"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Autologous chondrocyte implantation has been used since 19945 as treatment for cartilage defects with good long-term results.20,21 Little is known, however, of the effect of the chondral injury needed to source the chondrocytes for ACI on knee function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>There are many reports on the use of osteochondral grafting for locations such as the ankle, where the donor site has been the knee; a few of these studies make reference to donor-site morbidity,1-4,6,8,14,22-25 but often is not a focused outcome of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Chondral harvest from the knee for the treatment of the ankle is rarely performed nowadays as most chondral harvests are taken from the joint to be treated7,9,26 for various reasons, including restricting surgical trauma to a second joint and both anatomical and biomechanical differences between knee and ankle cartilage.27 A recent study has also demonstrated that chondrocytes extracted from the margins of both grade III and IV osteochondral lesions in the knee are comparable to those from non-weightbearing areas of the joint currently used for chondral harvest.28 Adopting this type of approach would eliminate any potential for donor-site morbidity, but there are no long-term clinical data on the outcome of the use of debrided edge cartilage as a source of autologous chondrocytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, our study is the first to look at the effects of chondral harvest alone on knee function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>We found that following a biopsy of approximately 270 mg of cartilage from the knee, the majority of patients maintained a good or excellent Lysholm score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Scores at 13.7 months postharvest were not significantly different to preoperative scores and were maintained at 4.8 years follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Although our study did not assess the area of chondral harvest, we did record the mass of the tissue harvested and we did not find a significant correlation between it and change in knee function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In addition, we found no correlation between either the patient’s age or sex and knee function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>It is also worth noting that whilst none of the patients in our study had previously sought treatment for their knees prior to harvest, the preoperative Lysholm scores were not all 100, with some as low as 62.5 (where scores less than 83 are considered “fair” and scores less than 64 are considered “poor”).16 Two patients who received ACI for chondral defects in the hip, reported low preoperative Lysholm scores, which could be attributed to referred pain from the hip,29 particularly as the Lysholm score increased dramatically at the first annual review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>This demonstrates how patient perception and clinical observation differ and do not always correlate; it also highlights the importance of comparing the difference in knee scores from pre- to postoperative rather than the postoperative score in isolation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Likewise, a reduced Lysholm score at the latest follow-up could possibly be due to either existing or newly developed degenerative changes within the joint and not actually related to the donor-site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>However, our results demonstrate that the median Lysholm score at latest follow-up for the opposite knee to which the harvest was taken was significantly greater than the harvest knee, despite both knees having a median Lysholm score of 100 preoperatively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This, we believe, is a reflection on the spread of the data and the limited number of patients in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Indeed, some studies have refrained from using the Lysholm score as a measure of knee function when analyzing the effect of an osteochondral harvest for ankle mosaicplasty, as they believe that the score may be biased by the painful and functionally reduced ipsilateral ankle joint and hence mask the true knee score.25 We respect that the Lysholm score is not, in everyone’s opinion, the best score to use and there are several other scores that are also validated which are frequently used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>However, the scores used in the present study are historical, some being collected up to 17 years ago when only Lysholm scores were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Despite this, the Lysholm score is recognised as a reliable measure for use in patients with chondral injuries.30 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The first ACI procedures reported harvesting cartilage from “a minor load-bearing area of the upper medial femoral condyle.”5 One would assume this was to limit potential donor-site morbidity, although this particular rationale was not mentioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A study using a biomechanical cadaveric model demonstrated the lowest contact pressures in the knee to be on the medial trochlea and thus recommended this location for future procedures requiring an osteochondral harvest to minimize donor site morbidity.31 Garretson et al.31 also suggest the “worse” place for an osteochondral harvest to be the central trochlea, due to having the highest contact pressures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in our study, we found patients who had a harvest obtained from either the central or the medial trochlea had significantly better Lysholm scores at latest follow-up than those where the harvest was taken from the intercondylar notch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Garretson et al.’s study did not include the intercondylar notch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, we were unable to statistically compare the effect of a chondral harvest from the lateral trochlea with the other locations included in this study due to lack of patients within this category, but, at the latest follow-up, both patients only had a “fair” Lysholm score indicating the lateral trochlea to be a less than optimal harvest location. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, the small number of patients involved in the study (n = 25) and even fewer numbers for individual locations (n = 2-10) is obviously a limiting factor in being able to make any statistically supported recommendations for an optimal location for chondral harvest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>It is difficult to make a direct comparison of donor site morbidity between osteochondral and chondral harvests due to the difference in the size of harvest, the types of tissue removed and the resulting defect created. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>One could speculate that perhaps an osteochondral harvest may in fact have an improved healing potential since they extend beyond the subchondral bone and thus encourage bleeding and entry of bone marrow stromal cells into the donor site, which may contribute to the repair process, much in the way that a standard microfracture procedure works. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>A chondral harvest, however, does not extend into the subchondral bone and so there is no such response stimulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, only 1 donor site is required for a chondral harvest for ACI, whereas procedures like mosaicplasty often result in multiple donor sites and have a greater overall donor area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Large areas of OATS harvests have previously been reported to correlate with a poorer Lysholm score at final follow-up.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Macroscopically, all 4 donor sites (1 from knee harvest for ankle ACI and 3 from knee ACI patients) observed by arthroscopy in our study were found to have healed with good integration into the surrounding cartilage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>One donor site in particular, which was noted to be of a softer consistency than the surrounding cartilage, could indicate the presence of a fibrocartilaginous-like tissue rather than a hyaline-like tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Microscopic examination of 3 repair tissue biopsies revealed 2 were a mixture of both hyaline cartilage and fibrocartilage while the other was solely hyaline cartilage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have reported that following an osteochondral harvest, the donor site fills with a fibrocartilaginous tissue.1 It is possible that the hyaline cartilage observed microscopically, or at least some of it, could be residual native hyaline cartilage due to the nature of the gouge instrument used to harvest the initial cartilage for stage I and the “U-shape” of the defect left behind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>However, there is evidence that the repair tissue formed at the treatment site following ACI matures with time32,33 and so maturation of the tissue formed in the donor site may also occur. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our study demonstrates that at a mean of 4.8 years after chondral harvest for ACI treatment, there was no significant change in median Lysholm knee scores compared to preoperative scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that there is no significant harvest site morbidity of the knee associated with harvesting cells for use in ACI, particularly when taken from the central or medial trochlea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Some patients, however, did report greater pain, catching and locking at their final follow-up, though whether this was due to donor site morbidity per se or injury or degeneration during the average 4.8-year postharvest follow-up time, is not possible to differentiate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>However, one should carefully consider the location for chondral harvest as this has been shown to affect knee function long term. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>It is recommended that patients should be made aware that they may experience some functional deficit, which is likely to be transient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>It is also vital that preoperative knee scores are measured, as patients who rate their knees as asymptomatic may have lower knee scores than the surgeon assumes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>While this study demonstrates no significant donor-site morbidity and good healing of the chondral harvest site both macroscopically and microscopically, more in-depth studies with a larger cohort of patients are required to fully assess the effect of harvest location on knee function and both the in vivo appearance and the histological quality of the repair tissue formed within the donor site to fully assess donor site morbidity and understand the processes involved in what appears to be spontaneous cartilage regeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Acknowledgments and Funding: We are grateful to the Arthritis Research UK for supporting this work (Grants 19429 and 18480) and to Mr Paul Harrison and the OsCell team (The John Charnley Laboratory, RJAH Orthopaedic Hospital, UK) for the expansion and preparation of harvested chondrocytes for the ACI procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>We also acknowledge Dr Jan-Herman Kuiper and Mr Tim Knight for their advice on statistics and Mr Robin Gilbert for his assistance in obtaining some clinical data. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Declaration of Conflicting Interests: The Author(s) declare(s) that there are no conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Ethical Approval: Ethical approval for this study was obtained from the West Midlands National Research Ethics Service (REACT 09/H1203/90). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>1 AhmadCSGuineyWBDrinkwaterCJ. Evaluation of donor site intrinsic healing response in autologous osteochondral grafting of the knee. Arthroscopy. 2002;18:95-8.11774149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr2-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>2 IwasakiNKatoHKamishimaTSuenagaNMinamiA. Donor site evaluation after autologous osteochondral mosaicplasty for cartilaginous lesions of the elbow joint. Am J Sports Med. 2007;35:2096-100.17724093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr3-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>3 HangodyLKishGModisLSzerbIGasparLDioszegiZ Mosaicplasty for the treatment of osteochondritis dissecans of the talus: two to seven year results in 36 patients. Foot Ankle Int. 2001;22:552-8.11503979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr4-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>4 Al ShaikhRAChouLBMannJADreebenSMPrieskornD. Autologous osteochondral grafting for talar cartilage defects. Foot Ankle Int. 2002;23:381-9.12043980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr5-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>5 BrittbergMLindahlANilssonAOhlssonCIsakssonOPetersonL. Treatment of deep cartilage defects in the knee with autologous chondrocyte transplantation. N Engl J Med. 1994;331:889-95.8078550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr6-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>6 WhittakerJPSmithGMakwanaNRobertsSHarrisonPELaingP Early results of autologous chondrocyte implantation in the talus. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2005;87:179-83.15736739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr7-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>7 GianniniSBudaRRuffilliACavalloMPagliazziGBulzaminiMC Arthroscopic autologous chondrocyte implantation in the ankle joint. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2014;22:1311-9.23996105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr8-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>8 NamEKFerkelRDApplegateGR. Autologous chondrocyte implantation of the ankle: a 2- to 5-year follow-up. Am J Sports Med. 2009;37:274-84.19104032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr9-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>9 KwakSKKernBSFerkelRDChanKWKasraeianSApplegateGR. Autologous chondrocyte implantation of the ankle: 2- to 10-year results. Am J Sports Med. 2014;42:2156-64.25056988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr10-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>10 AkimauPBhosaleAHarrisonPERobertsSMcCallIWRichardsonJB Autologous chondrocyte implantation with bone grafting for osteochondral defect due to posttraumatic osteonecrosis of the hip—a case report. Acta Orthop. 2006;77:333-6.16752299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr11-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>11 RobertsSMcCaskieARichardsonJBBhattacharjeeA. Cartilage repair in the hip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In: ShettyAAKimS-JNakamuraNBrittbergM, editors. Techniques in cartilage repair surgery. New York, NY: Springer; 2014 p. 259-66. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr12-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>12 WrightKTMennanCFoxHRichardsonJBBanerjeeRRobertsS. Characterization of the cells in repair tissue following autologous chondrocyte implantation in mankind: a novel report of two cases. Regen Med. 2013;8:699-709.24147526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr13-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>13 FontanaABistolfiACrovaMRossoFMassazzaG. Arthroscopic treatment of hip chondral defects: autologous chondrocyte transplantation versus simple debridement—a pilot study. Arthroscopy. 2012;28:322-9.22142720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr14-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>14 ReddySPedowitzDIParekhSGSennettBJOkerekeE. The morbidity associated with osteochondral harvest from asymptomatic knees for the treatment of osteochondral lesions of the talus. Am J Sports Med. 2007;35:80-5.16957009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr15-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>15 SmithHJRichardsonJBTennantA. Modification and validation of the Lysholm Knee Scale to assess articular cartilage damage. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2009;17:53-8.18556222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr16-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>16 TegnerYLysholmJ. Rating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuries. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1985;(198):43-9.4028566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr17-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>17 Mainil-VarletPVan DammeBNesicDKnutsenGKandelRRobertsS. A new histology scoring system for the assessment of the quality of human cartilage repair: ICRS II. Am J Sports Med. 2010;38:880-90.20203290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr18-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>18 RobertsSMcCallIWDarbyAJMenageJEvansHHarrisonPE Autologous chondrocyte implantation for cartilage repair: monitoring its success by magnetic resonance imaging and histology. Arthritis Res Ther. 2003;5:R60-73.12716454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr19-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>19 HeintjesEM. Non-traumatic knee complaints in adolescents and young adults in general practice. Erasmus University Rotterdam; 2006 Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://repub.eur.nl/pub/8555">http://repub.eur.nl/pub/8555</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr20-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>20 PetersonLVasiliadisHSBrittbergMLindahlA. Autologous chondrocyte implantation: a long-term follow-up. Am J Sports Med. 2010;38:1117-24.20181804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr21-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>21 BhosaleAMKuiperJHJohnsonWEHarrisonPERichardsonJB. Midterm to long-term longitudinal outcome of autologous chondrocyte implantation in the knee joint: a multilevel analysis. Am J Sports Med. 2009;37(Suppl 1):131S-138S.19861698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr22-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>22 MatricaliGADereymaekerGPLuytenFP. Donor site morbidity after articular cartilage repair procedures: a review. Acta Orthop Belg. 2010;76:669-74.21138224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr23-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>23 QuarchVMEnderleELotzJFroschKH. Fate of large donor site defects in osteochondral transfer procedures in the knee joint with and without TruFit plugs. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2014;134:657-66.24488360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr24-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>24 PaulJSagstetterAKrinerMImhoffABSpangJHinterwimmerS. Donor-site morbidity after osteochondral autologous transplantation for lesions of the talus. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009;91:1683-8.19571091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr25-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>25 ValderrabanoVLeumannARaschHEgelhofTHintermannBPagenstertG. Knee-to-ankle mosaicplasty for the treatment of osteochondral lesions of the ankle joint. Am J Sports Med. 2009;37(Suppl 1):105S-111S.19841140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr26-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>26 GianniniSBudaRGrigoloBVanniniFDe FranceschiLFacchiniA. The detached osteochondral fragment as a source of cells for autologous chondrocyte implantation (ACI) in the ankle joint. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2005;13:601-7.15979012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr27-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>27 TreppoSKoeppHQuanECColeAAKuettnerKEGrodzinskyAJ. Comparison of biomechanical and biochemical properties of cartilage from human knee and ankle pairs. J Orthop Res. 2000;18:739-48.11117295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr28-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>28 BekkersJESarisDBTsuchidaAIvan RijenMHDhertWJCreemersLB. Chondrogenic potential of articular chondrocytes depends on their original location. Tissue Eng Part A. 2014;20:663-71.24059650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr29-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>29 KhanAMMcLoughlinEGiannakasKHutchinsonCAndrewJG. Hip osteoarthritis: where is the pain? Ann R Coll Surg Engl. 2004;86:119-21.15005931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr30-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>30 CollinsNJMisraDFelsonDTCrossleyKMRoosEM Measures of knee function: International Knee Documentation Committee (IKDC) Subjective Knee Evaluation Form, Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS), Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score Physical Function Short Form (KOOS-PS), Knee Outcome Survey Activities of Daily Living Scale (KOS-ADL), Lysholm Knee Scoring Scale, Oxford Knee Score (OKS), Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC), Activity Rating Scale (ARS), and Tegner Activity Score (TAS). Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2011;63(Suppl 11):S208-28.22588746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr31-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>31 GarretsonRB3rdKatolikLIVermaNBeckPRBachBRColeBJ. Contact pressure at osteochondral donor sites in the patellofemoral joint. Am J Sports Med. 2004;32:967-74.15150045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr32-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>32 RobertsSMenageJSandellLJEvansEHRichardsonJB. Immunohistochemical study of collagen types I and II and procollagen IIA in human cartilage repair tissue following autologous chondrocyte implantation. Knee. 2009;16:398-404.19269183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bibr33-1947603515607963"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>33 McCarthyHSRobertsS. A histological comparison of the repair tissue formed when using either Chondrogide® or periosteum during autologous chondrocyte implantation. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2013;21:2048-57.24161708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
