<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4649626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep16912</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep16912</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Sialylation of the prion protein glycans controls prion replication rate and glycoform ratio </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katorcha</surname><given-names>Elizaveta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Makarava</surname><given-names>Natallia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Savtchenko</surname><given-names>Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baskakov</surname><given-names>Ilia V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Center for Biomedical Engineering and Technology, University of Maryland School of Medicine</institution>, Baltimore, Maryland, 21201 <country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Anatomy and Neurobiology, University of Maryland School of Medicine</institution>, Baltimore, Maryland, <country>United States of America</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>Baskakov@umaryland.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>16912</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>08</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Prion or PrPSc is a proteinaceous infectious agent that consists of a misfolded and aggregated form of a sialoglycoprotein called prion protein or PrPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>PrPC has two sialylated N-linked carbohydrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In PrPSc, the glycans are directed outward, with the terminal sialic acid residues creating a negative charge on the surface of prion particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The current study proposes a new hypothesis that electrostatic repulsion between sialic residues creates structural constraints that control prion replication and PrPSc glycoform ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In support of this hypothesis, here we show that diglycosylated PrPC molecules that have more sialic groups per molecule than monoglycosylated PrPC were preferentially excluded from conversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>However, when partially desialylated PrPC was used as a substrate, recruitment of three glycoforms into PrPSc was found to be proportional to their respective populations in the substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In addition, hypersialylated molecules were also excluded from conversion in the strains with the strongest structural constraints, a strategy that helped reduce electrostatic repulsion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Moreover, as predicted by the hypothesis, partial desialylation of PrPC significantly increased the replication rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This study illustrates that sialylation of N-linked glycans creates a prion replication barrier that controls replication rate and glycoform ratios and has broad implications. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Prion diseases are a family of lethal, transmissible, neurodegenerative disorders that can be sporadic, inheritable or transmissible in origin12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A central event underlying the molecular mechanism of prion diseases involves conformational changes of the cellular form of the prion protein (PrPC) into the disease-associated transmissible form (PrPSc)1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Multiple alternative, conformationally distinct, self-replicating states referred to as prion strains that give rise to different prion disease phenotypes can be produced within the same host or PrPC amino acid sequence3456. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Among the parameters identified over the years that control prion transmission and replication are the amino acid sequence of PrPC and strain-specific structure of PrPSc7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>PrPC is subject to two types of posttranslational modifications, which include attachment of GPI anchor to the C-terminal residue Ser-231 and up to two N-linked carbohydrates to residues Asn-181 and Asn-197891011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Roles of N-linked glycans and the GPI-anchor in prion transmission, spread, and pathogenesis have been the subjects of a number of studies in the last decade1213141516. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The N-linked glycans are sialylated at the terminal positions, with each glycan being able to carry up to five sialic acid residues17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Despite the discovery of PrP sialylation more than 25 years ago, the potential role of sialylation in prion replication has not been explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Terminal sialylation of glycans significantly alters the physical properties of both states, PrPC and PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In the absence of posttranslational modifications, the theoretical pI of the full-length prion protein is 9.6 and the estimated charge at pH 7.5 is + 9.518. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, due to glycan sialylation, the actual pI of PrP molecules was found to be highly heterogeneous and spread from pH 9.6 to acidic pH1819. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In intact PrPSc, the glycans are believed to be directed outwards, with the terminal sialic acid residues located at the interface with the extracellular environment or solvent202122. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Because sialic acid residues create a dense negative charge on the PrPSc surface, glycan sialylation might play a major role in modulating interactions between PrPSc and PrPC and defining prion replication rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In previous study, we showed that sialylation level of PrPSc controls prion infectivity18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>We also noticed that changes in sialylation levels of PrPC influence PrPSc replication rate and the ratio of three glycoforms within newly formed PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These findings led to a new hypothesis that electrostatic repulsion between sialic acid residues creates a replication barrier that slows down prion replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Moreover, as diglycosylated glycoforms have more sialic acid residues per PrP molecule than mono- or unglycosylated glycoforms, this hypothesis also proposes that sialylation controls PrPSc glycoform ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In previous studies that examined prions formed in familial and sporadic prion diseases, the three glycoforms were found to be recruited into PrPSc in a selective fashion23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>PrPSc glycoform ratios are believed to be an intrinsic characteristic of prion strains or subtypes and, as such, have been used for strain typing2425. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, it still remains puzzling as to why the proportions of three glycoforms vary in a strain-specific manner, even within the same host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Here we propose that diglycosylated glycoforms are selectively excluded to reduce electrostatic repulsion between sialic acid residues within PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The current study tests the above hypothesis on the role of sialylation in controlling the prion replication barrier and glycoform ratios. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Sialylation status controls strain-specific glycoform ratio of PrPSc </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>For establishing a relationship between sialylation status and glycoform ratios, a panel of hamster (263K, HY, DY and SSLOW) and mouse (ME7, 22L and RML) strains were employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To produce PrPSc with reduced sialylation levels, normal brain homogenate (NBH) was treated with sialidase from Arthrobacter ureafaciens, which has broad substrate specificity and cleaves α2–3 and α2–6 linked sialic acid residues on N-linked glycans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Sialidase treated NBH was used as a substrate for PMCAb (a PMCAb format that utilizes desialylated substrate will be referred to as dsPMCAb) as previously described18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Western blots were used to compare the glycoform ratios in PrPSc and dsPMCAb products (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>All mouse and hamster strains tested showed significant increase in diglycosylated glycoforms at the expense of mono- and unglycosylated glycoforms in dsPMCAb products in comparison to corresponding brain-derived materials (Fig. 1A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All three mouse strains (ME7, 22L, RML) showed considerable amounts of mono- and unglycosylated glycoforms in dsPMCAb products relative to that of dsPMCAb-derived material of hamster strains (263K, HY, DY, SSLOW). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This higher proportion of mono- and non-glycosylated forms is a distinct trait of mouse strains, as all brain-derived mouse materials also showed higher proportions of mono- and unglycosylated forms relative to those of hamster strains26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, a considerable shift in glycoform ratios in favor of diglycosylated forms was observed in all mouse and hamster strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The differences in sialylation status between brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials were analyzed using 2D gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The two N-linked glycans can carry up to five terminal sialic acid residues each adding negative charges to individual PrP molecules17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Because the samples were denatured prior to 2D gel electrophoresis, the distribution of charge isoforms in the horizontal dimension reflects sialylation status of individual PrP molecules, where hypersialylated molecules run toward acidic pH and hyposialylated toward basic pH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Consistent with previous studies2728, unglycosylated forms that lack glycans and glycan-linked sialylation typically showed more than one charge isoforms (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This charge heterogeneity is attributed to the structural heterogeneity of the GPI anchors, a fraction of which could be also subject to single sialylation8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Unglycosylated forms could serve as a reference for charge heterogeneity resolved by 2D not attributable to sialylation of N-linked glycans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>For all strains tested, the distribution of dsPMCAb-derived products was shifted towards basic pH relative to that of brain-derived materials as expected (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Such shifts document changes in sialylation status of dsPMCAb-derived materials that were produced from a partially desialylated substrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>To analyze individual sialylation profiles, charged isoforms were separated arbitrarily into two categories, as described in Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Isoforms located toward acidic pH from pI 7.5 will be designated as hypersialylated and those toward basic pH will be designated as hyposialylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The percentage of sum intensities of hypersialylated isoforms relative to the total intensities of all isoforms was used to compare the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To establish a correlation between sialylation status and glycoform ratio, the percentage of PrPSc diglycosylated forms was plotted as a function of the percentage of hypersialylated isoforms for brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>This plot revealed a relationship between sialylation status and glycoform ratio: a decrease in sialylation levels of dsPMCA-derived products always resulted in considerable increase in recruitment of diglycosylated forms into PrPSc at the expense of mono- and unglycosylated glycoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>This correlation was observed for all strains tested from two different hosts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In summary, the changes in glycoform ratios in response to changes in sialylation status support the hypothesis that negative charges of sialic acid residues create electrostatic repulsion that limits recruitments of diglycosylated glycoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Partial desialylation of PrPC abolishes electrostatic repulsion, and as a result, the proportion of diglycosylated glycoforms rises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The following testable predictions were postulated based on the above hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>First, it is predicted that negative selection of diglycosylated forms upon conversion of PrPC into PrPSc takes place, i.e the proportion of diglycosylated glycoforms in PrPSc should be lower than that in PrPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The extent of negative selection should depend on a strain-specific structure and degree of electrostatic repulsion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>For strain structures with close proximity of glycan moieties, the negative selection should be the strongest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Second, to counteract electrostatic repulsion, it is predicted that negative selection of hypersialylated diglycosylated isoforms takes place in addition to negative selection of diglycosylated forms in general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This negative selection should be the strongest for those strains that show the strongest negative selection of diglycosylated glycoforms, i.e. for strains with the highest proportion of monoglycosylated forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Third, if glycan sialylation indeed creates a barrier for prion conversion, desialylation of PrPC is predicted to remove this barrier and lead to an increase in prion amplification rates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Negative selection of diglycosylated forms upon conversion of PrPC into PrPSc </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>To test whether diglycosylated forms are underrepresented in PrPSc in comparison to that of PrPC, glycoform profiles of three mouse strains were compared to that of mouse PrPC (Fig. 1A,C–E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Consistent with previous studies26, in PrPC the diglycosylated forms were found to be predominant, while unglycosylated were the least represented (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In PrPSc of all three strains, the proportion of di- versus mono- and unglycosylated forms shifted in favor of mono- and unglycosylated glycoforms (Fig. 1A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>This result argues that the diglycosylated form is subject to negative selection upon conversion of PrPC into PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The shift was most substantial for the RML strain, illustrating that the extent of a negative selection is determined by a strain-specific structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, upon desialylation of the substrate, the dsPMCA-derived products showed a glycoform profile reminiscent of that of normal substrate, where diglycosylated forms were predominant (Fig. 1C,E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in dsPMCA-derived products all three strains exhibited a very similar glycoform profile (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that reducing the content of sialic acid residues on PrPC glycans result in recruitment of the three glycoforms into PrPSc proportionally to their relative populations in a substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>A similar trend was found in hamster strains, although it was less pronounced (Fig. 1B), because diglycosylated forms were predominant in brain-derived PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Together, these results illustrate that diglycosylated glycoforms are underrepresented in PrPSc, the extent of this effect is strain- and species-specific, and that PrPSc structures of hamster strains accommodate diglycosylated glycoforms better than those of mouse strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Negative selection of hypersialylated diglycosylated isoforms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Among three glycoforms, diglycosylated PrP exhibit the highest charge heterogeneity, as it can accommodate up to ten negatively charged sialic acid residues on two glycans per molecule17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>As a result, the charge distribution of diglycosylated isoforms is shifted toward acidic pH and typically extends beyond that of monoglycosylated isoforms, which accommodate only up to five sialic residues per molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The extent to which diglycosylated isoforms migrate beyond monoglycosylated isoforms toward acidic pH reports on recruitment of hypersialylated diglycosylated isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Careful analysis of 2D results revealed that in brain-derived PrPSc hypersialylated diglycosylated molecules were recruited in a strain-specific manner (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Hamster strains showed the most substantial extension of diglycosylated isoforms toward acidic pH relative to the distribution of monoglycosylated isoforms (Figs 2B and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that hypersialylated diglycosylated molecules are well represented in PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>It is also consistent with the previous results showing that structures of hamster strains accommodate diglycosylated PrP relatively well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In contrast to hamster strains, in mouse strain RML the distribution of diglycosylated isoforms does not extend beyond that of monoglycosylated isoforms at acidic pH (Figs 2A and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>This indicates that a negative selection of hypersialylated diglycosylated molecules takes place in addition to a general negative selection of diglycosylated glycoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>For the other two mouse strains 22L and ME7, the diglycosylated isoforms extended beyond monoglycosylated isoforms at acidic pH, although not to such a degree as those of hamster strains (Figs 2A and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Overall, the strain-specific structures that tolerate less diglycosylated forms also tend to exclude hypersialylated diglycosylated forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In fact, plotting strain-specific percentage of diglycosylated isoforms versus percentage of hypersialylated isoforms revealed a correlation between the two parameters that fits well to a linear function with R-squared value of 0.89 (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Sialylation of PrPC glycans controls replication barrier </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>It is predicted that sialylation of PrPC glycans creates a replication barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>To test this hypothesis, we compared amplification rates of ME7, RML and 22L in normal versus desialylated substrates using PMCAb and dsPMCAb, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>For comparing amplification rates, sets of serial PMCAb or dsPMCAb reactions were conducted with dilution folds between serial rounds starting from 1:3 and higher (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The amplification rate is defined operationally as the highest dilution between serial rounds at which amplification is still capable of compensating the effect of dilution as described previously2930. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In desialylated substrate, the amplification rate increased from 5- to 100-fold for ME7 and from 10- to at least 500-fold for RML and 22 L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Notably, consistent with previous results, dsPMCAb-derived products showed a higher proportion of diglycosylated glycoforms relative to PMCAb-derived products in all three strains (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In the absence of posttranslational modifications, prion protein has a strong positive charge at physiological pH with the theoretical pI of 9.618. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Sialylation of glycans can add up to ten negatively charged residues and shifts the pI toward acidic pH, making the population of PrP molecules highly heterogeneous with respect to pI and the net charges at physiological pH1718. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In PrPSc particles, glycans are believed to be directed outward where the terminal sialic acid residues create a dense negative charge on the PrPSc surface202122. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The current study proposed that due to electrostatic repulsion, sialylation of glycans creates structural constraints for PrPSc replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Several testable predictions were postulated based on this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>First, to reduce electrostatic repulsion, it is expected that PrPC with a heavy sialylation level is partially excluded from the conversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This could be achieved via (i) selective recruitment of mono- and unglycosylated PrPC at the expense of diglycosylated PrPC and (ii) preferential exclusion of hypersialylated diglycosylated PrPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Depending on the strain-specific alignment of glycan moieties, the extent of this effect is expected to be strain-specific (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Second, an increase in the rate of prion amplification is expected when the constraints imposed by sialic acid residues are relieved by employing a substrate with low sialylation levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In other words, sialylation of PrPC glycans creates a replication barrier that can be reduced by reducing sialylation levels of a substrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In support of the above hypothesis, the current work showed that the relative population of diglycosylated forms was lower in PrPSc than those in PrPC, and that the negative selection of diglycosylated forms was strain-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>RML showed the strongest exclusion of diglycosylated forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The hamster strains (263K, HY, DY, SSLOW) had the weakest negative selection, while 22L and ME7 strains were in the middle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, in PrPSc generated from PrPC that was partially desialylated, the relative populations of glycofoms were found to be very similar to those of the substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This observation illustrates that the pressure for preferential selection of un- and monoglycosylated forms was released by cleaving sialic acid residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In addition to the negative selection of diglycosylated forms, strains with the strongest structural constraints also excluded hypersialylated molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>RML showed the strongest negative selection of diglycosylated and also hypersialylated forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In fact, a strong correlation between strain-specific percentage of diglycosylated forms and hypersialylated forms presented in Fig. 3 for brain-derived material suggests that the negative selection of both is attributed to the same structural constrains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The glycoform ratios within PrPSc are believed to be one of the intrinsic characteristics of prion strains or PrPSc subtypes (reviewed in31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In fact, the glycoform ratios have been used for strain typing and classification of CJD type2425. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>It was not clear why three glycoforms are recruited by prion strains in different proportions even within the same host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The current work demonstrates that the strain-specific ratio of the three glycoforms is a result of negative selection of heavily sialylated PrP molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The extent to which heavily sialylated PrP is excluded is presumably controlled by the strain-specific structure of PrPSc and relative position of the two glycans (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, when exposed to desialylated substrate, prion strains lose strain-specific selectivity toward different glycoforms and the glycoform ratio within PrPSc mirrors that of PrPC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Brain-derived PrPSc of different strains was found to be different with respect to its sialylation status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>(Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In combination with substantial strain-specific differences in glycoform ratios, these differences are likely to produce distinct strain-specific density of sialic acid residues on a surface of PrPSc particles and distinct strain-specific pIs of PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For instance, at physiological pH, RML PrPSc particles are expected to have net positive charges, whereas PrPSc particles of hamster strains are expected to be charged negatively (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Terminal sialic acid residues constitute key elements of diverse functional epitopes that are recognized by dozens of cell receptors including siglecs and selectins3233. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Through these functional epitopes, sialylation of glycoproteins mediate their interaction with cells of the innate immune system and microglia34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>These interactions define the ultimate fate of mammalian cells, glycoproteins in circulation and microbial pathogens3536. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>It remains to be established whether strain-specific differences in PrPSc sialylation play any role in defining strain-specific neurotropism and lymphotropism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The current study illustrates that PrPSc glycoform ratio is not only controlled by strain or host, but also by sialylation level of PrPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>As such, experiments on infecting new hosts or cell lines with unknown PrPC sialylation status should be interpreted with great care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, shifts in glycoform ratios toward diglycosylated glycoforms were observed in scrapie-infected cells treated with swainsonine, a compound that inhibits complex glycosylation3738. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It was concluded that selection of minor strain variants or structural mutants occurred3738. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Because treatment with swainsonine blocks complex glycosylation including sialylation, it is expected that the glycoform ratios would change in favor of diglycosylated forms regardless whether selection of a new variants occurs or not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The current work predicts that if the PrPSc glycoform ratio changes upon infecting a new host, this change is indicative of an altered sialylation status of PrPC and, specifically, a shift toward diglycosylated forms would suggest a reduced sialylation level of PrPC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The hypothesis presented in the current work introduces new constraints for establishing PrPSc structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>To account for the negative selection of diglycosylated/hypersialylated PrPC, glycans of the neighboring PrP molecules should be aligned in close proximity to each other within assembled PrPSc particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The average volume and dimension of glycan moieties should be taken into consideration for estimating the proper folding pattern and the number of intramolecular rings or layers acquired by a single polypeptide chain within intact PrPSc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>More substantial clashes between glycans of neighboring diglycosylated forms are expected for strains or PrPSc subtypes with predominantly monoglycosylated forms, such as sporadic CJD, in comparison with the strains where diglycosylated forms are predominant, such as new variant CJD24 (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>For the three mouse strains tested in the current study, partial desialylation of PrPC increased the replication rates by 20–50 fold (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that sialylation of PrP glycans contributes to a replication barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>An alternative explanation is that sialidase treatment of NBH had an effect other than on PrPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>While this seems to be unlikely, this possibility should not be discarded completely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, partial desialylation of PrPC was also found to considerably reduce the barrier in cross-seeded PMCAb reactions18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Together, these data suggest that the replication barrier attributable to glycan sialylation is universal, i.e. it might not only control the rate of prion replication within the same host but also the barrier associated with prion transmission between different species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>There might be several components that underlie a replication barrier attributable to sialylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>First, electrostatic repulsion between negatively charged sialic acid residues on glycans of PrPSc and PrPC limits the range of PrPC molecules suitable for conversion to those with moderate sialylation levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Second, even for the PrPC molecules that are suitable for conversion, electrostatic repulsion of surface glycans might slow down the rates of PrPC binding to PrPSc and PrPC conversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Third, electrostatic repulsion between surface glycans of nascent PrPSc has a negative impact on thermodynamic stability of PrPSc particles, the effect that has to be counteracted by other forces that stabilize packing of polypeptide chains within PrPSc particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Notably, while thermodynamic stability of PrPSc varies depending on strain-specific structure6293940, the range of strain-specific thermodynamic stabilities of PrPSc is typically lower than those of amyloid fibrils generated in vitro using recombinant PrP4142. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In part, this could be due to electrostatic repulsion between sialylated glycans that recombinant PrP lacks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>According to the hypothesis introduced here, the same structural constraints account for at least part of the replication barrier and the degree to which diglycosylated forms are excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>If this is true, there should be a correlation between strain-specific glycoform ratios and the efficiency of prion replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Indeed, mouse strains have a high proportion of monoglycosylated glycoforms and also slow replication rates in PMCA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Similar correlations between glycoform ratio and the replication efficiency was observed for two forms of CJD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>It is known that nvCJD, which is predominantly diglycosylated, replicates in PMCA with a much better efficiency than sCJD, which is predominantly monoglycosylated434445. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, not all strains with predominantly diglycosylated glycoforms display fast replication rates suggesting that factors other than sialylation contribute to the replication barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>For instance, hamster-adapted strains DY, 139H and 22AH are predominantly diglycosylated, but replicate very slowly39. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Normal and scrapie brain materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Weanling Golden Syrian hamsters or C57BL/6NHsd mice were inoculated intracerebrally under 2% O2/4 MAC isoflurane anesthesia using scrapie brain homogenates of hamster- or mouse-adapted strains, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For the synthetic strain SSLOW, animals of fourth serial SSLOW passage were used for analysis46. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Animals were euthanized at the terminal stage of the disease and brains were collected for subsequent analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>This study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The animal protocol was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the University of Maryland, Baltimore (Assurance Number A32000-01; Permit Number: 0215002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Protein misfolding cyclic amplification with beads (PMCAb) and PMCAb in desialylated substrate (dsPMCAb) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>10% normal brain homogenate (NBH) from healthy hamsters or mice was prepared as described previously47. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>To produce desialylated substrates for dsPMCAb, 10% NBH was treated with Arthrobacter ureafaciens sialidase (cat # P0722L, New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA) as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>After preclearance of NBH at 500 × g for 2 min and addition of the enzyme buffer supplied with the manufacturer to supernatant 200 units/mL of sialidase were added to the supernatant, incubated on a rotator at 37 °C for 5 h and the resulting material referred to as dsNBH substrate used in dsPMCAb. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>PMCAb and dsPMCAb reactions were conducted as previously described1848 using Misonix S-4000 microplate horn (Qsonica LLC, Newtown, CT) in the presence of two 2/32” Teflon beads in each tube (McMaster-Carr, Elmhurst, IL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>One round consisted of 20 sec sonications delivered at 170 W energy output applied every 20 min during a 24 hour period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>For each subsequent round, 10 μl (for hamster strains) or 20 μl (for mouse strains) of the reaction products from the previous round were mixed with 90 or 80 μl of fresh substrate, respectively, or as specified for the amplification rate experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Western blots </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>10 μL of 10% brain homogenate or dsPMCAb-derived materials were supplemented with 5 μL 1% SDS and 5 μL proteinase K (cat. # P8107S, New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA), to a final concentration of 0.25% SDS and 25 μg/mL proteinase K, and incubated at 37 °C for 1 hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Then, SDS sample buffer was added, samples were boiled for 10 minutes and loaded onto NuPage 12% BisTris gel (cat. # NP0341BOX, Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA), transferred to PVDF membrane, and probed with 3F4 (cat. #SIG-39600, Covance) or Ab3531 antibody (Abcam). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Preparation of brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials for 2D </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>10% (wt/vol) of scrapie brain homogenates were prepared in PBS using glass/Teflon homogenizers attached to a cordless 12 V compact drill (Ryobi) as previously described46. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>For 2D electrophoresis of brain-derived materials, an aliquot of 10% (wt/vol) homogenate was diluted with nine volumes of 1% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 in PBS, sonicated for 30 s inside a Misonix S-4000 microplate horn (Qsonica LLC, Newtown, CT), and treated with 25 μg/mL proteinase K for 30 min at 37 °C. dsPMCAb materials were treated with 25 μg/mL PK in the presence of 0.25% SDS for 60 min at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Resulting brain and dsPMCAb samples were supplemented with 4xSDS loading buffer, heated for 10 min in a boiling water bath and processed for 2D electrophoresis as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>2D electrophoresis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Samples of 25 μL volume prepared in loading buffer as described above were solubilized for 1 h at room temperature in 200 μL solubilization buffer (8 M Urea, 2% (wt/vol) CHAPS, 5 mM TBP, 20 mM TrisHCl pH 8.0), then alkylated by adding 7 μL of 0.5 M iodoacetamide and incubated for 1 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Then, 1150 μL of ice-cold methanol was added and samples were incubated for 2 h at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 16,000 g at 4 °C, supernatant was discarded and the pellet was re-solubilized in 160 μL rehydration buffer (7 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 1% (wt/vol) DTT, 1% (wt/vol) CHAPS, 1% (wt/vol) Triton X-100, 1% (vol/vol) ampholyte, trace amount of Bromophenol Blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Fixed immobilized pre-cast IPG strips with a non-linear pH gradient 3–10 used in the previous study18 were replaced by fixed immobilized pre-cast IPG strips with a linear pH gradient 3–10 (cat. # ZM0018, Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) that provide a better resolution of charge isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Strips were rehydrated in 155 μL of the resulting mixture overnight at room temperature inside IPG Runner cassettes (cat. # ZM0003, Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Isoelectrofocusing (first dimension separation) was performed at room temperature with rising voltage (175V for 15 minutes, then 175–2,000V linear gradient for 45 minutes, then 2,000 V for 30 minutes) on Life Technologies Zoom Dual Power Supply, using the XCell SureLock Mini-Cell Electrophoresis System (cat. # EI0001, Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The IPG strips were then equilibrated for 15 minutes consecutively in (i) 6 M Urea, 20% (vol/vol) glycerol, 2% SDS, 375 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.8, 130 mM DTT and (ii) 6 M Urea, 20% (vol/vol) glycerol, 2% SDS, 375 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.8, 135 mM iodoacetamide, and loaded on 4–12% Bis-Tris ZOOM SDS-PAGE pre-cast gels (cat. # NP0330BOX, Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>For the second dimension, SDS-PAGE was performed for 1 h at 170 V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting was performed as described elsewhere, blots were stained using 3F4 or Ab3531 antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Western blot densitometry analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>1D or 2D western blot signal intensity was digitized for densitometry analysis using AlphaView software (ProteinSimple, San Jose, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>For densitometry analysis of the glycoform distribution (expressed as a percentage of the diglycosylated form), target bands were selected using a uniform rectangular sampling area that encompassed the band of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Background optical density of an equal area from the same blot was determined and subsequently subtracted from the density of the bands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>At least three measurements from independent gel loadings were used for each sample for calculating mean and standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>For analysis of sialylation, 2D blots were aligned horizontally and a line drawn at pI 7.5 was used to arbitrarily separate charge isoforms into hypersialylated and hyposialylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In the software window, a rectangle was drawn to confine the spots of interest, and the densities measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The intensity of an equal background area from the same blot was subtracted before calculations were done. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The acquired spot ensemble intensities were used to calculate percentage of “hypersialylated” isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Hypersialylated isoforms were defined operationally as all isoforms located to the left of the pI7.5 line; the percentage of hypersialylated isoforms was calculated assuming the total intensity of all isoforms as 100%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>For generating glycoform profiles or sialylation profiles for di- and monoglycosylated glycoforms, densitometry analysis of 1D or 2D blots, respectively, was performed using the “Lane profile” function in the AlphaView program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>For data presented in normalized format (Fig. 4), the highest curve signal value was taken as 100%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Additional Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Katorcha, E. et al. Sialylation of the prion protein glycans controls prion replication rate and glycoform ratio. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Rep. 5, 16912; doi: 10.1038/srep16912 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We thank Pamela Wright for editing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Financial support for this study was provided by National Institute of Health Grants R01 NS045585 and R01 NS074998. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>B. Novel proteinaceous infectious particles cause scrapie. Science 216, 136–144 (1982).6801762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>B. Prion diseases and the BSE crisis. Science 278, 245–251 (1997).9323196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>CaugheyB., RaymondG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; BessenR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>A. Strain-dependent differences in b-sheet conformations of abnormal prion protein. J.Biol.Chem. 273, 32230–32235 (1998).9822701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>ThomzigA., SpassovS., FriedrichM., NaumannD. &amp; BeekesM. Discriminating Scrapie and Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy Isolates by Infrared Spectroscopy of Pathological Prion Protein. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Chem. 279, 33854 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>SafarJ. et al. Eight prion strains have PrP Sc molecules with different conformations. Nat.Med. 4, 1157–1165 (1998).9771749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>PeretzD. et al. Strain-specified relative conformational stability of the scrapie prion protein. Protein Sci. 10, 854–863 (2001).11274476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>CohenF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>E. &amp; PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>B. Pathologic conformations of prion proteins. Annu Rev Biochem 67, 793–819 (1998).9759504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>StahlN. et al. Glycosylinositol phospholipid anchors of the scrapie and cellular prion proteins contain sialic acid. Biochemistry 31, 5043–5053 (1992).1350920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>TurkE., TeplowD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>B., HoodL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>E. &amp; PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>B. Purification and properties of the cellular and scrapie hamster prion proteins. Eur J Biochem 176, 21–30 (1988).3138115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>StahlN. et al. Structural studies of the scrapie prion protein using mass spectrometry and amino acid sequencing. Biochemistry 32, 1991–2002 (1993).8448158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>EndoT., GrothD., PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; KobataA. Diversity of oligosaccharide structures linked to asparagines of the scrapie prion protein. Biochemistry 28, 8380–8388 (1989).2574992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>ChesebroB. et al. Anchorless prion protein result in infectious amyloid disease without clinical scrapie. Science 308 1435–1439 (2005).15933194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>MahalS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>P. et al. Propagating of RML prions in mice expressing PrP devoid of GPI anchor leads to formation of a novel, stable prion strain. PLOS Pathog. 8, e1002746 (2012).22685404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>TuziN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>L. et al. Host PrP Glycosylation: A Major Factor Determining the Outcome of Prion Infection. PLOS Biology 6, e100 (2008).18416605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>CancellottiE. et al. Glycosylation of PrPC determines timing of neuroinvasion and targeting in the brain following transmissible spongiform encephalopathy infection by a peripheral route. J Virol 84, 3464–3475 (2010).20106922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>NeuendorfE. et al. Glycosylation Deficiency at Either One of the Two Glycan Attachment Sites of Cellular Prion Protein Preserves Susceptibility to Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy and Scrapie Infections. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Chem. 279 53306–53316 (2004).15448157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>RuddP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>M. et al. Glycosylation differences between the normal and pathogenic prion protein isoforms. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 96, 13044–13049 (1999).10557270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>KatorchaE., MakaravaN., SavtchenkoR., D’AzzoA. &amp; BaskakovI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>V. Sialylation of prion protein controls the rate of prion amplification, the cross-species barrier, the ratio of PrPSc glycoform and prion infectivity. PLOS Pathog. 10, e1004366 (2014).25211026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>DeArmondS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>J. et al. PrPC glycoform heterogeneity as a function of brain region: implications for selective targeting of neurons by prion strains. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 58, 1000–1009 (1999).10499442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>WilleH. et al. Structural studies of the scrapie prion protein by electron crystallography. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>USA 99, 3563–3568 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>GovaertsC., WilleH., PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; CohenF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>E. Evidance for assembly of prions with left-handed b-helices into trimers. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>USA 101, 8342–8347 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>RequenaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; WilleH. The Structure of the infectious prion protein: Experimental data and molecular models. Prion 8, 60–66 (2014).24583975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>XiaoX. et al. Glycoform-Selective Prion Formation in Sporadic and Familial Forms of Prion Disease. PLoS One 8, e58786 (2013).23527023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>CollingeJ., SidleK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>L., MeadsJ., IronsideJ. &amp; HillA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>F. Molecular analysis of prion strain variation and the aetiology of “new variant” CJD. Nature 383, 685–690 (1996).8878476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>SomervilleR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>A. Host and transmissible spongiform encephalopathy agent strain control glycosylation of PrP. J Gen Virol 80, 1865–1872 (1999).10423157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>NishinaK. et al. The Stoichiometry of Host PrPC Glycoforms Modulates the Efficiency of PrPSc formation in vitro. Biochemistry 45, 14129–14139 (2006).17115708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>ZouW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Q. et al. Identification of Novel Proteinase K-resistant C-terminal Fragments of PrP in Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease. J.Biol.Chem. 278, 40429–40436 (2003).12917418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>MonacoS. et al. Allelic origin of protease-sensitive and protease-resistant prion protein isoforms in Gerstmann-Sträussler-Scheinker disease with the P102L mutation. PLoS One 7, e32382 (2012).22384235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Gonzalez-MontalbanN., MakaravaN., SavtchenkoR. &amp; BaskakovI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>V. Relationship between Conformational Stability and Amplification Efficiency of Prions. Biochemistry 50, 7933–7940 (2011).21848309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Gonzalez-MontalbanN., LeeY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>J., MakaravaN., SavtchenkoR. &amp; BaskakovI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>V. Changes in prion replication environemnt cause prion strain mutation. Faseb J. 27, 3702–3710 (2013).23729586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>LawsonV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>A., CollinsS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>J., MastersC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; HillA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>F. Prion protein glycosylation. J Neurochem 93, 793–801 (2005).15857383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>KooykY. &amp; RabinovichG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>A. Protein-glycan interactions in the control of innate and adaptive immune responses. Nat Immunology 9, 593–601 (2008).18490910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>RabinovichG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; CrociD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>O. Regulatori Circuits Mediated by Lectin-Glycan Interaction in Autoimmunity and Cancer. Immunity 36, 322–335 (2012).22444630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>VarkiA. Uniquely human evolution of sialic acid genetics and biology. Proc Acad Natl Sci USA 107, 8939–8946 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>VarkiA. Sialic acids in human health and disease. Trends in Molecular Medicine 14, 351–360 (2008).18606570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>BrownG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; NeherJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>J. Microglial phagocytosis of live neurons. Nat Rev Neuroscience 15, 209–216 (2014).24646669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>LiJ., BrowningS., MahalS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>P., OelschlegelA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; WeissmannC. Darwinian evolution of prions in cell culture. Science 327, 869–872 (2010).20044542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>BrowningS. et al. Abrogation of Complex Glycosylation by Swainsonine Results in Strain- and Cell-specific Inhibition of Prion Replication J Biol Chem 286, 40962–40973 (2011).21930694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>AyersJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>L. et al. The strain-encoded relationship between PrP replication, stability and processing in neurons is predictive of the incubation period of disease. PLOS Pathog. 7, e1001317 (2011).21437239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>ColbyD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>W. et al. Design and construction of diverse mammalian prion strains. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>USA 106, 20417–20422 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SunY. et al. Site-specific conformational studies of PrP amyloid fibrils revealed two cooperative folding domain within amyloid structure. J.Biol.Chem. 282, 9090–9097 (2007).17244617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>SunY. et al. Conformational stability of PrP amyloid firbils controls their smallest possible fragment size. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Biol. 376, 1155–1167 (2008).18206163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>JonesM. et al. Human platelets as a substrate source for the in vitro amplification of the abnormal prion protein (PrP) associated with variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease. Transfusion 49, 1537–2995 (2009).19413736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>LacrouxC. et al. Preclinical detection of variant CJD and BSE prions in blood. PLOS Pathog. 10, e1004202 (2014).24945656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>ModaF. et al. Prions in the urine of patients with variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease. N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Engl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Med. 371, 530–539 (2014).25099577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>MakaravaN. et al. Stabilization of a prion strain of synthetic origin requires multiple serial passages. J Biol Chem 287, 30205–30214 (2012).22807452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>MakaravaN. et al. Genesis of mammalian prions: from non-infectious amyloid fibrils to a transmissible prion disease. PLoS Pathogen 7, e1002419 (2011).22144901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Gonzalez-MontalbanN. et al. Highly Efficient Protein Misfolding Cyclic Amplification. PLoS Pathogen 7, e1001277 (2011).21347353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions E.K. and I.V.B. conceived the experiments; E.K., N.M. and R.S. conducted the experiments; E.K. and I.V.B. analyzed the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>E.K. and I.V.B. wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Analysis of glycoform profiles of brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials.</title><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Western blots of scrapie brain-derived (SBH) and dsPMCAb-derived materials of mouse strains ME7, 22L and RML (A) or hamster strains 263K, HY, DY, SSLOW (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>For producing dsPMCA-derived material, dsPMCAb reactions were seeded with brain material and propagated in serial dsPMCA to the final dilution of brain material 108-fold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Mouse or hamster normal brain homogenates (MoNBH or HaNBH, respectively) are shown as references. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>All samples except MoNBH and HaNBH were treated with PK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Mouse and hamster materials were stained with Ab3531 or 3F4 antibodies, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Black triangles, white triangles and arrows mark di-, mono- and non-glycosylated glycoforms, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Glycoform profiles of mouse PrPC from three independent normal brain materials (C), scrapie brain-derived material (D) or dsPMCAb-derived material (E) for ME7 (solid lines), 22L (dotted lines) and RML (dashed lines). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Profiles were built and normalized as described in Materials and Methods using results of 1D Western blots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Analysis of sialylation status of scrapie brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials.</title><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>2D analysis of charge distribution of scrapie brain- and dsPMCAb-derived materials for mouse strains RML, 22L and ME7 (A) and hamster strains 263K, HY, DY and SSLOW (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>dsPMCAb-derived materials were produced as described in the legend to Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>The dash line shows position of pI 7.5 and arbitrary divides “hypersialylated” and “hyposialylated” PrP molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Appearance of more than one charge isoform for unglycosylated PrP is attributed to structural heterogeneity of the GPI anchor8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, due to sialylation of glycans, monoglycosylated PrPs can carry up to five negatively charged sialic acid residues, while diglycosylated PrPs – up to ten sialic acid residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>As a result, the distribution of charge isoform is shifted toward acidic pH for monoglycosylated PrPs and even more so for diglycosylated PrPs, relative to that of unglycosylated PrPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>All samples were treated with PK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Mouse and hamster materials were stained with Ab3531 or 3F4 antibodies, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Black triangles, white triangles and arrows mark di-, mono- and non-glycosylated glycoforms, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Correlation between PrP<sup>Sc</sup> sialylation status and glycoform ratio.</title><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Percentage of diglycosylated glycoforms plotted as a function of percentage of hypersialylated isoforms for brain-derived (circles) and dsPMCAb-derived materials (diamonds) for mouse (RML, 22L and ME7) and hamster (263K, HY, DY and SSLOW) strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Arrows show shifts in glycoform ratio after amplification in dsPMCAb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Percentage of diglycosylated glycoforms and hypersialylated isoforms are calculated as described in Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>For each strain, at least three glycoform ratio values were acquired from independent brain materials or dsPMCA reactions; the variations were used to calculate mean and standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>For RML, 22L and 263K brain materials at least three sialylation ratio values were available, permitting to calculate mean and standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Black solid line shows the result of linear fitting of the percent of diglycosylated as a function of the percent of hypersialylated for brain-derived PrPSc, R2 = 0.89. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Sialylation profiles of di- and mono-glycosylated glycoforms of brain-derived materials.</title><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Sialylation profile of di- (solid lines) or mono-glycosylated (dashed lines) glycofoms of brain-derived materials for 263K, 22L, ME7 and RML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Profiles were built as described in Materials and Methods using results of 2D Western blots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Analysis of amplification rates in PMCAb and dsPMCAb.</title><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Mouse scrapie brain materials were diluted 102-fold into 10% МоNBH or desialylated МоNBH and subjected to four serial PMCAb or dsPMCAb rounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>The material amplified in each round was diluted to a specified dilution fold for the next round as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Unamplified scrapie seeds diluted into NBH are shown as round 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Samples were treated with PK as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>All blots were stained with Аb3531 antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Schematic diagram illustrating how relative position of two glycans creates structural constraints.</title><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>(A) A strain with minor clashes between glycans that belong to neighboring PrP monomers can recruit diglycosylated monomers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>This strain is characterized by low electrostatic repulsion between sialylated glycans (schematically marked by lightning bolts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>(B) A strain with substantial spatial constraints between glycans from neighboring monomers limits percentage of diglycosylated molecules due to high electrostatic repulsion between sialic acids (red circles with negative charge) from neighboring N-glycans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep16912-f6"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
