<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Crit Care</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Critical Care</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1364-8535</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1466-609X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4464872</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26067660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-015-0961-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Burn wound healing and treatment: review and advancements </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>Matthew P.</given-names></name><address><email>p.rowan.vol@mail.mil</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cancio</surname><given-names>Leopoldo C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elster</surname><given-names>Eric A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>Lloyd F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Natesan</surname><given-names>Shanmugasundaram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Rodney K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christy</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Kevin K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>United States Army Institute for Surgical Research, 3698 Chambers Pass, Fort Sam Houston, TX 78234 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, 4301 Jones Bridge Rd, Bethesda, MD 20814 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Brooke Army Medical Center, 3551 Roger Brook Dr, Fort Sam Houston, TX 78234 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>243</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>© Rowan et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Burns are a prevalent and burdensome critical care problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The priorities of specialized facilities focus on stabilizing the patient, preventing infection, and optimizing functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Research on burns has generated sustained interest over the past few decades, and several important advancements have resulted in more effective patient stabilization and decreased mortality, especially among young patients and those with burns of intermediate extent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, for the intensivist, challenges often exist that complicate patient support and stabilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, burn wounds are complex and can present unique difficulties that require late intervention or life-long rehabilitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In addition to improvements in patient stabilization and care, research in burn wound care has yielded advancements that will continue to improve functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This article reviews recent advancements in the care of burn patients with a focus on the pathophysiology and treatment of burn wounds. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Acute thermal injuries requiring medical treatment affect nearly half a million Americans each year, with approximately 40,000 hospitalizations and 3,400 deaths annually [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The survival rate for admitted burn patients has improved consistently over the past four decades [2] and is currently a favorable 97 % for patients admitted to burn centers [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>This can be largely attributed to national decreases in burn size, improvements in burn critical care, and advancements in burn wound care and treatment that have been driven by research, as reflected in the dramatic increase in burn publications over the last several decades [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Since the first International Congress on Research in Burns over 50 years ago, progress has been made in a host of areas, and vital improvements in early resuscitation, infection management, wound excision and coverage, and fluid management have helped in the fight against burn mortality [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This review presents an update on the care of burn patients, with special emphasis on the mechanisms underlying burn wound healing and recent advancements in burn wound care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Pathophysiology of burn wounds </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Thermal burns from dry sources (fire or flame) and wet sources (scalds) account for approximately 80 % of all reported burns [8] and can be classified based on the depth of burn [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In addition to local injury at the site of burn, severe thermal injury over a large area of the skin, roughly 20 % total body surface area (TBSA) or greater, results in acute systemic responses collectively known as burn shock [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Burn shock is characterized by increased capillary permeability, increased hydrostatic pressure across the microvasculature, protein and fluid movement from the intravascular space into the interstitial space, increased systemic vascular resistance, reduced cardiac output, and hypovolemia requiring fluid resuscitation [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The edema that forms in the interstitial space forms rapidly in the first 8 h following burn injury, and continues to form more slowly for at least 18 h [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Volume requirements for resuscitation can be estimated by the total burn size and the patient’s weight (or body surface area). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Additional factors influencing these needs include the presence or absence of inhalation injury, the extent of full-thickness burns, and the time since injury [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The actual fluid infusion rate is then titrated hourly, based on the adequacy of physiological responses, such as the urine output [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Following successful resuscitation, patients with larger burns then enter a more prolonged period of hypermetabolism, chronic inflammation, and lean body mass wasting, all of which may impair wound healing [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Additionally, an increased susceptibility to infection due to altered immune status may lead to sepsis, further exacerbating systemic inflammation [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Sustained hypermetabolism and inflammation impair wound healing through delayed re-epithelialization [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The extent of inflammation and hypermetabolism is related to the extent [19] and depth of burn, as deeper burns show higher levels of circulating cytokines [20] and a greater hypermetabolic response [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the extent of burn is an efficient predictor of hospital length of stay [19, 22] and mortality [19, 23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>According to one model, the burn wound can be divided into three zones based on the severity of tissue destruction and alterations in blood flow [10, 24–26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The central part of the wound, known as the zone of coagulation, is exposed to the greatest amount of heat and suffers the most damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Proteins denature above 41 °C (106 °F), so excessive heat at the site of injury results in extensive protein denaturation, degradation, and coagulation, leading to tissue necrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Around the central zone of coagulation is the zone of stasis, or zone of ischemia, which is characterized by decreased perfusion and potentially salvageable tissue [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In this zone, hypoxia and ischemia can lead to tissue necrosis within 48 h of injury in the absence of intervention [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms underlying apoptosis and necrosis in the ischemic zone remain poorly understood, but appear to involve immediate autophagy within the first 24 h following injury and delayed-onset apoptosis around 24 to 48 h postburn [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Other studies have shown apoptosis to be active as early as 30 min postburn [28] depending on the intensity of the burn injury [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress may play a role in the development of necrosis, as preclinical studies have demonstrated promising reductions in necrosis with systemic antioxidant administration [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>At the outermost regions of the burn wound is the zone of hyperemia that receives increased blood flow via inflammatory vasodilation and will likely recover, barring infection or other injury [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Although burns are different from other wounds in some respects, such as the degree of systemic inflammation [31], healing of all wounds is a dynamic process with overlapping phases [32] (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The initial inflammatory phase brings neutrophils and monocytes to the site of injury via localized vasodilation and fluid extravasation, thereby initiating an immune response that is later sustained by the recruitment of macrophages by chemokines [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The inflammatory phase serves not only to prevent infection during healing, but also to degrade necrotic tissue and activate signals required for wound repair [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Following, and overlapping with the inflammatory response, the proliferative phase is characterized by keratinocyte and fibroblast activation by cytokines and growth factors [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In this phase, keratinocytes migrate over the wound to assist in closure and restoration of a vascular network, which is a vital step in the wound healing process [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This network of communication between stromal, endothelial, and immune cells determines the course of healing, including closure and revascularization.Table 1Phases of wound healingPhaseCharacteristicsKey playersInflammatoryVasodilationNeutrophilsFluid extravasationMonocytesEdemaMacrophagesProliferativeWound closureKeratinocytesRevascularizationFibroblastsRemodelingWound maturationCollagenScarringElastinFibroblasts/myofibroblasts </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Overlapping with the proliferative phase, the final phase of healing involves remodeling the wound [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>During the remodeling phase, the wound scar matures [31] as collagen and elastin are deposited and continuously reformed as fibroblasts become myofibroblasts [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblasts adopt a contractile phenotype, and thus are involved in wound contracture [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The conversion from fibroblasts to myofibroblasts controls a delicate balance between contraction and re-epithelialization that, in part, determines the pliability of the repaired wound [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In addition to fibroblast conversion, apoptosis of keratinocytes and inflammatory cells are key steps in the termination of wound healing and the overall final appearance of the wound [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Optimization of burn wound healing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Inflammation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Inflammation is vital to successful burn wound healing, and inflammatory mediators (cytokines, kinins, lipids, and so forth) provide immune signals to recruit leukocytes and macrophages that initiate the proliferative phase [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Wound re-epithelialization, or closure, in the proliferative phase via keratinocyte and fibroblast activation, or migration from dedifferentiated hair follicles and other epidermal analogs [41, 42], is mediated by cytokines recruited in the inflammatory phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>While this indicates that inflammation is essential for wound healing, aberrant inflammatory pathways have also been linked to hypertrophic scarring, and anti-inflammatory treatments could potentially aggravate symptoms and delay wound healing [40, 43, 44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Significant edema that is initiated by several factors including vasodilation, extravascular osmotic activity, and increased microvascular permeability often accompanies inflammation [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Excessive or prolonged edema and inflammation exacerbate pain and impair wound healing [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, studies suggest that in the absence of infection, inflammation might not be required for tissue repair [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Since inflammation can have both beneficial and detrimental effects on burn wound healing, the clinical challenge becomes management, applying therapeutic intervention only when inflammation and edema become excessive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Treatment of inflammation in large burns is difficult, as recently discussed in detail elsewhere [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Traditional anti-inflammatory treatments that focus on the inhibition of prostaglandin synthesis, such as nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or glucocorticoids, impair wound healing [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>However, steroid administration has been shown to reduce inflammation, pain, and length of hospital stay in burn patients in several small studies [48, 49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Early excision and grafting has become the gold standard for treatment of full and deep partial thickness burns [50, 51], in part because early excision helps reduce the risk of infection and scarring [52–54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The timing of debridement coincides with the inflammatory phase of healing, as the burn eschar removed during excision is an inflammatory nidus and a rich pabulum for bacterial proliferation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Nontraditional anti-inflammatory treatments, such as opioids, have gained considerable attention but have yet to translate promising preclinical results into clinical practice for wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>While the majority of animal studies have demonstrated consistent anti-inflammatory effects of opioids on peripheral neurons [55], clinical studies have shown little to no effect on inflammation [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, topical morphine delayed the early inflammatory phase and accelerated the later proliferative phase [57, 58], which is supported by in vitro studies showing opioid stimulation of keratinocyte migration [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Large-scale clinical trials evaluating opioid efficacy on wound healing have not yet been conducted [60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The skin functions as a barrier to the external environment to maintain fluid homeostasis and body temperature, while providing sensory information along with metabolic and immunological support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Damage to this barrier following a burn disrupts the innate immune system and increases susceptibility to bacterial infection [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Burn wound infection was defined in a rat model with Pseudomonas aeruginosa [62, 63], in which the following progression was observed: burn wound colonization; invasion into subjacent tissue within 5 days; destruction of granulation tissue; visceral hematogenous lesions; and leukopenia, hypothermia, and death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Burn patients are at high risk for infection [64], especially drug-resistant infection [65], which often results in significantly longer hospital stays, delayed wound healing, higher costs, and higher mortality [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Infection can lead to the development of a pronounced immune response, accompanied by sepsis or septic shock, which results in hypotension and impaired perfusion of end organs, including the skin – all processes that delay wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the leading causes of death following a severe burn are sepsis and multiorgan failure [67–69], so prevention and management of infection is a primary concern in the treatment of burn patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Early and accurate diagnosis of infection is difficult: C-reactive protein and the white blood cell count are most often used, since the diagnostic power of procalcitonin is questionable in burns [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Consensus definitions of sepsis and infection have recently been proposed that are more relevant to the burn population and are often used clinically but still require validation [71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The management of burn wound infections has been extensively reviewed elsewhere [61, 64–66, 72–77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Since the adoption of topical antibiotics, such as mafenide in the 1960s and silver sulfadiazine in the 1970s, and of early excision and grafting in the 1970s and thereafter, systemic infections and mortality have consistently decreased [68, 72, 78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacterial infections still remain one of the most common causes of mortality following burn injury [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Bacterial cultures can aid in the selection of an appropriate antibiotic, especially in cases of bacterial drug resistance, but altered pharmacokinetic parameters in burn patients must be considered and dosing should be adjusted accordingly to maximize antibiotic efficacy [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Importantly, effective topical antimicrobials do not exist for invasive fungal infections, and fungal wound infections are associated with greater mortality rates in large burns (&gt;30 % TBSA) [80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Owing to high lethality, suspicion of an invasive burn wound infection mandates rapid diagnosis, often by histopathology, and excision or re-excision of the wound. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Nutrition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Sustained hypermetabolism, hormone elevations, and muscle wasting following severe burn injury all contribute to the clinical outcome, with magnitude and duration that are unique to burns [81, 82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, reducing the impact of a hypermetabolic state and providing adequate nutrition are key factors that affect burn wound healing and recovery [83], as has been reviewed elsewhere [84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>There is a difficult balance between the additional caloric needs to meet the demand from hypermetabolism and the consequences of nutrient overconsumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Nutritional support following a burn injury is a complex issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For example, early excision and aggressive feeding in children does not diminish energy expenditure but is associated with decreased muscle protein catabolism, a decreased rate of burn sepsis, and significantly lower bacterial counts from excised tissue [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In adults, early nutritional support is correlated with shorter stays, accelerated wound healing, and decreased risk of infection [86]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Several nutritional factors must be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For example, excess carbohydrate consumption may lead to hyperglycemia [87] that can exacerbate systemic inflammation and muscle degradation [88, 89]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, excess fat consumption may exaggerate the immunosuppressed state [90]; and since major burn injuries may also result in immunosuppression [91], this exaggeration may increase the risk for infection and sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Carbohydrate and fat intake must therefore be closely monitored in burn patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Guidelines for nutritional support of burn patients vary, but consensus recommendations have been given by the American Burn Association and the American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition for carbohydrates, proteins, and fats [84]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In addition to support with amino acids and vitamins [84], administration of insulin has been shown to decrease healing time by reducing protein catabolism and increasing skeletal muscle protein synthesis [92–96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>More research is needed to optimize insulin delivery, as many recombinant growth factors, such as epidermal growth factor and transforming growth factor, are often cost prohibitive [93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Other anabolic agents, such as oxandrolone, have been shown to increase lean body mass recovery, decrease length of stay, and improve overall outcomes, including wound healing [97–100]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Additionally, while conventional theory suggests that hemoglobin levels must be maintained above 10 g/dl to promote wound healing [101], preliminary evidence suggests that mild to moderate anemia has no effect on graft success if perfusion is maintained with proper circulatory volume [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The results of a multicenter, randomized, controlled trial (ClinicalTrials.gov NCT01079247) comparing blood transfusion with lower volumes (target hemoglobin of 7 to 8 g/dl) and conventional volumes (target hemoglobin &gt;10 g/dl) for a large cohort of patients are expected soon and will allow for more definitive clinical guidelines on blood transfusion volumes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Resuscitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Severe thermal injuries over a large area of the skin (&gt;20 % TBSA) require fluid resuscitation for stabilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Although volume guidelines and fluid compositions vary widely between centers, the goal of fluid resuscitation is to maintain organ perfusion with the least amount of fluid necessary [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Common traditional resuscitation formulas, such as the modified Brooke, and Parkland formulas, employ crystalloids such as lactated Ringer’s that contain sodium, chloride, calcium, potassium, and lactate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>During large-volume resuscitations, the addition of colloids (for example, albumin, fresh frozen plasma) as adjuncts has been successful in reducing the total volume [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Despite extensive research into resuscitation fluid compositions and volumes, little is known about the effect of resuscitation on wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A recent meta-analysis showed a positive association between the number of grafting procedures and hypernatremia, suggesting that high serum sodium levels may inhibit graft take [103]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we have recently shown that the rate of wound closure (healing rate) is significantly faster in patients who received lower 24-h fluid resuscitation volumes [104]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>More work is needed to evaluate the effect of resuscitation on wound healing trajectories before clinical recommendations for preferred fluid compositions and volumes can be made. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Wound coverage and grafting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Early excision and grafting has been the standard of care for decades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Most studies have shown that excision within 24 to 48 h after injury is associated with decreased blood loss, infection, length of hospital stay and mortality, and increased graft take [105–108], although mortality reductions may only occur in patients without inhalation injury [109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Since one of the main challenges in treating acute thermal injuries is preventing infection, excising the eschar and covering the wound as early as possible are critical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The standard for rapid and permanent closure of full-thickness burns is a split-thickness skin graft from an uninjured donor site on the same patient (autograft). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Such grafting provides sufficient coverage without risk of rejection, although meta-analyses have yet to determine the failure rate of split-thickness skin grafts in burn patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Split-thickness skin grafts can be meshed with variable expansion ratios to increase the coverage area, but concerns remain over the effect that meshing has on range of motion [110] and the graft site healing rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, donor sites are painful and impose their own wound-healing burden on the patient [111]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Various dressings have been used to cover donor sites during healing, with variable results [112]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Patients with more extensive burns often require temporary coverage with an allograft, xenograft, skin substitute, or dermal analog due to insufficient or unavailable donor sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Allografts, or tissue taken from a living or deceased human donor, and xenografts, taken from a different species, promote re-epithelialization and prepare the wound bed for autograft, increasing the healing rate when compared with traditional dressings [113]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A recent meta-analysis suggested that since allografts and xenografts appear to be equally effective, xenografts may be a superior choice for their increased safety and reduced price [114]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>However, caution should be exercised in drawing broad conclusions from this meta-analysis because the cited studies lack standardization and critical details such as depth and size of burn, and many studies cited were merely anecdotal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>A cadaver allograft is thus widely considered the best material for temporary closure of excised wounds in patients with extensive, life-threatening burns and inadequate donor sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The cadaver allograft is also the preferred material for protection of widely meshed autografts (3:1 or higher meshing ratios) during healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In the latter setting, the allograft is applied over the meshed autograft in the manner of a sandwich. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>A variety of different skin substitutes and dermal analogs exist [115–119] (Table 2) that can be broadly divided into those which replace the epidermis or replace the dermis [120, 121]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Epidermal substitutes are normally only a few cell layers thick and lack normal dermal components [122, 123]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Commercially available dermal substitutes include acellular matrices, commonly from human – for example, Alloderm (LifeCell, Bridgewater, NJ, USA) or GraftJacket (KCI, San Antonio, TX, USA) – or other sources (for example, Integra; Integra LifeSciences, Plainsboro, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Biobrane (Smith &amp; Nephew, London, UK) is a semisynthetic, bilaminar material consisting of a nylon-mesh dermal analog (bonded with porcine collagen) and a silicone epidermal analog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Biobrane is used for temporary closure of superficial burns and donor sites [124, 125]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Products currently under development integrate the concept of dermal scaffolds that actively promote revascularization by incorporating stem cells and growth factors to recreate a favorable cellular microenvironment [126, 127].Table 2Skin substitutes and coverage optionsProduct nameClassificationCharacteristicsAvailability (company)EpiDexAutologousKeratinocyte-basedNo (Modex, Lausanne, Switzerland)AllodermAcellularHuman originYes (LifeCell, Bridgewater, NJ, USA)Dermal matrixGraftJacketAcellularHuman originYes (KCI, San Antonio, TX, USA)Tissue scaffoldIntegraAcellularBovine/shark originYes (Integra, Plainsboro, NJ, USA)Bilayer matrixBiobraneAcellularBiocomposite dressing, nylon fibers in silicone with collagenYes (Smith &amp; Nephew, London, UK)DermagraftCellularBioabsorbable polyglactin mesh scaffold with human fibroblasts (neonatal origin)Yes (Organogenesis, Canton, MA, USA)EpicelCellularKeratinocyte-based cultured epidermal autograftYes (Genzyme, Cambridge, MA, USA)RecellCellularAutologous cell suspension of keratinocytes, fibroblasts, Langerhans cells and melanocytesYes (Avita, Northridge, CA, USA)Sprayable after culture </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Numerous options exist for dressings [128, 129]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The selection of an appropriate dressing depends on several factors, including depth of burn, condition of the wound bed, wound location, desired moisture retention and drainage, required frequency of dressing changes, and cost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>While many factors must be considered in dressing selection, the goals in selecting the most appropriate dressing should include providing protection from contamination (bacterial or otherwise) and from physical damage, allowing gas exchange and moisture retention, and providing comfort to enhance functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The traditional approach to burn wound care developed at the US Army Burn Center includes alternation of mafenide acetate cream in the morning and silver sulfadiazine cream in the evening, with gauze dressings used over the creams. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>More recently, silver-impregnated and other dressings have been introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Major classes of dressings include: alginate, for example Aquacel (ConvaTec, Bridgewater, NJ, USA), Comfeel (Coloplast, Minneapolis, MN, USA), or Sorbsan (Mylan, Morgantown, WV, USA); antimicrobial, for example Acticoat (Smith &amp; Nephew, London, UK) or Silverlon (Argentum, Geneva, IL, USA); collagen, for example Fibracol (Johnson &amp; Johnson, New Brunswick, NJ) or Puracol (Medline, Mundelein, IL, USA); hydrocolloid, for example Duoderm (ConvaTec, Bridgewater, NJ, USA), Granuflex (ConvaTec, Bridgewater, NJ, USA), or Tegaderm (3M, Maplewood, MN, USA); hydrogel, for example Dermagel (Maximilian Zenho &amp; Co, Brussels, Belgium), SilvaSorb (Medline, Mundelein, IL, USA), or Skintegrity (Medline, Mundelein, IL, USA); and polyurethane foam, for example Allevyn (Smith &amp; Nephew, London, UK) or Lyofoa (Molnycke, Gothenburg, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Notably, many of these dressings exhibit antimicrobial properties through silver impregnation, but recent studies suggest silver may delay wound healing and should not be routinely used on uninfected donor skin [130, 131] even though silver dressings may reduce wound pain [132]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In patients with extensive or deep burns, antimicrobial efficacy should be the first priority in burn wound care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, cell-based techniques for more permanent coverage have made progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Research on cultured epithelial cells has made advancements, especially with respect to culture time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Culture-based options, such as Epicel (Genzyme, Cambridge, MA, USA), use a small biopsy of the patient’s skin to provide keratinocytes, which are expanded over 2 to 3 weeks (for Epicel, in the presence of proliferation-arrested murine fibroblasts) into a confluent epidermal autograft. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Other options, such as ReCell (Avita, Northridge, CA, USA), take a small biopsy of the patient’s skin and prepare a mixture of keratinocytes, melanocytes, and stem cells in a liquid formulation for spraying onto the excised burn wound during the same operation [133–135]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These techniques may reduce the amount of donor skin needed for treatment of large burns, significantly reducing the healing time of both the donor and the burn sites, and increasing overall graft success and scar quality [136]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>More work is needed on cell-based coverage options before widespread implementation can be recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Keratinocytes and stem cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As mentioned previously, keratinocytes play a vital role in wound closure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Cytokine activation causes keratinocyte migration in the proliferative phase, leading to closure and restoration of a vascular network [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Keratinocytes can also be activated by mu opioid receptor agonists [59] but the role of these agonists on inflammation and wound closure remains unclear [57, 58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Despite positive studies with EpiDex (Modex, Lausanne, Switzerland) – an engineered, fully differentiated autologous skin substitute derived from keratinocytes showing efficacy comparable with split-thickness skin grafts in wound closure and healing [137] – results have yet to translate into clinically viable options. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Studies evaluating expansion of keratinocytes on human fibroblasts following trypsin extraction [138], and using engineered skin with keratinocytes on a fibrin matrix [139], have demonstrated improvements in wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Retrospective analyses on autologous keratinocytes showed that cultured allogeneic or autologous keratinocytes may accelerate wound healing [140, 141]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the future impact of keratinocyte-mediated cell coverage options is promising, but more research is needed [134]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Additionally, keratinocyte-based treatments should be pursued carefully, as overactivation of keratinocytes can contribute to the development of hypertrophic scarring [43, 142]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The use of adult stem cells, including bone marrow stem cells, hair follicle stem cells, and adipose stem cells, in acute burn care is an exciting topic [143]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Addition of bone marrow stem cells to nonhealing chronic wounds leads to engraftment of cells and enhanced wound healing [144, 145]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Moreover, studies have reported that bone marrow stem cells can transdifferentiate towards multiple skin cell types [146]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Mechanisms of action of bone marrow stem cells in burns are not fully elucidated, but modulation of inflammation has occurred after radiation burns in humans [147]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Similarly, adipose stem cells accelerate re-epithelialization by paracrine activation of host cells via growth factor secretion [148, 149]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Also, hair follicle stem cells are capable of generating a stratified epidermis on human burn wounds [150]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the possibility of generating a cellular skin equivalent is being explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Hair follicle stem cells have been incorporated into products, such as Integra, to investigate wound healing [151]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>A cultured skin substitute using adipose stem cells and keratinocytes has been developed that produces epidermal, dermal, and hypodermal stratification [152]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Moreover, human adipose stem cells that would normally be discarded have recently been isolated from debrided burn eschar tissue [153] and used to generate a tri-layered, vascularized construct [154]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Promising data with nonembryonic stems cells such as these have stimulated interest into future applications and development, and undoubtedly further investigations will produce exciting results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Other considerations and future directions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Monitoring and predicting wound healing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>No new skin-based technology can substitute for careful attention by the burn team to the progress (or lack thereof) of wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The WoundFlow computer software program was developed as an enhancement over the traditional paper Lund–Browder diagram to more accurately quantify and track burn injuries over time [104, 155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>WoundFlow is an electronic mapping program that calculates burn size and tracks wound healing [104, 155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The ability to accurately track burn wound healing over time will support both clinical care and future studies that compare healing rates and outcomes following different treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Notably, this study demonstrated that delayed wound healing was associated with a significantly higher risk of mortality [104, 155]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The ability to predict whether a burn wound will spontaneously heal or not would greatly improve patient care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the ability to uniquely tailor treatment to each individual patient would improve patient outcomes and decrease the time to functional recovery, reducing the overall cost of care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Biomarkers may provide a means to allow for tailored treatments and to give insight into wound healing mechanisms [156–161]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Significant efforts in the search for predictive biomarkers for wound failure have determined that serum cytokines, such as interleukin-3 and 12p70, and serum procalcitonin are independently associated with wound failure [161]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Additional candidates have been identified [158–160] but further work is needed to model complex, temporal serum cytokine profiles into an effective predictor for wound healing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In addition to evaluating serum cytokine profiles, candidate biomarkers have been identified in wound effluent [161], which may be a better medium for predicting local wound healing than cytokines in the circulation [162]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Wound exudate has been shown to contain elevated levels of immunosuppressive and proinflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-1β, interleukin-2, interleukin-6, and tumor necrosis factor alpha [163]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In fact, dipeptidyl peptidase IV and aminopeptidase have been identified in burn wound exudate with a significantly different ratio from that found in plasma [164]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Other work on local wound biomarkers using biopsies has shown that a host of proteins are upregulated during wound healing [165]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>More work is needed to establish a biomarker profile that can accurately predict wound healing and to identify potential novel areas for therapeutic intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition to examining burn wounds directly, and the wound exudate, another potential method for examining the ability of burn wounds to heal is non-invasive imaging [166]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>To this end, a number of non-invasive imaging techniques have been investigated for their use in determining burn depth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Such techniques include terahertz imaging, spatial-frequency-domain imaging, near-infrared spectroscopic imaging, and reflectance-mode confocal microscopy, among others [167–172]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>While many of these techniques have not yet been refined sufficiently for clinical application, the most successful research efforts into imaging techniques for burn wounds examine blood flow, such as laser Doppler imaging and indocyanine green angiography [173]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Laser Doppler imaging provides the most evidence for accurately assessing burn severity [174], but it has been shown that laser Doppler imaging is only superior to visual assessment 48 h after thermal injury [175]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Additional studies are needed to fully explore the potential for incorporation of non-invasive imaging modalities into the routine treatment of burn wounds. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Obese patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>As the obese population continues to grow [176], new treatment approaches will be required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Obese burn patients present with a variety of unique characteristics that include: increased rates of diabetes, hypertension, cardiac disease, and pulmonary disease; altered pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics; and altered immune responses [177]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Even the commonly used Lund–Browder chart for estimation of TBSA is problematic for obese patients because it fails to account for altered body-mass distribution in these patients [178]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Hence, analysis of group differences and controlled clinical studies in unique patient populations are needed [179]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Older patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Census predictions suggest that the older population will double in the next 20 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Since older people are at increased risk for burn injury, an increasing number of burn injuries among the older population should be expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A recent review delineated the unique burn pathophysiology, comorbidities, and treatment strategies for the older population [180]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Detailing all of the unique considerations for the older burn population is outside the scope of this review, but several key points are noteworthy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Most burns among older people occur at home, especially in the kitchen and bathroom, due to diminished alertness, slower reaction time, and reduced mobility [181]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Reductions in metabolic rate and skin thickness with age result in more severe burns, and more extensive full-thickness burns are associated with increased mortality [182]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Comorbidities such as diabetes and cardiovascular disease complicate treatment, and may exacerbate the postburn hypermetabolic response [183]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Several formulas for predicting the survival of older patients, such as the Baux score [184], have received wide acceptance and can help guide clinicians in patient treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Unique treatment considerations for older patients should include attentive resuscitation to reduce the risk of volume overload, judicious ventilator support, careful analgesic administration, prudently timed excision and grafting, and extended rehabilitation for functional recovery [180]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The older population presents a unique challenge to the burn clinician, and the treatment of patients must be carefully considered on a case-by-case basis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Future directions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Adult burn patients with increased markers of inflammatory stress exhibit reduced serum levels of vitamin A despite normal markers of oxidative stress [185–187]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Additionally, limited preclinical studies show that polyprenoic acid and retinol can facilitate wound healing [188], and that retinoids are efficacious on a variety of other skin conditions [189]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Moreover, early clinical studies have shown that retinoid treatment effectively increases scar elasticity [190, 191]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these data highlight the need for studies evaluating retinoids on burn wound healing outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Pirfenidone was originally developed as an antihelminthic and antipyretic agent, but recent work has demonstrated that it also has anti-inflammatory, antioxidative, and antiproliferative effects [192]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>In particular, the antifibrotic properties of pirfenidone attenuate fibroblast proliferation and collagen deposition in vitro and in preclinical models [192]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Pirfenidone is approved for the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in Europe, Japan, and the USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The antifibrotic actions of pirfenidone and other data suggest that pirfenidone could modulate the tissue response to injury at multiple stages of wound repair to improve scarring and function as an adjuvant for abnormal wound healing processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Preclinical investigations are currently underway in rabbits [193, 194] and rats [195], but controlled clinical studies are needed to evaluate the safety and efficacy of pirfenidone on abnormal wound healing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The treatment of burn wounds with hyperbaric oxygen was first investigated in the mid-1960s and garnered some attention in the decades following, but controversy remains over potential risks and costs [196, 197]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Recent work in rat models has shown that hyperbaric oxygen reduces healing time and improves scar appearance of burn injuries [198]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Advancements in hyperbaric chambers have reduced the overall cost associated with treatment, and controlled clinical trials in humans are beginning to produce data supporting the conclusion that hyperbaric oxygen is safe and effective for improving burn wound healing [199–201]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>However, more data are needed before broad conclusions can be made about the overall utility of hyperbaric oxygen for treating burns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Future research on burn patient care will focus on a variety of areas [202]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Considering a current survival rate of over 97 % for burn patients [3], major advancements from the past several decades have improved patient care such that significant future improvements in patient survival rate will be more difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>However, improvements are still needed in individualized care, namely prediction of patient outcomes and the ability to tailor treatment to optimize functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Improvements are also needed to accelerate wound closure and healing and to improve psychological care to promote successful reintegration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Research in inflammation, infection, stem cells, grafting, biomarkers, inflammation control, and rehabilitation will continue to improve individualized care and create new treatment options. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The various clinical challenges in treating acute thermal injuries include balancing the many factors that affect wound healing to reduce the length of stay (and associated cost of treatment), the risk of infection, the time to wound closure, and the overall time to functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The treatment of burn wounds has evolved over several decades through clinical and preclinical research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Significant advancements have been made in patient care, including tracking wound healing, developing novel graft and coverage options, controlling inflammation, optimizing dietary needs, and testing unique pharmacological interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>As a result of these efforts, patient survival has improved along with a concomitant decrease in the length of stay, which in turn results in a decreased cost to the patient and the medical providers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>A summary of selected clinical recommendations is provided (Table 3) to aid the intensivist, but it is important to remember that burn patients present unique challenges based on multiple variables (for example, age, TBSA, comorbidities) and treatment decisions must be tailored to each patient’s needs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Current and future research will continue to identify novel targets and treatment paradigms to further improve burn wound care.Table 3Recommendations for the intensivistAccurate measurement of burn size using a Lund–Browder chartCarefully titrated fluid resuscitation, to balance risks of edema formation with those of ongoing hypoperfusionEarly initiation of effective topical antimicrobial therapy (mafenide acetate or silver-based creams/dressings)Daily inspection of the wounds by a qualified surgeon or wound care expertEarly excision and grafting of all full thickness and deep partial thickness burnsAggressive treatment of infected wounds (resuscitate, broad-spectrum topical and systemic antimicrobials, excision, or re-excision)Rehabilitation in the ICU to minimize the functional consequences of prolonged immobilization and contracture formation </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviation</title><def-list><def-item><term>TBSA</term><def><p>Total body surface area</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>MPR and KKC outlined the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>MPR wrote all drafts of the manuscript, with primary editing and revision support from LCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>All authors contributed information for the manuscript, participated in its revision, and approved the final version for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the staff of the Clinical Trials task area at the US Army Institute of Surgical Research for administrative support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The authors would also like to thank Dr Harold Klemcke for critical review of this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This work was supported in part by an appointment (MPR) to the Postgraduate Research Participation Program and an appointment (LCC) to the Knowledge Preservation Program at the US Army Institute of Surgical Research administered by the Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education through an interagency agreement between the US Department of Energy and US Army Medical Research and Materiel Command. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The opinions or assertions contained herein are the private views of the authors and are not to be construed as official or as reflecting the views of the Department of the Army or the Department of Defense. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>1.GibranNSWiechmanSMeyerWEdelmanLFauerbachJGibbonsLAmerican Burn Association consensus statementsJ Burn Care Res2013343615<?supplied-pmid 23835626?>23835626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>2.MannRHeimbachDPrognosis and treatment of burnsWest J Med199616521520<?supplied-pmid 8987427?>8987427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>3.American Burn Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Burn incidence and treatment in the United States: 2013 fact sheet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ameriburn.org/resources_factsheet.php">http://www.ameriburn.org/resources_factsheet.php</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Accessed 12 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>4.SenSPalmieriTGreenhalghDReview of burn research for the year 2013J Burn Care Res2014353628<?supplied-pmid 25094008?>25094008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>5.WolfSEArnoldoBDThe year in burns 2011Burns2012381096108<?supplied-pmid 23067558?>23067558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>6.BurdAResearch in burns – present and futureIndian J Plast Surg201043S114<?supplied-pmid 21321644?>21321644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>7.ThomasSJKramerGCHerndonDNBurns: military options and tactical solutionsJ Trauma200354S20718<?supplied-pmid 12768127?>12768127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>8.American Burn Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>National Burn Repository 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>2014. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ameriburn.org/2014NBRAnnualReport.pdf">http://www.ameriburn.org/2014NBRAnnualReport.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Accessed 12 May 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>9.KaganRJPeckMDAhrenholzDHHickersonWLHolmesJKorentagerRSurgical management of the burn wound and use of skin substitutes: an expert panel white paperJ Burn Care Res201334e6079<?supplied-pmid 23446645?>23446645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>10.NisanciMEskiMSahinIIlganSIsikSSaving the zone of stasis in burns with activated protein C: an experimental study in ratsBurns201036397402<?supplied-pmid 19765907?>19765907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>11.RobinsEVBurn shockCrit Care Nurs Clin North Am19902299307<?supplied-pmid 2357324?>2357324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>12.PhamTNCancioLCGibranNSAmerican Burn AssociationAmerican Burn Association practice guidelines burn shock resuscitationJ Burn Care Res20082925766<?supplied-pmid 18182930?>18182930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>13.ShiraniKZVaughanGMMasonADJrPruittBAJrUpdate on current therapeutic approaches in burnsShock19965416<?supplied-pmid 8821097?>8821097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>14.DriesDJManagement of burn injuries – recent developments in resuscitation, infection control and outcomes researchScand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med20091714<?supplied-pmid 19284591?>19284591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>15.PorterCHurrenNMHerndonDNBorsheimEWhole body and skeletal muscle protein turnover in recovery from burnsInt J Burns Trauma20133917<?supplied-pmid 23386981?>23386981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>16.FarinaJAJrRosiqueMJRosiqueRGCurbing inflammation in burn patientsInt J Inflamm20132013715645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>17.EdgarDWFishJSGomezMWoodFMLocal and systemic treatments for acute edema after burn injury: a systematic review of the literatureJ Burn Care Res20113233447<?supplied-pmid 21252688?>21252688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>18.SommerKSanderALAlbigMWeberRHenrichDFrankJDelayed wound repair in sepsis is associated with reduced local pro-inflammatory cytokine expressionPLoS One20138<?supplied-pmid 24086305?>24086305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>19.WilmoreDWLongJMMasonADJrSkreenRWPruittBAJrCatecholamines: mediator of the hypermetabolic response to thermal injuryAnn Surg197418065369<?supplied-pmid 4412350?>4412350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>20.SakalliogluAEBasaranOKarakayaliHOzdemirBHYucelMAratZInteractions of systemic immune response and local wound healing in different burn depths: an experimental study on ratsJ Burn Care Res20062735766<?supplied-pmid 16679907?>16679907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>21.PereiraCTHerndonDNThe pharmacologic modulation of the hypermetabolic response to burnsAdv Surg20053924561<?supplied-pmid 16250555?>16250555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>22.HussainADunnKWPredicting length of stay in thermal burns: a systematic review of prognostic factorsBurns201339133140<?supplied-pmid 23768707?>23768707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>23.ColohanSMPredicting prognosis in thermal burns with associated inhalational injury: a systematic review of prognostic factors in adult burn victimsJ Burn Care Res20103152939<?supplied-pmid 20523229?>20523229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>24.JacksonDMThe diagnosis of the depth of burningBr J Surg19534058896<?supplied-pmid 13059343?>13059343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>25.HettiaratchySDziewulskiPABC of burns: pathophysiology and types of burnsBMJ200432814279<?supplied-pmid 15191982?>15191982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>26.KowalskeKJBurn wound carePhys Med Rehab Clin North Am20112221327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>27.TanJQZhangHHLeiZJRenPDengCLiXYThe roles of autophagy and apoptosis in burn wound progression in ratsBurns20133915516<?supplied-pmid 23751274?>23751274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>28.SingerAJMcClainSATairaBRGuerrieroJLZongWApoptosis and necrosis in the ischemic zone adjacent to third degree burnsAcad Emerg Med20081554954<?supplied-pmid 18616442?>18616442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>29.MatylevitchNPSchuscherebaSTMataJRGilliganGRLawlorDFGoodwinCWApoptosis and accidental cell death in cultured human keratinocytes after thermal injuryAm J Pathol199815356777<?supplied-pmid 9708816?>9708816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>30.DenizMBormanHSeyhanTHaberalMAn effective antioxidant drug on prevention of the necrosis of zone of stasis: N-acetylcysteineBurns2013393205<?supplied-pmid 22853970?>22853970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>31.TiwariVKBurn wound: how it differs from other wounds?Indian J Plast Surg20124536473<?supplied-pmid 23162236?>23162236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>32.GurtnerGCWernerSBarrandonYLongakerMTWound repair and regenerationNature200845331421<?supplied-pmid 18480812?>18480812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>33.ReinkeJMSorgHWound repair and regenerationEur Surg Res2012493543<?supplied-pmid 22797712?>22797712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>34.WernerSKriegTSmolaHKeratinocyte–fibroblast interactions in wound healingJ Invest Dermatol20071279981008<?supplied-pmid 17435785?>17435785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>35.PastarIStojadinovicOYinNCRamirezHNusbaumAGSawayaAEpithelialization in wound healing: a comprehensive reviewAdv Wound Care2014344564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>36.WidgerowADCellular/extracellular matrix cross-talk in scar evolution and controlWound Repair Regen20111911733<?supplied-pmid 21362079?>21362079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>37.SingerAJClarkRACutaneous wound healingN Engl J Med199934173846<?supplied-pmid 10471461?>10471461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>38.HinzBFormation and function of the myofibroblast during tissue repairJ Invest Dermatol200712752637<?supplied-pmid 17299435?>17299435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>39.SnowdenJMWound closure: an analysis of the relative contributions of contraction and epithelializationJ Surg Res19843745363<?supplied-pmid 6513541?>6513541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>40.ShihBGarsideEMcGroutherDABayatAMolecular dissection of abnormal wound healing processes resulting in keloid diseaseWound Repair Regen20101813953<?supplied-pmid 20002895?>20002895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>41.ClaudinotSNicolasMOshimaHRochatABarrandonYLong-term renewal of hair follicles from clonogenic multipotent stem cellsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20051021467782<?supplied-pmid 16203973?>16203973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>42.ItoMLiuYYangZNguyenJLiangFMorrisRJStem cells in the hair follicle bulge contribute to wound repair but not to homeostasis of the epidermisNat Med20051113514<?supplied-pmid 16288281?>16288281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>43.CurranTAGhaharyAEvidence of a role for fibrocyte and keratinocyte-like cells in the formation of hypertrophic scarsJ Burn Care Res20133422731<?supplied-pmid 22955158?>22955158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>44.TabasIGlassCKAnti-inflammatory therapy in chronic disease: challenges and opportunitiesScience201333916672<?supplied-pmid 23307734?>23307734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>45.ArtursonGForty years in burns research – the postburn inflammatory responseBurns200026599604<?supplied-pmid 10925181?>10925181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>46.SzpaderskaAMDiPietroLAInflammation in surgical wound healing: friend or foe?Surgery20051375713<?supplied-pmid 15855932?>15855932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>47.FranzMGSteedDLRobsonMCOptimizing healing of the acute wound by minimizing complicationsCurr Probl Surg200744691763<?supplied-pmid 18036992?>18036992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>48.StubhaugARomundstadLKaasaTBreivikHMethylprednisolone and ketorolac rapidly reduce hyperalgesia around a skin burn injury and increase pressure pain thresholdsActa Anaesthesiol Scand200751113846<?supplied-pmid 17714578?>17714578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>49.HuangGLiangBLiuGLiuKDingZLow dose of glucocorticoid decreases the incidence of complications in severely burned patients by attenuating systemic inflammationJ Crit Care201530e711<?supplied-pmid 25307976?>25307976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>50.JanzekovicZA new concept in the early excision and immediate grafting of burnsJ Trauma19701011038<?supplied-pmid 4921723?>4921723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>51.OrgillDPExcision and skin grafting of thermal burnsN Engl J Med2009360893901<?supplied-pmid 19246361?>19246361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>52.BarretJPHerndonDNEffects of burn wound excision on bacterial colonization and invasionPlast Reconstruct Surg200311174450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>53.CramerLMMcCormackCRCarrollDBProgressive partial excision and early graftin in lethal burnsPlast Reconstruct Surg Transplant Bull1962305959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>54.EngravLHHeimbachDMReusJLHarnarTJMarvinJAEarly excision and grafting vs. nonoperative treatment of burns of indeterminant depth: a randomized prospective studyJ Trauma19832310014<?supplied-pmid 6355500?>6355500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>55.SteinCKuchlerSNon-analgesic effects of opioids: peripheral opioid effects on inflammation and wound healingCurr Pharm Des201218605369<?supplied-pmid 22747536?>22747536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>56.BrackARittnerHLSteinCImmunosuppressive effects of opioids – clinical relevanceJ Neuroimmune Pharmacol20116490502<?supplied-pmid 21728033?>21728033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>57.RookJMHasanWMcCarsonKEMorphine-induced early delays in wound closure: involvement of sensory neuropeptides and modification of neurokinin receptor expressionBiochem Pharmacol200977174755<?supplied-pmid 19428329?>19428329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>58.RookJMMcCarsonKEDelay of cutaneous wound closure by morphine via local blockade of peripheral tachykinin releaseBiochem Pharmacol2007747527<?supplied-pmid 17632084?>17632084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>59.BigliardiPLBuchnerSRufliTBigliardi-QiMSpecific stimulation of migration of human keratinocytes by mu-opiate receptor agonistsJ Recept Signal Transduct Res2002221919<?supplied-pmid 12503615?>12503615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>60.SteinCKuchlerSTargeting inflammation and wound healing by opioidsTrends Pharmacol Sci20133430312<?supplied-pmid 23602130?>23602130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>61.ChurchDElsayedSReidOWinstonBLindsayRBurn wound infectionsClin Microbiol Rev20061940334<?supplied-pmid 16614255?>16614255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>62.TeplitzCDavisDWalkerHLRaulstonGLMasonADJrMoncriefJAPseudomonas burn wound sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>II Hematogenous infection at the junction of the burn wound and the unburned hypodermisJ Surg Res1964421722<?supplied-pmid 14160480?>14160480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>63.TeplitzCDavisDMasonADJrMoncriefJAPseudomonas burn wound sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>I Pathogenesis of experimental pseudomonas burn wound sepsisJ Surg Res1964420016<?supplied-pmid 14160479?>14160479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>64.CobanYKInfection control in severely burned patientsWorld J Crit Care Med2012194101<?supplied-pmid 24701406?>24701406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>65.BranskiLKAl-MousawiARiveroHJeschkeMGSanfordAPHerndonDNEmerging infections in burnsSurg Infect20091038997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>66.ShuppJWPavlovichARJengJCPezzulloJCOetgenWJJaskilleADEpidemiology of bloodstream infections in burn-injured patients: a review of the national burn repositoryJ Burn Care Res2010315218<?supplied-pmid 20616647?>20616647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>67.BloemsmaGCDokterJBoxmaHOenIMMortality and causes of death in a burn centreBurns20083411037<?supplied-pmid 18538932?>18538932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>68.ChippEMilnerCSBlackburnAVSepsis in burns: a review of current practice and future therapiesAnn Plastic Surg20106522836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>69.WilliamsFNHerndonDNHawkinsHKLeeJOCoxRAKulpGAThe leading causes of death after burn injury in a single pediatric burn centerCrit Care200913R183<?supplied-pmid 19919684?>19919684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>70.MannEAWoodGLWadeCEUse of procalcitonin for the detection of sepsis in the critically ill burn patient: a systematic review of the literatureBurns20113754958<?supplied-pmid 20537467?>20537467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>71.GreenhalghDGSaffleJRHolmesJHGamelliRLPalmieriTLHortonJWAmerican Burn Association consensus conference to define sepsis and infection in burnsJ Burn Care Res20072877690<?supplied-pmid 17925660?>17925660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>72.D'AvignonLCChungKKSaffleJRRenzEMCancioLCPrevention of Combat-Related Infections Guidelines Panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Prevention of infections associated with combat-related burn injuriesJ Trauma201171S2829<?supplied-pmid 21814094?>21814094 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>73.D'AvignonLCHoganBKMurrayCKLooFLHospenthalDRCancioLCContribution of bacterial and viral infections to attributable mortality in patients with severe burns: an autopsy seriesBurns2010367739<?supplied-pmid 20074860?>20074860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>74.HospenthalDRMurrayCKAndersenRCBellRBCalhounJHCancioLCGuidelines for the prevention of infections associated with combat-related injuries: 2011 update: endorsed by the Infectious Diseases Society of America and the Surgical Infection SocietyJ Trauma201171S21034<?supplied-pmid 21814089?>21814089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>75.HospenthalDRMurrayCKAndersenRCBliceJPCalhounJHCancioLCGuidelines for the prevention of infection after combat-related injuriesJ Trauma200864S21120<?supplied-pmid 18316965?>18316965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>76.RaflaKTredgetEEInfection control in the burn unitBurns201137515<?supplied-pmid 20561750?>20561750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>77.Rowley-ConwyGInfection prevention and treatment in patients with major burn injuriesNurs Stand201025512<?supplied-pmid 21138123?>21138123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>78.BrownTPCancioLCMcManusATMasonADJrSurvival benefit conferred by topical antimicrobial preparations in burn patients: a historical perspectiveJ Trauma2004568636<?supplied-pmid 15187754?>15187754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>79.RobertsJAAbdul-AzizMHLipmanJMoutonJWVinksAAFeltonTWIndividualised antibiotic dosing for patients who are critically ill: challenges and potential solutionsLancet Infect Dis201414498509<?supplied-pmid 24768475?>24768475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>80.HorvathEEMurrayCKVaughanGMChungKKHospenthalDRWadeCEFungal wound infection (not colonization) is independently associated with mortality in burn patientsAnn Surg200724597885<?supplied-pmid 17522525?>17522525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>81.HerndonDNTompkinsRGSupport of the metabolic response to burn injuryLancet20043631895902<?supplied-pmid 15183630?>15183630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>82.WilliamsFNHerndonDNJeschkeMGThe hypermetabolic response to burn injury and interventions to modify this responseClin Plast Surg20093658396<?supplied-pmid 19793553?>19793553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>83.AndelHKamolzLPHoraufKZimpferMNutrition and anabolic agents in burned patientsBurns2003295925<?supplied-pmid 12927986?>12927986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>84.AbdullahiAJeschkeMGNutrition and anabolic pharmacotherapies in the care of burn patientsNutr Clin Pract20142962130<?supplied-pmid 25606644?>25606644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>85.HartDWWolfSEChinkesDLBeaufordRBMlcakRPHeggersJPEffects of early excision and aggressive enteral feeding on hypermetabolism, catabolism, and sepsis after severe burnJ Trauma20035475561<?supplied-pmid 12707540?>12707540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>86.MosierMJPhamTNKleinMBGibranNSArnoldoBDGamelliRLEarly enteral nutrition in burns: compliance with guidelines and associated outcomes in a multicenter studyJ Burn Care Res2011321049<?supplied-pmid 21116188?>21116188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>87.MecottGAAl-MousawiAMGauglitzGGHerndonDNJeschkeMGThe role of hyperglycemia in burned patients: evidence-based studiesShock201033513<?supplied-pmid 19503020?>19503020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>88.GoreDCChinkesDLHartDWWolfSEHerndonDNSanfordAPHyperglycemia exacerbates muscle protein catabolism in burn-injured patientsCrit Care Med200230243842<?supplied-pmid 12441751?>12441751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>89.KulpGATiltonRGHerndonDNJeschkeMGHyperglycemia exacerbates burn-induced liver inflammation via noncanonical nuclear factor-kappaB pathway activationMol Med20121894856<?supplied-pmid 22572938?>22572938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>90.Cunningham-RundlesSMcNeeleyDFMoonAMechanisms of nutrient modulation of the immune responseJ Allergy Clin Immunol2005115111928<?supplied-pmid 15940121?>15940121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>91.SchwachaMGChaudryIHThe cellular basis of post-burn immunosuppression: macrophages and mediatorsInt J Mol Med20021023943<?supplied-pmid 12165794?>12165794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>92.FerrandoAAChinkesDLWolfSEMatinSHerndonDNWolfeRRA submaximal dose of insulin promotes net skeletal muscle protein synthesis in patients with severe burnsAnn Surg1999229118<?supplied-pmid 9923795?>9923795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>93.HrynykMNeufeldRJInsulin and wound healingBurns201440143346<?supplied-pmid 24810536?>24810536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>94.PidcokeHFBaerLAWuXWolfSEAdenJKWadeCEInsulin effects on glucose tolerance, hypermetabolic response, and circadian-metabolic protein expression in a rat burn and disuse modelAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol2014307R110<?supplied-pmid 24760998?>24760998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>95.PidcokeHFWadeCEWolfSEInsulin and the burned patientCrit Care Med200735S52430<?supplied-pmid 17713403?>17713403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>96.SakuraiYAarslandAHerndonDNChinkesDLPierreENguyenTTStimulation of muscle protein synthesis by long-term insulin infusion in severely burned patientsAnn Surg199522228394<?supplied-pmid 7677459?>7677459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>97.HartDWWolfSERamzyPIChinkesDLBeaufordRBFerrandoAAAnabolic effects of oxandrolone after severe burnAnn Surg200123355664<?supplied-pmid 11303139?>11303139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>98.TuvdendorjDChinkesDLZhangXJSumanOEAarslandAFerrandoALong-term oxandrolone treatment increases muscle protein net deposition via improving amino acid utilization in pediatric patients 6 months after burn injurySurgery201114964553<?supplied-pmid 21333314?>21333314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>99.WolfSEEdelmanLSKemalyanNDonisonLCrossJUnderwoodMEffects of oxandrolone on outcome measures in the severely burned: a multicenter prospective randomized double-blind trialJ Burn Care Res2006271319<?supplied-pmid 16566555?>16566555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>100.WolfSEThomasSJDasuMRFerrandoAAChinkesDLWolfeRRImproved net protein balance, lean mass, and gene expression changes with oxandrolone treatment in the severely burnedAnn Surg200323780110<?supplied-pmid 12796576?>12796576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>101.BainsJWCrawfordDTKetchamASEffect of chronic anemia on wound tensile strength: correlation with blood volume, total red blood cell volume and proteinsAnn Surg19661642436<?supplied-pmid 5915934?>5915934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>102.AgarwalPPrajapatiBSharmaDEvaluation of skin graft take following post-burn raw area in normovolaemic anaemiaIndian J Plast Surg2009421958<?supplied-pmid 20368857?>20368857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>103.NamdarTStollwerckPLStangFHEisenbeissWSiemersFMailanderPImpact of hypernatremia on burn wound healing: results of an exploratory, retrospective studyOstomy Wound Manage201157304<?supplied-pmid 21422481?>21422481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>104.NitzschkeSLAdenJKSerio-MelvinMLShingletonSKChungKKWatersJAWound healing trajectories in burn patients and their impact on mortalityJ Burn Care Res2014354749<?supplied-pmid 25144807?>25144807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>105.DesaiMHHerndonDNBroemelingLBarrowRENicholsRJJrRutanRLEarly burn wound excision significantly reduces blood lossAnn Surg19902117539<?supplied-pmid 2357138?>2357138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>106.HerndonDNBarrowRERutanRLRutanTCDesaiMHAbstonSA comparison of conservative versus early excision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Therapies in severely burned patientsAnn Surg198920954752<?supplied-pmid 2650643?>2650643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>107.SaaiqMZaibSAhmadSEarly excision and grafting versus delayed excision and grafting of deep thermal burns up to 40 % total body surface area: a comparison of outcomeAnn Burns Fire Disasters2012251437<?supplied-pmid 23467391?>23467391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>108.Vinita P, Khare NA, Chandramouli M, Nilesh S, Sumit B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of early excision and grafting vs delayed grafting in burn patients in a developing country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>J Burn Care Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>2014; doi:10.1097/BCR.0b013e31827e4ed6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>109.OngYSSamuelMSongCMeta-analysis of early excision of burnsBurns20063214550<?supplied-pmid 16414197?>16414197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>110.SchwanholtCGreenhalghDGWardenGDA comparison of full-thickness versus split-thickness autografts for the coverage of deep palm burns in the very young pediatric patientJ Burn Care Rehab1993142933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>111.AkanMYildirimSMisirliogluAUlusoyGAkozTAvciGAn alternative method to minimize pain in the split-thickness skin graft donor sitePlast Reconstruct Surg200311122439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>112.VoineskosSHAyeniOAMcKnightLThomaASystematic review of skin graft donor-site dressingsPlast Reconstruct Surg2009124298306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>113.HermansMHPreservation methods of allografts and their (lack of) influence on clinical results in partial thickness burnsBurns20113787381<?supplied-pmid 21353745?>21353745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>114.HermansMHPorcine xenografts vs. (cryopreserved) allografts in the management of partial thickness burns: is there a clinical difference?Burns20144040815<?supplied-pmid 24018214?>24018214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>115.EhrenreichMRuszczakZTissue-engineered temporary wound coverings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Important options for the clinicianActa Dermatovenerol Alp Pannonica Adriat200615513<?supplied-pmid 16850093?>16850093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR116"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>116.EhrenreichMRuszczakZUpdate on tissue-engineered biological dressingsTissue Eng200612240724<?supplied-pmid 16995775?>16995775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR117"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>117.GroeberFHoleiterMHampelMHindererSSchenke-LaylandKSkin tissue engineering – in vivo and in vitro applicationsClin Plast Surg2012393358<?supplied-pmid 22099847?>22099847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR118"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>118.MansbridgeJSkin tissue engineeringJ Biomater Sci Polym Ed20081995568<?supplied-pmid 18644224?>18644224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR119"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>119.MansbridgeJNTissue-engineered skin substitutes in regenerative medicineCurr Opin Biotechnol2009205637<?supplied-pmid 19782559?>19782559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR120"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>120.CatalanoECochisAVaroniERimondiniLAzzimontiBTissue-engineered skin substitutes: an overviewJ Artif201316397403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR121"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>121.ShevchenkoRVJamesSLJamesSEA review of tissue-engineered skin bioconstructs available for skin reconstructionJ R Soc Interface2010722958<?supplied-pmid 19864266?>19864266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR122"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>122.AtiyehBSCostagliolaMCultured epithelial autograft (CEA) in burn treatment: three decades laterBurns20073340513<?supplied-pmid 17400392?>17400392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR123"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>123.FangTLineaweaverWCSailesFCKisnerCZhangFClinical application of cultured epithelial autografts on acellular dermal matrices in the treatment of extended burn injuriesAnn Plast Surg20147350915<?supplied-pmid 24322642?>24322642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR124"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>124.JeschkeMGFinnertyCCShahrokhiSBranskiLKDibildoxMOrganizationABAWound coverage technologies in burn care: novel techniquesJ Burn Care Res20133461220<?supplied-pmid 23877140?>23877140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR125"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>125.SuppDMBoyceSTEngineered skin substitutes: practices and potentialsClin Dermatol20052340312<?supplied-pmid 16023936?>16023936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR126"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>126.KampmannALindhorstDSchumannPZimmererRKokemullerHRuckerMAdditive effect of mesenchymal stem cells and VEGF to vascularization of PLGA scaffoldsMicrovasc Res201390719<?supplied-pmid 23899416?>23899416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR127"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>127.ParkKMGerechtSHarnessing developmental processes for vascular engineering and regenerationDevelopment201414127609<?supplied-pmid 25005471?>25005471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR128"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>128.BroussardKCPowersJGWound dressings: selecting the most appropriate typeAm J Clin Dermatol20131444959<?supplied-pmid 24062083?>24062083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR129"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>129.WasiakJClelandHCampbellFSpinksADressings for superficial and partial thickness burnsCochrane Database Syst Rev20133<?supplied-pmid 23543513?>23543513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR130"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>130.AzizZAbuSFChongNJA systematic review of silver-containing dressings and topical silver agents (used with dressings) for burn woundsBurns20123830718<?supplied-pmid 22030441?>22030441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR131"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>131.NikkhahDGilbertPBoothSDheansaBShould we be using silver based compounds for donor site dressing in thermal burns?Burns20133913245<?supplied-pmid 23611244?>23611244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR132"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="?"><plain>132.AbboudECLegareTBSettleJCBoubekriAMBarilloDJMarcetJEDo silver-based wound dressings reduce pain? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>A prospective study and review of the literatureBurns201440S407<?supplied-pmid 25418437?>25418437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR133"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>133.NavarroFAStonerMLParkCSHuertasJCLeeHBWoodFMSprayed keratinocyte suspensions accelerate epidermal coverage in a porcine microwound modelJ Burn Care Rehab2000215138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR134"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>134.WoodFMKolybabaMLAllenPThe use of cultured epithelial autograft in the treatment of major burn wounds: eleven years of clinical experienceBurns20063253844<?supplied-pmid 16777338?>16777338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR135"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>135.WoodFMKolybabaMLAllenPThe use of cultured epithelial autograft in the treatment of major burn injuries: a critical review of the literatureBurns200632395401<?supplied-pmid 16621307?>16621307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR136"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>136.TenenhausMRennekampffHOSurgical advances in burn and reconstructive plastic surgery: new and emerging technologiesClin Plast Surg20123943543<?supplied-pmid 23036294?>23036294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR137"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>137.TauscheAKSkariaMBohlenLLieboldKHafnerJFriedleinHAn autologous epidermal equivalent tissue-engineered from follicular outer root sheath keratinocytes is as effective as split-thickness skin autograft in recalcitrant vascular leg ulcersWound Repair Regen20031124852<?supplied-pmid 12846911?>12846911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR138"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>138.BissonFRochefortELavoieALaroucheDZanioloKSimard-BissonCIrradiated human dermal fibroblasts are as efficient as mouse fibroblasts as a feeder layer to improve human epidermal cell culture lifespanInt J Mol Sci2013144684704<?supplied-pmid 23443166?>23443166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR139"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>139.IdrusRBRameliMALowKCLawJXChuaKHLatiffMBFull-thickness skin wound healing using autologous keratinocytes and dermal fibroblasts with fibrin: bilayered versus single-layered substituteAdv Skin Wound Care20142717180<?supplied-pmid 24637651?>24637651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR140"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>140.AuxenfansCMenetVCatherineZShipkovHLacroixPBertin-MaghitMCultured autologous keratinocytes in the treatment of large and deep burns: a retrospective study over 15 yearsBurns201541719<?supplied-pmid 24996248?>24996248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR141"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>141.AuxenfansCShipkovHBachCCatherineZLacroixPBertin-MaghitMCultured allogenic keratinocytes for extensive burns: a retrospective study over 15 yearsBurns201440828<?supplied-pmid 23764150?>23764150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR142"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>142.van der VeerWMBloemenMCUlrichMMMolemaGvan ZuijlenPPMiddelkoopEPotential cellular and molecular causes of hypertrophic scar formationBurns2009351529<?supplied-pmid 18952381?>18952381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR143"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>143.LewisCJStem cell application in acute burn care and reconstructionJ Wound Care20132278<?supplied-pmid 23299352?>23299352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR144"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>144.BadiavasEVThe potential of bone marrow cells to orchestrate homeostasis and healing in skinBlood Cells Mol Dis200432213<?supplied-pmid 14757408?>14757408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR145"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>145.BadiavasEVAbediMButmarcJFalangaVQuesenberryPParticipation of bone marrow derived cells in cutaneous wound healingJ Cell Physiol200319624550<?supplied-pmid 12811816?>12811816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR146"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>146.SasakiMAbeRFujitaYAndoSInokumaDShimizuHMesenchymal stem cells are recruited into wounded skin and contribute to wound repair by transdifferentiation into multiple skin cell typeJ Immunol200818025817<?supplied-pmid 18250469?>18250469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR147"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>147.BeyEPratMDuhamelPBenderitterMBrachetMTrompierFEmerging therapy for improving wound repair of severe radiation burns using local bone marrow-derived stem cell administrationsWound Repair Regen201018508<?supplied-pmid 20082681?>20082681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR148"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>148.KimWSParkBSSungJHYangJMParkSBKwakSJWound healing effect of adipose-derived stem cells: a critical role of secretory factors on human dermal fibroblastsJ Dermatol Sci2007481524<?supplied-pmid 17643966?>17643966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR149"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>149.NakagamiHMaedaKMorishitaRIguchiSNishikawaTTakamiYNovel autologous cell therapy in ischemic limb disease through growth factor secretion by cultured adipose tissue-derived stromal cellsArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol20052525427<?supplied-pmid 16224047?>16224047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR150"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>150.KurataSItamiSTerashiHTakayasuSSuccessful transplantation of cultured human outer root sheath cells as epitheliumAnn Plast Surg1994332904<?supplied-pmid 7985965?>7985965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR151"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>151.NavsariaHAOjehNOMoiemenNGriffithsMAFrameJDReepithelialization of a full-thickness burn from stem cells of hair follicles micrografted into a tissue-engineered dermal template (Integra)Plast Reconstruct Surg200411397881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR152"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>152.TrottierVMarceau-FortierGGermainLVincentCFradetteJIFATS collection: using human adipose-derived stem/stromal cells for the production of new skin substitutesStem Cells200826271323<?supplied-pmid 18617689?>18617689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR153"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>153.NatesanSWriceNLBaerDGChristyRJDebrided skin as a source of autologous stem cells for wound repairStem Cells201129121930<?supplied-pmid 21674701?>21674701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR154"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>154.ChanRKZamoraDOWriceNLBaerDGRenzEMChristyRJDevelopment of a vascularized skin construct using adipose-derived stem cells from debrided burned skinStem Cells Int20122012841203<?supplied-pmid 22848228?>22848228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR155"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>155.WilliamsJFKingBTAdenJKSerio-MelvinMChungKKFenrichCAComparison of traditional burn wound mapping with a computerized programJ Burn Care Res201334e2935<?supplied-pmid 23292593?>23292593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR156"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>156.BrownTSSaffordSCaramanicaJElsterEABiomarker use in tailored combat casualty careBiomark Med2010446573<?supplied-pmid 20550480?>20550480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR157"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>157.HawksworthJSStojadinovicAGageFATadakiDKPerduePWForsbergJInflammatory biomarkers in combat wound healingAnn Surg200925010027<?supplied-pmid 19953718?>19953718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR158"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>158.HahmGGlaserJJElsterEABiomarkers to predict wound healing: the future of complex war wound managementPlast Reconstruct Surg201112721S6S </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR159"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>159.ChromyBAEldridgeAForsbergJABrownTSKirkupBCElsterEProteomic sample preparation for blast wound characterizationProteome Sci20141210<?supplied-pmid 24529238?>24529238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR160"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>160.ChromyBAEldridgeAForsbergJABrownTSKirkupBCJaingCWound outcome in combat injuries is associated with a unique set of protein biomarkersJ Transl Med201311281<?supplied-pmid 24192341?>24192341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR161"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>161.ForsbergJAPotterBKPolferEMSaffordSDElsterEADo inflammatory markers portend heterotopic ossification and wound failure in combat wounds?Clin Orthop Relat Res2014472284554<?supplied-pmid 24879568?>24879568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR162"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>162.Mikhal'chikEVPiterskayaJABudkevichLYPen'kovLYFacchianoADe LucaCComparative study of cytokine content in the plasma and wound exudate from children with severe burnsBull Exp Biol Med20091487715<?supplied-pmid 20396789?>20396789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR163"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>163.WidgerowADKingKTussardiITBanyardDAChiangRAwadAThe burn wound exudate – an under-utilized resourceBurns201541117<?supplied-pmid 24986597?>24986597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR164"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>164.PragerMDSabehFBaxterCRAtilesLHartlineBDipeptidyl peptidase IV and aminopeptidase in burn wound exudates: implications for wound healingJ Trauma19943662933<?supplied-pmid 7910639?>7910639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR165"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>165.MauskarNASoodSTravisTEMattSEMinoMJBurnettMSDonor site healing dynamics: molecular, histological, and noninvasive imaging assessment in a porcine modelJ Burn Care Res20133454962<?supplied-pmid 23511287?>23511287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR166"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>166.KaiserMYafiACinatMChoiBDurkinAJNoninvasive assessment of burn wound severity using optical technology: a review of current and future modalitiesBurns20113737786<?supplied-pmid 21185123?>21185123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR167"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>167.ArbabMHDickeyTCWinebrennerDPChenAKleinMBMouradPDTerahertz reflectometry of burn wounds in a rat modelBiomed Opt Express20112233947<?supplied-pmid 21833370?>21833370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR168"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>168.CrossKMLeonardiLGomezMFreisenJRLevasseurMASchattkaBJNoninvasive measurement of edema in partial thickness burn woundsJ Burn Care Res20093080717<?supplied-pmid 19692905?>19692905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR169"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>169.CrossKMLeonardiLPayetteJRGomezMLevasseurMASchattkaBJClinical utilization of near-infrared spectroscopy devices for burn depth assessmentWound Repair Regen20071533240<?supplied-pmid 17537120?>17537120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR170"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>170.NguyenJQCrouzetCMaiTRiolaKUchitelDLiawLHSpatial frequency domain imaging of burn wounds in a preclinical model of graded burn severityJ Biomed Opt20131866010<?supplied-pmid 23764696?>23764696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR171"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>171.SowaMGLeonardiLPayetteJRCrossKMGomezMFishJSClassification of burn injuries using near-infrared spectroscopyJ Biomed Opt200611054002<?supplied-pmid 17092151?>17092151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR172"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>172.SowaMGLeonardiLPayetteJRFishJSMantschHHNear infrared spectroscopic assessment of hemodynamic changes in the early post-burn periodBurns2001272419<?supplied-pmid 11311517?>11311517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR173"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>173.DevganLBhatSAylwardSSpenceRJModalities for the assessment of burn wound depthJ Burns Wounds20065<?supplied-pmid 16921415?>16921415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR174"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>174.PapeSASkourasCAByrnePOAn audit of the use of laser Doppler imaging (LDI) in the assessment of burns of intermediate depthBurns2001272339<?supplied-pmid 11311516?>11311516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR175"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>175.HoeksemaHVan de SijpeKTonduTHamdiMVan LanduytKBlondeelPAccuracy of early burn depth assessment by laser Doppler imaging on different days post burnBurns2009353645<?supplied-pmid 18952377?>18952377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR176"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>176.OgdenCLCarrollMDKitBKFlegalKMPrevalence of childhood and adult obesity in the United States, 2011–2012JAMA201431180614<?supplied-pmid 24570244?>24570244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR177"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>177.GoutosISadideenHPandyaAAGhoshSJObesity and burnsJ Burn Care Res20123347182<?supplied-pmid 22274633?>22274633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR178"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>178.NeamanKCAndresLAMcClureAMBurtonMEKemmeterPRFordRDA new method for estimation of involved BSAs for obese and normal-weight patients with burn injuryJ Burn Care Res2011324218<?supplied-pmid 21562463?>21562463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR179"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>179.LiodakiESenyamanOStollwerckPLMollmeierDMaussKLMailanderPObese patients in a burn care unit: a major challengeBurns201440173842<?supplied-pmid 24986594?>24986594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR180"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>180.KeckMLumentaDBAndelHKamolzLPFreyMBurn treatment in the elderlyBurns20093510719<?supplied-pmid 19520515?>19520515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR181"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>181.LewandowskiRPeggSFortierKSkimmingsABurn injuries in the elderlyBurns1993195135<?supplied-pmid 8292237?>8292237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR182"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>182.HuntJLPurdueGFThe elderly burn patientAm J Surg19921644726<?supplied-pmid 1443371?>1443371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR183"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>183.WilliamsGJHerndonDNModulating the hypermetabolic response to burn injuriesJ Wound Care200211879<?supplied-pmid 11933730?>11933730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR184"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>184.RobertsGLloydMParkerMMartinRPhilpBShelleyOThe Baux score is dead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Long live the Baux score: a 27-year retrospective cohort study of mortality at a regional burns serviceJ Trauma Acute Care Surg2012722516<?supplied-pmid 22310134?>22310134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR185"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>185.NordlundMJPhamTNGibranNSMicronutrients after burn injury: a reviewJ Burn Care Res20143512133<?supplied-pmid 23739487?>23739487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR186"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>186.PintaudiAMTesoriereLD'ArpaND'AmelioLD'ArpaDBongiornoAOxidative stress after moderate to extensive burning in humansFree Radic Res20003313946<?supplied-pmid 10885621?>10885621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR187"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>187.VinhaPPMartinezEZVannucchiHMarchiniJSFarinaJAJrJordaoAAJrEffect of acute thermal injury in status of serum vitamins, inflammatory markers, and oxidative stress markers: preliminary dataJ Burn Care Res201334e8791<?supplied-pmid 23370992?>23370992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR188"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>188.AidaTMurataJAsanoGKandaYYoshinoYEffects of polyprenoic acid on thermal injuryBr J Exp Pathol1987683518<?supplied-pmid 3620330?>3620330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR189"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>189.NickleSBPetersonNPetersonMUpdated physician's guide to the off-label uses of oral isotretinoinJ Clin Aesthet Dermatol201472234<?supplied-pmid 24765227?>24765227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR190"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>190.DematteMFGemperliRSallesAGDolhnikoffMLancasTSaldivaPHMechanical evaluation of the resistance and elastance of post-burn scars after topical treatment with tretinoinClinics201166194954<?supplied-pmid 22086527?>22086527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR191"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>191.SallesAGGemperliRToledoPNFerreiraMCCombined tretinoin and glycolic acid treatment improves mouth opening for postburn patientsAesthet Plast Surg20063035662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR192"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>192.Macias-BarraganJSandoval-RodriguezANavarro-PartidaJArmendariz-BorundaJThe multifaceted role of pirfenidone and its novel targetsFibrogenesis Tissue Repair2010316<?supplied-pmid 20809935?>20809935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR193"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>193.JungKIChoiJSKimHKShinSYEffects of an anti-transforming growth factor-beta agent (pirfenidone) on strabismus surgery in rabbitsCurr Eye Res2012377706<?supplied-pmid 22671031?>22671031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR194"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>194.ZhongHSunGLinXWuKYuMEvaluation of pirfenidone as a new postoperative antiscarring agent in experimental glaucoma surgeryInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci201152313642<?supplied-pmid 21330661?>21330661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR195"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>195.ChowdhurySGuhaRTrivediRKompellaUBKonarAHazraSPirfenidone nanoparticles improve corneal wound healing and prevent scarring following alkali burnPLoS One20138<?supplied-pmid 23940587?>23940587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR196"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>196.CianciPSatoRAdjunctive hyperbaric oxygen therapy in the treatment of thermal burns: a reviewBurns199420514<?supplied-pmid 8148076?>8148076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR197"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>197.CianciPWilliamsCLuedersHLeeHShapiroRSextonJAdjunctive hyperbaric oxygen in the treatment of thermal burns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>An economic analysisJ Burn Care Rehab1990111403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR198"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>198.SelcukCTOzalpBDurgunMTekinAAkkocMFAlabalikUThe effect of hyperbaric oxygen treatment on the healing of burn wounds in nicotinized and nonnicotinized ratsJ Burn Care Res201334e23743<?supplied-pmid 23271059?>23271059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR199"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>199.CianciPSladeJBJrSatoRMFaulknerJAdjunctive hyperbaric oxygen therapy in the treatment of thermal burnsUndersea Hyperb Med20134089108<?supplied-pmid 23397872?>23397872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR200"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>200.EskesAVermeulenHLucasCUbbinkDTHyperbaric oxygen therapy for treating acute surgical and traumatic woundsCochrane Database Syst Rev201312<?supplied-pmid 24343585?>24343585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR201"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="?"><plain>201.EskesAMUbbinkDTLubbersMJLucasCVermeulenHHyperbaric oxygen therapy: solution for difficult to heal acute wounds? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Systematic reviewWorld J Surg20113553542<?supplied-pmid 21184071?>21184071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR202"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>202.WolfSETompkinsRGHerndonDNOn the horizon: research priorities in burns for the next decadeSurg Clin North Am20149491730<?supplied-pmid 25085097?>25085097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
