<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &amp; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4912736</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1624</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1624-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite marker analysis of Haemonchus contortus populations from Pakistan suggests that frequent benzimidazole drug treatment does not result in a reduction of overall genetic diversity </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>Umer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>Kamran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shabbir</surname><given-names>Muhammad Zubair</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>Muhammad Imran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>Shoaib</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gilleard</surname><given-names>John S.</given-names></name><address><email>jsgillea@ucalgary.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Comparative Biology and Experimental Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Calgary Alberta, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Parasitology, University of Veterinary and Animal sciences Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Quality Operations Laboratory, University of Veterinary and Animal Sciences, Lahore, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Pharmacology, University of Veterinary and Animal sciences Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Present Address: Roslin Institute, Royal (Dick) School of Veterinary Studies, University of Edinburgh, Scotland, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>349</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The impact of drug selection pressure on the overall genetic diversity of parasitic nematode populations in the field is poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In this study, we address this issue for the small ruminant parasite Haemonchus contortus in the Punjab, Pakistan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This region provides an opportunity to compare H. contortus populations that have been subjected to a prolonged period of frequent benzimidazole drug treatments on government farms with parasite populations that have been exposed to little or no drug treatment in neighbouring pastoral herds. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Adult H. contortus worms were collected from the abomasa of small ruminants from three government farms frequently using benzimidazole drugs, and closed to animal movement, for over 30 years and also from from eighteen pastoral herds subject to minimal drug selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The frequency of three known benzimidazole resistance associated mutations was determined in each parasite population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>For the seven parasite populations in which resistance mutations were found, the diversity, geographical distribution and phylogenetic relationships of isotype-1 β-tubulin benzimidazole resistance haplotypes were determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In addition, the genetic diversity of the parasite populations on the three government farms were compared with those from four pastoral herds. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The F200Y (TAC) resistance mutation was present at a very high frequency in H. contortus populations from government herds, but not from pastoral herds, consistent with their respective drug selection histories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Population genetic analysis, using a panel of microsatellite markers, revealed that there was little genetic differentiation among the parasite populations with no significant difference in the overall genetic diversity between government and pastoral herds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In addition, sequence analysis of the isotype-1 β-tubulin locus revealed multiple F200Y (TAC) haplotypes demonstrating soft selective sweeps even in government herds with little or no contemporary parasite migration. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The results suggest that, although the frequent drug treatment used on government farms has selected for a high frequency of benzimidazole resistance mutations, there has been little or no reduction in the overall genetic diversity of the selected parasite populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13071-016-1624-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic></kwd><kwd>Helminth</kwd><kwd>β-tubulin</kwd><kwd>Anthelmintic</kwd><kwd>Drug resistance</kwd><kwd>Benzimidazole</kwd><kwd>Albendazole</kwd><kwd>Soft selective sweep</kwd><kwd>Genetic diversity</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000038</institution-id><institution>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>RGPIN/371529-2209</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000268</institution-id><institution>Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BB/E018505/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Anthelmintic resistance in parasitic nematodes is a global threat to sustainable livestock production [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, we still have a limited understanding of how drug selection affects parasite populations and how resistance emerges at the population level. Haemonchus contortus is one of the most economically important helminth parasites of small ruminants worldwide and is an important model for anthelmintic resistance research [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This parasite has developed resistance to all the major anthelmintic drug classes and resistance to multiple drug classes occurs, often at high frequency, in many parts of the world [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Benzimidazole drugs have been used to control livestock parasites for over 40 years and resistance to this drug class is at an advanced stage in many parts of the world [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>We have sufficient knowledge of the molecular basis of resistance for this drug class in order to study the emergence and spread of anthelmintic resistance mutations in field populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Three single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the isotype-1 β-tubulin gene have been associated with benzimidazole resistance in H. contortus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The F200Y (TTC to TAC) mutation has been found in every country examined to date and is often present at high frequency [5–9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>We have recently presented genetic evidence that this mutation independently arises multiple times in a geographical region and spreads between sites by migration [5, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The SNPs at codons F167Y (TTC to TAC) and E198A (GAA to GCA) have also been reported in multiple countries but have a more variable occurrence and are generally present at lower frequency than the F200Y (TTC to TAC) mutation [5–7, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We have recently provided genetic evidence to show that E198A (GCA) mutation present in multiple populations in southern India was derived from a single origin [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>We are investigating the population genetics of benzimidazole resistance in H. contortus in a variety of different countries to provide insights into its origin and spread [5, 6, 10, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Benzimidazole resistance is at an advanced stage in most countries that we, and others, have examined to date due to the widespread use of this drug class over many years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In places such as the United Kingdom (UK), western Europe, Australia and North America most H. contortus populations have moderate to high levels of benzimidazole resistance [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In these countries, most parasite populations have at least one of the resistance-associated mutations at high frequency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We have been seeking locations where we can investigate benzimidazole resistance at an earlier stage of its emergence and Pakistan is a potentially interesting country in this respect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Economic constraints mean that most farmers do not use specific anthelmintic treatment regimes, anthelmintics are often diluted before administration and generic drugs of unknown quality are often used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Consequently, we anticipated that benzimidazole resistance might be at a relatively early stage of emergence in animals from small rural farms or owned for subsistence purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In contrast, government farms tend to use frequent treatments with benzimidazole drugs providing a potentially interesting contrast in the same geographical region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>There are only a few published studies on benzimidazole resistance in Pakistan but there is information to suggest resistance may not yet be widespread [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Fecal egg count reduction tests performed on Beetal goats on eighteen farms in the Faisalabad district of the Punjab showed oxfendazole efficacies of between 80–100 % (over 95 % fecal egg count reduction on eleven on the farms) [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The sequencing of an isotype-1 β-tubulin gene fragment from 95 adult H.contortus worms collected from abattoirs in the Punjab and North West Frontier provinces revealed just a 7.86 % frequency of the F200Y (TAC) mutation [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In the present paper, we show that the F200Y (TAC) benzimidazole resistance mutation is present at very low frequencies in eighteen H. contortus populations sourced from sheep and goats from rural locations in the Punjab Province of Pakistan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In contrast, this mutation is present at very high frequencies in three government farms that have used frequent and regular anthelmintic treatments for over 30 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In spite of this difference in drug selection, population genetic analysis, using a panel of microsatellite markers, revealed no significant difference in the overall genetic diversity between the government and pastoral herds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In addition, phylogenetic analysis of isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes reveals multiple F200Y(TAC) haplotypes are present in H. contortus on the closed government herds suggesting the presence of soft selective sweeps in the absence of significant contemporary parasite migration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Parasite collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Adult H. contortus worms were harvested from the abomasa of eighteen individual ruminant hosts, known to originate from different pastures/villages in the Punjab province of Pakistan in 2012, from abattoirs who source local animals (Fig. 1; Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Adult worms, were also obtained from necropsied animals from three government farms in the Punjab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Five of these H. contortus populations were collected from sheep comprising two from the Lahore abattoir (Pop16S and Pop13S), one from the Sargodha abattoir (Pop24S), one from the Jahangirabad government farm (Pop3S) and one from the Okara government farm (Pop1S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Sixteen of these H. contortus populations were collected from goats comprising six from the Lahore abattoir (Pop5G, Pop7G, Pop6G, Pop4G, Pop8G, Pop10G), three from the Okara abattoir (Pop27G, Pop28G, Pop29G), two from the Sahiwal abattoir (Pop31G, Pop33G), four from the Gujranwala abattoir (Pop17G, Pop19G, Pop20G, Pop21G) and one from the Layyah government farm (Pop2G) (Fig. 1: Additional file 1: Table S1).Fig. 1Relative frequencies of the F200Y (TAC), F167Y (TAC) and E198A (GCA) isotype-1 β-tubulin benzimidazole resistance mutations in H. contortus populations from the Punjab region of Pakistan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Each H. contortus population is represented by three pie charts; one for each resistance mutation; F200Y (TTC/TAC), F167Y (TTC/TAC) and E198A (GAA/GCA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Each of these pie charts shows the relative frequency of the resistant versus susceptible SNP, based on allele quantification by pyrosequence genotyping of pooled DNA from between 14–32 worms per population (Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The resistance-associated SNP genotype frequency - F200Y (TAC) - is shown in white and the “susceptible” SNP genotype frequencies - F200Y (TTC), F167Y (TTC) and E198A (GAA) - are shown in black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Geographic locations of abattoirs are indicated with small circles on the map and the abattoir names from which the samples were obtained are shown above the labelling lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The province is indicated on the map (A) Punjab </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The Layyah government farm (pop2G) was established in 1980 from angora goats sourced from Turkey which were crossed with locally sourced goats of the “hairy breed”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This herd has been treated with anthelmintics (levamisole HCL and oxfendazole) approximately every 3 months since its establishment and has been closed to animal movement since that time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The Okara (Pop1S) and Jahangirabad (Pop3S) government farms were established using local sheep breeds (lohi and kajli) in 1985 and 1989 respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Both these herds have been treated alternately with albendazole and oxfendazole approximately every 3 months since their establishment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>There has been some historical movement of sheep between the Okara and Jahangirabad farms but these herds have otherwise been closed to animal movement since they were established. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA isolation and species confirmation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Adult worms were fixed in 70 % ethanol immediately following removal from the host abomasum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The heads of individual worms were dissected and lysed in single 0.2 μl tubes containing 50 μl of proteinase K lysis buffer and stored at -80 °C as previously described [5, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>One microliter of 1:5 dilution of neat single worm lysate was used as PCR template and identical dilutions of lysate buffer, made in parallel, were used as negative controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>To prepare pooled lysates of each population, 1 μl aliquots of each individual neat adult worm head lysate were pooled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>One microliter of a 1:20 dilution of pooled lysate was used as template for subsequent PCRs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A combination of gross morphological identification and genotyping of the SNP at position 24 of the ITS-2 rDNA was used to confirm the identity of H. contortus in these populations as previously reported [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>A minimum of 14 and a maximum of 32 individual adult H. contortus worms were identified per population (560 H. contortus worms in total). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Individual H. contortus DNA lysates were pooled for each population for isotype-1 β-tubulin genotyping. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Pyrosequence genotyping to determine the relative frequencies of the isotype-1 β-tubulin F200Y(TAC), E198A(GCA) and F167Y(TAC) benzimidazole resistance-associated SNPs in H. contortus populations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>A 328 bp fragment, spanning exons 4 and 5 and intervening intron of the isotype-1 β-tubulin gene was PCR amplified from pooled DNA lysates for each of the 21 H. contortus populations (Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Final PCR conditions were 1X thermopol reaction buffer, 2 mM MgSO4, 100 μM dNTPs, 0.1 μM forward and reverse primers and 1.25U Taq DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Ipswich,USA) and a previously published primer pair was used; forward primer (HcPYRF: 5′-GAC GCA TTC ACT TGG AGG AG-3′) and reverse primer (HcPYRR: 5′-Biotin-CAT AGG TTG GAT TTG TGA GTT-3′) [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The thermo-cycling parameters consisted of an initial 95 °C for 5 min followed by 35 cycles of 95 °C for 1 min, 53 °C for 1 min and 72 °C for 1 min with a single final extension cycle of 72 °C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Following PCR amplification, the relative frequency of the F167Y (TAC), E198A (GCA) and F200Y (TAC) isotype-1 β-tubulin SNPs in the amplicons derived from each parasite population were determined by pyrosequence genotyping using the PryoMark ID system using the allele quantification (AQ) mode (Biotage, Uppsala, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Previously published sequencing primers were used for the F167Y (TAC), E198A (GCA) and F200Y (TAC) mutations; Hcsq167: 5′-ATA GAA TTA TGG CTT CGT-3′, Hcsq198: 5′-ACT GGT AGA GAA CAC CG-3′ and Hcsq200: 5′- TAG AGA ACA CCG ATG AAA CAT-3′, respectively [8, 10, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The base dispensation was set to GATGCTCGT for codon 167, GATGCAGCA for codon 198, and GATGCTGTA for codon 200. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Peak heights were measured using the AQ mode of the PSQ 96 single nucleotide position software as previously described [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cloning and sequencing of an isotype-1 β-tubulin fragment encompassing the F200Y (TAC), E198A (GCA) and F167Y (TAC) mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The same 328 bp isotype-1 β-tubulin fragment described above was also amplified, cloned and sequenced from the pooled lysates from the seven H. contortus populations in which the F200Y (TAC) was detected (Pop24S, Pop1S, Pop27G, Pop2G, Pop3S, Pop5G and Pop13S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Primers HcPYRF: 5′-GAC GCA TTC ACT TGG AGG AG-3′ and HcPYRR: 5′-CAT AGG TTG GAT TTGTGA GTT-3′ were again used but with the following PCR reaction conditions; 5X Phusion HF reaction buffer, 2 mM MgSO4, 200uM dNTPs, 0.2uM forward and reverse primers and 1U of Phusion high fidelity DNA polymerase (Finenzyme inc., Keilaranta, Finland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The thermo-cycling parameters of isotype-1 β-tubulin consisted of an initial 98 °C for 30 s followed by 35 cycles of 98 °C for 10 s, 59 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 1 min with a single final extension cycle of 72 °C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Amplicons were cloned into PJET 1.2/BLUNT vector (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, USA) and sequenced using previously described standard procedures [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Sequences were aligned with the H. contortus isotype-1 β-tubulin sequence (Acc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>No. X67489) and edited using Geneious Pro 5.4 software [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A previously described approach was used to bioinformatically filter the isotype-1 β-tubulin sequences to remove SNPs occurring only once in the dataset and ensure PCR-induced mutations were not included in the analysis [5, 10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic network analysis of H. contortus isotype-1 β-tubulin sequences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Networks based on genetic distance were computed using the neighbour-net method employed in SplitsTree4 [18] to produce circular (equal angle) split networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Median joining networks were generated in Network 4.6.1 software (Fluxus Technology Ltd., Clare, England). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A full median network containing all possible shortest trees was generated by setting the epsilon parameter equal to the greatest weighted distance (epsilon = 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>All unnecessary median vectors and links were removed with the MP (Maximum Parsimony) option [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic network tree of the isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes was reconstructed using maximum likelihood (ML) in MEGA5 [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The program jModeltest 12.2.0 [21] was used to select the appropriate model of nucleotide substitutions for ML analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>According to Bayesian information criterion the best scoring was Hasegawa-Kishino-Yano (HKY + G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The model of substitution was used with parameters estimated from data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Branch supports were obtained by 1,000 bootstraps of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The most probable ancestral node was determined by rooting the networks to a closely related outgroup and Haemonchus placei sequence was used to root the H. contortus network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite genotyping and population genetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Previously described H. contortus microsatellites were screened to produce a panel of eight markers that consistently amplified from the Pakistan populations under study (data not shown) [5, 22, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A summary of primer sequences and allele ranges are given in Additional file 2: Table S2 and the PCR conditions for each marker were as previously described [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The forward primer of each microsatellite primer pair was 5′ end labelled with fluorescent dye (IDT, Canada) and the GeneScan ROX 400 internal size standard was used on the ABI Prism 3100 genetic analyser (Applied Biosystems, Carlesbad, California, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Individual chromatograms were analysed using Gene Mapper software version 4.0 to accurately size the amplicons and determine genotypes (Applied Biosystems, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Fixation index (pairwise FST) values were calculated from the multi-locus microsatellite genotype data, by random permutation in Arlequin 3.11 [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Exact test was used to statistically evaluate deviations from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium for all populations [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Significance levels were adjusted using the sequential method of Bonferroni for multiple comparisons in the same dataset [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>There was a significant departure from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, even after Bonferroni correction, for 10 out of the 56 loci combinations for H. contortus (Additional file 3: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The presence of null alleles for microsatellite loci has been previously reported and is the likely reason for these departures from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium [22, 27–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) was estimated through partition of microsatellite diversity between and within populations [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Log-likelihood ratio test statistic (G-test), used to estimate the linkage disequilibrium analysis, was carried out by Arlequin 3.11 [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Expected and observed heterozygosity (He and Ho), allele richness and estimation of inbreeding coefficient (FIS) for each locus were calculated using Arlequin 3.1 (Additional file 3: Table S3) [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>As the number of alleles and expected heterozygosity are dependent on sample size, in order to compare populations, expected heterozygosity (Hexpc) and allele richness (Ac) were also calculated per locus for each population with correction for unequal sample size using POPTREE2 [31] and MSA 4.05 [32], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Differences in these measures of genetic diversity between populations were tested for statistical significance using a Wilcoxon rank sum test [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The F200Y (TAC) isotype-1 β-tubulin mutation was found at high frequency in H. contortus populations on government farms but only rarely from animals from pastoral locations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A 328 bp fragment of the isotype-1 β-tubulin gene was PCR amplified from 21 H. contortus populations (3 populations from government farms and 18 populations from pastoral locations) and the relative frequencies of the three currently known benzimidazole resistance-associated SNPs F167Y (TAC), E198A (GCA) and F200Y (TAC) was determined by pyrosequence genotyping (using pools of 14 to 32 worms per population; see Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The benzimidazole resistance-associated F200Y (TAC) SNP was found at high frequency (81–100 %) in all three parasite populations from government farms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In contrast, it was not detected in 14 out of the 18 pastoral populations and only detected at low frequency (2–6 %) in the remaining four (Fig. 1 and Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The F167Y (TAC) and E198A (GCA) SNPs were not detected in any of the populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Genetic diversity and population structure of H. contortus populations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A panel of eight microsatellites were used to genotype between 14 and 29 individual worms, from each of the seven populations found to contain benzimidazole resistance alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Three of these populations were from goats (Pop27G, Pop2G and Pop5G) and four from sheep (Pop1S, Pop24S, Pop3S and Pop13S). Haemonchus contortus showed a high level of overall genetic diversity in all populations with a mean number of alleles per locus of 7.250 ± 1.208 (range 2–17) and expected heterozygosity (He) across all loci ranging between 0.646 and 0.707 (Additional file 3: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Correction of these values for unequal sample size allowed the diversity between populations to be compared; overall corrected allelic richness (Ac, mean 5.253 ± 0.276) and expected heterozygosity (Hexpc, range 0.642–0.708). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>There were no statistically significant differences in the overall genetic diversity, as measured by corrected allelic richness or expected heterozygosity, between any of the seven populations (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>There were no major departures from linkage equilibrium for any particular combination of loci across all populations indicating that alleles at these loci were randomly associating and not genetically linked (data not shown).Fig. 2Genetic diversity of the seven H. contortus populations based on microsatellite marker genotyping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The corrected mean allelic richness Ac (Panel a) and mean expected heterzygosity (Hexpc) (Panel b) of the eight microsatellite markers are shown for each population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Error bars indicate the standard error of the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>He and allelic richness were calculated per locus for each population with correction for unequal sample size using POPTREE2 and MSA4.05 [31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The mean He and allelic richness were compared for statistically significant differences between each pairwise combination of populations using a Wilcox rank sum test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>No differences were statistically significant at P = 0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Only 0.003 % of the overall genetic diversity partitioned between populations demonstrating very low genetic sub-structuring of H. contortus between the seven locations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>This was also reflected by the very low pairwise FST estimates with only two out of 21 possible pairwise comparisons showing significant values (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Even in these cases, the FST values were very low; 0.0175 between Pop2G and Pop24S and 0.0145 between Pop2G and Pop13S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>There was also no significant genetic differentiation between the H. contortus populations taken from sheep and goats (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with our previous finding in southern India and supports the view that H. contortus is freely shared between the two hosts with little or no host species barrier.Table 1Pairwise FST values based on genotyping 18 individual worms from each of seven  H. contortus populations with eight microsatellite markersPop1SPop27GPop2GPop24SPop3SPop5GPop27G0.0036Pop2G-0.00890.0059Pop24S-0.00570.0085 0.0175 Pop3S-0.03690.00410.00280.0062Pop5G-0.0209-0.0211-0.0137-0.00660.0167Pop13S-0.0014-0.0511 0.0145 0.00170.0111-0.0119Pairwise comparisons with statistically significant genetic differentiation (P &lt; 0.001) are highlighted in bold and underlined </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Sequence diversity and phylogenetic relationships of H. contortus isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes from government farms and pastoral locations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The 328 bp isotype-1 β-tubulin fragment was PCR amplified, cloned and sequenced from pooled DNA from each of the seven parasite populations in which the F200Y (TAC) resistance mutation was detected; three populations from government farms (Pop1S, Pop2G and Pop3S) and four populations from rural locations (Pop24S, Pop27G, Pop5G and Pop13S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Following bioinformatic filtering (see Methods), a total of 21 different isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes (GenBank accession numbers KR269920–KR269940) were identified in the 89 sequences generated from the seven populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Six out of the twenty one haplotypes encoded the F200Y(TAC) resistance polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Summary statistics of the isotype-1 β-tubulin fragment diversity are shown in Additional file 4: Table S4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A SplitsTree network was constructed with all twenty one isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes to examine their phylogenetic relationships (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The F200Y(TAC) resistance polymorphism was present on haplotypes located in four different parts of the network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Each of these resistance haplotypes were more closely related to one or more susceptible haplotypes than to any of the other resistance haplotypes suggesting they were independently derived. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>A maximum likelihood (ML) tree was also constructed and showed the same phylogenetic relationships (Additional file 5: Figure S2).Fig. 3SplitsTree network of 89 H. contortus isotype-1 β-tubulin sequences from seven populations (Pop24S, Pop1S, Pop27G, Pop2G, Pop3S, Pop5G and Pop13S) generated with the neighbour-net method of SplitsTree4 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The circles in network represent the different haplotypes and the size of the circles is proportional to the frequency in the overall dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The haplotypes containing the different mutations are shaded as follows: susceptible haplotypes containing F200Y (TTC)/F167Y (TTC)/E198A (GAA) are black; P200Y resistant haplotypes containing F200Y (TAC)/F167Y (TTC)/E198A (GAA) are white  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Geographical distribution of F200Y (TAC) isotype-1 β-tubulin benzimidazole resistance haplotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The three parasite populations from government farms (Pop1S, Pop3S and Pop2G) and one of the parasite populations from a pastoral location (Pop27G) each contained multiple resistance haplotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The three remaining parasite populations from rural locations (Pop24S, Pop5G, and Pop13S) contained just a single resistance haplotype (Additional file 6: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>All four parasite populations from rural locations (Pop24S, Pop27S, Pop5S and Pop13S) showed a high degree of susceptible haplotype diversity whereas the three parasite populations from government farms (Pop1S, Pop3S and Pop2G) did not (Additional file 6: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A Median-Joining network was constructed to integrate the phylogenetic relationships and frequencies of the different isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes with geographical information (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The Median-Joining network was largely congruent with the SplitsTree network and maximum likelihood tree with only minor differences (Fig. 3; Additional file 5: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Four of the six resistance haplotypes (Hr22, Hr23, Hr12 and Hr31) were present in multiple parasite populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Resistance haplotypes Hr23 and Hr31 were present in two different government farms (Pop2G/Pop3S and Pop1S/Pop3S respectively) but were not detected in any of the eighteen pastoral populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Resistance haplotype Hr22 was present in all three government farms (Pop1S, Pop3S, and Pop2G) as well as in one pastoral population (Pop24S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Resistance haplotype Hr12 was present in just one government farm (Pop2G) and also in several pastoral populations (Pop13S, Pop27G and Pop5G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The two remaining resistance haplotypes (Hr16 and Hr3) were present at low frequency in just a single pastoral population (Pop27G) (Fig. 4).Fig. 4Median joining network of 89 H. contortus isotype-1 β-tubulin sequences from seven populations (Pop24S, Pop1S, Pop27G, Pop2G, Pop3S, Pop5G and Pop13S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A full median network containing all possible shortest trees was generated by setting the epsilon parameter equal to the greatest weighted distance (epsilon = 10) using Network 4.6.1 (Fluxus Technology Ltd.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>All unnecessary median vectors and links are removed with the MP option [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The size of circle representing each haplotype is proportional its frequency in the overall dataset and the colours in the circles reflect the frequency distribution in each geographical location as indicated on the colour key on the inset map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Small red dots represent median vectors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The number of mutations separating adjacent sequence nodes or median vectors is indicated along connecting branches and the length of the lines connecting haplotypes is proportional to the number of nucleotide changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The most probable ancestral node is determined by rooting the network to a closely related outgroup H. placei (Hp) (GenBank accession number KJ598498.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The text providing the name of each haplotype is colour-coded as follows; susceptible haplotype F200Y (TTC)/F167Y (TTC)/E198A (GAA) is in black text; P200Y resistant haplotype F200Y (TAC)/F167Y (TTC)/E198A (GAA) is in blue text </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In most regions of the world examined to date, benzimidazole resistance is at an advanced stage in H. contortus with at least one of the known resistance mutations being present at a high frequency in most populations [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>It is difficult to disentangle the population genetics of resistance and draw conclusions about its origins and spread in such regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In part, this is because of the difficulty of finding natural field populations that have been subject to minimal drug selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The Punjab region of Pakistan provides an interesting study region in this respect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Small ruminants in pastoral herds in the rural regions of Punjab, Pakistan are rarely treated with effective anthelmintic drugs due to economic and logistical constraints. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>In contrast, small ruminants on government farms are treated very frequently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This provides the interesting situation in which parasite populations that have been subject to intense drug selection pressure over many years are in close geographic proximity to parasite populations that have been subject to little or no drug selection pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>We identified three government herds which were founded from locally derived breeding stock over 30 years ago and have been subsequently closed to animal movement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In the case of the Okara (Pop1S) and Jahangirabad (Pop3S) herds, they were derived exclusively from local breeding stock and, although there has been some limited movement of stock between these two farms, they have been otherwise closed to animal movement since their foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Further, the sheep on these farms have been treated with benzimidazole drugs approximately every three months over the last 30 years with no history of any other drug class being used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The third government farm in Layyah (Pop2G) was originally established from locally derived goats crossed with angora goats imported from Turkey and has also been closed to animal movement since its foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>We have compared these government farms with those the surrounding pastoral herds in order to investigate the effects of benzimidazole selection on the genetic diversity of H. contortus populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>As expected from the known patterns of drug use, we found that the F200Y (TAC) resistance mutation was present at high frequencies on all three government farms but was absent, or present a very low frequency, in all the pastoral parasite populations sampled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This study thus provides further clear evidence associating the F200Y (TAC) mutation with benzimidazole resistance in H. contortus; the only three farms out of the 21 examined which had a history of intensive benzimidazole use are also the only ones with a high frequency of this mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that the F167Y (TAC) and E198A (GCA) mutations were not detected in any of the H. contortus populations, including the three government farms subject to intense benzimidazole selection pressure over many years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous studies from different regions the world that have shown the F200Y (TAC) mutation to be essentially ubiquitous in drug selected populations whereas the other two mutations occur more sporadically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>For example, in our recent work in southern India the F167Y (TAC) mutation was apparently absent and the E198A (GCA) mutation, although present at multiple locations, appears to have been derived from a single origin in the region [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In the study reported here, the F200Y (TAC) mutation was present on multiple haplotypes on each of the government farms; Hr12/Hr22/Hr23 for Layyah (Pop2G), Hr22/Hr31/Hr23 for Jahangirabad (Pop3S) and HR22/Hr31 for Okara (Pop1S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These resistance haplotypes are phylogenetically distant to each other in the haplotype network, being more closely related to one or more susceptible haplotypes than to any of the other resistant haplotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>This suggests that they were derived from independent origins with the possible exception of haplotypes Hr22 and Hr31 since these are more closely related (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Overall, these new data from Pakistan provide further support for the hypothesis that F200Y (TAC) mutations occur commonly and repeatedly whereas the F167Y (TAC) and E198A (GCA) mutations are much rarer, possibly due to differences in fitness costs between the different mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of the F200Y (TAC) mutations on multiple divergent haplotypes on each government farm suggests that a soft selective sweep has occurred at the isotype-1 β-tubulin locus in each population (Fig. 4 and Additional file 6: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Previous work has demonstrated that soft selective sweeps can occur at the isotype-1 β-tubulin locus in both H. contortus and Teladorsagia circumcincta [5, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>However, these previous studies in the UK and India, were in situations where animal movement was high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Consequently, in those cases the resistance haplotype diversity found at each location could have been due, at least in part, to the migration of resistance haplotypes between farms [5, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>However, the government farms in this study have been closed to animal movement for over 30 years and so the soft selective sweeps must have occurred in the absence of significant contemporary migration of resistance alleles between farms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>A variety of studies suggest that laboratory strains of H. contortus generally retain high levels of genetic diversity, even if subject to drug selection [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, there is little information on the impact of anthelmintic drug selection on the overall genetic diversity of parasite populations in the field [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A comparison of parasite populations on closed government farms in the Punjab, Pakistan, which have a history of frequent benzimidazole drug treatment, with those from neighbouring pastoral herds, that have been subject to little or no drug treatment, provides a valuable opportunity to explore this question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We used a panel of eight previously characterised microsatellite markers to compare the genetic diversity of H. contortus populations from three government farms with those from four pastoral herds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>There was a high level of allelic polymorphism for all of the microsatellite markers in all seven populations consistent with the high level of genetic diversity expected for this parasite [5, 29, 35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The parasite populations on the three government farms had a similarly high level of genetic diversity as those from the pastoral herds (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Indeed, there was no statistically significant difference in the overall level of genetic diversity, as measured by microsatellite marker polymorphism, between any of the populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that frequent benzimidazole use over the last 30 years on the three government farms has not resulted in an overall reduction in genetic diversity of the parasite populations despite the loss of virtually all susceptible isotype-1 β- tubulin haplotypes on these three farms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>There was also very low population sub-structuring among the seven parasite populations with the pairwise microsatellite Fst values being non-significant between the government farms (Table 1 and Additional file 3: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This suggests there has been little population bottlenecking or genetic drift, even for those parasite populations under intensive drug selection and closed to contemporary gene flow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>This is likely due to the very large effective population sizes of this parasite species maintaining high genetic diversity [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>One important implication of these results is that genetic changes associated with drug selection, such as loss of polymorphism and linkage disequilibrium, are likely to be largely confined to the regions of the genome surrounding the loci under selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Although further work, using larger numbers of genome-wide markers, is needed to confirm this hypothesis, it bodes well for the use of genome-wide scans to identify genetic loci underlying anthelmintic drug resistance for this and related parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The F200Y(TAC) benzimidazole resistance mutation was present at very high frequencies in H. contortus populations from three government farms, but not from eighteen pastoral herds, in the Punjab region of Pakistan, consistent with known differences in drug treatment history. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Multiple F200Y(TAC) haplotypes were present in H. contortus populations from each of the “closed” government herds suggesting soft selective sweeps have occurred even in the absence of significant contemporary parasite migration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The selection for a high frequency of benzimidazole resistance alleles on government farms did not lead to a loss in overall genetic diversity, based on microsatellite marker genotyping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This observation has a number of important implications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the retention of high genetic diversity in drug resistance parasite populations suggests they are likely to retain adaptive capacity to other selective pressures including treatment with other drug classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Secondly, genetic changes associated with drug selection, such as loss of polymorphism and linkage disequilibrium, may be largely confined to the regions of the genome surrounding the loci under selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec16"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Allele frequency (%) of non-synonymous SNPs in isotype-1 β-tubulins from 21 H. contortus populations across the Punjab province in Pakistan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 19 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM2_ESM.docx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2: Table S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Summary of panel of microsatellites used for population genetics analysis of H. contortus (DOCX 17 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM3_ESM.docx" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3: Table S3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Population genetic data for each microsatellite marker from seven populations of H. contortus based on the panel of eight microsatellite loci (DOCX 23 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4: Table S4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Summary statistics of the isotype-1 β-tubulin fragment diversity (XLSX 9 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM5_ESM.tif" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5: Figure S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Maximum likelihood tree of isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes cloned and sequenced from the seven H. contortus populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>(TIF 575 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2016_1624_MOESM6_ESM.tif" id="MOESM6"><label>Additional file 6: Figure S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Histograms showing frequencies of the resistant and susceptible isotype-1 β-tubulin haplotypes from seven H. contortus parasite populations (TIF 831 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to the Vice Chancellor (Prof. Dr. Talat Naseer Pasha) of the University of Veterinary and Animal Science Lahore Pakistan for his support in supplying parasite material.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>We would like to thank Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) (Grant number RGPIN/371529-2209), NSERC-CREATE Host Pathogen Interactions (HPI) graduate training program at the University of Calgary as well as the BBSRC for funding support (Grant number BB/E018505/1).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All sequence data are publicly available: GenBank accession numbers KR269920–KR269940.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>Dr JG directed the project, coordinated and managed the study and co-wrote the manuscript. Dr UNC performed the laboratory work, analysed the data and co-wrote the manuscript. Dr ER assisted with the microsatellite genotyping and the data analysis. Field samples (adult worms) were collected from the abomasum of ruminants from different abattoirs by Dr KA, Dr SA, Dr MIR and Dr MZS (University of Veterinary and Animal Sciences, Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan). All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>1.KaplanRMDrug resistance in nematodes of veterinary importance: a status reportTrends Parasitol2004201047748110.1016/j.pt.2004.08.001<?supplied-pmid 15363441?>15363441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>2.GilleardJSHaemonchus contortus as a paradigm and model to study anthelmintic drug resistanceParasitology2013140121506152210.1017/S0031182013001145<?supplied-pmid 23998513?>23998513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>3.WallerPJAnthelmintic resistanceVet Parasitol1997723–439140510.1016/S0304-4017(97)00107-6<?supplied-pmid 9460208?>9460208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>4.McKellarQAJacksonFVeterinary anthelmintics: old and newTrends Parasitol2004201045646110.1016/j.pt.2004.08.002<?supplied-pmid 15363438?>15363438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>5.RedmanEWhitelawFTaitABurgessCBartleyYSkucePJacksonFGilleardJThe emergence of resistance to the benzimidazole anthlemintics in parasitic nematodes of livestock is characterised by multiple independent hard and soft selective sweepsPLoS Negl Trop Dis201592e000349410.1371/journal.pntd.0003494<?supplied-pmid 25658086?>25658086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>6.ChaudhryUGilleardJMolecular analysis of benzimidazole resistance in Haemonchus contortus and Haemonchus placei2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>7.BrasilBSNunesRLBastianettoEDrummondMGCarvalhoDCLeiteRCMolentoMBOliveiraDAGenetic diversity patterns of Haemonchus placei and Haemonchus contortus populations isolated from domestic ruminants in BrazilInt J Parasitol201242546947910.1016/j.ijpara.2012.03.003<?supplied-pmid 22787588?>22787588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>8.HoglundJGustafssonKLjungstromBLEngstromADonnanASkucePAnthelmintic resistance in Swedish sheep flocks based on a comparison of the results from the faecal egg count reduction test and resistant allele frequencies of the beta-tubulin geneVet Parasitol20091611–2606810.1016/j.vetpar.2008.12.001<?supplied-pmid 19155135?>19155135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>9.SilvestreAHumbertJFDiversity of benzimidazole-resistance alleles in populations of small ruminant parasitesInt J Parasitol200232792192810.1016/S0020-7519(02)00032-2<?supplied-pmid 12062563?>12062563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>10.ChaudhryURedmanEMRamanMGilleardJSGenetic evidence for the spread of a benzimidazole resistance mutation across southern India from a single origin in the parasitic nematode Haemonchus contortusInt J Parasitol20154511721810.1016/j.ijpara.2015.04.007<?supplied-pmid 26099649?>26099649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>11.Barrère V, Alvarez L, Suarez G, Ceballos L, Moreno L, Lanusse C, RK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Relationship between increased albendazole systemic exposure and changes in single nucleotide polymorphisms on the β-tubulin isotype 1 encoding gene in Haemonchus contortus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Vet Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>2012;186(3–4):344–9. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>12.Chaudhry U, Miller M, Yazwinski T, Kaplan R, Gilleard J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The presence of benzimidazole resistance mutations in Haemonchus placei of US cattle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Vet Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>2014;204(3-4):411-5. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>13.SaeedMIqbalZJabbarAMasoodSBabarWSaddiqiHAYaseenMSarwarMArshadMMultiple anthelmintic resistance and the possible contributory factors in Beetal goats in an irrigated area (Pakistan)Res Vet Sci201088226727210.1016/j.rvsc.2009.08.004<?supplied-pmid 19733870?>19733870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>14.HussainTPeriasamyKNadeemAEllahi BabarMPichlerRDialloASympatric species distribution, genetic diversity and population structure of Haemonchus isolates from domestic ruminants in PakistanVet Parasitol20142063–418819910.1016/j.vetpar.2014.10.026<?supplied-pmid 25468018?>25468018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>15.ChaudhryURedmanEAbbasMMuthusamyRAshrafKGilleardJGenetic evidence for hybridisation between Haemonchus contortus and Haemonchus placei in natural field populations and its implications for interspecies transmission of anthelmintic resistanceInt J Parasitol2015452–314915910.1016/j.ijpara.2014.09.002<?supplied-pmid 25449043?>25449043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>16.von Samson-HimmelstjernaGWalshTKDonnanAACarriereSJacksonFSkucePJRohnKWolstenholmeAJMolecular detection of benzimidazole resistance in Haemonchus contortus using real-time PCR and pyrosequencingParasitology2009136334935810.1017/S003118200800543X19154653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>17.Drummond AJABBuxtonSCheungMCooperADuranCFieldMHeledJKearseMMarkowitzSMoirRStones-HavasSSturrockSThiererTWilsonAGeneious v5.62012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>18.HusonDHBryantDApplication of phylogenetic networks in evolutionary studiesMol Biol Evol200623225426710.1093/molbev/msj030<?supplied-pmid 16221896?>16221896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>19.PolzinTDaneschmandSVOn Steiner trees and minimum spanning trees in hypergraphsOper Res Lett200331122010.1016/S0167-6377(02)00185-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>20.TamuraKPetersonDPetersonNStecherGNeiMKumarSMEGA5:Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony MethodsMol Biol Evol201128102731273910.1093/molbev/msr121<?supplied-pmid 21546353?>21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>21.PosadaDJModelTest: phylogenetic model averagingMol Biol Evol2008251253125610.1093/molbev/msn083<?supplied-pmid 18397919?>18397919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>22.RedmanEPackardEGrilloVSmithJJacksonFGilleardJSMicrosatellite analysis reveals marked genetic differentiation between Haemonchus contortus laboratory isolates and provides a rapid system of genetic fingerprintingInt J Parasitol200838111112210.1016/j.ijpara.2007.06.008<?supplied-pmid 17727857?>17727857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>23.OtsenMPlasMEGroeneveldJRoosMHLenstraJAHoekstraRGenetic markers for the parasitic nematode Haemonchus contortus based on intron sequencesExp Parasitol200095322622910.1006/expr.2000.4532<?supplied-pmid 10964652?>10964652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>24.ExcoffierLLavalGSchneiderSArlequin (version 3.0): an integrated software package for population genetics data analysisEvol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics Online200514750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>25.GuoSWThompsonEAPerforming the exact test of Hardy-Weinberg proportion for multiple allelesBiometrics199248236137210.2307/2532296<?supplied-pmid 1637966?>1637966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>26.RiceWAnalyzing tables of statistical testsEvolution19894322322510.2307/2409177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>27.GrilloVJacksonFCabaretJGilleardJSPopulation genetic analysis of the ovine parasitic nematode Teladorsagia circumcincta and evidence for a cryptic speciesInt J Parasitol2007373–443544710.1016/j.ijpara.2006.11.014<?supplied-pmid 17234192?>17234192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>28.HuntPWKnoxMRLe JambreLFMcNallyJAndersonLJGenetic and phenotypic differences between isolates of Haemonchus contortus in AustraliaInt J Parasitol2008388–988590010.1016/j.ijpara.2007.11.001<?supplied-pmid 18068173?>18068173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>29.SilvestreASauveCCortetJCabaretJContrasting genetic structures of two parasitic nematodes, determined on the basis of neutral microsatellite markers and selected anthelmintic resistance markersMol Ecol200918245086510010.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04421.x<?supplied-pmid 19900171?>19900171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>30.ExcoffierLSmousePEQuattroJMAnalysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes: application to human mitochondrial DNA restriction dataGenetics19921312479491<?supplied-pmid 1644282?>1644282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>31.TakezakiNNeiMTamuraKPOPTREE2: Software for constructing population trees from allele frequency data and computing other population statistics with Windows interfaceMol Biol Evol201027474775210.1093/molbev/msp312<?supplied-pmid 20022889?>20022889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>32.DieringerDSchlöttererCMicrosatellite analyser (MSA): a platform independent analysis tool for large microsatellite data setsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Notes20033116716910.1046/j.1471-8286.2003.00351.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>33.WilcoxonFIndividual comparisons by ranking methodsBiometrics19451808310.2307/3001968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>34.Gilleard JS, Redman E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Genetic diversity and population structure of Haemonchus contortus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Adv Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>2016;93:31-68 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>35.BlouinMSYowellCACourtneyCHDameJBHost movement and the genetic structure of populations of parasitic nematodesGenetics1995141310071014<?supplied-pmid 8582607?>8582607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
