<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Neuroinflammation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1742-2094</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4574349</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26376776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">399</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-015-0399-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Early pro-inflammatory cytokine elevations in the DBA/2J mouse model of glaucoma </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Gina N.</given-names></name><address><email>gwilso12@kent.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inman</surname><given-names>Denise M.</given-names></name><address><email>dinman@neomed.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Denger-Crish</surname><given-names>Christine M.</given-names></name><address><email>ccrish@neomed.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Matthew A.</given-names></name><address><email>msmith13@neomed.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Crish</surname><given-names>Samuel D.</given-names></name><address><email>scrish@neomed.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Northeast Ohio Medical University, 4209 State Route 44, Rootstown, OH 44272 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Biomedical Sciences Graduate Program, Kent State University, 800 E. Summit Street, Kent, OH 44240 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Integrated Pharmaceutical Medicine Graduate Program, Northeast Ohio Medical University, 4209 State Route 44, Rootstown, OH 44272 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>176</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Wilson et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Neuroinflammation—astrogliosis, microglial activation, and changes in cytokine signaling—is a prominent feature of neurodegenerative disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Glaucoma is a group of chronic neurodegenerative conditions that make up the leading cause of irreversible blindness worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Neuroinflammation has been postulated to play a significant role in the pathogenesis and progression of glaucomatous neurodegeneration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Though much is known regarding inflammation in the eye in glaucoma, little is known about cytokine activity outside of the retina where pathologies develop early. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We traced the primary visual projection from the eye to the superior colliculus (SC) in DBA/2J and DBA/2J.Gpnmb+ (control) mice using the anterograde tracer cholera toxin-B (CTB) to assay axonal transport deficits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Forty-eight hours later, visual structures were microdissected from fresh tissue based on transport outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Using magnetic bead multiplexing assays, we measured levels of 20 cytokines in the retina, proximal and distal optic nerves, CTB-positive and negative SC subdivisions, cerebellum, and serum at different ages representing different stages of pathology. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokine levels in mice often changed in the same direction based on strain, age, and tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Significant elevations in retinal pro-inflammatory cytokines were observed in young DBA/2J mice compared to controls, followed by an age-dependent decrease in the DBA/2J mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Proximal optic nerve of young DBA/2J mice showed a 50 % or greater decrease in levels of certain cytokines compared to older DBA/2J cohorts and controls, while both proximal and distal optic nerve of DBA/2Js showed elevations in IL-1β at all ages compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-6 levels varied in accordance with transport outcome in the SC: IL-6 was elevated 44–80 % in glaucomatous DBA/2J collicular regions deficient in anterograde transport from retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) compared to areas with intact transport. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Dysregulation of cytokine signaling in the RGC projection of DBA/2J mice was evident early in distal retinal targets, well before intraocular pressure elevation or axonal degeneration begins. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cytokines</kwd><kwd>Glaucoma</kwd><kwd>Inflammation</kwd><kwd>Intraocular pressure</kwd><kwd>Aging</kwd><kwd>Neurodegeneration</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Defects in axonal transport have been reported among the earliest pathologies in many neurodegenerative disorders [1, 2], including glaucoma [3–6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Anterograde transport deficits have been found to precede retrograde deficits and overt structural degeneration of retinal ganglion cell (RGC) axons [7], indicating that an intact and semi-functional axon persists after initial onset of pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, astrogliosis occurs in the superior colliculus (SC) after transport deficits but before axon loss [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Given the early appearances of axon transport deficits and neuroinflammation, obvious questions concern the relationship between these two processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>While much has been reported on inflammation in the retina and optic nerve head, details of immune dysfunction such as changes in cytokine levels have not been examined further along the retinal projection—an area where we first see transport deficits and degeneration [4, 9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Glaucomatous neurodegeneration is predicted to afflict nearly 80 million people worldwide by the year 2020 [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Age and elevated intraocular pressure (IOP) are major risk factors for glaucoma, with IOP currently comprising the only target of FDA-approved drug treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, what actually blinds in the disease is the dysfunction and degeneration of RGCs [12, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Also, given the common incidence of elevated IOP without glaucomatous vision loss as well as normal tension glaucoma, it is clear that many other factors play a role in the development and progression of this degenerative disease [14–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Abnormal activation of the immune system has been shown to produce glaucomatous pathology in the absence of elevated IOP [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Bosco and colleagues have shown microglial activation within young DBA/2J mouse retina, pre-laminar optic nerve, and nerve head [17, 18], which suggests a role for immunomodulatory molecules such as cytokines early in pathology in moderately elevated IOP contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>At the other extreme, models of high IOP and nerve crush have also demonstrated some reliance on immunomodulation for either protection [19] or propagation of damage [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Cytokine activity is thought to play a substantial part in anterior chamber changes that can result in elevated IOP [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, increased IL-18 within anterior chamber structures has been evident even in young DBA/2J mice before they exhibit elevated IOP [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Additionally, increases in IL-6-type cytokines and members of the JAK-STAT (Janus kinase signal transducer and activator of transcription) signaling pathway were shown in early pressure-induced optic nerve head (ONH) injury [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Microglial release of IL-6 in mixed cultures of RGCs, microglia, and astrocytes in response to hydrostatic pressure illustrates an important link between cytokine levels and risk factors for developing glaucoma [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Upregulation of genes associated with immune responses (e.g., Edn2) have been localized to the retina and ONH of DBA/2J mice very early on in this disease model, and therapeutic attempts to block these responses have shown promise in ameliorating glaucomatous pathology [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Previous characterizations of cytokine levels in the context of glaucoma and related stressors, however, being primarily isolated to portions of the anterior chamber or retina, fail to tell the entire story regarding inflammatory signaling in glaucomatous neurodegeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Observations of microglial status within the proximal portion of the RGC projection, in conjunction with cytokine measurements in the eye, suggest that inflammatory signaling may be an early and ubiquitous dysfunction that appears prior to clinically diagnosable vision loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it would be beneficial to assess cytokine levels throughout the entire RGC projection, especially given the observation of anterograde transport deficits and distal axonopathy in glaucoma [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, elucidating any relationship between cytokine levels and axonal transport outcome to the SC is important in moving towards a clinically relevant means of preventing, halting, or treating the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>If changes in cytokine signaling do occur within the RGC projection prior to transport loss and RGC death, such findings could open the door for potential therapies that focus on restoring and maintaining function rather than replacing lost structure or treating risk factors, such as IOP, in lieu of the actual mechanisms that drive vision loss. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Mixed-sex DBA/2J (n = 32; 10–12 per age group) and DBA/2J-Gpnmb+ (n = 14; 6–8 per group) mice of different ages were used for these studies (refer to Table 1 for specific group nomenclature and group n values). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The DBA/2J mouse has two loss of function mutations that produce iris atrophy resulting in age-related elevation of IOP and progressive degeneration of visual structures that mimic human glaucoma [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>DBA/2J-Gpnmb+ mice (D2G) have the same background as DBA/2J mice; however, they express a functioning wild-type Gpnmb+ allele that prevents them from developing elevated IOP or glaucomatous pathology [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>All animals were originally obtained from The Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA) and were then housed and aged in the Comparative Medicine Unit at Northeast Ohio Medical University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>As the DBA/2J model has shown pathological variability in the literature, we based our age groups for comparison on previous work published by ours and other lab groups [4, 7, 8, 28] and included the following: 3–5-month-old mice (D3–5) representing pre-glaucomatous ages, 8–10-month-old mice (D8–10) representing early glaucomatous pathology where anterograde transport deficits and mild axonopathy are evident, and 12–15-month-old mice (D12–15) representing increasing transport deficits and axonopathy characteristic of late glaucomatous pathology [4, 7, 8, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For controls, we used 3–5-month- and 12–15-old D2G mice to represent ages targeted for pre-glaucomatous and late glaucomatous time points (G3–5 and G12–15, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Staging of glaucomatous mice was based on previous work from our lab as well as others (refer to [4, 7, 28]) and was based on the loss of anterograde and retrograde transport and eventual RGC loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We examined all retinas before tissue preparation to determine that our tracer injections succeeded and we did not see large-scale loss of RGCs or diminished uptake of CTB (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>All mice were maintained in the same housing unit under a 12-h light/dark cycle with standard rodent chow available ad libitum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All experimental procedures were approved by the Northeast Ohio Medical University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.Fig. 1Coverage of cholera toxin-B (CTB) transport in the superior colliculus (SC). a–c Whole mount brain (cortex removed) of three mice demonstrating varying degrees of anterograde transport to major retinal targets that include lateral geniculate nucleus (LGN), pretectum (PT), and SC. a Colliculi taken from a 12-month-old D2G control mouse show intact axonal transport with full CTB coverage in both right and left SC. b Colliculi taken from a 14-month-old DBA/2J mouse show compromised transport; left SC has 56 % CTB coverage, right SC has 18 % CTB coverage. c Colliculi taken from 12-month-old DBA/2J mouse demonstrate both complete CTB dropout (left SC, 0 % CTB) and complete CTB coverage (right SC, 100 % CTB). Dotted lines indicate delineation used for microdissections of CTB-negative (i.e., transport absent) areas. d, e Whole mount retinas with successful CTB uptake via intravitreal injection. f Whole mount SC with areas of transport loss, corresponding to retinas in d and e. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Retinal images (d, e) provide evidence that lack of CTB in SC is not indicative of failed intravitreal injection or lack of CTB uptake </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Intravitreal injection of CTB </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Animals were anesthetized with 2.5 % isoflurane and placed prone in a stereotaxic device (Stoelting, Wood Dale, IL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Cholera toxin B-subunit conjugated to Alexa Fluor 488 (CTB) was injected into both eyes intravitreally (1.5 μl of 0.1 % CTB in sterile phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) per eye; Life Technologies: Grand Island, NY) using a 33-gauge needle attached to a 25 μl Hamilton syringe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Forty-eight hours later, animals were sacrificed by decapitation under 2.5 % isoflurane anesthesia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Microdissection and tissue collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Retina, ONs, SC, and cerebellum (as a non-glaucomatous control tissue) were collected and immediately frozen on dry ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Whole blood samples were collected in tubes containing 500 mM EDTA on wet ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>ONs were bisected for analysis of the proximal portion (pON) and distal portion (dON) separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Whole-mount SC were imaged using a Zeiss AxioZoom V16 epifluorescent microscope equipped with a digital high-resolution camera (AxioCam MRm Rev.3; Zeiss, Jena, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Under ×16.2 magnification, SC were microdissected into “transport intact” (i.e., “CTB-positive”) and “transport absent” (i.e., “CTB-negative”) samples which were analyzed separately in order to parse the relationship between transport outcome and protein levels (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Retinas were flattened and examined to determine success of the tracer injection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Whole blood samples were centrifuged at 2000×g for 10 min at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Supernatants were collected and centrifuged for 10 min at 10,000×g and 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Final supernatant was used for serum analyses as a control for global changes in inflammatory markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Samples were stored at −80 °C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Tissue processing and multiplex procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Tissue samples were rinsed with cold PBS to remove residual blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Samples were homogenized via sonication (10 % amplitude for two 2-s pulses) approximately 200 μl of 0.1 % Igepal Ca-630 detergent dissolved in PBS with protease inhibitor cocktail (1× Halt Cocktail; Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA) and centrifuged at 1000×g for 10 min after which supernatants were collected for further analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We obtained 150–230 μg of protein from each half of the optic nerve and greater than 500 μg protein each from the retina and SC samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>These amounts were sufficient to perform our bead-based multiplex assays, so samples were not pooled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Multiplex assays were conducted in flat-bottom 96-well plates according to manufacturer’s instructions using reagents provided with the kit (Invitrogen Mouse 20-plex Cytokine Panel, Cat# LMC0006M; Life Technologies: Grand Island NY, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In brief, 50 μl of antibody-coupled bead solution was pipetted into each well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Samples were diluted 1:4 in assay diluent to a total volume of 100 μl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>One hundred microliters of reconstituted standard was serially diluted (1:3) and added to appropriate wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Fifty microliters of Igepal buffer diluted in 50 μl assay buffer was used as a blank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Finally, 50 μl of incubation buffer was added to all wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Plates were kept light-protected during an overnight incubation (4 °C, 16–18 h) on a titer plate shaker at 600 rpm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Following sample incubation, plates were washed with a mild detergent solution using a magnetic 96-well separator three times (1 min per wash). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>One hundred microliters of horseradish peroxidase-conjugated detection antibody was added to each well and incubated at RT for 1 h (shaking at 600 rpm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Plates were washed three times and 100 μl of streptavidin-rpe was added to each well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>After the 30-min streptavidin-rpe incubation, plates were again washed three times followed by a final addition of 125 μl wash solution to all wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>After 3 min of vigorous shaking, plates were read on a Luminex Magpix unit (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA) and initial analyses were performed by Xponent software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Results were exported into Microsoft Excel for further processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Sample size was set to 50 μl, and minimum count was set to 100 events/bead region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Bicinchoninic acid assays for total protein concentration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of each tissue homogenate was diluted 1:10 in phosphate buffer, and total protein content was assessed in tissue samples using bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay, following manufacturer’s instructions (Cat# 23225, Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Cytokine levels were all normalized to total protein concentration by dividing cytokine concentration (pg/ml) by total protein (μg/ml) within each tissue extract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Samples were not pooled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>FGF-2 immunofluorescence and microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Whole mount retina and retinal cross sections from representative animals in each age group, traced with CTB, were assayed for fibroblast growth factor (FGF)-2 localization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Since FGF-2 is present at higher levels than most other cytokines, and it showed specific differences between groups in multiplex analyses, it was chosen for immunostaining to determine if multiplex differences could be supported by histology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Tissue was collected from animals given a lethal dose of sodium pentobarbital (120 mg/kg, ip.) and transcardially perfused with 4 % paraformaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The eyes were enucleated and postfixed for 2 h, and then the tissue was placed in a 20 % sucrose cryoprotectant solution (%w/v in PBS) prior to dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Retina designated for cross-sectioning were embedded in gelatin, and 10-μm sections were taken on a cryostat. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Whole retina were assayed as free-floating sections while cross sections were assayed on slide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The tissues were blocked with a 5 % normal donkey serum and 1 % Triton-X 100 in PBS for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Then, the tissues were incubated for 48 h at 4 °C in the following primary antibody cocktail (diluted in 3 % serum, 1 % Triton in PBS): rabbit polyclonal anti-FGF-2 (1:200, Santa Cruz, SC-7911; Dallas, TX) and mouse monoclonal anti-GFAP (1:500, Millipore, MAB360; Billerica, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Following three 10-min washes with PBS, secondary antibody cocktail was added for 2 h at room temperature, which contained donkey anti-rabbit Alexafluor 594 (1:250, Jackson Laboratories, 711-586-152; West Grove, PA) and donkey anti-mouse Alexafluor 647 (1:250, Invitrogen, A-31571; Grand Island, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The tissue was then rinsed three times with PBS and mounted and coverslipped with Fluoromount-G (Southern Biotech, Birmingham, AL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Retinas were photographed with a Zeiss Axio Imager M2 epifluorescent microscope equipped with a digital high-resolution camera (AxioCam MRm Rev.3; Zeiss, Jena Germany) and a computer-guided motorized X-Y stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>An apotome module (Zeiss Apotome.2) was used to collect z-stack of images using structured illumination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Data from XPonent and Excel were imported into IBM SPSS for Windows 22.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) for statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Multicolinearity between variables was observed, necessitating the use of univariate analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In order to compare relationships between the different cytokines and minimize the skewed distributions, a log10(x + 1) transformation was used to normalize data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Results are reported as mean log (cytokine concentration + 1) ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The log10(x + 1) was chosen to minimize negative skewedness that would arise due to values between 0 and 1 [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Except in the case of distal optic nerve, few differences between cytokine levels in young and old control D2G mice were observed by two-tailed, independent samples t tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to simplify analysis and result presentation, data from these mice were combined into one D2G control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In cases where age-dependent effects were indicated for young and old D2G controls, these data are either shown graphically or noted within the results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>One-way analyses of variance (ANOVAs) were used to test for differences in cytokine levels among groups of mice categorized by age and strain [D2G, D3–5, D8–10, D12–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Tukey’s honestly significant difference (HSD) post hoc measures were used to identify specific differences between age and strain groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Separate analyses were performed for each brain structure (retina, pON, dON, SC, cerebellum) and serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Due to multiple differences observed in dON between G3–5 and G12–15 mice via t tests, subsequent post hoc comparisons separated G3–5 and G12–15 groups for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Cytokines included in analyses were FGF-2, interleukin-1β (IL-1β), interleukin-1α (IL-1α), interleukin-10 (IL-10), interleukin-13 (IL-13), interleukin-6 (IL-6), interleukin-12 (IL-12), interleukin (IL-17), macrophage inflammatory protein-1α (MIP-1α), interleukin-5 (IL-5), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleukin-2 (IL-2), interleukin-4 (IL-4), monokine induced by interferon-γ (MIG), monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), keratinocyte chemoattractant (KC), and interferon-γ (IFN-γ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>For subdivisions of SC based on transport outcome, ANOVAs were run comparing “CTB-positive” and “CTB-negative” tissue for the relevant age/strain groups (as anticipated, D3-5 and D2G animals did not have CTB-negative variables due to intact transport). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>For purposes of clarity, graphical representations usually include only those cytokines that showed significant differences between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>GM-CSF and IP-10 were eliminated from statistical analyses due to inconsistent values within and between groups and low number of structures registering readable levels of these cytokines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Pearson product-moment correlation coefficients were computed to assess the relationship between individual cytokine levels in the retina and SC for each strain and age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Alpha for all tests was set at 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Early elevations in cytokine levels within the DBA/2J retina </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We found significantly elevated anti-inflammatory FGF-2 in 8–10-month DBA/2J retinas compared to D2G controls (F3, 38 = 6.937, p &lt; 0.001), with a trend towards increased FGF-2 in the D12–15 group (p = 0.08). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory cytokines IL-5 (F3, 39 = 5.686, p = 0.003) and IL-10 (F3, 25 = 5.526, p = 0.006) were also elevated in the retina of D8–10 mice compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The following pro-inflammatory cytokines were elevated early in D3–5 mouse retina compared to controls: VEGF (F3, 39 = 3.098, p = 0.039), IL-12 (F3, 39 = 3.982, p = 0.015), IL-17 (F3, 39 = 3.693, p = 0.020), IL-1α (F3, 36 = 2.924, p = 0.048), TNF-α (F3, 38 = 3.051, p = 0.041), IFN-γ (F3, 37 = 3.904, p = 0.017), MIG (F3, 39 = 3.453, p = 0.030), MIP-1α (F3, 30 = 3.255, p = 0.032), and KC (F3, 39 = 6.311, p = 0.009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>KC also remained elevated in the D8-10 retina (p = 0.005) prior to an age-dependent decrease also observed in other cytokines (see Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the following pro-inflammatory cytokines peaked at 8–10 months of age in DBA/2J retinas, reaching levels that were significantly greater than D2G controls: VEGF (F3, 39 = 3.098, p = 0.032), IL-17 (F3, 39 = 3.693, p = 0.034), IL-1α (F3, 36 = 2.924, p = 0.029), TNF-α (F3, 38 = 3.051, p = 0.029), and IFN-γ (F3, 37 = 3.904, p = 0.033).Fig. 2Cytokine protein levels in retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory mediators (FGF-2, IL-10, and IL-5) were elevated in 8–10-month DBA/2J mice and often demonstrated an age-dependent decrease (a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A number of pro-inflammatory mediators, such as TNF-α, were also elevated in D8–10 mice; others, such as IL-12 and MIP-1α, were elevated in D3–5, often demonstrating an age-dependent decrease. Error bars depict standard error of the mean. Asterisk indicates that the group has significantly greater levels than bracketed comparison (p &lt; 0.05). b Photomicrographs depicting CTB (first column) and elevated immunostaining for FGF-2 (second column) and GFAP (third column) in representative DBA/2J retina whole mount compared to a D2G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Merged images for all stains are shown in the fourth column. c Photomicrographs of elevated FGF-2 immunostaining in retinal cross sections of representative DBA/2J compared to D2G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 50 μm </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>No significant differences between old and young D2G retina were shown for the following cytokines: FGF-2 (t(9) = −2.173, p = 0.058), IL-10 (t(6) = 0.389, p = 0.711), IL-5 (t(10) = −0.166, p = 0.871), VEGF (t(10) = 0.339, p = 0.742), IL-12 (t(10) = 1.000, p = 0.341), IL-17 (t(10) = 1.213, p = 0.92), IL-1α (t(10) = 0.552, p = 0.593), TNF-α (t(10) = −0.411, p = 0.690), IFN-γ (t(9) = −0.333, p = 0.747), MIG (t(10) = −0.385, p = 0.708), MIP-1α (t(10) = 1.206, p = 0.255), and KC (t(10) = −0.957, p = 0.361) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Select pro-inflammatory cytokines are elevated in pON of DBA/2J mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Unlike the retina, where cytokines often reached peak values at D3–5 or D8–10 age groups, cytokines showed a number of different responses in pON of DBA/2J mice (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The levels of the anti-inflammatory modulator, FGF-2, were significantly lower in pON of D3–5 mice compared to all other groups (F3, 36 = 6.577, p &lt; 0.05).Fig. 3Cytokine protein levels in proximal optic nerve (pON). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory FGF-2 and pro-inflammatory IL-6 and MIP-1α levels were lower in the pON of young DBA/2J mice than all other groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-12 was only elevated in pON of young and middle-aged DBA/2J mice. Asterisk indicates that D3–5 mice have significantly lower cytokine levels than D2G controls and D8–10 and D12–15 pON. Number sign indicates significance greater than bracketed comparison (p &lt; 0.05). Arrows indicate values below limits of detection for the assay. Error bars depict standard error of the mean </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>While the pro-inflammatory cytokine, MIP-1α, was significantly lower in pON of D3–5 mice compared to controls (F3, 36 = 4.125, p = 0.009), others showed elevations in DBA/2J groups compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-6 was elevated in D12–15 mice compared to controls and D3–5 mice (F3, 34 = 6.041, p = 0.014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>IL-12, on the other hand, was significantly elevated in D3–5 and D8–10 mice compared to controls and D12–15, which showed little to no IL-12 in pON (F3, 28 = 3.682, p = 0.026). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Finally, IL-1β was elevated in all DBA/2J groups compared to controls (F3, 15 = 5.948, p = 0.036). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(Data are illustrated in Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>No significant differences were seen between old and young D2G pON in the following cytokines: FGF-2 (t(10) = −1.921, p = 0.084), IL-1β (t(4) = 1.633, p = 0.178), IL-6 (t(9) = 0.003, p = 0.998), IL-12 (no IL-12 was detected in D2Gs, so t test not computed), MIP-1α (t(10) = 0.450, p = 0.662). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>However, MCP-1 (t(6) = 4.130, p = 0.006) and IL-5 (t(9) = 2.871, p = 0.018) were significantly reduced in old D2G pON compared to young D2G pON; MCP-1 showed the opposite trend in DBA/2J pON, and IL-5 was not significantly different among DBA/2J pONs across ages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>D2G controls were combined since no differences were shown among cytokines that changed significantly for the D2 pON (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Age-dependent effects in the distal ON of D2G controls are absent in DBA/2J mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Few significant differences were observed in dON among DBA/2J groups (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-1β was elevated in dON of all DBA/2J mice compared to that of controls (F3, 26 = 3.274, p = 0.039); notably, this pro-inflammatory cytokine was not detected in D2G mice at all, but was detected in all DBA/2J groups to some degree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Also, pro-inflammatory MCP-1 was significantly elevated in D8–10 and D12–15 dON compared to controls (F3, 23 = 3.186, p = 0.046).Fig. 4Cytokine protein levels in distal optic nerve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>For all cytokines shown, with the exception of IL-1β and MCP-1, there was a significant age-dependent increase in D2G control mice that was not apparent in DBA/2J mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-1β was only detected in DBA/2J mice (arrows indicate values below the detection limit of assay). Asterisk indicates that the group has significantly higher levels than bracketed comparisons (p &lt; 0.05). Error bars show the standard error of the mean </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, unlike other tissue types, the dON showed a variety of differences between young and old D2G mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Therefore, analyses used the separated D2G groups as described previously (G3–5 and G12–14), along with D3–5, D8–10, and D12–15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory cytokines and growth factors that showed a significant elevation in G12–15 compared to G3–5 mice were as follows: VEGF (t(10) = 4.025, p = 0.002), MIG (t(9) = 3.572, p = 0.006), and KC (t(10) = 4.698, p = 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>MIP-1α was significantly elevated in G12–15 compared to G3–5 and all DBA/2J groups (F4, 39 = 7.060, p ≤ 0.009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory cytokines that showed an age-dependent elevation between G3–5 and G12–15 were IL-10 (t(6) = 5.831, p = 0.001) and IL-4 (t(10) = 2.576, p = 0.028). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Notably, G12–15 mice had significantly increased anti-inflammatory IL-10 levels compared to DBA/2J mice of all ages (F4, 29 = 5.107, p = 0.029). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>(Data are illustrated in Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Early increases in pro-inflammatory cytokine levels in the DBA/2J SC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Early increases in cytokine levels were observed in SC of DBA/2J mice (without accounting for transport differences) compared to D2G controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory modulators IL-4 (F3, 40 = 5.605, p = 0.003) and IL-5 (F3, 41 = 3.713, p = 0.019) were both significantly elevated in D8–10 mice compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory modulators, IFN-γ (F3, 31 = 4.352, p = 0.012) and KC (F3, 42 = 6.035, p = 0.002), were significantly increased in both D3–5 mice and D8–10 mice compared to D2G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-12 was detected at extremely low levels in controls and old DBA/2J SC, but in respect to these values was increased in D8–10 mice and levels were significantly higher in D3–5 mice (F3, 37 = 5.021, p = 0.005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(Data are illustrated in Fig. 5).Fig. 5Cytokine protein levels in superior colliculus (SC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory IL-4 and IL-5 were elevated in D8–10 mice, while pro-inflammatory IFN-γ and KC were elevated in D3–5 and D8–10 DBA/2J mice compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Pro-inflammatory IL-12 levels were increased in D3–5 DBA/2J mice compared to controls and 12–15 DBA/2J mice. Arrows indicate levels below the detection limit of the assay. Asterisk indicates that the group has significantly higher levels than bracketed comparisons (p &lt; 0.05). Error bars indicate the standard error of the mean </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between old and young D2G SC for the majority of cytokines, including those illustrated (IL-4, IL-5, IL-6 IFN-γ, MIG, IL-12, and KC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, pro-inflammatory IL-17 was significantly reduced in old D2G SC compared to young D2G cohorts (t(10) = 3.820, p = 0.003; data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>IL-6 is the only cytokine that demonstrates a relationship to axonal transport outcome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Most cytokines did not differ based on anterograde transport outcome of CTB; however, IL-6 was an exception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>IL-6 levels were significantly increased in transport-absent SC compared to transport-intact SC (F5, 31 = 5.543, p = 0.001; Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This finding is of particular interest because elevation of IL-6 was not apparent when analyzing the SC data before segregation of samples based on transport outcome.Fig. 6IL-6 levels based on age, strain, and CTB transport to the superior colliculus (SC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Differences in collicular IL-6 levels emerged in 12–15-month-old mice based on transport outcome, with transport absent regions (CTB−) demonstrating significantly greater IL-6 than transport intact (CTB+) regions (asterisk indicates p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>There is no anticipated loss of transport in controls and D3–5-month-old groups. Error bars show standard error of the mean </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Cerebellum </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>No significant differences in cerebellar cytokine levels were observed in DBA/2J and D2G mice across ages (Table 2) indicating that differences in cytokine levels are not generalizable to the nervous system in these mice.Table 1Summary of group nomenclature and N valuesStrainAgeGroup nomenclatureMice per group (N)Projections analyzed (n)D2G3–5 monthsD2Ga 48D2G12–15 months46DBA/2J3–5 monthsD3–5510DBA/2J8–10 monthsD8–10612DBA/2J12–15 monthsD12–15510 aYoung and old D2G mice were combined into a single control group in order to simplify results when possible; independent samples t tests indicated that young and old D2G mice showed few differences in their cytokines levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>When detected, differences were described within the results section using G3–5 and G12–15 (referring to young and old D2G mice, respectively)Table 2Cerebellar cytokine levels across age and strainG3–5G12–15D3–5D8–10D12–15Mean (pg/mg protein)±SEMMean (pg/mg protein)±SEMMean (pg/mg protein)±SEMMean (pg/mg protein)±SEMMean (pg/mg protein)±SEMFGF-2574.4020.60562.7030.40452.6012.30473.30122.50531.3057.20IFN-γ2.200.902.001.001.800.906.302.902.201.80IL-1α2.500.301.200.301.800.904.401.802.901.60IL-1β2.600.8016.8012.507.206.207.103.909.605.20IL-22.300.602.500.301.100.604.402.903.101.70IL-46.775.9027.500.1021.5014.003.000.0023.8020.90IL-51.660.681.800.563.600.914.562.103.011.17IL-69.801.808.700.305.100.8010.604.508.703.40IL-101.600.2014.603.808.206.0030.1027.9026.8023.70IL-133.103.107.907.902.600.9012.607.309.875.00IL-12––––3.301.900.900.90––IL-170.200.030.040.020.040.010.300.100.200.09KC215.5532.7699.2567.50133.0763.85268.0666.14199.6760.04MCP-1N/AN/A––––1.901.901.350.69MIG86.9619.4810.402.4011.732.7212.984.8612.094.64MIP-1α10.100.307.800.109.180.6014.435.2010.302.95TNF-α0.720.721.200.4611.706.351.481.481.721.72En dashes indicate that all values were below the limit of detection; for such cases, a zero was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>N/A indicates that the majority of samples had no reading or an error reading, which is distinguished from a reading that is simply below the limit of detection </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Serum </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>There were no differences between DBA/2J and D2G serum levels of cytokines, indicating that changes observed in visual system tissues were not globally present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Cytokine measurements in serum showed much higher inter-sample variability than cytokine levels in the other tissue analyzed in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Relationship between retina and SC cytokine levels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Given the frequent disconnect between pathology in the retina versus targets in the brain, we sought to identify any relationships in cytokine levels between these two structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Few cytokines showed a strong and consistent relationship between retinal and collicular levels (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>However, FGF-2 levels in the retina and SC were significantly correlated in our youngest D2G and DBA/2J mice [Fig. 7, G3–5 (r2 = 0.887, p = 0.018); D3–5 (r2 = 0.849, p = 0.016)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>This relationship was not reflected in older animals of either strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests that age, independent of pathology, may disrupt the association between retinal and collicular FGF-2 levels in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Pathological changes may further challenge this relationship, as we observed elevations in absolute retinal FGF-2 levels in DBA/2J mice compared to controls (see Fig. 2).Fig. 7Scatterplot showing relationship between retinal and collicular FGF-2 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Symbols represent individual retina versus the corresponding superior colliculus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Significant positive correlations were indicated between retinal and collicular FGF-2 levels for both young D2G (3–5 months) and young DBA/2J (3–5 months) mice (Pearson’s r 2). Regression lines have been drawn for each of these groups to illustrate these relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>No significant relationships were shown for other groups, including aged D2G mice. p values are indicated on the figure </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Additionally, IL-6 retinal and collicular levels in young D2G mice were positively correlated, and there was a trend towards this effect in the oldest D2G mice [G3–5 (r2 = 0.961, p = 0.009); G12–15 (r2 = 0.736, p = 0.08)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>No such relationships between retinal and collicular IL-6 levels were shown in any DBA/2J group (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The absence of this relationship in DBA/2J mice at any age indicates that there may be an early and sustained disruption in the association of retinal and collicular IL-6.Fig. 8Scatterplot showing relationship between retinal and collicular IL-6. Symbols represent individual retina versus the corresponding superior colliculus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>A significant, positive correlation between retinal and collicular IL-6 levels in young D2G mice (Pearson’s r 2) and a strong trend towards this same relationship was indicated in old D2G mice. Regression lines have been drawn for each of these groups to illustrate relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>No significant relationships were shown for other groups. p values are indicated on figure </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>FGF-2 immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Cross sectioned and whole retina show a clear distinction in FGF-2 levels between D2G and DBA/2J groups, with all DBA/2J groups demonstrating increased FGF-2 immunoreactivity (Fig. 2), which supports multiplex data from the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The distinction between DBA/2J groups illustrated by multiplex analyses, however, is not as apparent in histological sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Inner and outer plexiform layers are most densely stained for FGF-2, with diffuse staining throughout other layers of the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Data illustrates that the retinal ganglion cell layer is not the only location of FGF-2, and therefore, the FGF-2 detected by multiplex analyses is mostly due to its concentration in these other layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This also suggests that glia and other cell types constitute the majority of FGF-2 production in the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Müller glia are likely a major producer of FGF-2 as reported by Hageman and colleagues [30] and others (refer to [31, 32]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Glaucoma is an age-related degenerative disorder in which microglial abnormalities have been described, especially at the optic nerve head and retina [18, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Specifically, microglia are found in activated, ramified clusters within the glaucomatous optic nerve head [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>However, despite the initial changes to ONH, we have previously reported that pathology, presumably due to these changes, manifests distally in retinal targets such as SC [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This disparity between locations of the stressor and manifestation of pathology is commonly seen in neurodegenerative disorders [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Despite this pattern of progression, a comprehensive description of cytokine profiles throughout this projection apart from retina and optic nerve head has not been done. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Our work provides an age-dependent analysis of cytokine levels throughout the entire retinal projection of the glaucomatous DBA/2J model with respect to functional outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Cytokine protein levels along RGC projection with age and pathology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Early elevations of classically categorized pro-inflammatory cytokines—specifically IFNγ, MIG, KC, TNF-α, and MIP-1α—observed in the retina and SC may signal the progression of pathological changes in the visual projection of DBA/2J mice prior to functional transport loss and RGC death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>While the majority of changes we observed were in pro-inflammatory mediators, our results suggest that anti-inflammatory cytokines may play a compensatory role early in glaucoma prior to transport loss, as evidenced by early elevations in retinal IL-5 and IL-10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Other work has shown that IL-10 plays a role in RGC survival and IL-5 has similar functions [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>TNF-α is another important pro-inflammatory cytokine that was found to be upregulated in the retina of 8–10-month DBA/2J mice, which is expected given that TNF-α has cytotoxic effects associated with apoptotic signaling [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In support of our findings, recent work has shown that TNF-α may actually be protective early in glaucomatous pathology, as TNF-α expression is upregulated immediately following nerve crush and TNF-α deficiency intensifies RGC injury following nerve crush [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Previous work from other laboratories has shown increased immunolabeling of TNF-α and its associated death receptor, TNF-R1, in the optic nerve head and retina of glaucomatous human donor eyes [37, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>While TNF-α was upregulated primarily in glia of retina and optic nerve head, the TNF-1R was most prominent in RGC bodies, suggesting that RGCs may be especially susceptible to the effects of TNF-α [37, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Conversely, TNF-α has also been shown to have early neuroprotective effects via actions of the less-prominent TNF-R2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>While some RGC death can be observed in the 8–10-month DBA/2J retina, the protective effects associated with TNF-R2 may be why there is a temporal delay between observed TNF-α elevations and the age at which RGC death becomes overwhelmingly significant (13–15 months; refer to [7]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Additionally, FGF-2 upregulation was shown in the retina of 8–10-month-old DBA/2J mice (with trends towards this elevation in D3–5 and D12–15 groups), suggesting that FGF-2 may be an early signal of cellular stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Recently, the Noda laboratory described the response of microglia to FGF-2 with experiments that demonstrated that (a) degenerating neurons released FGF-2 and that (b) microglia specifically responded to this FGF-2 release by adopting an amoeboid phenotype and migrating towards FGF-2 at sites of neuronal degeneration [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In our studies, FGF-2 levels in retina and SC of young D2G mice were similar, but became dissociated in older D2Gs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This age-dependent pattern of FGF-2 expression in the retina and SC was recapitulated in DBA/2J mice, but their overall FGF-2 levels were an order of magnitude above those of the D2G controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Therefore, while FGF-2 levels may become deregulated between the retina and SC as a feature of normal aging, it is likely that the actual magnitude of concentrations and not the relative values between structures are the important factor in DBA/2J pathology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Immunostaining in the retina also supported multiplex FGF-2 data overall, showing an increase in the DBA/2J retina compared to D2G controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that FGF-2 expression was apparent in several layers, specifically the outer and inner plexiform layers of the retina and not just in ganglion cells; this is relevant since the whole retina was analyzed in the multiplexing experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>FGF-2 is produced by a variety of cell types including Müller glia, RGCs, and other cell types [30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, FGF-2 stimulates Müller cell proliferation [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Wen and colleagues also showed that FGF-2 is upregulated in the retina in response to acute, mechanical injury and suggested that this actually serves as a protective response in the context of photoreceptor degeneration [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>While chronic, glaucomatous neurodegeneration differs distinctly from this acute type of photoreceptor degeneration, it is still a logical extrapolation that our observed FGF-2 elevations within DBA/2J retina could be an intrinsic signal or attempt to by retinal cells to be “rescued.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>While FGF-2 elevations and other anti-inflammatory changes in the SC did differ significantly between DBA/2J age groups, anti-inflammatory IL-4 and IL-5 were elevated in the D8–10 age group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a number of pro-inflammatory cytokines were elevated in young DBA/2J mice compared to D2G mice and older DBA/2J mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>For example, KC was elevated in all D3–5 and D8–10 groups compared to D2G mice, which may drive some of the more prolonged inflammation and advanced pathology within the DBA/2J strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>This idea is supported by data in htau mice, a common neurodegenerative model for Alzheimer’s disease, which show elevated KC and MIG, among other pro-inflammatory mediators, within their cortex when compared to controls [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Other pro-inflammatory cytokines elevated in D3–5 SC included IL-12 and IFN-γ, which may also perpetuate early pathology prior to transport loss. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, distal portions of the ON in control mice showed age-dependent elevations in cytokines—a finding that was absent in aging DBA/2J mice and contrasted with findings in other regions of the visual projection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Some notable changes in dON of D2G mice with age were in levels of anti-inflammatory cytokines IL-10, and IL-4, suggesting that these may be protective elevations that occur in the distal projection of the ON during normal aging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This was corroborated by the finding that DBA/2J mice lacked this response as they aged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Notably, IL-1β was significantly elevated in both proximal and distal portions of the optic nerve in DBA/2J mice compared to controls, indicating a possible role for this cytokine in distal axonopathy in glaucoma [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>IL-1β has been shown to be an upstream activator of JNK via transforming growth factor-β activating kinase-1 (TAK1) [41], and hyperphosphorylation of neurofilaments and motor proteins by JNK may alter the substrate and machinery by which axonal transport occurs to sustain cellular and axonal viability [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Cytokines and axonal transport </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Largely, changes in cytokine levels were independent of axonal transport outcome in the SC as well as in the corresponding retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>However, due to the small sample size and variability within the DBA/2J strain, these data should be interpreted cautiously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, IL-6 was the only molecule that differed based on transport outcome; as expected, IL-6 levels were highest in the most pathological (i.e., transport-absent) SC at 12–15 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Given that RGC death in DBA/2J mice occurs most significantly at 18 months of age [28] and D8–10 SC showed no differences in IL-6 based on transport, increased IL-6 in transport-deficient SC of D12–15 mice may signal impending RGC loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This contrasts with reports in the retina, which has shown that an IL-6 transducer was elevated under conditions of glaucoma-related stress before RGC loss [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The function of IL-6 in these regions has been suggested to be involved in the regeneration of injured axons in optic nerve trauma and more acute IOP elevation [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The chronic degeneration in DBA/2J mice, however, presents a more complicated scenario. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>While IL-6 levels were significantly reduced in the proximal optic nerve of DBA/2J mice compared to controls, possibly due to transport deficits, these levels increased with age and were significantly greater in the SC of the oldest DBA/2J groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Given that we do not see extensive axon injury until then [4, 7, 8, 28], elevation of IL-6 within the D12-15 SC suggests that this signaling may be a neuroprotective mechanism attempting to salvage or replace lost connections [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>We observed that IL-6 levels were highly correlated between the retina and SC of young D2G mice, and there was a trend toward this relationship in the old D2G controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>However, in DBA/2J mice, we did not see a relationship between retinal and collicular IL-6. As has been suggested previously [44], IL-6 may be elevated specifically in response to axon damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Given that we have previously reported distal axonopathy in this model, we would expect elevations in IL-6 to occur in the distal targets (e.g., SC) first, therefore uncoupling the relationship between retina and SC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec23" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Dysregulation of cytokine signaling throughout the RGC projection of DBA/2J mice is evident early in pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Early elevations of classic pro-inflammatory cytokines in the retina—specifically IFNγ, MIG, KC, TNF-α, and MIP-1α as well as consistent elevations in IL-1β throughout the ON may signal the progression of pathological changes in the visual projection of DBA/2J mice prior to functional transport loss and RGC death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Additionally, differences in cytokine levels, either age-related or strain-related, are compartmentalized throughout the RGC projection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Overall, DBA/2J mice show many age-dependent changes in pro-inflammatory cytokines and some alterations in anti-inflammatory cytokines that are not observed in control mice within the retina and proximal ON and SC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that changes in cytokine and growth factor levels may occur prior to functional transport loss and are consistent with previous work showing inflammatory changes and immune-mediated vasoconstriction early in glaucomatous pathology [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Such alterations in immunomodulatory molecules may be among the subtle changes that occur prior to overt cytoskeletal damage, loss of axonal transport, and cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>However, IL-6 levels were elevated in accordance with axonal transport loss in our oldest DBA/2J mice, indicating that IL-6 may be a reliable marker of late pathological states [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Previous work by Luterman and colleagues [45] showed a similar pattern in patients with late/terminal Alzheimer’s disease exhibiting greater amounts of IL-6 mRNA in entorhinal cortex and temporal gyrus compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>This group also demonstrated that levels of IL-6 were positively correlated with neurofibrillary tangles [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Thus, IL-6 elevations in the SC may be closely coupled to structural demise and axonal loss, as previous work from our lab has shown that both retrograde transport deficits and structural loss are characteristic of the 12–15-month DBA/2J group [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>However, the current study did not directly assess this relationship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Given that our findings indicate a complex role for cytokine signaling throughout the RGC projection, it would be interesting to parse out immune cell phenotypes responsible for cytokine release versus resting, phagocytotic, primed, or senescent phenotypes throughout the projection as a function of strain and age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Additionally, further investigation into the interplay between the immune system and axonal transport disruption via downstream, kinase-mediated cytoskeletal, or motor protein modifications could also provide important insight into the progression and potential therapeutic targets of glaucoma and other related neurodegenerations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>GNW conducted all multiplex assays and was involved in the design, analysis, and interpretation of data as well as writing and revising the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>SDC and DMI conceptualized and designed the studies and assisted in the critical revision of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>CMDC analyzed and interpreted the data and assisted in writing and critically revising the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>MAS performed technical support and assisted in data analysis and manuscript preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a grant from the National Eye Institute (EY022358) to SDC. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>1.AdalbertRNogradiABabettoEJaneckovaLWalkerSAKerschensteinerMSeverely dystrophic axons at amyloid plaques remain continuous and connected to viable cell bodiesBrain2009132Pt240216<?supplied-pmid 19059977?>19059977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>2.BradySMorfiniGA perspective on neuronal cell death signaling and neurodegenerationMol Neurobiol2010421253110.1007/s12035-010-8128-2<?supplied-pmid 20480262?>20480262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>3.AndersonDRHendricksonAEffect of intraocular pressure on rapid axoplasmic transport in monkey optic nerveInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci1974131077183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>4.CrishSDSappingtonRMInmanDMHornerPJCalkinsDJDistal axonopathy with structural persistence in glaucomatous neurodegenerationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201010711519620110.1073/pnas.0913141107<?supplied-pmid 20194762?>20194762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>5.MincklerDSTsoMOZimmermanLEA light microscopic, autoradiographic study of axoplasmic transport in the optic nerve head during ocular hypotony, increased intraocular pressure, and papilledemaAm J Ophthalmol19768257415710.1016/0002-9394(76)90012-X<?supplied-pmid 63246?>63246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>6.MincklerDSBuntAHJohansonGWOrthograde and retrograde axoplasmic transport during acute ocular hypertension in the monkeyInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci19771642641<?supplied-pmid 67096?>67096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>7.Dengler-CrishCMSmithMAInmanDMWilsonGNYoungJWCrishSDAnterograde transport blockade precedes deficits in retrograde transport in the visual projection of the DBA/2J mouse model of glaucomaFront Neurosci2014811210.3389/fnins.2014.0029024478622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>8.CrishSDDapperJDMacnameeSEBalaramPSidorovaTNLambertWSFailure of axonal transport induces a spatially coincident increase in astrocyte BDNF prior to synapse loss in a central targetNeuroscience2013229557010.1016/j.neuroscience.2012.10.069<?supplied-pmid 23159315?>23159315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>9.Schlamp CL, Li Y, Dietz JA, Janssen KT, Nickells RW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Progressive ganglion cell loss and optic nerve degeneration in DBA/2J mice is variable and asymmetric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>BMC Neruosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>2006. doi:10.1186/1471-2202-7-66. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>10.NickellsRWFrom ocular hypertension to ganglion cell death: a theoretical sequence of events leading to glaucomaCan J Ophthalmol20074222788710.3129/canjophthalmol.i07-036<?supplied-pmid 17392853?>17392853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>11.QuigleyHABromanATThe number of people with glaucoma worldwide in 2010 and 2020Br J Ophthalmol200690262710.1136/bjo.2005.081224<?supplied-pmid 16488940?>16488940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>12.QuigleyHANeuronal death in glaucomaProg Retin Eye Res1999181395710.1016/S1350-9462(98)00014-7<?supplied-pmid 9920498?>9920498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>13.AlmasiehMWilsonAMMorquetteBVargasJLCDi PoloAThe molecular basis of retinal ganglion cell death in glaucomaProg Retin Eye Res20123121528110.1016/j.preteyeres.2011.11.002<?supplied-pmid 22155051?>22155051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>14.WaxMBTezelGYangJPengGPatilRVAgarwalNInduced autoimmunity to heat shock proteins elicits glaucomatous loss of retinal ganglion cell neurons via activated T-cell-derived Fas-ligandNeurobiol Dis200828461208596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>15.TezelGThorntonILTongMGLuoCYangXCaiJImmunoproteomic analysis of potential serum biomarker candidates in human glaucomaInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci2012531382223110.1167/iovs.12-10076<?supplied-pmid 23150628?>23150628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>16.TezelGImmune regulation toward immunomodulation for neuroprotection in glaucomaCurr Opin Pharmacol201313233110.1016/j.coph.2012.09.013<?supplied-pmid 23084793?>23084793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>17.BoscoAInmanDMSteeleMRWuGSotoIMarsh-AmstrongNReduced retina microglial activation and improved optic nerve integrity with minocycline treatment in the DBA/2J mouse model of glaucomaInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci200849414374610.1167/iovs.07-1337<?supplied-pmid 18385061?>18385061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>18.BoscoASteeleMRVetterMLEarly microglia activation in a mouse model of chronic glaucomaJ Comp Neurol2011519459962010.1002/cne.22516<?supplied-pmid 21246546?>21246546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>19.MacNairCEFernandesKASchlampCLLibbyRTNickellsRWTumor necrosis factor alpha has an early protective effect on retinal ganglion cells after optic nerve crushJ Neuroinflammation20141119410.1186/s12974-014-0194-325407441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>20.Morzaev D, Nicholson JD, Caspi T, Weiss S, Hochhauser E, Goldenberg-Cohen N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Toll-like receptor-4 knockout mice are more resistant to optic nerve crush damage than wild-type mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Clin Exp Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>2015. doi:10.1111/ceo.12521. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>21.ZhouXLiFKongLTomitaHLiCCaoWInvolvement of inflammation, degradation and apoptosis in a mouse model of glaucomaJ Biol Chem200528031240810.1074/jbc.M502641200<?supplied-pmid 15985430?>15985430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>22.KuchteyJRezaeiKAJaru-AmpornpanPSternbergPJrKuchteyRWMultiplex cytokine analysis reveals elevated concentration of interleukin-8 in glaucomatous aqueous humorInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci201015126441710.1167/iovs.10-521620592224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>23.JohnsonECDoserTACepurnaWODyckJAJiaLGuoYCell proliferation and interleukin-6-type cytokine signaling are implicated by gene expression responses in early optic nerve head injury in rat glaucomaInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci20115215041810.1167/iovs.10-5317<?supplied-pmid 20847120?>20847120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>24.SappingtonRMChanMCalkinsDJInterleukin-6 protects retinal ganglion cells from pressure-induced deathInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci200647729324210.1167/iovs.05-1407<?supplied-pmid 16799036?>16799036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>25.HowellGRMacalinaoDGSousaGLWaldenMSotoIKneelandSCMolecular clustering identifies complement and endothelin induction as early events in a mouse model of glaucomaJ Clin Invest2011121414294410.1172/JCI44646<?supplied-pmid 21383504?>21383504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>26.JohnSWMSmithRSSavinovaOVHawesNLChangBTurnbullDEssential iris atrophy, pigment dispersion, and glaucoma in DBA/2J miceInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci199839695162<?supplied-pmid 9579474?>9579474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>27.Howell GR, Libby RT, Marchant JK, Wilson LA, Cosma IM, Smith RS, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Absence of glaucoma in DBA/2J mice homozygous for wild-type versions of Gpnmb and Tyrp1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>BMC Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>2007. doi:10.1186/1471-2156-8-45. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>28.BuckinghamBPInmanDMLambertWOglesbyECalkinsDJSteeleMRProgressive ganglion cell degeneration precedes neuronal loss in a mouse model of glaucomaJ Neurosci2008281127354410.1523/JNEUROSCI.4443-07.2008<?supplied-pmid 18337403?>18337403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>29.LanchinJMMcGeePLGreenbaumCJPalmerJPescovitzMDGottliebPSample size requirements for studies of treatment effects on beta-cell function in newly diagnosed type 1 diabetesPLoS ONE201161110.1371/journal.pone.0026471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>30.HagemanGSKirchoff-RempeMALewsGPFisherSKAndersonDHSequestration of basic fibroblast growth factor in the primate retinal interphotoreceptor matrixProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19918867061010.1073/pnas.88.15.6706<?supplied-pmid 1862095?>1862095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>31.WenRSongYChengTMatthesMTYasumuraDLaVailMMInjury-induced upregulation of bFGF and CNTF mRNAs in the rat retinaJ Neurosci19951511737785<?supplied-pmid 7472491?>7472491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>32.PuroDGManoTModulation of calcium channels in human retinal glial cells by basic fibroblast growth factor: a possible role in retinal pathobiologyJ Neurosci1991116187380<?supplied-pmid 1646301?>1646301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>33.NeufeldAHMicroglia in the optic nerve head and the region of parapapillary chorioretinal atrophy in glaucomaArch Ophthalmol199911781050610.1001/archopht.117.8.1050<?supplied-pmid 10448748?>10448748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>34.Cuchillo-IbanezISeereeramAByersHLLeungKYWardMAAndertonBHPhosphorylation of tau regulates its axonal transport by controlling its binding to kinesinFASEB J200822931869510.1096/fj.08-109181<?supplied-pmid 18511549?>18511549 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>35.HuangPZhangS-MZhangCThe two sides of cytokine signaling and glaucomatous optic neuropathyJ Ocul Biol Dis Inform200929810310.1007/s12177-009-9034-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>36.TezelGTNF-α signaling in glaucomatous neurodegenerationProg Brain Res20081734092110.1016/S0079-6123(08)01128-X<?supplied-pmid 18929124?>18929124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>37.YanXTezelGWaxMBEdwardDPMatrix metalloproteinases and tumor necrosis factor alpha in glaucomatous optic nerve headArch Ophthalmol20001186667310.1001/archopht.118.5.666<?supplied-pmid 10815159?>10815159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>38.TezelGLiLYPatilRVWaxMBTumor necrosis factor-alpha and its receptor-1 in the retina of normal and glaucomatous eyesInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci2001428178794<?supplied-pmid 11431443?>11431443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>39.Noda M, Takii K, Parajuli B, Kawanokuchi J, Sonobe Y, Takeuchi H, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>FGF-2 released from degenerating neurons exerts microglial-induced neuroprotection via FGFR3-ERK signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>J Neuroinflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>2014. doi:10.1186/1742-2094-11-76. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>40.Garwood CJ, Cooper JD, Hanger DP, Noble W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Anti-inflammatory impact of minocycline in a mouse model of tauopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Front Psychiatry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>2010. doi:10.3389/fpsyt.2010.00136. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>41.WestonCRDavisRJThe JNK signal transduction pathwayCurr Opin Cell Biol2007192142910.1016/j.ceb.2007.02.001<?supplied-pmid 17303404?>17303404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>42.FalzoneTLStokinGBLilloCRodriguesEMWestermanELWilliamsDSAxonal stress kinase activation and tau misbehavior induced by kinesin-1 transport defectsJ Neurosci2009291857586710.1523/JNEUROSCI.0780-09.2009<?supplied-pmid 19420244?>19420244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>43.EchevarriaFDWalkerCCAbellaSKWonMSappingtonRMStressor-dependent alterations in glycoprotein 130: implications for glial cell reactivity, cytokine signaling and ganglion cell health in glaucomaJ Clin Exp Ophthalmol201343128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>44.ChidlowGWoodJPMEbneterACassonRJInterleukin-6 is an efficacious marker of axonal transport disruption during experimental glaucoma and stimulates neuritogenesis in cultured retinal ganglion cellsNeurobiol Dis20124835688110.1016/j.nbd.2012.07.026<?supplied-pmid 22884876?>22884876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>45.LutermanJDHaroutunianVYemulSHoLPurohitDAisenPSCytokine gene expression as a function of the clinical progression of Alzheimer disease dementiaArch Neurol200057811536010.1001/archneur.57.8.1153<?supplied-pmid 10927795?>10927795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
