<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nutr J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nutrition Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2891</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4627615</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26514332</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12937-015-0105-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A randomized two way cross over study for comparison of absorption of vitamin D3 buccal spray and soft gelatin capsule formulation in healthy subjects and in patients with intestinal malabsorption </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Satia</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><address><email>milansatia@ethicare-cro.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mukim</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><address><email>drmukim@indiatimes.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tibrewala</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><address><email>kdtibrewala@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhavsar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><address><email>drmsbhavsar@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Ethicare Clinical Trial Services, Ahmedabad, India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Mukim Medical And Nursing Homes, Ahmedabad, India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Tibrewala’s Clinic, Ahmedabad, India </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Bhavsar’s Clinic, Ahmedabad, India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>114</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Satia et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D deficiency has been proposed to contribute to the development of malabsorption diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Despite this, the vitamin D status of these patients is often neglected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The objective of the present work was to compare the absorption of vitamin D3 through the oral route by comparing a 1000 IU soft gelatin capsule and a 500 IU buccal spray (delivering 1000 IU in two spray shots) in healthy subjects and in patients with malabsorption disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>An open label, randomized, two-periods, two-way cross over study was conducted, first in healthy subjects (n = 20) and then in patients with malabsorption syndrome (n = 20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The study participants were equally divided and received either of the treatments (buccal spray, n = 7; soft gelatin capsule, n = 7; control, n = 6) in Period I for 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>After washout of another 30 days, the treatments were changed in crossover fashion in Period II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Fasting blood samples were collected to measure baseline 25-hydroxyvitamin D [25(OH)D] levels in all participants at day 0 (Screening visit), day 30 (completion of period I), day 60 (end of wash out and initiation of period II) and day 90 (completion of period II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Safety was evaluated by hematology and biochemistry analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses was performed using differences of mean and percentage change from baseline of 25(OH)D levels between two formulation by two tailed Paired t-test with 95 % confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In healthy subjects, the mean increase in serum 25(OH)D concentration was 4.06 (95 % CI 3.41, 4.71) ng/ml in soft gelatin capsule group and 8.0 (95 % CI 6.86, 9.13) ng/ml in buccal spray group after 30 days treatment (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In patients with malabsorption disease, the mean increase in serum 25(OH)D concentration was 3.96 (95 % CI 2.37, 5.56) ng/ml in soft gelatin capsule group and 10.46 (95 % CI 6.89, 14.03) ng/ml in buccal spray group (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It can be concluded from the results that the buccal spray produced a significantly higher mean serum 25(OH)D concentration as compared to the soft gelatin capsule, in both healthy subjects as well as in patients with malabsorption syndrome over a period of 30 days administration in a two way cross over study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Treatments were well tolerated by both subject groups </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Trial Registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ctri.nic.in/Clinicaltrials/pmaindet2.php?trialid=6625">CTRI/2013/06/003770</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Vitamin D3</kwd><kwd>25-hydroxyvitamin D</kwd><kwd>Malabsorption Syndrome</kwd><kwd>Buccal Spray</kwd><kwd>Cross Over Study</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Pharma Base SA</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D is essential for active intestinal calcium absorption and plays a central role in maintaining calcium homeostasis and skeletal integrity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>It is derived mainly from cutaneous synthesis in the presence of ultraviolet sunlight while dietary intake constitutes a minor fraction [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D deficiency is a common problem through the world [2, 3] and is assessed by low serum concentration of the major circulating metabolite 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The prevention of vitamin D deficiency and insufficiency remains a priority of international health services [6–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D deficiency has been proposed to contribute to the development of intestinal bowel diseases like Crohn's disease, steatorrhea and ulcerative colitis [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Conversely, people who have such illnesses have a reduced absorption of vitamin D3 through the intestine [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition, osteomalacia occurs in patients with a wide variety of disorders affecting the stomach and small bowel, especially when associated with steatorrhea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The pathogenesis of this osteomalacia has in part been explained by malabsorption in vitamin D [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Earlier reports show that orally administered tritiated vitamin D3 was malabsorbed in patients with celiac disease, biliary obstruction or pancreatic disease [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The pathogenesis of vitamin D deficiency in these patients remains unclear but it is thought to result primarily from fat soluble vitamin malabsorption due to the presence of intestinal disease conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Despite vitamin D malabsorption in patients with gastrointestinal or liver disease, the vitamin status of these patients is often neglected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Although vitamin D supplements are often prescribed, adequate absorption of these formulations has not been documented [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D is known to be liposoluble, and its relative bioavailability could result in unfavorable conditions when administered in solid form (capsule), since the process of its release is a factor limiting the rate of absorption, bearing in mind that bioavailability is related not only to the pharmaceutically active molecules, but also, to the formulation and excipients used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Vitamin D3 taken by oral route (peroral delivery) is absorbed in the intestine, where the lining of the digestive tract is aqueous in nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Therefore vitamin D3, a fat-soluble molecule, in order to be absorbed, must be made water soluble in the intestine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This is accomplished in two steps: emulsification of vitamin D3 in the intestinal lumen, through the action of bile salts, forming small droplets which are dispersed and incorporated into micelles-complex aggregates formed by the interaction of free fatty acids, monoglycerides, and bile salts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Micelles are sufficiently water-soluble to access the intestinal brush border where upon the vitamin D3 content is released and then absorbed [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>When sprayed inside the mouth, the fine micro sized droplets of vitamin D3 are believed to be quickly and completely absorbed through the buccal mucosa into the numerous capillaries and veins lying close to the tissue surface [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Considering the possibility of reduced vitamin D absorption in healthy subjects and even in patients with malabsorption syndrome, a buccal spray formulation was developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the objective of the present work was to compare the absorption of vitamin D3 through the oral route (soft gelatin capsule form) and buccal spray in healthy subjects and patients with intestinal malabsorption syndrome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Study design and patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>An open label, randomized, two-periods, two-way cross over study was conducted, first in healthy subjects and then in patients with malabsorption syndrome, with a similar study design except the presence of disease status in patients with malabsorption syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>After approval from the Spandan-IEC ethics committee (registration no: ECR/67/Indt/GJ/2013), the informed consent of study participants were taken and the formulation was administered for 30 days in period I where half of the subjects and patients (collectively participants) received capsule formulation and half of the participants received buccal spray formulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>After completion of treatment in period I, all participants were given 30 days wash out before initiating period II where treatment has changed in cross over fashion, i.e. the participants who received capsule formulation in period I have received buccal spray in period II and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The clinical study was registered in a centralized clinical trial registry of India (CTRI) before initiating the enrollment of the first patient in the study (CTRI/2013/06/003770). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The inclusion criteria were as follows: subjects of either sex between 18 and 65 years of age, with a Body Mass Index (BMI) between 18.0 and 30.0 kg/m2, and the ability to comply with study procedures in the opinion of the investigators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>For healthy subjects: no history of liver, kidney or cardiovascular disease, or of any other medical conditions or medications likely to affect vitamin D3 absorption or metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For patients with malabsorption syndrome: confirmed diagnosis of any one of the following malabsorption disease conditions like ulcerative colitis, Crohn’s disease or steatorrhea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Patient with history of above diseases, who are on therapy, were selected for the screening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In these patients, malabsorption syndrome was diagnosed by clinical symptoms like abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, and subcutaneous fat loss together with blood tests like haematology and biochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Stool examination was also performed for all patients to confirm rectal bleeding, presence of occult blood, infectious organisms, or fat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Finally, colonoscopy was performed in all patients to objectively assess the extent of inflammation to confirm the diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The exclusion criteria were as follows: systemic inflammatory or malignant disease; hepatic or renal failure; uncontrolled hypo- or hyperthyroidism, or the use of drugs that are known to affect bone metabolism such as bisphosphonates, glucocorticoids and anti-convulsants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A pregnant or desired to be pregnant woman during study period was also excluded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Data collected at baseline </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Each participant completed a self-administered questionnaire before enrollment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>During completion of the questionnaire, they had the possibility to ask for assistance (i.e. clarification of question or any other issue) from one of the project leaders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The questionnaire included questions about usual intake of vitamin D containing foods, clothing and sun exposure habits, as well as height &amp; weight, date of birth, and education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Body mass index was derived as wt/ht2 (kg/m2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Blood pressure was measured through sphygmomanometer and vitals (heart rate, body temperature) were also recorded for safety purposes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Collection and analyses of blood samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Fasting blood samples were collected to measure baseline 25(OH)D levels in all the participants at day 0 (Screening visit), day 30 (completion of period I), day 60 (end of wash out and initiation of period II) and day 90 (completion of period II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were centrifuged (15 min; 2000 g at 4 °C) within 30 min of blood collection and separated serum samples were immediately frozen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were stored at −20 °C until analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Serum 25(OH)D levels were measured by Electrochemiluminescence (ECLIA) assay method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>This assay was carried out through quantitative determinations of total 25-hydroxyvitamin D in serum samples using a standard kit available from Roche diagnostics GmbH, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All analyses were done in a central independent clinical analysis laboratory (APL Institute of Clinical Laboratory &amp; Research Pvt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Ltd., Ahmedabad, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The kit has a limit of detection of 3 ng/mL and has a linearity of 0.0 to 60.0 ng/mL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The intra-assay and inter-assay co-efficient of variation were 4 % and 6 %, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Elecsys e-immunoassay analyzers were used for this assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Safety parameters were evaluated including hematology analyses (complete blood counts), biochemical analyses (serum creatinine, total bilirubin, urea, SGOT, SGPT, alkaline phosphates, calcium) and urine was collected for urine routine and microbiological analyses at screening visit (day 0) and at the end of period II visit (day 90). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Intervention randomization and compliance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Randomization and group allocation: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The participants were enrolled at two different hospital sites in India; one physician’s site where all healthy subjects were recruited and a gastroenterologist’s site where all patients with intestinal malabsorption were recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Out of the forty-eight participants who met the eligibility criteria, forty (twenty healthy and twenty patients) had agreed to participate and were found eligible, signed a written consent form, and completed a self administered questionnaire concerning usual diet and sun exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, a venous blood sample was drawn, and a participant received a sealed, non-transparent envelope with the allocated treatment intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The randomization procedure was performed beforehand by a statistician by block randomization with blocks of two to one ratio, where the first two participants were randomly given each treatment and a third participant served as a control and didn’t receive any treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The participants were allocated to the interventions as they visited the clinic i.e. the first subject was allocated to buccal spray group, second to soft gelatin capsule group and third to the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This was done in order to distribute the participants equally in the two interventions (Group I and Group III) and half of the participants served as a control (Group II and Group IV). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Twenty healthy subjects enrolled for the study were recruited at a physician’s site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>They were randomized and enrolled into group I and II: fourteen subjects were enrolled for vitamin D3 treatment and labeled as group I (healthy subjects), while every third subject (total six subjects) were not given any treatment (labeled as group II) and acted as the control for group I. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The twenty patients with confirmed diagnosis of malabsorption syndromes (nine with ulcerative colitis, four with Crohn’s disease and seven with steatorrhea) were recruited at a gastroenterologist’s hospital site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Fourteen subjects were enrolled for vitamin D3 treatment and labeled as group III (patients with malabsorption syndrome), while every third subject (total six subjects) were not given any treatment (labeled as group IV) and acted as the control for group III. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>All patients continued to take their treatment for ulcerative colitis, Crohn’s disease and steatorrhea as prescribed by gastroenterologists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Treatment allocation was assigned to each participant according to their number of sequence of attendance at the blood sampling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Treatment allocation was concealed in envelopes numbered in ascending order that they met. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Study personnel involved in recruitment and data collection were blinded to the participant’s treatment allocation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>All participants were instructed to maintain their routine lifestyle including diet habits and sun exposure during the entire study period, to minimize interference with the daily routine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The buccal spray and soft gelatin capsules containing vitamin D3 were supplied by Pharma Base, India (a subsidiary of Pharma Base SA, Switzerland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The soft gelatin capsule formulation was purchased from the Indian market. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The analysis of both the formulations was done in triplicate according to the method described in European Pharmacopeia at an independent analytical laboratory (Oasis Testing House, Ahmedabad, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The soft gelatin capsule formulation had a label content of 1000 IU per capsule and the buccal spray formulation had a label content of 500 IU/spray shot. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>All participants in group I &amp; III were randomized to receive either the vitamin D3 buccal spray (2 sprays each of 500 IU) or soft gelatin capsule containing vitamin D3 (1000 IU) for 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Of the fourteen subjects in each group, half received buccal spray and half received soft gelatin capsule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This was considered as period I of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>After the completion of the 30-day treatment, all participants were given a 30-day washout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The next treatment in period II was changed in a crossover fashion; those participants who had received the buccal spray formulation (vitamin D3) in period I received the soft gelatin capsule formulation in period II and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The treatment in period II continued in group I and group III participants for the next 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The detailed study flow chart is described in Fig. 1.Fig. 1Study flow chart </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Compliance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>All participants were instructed to take the two buccal sprays and one soft gelatin capsule every day irrespective of the period of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Formulation for 7 days was handed over to each participants under group I &amp; III at baseline, along with the compliance form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The participants were instructed to mark the intake and time of intake of number of spray shots or capsule of each day of the study period, as well as to note any extraordinary event that occurred during the period (forgetting to take a spray shot or capsule). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>If forgetting to take spray shot or capsule, the participants were instructed to take a double dose on the following day, in order to take altogether 60 spray shots or 30 capsules during the study periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The participants were recommended to take spray shots or capsules after the main meal of the day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, participants were not instructed to standardize meals or time between meals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>All participants were also instructed not to change their daily routine, meal habits, as well as their sun exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This was done to minimize interference with daily routine and thus maximizing compliance with taking study medication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>All participants in group I and III were instructed to visit the site every week to check compliance with the intake of study medication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Participants in control groups (Group II and Group IV) were instructed to visit their respective clinic after 30 days for their blood sample collection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>All participants who received treatment were also instructed to note any adverse events during the entire 90 days of the study which included period I, washout period and period II in a separately given adverse event recording form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Stastical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Sample size </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The sample size of this crossover study was based on the changes in 25(OH)D levels where goal was to detect: 1) percent increase between pre-dose and post-dose levels within treatments, and 2) to have significant difference of percent change in 25(OH)D levels between the treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>To achieve type-I error rate of less than 5 % (2 tailed), a sample size of 12 subjects in buccal spray group (healthy or patients) was sufficient to provide a statistical power of 80 % to detect a clinically significant mean difference of 5 % in 25(OH)D levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Demographic and baseline characteristic </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A descriptive statistics was applied for demographics; age (years), weight (kg), body mass index (kg/m2); and were presented as mean ± standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Efficacy analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism 5, version 5.03 (GraphPad Software, Inc., CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Differences of mean and percentage change from baseline of 25(OH)D levels between two formulation groups, soft gelatin capsules and buccal spray, were evaluated using two tailed Paired t-test with 95 % confidence interval separately for both healthy subjects and patients with intestinal malabsorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For comparison between control group and either of the treatments, unpaired t-test with 95 % confidence interval was used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Safety analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The number and proportion of subjects with changes in laboratory value (change from baseline to end of study visit for complete blood count, serum creatinine, total bilirubin, urea, SGOT, SGPT, alkaline phosphates and calcium) was summarized and the difference was analyzed by chi –square test from normal to abnormal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In total, thirty eight individuals, thirteen healthy individuals with six control and thirteen patients with malabsorption syndrome with six control, fulfilled the eligibility criteria and completed the study (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Two participants (one healthy subject and one patient) reported vitamin D3 intake compliance of less than 90 % and therefore were not considered for final analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In healthy subjects, at baseline, 85 % (n = 12) of the subjects had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml, and one individual each (7.14 %) had serum 25(OH)D concentration &gt;30 ng/ml and &lt;10 ng/ml each in the oral soft gelatin capsule group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>While in the buccal spray group, at baseline all subjects had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in patients with malabsorption disease who received oral soft gelatin capsules, at baseline 8 (57.14 %) patients had serum 25(OH)D concentration below 10 ng/ml, 5 (35.71 %) patients had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 20 ng/ml, and one individual (7.14 %) had serum 25(OH)D concentration above 20 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>However, in the buccal spray group, at baseline 9 (64.28 %) patients had serum 25(OH)D concentration below 10 ng/ml and 5 (35.71 %) patients had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 20 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>There were no striking differences in baseline characteristics between healthy individuals or patients with malabsorption disease with their corresponding control groups (Table 1).Table 1Demographic Data for Healthy Subjects and Patients with malabsorption syndromeParametersHealthy Subjects Group IHealthy Subjects Control Group IIPatients with malabsorption syndrome Group IIIPatients with malabsorption syndromeControlGroup IVN146146SexMale = 7, Female = 7Male = 3, Female = 3Male = 7, Female = 7Male = 3, Female = 3Age (Yrs)36.21 ± 9.9734.00 ± 6.4239.93 ± 11.6544.17 ± 5.56(Range)(25–60)(25–42)(26–63)(38–53)Height (cms)159.86 ± 13.43161.33 ± 14.12162.29 ± 8.54164.33 ± 8.55BMI23.39 ± 3.8821.40 ± 2.3921.48 ± 2.8223.64 ± 3.02All values are expressed in Mean ± SD; N-number subjects in each group </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Effect of intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The control groups in each subject population were compared with their corresponding treatment group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The control groups for healthy subjects as well as patients with malabsorption syndrome showed no change in 25(OH)D concentration over a period of 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The mean baseline levels of 25(OH)D in healthy subjects was 18.25 ng/ml and in patients with malabsorption syndrome was 11.7 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These mean levels remained at 18.06 ng/ml and 12.52 ng/ml after 30 days in healthy subjects and patients with malabsorption syndrome respectively (Fig. 2), which was statistically non-significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>When control group in healthy subjects was compared with their corresponding treatment groups, it was found that the difference of mean between control group and buccal spray group was 7.47 (95 % CI, 5.27, 9.67) which was significant (p &lt; 0.05), and the same between control group and soft gelatin capsule group was 3.53 (95 % CI, 1.79, 5.28) which was also statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Similarly in patients, the difference of mean between control group and buccal spray group was 8.53 (95 % CI, 2.74, 14.31) which was significant (p &lt; 0.05), while the difference of mean between control group and soft gelatin capsule group was 2.03 (95 % CI, −1.44, 5.50) which was statistically not significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>This shows that buccal spray was more effective to increase mean 25(OH)D levels as compared to oral soft gelatin capsule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Table 2 describes these data.Fig. 2Mean 25(OH)D level in study subjectsTable 2Comparison of 25(OH)D in control group and their corresponding treatment groups after 30 daysComparisonDifference of mean95 % CIP ValueHealthy – Buccal Spray vs. Control7.475.27 to 9.67&lt;0.0001Healthy – Soft Gelatin Capsule vs. Control3.531.79 to 5.280.0005Patients – Buccal Spray vs. Control8.532.74 to 14.310.0064Patients – Soft Gelatin Capsule vs. Control2.03−1.44 to 5.500.2338 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of buccal spray and soft gelatin capsule to increase the 25(OH)D levels after 30 days of administration was evaluated and compared with each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>After 30 days of administration, overall mean serum 25(OH)D concentration in healthy subjects was 22.75 (sd 6.75) ng/ml as compared to baseline value of 18.69 (sd 5.88) ng/ml in the soft gelatin capsule group, with the mean increase of 4.06 (95 % CI 3.41, 4.71) ng/ml (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, in the buccal spray group, the mean serum 25(OH)D concentration was 26.91 (sd 5.72) ng/ml as compared to baseline value of 18.91 (sd 4.3) ng/ml, with the mean increase of 8.0 (95 % CI 6.86, 9.13) ng/ml (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The difference in mean increase between both the groups was 3.95 (95 % CI 3.19, 4.69) which was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.0001).Table 3Level of 25(OH)D in Healthy Subjects and Patients with malabsorption syndrome after 30 day administration of vitamin D3 buccal spray and soft gelatin capsuleParametersMean baseline value in ng/mlMean value in ng/ml after 30 day of treatmentDifference of meanPercentage mean increase from baselineHealthy SubjectsSoft gelatin Capsule Formulation Mean18.69 ± 5.8822.75 ± 6.754.0621.72 % Range9.25, 30.0512.75, 35.522.5, 5.615.36, 37.79 n13131313 95 % CI15.14 to 22.2418.67 to 24.423.41 to 4.7116.42 to 24.42Buccal Spray Formulation Mean18.91 ± 4.326.91 ± 5.727.99542.99 % Range13.36, 26.8219.6, 38.54.5, 11.6729.21, 68.71 n13131313 95 % CI16.31 to 21.5123.45 to 30.366.86 to 9.1337.19 to 48.79Patients with intestinal malabsorption syndromeSoft gelatin Capsule Formulation Mean11.01 ± 6.4314.97 ± 9.013.96536.02 % Range2.9, 26.54.6, 36.891.06,10.3924.62,58.73 n13131313 95 % CI7.12 to 14.899.52 to 20.422.37 to 5.5630.42 to 41.62Buccal Spray Formulation Mean10.01 ± 4.2920.47 ± 7.8910.46117.8 % Range4.6, 18.859.8, 34.644.25, 27.4461.31,381.1 n13131313 95 % CI7.42 to 12.615.7 to 25.246.89 to 14.0364.71 to 170.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>When calculated from baseline, the mean percentage change in serum 25(OH)D concentration in healthy subjects after 30 days treatment with soft gelatin capsule was 21.72 % (95 % CI 16.42, 24.42), while the same in buccal spray group was 42.99 % (95 % CI 37.19, 48.79) with a mean difference of 20.42 % (95 % CI 16.42, 24.42) between two groups (p &lt; 0.0001) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A total of 11 (85 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml, and two individuals (15.38 %) now had serum 25(OH)D concentration &gt;30 ng/ml in the soft gelatin capsule group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, in the buccal spray group, 10 (75.88 %) subjects had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml and 3 (23.1 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration &gt;30 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Similarly in patients with malabsorption syndrome, overall mean serum 25(OH)D concentration after 30 days of administration of soft gelatin capsule was 14.97 (sd 9.01) ng/ml as compared to baseline value of 11.01 (sd 6.43) ng/ml, with the mean increase of 3.96 (95 % CI 2.37, 5.56) ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>While in buccal spray group, mean serum 25(OH)D concentration was 20.47 (sd 7.89) ng/ml as compared to baseline value of 10.01 (sd 4.29) ng/ml, with the mean increase of 10.46(95 % CI 6.89, 14.03) ng/ml (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The difference in mean increase between both the groups was 6.50 (95 % CI 3.78, 9.22) which was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The mean percentage change in serum 25(OH)D concentration in patients with malabsorption syndrome after 30 days treatment with soft gelatin capsule was 36.02 % (95 % CI 30.42, 41.62), while the same value in buccal spray group was 117.8 % (95 % CI 64.71, 170.8) with a mean difference of 81.75 % (95 % CI 29.80, 133.7) between the two treatments (p &lt; 0.005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>A total of four (31 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration below 10 ng/ml, eight (61 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml, and one individual (7.7 %) had serum 25(OH)D concentration above 30 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>However, in the buccal spray group, only 7.7 % (1 subject) now had serum 25(OH)D concentration below 10 ng/ml, ten (76.9 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration between 10 and 30 ng/ml and two (15.4 %) subjects now had serum 25(OH)D concentration more than 30 ng/ml (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Statistical considerations with respect to period, sequence and power: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were performed using SAS v9.2 (SAS Institute Inc, Cary, NC, USA) for the post-hoc evaluation of sequence and period effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The statistical method adopted for this analysis was period + sequence + Subject (sequence) + treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>It was observed that there is no significant difference in sequence effect in healthy subjects (p = 0.5251) and in patients with malabsorption syndrome (p = 0.0532). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It was also revealed that there is no statistically significant period effect in healthy subjects (p = 0.6920) as well as in patients with malabsorption syndrome (p = 0.0715). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The post-hoc power analyses with intra-subject variability were also derived for both the group of subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In healthy subjects, statistical power obtained was 99.42 with an 11.81 % intra-subject variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>While, in patients with malabsorption syndrome it was 81.62 with an intra-subject variability of 21.86 %. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Safety evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>There were no significant changes in any of the hematology and biochemistry parameters studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>There are also no notable changes in the vitals for any of the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>No adverse event reported after administration of the buccal spray or soft gelatin capsule formulations of vitamin D3 during entire study period in healthy or patients with malabsorption disease and hence the product is considered safe. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Supplemental fat-soluble vitamin D is usually made without determination of whether oral doses are adequately absorbed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The evidence of vitamin D malabsorption (Osteomalacia, rickets, hypocalcaemia, or reduced circulating concentration of 25(OH)D) persists despite routine vitamin D supplementation in cystic fibrosis [14], Crohn’s disease [15], Intestinal resection [16–19], ulcerative colitis, liver disease [20–22] and other malabsorption syndrome [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Many factors are involved in the absorption of vitamin D, including gastric, pancreatic, and biliary secretions, micelle formation, and diffusion through the unstirred water layer, brush border membrane uptake, and transport out of the intestinal cell [24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>As vitamin D is a relatively non-polar sterol, it must be solubilized by incorporation into a bile salt micelle solution in order to be absorbed in the aqueous phase [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>This process is severely inhibited if there is any interruption of normal pancreatic or biliary secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>As fat-soluble vitamins are fairly sensitive to disturbances in lipid absorption, vitamin malabsorption may occur in conditions like steatorrhea, ulcerative colitis, and Crohn’s disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Serum concentrations of 25-hydroxyvitamin D are good indicators of long term vitamin D levels in the body but are insensitive to single doses of vitamin D and do not rise out of the normal range unless doses of vitamin D are chronically administered [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Considering the malabsorption in intestinal disease and a possible poor and complex absorption with oral formulations, a novel nanoemulsion formulation of buccal spray was developed where vitamin D3 is suspended in an aqueous base which can be easily absorbed through the mucosal layer of the mouth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We compared the serum concentration of vitamin D after 30 days administration with the soft gelatin capsule and the aqueous based buccal spray formulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first randomized two way cross over trial comparing the increase in 25(OH)D levels in healthy adults and patients with intestinal malabsorption receiving similar oral doses of two different formulations (per oral and buccal spray). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The analyses of baseline levels of study participants showed that vitamin D deficiency was prevalent in both healthy subjects and patients with intestinal malabsorption syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, patients were more vitamin D deficient as compared to healthy subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Four weeks administration of 1000 IU per day increased mean serum 25(OH)D in all treatment groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In healthy subjects, soft gelatin capsule increased serum 25(OH)D level by 22.5 % (Range 15.4 to 37.8 %), while the buccal spray increased serum 25(OH)D level by 43 % (range 29.2 to 68.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in patients with intestinal malabsorption, soft gelatin capsule increased serum 25(OH)D level by 36 % (range 24.6 to 58.7 %) and the buccal spray increased serum 25(OH)D by 117.8 % (range 61.3 to 381.1 %). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The result implies that the buccal spray formulation had a significantly higher mean increase in both the subject groups, healthy subjects and patients with intestinal malabsorption syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the mean increase was much higher in the patients group as compared to the healthy subjects group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>This may be because increase in serum 25(OH)D after supplementation is known to be inversely related to baseline 25(OH)D concentration [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the mean baseline levels were almost half in patients with intestinal malabsorption as compared to the baseline levels found in healthy subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>This indicates the presence of vitamin D3 deficiency in the patient group as compared to healthy subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The primary and the most important source of vitamin D is sunlight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Although excessive exposure to sunlight and vitamin D have been positively associated with non-melanoma skin cancer [29], ecological studies suggest that sunlight may protect against female breast, ovarian, prostate, and colon cancer [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Solar UV-B exposure and the amount of exposure to sun are related inversely with cancer mortality and survival in detailed epidemiological studies [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Some analytical studies suggest a protective association between circulating vitamin D in blood, which is largely derived from sunlight or dietary vitamin D, and colorectal cancer and prostate cancer [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, looking at the overall baseline levels of all participants in the present study, it is also advisable to increase the moderate daily sun exposure and to improve clothing apart from vitamin D3 supplementation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>We conclude that the buccal spray formulation was able to increase mean serum vitamin D3 concentration significantly higher as compared to the soft gelatin capsule, in both healthy subjects (1.9 times) as well as in patients with intestinal malabsorption syndrome (2.6 times). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Availability of supporting data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The data set(s) supporting the results of this article is (are) included within the article. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>25(OH)D</term><def><p>25-hydroxyvitamin D</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTRI</term><def><p>clinical trial registry of India</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>Body Mass Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECLIA</term><def><p>Electrochemiluminescence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IU</term><def><p>International Unit</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Authors' contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>MCS participated in design of the study, analyses and interpretation of data, performed the statistical analyses, and drafting revising, and finalizing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>AGM participated as investigator in the study, involved in healthy subject recruitment, their compliance and acquisition of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>KDT participated as investigator in the study, involved in patient recruitment, their compliance and acquisition of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>MSB participated as investigator in the study, involved in patient recruitment, their compliance and acquisition of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The buccal spray was provided by Pharma Base SA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to those who gave their consent to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was reviewed and approved by Spandan–Ethics committee and we thank specifically Dr. Gaurang Shah, chairman, Spandan Ethics committee for his valuable contribution and encouragement throughout the project. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>1.HolickMFShilsMEOlsonJAShikeMRossACVitamin DModern nutrition for health and disease1999BaltimoreWilliams and Wilkins329345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>2.ViethRVitamin D supplementation, 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations, and safetyAm J Clin Nutr1999695842856<?supplied-pmid 10232622?>10232622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>3.UtigerRDThe need for more vitamin DN Engl J Med19983381282882910.1056/NEJM199803193381209<?supplied-pmid 9504945?>9504945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>4.HaderslevKVJeppesenPBSorensenHAMortensenPBStaunMVitamin D status and measurements of markers of bone metabolism in patients with small intestinal resectionGut200352565365810.1136/gut.52.5.653<?supplied-pmid 12692048?>12692048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>5.HolickMFVitamin D: important for prevention of osteoporosis, cardiovascular heart disease, type 1 diabetes, autoimmune diseases, and some cancersSouth Med J200598101024102710.1097/01.SMJ.0000140865.32054.DB<?supplied-pmid 16295817?>16295817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>6.SchuchNJGarciaVCMartiniLAVitamin D and endocrine diseasesArq Bras Endocrinol Metabol200953562563310.1590/S0004-27302009000500015<?supplied-pmid 19768253?>19768253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>7.BandeiraFGrizLDreyerPEufrazinoCBandeiraCFreeseEVitamin D deficiency: A global perspectiveArq Bras Endocrinol Metabol200650464064610.1590/S0004-27302006000400009<?supplied-pmid 17117289?>17117289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>8.HolickMFVitamin D: the underappreciated D-lightful hormone that is important for skeletal and cellular healthCurr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes200291879810.1097/00060793-200202000-00011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>9.ThompsonGRLewisBBoothCCAbsorption of vitamin D3-3H in control subjects and patients with intestinal malabsorptionJ Clin Invest19664519410210.1172/JCI105327<?supplied-pmid 4285212?>4285212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>10.LoCWParisPWClemensTLNolanJHolickMFVitamin D absorption in healthy subjects and in patients with intestinal malabsorption syndromesAm J Clin Nutr1985424644649<?supplied-pmid 4050723?>4050723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>11.JavorskyBRMaybeeNPadiaSHDalkinACMaybeeBRJNVitamin D deficiency in gastrointestinal diseasePract Gastroenterol2006365272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>12.AvioliLVAbsorption and metabolism of vitamin D3 in manAm J Clin Nutr1969224437446<?supplied-pmid 4305087?>4305087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>13.Micellized Vitamin D3 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.klaire.com/images/k-mcd_update_fall_2010.pdf">www.klaire.com/images/k-mcd_update_fall_2010.pdf</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>14.HahnTJSquiresAEHalsteadLRStromingerDBReduced serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentration and disordered mineral metabolism in patients with cystic fibrosisJ Pediatr1979941384210.1016/S0022-3476(79)80346-7<?supplied-pmid 758419?>758419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>15.DriscollRHJrMeredithSCSitrinMRosenbergIHVitamin D deficiency and bone disease in patients with Crohn's diseaseGastroenterology198283612521258<?supplied-pmid 6982188?>6982188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>16.MarkestadTAksnesLFinnePHAarskogDDecreased vitamin D absorption after limited jejunal resection in a prematureJ Pediatr198210161001100810.1016/S0022-3476(82)80031-0<?supplied-pmid 7143152?>7143152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>17.CompstonJECreamerBPlasma levels and intestinal absorption of 25-hydroxyvitamin D in patients with small bowel resectionGut197718317117510.1136/gut.18.3.171<?supplied-pmid 856674?>856674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>18.CompstonJEAyersABHortonLWTigheJRCreamerBOsteomalacia after small-intestinal resectionLancet19781805491210.1016/S0140-6736(78)90358-6<?supplied-pmid 74542?>74542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>19.CompstonJEMerrettALLedgerJECreamerBFaecal tritium excretion after intravenous administration of 3H-25-hydroxyvitamin D3 in control subjects and in patients with malabsorptionGut198223431031510.1136/gut.23.4.310<?supplied-pmid 7076008?>7076008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>20.WagonfeldJBNemchauskyBABoltMHorstJVBoyerJLRosenbergIHComparison of vitamin D and 25-hydroxy-vitamin-D in the therapy of primary biliary cirrhosisLancet19762798239139410.1016/S0140-6736(76)92407-7<?supplied-pmid 73853?>73853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>21.MatloffDSKaplanMMNeerRMGoldbergMJBitmanWWolfeHJOsteoporosis in primary biliary cirrhosis: effects of 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 treatmentGastroenterology1982831 Pt 197102<?supplied-pmid 7075948?>7075948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>22.DanielssonALorentzonRLarssonSEIntestinal absorption and 25-hydroxylation of vitamin D in patients with primary biliary cirrhosisScand J Gastroenterol198217334935510.3109/00365528209182066<?supplied-pmid 7134862?>7134862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>23.SchoenMSLindenbaumJRoginskyMSHoltPRSignificance of serum level of 25-hydroxycholecalciferol in gastrointestinal diseaseAm J Dig Dis197823213714210.1007/BF01073189<?supplied-pmid 623077?>623077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>24.ThompsonGRAbsorption of fat-soluble vitamins and sterolsJ Clin Pathol Suppl (R Coll Pathol)19715858910.1136/jcp.s3-5.1.85 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>25.HinesCJrVitamins, Absorption and malabsorptionArch Intern Med1978138461962110.1001/archinte.1978.03630280081025<?supplied-pmid 637644?>637644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>26.MaislosMSilverJFainaruMIntestinal absorption of vitamin D sterols: differential absorption into lymph and portal blood in the ratGastroenterology198180615281534<?supplied-pmid 7227777?>7227777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>27.DaviesMMawerEBKlassHJLumbGABerryJLWarnesTWVitamin D deficiency, osteomalacia, and primary biliary cirrhosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Response to orally administered vitamin D3Dig Dis Sci198328214515310.1007/BF01315144<?supplied-pmid 6297863?>6297863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>28.HeaneyRPDaviesKMChenTCHolickMFBarger-LuxMJHuman serum 25-hydroxycholecalciferol response to extended oral dosing with cholecalciferolAm J Clin Nutr2003771204210<?supplied-pmid 12499343?>12499343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>29.FeskanichDMaJFuchsCSKirknerGJHankinsonSEHollisBWGiovannucciELPlasma vitamin D metabolites and risk of colorectal cancer in womenCancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev200413915021508<?supplied-pmid 15342452?>15342452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>30.AliMVaidyaVVitamin D and cancerJ Cancer Res Ther20073422523010.4103/0973-1482.38998<?supplied-pmid 18270398?>18270398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>31.BoscoeFPSchymuraMJSolar ultraviolet-B exposure and cancer incidence and mortality in the United States, 1993–2002BMC Cancer2006626410.1186/1471-2407-6-264<?supplied-pmid 17096841?>17096841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
