<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Atypon//DTD Atypon Systems Journal Archiving and Interchange NLM DTD v3.0.6 20130326//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName atypon-archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0.6?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName atyponoasis-oasisns2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transgend Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transgend Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">trgh</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Transgender Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2380-193X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>140 Huguenot Street, 3rd FloorNew Rochelle, NY 10801USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5367487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1089/trgh.2016.0026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/trgh.2016.0026</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Transgender and Gender Nonconforming in Emergency Departments: A Qualitative Report of Patient Experiences </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chisolm-Straker</surname><given-names>Makini</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1,</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jardine</surname><given-names>Logan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bennouna</surname><given-names>Cyril</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morency-Brassard</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coy</surname><given-names>Lauren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Egemba</surname><given-names>Maria Olivia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>Peter L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label>Department of Emergency Medicine, <institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</institution>, New York City, New York.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label>Department of Emergency Medicine, <institution>SUNY Downstate College of Medicine</institution>, Brooklyn, New York.</aff><aff id="aff3"><label><sup>3</sup></label>Department of Population and Family Health, <institution>Columbia University School of Public Health</institution>, New York City, New York.</aff><aff id="aff4"><label><sup>4</sup></label>Emergency Response Team, <institution>International Rescue Committee</institution>, New York City, New York.</aff><aff id="aff5"><label><sup>5</sup></label>Obstetrics, Gynecology and Reproductive Services, Bixby Center for Global Reproductive Health, <institution>University of California</institution>, San Francisco, San Francisco, California.</aff><aff id="aff6"><label><sup>6</sup></label>New York City Teens Connection, <institution>Center for Health Equity</institution>, New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, Queens, New York.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1"><label><sup>*</sup></label>Address correspondence to: Makini Chisolm-Straker, MD, MPH, Department of Emergency Medicine, <institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</institution>, 3 East 101st Street, 2nd Floor, New York City, NY 10029, E-mail: <email xlink:href="Makini.Chisolm-Straker@mssm.edu">Makini.Chisolm-Straker@mssm.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© Makini Chisolm-Straker <italic>et al</italic>. 2017; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="trgh.2016.0026.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Background: Individuals who have a transgender or gender nonconforming (TGGNC) experience belong to a marginalized segment of the U.S. population, and healthcare can be difficult for them to navigate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Although emergency departments (EDs) traditionally serve as healthcare “safety nets” for vulnerable populations, quantitative studies outside the United States have found that TGGNC-experienced persons tend to avoid EDs and/or have negative experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This qualitative study primarily describes the ED experiences of people with a TGGNC history; furthermore, the study explores reasons why this population avoids U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>EDs and their recommendations for improvements to ED care. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods: This qualitative study used data about TGGNC-historied persons' experiences in U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>EDs from retrospective, anonymous, written surveys (paper or web based). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>National data collection took place from June 2012 through December 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Participant responses (n=240) were examined using thematic analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results: Using a framework that recognized positive and negative responses, the themes of Self-Efficacy and Power Inequity surfaced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These themes exposed the tension between patients with TGGNC experiences and clinicians who were perceived to lack training in this area, resulting in negative patient experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>When practitioners had specific training about this population, participants reported positive care experiences. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusions: This study indicates that many TGGNC-historied persons who use U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>EDs have negative experiences, largely due to lack of provider sensitivity toward and training about this patient population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Data from this investigation suggest that training of U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>ED providers and institutional support would help improve care for this marginalized group. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title><bold>Keywords:</bold> </title><kwd>discrimination</kwd><kwd>emergency department</kwd><kwd>emergency medicine</kwd><kwd>gender nonconforming</kwd><kwd>patient perception</kwd><kwd>power</kwd><kwd>provider training</kwd><kwd>stigma</kwd><kwd>transgender</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="5"/><ref-count count="30"/><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s001"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Gender is frequently perceived to be binary and correlative to anatomical sex, but this is not the case for all.1,2 Gender is an internal experience and relates to masculinity, femininity, and their various combinations; it can be demonstrated through body language, clothing, voice, and other social and cultural expressions.3 Those with a transgender or gender nonconforming (TGGNC) life experience or history* have a gender identity different than the gender assumed at birth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Individuals with TGGNC life experiences are among the most marginalized and disenfranchised people in the United States: They disproportionately experience homelessness, underemployment, and live in extreme poverty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in one national study, 41% had attempted suicide compared to the general population's rate of less than 2%.4,5 Unemployed people with a TGGNC life experience are more likely to perform work in the “underground economy” (e.g., sex work or selling drugs), be incarcerated, or use alcohol or illicit substances to cope with mistreatment experienced; this group (unemployed with a TGGNC history) is four times more likely to be HIV infected.4 And in a 2011 national study by the National Center for Transgender Equality, many with a TGGNC experience had survived physical (61%) and sexual (64%) assault.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Multiple studies report that TGGNC-historied people frequently avoid accessing necessary healthcare because of harassment and discrimination in healthcare settings.4,6–14 Emergency Departments (EDs) are the de facto “safety net” of the U.S. healthcare system, open to anyone in medical need, at any time.15 The Emergency Medicine Treatment and Active Labor Act of 1986 was enacted to prevent clinicians from turning away those who lack insurance or the ability to pay but have emergency medical conditions.16 This has resulted in EDs being a setting where anyone can request evaluation and treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Thus EDs, which serve many marginalized populations, should also be able to care for patients with a TGGNC history, who are clearly among the nation's most vulnerable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>While 92% of general ED patients in the United States report being satisfied with the emergency care received,17 it is unknown how TGGNC-historied persons in the United States experience the nation's EDs, which should be accessible to this vulnerable population, as it is for others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This investigation explores how TGGNC-historied persons, as a disenfranchised group, experience care in the medical safety net of the United States. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s002"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>“TG in the ED” was an anonymous, retrospective, written survey accessible in English and Spanish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The survey was available online via SurveyMonkey and in paper form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Data collection started in June 2012 and ended in December 2014, when new surveys no longer revealed new themes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Eligible participants self-identified as having a TGGNC life experience, were at least 18 years old, could read and write in English or Spanish, and wanted, needed, and/or had used an ED in the United States. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>A convenience sample of participants was recruited from across the United States via community and health centers that serve lesbian, gay, bisexual, and TGGNC-experienced (LGBT) persons; Facebook†; a 2014 national conference on transgender health18; and word-of-mouth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The institutional review boards of both The Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai and Columbia University in New York City approved the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Written and verbal consent was waived to protect the anonymity of participants and no remuneration was provided for participation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The survey questions were drafted based on the existing literature and refined by TGGNC health experts, including persons with a TGGNC life experience and those providing healthcare to this population for at least 10 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Free response questions were posed to participants about experiences in the ED, as well as current gender identity, reasons for nonuse of the ED, and recommendations for ED clinicians to improve their care of this patient population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As data were being collected, the research team developed a simple conceptual framework (Fig. 1) based on social cognitive theory (SCT) and stigma theory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>These public health theories helped guide analysis of how participants experienced ED care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>SCT posits that behavior is influenced by environmental and personal factors, as well as the behavior itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>This model is strongly based on the role of self-efficacy (an individual's belief in their own capacity to execute behaviors necessary to achieve specific goals) in behavior change.19 Yet, SCT alone does not account for the patient–provider power differential and its effects on patient experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Stigma theory rests on the idea that all social relationships occur within an unequal structure, in which some groups have more social, political, and/or economic power than others; and that traditional power holders may, intentionally or unintentionally, use stigma and discrimination to reinforce existing structural inequities to assert their possession of power.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><bold>FIG. 1.</bold></label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Conceptual framework: Social cognitive theory and stigma theory. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fig-1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The primary survey question for those who sought emergency medical care was open ended: “Please tell us about your experience.” To examine the data, investigators collaboratively developed labels, or codes, to apply to lines of text such that similar pieces of information could be grouped and compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The codes were synthesized into one codebook, with rules on when to use or not use each code. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Two expert consultants in qualitative analysis, acquainted with the data, reviewed the codebook and then with the team coded five pages of data to determine utility of codes and finalize the codebook. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Codes were applied to the data using NVivo 10.‡,21 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To classify respondents' reports about their experiences in the ED, the principal investigator (MCS) first examined the frequency with which each code was applied, then all text that fell under multiple codes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Next, each ED experience was reviewed for all codes used to describe the experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For the data display (Table 1), the codes were then grouped according to SCT-influenced categories: the category of “Provider Behavior” included the codes “competency,” “outed,” “provider discomfort,” and “confidentiality.” Under “Patient–Provider Encounter” were the codes “respect,” “gendered,” “inappropriate,” and “perceived medical care.” “Systems Issues” included “institutional practice,” and the category of “Self-Efficacy” incorporated “fear,” “disclosure,” and “self-efficacy.” An experience was considered “negative” if the participant expressed discontent with medical care and/or interactions with ED personnel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>When participants described satisfaction with care and/or interactions, a “positive” interaction was inferred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Data Display, Abridged </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Conceptual frame </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Code </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Positive interpretation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Negative interpretation </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Provider behavior </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Competency </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Participants who reported positive experiences with provider competency noted TGGNC-related training of staff. “I have had positive experiences (in terms of my trans status) in the ER, probably because it is [name of hospital] and they are educated for the most part about trans issues.” R134 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Participants stated that their providers did not know how TGGNC life experience is relevant to a chief complaint or how hormone use affects health.“Treated by a resident, who told me ‘I don't understand your body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>I will just consider you female, but who knows what those hormones you are taking could be doing to you’.” R155 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Patient–provider encounter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Gendered </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Some described being properly pronouned or named and feeling respected because of this.“I was actually treated really nicely by the doctors and hospital staff…they treated me like the woman that I am and I would recommend that hospital to anyone who asked.” R86 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Participants who described being misgendered mostly noted that even after their gender identity or experience was disclosed they were mispronouned.“It was humiliating because I was repeatedly referred to by my birth sex after repeatedly asking them to call me by male pronouns.” R59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Patient–provider encounter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Inappropriate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This code captured participant descriptions of provider gawking, persistent staff focus on genital examinations, unnecessary history taking about gender-related surgeries, sexual history, assumption of sexually transmitted infections, drug use, psychological disorder, and use of patient for “teaching” that was interpreted as being put on display.“I was…repeatedly asked if I was drunk or on drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>I was neither. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Injury to leg required stitches.” R170 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Self efficacy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Self efficacy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Those who had others advocate on their behalf reported experiencing respect and proper pronouning. “Emergency appendectomy needed….both my primary physician and spouse took very good care to ensure I was treated respectfully.” R129 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Those who reported being able to advocate for themselves usually did not have a positive experience; others found themselves unable to advocate for themselves at all.“I had a baby and probably could have used some gender related support from a licensed professional during the delivery, but was too frightened to ask for it.” R18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1"><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A summary of the context in which each code was found was grouped into the “positive” and/or “negative” column of the data display with illustrative participant quotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Some codes were only negative, so no positive data were found there. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf2"><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>TGGNC, transgender or gender nonconforming. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>As a team of six investigators with diverse qualities, it was important to recognize how the investigators' identities and experiences might shape the analysis and bias findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Collectively, the team accounted for these subjectivities by working independently first and then coming together, with the consultants, to review strengths and limitations of the separate efforts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>For example, the consultants appreciated that most codes were initially biased toward reflecting negative experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Hence, many such codes were changed, before being applied to the data, to be neutral, such that positive experiences could be recognized. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>“Member checking”22 was performed, to determine whether the investigators' interpretations of these data reflected the experiences of TGGNC-historied persons receiving emergency care in the United States. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Advertised for 6 months on Facebook, this anonymous validation survey was completed by five English-literate, self-identified TGGNC-experienced individuals, some of whom may have participated in the original survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>These persons were given a brief summary of the findings and asked to anonymously report, via SurveyMonkey, whether they considered the results accurate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s003"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Two hundred forty participants completed the main survey; Table 2 describes the demographics and medical characteristics of the sample. Table 3 describes reasons respondents reported for not using EDs; the most common explanations were previous negative experiences or fear of experiencing discrimination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Participant Characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>% </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>n=240 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Age (in years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain> 18–24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>17.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain> 25–35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>50.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>121 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain> 36–45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>16.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain> 46–55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>9.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain> 56–64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain> ≥65 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>0.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Annual income (in USD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain> &lt;11,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>16.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain> 11,001–22,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>15.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain> 22,001–35,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>15.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain> 35,001–45,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>10.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain> 45,001–55,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>7.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain> 55,001–70,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>12.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain> 70,001–90,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>6.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain> 90,001–100,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>4.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain> &gt;100,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>9.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Highest level of education completed </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain> Junior high/middle school </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>1.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain> High school </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>6.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain> Some college/university </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>22.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain> College/university </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>35.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain> Certificate program </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>2.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain> Graduate/professional school </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>31.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Race and/or ethnicitya </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain> Asian/Asian American </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>4.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain> African American/black </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>3.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain> Latino/Hispanic </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>10.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain> Native American/Amerindian/Alaskan Native/Pacific Islander </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>2.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain> White </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>82.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>198 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain> Other </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>2.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Sex assigned at birth </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain> Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>60.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>145 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain> Male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>21.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain> Other </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>0.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Ever-used gender-affirming hormones </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>22.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>65.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>157 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain> Not applicableb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>2.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Prescribed by a licensed provider (n=157) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>3.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>95.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>At least one gender-affirming surgery </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>38.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>51.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>124 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Have a primary care provider </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>17.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>72.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>174 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Ever wanted/needed to use ED </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>13.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>180 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Went to ED (n=180) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain> No </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>8.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain> Yes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>90.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>163 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Respondents were able to choose more than one category. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf4"><label><sup>b</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Respondents with a gender nonconforming experience may not desire hormone use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf5"><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>ED, emergency department. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Reasons for Transgender or Gender Nonconforming Nonuse of U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Emergency Departments </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Conceptual frame </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Reason </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Frequency (n=35),a % (n) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Personal </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Lack of medical insurance </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>31.4 (11) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Fear of being outed, misgendered, or experiencing discrimination </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>60 (21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Provider behavior </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Past witnessing of medical personnel gossiping, mocking, or telling jokes about the TGGNC patients </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>45.7 (16) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Patient–provider encounter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Past experience of being purposely outed by healthcare professional </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>8.6 (3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Past experience with visibly uncomfortable providers and/or being asked inappropriate questions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>34.3 (12) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Past experience of staff refusal to use preferred pronouns </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>62.9 (22) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Past experience of transphobia as a patient </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>37.1 (13) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Systems issues </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Medical facilities are unable to provide accommodations for TGGNC patients </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>42.9 (15) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Providers are poorly educated in TGGNC health-related issues </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>40 (14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf6"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Participants who answered this question could offer multiple reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Recommendations were included here if they resonated with responses to other questions, not based on frequency to one question. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Two overarching themes emerged from the codes related to experiences of emergency care (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The conceptual frame of “Self-Efficacy” allowed the larger theme of Self-Efficacy to materialize; and the conceptual frames “Provider Behavior,” “Patient–Provider Encounter,” and “Systems Issues” were encompassed by the stigma theory-influenced theme of Power Inequity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>These two themes guided the analysis toward an appreciation of the altered power dynamic between providers and patients that results from TGGNC-historied patients presenting to EDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>All validation surveys confirmed the interpretation that regardless of intent, the providers' efforts to compensate for inexperience with TGGNC-related health issues and to assert themselves as knowledgeable authorities led to negative experiences for many study participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><bold>FIG. 2.</bold></label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Thematic analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fig-2"/></fig></SecTag><sec id="s004"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Self-efficacy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The code “disclosure” centered on participants' discussions about considerations of divulging their TGGNC experience to ED staff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Whether forced or elective, “disclosure” was generally linked to a perception of poor medical care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>One respondent recounted, </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>…I revealed my status, which no one knows usually until I tell them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>And then things got weird. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The doctors were very rude, barely treated me, and tried to get rid of me as quickly as possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>And worst of all, when I tried to use the woman's restroom before I left, they threatened to call security on me. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>It was humiliating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>I would die before I went back there again (R21). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Some participants disclosed their TGGNC history and reported being treated with respect, which most attributed to the staff being well trained: “I have had positive experiences (in terms of my trans status) in the ER probably because…they are educated for the most part about trans issues” (R133). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Another participant's positive experience was attributed to having a support network advocating for quality care: “…both [my] primary physician and spouse took very good care to ensure I was treated respectfully” (R127). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Some reported not disclosing and feeling respected because they could pass within the gender binary or they were unsure if their clinician(s) were aware of their TGGNC history. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The “self-efficacy” code was used when participants spoke up for themselves, with resultant positive or negative experiences, and also when participants purposefully had someone else advocate on their behalf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Some found that the traditional provider–patient hierarchy barred their self-efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>About a portion of the physical examination that may have been unnecessary, one participant said, “I didn't ask at the time because…I have been taught that doctors know better than I do” (R118). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>However, even those who reported being able to advocate for themselves often did not have a positive experience: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>I always remind them when I check in that I am trans (FTM§). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>I would rather providers feel uncomfortable before they see me and then get their s—- together by the time they come in. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Even though I do that, the providers always ask me questions about my penis and fail to ask important questions pertinent to people with female anatomy until I prompt them to.… (R123) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Those who had others advocate on their behalf experienced respect and proper pronouning. “My experience was generally positive, but I made sure to have a friend come with me. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The doctors referred to me by [desired] female pronouns…” (R148). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s005"><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Power inequity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Many of the negative experiences described by participants included difficulties with practitioner knowledge in treating TGGNC-experienced patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Generally, providers did not seem to know when and how TGGNC-related medical history was relevant to a chief complaint: “Doctor unable to consider that my female history and male hormones could impact my health in the situation presented” (R132). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Participants conveyed expecting providers to be unaware and reported having to explain the medical relevance of TGGNC medical histories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>When positive experiences were noted, they were attributed to purposeful training: “Once I spoke with the Dr. the whole team was great. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>I later learned my primary care Dr. had worked at that hosp. prior, and had explained gender issues with much of the senior staff” (R25). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Respondents noticed that in situations in which their clinicians admitted they were not knowledgeable about TGGNC-related health issues, these providers were rude and unprofessional. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>One participant reported that the nurses “…[said] things like how it was against God and just wasn't right” (R82). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Providers who demonstrated discomfort with this patient population commonly misgendered patients: “Referred to as a woman even after I explained to the doctor that I was a transmale, they ignored my statement and proceeded to call me she” (R210). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>In addition to misgendering patients, having insufficient medical knowledge, and visibly expressing discomfort, clinicians were often perceived to perform unnecessary histories and physical examinations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>One participant reported being “questioned a lot about my sex life when I went for pneumonia” (R62). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Participants described experiencing open gawking, superfluous history taking about gender-related surgeries, assumption of sexually transmitted infections, drug use, and psychiatric disease, and being put on display. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>One participant shared, “I have also had doctors/nurses call over other people on duty to come look at me for no reason. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>It made me feel like an animal in a zoo” (R208). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Participants also reported having their gender “variance” verbally or physically exposed in the waiting area in front of other patients: “One visit required an ekg, and after telling the staff I was trans, they continued to open my shirt with the doors and curtains open to the ER waiting room” (R10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Moreover, failure of practitioners to communicate led participants to assume they had received an inappropriate examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>For example, one participant survived a motor vehicle collision and experienced head and neck trauma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>The participant reported the provider </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>…[felt] parts of my lower body (through my clothes) that seemed to have nothing to do with my head/neck/spine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>He specifically felt where my hips were, using both hands to register where they were. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>To this day I don't know if this was medically necessary or if he was medically curious about my transsexuality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>(R118). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></disp-quote><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Most likely, this participant is describing the basics of a secondary survey, in which the clinician assesses pelvis stability, but in the absence of communication, the patient inferred the worst. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>To improve ED care, participants recommended that hospitals develop TGGNC-sensitive protocols and practitioner trainings to ensure privacy, respect, and appropriate treatment for patients (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>They recommended focusing on the application of gendered language and improving both intake procedures and modes of communication that currently risk unnecessarily exposing a patient's TGGNC experience. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Participant Recommendations to Improve the Emergency Department Care of Persons with a Transgender or Gender Nonconforming Experience </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Conceptual frame </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Recommendation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Frequency (123),a % (n) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Provider behavior </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Do not discuss gender identity or TGGNC experience (e.g., gender-affirming surgeries) with others, including healthcare providers, unless it is relevant to provision of care. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>22.8 (28) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Ask sensitive questions in private spaces only. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>5.7 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Call out last names only (no prefixes) in group areas, such as waiting rooms. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>2.4 (3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Patient–provider encounter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Standard practice of providers should be to ask patients' preferred pronoun and name and use these throughout care. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>44.7 (55) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Do not ask about gender and/or TGGNC experience if it is not relevant to ED care. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>35.8 (44) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Avoid gender-specific terms, including social titles (eg: Ms., Mr.). </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>1.6 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Systems issues </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Systematic, required training of ED providers on TGGNC medical issues, including gender-affirming surgeries, potential postoperative complications, common hormone therapies, and related side effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Providers should also be trained on the social stigma and marginalization this population experiences generally and in healthcare settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>13.8 (17) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Incorporate pronoun and name preference in registration forms.b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>9.8 (12) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Train clinicians on how to ask, when clinically relevant, about sensitive gender information. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>4.1 (5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Offer gender-neutral spaces, including hospital rooms and restrooms.c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>2.4 (3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf7"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Participants could offer more than one recommendation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Recommendations were included here if they resonated with responses to other questions, not based on frequency to one question. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf8"><label><sup>b</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>While most who commented on pronoun preference on registration forms were in favor of this addition, some were concerned about the potential ramifications of a TGGNC experience being in their medical record. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf9"><label><sup>c</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Applicable to all areas of the hospital, not just emergency departments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s006"><title><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>While many factors impact patient satisfaction with ED experiences, clinician knowledge is not usually identified as a key area for improvement.17,23–27 However, participants in this study reported having to tell their practitioners if and how their TGGNC medical history was relevant to the presenting complaint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>This lack of practitioner knowledge on the issue was strongly tied to negative experiences for TGGNC-experienced patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Further research should examine the curricula of professional healthcare schools and EDs that provide TGGNC health training to students and staff and explore efforts to systematize such education. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Particularly concerning among the negative experiences, multiple participants reported experiencing unwanted examinations, similar to the qualitative findings from a European study.9 Even when a clinician considers an examination necessary, patients with capacity have the right to refuse examinations or treatment plans.28–30 Examinations performed out of provider desire to learn more about TGGNC-related medicine are appropriate only with patient permission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>When practitioners believe an examination (or history element) is relevant, it is particularly important to explain the clinical reasoning to patients of marginalized populations, including TGGNC-experienced patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Not communicating why an examination (or history element) is relevant to care alienates this vulnerable and high-risk group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Similar to TGGNC-historied reports of general healthcare avoidance,2,4,7,9–14 many participants in this ED-focused study indicated that they have avoided ED care due to fear of or previous experience of unwanted examinations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The negative experiences reported additionally included inappropriate history taking, illness assumption, and misgendering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>TGGNC-historied persons have also described these experiences in general medicine reports in Europe, New Zealand, and in some U.S. states.2,4,7,9–14 Such staff actions lead to TGGNC-experienced patients, even those who have not used the ED but have heard of such interactions, avoiding needed medical care (Table 3).2,4,7,9–14 More research is needed to explore why patients who had a cisgender** advocate had more positive ED experiences than those who advocated for themselves; similarly, more research should examine why TGGNC-historied patients who appeared cisgender had a better ED experience than patients who did not. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s007"><title><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>As a survey promoted by organizations and clinics that serve LGBT populations, this study has limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Respondents had relatively high educational and income levels; they may differ from those without access to primary care or kin advocates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Insurance status was not systematically assessed in this study, although several participants noted that not having insurance or the gender marker with their insurance impacted their decision to seek ED care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Further research should explore whether insurance status and insurance gender markers have any impact on ED care experiences among TGGNC-historied persons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Despite specific attempts to optimize diversity, respondents are largely white and were designated “female” at birth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>As with any voluntary survey, persons with negative experiences may be more likely to participate than those with positive experiences, and here they may be more likely to attribute their negative experience to a TGGNC history. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the negative experiences reported are concerning and largely elucidate the findings of previous quantitative studies.4,12 The written, anonymous format permitted a large, national sample but barred discussion with participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Still, this study, the first of its kind in the United States, situates the responses within a framework of social theory and contributes to a richer understanding of what shapes the ED experiences of TGGNC-historied persons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s008"><title><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>As the frontline of protection for the nation's public health, U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>ED providers must be prepared to serve the most vulnerable and high-risk populations: ED visits can be unique opportunities to link marginalized patients to needed social and medical resources with the purpose of comprehensively improving the health of communities.15 This study demonstrates that TGGNC-historied patients in the United States have negative and alienating ED experiences, which they attribute to lack of provider training on care provision for this population. Table 5 lists resources clinicians may find useful in learning more about TGGNC healthcare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Further research is needed to examine interventions that may strengthen EDs' ability to function as the safety net for this socially and economically marginalized group with significant health concerns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Educational Resources </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left"/><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>“Affirmative Care for Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming People: Best Practices for Front-line Healthcare Staff,” by the National LGBT Health Education Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Available at: www.lgbthealtheducation.org/wp-content/uploads/13-017_TransBestPracticesforFrontlineStaff_v9_04-30-13.pdf </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>“Understanding Transgender: Frequently Asked Questions about Transgender People,” by the National Center for Transgender Equality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Available at: http://transequality.org/issues/resources/understanding-transgender-people-faq </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>“Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender-Nonconforming People.” World Professional Association for Transgender Health, 7th Version, 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Available at: www.wpath.org </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>“Transgender Patients in the ED.” Emergency Physicians Monthly, August 19, 2015. Available at: http://epmonthly.com/article/transgender-patients-in-the-ed/ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s009"><title><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Contributor Acknowledgments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Qualitative research consultants: Marina Catallozzi, MD, Timothy D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Cunningham, MSN, RN; Survey Development: Gavriel Ansara, PhD, MSc, Maddie Deutsch, MD, Alex Gonzalez, MD, MPH, Eva Hersch, MD, Ruben Hopwood, MDiv, PhD, Asa Radix, MD, MPH, Lynne D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Richardson, MD, Norman Spack, MD; Recruiting Organizations: Callen-Lorde Community Health Center, New York; Gay Central Valley, California; GLBT Advocacy and Youth Services, Inc., Alabama; Mazzoni Family and Community Medicine, Pennsylvania; Oasis Youth Center, Washington; SAGE Metro, Michigan; The Gay &amp; Lesbian Community Center, Pennsylvania. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s010" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Author Disclosure Statement</title><p>No competing financial interests exist.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="parsed"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>1AnsaraYG, HegartyP Methodologies of misgendering: recommendations for reducing cisgenderism in psychological research. Feminism Psychol. 2014;24:259–270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>2ScheimAI, BauerGR Sex and gender diversity among transgender persons in Ontario, Canada: results from a respondent-driven sampling survey. J Sex Res. 2015;52:1–1424750105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>3Understanding Transgender: Frequently Asked Questions About Transgender People. A Resource from the National Center for Transgender Equality, 5 2009 Available at: http://transequality.org/Resources/index.html (last accessed 923, 2014) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>4GrantJM, MottetLA, TanisJ Injustice at Every Turn, A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>The National Center for Transgender Equality and the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force. 2011 Available at: www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf (accessed 124, 2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>5KochanekKD, MurphySL, AndersonRN, ScottC Deaths: final data for 2002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>National Vital Statistics Reports, 53 (5). Hyattsville, MD: National Center for Health Statistics, 2004 DHHS Publication No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(PHS) 2005-1120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>6LombardiEL, WilchinsRA, PriesingD, MaloufD Gender violence: transgender experiences with violence and discrimination. J Homosex. 2001;42:89–10111991568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>7ClarkTC, LucassenMFG, BullenP, et al. The health and well-being of transgender high school students: results from the New Zealand adolescent health survey (Youth’12). J Adolesc Health. 2014;55:93–9924438852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>8ShermanMD, KauthMR, ShipherdJC, StreetRLJr Communication between VA providers and sexual and gender minority veterans: a pilot study. Psychol Serv. 2014;11:235–24224588107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>9WhittleS, TurnerL, CombsR, RhodesS Transgender EuroStudy: Legal Survey and Focus on the Transgender Experience of Health Care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>ILGA-Europe. 2008 Available at: www.ilga-europe.org/resources/ilga-europe-reports-and-other-materials/transgender-eurostudy-legal-survey-and-focus (accessed 124, 2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>10PittsMK, CouchM, MulcareH, et al. Transgender people in Australia and New Zealand: health, well-being and access to health services. Feminism Pyschol. 2009;19:475–495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>11BauerGR, HammondR, TraversR, et al. ‘I don't think this is theoretical; this is our lives’: how erasure impacts health care for transgender people. J Assoc Nurses AIDS Care. 2009;20:348–36119732694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>12The State of Transgender California Report. Results from the 2008 California Transgender Economic Health Survey. San Francisco, CA: The Transgender Law Center </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>13BrownJF, FuJ Emergency department avoidance by transgender persons: another broken thread in the ‘safety net’ of emergency medicine care. Ann Emerg Med. 2014;63:721–72224342814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>14BauerGR, ScheimAI, DeutschMB, MassarellaC Reported emergency department avoidance, use, and experiences of transgender persons in Ontario, Canada: results from a respondent-driven sampling survey. Ann Emerg Med. 2014;63:713–72024184160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>15MarxJA The rightness of emergency medicine. J Emerg Med. 2004;27:307–31215388223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>16Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (COBRA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Pub Law No 99-272, Title IX, Section 9121, 100 Stat 167 (1986) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>17MarcoCA, DavisA, ChangS, et al. ED patient satisfaction: factors associated with satisfaction with care. Am J Emerg Med. 2015;33:1708–170926364146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>18Philadelphia Trans-Health Conference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Available at: www.trans-health.org (accessed 111, 2016) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>19Physical Activity and Health: A Report of the Surgeon General. National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Available at: www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/sgr/chap6.htm (last accessed 1010, 2014) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>20PoteatT, GermanD, KerriganD Managing uncertainty: a grounded theory of stigma in transgender health care encounters. Soc Sci Med. 2013;84:22–2923517700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>21NVivo Qualitative Data Analysis Software; QSR International Pty Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Version 10. 2014 Available at: www.qsrinternational.com/what-is-nvivo (accessed 124, 2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>22LincolnYS, GubaEG Naturalistic Inquiry. Newbury Park CA: Sage Publications 1985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="?"><plain>23KilaruAS, MeiselZF, PaciottiB, et al. What do patients say about emergency departments in online reviews? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>A qualitative study. BMJ Qual Saf. 2015;25:14–24 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>24MessinaG, VenciaF, MecheroniS, et al. Factors affecting patient satisfaction with emergency department care: an Italian rural hospital. Glob J Health Sci. 2014;7:30–39 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>25MorganMW, SalzmanJG, LeFevereRC, et al. Demographic, operational, and healthcare utilization factors associated with emergency department patient satisfaction. West J Emerg Med. 2015;16:516–52626265963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>26TaylorC, BengerJR Patient satisfaction in emergency medicine. Emerg Med J. 2004;21:528–53215333521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>27KardanmoghadamV, MovahedniaN, MovahedniaM, et al. Determining patients' satisfaction level with hospital emergency rooms in Iran: a meta-analysis. Glob J Health Sci. 2015;7:260–269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>28SimpsonO Consent and assessment of capacity to decide or refuse treatment. Br J Nurs. 2011;20:510–51321537284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>29TaylorH Determining capacity to consent to treatment. Nurs Times. 2013;109:12–14 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>30AbdalrahamanIB, OsmanAM, AliBM, et al. Autonomy and confidentiality: patients' perspectives. Trop Doct. 2014;45:79–8325540168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><ref-list><p><bold>Cite this article as:</bold> Chisolm-Straker M, Jardine L, Bennouna C, Morency-Brassard N, Coy L, Egemba MO, Shearer PL (2017) Transgender and gender nonconforming in emergency departments: a qualitative report of patient experiences, <italic>Transgender Health</italic> 2:1, 8–16, DOI: 10.1089/trgh.2016.0026.</p></ref-list><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations Used</title><def-list><def-item><term id="G1">EDs</term><def><p>Emergency Departments</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">SCT</term><def><p>social cognitive theory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">TGGNC</term><def><p>transgender or gender nonconforming</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><sec id="s011"><title/><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><label><sup>*</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Transgender “life experience” and “history,” instead of transgender “identity,” is used in this article based upon validation survey feedback from experienced leaders in the TGGNC health field: “Transgender” describes an experience, not necessarily an identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>It was noted that “being transgender” leaves out people who simply identify as one gender, but were formerly recognized as another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>For example, one might identify as male, but was once recognized as female; such a man may not identify as “transgender,” only as male. “History” and “life experience” were suggested for use as more encompassing of the ways in which people understand themselves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="other"><label><sup>†</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>www.Facebook.com/TGinED </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn3" fn-type="other"><label><sup>‡</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>NVivo is software designed to help qualitative investigators organize, conceptualize, and understand raw, unstructured data such as participant survey responses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn4" fn-type="other"><label><sup>§</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>FTM: Female to Male. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn5" fn-type="other"><label><sup>**</sup></label><p><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>“Cisgender” describes a person whose performed gender conforms to his or her assigned gender at birth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></sec></back></article>
