<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JMIR Res Protoc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JMIR Res Protoc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ResProt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JMIR Research Protocols</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1929-0748</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5962829</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">v7i5e124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/resprot.8827</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Protocol</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Effect of Rebound Exercises and Circuit Training on Complications Associated with Type 2 Diabetes: Protocol for a Randomized Controlled Trial </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Eysenbach</surname><given-names>Gunther</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Pefile</surname><given-names>Ntsikelelo</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Akindele</surname><given-names>Mukadas</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Umar</surname><given-names>Badaru</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kaka</surname><given-names>Bashir</given-names></name><degrees>BSc (Hons), MSc, PhD, PT</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><address><institution>Discipline of Physiotherapy</institution><institution>School of Health Sciences, College of Health Sciences</institution><institution>University of KwaZulu-Natal</institution><addr-line>Block E-5</addr-line><addr-line>University road</addr-line><addr-line>Durban, 4000</addr-line><country>South Africa</country><phone>27 312607938 ext 7938</phone><fax>27 312607938</fax><email>bkaka.pth@buk.edu.ng</email></address><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9138-0675</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Maharaj</surname><given-names>Sonill Sooknunan</given-names></name><degrees>BPaed Sc, BEd, BPhysio, MMedSci (Sports Medicine), PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8288-6105</contrib-id></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Discipline of Physiotherapy</institution>
<institution>School of Health Sciences, College of Health Sciences</institution>
<institution>University of KwaZulu-Natal</institution>
<addr-line>Durban</addr-line>
<country>South Africa</country></aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding Author: Bashir Kaka
<email>bkaka.pth@buk.edu.ng</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e124</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©Bashir Kaka, Sonill Sooknunan Maharaj. Originally published in JMIR Research Protocols (http://www.researchprotocols.org), 07.05.2018.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in JMIR Research Protocols, is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.researchprotocols.org,">http://www.researchprotocols.org,</ext-link> as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.researchprotocols.org/2018/5/e124/"/><abstract><sec sec-type="background"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The incidence of type 2 diabetes mellitus, a chronic lifestyle disease, and its complications are on the rise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Exercise has been documented as being effective in the management of musculoskeletal pain, depression, and reduction of hyperglycemia in diabetic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, there is no consensus regarding the types of exercise that reduce musculoskeletal pain and depression and improve quality of life as well as respiratory function among individuals with type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study is to determine the effects of rebound and circuit training on musculoskeletal pain, blood glucose level, cholesterol level, quality of life, depression, and respiratory parameters in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A total of 70 participants are expected to be recruited in this single blind randomized controlled trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Computer-generated random numbers will be used to randomize the participants into 3 groups, namely, the rebound exercise group, the circuit exercise group, and the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Measurements will be taken at baseline and at the end of the 8 weeks of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Participants’ musculoskeletal pain will be assessed using the visual analog scale, quality of life will be assessed using the SF 12 Health Survey Questionnaire, depression using the Beck Depression Inventory, respiratory parameters using the spirometer, and biochemical parameters such as glucose level and cholesterol level using the glucometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Data will be analyzed using descriptive statistics and inferential statistics of multivariate analysis of variance between the groups and paired t test within the group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Alpha will be set at .05. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The results of this study will identify the effectiveness of rebound exercise and circuit training, compared with the control, in the management of type 2 diabetes mellitus and on quality of life, musculoskeletal pain, depression, glycemic control, cholesterol level, as well as improvement in respiratory function. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Though different additional strategies such as exercise and dietary and lifestyle modifications exist for the control of type 2 diabetes, they are mostly applied for the control of glucose level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>No strategies have been identified for the control of complications associated with diabetes such as musculoskeletal pain, depression, and reduction in quality of life. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="Trial Registration"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Trial Registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Clinicaltrials.gov NCT03200795; https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03200795 (Archived by WebCite at http://www.webcitation.org/6mBgcj6z7) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>diabetes</kwd><kwd>musculoskeletal pain</kwd><kwd>exercise</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Overview </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Diabetes is a global epidemic disease [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The global prevalence of diabetics is currently estimated to be 415 million and is projected to rise to over 642 million by the year 2040, with Asians suffering the bulk of the total diabetes epidemic [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The International Diabetes Federation (IDF) estimated that there were 14.2 million diabetes patients living in Africa in 2015, excluding the 67% of patients that are undiagnosed, and the projection rate is expected to rise to 34.2 million by 2040 [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>South Africa is among the most populous African countries with the highest number of people with diabetes with 2.3 million people, followed by Democratic Republic of Congo 1.8 million, Nigeria 1.6 million, and Ethiopia 1.3 million. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Nearly half of the adults with diabetes live in these countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In South Africa, the prevalence of diabetes mellitus (DM) is estimated to be about 6%, excluding the undiagnosed cases, whereas 9% of the population has prediabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>DM accounts for 58 deaths daily and is the fifth highest cause of natural deaths [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The highest prevalence of diabetes is among the Indian population (11%-13%), as this group has a strong genetic predisposition to diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This is followed by 8% to 10% in the colored community, 5% to 8% among blacks, and 4% among whites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of diabetes in the public health sector of KwaZulu-Natal was found to be 14.3% higher than the national prevalence estimates [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Diabetes is a systemic disease that affects multiple body functions and structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The typical spectrum of problems of patients with DM can now be defined based on the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>For practical purposes and in line with the concept of condition-specific health status measures, DM problems can be classified as follows: body function as hematological system function, sensation of pain, musculoskeletal system, and respiratory system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>On the basis of activities and participation restriction, DM problems can be classified as quality of life (QoL) and psychosocial factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These will serve as a guide in clinical studies with DM or as a guide to multidisciplinary assessments in patients with DM [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In 2004, the US National Health Interview Survey reported that 58% of diabetic patients would have a functional disability [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The percentage of diabetic patients with a functional disability will increase as the number of diabetic patients increases and will constitute a major public health problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Recent data show that the prevalence of musculoskeletal pain (MSKP) manifestations in the hands and shoulders in patients with type 1 or type 2 diabetes is 30%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>These manifestations are closely linked to age [6] and prolonged disease duration [7,8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Musculoskeletal disorders are very common in diabetes and are associated with poor glycemic control and more complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Assessment of musculoskeletal disorders among diabetics should include an estimate of cholesterol, glycemic control, MSKP, respiratory parameters, and QoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>People with diabetes are at twice as high a risk of suffering from premorbid depression as the general population [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The coexistence of depression in people with diabetes catalyzes serious disease comorbidities, MSKP, decreased respiratory capacity, poor glycemic control which may lead to hyperlipidemia and poor QoL, and escalated health care expenditures [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Depressive symptoms are more likely to persist among persons with multiple diabetic-related complications such as musculoskeletal disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Increase in pain may lead to increased depression and reduction in respiratory capacity and QoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown that both exercises and pharmacotherapy [10] can decrease depression and improve glycemic control and overall QoL in persons with diabetes and thus, in addition, provide substantial financial savings and improved medical care for these individuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Exercise, in addition to diet modification and medication, has long been recommended as one of the 3 main components of diabetic therapy [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The low cost and nonpharmacological nature of exercise enhances its therapeutic appeal among type 2 diabetic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Published exercise intervention trials [12-15], using different types of intervention, usually have small sample sizes and the findings of their studies have varied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The optimal type, frequency, intensity, and duration of exercise for achieving therapeutic goals in type 2 diabetes are not known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The psychosocial variables and cardiorespiratory-related health of diabetics appear to be underexplored in exercise-related interventions [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Moreover, prospective randomized controlled trials (RCTs) on the effects of exercise in the prevention or treatment of musculoskeletal complications and disability seen in diabetes patients are needed [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Exercise has been documented as effective in the management of MSKP; however, there is no consensus regarding the type of exercises that improve MSKP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The effectiveness of exercise in reducing MSKP as well as depression and in improving respiratory function among individuals with type 2 diabetes has not been documented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Rebound exercise is a type of exercise that can aid the management of type 2 diabetes [17] and is likely to improve MSKP and depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Circuit resistance training (CRT) has recently been documented to be safe in the management of type 2 diabetes; however, its effects on MSKP and depression have not been assessed [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Rebound exercise on the mini trampoline moves all parts of the body at once, so it is also called cellular exercise [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>It may be superior to any other type of exercise as it utilizes gravity and forces of acceleration and deceleration so that at the top of the bounce one experiences weightlessness and at the bottom the weight doubles pulling into the center of the rebounder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Rebound exercise is also a form of aerobic exercise that increases oxygen consumption and stimulates immune response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Circuit training is a combination of strength training and aerobic exercises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Strengthening exercise is a resistance exercise that helps to keep the muscles flexible and strong and also strengthens the bones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Aerobic exercise, on the other hand, is a less vigorous exercise that increases oxygen consumption; the increase in oxygen consumption helps to burn more calories and stimulates immune response and cardiovascular health [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Rehabilitation can assist to retain physical and functional abilities as well as control psychological emotions [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Therefore, comprehensive rehabilitation to manage diabetes-related complications that encompasses exercises such as rebound and circuit training may improve glycemic control, reduce depression, and improve QoL and musculoskeletal functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Theoretical Framework </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have assessed the effect of combined resistance and aerobic exercises on type 2 DM patients and observed significant reductions in HbA1c [21-23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>However, Geirsdottir et al [24] did not observe any favorable changes in fasting glucose or HbA1c in patients with type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there is no consensus on the effect of CRT in type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Rebound exercise has been documented to be effective in reducing plasma fasting glucose, HbA1c, and body mass index (BMI) in type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>It is also simple, inexpensive and enjoyable [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it has been documented to improve QoL in patients with type 2 diabetes [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>However, its effect on MSKP, respiratory parameters, and depression has not been documented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Prospective RCTs on the effects of exercise in the prevention or treatment of musculoskeletal complications, cardiorespiratory parameters, and psychosocial variables seen in diabetes patients are needed [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In African countries, there is a paucity of reports that describe musculoskeletal disorders in diabetic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, no clinical trial has been conducted that compares the effect of rebound exercises and circuit training on MSKP, respiratory parameters, and psychosocial variables among patients with type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>No previous studies had been conducted to assess the effect of any treatment or prevalence of MSKP manifestations in diabetic patients or to evaluate the predisposing factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This study is, therefore, proposed to determine the effect of rebound exercises and circuit training on MSKP, as well as selected biochemical and psychosocial factors among individuals with type 2 diabetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The objective of this research is to investigate the effect of rebound exercises and circuit training and compare them to the routine care of type 2 diabetic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The objectives of this research are as follows; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of rebound exercises on glycemic control, cholesterol level, respiratory parameters, pain scores, depression, and QoL among type 2 diabetes patients </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of CRT on glycemic control, cholesterol level, respiratory parameters, pain scores, depression, and QoL among type 2 diabetes patients </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of routine care (control group) on glycemic control, cholesterol level, respiratory parameters, pain scores, depression, and QoL among type 2 diabetes patients </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To compare the effect of circuit training, rebound exercises, and routine care on glycemic control, cholesterol level, respiratory parameters, pain scores, depression, and QoL among type 2 diabetes patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Study Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The study is a single-blind, parallel RCT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>RCTs are quantitative, comparative, controlled experiments in which investigators study 2 or more interventions in a series of individuals who receive them in random order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The RCT is one of the simplest and most powerful tools in clinical research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The participants for the study will be patients diagnosed with type 2 diabetes by the attending physician at King Edward Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Participants will be considered eligible if they have been diagnosed with type 2 diabetes for at least 4 years and have been on oral hypoglycemic control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>They will be recruited consecutively as they are available through the outpatient endocrinology clinic of the hospital by a member of the research team. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Only participants with MSKP and depression will be included in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>They will be screened for MSKP using the Nordic Musculoskeletal Symptoms Questionnaire and for depression using the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The participants must be aged between 20 and 55 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Those within this age limit are considered to be adults with musculoskeletal affectation, as indicated by Nordic Musculoskeletal Symptom Questionnaire, and with at least ≥11 score on the BDI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Only participants who meet the inclusion criteria will be considered for the randomization into the groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The consent of the participants will be sought before they participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Patients will be excluded from the study if they are involved in sporting activities or if their musculoskeletal problems are severe and may prevent them from performing some of the exercises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Moreover, individuals with hypertension, coronary artery disease, or myocardial infarction; or who have had cardiac or abdominal surgery within the previous 6 months; or who have a history of fractures of the spine, hip, knee, or ankle joints; as well as those with lower limb weakness and deformities with a loss of protective sensation in the feet will be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Similarly, pregnancy or lactation, use of insulin, and the presence of retinopathy or nephropathy will make a patient ineligible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Finally, subjects who do not consent to participate will be excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Participants who meet the inclusion criteria will be randomized into 1 of the 3 groups of the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Setting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The research will be conducted at the Performance Laboratory of the Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The participants will be recruited from the King Edward Hospital, Durban. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>King Edward Hospital is a tertiary hospital that provides specialist services to the people of KwaZulu-Natal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>It is located in Durban City, Ethekwini Municipality, KwaZulu-Natal Province, South Africa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Study Team </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The study team will consist of 4 physiotherapists, of which 2 are clinicians and the other 2 are both clinicians and researchers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The team will also include an endocrinologist who is a physician with 10 years of research experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In addition, 2 among the physiotherapists will be research assistants and they will administer the treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The endocrinologist will screen the patients and ensure that they take the same medications and that they are medically fit, whereas the researchers will screen the participants to ensure that they meet the inclusion criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The study will comprise 3 groups; the rebound exercise group, the circuit resistance exercise training group, and the routine care group (the control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The routine care group will undergo one exercise training after 8 weeks of enrollment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Participants will be monitored for subjective fatigue, dyspnea, respiratory distress, profuse sweating, or unsteady gait during the exercise activities, as these may be indications that they have reached maximum exertion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Rebound Exercise Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Participants randomized to this group will be instructed on the proper techniques of the desired movements (hopping) on the rebounder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>All instruction and training will be provided by the research assistants who are physiotherapists practicing in South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>They will teach the participants how to rebound during the session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>To ensure exercise endurance, patients allocated to this group will complete a 6-min walk test (6MWT), as prescribed by the American Thoracic Society [25], which will be conducted along a straight 40-m Department of Physiotherapy passageway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>On successful completion of the 6MWT, patients will be given an opportunity to familiarize themselves with the equipment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Each participant will undergo 3 sessions a week for 8 weeks, with each session lasting between 15 and 25 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The exercise will involve bouncing on the center portion of a mini trampoline (2013 Portable Model Half-Fold Cellerciser) with feet slightly apart and knees in full extension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Each foot strike equals one step or bounce with step height. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>This will be defined as the distance between the foot at a maximum height of the jump and the bed of the center of the trampoline ranging between 10 and 15 cm [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Exercise durations were set at 5-min intervals with 3-min rest periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Each exercise program session will last 15 min with 9 min of rest for the first 4 weeks, progressing to 25 min with 15 min of rest in the subsequent 4 weeks, 3 times per week over 8 weeks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Bouncing frequency will be determined by signals from a metronome and will be set at between 90 and 120 bounces per minute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Heart rate training zone will be maintained during the exercise at a moderate intensity of 40% to 60% and will be calculated using the Karvonen formula ([heart rate reserve×training percentage]+resting heart rate) [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The heart rate will be monitored using the heart rate monitor (Polar Electro Oy) that will display the participant’s heart rate and emit a warning signal if the heart rate goes outside the prescribed training zone, thus serving as a guide and indicator for the participant to adjust the steps and bounce while on the trampoline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In addition, the Borg scale will be used to assess the rate of perceived exertion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Circuit Exercise Group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The circuit exercise for the participants in this group will be designed for each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To ensure exercise endurance, patients allocated to this group will complete a 6MWT, as prescribed by the American Thoracic Society [25], which will be conducted along a straight 40-m Department of Physiotherapy passageway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>On successful completion of the 6MWT, patients will be given an opportunity to familiarize themselves with the circuit exercise equipment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Exercise sessions will take place 3 times a week for 8 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The participants will undergo 10 min of warm up before and 10 min of cool down after the training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The stations for circuit training include 2 stations—1 and 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Station 1 is the resistance exercise, whereas station 2 is the aerobic exercise with the bicycle ergometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Station 1 comprises the following 6 substations: station A—bench press, station B—seated row, station C—lateral pull down, station D—biceps forward, station E—front thigh and back thigh, and station F—leg press. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Resistance exercises will be performed on weight machines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Throughout the resistance training program, participants will rotate among the different machines until they have used every one: the bench press, seated row, lateral pull down, biceps forward, front thigh, back thigh, leg press, and rowing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Participants will be instructed to exhale while lifting a weight and inhale while lowering it, to minimize blood pressure excursions, and to rest for 2-3 min between sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Participants will perform 1 set of resistance exercise 3 times weekly for the first 2 weeks, 4 sets of each resistance exercise 3 times weekly during weeks 3 and 4, and complete set of resistance exercise in the last 4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>For each station, the participants will spend 10 min; this includes the substations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Resistance will be increased by 5-10 kg, once the participant is able to perform more than 15 repetitions while maintaining proper form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>All the aerobic activities of the circuit training will be performed on a cycle ergometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Participants will be free to vary the machine used from one visit to the next. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Exercise intensity will be standardized by using heart rate monitors (Polar Electro Oy) that will display the participant’s heart rate and emit a warning signal if the heart rate goes outside the prescribed training zone, thus guiding the participant to adjust the workload up or down to achieve the desired intensity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In addition, the rate of perceived exertion will be measured using the Borg scale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The Routine Care Group (Control Group) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Participants in the control group will receive routine medication as prescribed by the attending physicians at the diabetes clinic and will be monitored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Their prescriptions will be guided by the IDF guidelines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>After 8 weeks of routine care, the participants will be enrolled into either the rebound exercise or circuit exercise group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The control group will be given health magazines to read, whereas the exercise groups will be engaged in the exercise programs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>All the 3 groups will receive routine medication and counseling regarding diet, weight control, and information to identify, minimize, or avoid complications of diabetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The following measurement would be taken during the data collection they are as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic variables: The sociodemographic variables of the participants will be recorded before the commencement of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>These include age, race, gender, height, weight, educational level, duration of diabetes, level of pain, blood pressure, pulse rate, and heart rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Pain intensity: The alternate visual analog scale will be used to assess the pain level of the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The participants will be requested to rate on a 0-10 scale, the level of pain they felt 6 weeks before and at present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>On the scale, 0 indicates no pain or no interference, whereas 10 is pain as bad as it could be/extreme interference [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The alternate visual analogue scale has been reported to have a high validity, increased patient compliance, greater sensitivity of measurement, and reduced bias [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>BDI: This will be used to assess and screen participants for depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The BDI is a 21-item multiple choice self-reported inventory, widely used to assess the presence and degree of depression in adolescents and adults [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The BDI is a self-administered questionnaire and it has a high test-retest reliability (Pearson r). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>QoL: The General Health Survey Short Form (SF-36) will be used to measure changes in the participant’s QoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The instrument has shown good validity and reliability of Cronbach alpha of .85 and reliability coefficient of .75 for all the domains except social functioning [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The short form, SF-36, measures perceived health in the areas of physical functioning, role-physical, bodily pain, general health, vitality, social functioning, role-emotional, and mental health, with higher scores (range 0-100) reflecting better-perceived health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Biochemical parameters: Fasting blood glucose in mmol/L, blood total cholesterol (TC) in mmol/L, low-density lipoprotein (LDL) mmol/L, very low-density lipoproteins (VLDL) mmol/L, and high-density lipoprotein (HDL) mmol/L will be determined at baseline and after 8 weeks of the program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A blood sample will be taken by pinprick using Accu-check Sofclix Pro Roche Diabetes care, South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Then, the following parameters will be evaluated: fasting glucose level using Accutrend (Roche Diagnostics, GmbH Germany); HDL-C using PEG þ cholesterol oxidase (Roche Diagnostics GmbH Germany); triglycerides using glycerol phosphate-PAP (Roche Diagnostics GmbH Germany); and TC using cholesterol oxidase-PAP (Roche Diagnostics GmbH Germany) to evaluate TC, LDL, VLDL, and HDL-C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Pulmonary parameters: Pulmonary function parameters will be measured at baseline and after the 8 weeks of the study using Spiro 232 (PK Morgan, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The following parameters will be measured: Forced expiratory volume in first second (FEV1) (It), forced vital capacity (FVC), FEV1/FVC ratio, peak expiratory flow rate, and maximal voluntary ventilation (It/min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The spirometer will be connected to a computer that will record all the values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Sample Size and Power Calculation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The sample size (N) will be determined using Cohen table [29] at alpha=.05 and degree of freedom (µ)=k−1, where k is the number of groups, with effect size f=0.35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>From the previous study [17] and power (w) 80%, sample size n=20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Sample size (N) will be 60, and 12 extra participants will be added to make room for attrition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the sample size will be 72 participants, and each group will be 24 participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Randomization and Blinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Randomization will be conducted using a computer-generated random allocation sequence schedule conducted by a physiotherapist who is not involved in the research and has experience in research, who will randomly allocate recruited participants into the rebound exercise group, circuit training group, and the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>To eliminate bias, the assessment of outcome will be performed by experienced assessors who will be blinded to the type of intervention as well as the intervention groups of the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Participants will also be instructed not to disclose their individual intervention groups to the assessors. Figure 1 shows the flow diagram. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Assessment of participants will be conducted at 2 stages: at baseline and at the end of 8 weeks of intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>To ensure a comprehensive assessment, a battery of measures was chosen covering the WHO-ICF model [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Certain tools were selected to cover the 3 key domains proposed by the ICF: body structures and function (hematological variables, MSKP, and respiratory parameters), activity, and participation (QoL and depression). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>At baseline, participants will be assessed for sociodemographic characteristics, which will include personal demographic information and diabetes-specific information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The personal demographic information will include age, sex, height, weight, marital status, educational qualification, and employment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The diabetes-specific information will include type of diabetes and duration since diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>At the baseline, the outcome measures to be used for these assessments are presented in the measurement section. Table 1 shows the instruments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Data Management </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Data from the trial will be monitored by regularly scrutinizing data files for omissions and errors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>All manually entered data will be double entered, and the source of any inconsistencies will be explored and resolved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Electronic data will be stored on password-protected servers at the Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal, Durban, and written forms and data will be stored in locked filing cabinets at the Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal, Durban. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Data will only be accessible to the researcher. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Each participant in the study will be provided with an identification number. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>All recorded data will be coded using this number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="figure1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>CONSORT flow chart. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="resprot_v7i5e124_fig1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Study assessment tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="200" span="1"/><col width="800" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Scales or tools </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Function or applications </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Metronome </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To provide signals for participants during exercises </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Mini trampoline </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>For rebound exercise </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Treadmill </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>For aerobic component of circuit training </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Biodata form </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>To record the sociodemographic variables of participants </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Alternate visual analog scale </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>To assess change in pain scores of participants </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Beck Depression Inventory </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>To assess change in depression of participants </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>General health survey short form (SF-36) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>To assess change in quality of life of participants </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Accutrend plus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>To assess the fasting glucose-level change and cholesterol-level change in participants </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Spiro232 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The spirometer will be used to measure change in forced expiratory volume, forced vital capacity, peak expiratory flow rate, and maximal voluntary ventilation </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Data Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Preliminary analysis will be performed to test the normality of the data using the Kolmogorov V-Smirnov test before the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Demographic data will be analyzed using descriptive statistics, whereas data on QoL and depression will be analyzed within the group using the Wilcoxon signed rank test and between the groups using the Kruskal-Wallis test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Post hoc test will be used for any significant F values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The paired t test will be used within the group for pain scores, fasting glucose, and cholesterol level of the participants and between groups using 1-way multivariate analysis of variance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Post hoc test will be used for any significant F values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The level of significance will be set at .05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The SPSS version 23 will be used for the analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Ethics and Informed Consent </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Ethical approval was sought and obtained from the University of KwaZulu-Natal Biomedical Research Ethics Committee South Africa (BREC/BF/371/17) and registered with Clinicaltrials.gov: NCT03200795. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Informed consent will also be obtained from the participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The results of this study are expected to provide additional information on the effect of rebound exercise and circuit training in the management of patients with musculoskeletal complications of diabetes in South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>It is hoped that it will lead to improvement in the QoL, reduction in MSKP and depression, improvement in glycemic control, reduction in cholesterol level, as well as improvement in respiratory capacity of type 2 diabetes patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>It is also expected to give information about which of the exercises is most effective in the management of patients with musculoskeletal diabetes complications in terms of pain relief, glycemic control, cholesterol level, improvement in QoL, level of depression, and respiratory capacity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Though different additional strategies such as exercise and dietary and lifestyle modifications exist for the control of type 2 diabetes, they are mostly applied for the control of glucose level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>No strategies have been identified for the control of complications associated with diabetes such as MSKP, depression, and reduction in the QoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>To date no additional rehabilitation [31] that is aimed at alleviating MSKP associated with diabetes complication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Exercises in the management of type 2 DM are of different type of different modes and intensity, most of the exercises are aerobic in nature and involves weight bearing, and strength training, mostly targeted for glycemic control, cholesterol, and few in QoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Exercises that are nonweight bearing, such as rebound exercises, and that require less equipment are used in the management of type 2 diabetes [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Studies on rebound exercises mostly focus on the glycemic control and change in cholesterol level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>This trial is focused on the effect of exercises such as rebound exercise on respiratory parameters, MSKP, and QoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The current literature suggests that emphasis in any current trial in the management of type 2 DM should focus on QoL, respiratory capacity, and psychosocial variables [32-34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Moreover, if studies on exercises among patients with diabetes focus on respiratory and musculoskeletal complications, they are likely to result in improved functions and reduce complications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The possible limitation of this protocol is that it is limited to the short-term effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>It is hoped that subsequent trials will look into the long-term effect of both rebound exercise and circuit training in the management of MSKP associated with diabetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the College of Health Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal, for supporting the research financially. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Conflicts of Interest: None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="abb1">BDI</term><def><p>Beck Depression Inventory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb2">DM</term><def><p>diabetes mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb3">FEV</term><def><p>forced expiratory volume</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb4">FVC</term><def><p>forced vital capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb5">HDL</term><def><p>high-density lipoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb6">ICF</term><def><p>International Classification of Functioning Disability and Health</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb7">IDF</term><def><p>International Diabetes Federation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb8">LDL</term><def><p>low-density lipoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb9">MSKP</term><def><p>musculoskeletal pain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb10">6MWT</term><def><p>6 min walk test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb11">QoL</term><def><p>quality of life</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb12">RCT</term><def><p>randomized controlled trial</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb13">SF-36</term><def><p>short form 36</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb14">VLDL</term><def><p>very low-density lipoprotein</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>1AroraEShenoySSandhuJSEffects of resistance training on metabolic profile of adults with type 2 diabetesIndian J Med Res20095129551591967537819675378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref2"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>2International Diabetes Federation20178022018-04-28IDF Diabetes Atlas - 8th Edition <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetesatlas.org/resources/2017-atlas.html">http://diabetesatlas.org/resources/2017-atlas.html</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="webcite" xlink:href="6z0izrOsb"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref3"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>3PillaySLutgeEAldousCThe burden of diabetes mellitus in KwaZulu-Natal’s public sector: a 5-year perspectiveS Afr Med J20163171064384510.7196/SAMJ.2016.v106i4.9920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref4"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>4RuofJCiezaAWolffBAngstFErgeletzisDOmarZKostanjsekNStuckiGICF core sets for diabetes mellitusJ Rehabil Med2004744 Suppl1006<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.medicaljournals.se/jrm/content/abstract/10.1080/16501960410016802"/>10.1080/165019604100168021537075615370756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref5"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>5EgedeLEEllisCDiabetes and depression: global perspectivesDiabetes Res Clin Pract201038733021210.1016/j.diabres.2010.01.0242018140520181405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref6"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>6ArdicFSoyupekFKahramanYYorganciogluRThe musculoskeletal complications seen in type II diabetics: predominance of hand involvementClin Rheumatol200392232293310.1007/s10067-003-0704-71450521714505217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref7"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>7AydenizAGursoySGuneyEWhich musculoskeletal complications are most frequently seen in type 2 diabetes mellitus?J Int Med Res20083635051110.1177/1473230008036003151853413218534132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref8"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>8CrispinJCAlcocer-VarelaJRheumatologic manifestations of diabetes mellitusAm J Med2003615114975371282920212829202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref9"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>9GanasegeranKRajendranAKAl-DubaiSAPsycho-socioeconomic factors affecting complementary and alternative medicine use among selected rural communities in Malaysia: a cross-sectional studyPLoS One2014911e112124<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0112124"/>10.1371/journal.pone.01121242537525625375256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref10"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>10MustafaKNKhaderYSBsoulAKAjlouniKMusculoskeletal disorders of the hand in type 2 diabetes mellitus: prevalence and its associated factorsInt J Rheum Dis20167197730510.1111/1756-185X.126172625914826259148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref11"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>11ThomasDEElliottEJNaughtonGAExercise for type 2 diabetes mellitusCochrane Database Syst Rev20067193CD00296810.1002/14651858.CD002968.pub21685599516855995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref12"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>12BaldiJCSnowlingNResistance training improves glycaemic control in obese type 2 diabetic menInt J Sports Med200382464192310.1055/s-2003-411731290508912905089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref13"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>13DelaFStallknechtBEffect of physical training on insulin secretion and action in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue of first-degree relatives of type 2 diabetic patientsAm J Physiol Endocrinol Metab201072991E8091<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.physiology.org/doi/abs/10.1152/ajpendo.00765.2009?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%3dpubmed"/>10.1152/ajpendo.00765.20092040700620407006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref14"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>14CuffDJMeneillyGSMartinAIgnaszewskiATildesleyHDFrohlichJJEffective exercise modality to reduce insulin resistance in women with type 2 diabetesDiabetes Care20031126112977821457822614578226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref15"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>15TessierDMénardJFülöpTArdilouzeJRoyMDubucNDuboisMGauthierPEffects of aerobic physical exercise in the elderly with type 2 diabetes mellitusArch Gerontol Geriatr200010013121211321109090711090907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref16"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>16ArdicFSoyupekFKahramanYYorganciogluRThe musculoskeletal complications seen in type II diabetics: predominance of hand involvementClin Rheumatol200392232293310.1007/s10067-003-0704-71450521714505217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref17"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>17MaharajSSNuhuJMThe effect of rebound exercise and treadmill walking on the quality of life for patients with non-insulin-dependent type 2 diabetesInt J Diabetes Dev Ctries201531435S222322910.1007/s13410-015-0350-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref18"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>18TobkinJHolistic Health Tools2018-04-10Rebounding Exercise - Getting a Jump on Great Health and Flexibility <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.holistichealthtools.com/rebound.html">http://www.holistichealthtools.com/rebound.html</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="webcite" xlink:href="6yZNacMCB"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref19"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>19HoffOMMidthjellKZwartJAHagenKThe association between diabetes mellitus, glucose, and chronic musculoskeletal complaints. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Results from the Nord-Trøndelag Health StudyBMC Musculoskelet Disord200812029160<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2474/9/160"/>10.1186/1471-2474-9-1601905573219055732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref20"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>20MandersonLWarrenNThe art of (re)learning to walk: trust on the rehabilitation wardQual Health Res201010201014183210.1177/10497323103731052055501220555012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref21"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>21MisraAAlappanNKVikramNKGoelKGuptaNMittalKBhattSLuthraKEffect of supervised progressive resistance-exercise training protocol on insulin sensitivity, glycemia, lipids, and body composition in Asian Indians with type 2 diabetesDiabetes Care2008731712827<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/18316394"/>10.2337/dc07-23161831639418316394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref22"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>22ChurchTSBlairSNCocrehamSJohannsenNJohnsonWKramerKMikusCRMyersVNautaMRodarteRQSparksLThompsonAEarnestCPEffects of aerobic and resistance training on hemoglobin A1c levels in patients with type 2 diabetes: a randomized controlled trialJ Am Med Assoc2010112430420225362<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/21098771"/>10.1001/jama.2010.171021098771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref23"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>23NuhuJMMaharajSSInfluence of a mini-trampoline rebound exercise program on insulin resistance, lipid profile and central obesity in individuals with type 2 diabetesJ Sports Med Phys Fitness2018458450350910.23736/S0022-4707.17.07120-12824938428249384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref24"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>24GeirsdottirOGArnarsonABriemKRamelAJonssonPVThorsdottirIEffect of 12-week resistance exercise program on body composition, muscle strength, physical function, and glucose metabolism in healthy, insulin-resistant, and diabetic elderly IcelandersJ Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci201211671112596510.1093/gerona/gls0962249653822496538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref25"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>25Pinto-PlataVMCoteCCabralHTaylorJCelliBRThe 6-min walk distance: change over time and value as a predictor of survival in severe COPDEur Respir J200412312833<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://erj.ersjournals.com/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=14738227"/>1473822714738227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref26"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>26OdoleACAkinpeluAOTranslation and alternate forms reliability of the Visual Analogue Scale in the three major Nigerian languagesInternet J Allied Health Sci Pract20097315<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nsuworks.nova.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1257&amp;context=ijahsp/"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref27"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>27BeckATSteerRABallRRanieriWComparison of Beck Depression Inventories -IA and -II in psychiatric outpatientsJ Pers Assess1996126735889710.1207/s15327752jpa6703_1389919728991972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref28"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>28MondJMitchisonDLatnerJHayPOwenCRodgersBQuality of life impairment associated with body dissatisfaction in a general population sample of womenBMC Public Health2013100313920<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcpublichealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2458-13-920"/>10.1186/1471-2458-13-9202408824824088248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref29"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>29CohenJStatistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences1977Cambridge, MassachusettsAcademic Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref30"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>30World Health Organization20012018-04-28The International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://psychiatr.ru/download/1313?view=name=CF_18.pdf">http://psychiatr.ru/download/1313?view=name=CF_18.pdf</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="webcite" xlink:href="6z0mXvDtl"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref31"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>31PefileNMothabengJNaidooSA multidisciplinary model to guide employment outcomes among people living with spinal cord injuries in South Africa: a mixed methods study protocolJMIR Res Protoc2016120654e238<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.researchprotocols.org/2016/4/e238/"/>10.2196/resprot.58872792377927923779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref32"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>32BrownJCeysensGBoulvainMExercise for pregnant women with gestational diabetes for improving maternal and fetal outcomesCochrane Database Syst Rev201712226CD01220210.1002/14651858.CD012202.pub22863970628639706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref33"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>33BarkiSKhanHMJilaniSMNooruddinMCommon musculoskeletal disorders in diabetes mellitus patientsPak J Rehabil2013215362<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.scribd.com/document/336189472/53-62-Barki-S-et-al-pdf"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref34"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>34MelinEOSvenssonRGustavssonSÅWinbergADenward-OlahELandin-OlssonMThulesiusHOAffect school and script analysis versus basic body awareness therapy in the treatment of psychological symptoms in patients with diabetes and high HbA1c concentrations: two study protocols for two randomized controlled trialsTrials2016427171221<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13063-016-1347-8"/>10.1186/s13063-016-1347-82712118527121185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
