<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Materials (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Materials (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">materials</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Materials</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1996-1944</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5457019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma9121002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">materials-09-01002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Cellulose Nanocrystal Membranes as Excipients for Drug Delivery Systems </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>Ananda M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-materials-09-01002">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-09-01002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-09-01002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>Juliana S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-materials-09-01002">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>Rafael G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-materials-09-01002">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carreño</surname><given-names>Neftali L. V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-materials-09-01002">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Labidi</surname><given-names>Jalel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-09-01002">2</xref><xref rid="c1-materials-09-01002" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Carofiglio</surname><given-names>Tommaso</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-materials-09-01002"><label>1</label>Postgraduated Program in Science and Material Engineering, Technology Development Center, Federal University of Pelotas, Gomes Carneiro 1, Pelotas-RS 96010-610, Brazil; <email>ananda.barbosa@ufpel.edu.br</email> (A.M.B.); <email>neftali@ufpel.edu.br</email> (N.L.V.C.)</aff><aff id="af2-materials-09-01002"><label>2</label>Chemical &amp; Environmental Engineering Department, University of the Basque Country UPV/EHU, Plaza Europa 1, Donostia-San Sebastian 20018, Spain; <email>jerobles001@ehu.eus</email></aff><aff id="af3-materials-09-01002"><label>3</label>Postgraduate Program in Dentistry, Federal University of Pelotas, Gonçalves Chaves 457, Pelotas-RS 96015-560, Brazil; <email>julianar.fo@ufpel.edu.br</email> (J.S.R.); <email>rglund@ufpel.edu.br</email> (R.G.L.)</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-materials-09-01002"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>jalel.labidi@ehu.eus</email>; Tel.: +34-943-017-178</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>1002</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>In this work, cellulose nanocrystals (CNCs) were obtained from flax fibers by an acid hydrolysis assisted by sonochemistry in order to reduce reaction times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The cavitation inducted during hydrolysis resulted in CNC with uniform shapes, and thus further pretreatments into the cellulose are not required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The obtained CNC exhibited a homogeneous morphology and high crystallinity, as well as typical values for surface charge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Additionally, CNC membranes were developed from CNC solution to evaluation as a drug delivery system by the incorporation of a model drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The drug delivery studies were carried out using chlorhexidine (CHX) as a drug and the antimicrobial efficiency of the CNC membrane loaded with CHX was examined against Gram-positive bacteria Staphylococcus aureus (S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Aureus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The release of CHX from the CNC membranes is determined by UV-Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The obtaining methodology of the membranes proved to be simple, and these early studies showed a potential use in antibiotic drug delivery systems due to the release kinetics and the satisfactory antimicrobial activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>cellulose nanocrystals</kwd><kwd>chlorhexidine</kwd><kwd><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Flax is a temperate-climate erected plant of the Linaceae family with usually 1 m height [1]; flax fibers have been used for thousands of years to make different textile products because of their good performance [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, flax has been studied like raw material for high value-added nanostructured cellulose production [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Cellulose nanocrystals (CNCs) correspond to the ordered crystalline components that can be extracted from various cellulosic materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The extraction of CNCs from fibers usually consists of an acid-induced de-structuring process during which heterogeneous acid hydrolysis involves the diffusion of acid molecules into cellulose fibers, followed by cleavage of glycosidic bonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This acid hydrolysis step is followed by several cycles of centrifugation, after which dialysis is performed to reach neutral pH and ultrasonication to redisperse CNC in a colloidal water suspension [4,5,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Approaches to optimize this methodology have been described [4,5,7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Properties such as biodegradability, bio-based, and biocompatibility make cellulose an important and fascinating polymer for many applications [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Therefore, functional materials can be developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Recent studies address the cellulose as excipient for drug delivery systems [9,10,11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The application of CNCs proves to be an alternative that deserves further clarification [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This work is aimed to analyze CNCs obtained by high frequency cavitation-inducted acid hydrolysis in order to obtain a different particle with high quality in a shorter period of time than normally used in the conventional hydrolysis and without catalyst or pretreatments and apply the obtained material as a membrane for drug delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Different characterizations were performed to assess the CNC and to analyze the colloid solution and the solid-state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, CNC membranes were developed with the addition of chlorhexidine (CNC-CHX membrane). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>CHX has broad antiseptic properties against a wide variety of Gram-negative and Gram-positive organisms because the positively charged parts of the CHX molecule react with the phosphate groups of lipopolysaccharides in the bacterial cell wall causing the antimicrobial activity of CHX [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>CNC-CHX membranes had the antibacterial activities investigated using Gram-positive (G+) bacteria S. aureus. S. aureus was chosen because this human pathogen can cause problems from skin infections to life-threatening health conditions [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The effects of different CHX dosages on the antibacterial activity of the nanocomposites were investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Experimental Procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2dot1-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Flax (Linus usitatisimum) was kindly provided by Artic Fiber Company Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>(Kiiminki, Finland), and sulfuric acid was provided by Panreac® (Barcelona, Spain). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>All other components were used at laboratory conditions and provided by Sigma-Aldrich Spain (Madrid, Spain). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Cavitation-Induced Acid Hydrolysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Flax fiber delignification was performed as described by Robles et al. [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Acid hydrolysis was performed for the bleached cellulose without pretreatments using a 10.2 M solution of H2SO4 (1:20 w/v) at two different temperatures (50 and 60 °C) inside an Elmasonic Elma S 70 H sonication bath, where cavitations were induced at 37 kHz, and time was varied from 30, 45 and 60 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>All reactions were stopped with cold distilled water (1:3 v/v), non-hydrolyzed fraction was separated with a glass funnel and the filtered fraction was centrifuged three times at 8000 rpm for 10 min and then dialyzed to distilled water until neutral pH was stabilized for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Membrane Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Three different concentrations of CHX were used to produce the membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The fraction of CHX (0.015 g, 0.0015 g or 0.00015 g) was dissolved into an appropriate solvent, and then 10 mL of nanocrystal solution was added for each fraction of CHX (selected nanocrystal suspension corresponds to 50 °C/45 min conditions described in Section 2.2), and this mixture continued being stirred and heated at 50 °C for 3 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Finally, the suspension was poured into aluminum dishes and put into an oven at 50 °C for 20 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2dot4dot1-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>2.4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Raw Material Chemical Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Chemical analysis of the flax fibers was performed to determine the amount of cellulose available for further extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This characterization was carried out according to the Technical Association of the Pulp and Paper Industry (TAPPI) standard methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot2-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2.4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Infrared Spectroscopy (FTIR-ATR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Infrared spectra were recorded on a Spectrum Two FT-IR Spectrometer manufactured by Perkin Elmer, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>(London, UK) equipped with a Universal Attenuated Total Reflectance accessory with an internal reflection diamond crystal lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The defined range was from 800 to 4000 cm−1 and the resolution 8 cm−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>For each sample, 10 scans were recorded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot3-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>2.4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Gravimetric Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Cellulose nanocrystals were dry measured to control the yield of each treatment after hydrolysis by using the following equation: Y = MC·MT/MS·MO,(1) where MC is the mass of dried cellulose nanocrystals (10–15 min in an oven at 105 °C); MT is the mass of the total suspension, MS is the mass of the suspension sample before drying; and MO is the cellulose mass before hydrolysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot4-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>2.4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Size Measurement and Zeta Potential </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Particle size and zeta potential were measured inside Malvern Z Nanosizer Equipment (Worcestershire, UK), refractive index for cellulose was considered at 1.47, and measurements were performed at 25 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For size analysis, 0.1 g·L−1 of cellulose suspension was put inside a disposable plastic cuvette performing 13 scans with an incidence angle of 173° repeated three times for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For zeta potential, nanocrystal suspensions were put inside Malvern folded capillary zeta cells and measured using the Smoluchowsky model (κ • a = 1.50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Ten scans were performed, and three specimens of each sample were measured [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot5-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>2.4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The 13C CP/MAS NMR spectrometry was performed using a Bruker 500 MHz spectrometer (Karlsruhe, Germany) at a frequency of 250 MHz with an acquisition time of 0.011 s at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The spectrum was recorded over 32 scans, and water was used as a solvent for all of the nanocrystalline celluloses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot6-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2.4.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>X-ray Diffraction (XRD) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>X-ray powder diffraction was measured to compare crystallinity achieved after each hydrolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Patterns were collected with a Panalytical Philips X’Pert PRO multipurpose diffractometer (Almelo, The Netherlands), with samples mounted on a zero background silicon wafer fixed in a generic sample holder, using monochromatic CuKα radiation (λ = 1.5418 Å), 2θ Bragg angle between 5 and 50°, step size of 0.026° and time per step of 80 s at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Crystalline contributions to the main signal were determined with the intensity observed at the traditional crystalline peaks: −110, 110, 200 and 004, while the amorphous contribution that is attributed to the broad signal observed at 2θ ≈ 18° [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Different approaches to estimate the crystallinity used first consisted of the traditional Segal method [18] expressed in Equation (2): CrI = 100(I_200/I_200 + I_am).(2) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The Segal method is not the most accurate method to determine cellulose crystallinity, but as it is the most widely used, it can be useful to compare results from this study to those made in the past [19,20,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>As a second and more precise method, Voigt functions were used to deconvolute peaks and determine the integrated surface corresponding to the peaks of 1–10, 110 and 200 Miller indices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Apparent crystallinity was estimated with the following equation: CrI = 100(A1–10 + A110 + A200)/(Atot),(3) in which A1–10 + A110 + A200 corresponds to the area of the crystalline region and Atot corresponds to the total area [22,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Crystallite size was estimated with the Scherrer equation using the peak corresponding to the 200 plane as seen in Equation (4): d200 = κλ/H200·cosθ,(4) with κ being the Scherrer constant most adjusted to the nanocrystal shape (0.86), λ the wavelength (1.5418 Å), H200 corresponds to the full width at half maximum intensity (FWHM) and θ is half the Bragg angle at peak maximum given in radians [24,25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot7-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>2.4.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Atomic force microscopy images were obtained operating in tapping mode with a NanoScope IIIa, Multimode TM-AFM from Digital Instruments-Veeco scanning probe microscope (Plainview, NY, USA) equipped with an integrated silicon tip cantilever with a resonance frequency of 300 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>To obtain representative results, different regions of the samples were scanned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot8-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>2.4.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Release Study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The absorbance of the sampled medium was measured using a UV-Vis V-630 spectrophotometer (Jasco Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>(Tokyo, Japan)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Firstly, an initial scanning was performed to determine the wavelength at which the readings would be carried out and the length of wavelength of 360 nm as selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Then, various dilutions were performed obtaining several different concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>These solutions of different concentrations were then taken to the UV spectrophotometer at wavelength 360 nm, the absorbance of the solutions at various concentrations was then determined, and then the calibration curve was developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The drug loaded membranes were weighed (0.0030 g for each sample) and put in a glass vessel containing 10 mL of Phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) buffer solution (pH 7) and the analysis was performed every half hour for four hours, and then readings were taken at 24 and 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The experiments were conducted in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4dot9-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>2.4.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Antibacterial Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Characterization of the Standard Drug </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To characterize the chlorhexidine, the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) were carried out by using broth microdilution techniques as described by the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (M11-A8) with few modifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Inoculum </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>S. aureus ATCC 19095 cultivars were individually grown overnight in aerobic conditions at 37 °C on Brain and Heart Infusion Agar (BHI), supplemented with 10% sucrose, for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Colonies of microorganisms were then suspended in Brain and Heart Infusion broth for S. aureus, in order to make a suspension of 3 × 108 CFU mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The microbial cell turbidity was then adjusted by spectrophotometry (spectrophotometer, Quimis, Brazil) at 405 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Determination of MIC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The stock solution of chlorhexidine was prepared in a dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) solution at a concentration of 500 μg·mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Chlorhexidine powder was previously weighed and dissolved in DMSO at 500 μg·mL−1 concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The solutions were diluted in Muller Hinton medium, and the final drug concentrations ranged from 0.97 to 500 μg·mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In addition, 100 μL of the inoculum suspension along with 100 μL of the final product were added to the microculture plate wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In the negative control, 100 μL of microorganism solution plus 100 μL of Muller Hinton medium was added, and 100 μL of Muller Hinton medium and 100 μL of the final product were added in the positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Three replicates were made for each concentration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>After 24 h of incubation at 35 °C, the absorbance of each well was read on a microplate reader (Thermo Plate TP-Reader, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) at a wavelength of 492 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After the well had been agitated, MIC endpoints were determined as the first concentration of the antibacterial agent at which turbidity in the well was ≥50% less than that in the control well [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The measurement for their antibacterial activity, expressed as the percentage of activity (% AE), was calculated with an adaptation from Felício et al. [27] according to Equation (5): %AE = 100 − (AE − AEB/AC − ACB) × 100,(5) where AE represents the absorbance of the test plates after the incubation time; AEB is the absorbance of plates containing medium, sample and inoculum at t = 0 of incubation; AC is the absorbance of plates containing negative control (without vehicle) (100% of inoculum growth); and ACB is the absorbance of plates containing culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>All of the MIC values were calculated by nonlinear regression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Determination of MBC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Each inoculum from the previous test that did not show growth was subcultured on agar plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>After 24 h of incubation, the reading was determined by the visible growth of strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The CBM was considered to be the first concentration of the antibacterial agent at which turbidity in the well was ≥50% less than that in the control well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Antibacterial Activity of the Drug Delivery System </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Modified direct contact test was used to evaluate the antimicrobial effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The modified direct contact test (mDCT) consists of the measurement of cinematic microbial growth by close contact between the micro-organism tested and the material [28] by using microplate 96-well cell cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Previously, the samples were sterilized by Gamma radiation into an Eldorado-78 equipment (Atomic Energy of Canada Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(Chalk River, ON, Canada)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>After sterilization, the specimens were placed in 96-well plates, with n = 6 for each group tested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Bacterial Strains and Culture Conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Staphylococcus aureus ATCC 19095 were individually grown overnight in aerobic conditions at 37 °C on Brain and Heart Infusion Agar (BHI) supplemented with 10% sucrose for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Colonies of microorganisms were then suspended in Brain and Heart Infusion broth for S. aureus, in order to make a suspension of 3 × 108 CFU mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The microbial cell turbidity was adjusted by spectrophotometry (spectrophotometer, Quimis, Brazil) at 405 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>From this inoculum was added 20 μL of bacterial suspension into each well to be evaluated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The materials were placed in microplate wells with the aid of sterile forceps being a specimen in each well, and the material was inoculated with 20 μL of microbial suspension (S. aureus + BHI + sucralose). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The discs were incubated for 1 or 24 h at 37 °C and approximately 100% relative humidity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Microplate wells containing the same volume of bacterial suspension without test discs were also incubated as controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, 180 μL of culture medium (BHI, Guangzhou Mecan Trading Co., Ltd., Guangzhou, China) was added into each well and shaken for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In addition, 100 μL of bacterial suspension from each well was transferred for dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Serial dilutions and platings were carried out in disposable Petri dishes containing BHI agar divided into eight parts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Each plate received two drops of 20 μL per dilution and was incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Beyond the period of incubation, the concentration of colony forming units (CFU mL−1) was counted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3dot1-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Raw Material Chemical Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Table 1 presents the chemical composition of flax fibers analyzed with standard methods as the mean of six tests for each standard, as well as a comparison to other previously published works in which flax fibers were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>A high content of cellulose was observed making flax a reliable source for cellulose nanocrystal extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The high amount of hemicelluloses present in this fibers makes it desirable to perform an alkali stage in the cellulose extraction sequence, while low lignin content allows for a less aggressive bleaching stage (hydrogen peroxide) to finally extract cellulose with high purity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>FTIR-ATR Spectroscopic Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Flax fibers were received untreated and were pulped and bleached in an integrated Elemental Chlorine Free sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In Figure 1A, it is possible to follow the appearance of the flax during the different steps of the treatment. Figure 1B shows the FT-IR spectra of flax fibers as received and flax cellulose fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Compared to flax fibers, flax cellulose fibers present more defined peaks and bands that are characteristic to cellulose and can be seen as follows: the band between 3600 and 3000 cm−1 corresponds to stretching vibrations of hydroxyl groups in cellulose, and the band between 3000 and 2600 cm−1 and 2860 cm−1 corresponds to –CH groups, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The signal of 2920 cm−1 corresponds to the CH3 group and the signal of 2860 cm−1 corresponds to the CH2 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The peak at 1645 cm−1 can be attributed to the bending mode of the absorbed water in carbohydrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The band at 1420 cm−1 corresponds to CH2 bending and the one at 1215 cm−1 is originated from the –OH in plane-bending cellulose [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The adsorption band at 1150 cm−1 can be attributed to C–O antisymmetric bridge stretching. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Finally, the peak at 890 cm−1 is characteristic of β-glycosidic linkages between glucose units [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Colloid Solution Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>To evaluate colloidal stability of the cellulose nanocrystals, 1 wt % solutions were prepared for each sample, and they were vortexed for a minute and photographed to evaluate initial conditions; solutions were left to rest for 21 days, after which another picture was made (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Samples showed different stabilities as colloidal suspensions after the final time elapsed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Anisotropic sedimentation was observed in samples elaborated with lower temperature, while those with higher temperatures had stronger isotropic phases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Regarding sonication time, it is clear that after longer sonication time, particles maintain isotropic dispersion in the water suspension, as the effect of the sulfuric acid after longer time generates a more charged surface of the nanocrystals that acts as a repulsive force maintaining nanocrystals suspended in polar liquids [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot4-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows the NMR spectra of the CNCs after different hydrolysis conditions, and the main signals between 110 and 55 ppm correspond to crystalline cellulose I [34] and are attributed to carbons in a hydroglucose units listed from C1 to C6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Differences observed between the CNC are attributed to the differences in the supramolecular structure or the polymer chain packing of the samples, which may be affected during the hydrolysis, and slight variations can be observed in C1 for 60-30 and 60-60 samples, with their peaks presenting sharper points in the region closer to C4, which is attributed to cellulose Iβ; on the other hand, 50-30, 50-45 and 60-45 celluloses present more rounded peaks for C1, which implies a mayor presence of paracrystalline cellulose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In C4 for the 60-60 sample, it can be appreciated that the excess of hydrolysis may have disintegrated polymeric chains to main glucose units, thus showing an increment in the amorphous region of C4 carbon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot5-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Size Measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In Figure 4, the histograms of the size distribution of each obtained nanocrystal are presented, 60-60 CNCs present the highest homogeneity, as almost 70% of them are contained in the 40–50 nm range, while 50-30 and 50-60 present more even dispersions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The higher percent of CNCs under the 60 nm limit that can be seen in 50-30 can be due to low hydrolysis during the reaction as they have the slowest yield (Table 2), meaning that most of the fibers were not hydrolyzed during the reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In addition, 50-45 and 60-45 also present higher homogeneity in their size distribution, as more than half of their counts are in the same range, being 50–60 nm for 50-45 and 40–50 nm for 60-45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>These two samples also presented higher yields in general, and CNC yields maintain a close correlation depending on the temperature and time used for the reaction, with the 60-60 treatment being an exception, as it presents smaller particles but also lower yield. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This can be due to cellulose polysaccharide chain degradation to single glucose chains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot6-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Yield and Zeta Potential </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>As a way to analyze the effectiveness of each treatment performed to obtain cellulose nanocrystals, all of the samples were filtered with a glass Buchner funnel with a sintered glass filter No. 1 to retain un-hydrolyzed fibers before centrifugation; therefore, homogeneous cellulose nanocrystal suspensions were obtained, with the removal of larger particles through filtration and the undesirable particles with the centrifugation, and yields were measured gravimetrically and results are shown in Table 2 as well as the zeta potential and the Scherrer approximated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Regarding zeta potential, all of the hydrolyzed nanocrystals showed surface charges in the range characteristic of such particles with only 50-30 and 60-60 being within the moderate range (±30 to ±40 mV), while the rest is in the incipient stability range (±10 to ±30 mV) with no significant variations between them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot7-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>X-ray Diffraction (XRD) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Figure 5 shows the scattered raw powder diffraction patterns, the position of the peak associated by the Segal method to main crystalline contribution, and the correspondences to the crystalline plane with Miller index (200) as marked, as well as the point associated with the amorphous contribution to the signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>While the intensity of the (200) plane is more or less the same in all cases, the one attributed to the amorphous region presents a constant decrease at longer reaction times. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>To determine the position of signals generated by the cellulose nanocrystals and gather more information about their composition, powder diffraction patterns were simulated with PeakFit 4.12 software by Systat Software, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>(San Jose, CA, USA) to fit the original pattern (R2 ≥ 0.998) and then deconvoluted using Voigt curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>All patterns correspond to those of native cellulose (cellulose Iα and Iβ) with stronger contributions attributed to cellulose Iβ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Cellulose crystallinity has been extensively evaluated by the Segal method, although this method is now considered imprecise and obsolete for quantitative analysis, and it is still used by many researchers around the world and therefore still represents an option for fast qualitative analysis, as it can be easily obtained and there is a larger amount of bibliographic references to compare with [20,35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the integrated area method has been gathering more attention as it can represent a more realistic approach to analyze the crystalline domains that are present in the cellulose nanocrystals after the extraction of non-crystalline regions [22]. Table 2 presents the crystallinity index corresponding to Segal and integral area methods as well as the size approximation of the (200) crystalline region as proposed by Scherrer for qualitative purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In general, a high crystallinity can be observed for all obtained nanocrystals, with a constant increase in cellulose crystallinity, as reaction time is longer for CNC obtained at 50 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In both Segal and deconvolution methods, the change in crystallinity for samples treated at 60 °C is very low, and when time elapses up to 60 min, it decreases, showing a possible de-crystallization of the cellulose nanocrystals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Crystallite size approximated by Scherrer equation (δ200) does not vary significantly between the different treatments used and are within the range of other reported data [15,36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot8-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The obtained nanocrystals present in all cases rod-like morphology characteristics of cellulose nanocrystals and homogeneous size in general (Figure 6), with significant variances depending on the method selected for their obtention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Nanocrystals obtained by methods involving higher temperatures (60-30, 60-45 and 60-60) present smaller particles in both length and width, with 60-60 having the smallest dimensions and 50-60 the largest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In the case of 50-30 nanocrystals, a larger aspect ratio can be observed in atomic force microscopy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The surface of selected elaborated membranes can be observed in Figure 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The CNC-CHX coatings become evident exhibiting the homogeneity of the membranes with different concentrations of the drug and random orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The membrane preparation methodology used in this study favors a controlled release of the drug since the membrane is formed with the drug in contrast to other studies that put the drug at the ready vehicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The AFM was also used for surface roughness determination; the changes in roughness have the expected behavior, as the amount of drug added reduces the roughness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The lower surface roughness (Table 3) of the samples CNC + 0.0015 g CHX and CNC + 0.00015 g CHX compared to the sample without drug (CNC) may be explained by the total dispersion of the dissolved drug in the cellulose solution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot9-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>3.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Drug Release </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Figure 8A presents the drug release of the membranes as a function of time; results are similar for the three tested concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>For the evaluation of drug delivery, the drug was added to CNC solutions and taken to the oven for solidification; this may account for the delivery of CHX around 10%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Literature reports that the mechanisms of adsorption of CHX onto cellulosic fibers appear to be controlled mainly by electrostatic forces between the cationic groups of the CHX and the carboxyl acid groups of cellulose fibers, as well as the hydrogen bonding between the biguanide group and the p-chlorophenol of the CHX with hydroxyl groups of cellulose [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Results demonstrate that the membrane could deliver the antimicrobial drug CHX with a satisfactory performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The CNC solution proves to be a promising vehicle for drug delivery, considering that the drug is not inserted superficially in the membrane but rather dissolved and inserted during the preparation of the membrane, giving a stronger interaction than membranes which are immersed in the solution containing the drug. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot10-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>3.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Antibacterial Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3dot10dot1-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>3.10.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC) of Chlorhexidine </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Broth microdilution technique was chosen in order to determine the susceptibility of the selected microorganism to the antimicrobial agent studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The results obtained for the minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration are shown in Figure 8B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The results show the MIC and MBC values (31.25 mg·mL−1 for S. aureus). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The data obtained suggest that the CHX was effective against S. aureus at even a 31.25 mg·mL−1 concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>As an expected behavior, the susceptibility of the microorganism varied according to the concentrations of the antimicrobial drugs agent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The inhibition against the microorganism was directly proportional to the concentration of chlorhexidine, constantly increasing as the concentration got higher than 31.25 mg·mL−1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot10dot2-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>3.10.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Modified Direct Contact Test (mDCT) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The ability of CNC-CHX membranes to inhibit the growth or even kill S. aureus cultivars was evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The CNC membrane without drugs was used as the control, and the inhibition results of S. aureus ATCC 19095 are presented in Figure 8C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The CNC membrane + 0.015 g CHX totally inhibited bacterial growth after 1 h and 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>There was a proportionally direct decrease in the inhibition of the bacteria growth in accordance with the decrease in drug concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In high concentrations, CHX is bactericidal via destruction of the cell membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This can be explained because at lower concentrations, CHX has bacteriostatic properties [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec4-materials-09-01002"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>CNCs were successfully obtained by high frequency cavitation induced acid hydrolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The analyses were performed to evaluate the characteristics of the particles, and the results showed that all times and temperatures tested are viable to obtain CNC without further treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This approach reduces the hydrolysis time by half compared with the conventional hydrolysis (without cavitation) and can be useful when morphology control of the CNC is an important aspect, and thus choice of conditions used in future works depends on the desired morphological features. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In this study, cellulose nanocrystals were applied in solution as excipient obtaining membranes charged with CHX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The methodology for obtaining the membranes proved to be simple and efficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The results of release experiments showed that the nanocrystal membranes had sustained release properties and the release kinetics show that the quantities delivered are maintained over at least 48 h even with a low concentration of drugs, and this makes CNC membranes a potential candidate for drug delivery applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The antibacterial activity of the CNC membrane with 0.015 g of CHX was found to be highly effective against S. aureus, showing that the CNC-CHX membranes can be used for antimicrobial applications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In future work, in vitro cytotoxicity assays will be performed to assess the cell viability provided by the CNC-CHX membranes, and the behavior of other drugs also incorporated into CNC membranes will be studied in order to clarify the behavior and compare the membrane with other excipients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to acknowledge the Department of Education, Universities and Investigation of the Basque Government (project IT1008-16), the Federal Agency for Support and Evaluation of Graduate Education (CAPES) through process BEX 8710/14-7, the Mexican Council of Science and Technology (CONACyT) through scholarship 216178 and theBrazilian National Council for Scientific and Technological Development for financial support through CNPq (# 482251/2013-1) for financially supporting this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The authors also thank Maite Insausti and Oihane Arriortua for their kind help and support with Nanosizer and SGIker of the University of the Basque Country UPV/EHU for technical and human support provided with XRD, NMR and AFM characterizations and Altair Faes of the Regional Center of Oncology of the Federal University of Pelotas (UFPel) for the use of the equipment Eldorado 78. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>A.M.B. and J.L. conceived and designed the experiments; E.R. and A.M.B. extracted the CNC and made the CNC membranes; JA.M.B. analyzed the drug release; J.S.R. and R.G.L. analyzed the antibacterial activity; A.M.B., E.R. and N.L.V.C. wrote the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. The founding sponsors had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript, and in the decision to publish the results.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>1. AlilaS.BesbesI.VilarM.R.MutjéP.BoufiS. Non-woody plants as raw materials for production of microfibrillated cellulose (MFC): A comparative study Ind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Crops Prod. 2013 41 250 259 10.1016/j.indcrop.2012.04.028  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2. BosH.L.Van den OeverM.J.A.PetersO.C.J.J. Tensile and compressive properties of flax fibres for natural fibre reinforced composites J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Mater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2002 37 1683 1692 10.1023/A:1014925621252  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>3. JonoobiM.OladiR.DavoudpourY.OksmanK.DufresneA.HamzehY.DavodiR. Different preparation methods and properties of nanostructurated cellulose from various natural resources and residues: A review Cellulose 2015 22 935 969 10.1007/s10570-015-0551-0  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>4. BondesonD.MathewA.OksmanK. Optimization of the isolation of nanocrystals from microcrystalline cellulose by acid hydrolysis Cellulose 2006 13 171 180 10.1007/s10570-006-9061-4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>5. LiJ.ZhangX.ZhangM.XiuH.HeH. Ultrasonic enhance acid hydrolysis selectivity of cellulose with HCl-FeCl3 as catalyst Carbohydr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Polym. 2015 117 917 922 10.1016/j.carbpol.2014.10.028 <?supplied-pmid 25498717?>25498717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>6. MorianaR.VilapanaF.KarlssonS.RibesA. Correlation of chemical, structural and thermal properties of natural fibres for their sustainable exploitation Carbohydr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Polym. 2014 112 422 431 10.1016/j.carbpol.2014.06.009 <?supplied-pmid 25129763?>25129763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>7. LiW.WangR.LiuS. Nanocrystalline cellulose prepared from softwood kraft pulp via ultrasonic assisted acid hydrolysis BioResources 2011 6 4271 4281  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>8. MontesS.AzcuneI.CabañeroG.GrandeH.-J.OdriozolaI.LabidiJ. Functionalization of Cellulose Nanocrystals in Choline Lactate Ionic Liquid Materials 2016 9 499 10.3390/ma9070499  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>9. KolakovicR.LaaksonenT.PeltonenL.LaukkanenA.HirvonenJ. Spraydried nanofibrillar cellulose microparticles for sustained drug release Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Pharm. 2012 430 44 55 10.1016/j.ijpharm.2012.03.031 <?supplied-pmid 22465549?>22465549 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>10. LavoineN.DeslogesI.SillardC.BrasJ. Controlled release and long-term antibacterial activity of chlorhexidine digluconate through the nanoporous network of microfibrillated cellulose Cellulose 2014 21 4429 4442 10.1007/s10570-014-0392-2  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>11. VeeramachineniA.K.SathasivamT.MuniyandyS.JanarthananP.LangfordS.J.YanL.Y. Optimizing Extraction of Cellulose and Synthesizing Pharmaceutical Grade Carboxymethyl Sago Cellulose from Malaysian Sago Pulp Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2016 6 170 10.3390/app6060170  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>12. WangC.HuangH.JiaM.JinS.ZhaoW.ChaR. Formulation and evaluation of nanocrystalline cellulose as a potential disintegrant Carbohydr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Polym. 2015 130 275 279 10.1016/j.carbpol.2015.05.007 <?supplied-pmid 26076627?>26076627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>13. AttinT.AbouassiT.BeckerK.WiegandA.RoosM.AttinR. A new method for chlorhexidine (CHX) determination: CHX release after application of differently concentrated CHX-containing preparations on artificial fissures Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Oral Investig. 2008 12 189 196 10.1007/s00784-007-0166-4 <?supplied-pmid 18057970?>18057970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>14. YerushalmiS.M.BuckM.E.LynnD.M.LemcoffN.G.MeijlerM.M. Multivalent Alteration of Quorum Sensing in Staphylococcus aureus Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Commun. 2013 49 5177 5179 10.1039/c3cc41645c <?supplied-pmid 23628938?>23628938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>15. RoblesE.UrruzolaI.LabidiJ.SerranoL. Surface modified nano-cellulose as reinforcement in poly(lactic acid) to conform new composites Ind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Crops Prod. 2015 71 44 53 10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.03.075  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>16. SmoluchowskiM. Contribution to the theory of electro-osmosis and related phenomena Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Crac. 1903 3 184 199  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>17. HeJ.ShizhongC.WangS. Preparation and crystalline analysis of high-grade bamboo dissolving pulp for cellulose acetate J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Polym. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2008 107 1029 1038 10.1002/app.27061  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>18. SegalL.CreelyJ.J.MartinA.E.Jr.ConradC.M. An empirical method for estimating the degree of crystallinity of native cellulose using the X-ray diffractometer Text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>J. 1959 29 786 794 10.1177/004051755902901003  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>19. FrenchA.D.Santiago CintrónM. Cellulose polymorphy, crystallite size, and the Segal Crystallinity Index Cellulose 2013 20 583 588 10.1007/s10570-012-9833-y  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>20. ParkS.BakerJ.O.HimmelM.E.ParillaP.A.JohnsonD.K. Cellulose crystallinity index: Measurement techniques and their impact on interpreting cellulose performance Biotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Biofuels 2010 3 10 10.1186/1754-6834-3-10 <?supplied-pmid 20497524?>20497524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>21. UrruzolaI.RoblesE.SerranoL.LabidiJ. Nanopaper from almond (Prunus dulcis) shell Cellulose 2014 21 1619 1629 10.1007/s10570-014-0238-y  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>22. HultE.L.IversenT.SugiyamaJ. Characterization of the supermolecular structure of cellulose in wood pulp fibres Cellulose 2003 10 103 110 10.1023/A:1024080700873  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>23. TerinteN.IbbettR.SchusterK.C. Overview on native cellulose and microcrystalline cellulose I structure studied by X-ray diffraction (WAXD): Comparison between measurement techniques Lenzing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Ber. 2011 89 118 131  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>24. ScherrerP. Bestimmung der Größe und der inneren Struktur von Kolloidteilchen mittels Röntgenstrahlen Nachr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Ges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Wiss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Gött. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Math.-Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Kl. 1918 1918 98 100  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>25. WarrenB.E. X-ray Diffraction Addison-Wesley Pub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Co. Reading, MA, USA 1969  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>26. PfallerM.A.MesserS.A.CoffmanS. Comparison of visual and spectrophotometric methods of MIC endpoint determinations by using broth microdilution methods to test five antifungal agents, including the new triazole D0870 J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 1995 33 1094 1097 <?supplied-pmid 7615712?>7615712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>27. FelícioR.AlbuquerqueS.YoungM.C.M.YokoyaN.S.DebonsiH.M. Trypanocidal, leishmanicidal and antifungal potential from marine red alga Bostrychia tenella J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Agardh (Rhodomelaceae, Ceramiales) J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Pharm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Biomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Anal. 2008 52 763 769 10.1016/j.jpba.2010.02.018 <?supplied-pmid 20236785?>20236785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>28. ZhangH.ShenY.RuseN.D.HaapasaloM. Antibacterial Activity of Endodontic Sealers by Modified Direct Contact Test against Enterococcus Faecalis J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Endod. 2009 35 1051 1055 10.1016/j.joen.2009.04.022 <?supplied-pmid 19567333?>19567333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>29. Abdul KhalilH.P.S.RozmanH.D.AhmadM.N.IsmailH. Acetylated Plant-Fiberreinforced Polyester Composites: A Study of Mechanical, Hygrothermal, and Aging Characteristics Polym.-Plast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Technol. 2000 39 757 781 10.1081/PPT-100100057  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>30. ThygesenA.MadsenB.BjerreA.B.LilholtH. Cellulosic Fibers: Effect of Processing on Fiber Bundle Strength J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Fibers 2011 8 161 175 10.1080/15440478.2011.602236  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>31. SunX.F.SunR.C.FowlerP.BairdM.S. Isolation and characterization of cellulose obtained by a two-stage treatment with organosolv and cyanamide activated hydrogen peroxide from wheat straw Carbohydr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Polym. 2004 55 379 391 10.1016/j.carbpol.2003.10.004  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>32. Buschle-DillerG.InglesbyM.K.WuY. Physicochemical properties of chemically and enzymatically modified cellulosic surfaces Colloids Surf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>A 2005 260 63 70 10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.02.031  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>33. RevolJ.F.BradfordH.GiassonJ.MarchessaultR.H.GrayD.G. Helicoidal self-ordering of cellulose microfibrils in aqueous suspension Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Macromol. 1992 14 170 172 10.1016/S0141-8130(05)80008-X 1390450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>34. GastJ.C.AtallaR.H.McKelveyR.D. The 13C-n.m.r. spectra of the xylo- and cello-oligosaccharides Carbohydr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Res. 1980 84 137 146 10.1016/S0008-6215(00)85437-3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>35. FrenchA.D. Idealized powder diffraction patterns for cellulose polymorphs Cellulose 2014 212 885 896 10.1007/s10570-013-0030-4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-materials-09-01002"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>36. YuH.Y.QinZ.Y.LiuL.YangX.G.ZhouY.YaoJ.M. Comparison of the reinforcing effects for cellulose nanocrystals obtained by sulfuric and hydrochloric acid hydrolysis on the mechanical and thermal properties of bacterial polyester Compos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Technol. 2013 87 22 28 10.1016/j.compscitech.2013.07.024  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Bleaching sequence diagrams (A) along with the corresponding infrared spectrum (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Pictures of the differently obtained cellulose nanocrystals in 1 wt % aqueous suspension before (a) and after 21 days of settlement (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(From left to right, 50-30; 50-45; 50-60; 60-30; 60-45; 60-60). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>NMR spectra of cellulose nanocrystals after different hydrolysis conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>(a) 50-30 (black), 50-45 (red) and 50-60 (green); (b) 60-30 (blue), 60-45 (orange) and 60-60 (violet). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Size histograms of the elaborated CNCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>(a) 50-30; (b) 50-45; (c) 50-60; (d) 60-30; (e) 60-45; (f) 60-60. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Raw and simulated powder diffraction patterns for: (a) 50-30; (b) 50-45; (c) 50-60; (d) 60-30; (e) 60-45 and (f) 60-60. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>AFM images of cellulose nanocrystals after different hydrolysis conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>(a) 50-30; (b) 50-45; (c) 50-60 (d) 60-30; (e) 60-45; (f) 60-60. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>AFM images of CNC membranes + 0.015 g CHX (a); CNC membranes + 0.0015 g CHX (b); and CNC membranes + 0.00015 g CHX (c) and the roughness of the membranes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="materials-09-01002-f008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Membrane release profile from 0 to 48 h and highlights for the first 250 min (A); in vitro antibacterial activity of chlorhexidine dissolved in DMSO against S. aureus (B); survival of S. aureus ATCC 19095 after modified direct contact test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Different capital letters represent statistically significant differences in the group and different lower case letters represent statistically significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05) (C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-09-01002-g008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="materials-09-01002-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-09-01002-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Chemical composition of the raw material used in this study compared to other sources. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Extractives </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Lignin </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Hemicelluloses </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>α-Cellulose </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>2.58 ± 2.11 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>1.70 ± 0.31 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>15.42 ± 0.53 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>63.91 ± 1 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>1.70 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>24.90 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>13.70 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>73.80 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>2.8 ± 0.50 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>8.7 ± 0.20 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>77 ± 0.30 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>4.70 d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>12.90 d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>68.70 d </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup> (his study); <sup>b</sup> [<xref rid="B29-materials-09-01002" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]; <sup>c</sup> [<xref rid="B6-materials-09-01002" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]; <sup>d</sup> [<xref rid="B30-materials-09-01002" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="materials-09-01002-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-09-01002-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Crystallinity properties of the different nanocrystals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Sample/Method </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Crystallinity Index (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Yield (g/g) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Zeta Potential (mV) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>δ200 (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Segal Method </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Deconvolution Method </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Scherrer Approximated </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>50-30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>86.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>80.19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>0.0930 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>−32.70 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>54.39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>50-45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>90.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>85.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>0.1799 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>−24.30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>51.91 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>50-60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>91.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>91.23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>0.4032 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>−24.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>50.68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>60-30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>90.82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>85.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>0.0656 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>−26.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>53.40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>60-45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>90.89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>87.93 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>0.1415 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>−25.40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>54.95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>60-60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>90.90 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>83.69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>0.0808 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>−31.35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>50.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="materials-09-01002-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-09-01002-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Root mean squared roughness (RMS) of the membranes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>SAMPLES </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>RMS * </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>CNC + 0.015 g CHX </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>44.85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>CNC + 0.0015 g CHX </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>CNC + 0.0015 g CHX </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>5.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>* Values were evaluated over an area of 25 nm<sup>2</sup> at different locations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
