<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5722940</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-17633-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Prediction of cassava protein interactome based on interolog method </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thanasomboon</surname><given-names>Ratana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalapanulak</surname><given-names>Saowalak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Netrphan</surname><given-names>Supatcharee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Saithong</surname><given-names>Treenut</given-names></name><address><email>treenut.sai@kmutt.ac.th</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8921 9789</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412151.2</institution-id><institution>Biological Engineering Program, </institution><institution>Faculty of Engineering, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi, </institution></institution-wrap>Bangkok, 10140 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8921 9789</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412151.2</institution-id><institution>Systems Biology and Bioinformatics Research Group, </institution><institution>Pilot Plant Development and Training Institute, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi (Bang Khun Thian), </institution></institution-wrap>Bangkok, 10150 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8921 9789</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412151.2</institution-id><institution>Bioinformatics and Systems Biology Program, </institution><institution>School of Bioresources and Technology, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi (Bang Khun Thian), </institution></institution-wrap>Bangkok, 10150 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419250.b</institution-id><institution>National Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology, </institution></institution-wrap>Pathum Thani, 12120 Thailand </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>17206</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Cassava is a starchy root crop whose role in food security becomes more significant nowadays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Together with the industrial uses for versatile purposes, demand for cassava starch is continuously growing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, in-depth study to uncover the mystery of cellular regulation, especially the interaction between proteins, is lacking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To reduce the knowledge gap in protein-protein interaction (PPI), genome-scale PPI network of cassava was constructed using interolog-based method (MePPI-In, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi">http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The network was constructed from the information of seven template plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In included 90,173 interactions from 7,209 proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>At least, 39 percent of the total predictions were found with supports from gene/protein expression data, while further co-expression analysis yielded 16 highly promising PPIs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In addition, domain-domain interaction information was employed to increase reliability of the network and guide the search for more groups of promising PPIs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the topology and functional content of MePPI-In was similar to the networks of Arabidopsis and rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The potential contribution of MePPI-In for various applications, such as protein-complex formation and prediction of protein function, was discussed and exemplified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The insights provided by our MePPI-In would hopefully enable us to pursue precise trait improvement in cassava. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Proteins are macromolecules that play crucial roles in a range of biological processes in cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>They do not only act as catalysts but are also involved in intracellular regulatory processes, e.g. signal transduction and transcriptional regulation1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Although specific function is assigned to each protein, too often, we see that the protein remains inactive in the cellular matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This is because the protein needs to go through some modification processes, such as protein dimerization and complex formation via protein binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Cooperation between proteins, called protein-protein interaction (PPI), allows cells to dynamically modulate when proteins and their counterparts are turned on to play roles in particular cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Since these interactions are highly dependent on prevailing conditions of exposure, the PPI is considered a type of biological language utilized to synchronize cellular regulation, especially at post-translational level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Due to the immense impact of PPIs on the regulation of cellular processes, great attempts have been devoted to capture the interactions between proteins as well as investigate their consequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Earlier, availability of experimental techniques, such as affinity chromatography, immunoprecipitation and chemical crosslinking, only allowed for investigation of interaction of one, or maximally, a few protein pair at once2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, large-scale detection of PPIs at genome-wide level has been made possible through yeast two-hybrid (Y2H), or affinity purification coupled with mass spectrometry (AP-MS)3–5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>With these techniques, however, it still seems impossible to acquire knowledge in protein science at the rate that is fast enough to catch up with the big data currently available in post-genomic era. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Computational inference technique is an alternative method that can be used to identify the interactions between proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This technique is based on the hypothesis that the function of proteins, and also the interaction among them are conserved across their evolutionary lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>By incorporating various types of data, such as amino acid sequences, functional domains, folding structure and co-evolution of interacting sites, successes in PPI conjecture in a wide range of organisms have been reported6–9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The information acquired from PPI prediction has helped expand the understanding of the regulation at protein level, such as PPI-based mechanism of signal transduction process, and molecular interaction underlying host-pathogen relationship10–12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Recently, in an effort to move beyond the available PPI data, sophisticated computational methods, such as machine learning13,14, Bayesian network15,16, physical docking17 and correlated mutation18, have been introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>To approach genome-wide prediction, machine learning based methods are of wide interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Series of effective algorithms have continuously been developed in an attempt to incorporate multiple genomic/proteomic features into a framework of PPI prediction19–22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These algorithmic methods predict PPI from amino acid sequences and their collective information, for instance evolutionary background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Some examples include support vector machine (SVM)13,14,23, rotation forest and decision tree24,25, Bayesian classification15,16, Naïve Bayes26, relevance vector machine (RVM)27,28 and weighted sparse representation (WSRC)29,30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These computational algorithms have contributed immensely to the study of PPI in a broad range of organisms, from bacteria16 to humans31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, the performance of the machine learning based-methods depends enormously on the numbers and quality of the employed data, especially the model-training information which are in general related to experimentally measured data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Application of such methods in non-model organisms, which always lack data, are quite challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To closely investigate the interaction of a protein set, computational methods that include information on protein structure into prediction regime, such as Struct2Net32 and physical docking17 are proposed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In plants, earlier studies of PPI were limited to only a few species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The current PPI information of plants, especially cassava, has constrained choices of predictive methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Not only the number of data is small, but only few experimental evidences are available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The computational prediction methods such as classification, machine learning and statistical inference were considered not suitable, and sometimes not applicable, for the status of data resource. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A simple computational technique called interolog, which relies on existing data, is often adopted for PPI prediction under this restriction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The interolog method is inspired by the hypothesis that the function of protein is retained and passed through their orthologs in evolution-related organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The method, basically, infers PPI information from other well-studied species by orthology-based deduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Most of PPI networks in plants were basically developed based on the interolog method, for example Arabidopsis6, rice33 and tomato34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The first plant PPI network constructed by interolog-based method was reported in 2007, describing 19,979 interactions of 3,617 Arabidopsis proteins35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Since the first publication was released, accuracy of the interolog-based PPI network has greatly been improved by integrating various sources of information, from both predictive studies and experimental measurements36–38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Presently, the PPI research of plant species has been expanded from model plants, e.g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Arabidopsis6,35–39 and rice9,33,40, to economic crops, e.g tomato34, maize41 and sweet orange42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The previous research works are the good evidences of the appropriateness of such method for PPI inference in plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) is an important crop of the world, since its roots feed at least 800 million people43. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Cassava yield improvement is thus, a major research topic ultimately aiming to guarantee food sufficiency for growing population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>To date, the advent of high-throughput technology has improved our understanding of various aspects of cassava, especially root development44,45 and starch biosynthesis46–48. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>However, the information at protein level, which drives the physiology of cassava, is still a mystery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Several reports on protein expression exist under the conditions of interest49–59, but they do not provide further information on PPIs that might relate to post-translational or protein-level regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Here, by employing interolog approach, we propose the first genome-scale protein-protein interaction network of cassava (MePPI-In), using available PPI data and information from a variety of plant species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Our MePPI-In contains 90,173 interactions interconnecting 7,209 cassava proteins (approximately 21 percent of all proteins in the whole genome). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>These interactions were partially supported by protein/gene expression and domain-domain interaction data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The resulting PPI network provided the landscape of possible interactions that might help fill the knowledge-gap on post-translational regulation in cassava as exemplified in the last section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Construction of cassava PPI network using interolog-based method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The interolog method is generally based on the inference of PPI information known to exist in other organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In this study, plant species, whose PPI information was employed for inference, were selected based on one of these criteria; (1) having a closed evolution with cassava (i.e. Ricinus communis (castor bean), Populus trichocarpa (poplar) and Glycine max (soybean)), (2) being recognized as a starch-storing plant (i.e. Solanum tuberosum (potato), Zea mays (maize) and Oryza sativa (rice)), or (3) having abundant PPI information (i.e. Arabidopsis thaliana). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The protein information of these template plants was obtained from Phytozome V960 and Uniprot61 databases, and the protein interaction information was collected from seven databases; IntAct62, MINT63, AtPIN36, AtPID37, PAIR38, APID39, and PRIN9 (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To find protein orthologs in cassava, we performed BLASTp search against the cassava genome sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The cassava orthologous proteins were identified if the identity percentage ≥ 60, coverage percentage ≥ 80 and e-value ≤ 10−10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>To be able to infer interaction that originally exists in one of the plant templates to cassava, orthologous proteins interconnected by such interaction must be identified in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The cassava PPI network, MePPI-In, was then visualized using Cytoscape software64.Figure 1Overall methodology of PPI prediction in cassava consisting of three parts: (a) Construction of protein-protein interaction network of cassava using interolog-based approach (MePPI-In), (b) Validation of the PPIs proposed in MePPI-In using protein/gene expression or domain-domain interaction (DDI) evidence, and (c) Characterization of MePPI-In based on three aspects – network topology, functional contents and biological inference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Validation of MePPI-In based on expression data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Protein and gene expression data were exploited in this prediction framework to directly indicate if the proteins, or products of genes, exist in real cassava system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, the proteins were considered available for the interactions among them to occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To perform this, we utilized seven sets of protein expression data (Li et al.50, Mitprasat et al.51, Naconsie et al.52, Otiwi et al.53, Sheffield et al.56, Vanderschuren et al.57 and Zhao et al.59), and four sets of gene expression data (Yang et al.45, Li et al.65, An et al.66 and Utsumi et al.67). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For the gene expression data, it is important to note that only highly expressed genes that showed expression level above the 80th percentile rank were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In MePPI-In, the nodes (proteins) were highlighted as blue color, if their expression information was available, as shown in Fig. 2.Figure 2Cassava protein-protein interaction network (MePPI-In) derived by the interolog-based method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The network contained 90,173 interactions (edges) interconnecting 7,209 proteins (nodes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Different colors were given to both edges and nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The black edges represent PPIs with DDI or co-expression support, while the grey ones represent those with no supporting data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Blue color nodes represent proteins with supporting expression data45,50–53,56,57,59,65–67, while the orange ones have no expression support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(All information is publicly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi">http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>From eleven datasets mentioned above, only the time-series datasets of Naconsie et al.52, Yang et al.45, Li et al.65 and An et al.66 were employed to investigate the correlation of the expression profiles for interacting protein pair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This was based on the hypothesis that the genes/proteins with co-expression profile would have greater probability to interact than uncorrelated ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Herein, the expression profiles of the highly expressed genes were determined based on Pearson’s correlation (Pearson correlation coefficient score (PCC))68, and co-expression of a protein pair in MePPI-In was suggested at PCC &gt; 0.9 and p-value &lt; 0.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Validation of MePPI-In based on domain-domain interaction (DDI) data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Since proteins always interact via specific domains, the reliability of predicted PPIs could be determined using information on domain-domain interaction (DDI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In this work, the domain information of all proteins in the cassava PPI network was obtained from Pfam database69 and the interactions between protein domains were collected from iPfam database70 (Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>From the original MePPI-In, different colors were given to the interactions (edges) with or without supporting DDI information as shown in Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Scoring the confidence of the MePPI-In </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The confidence of predicted PPIs in MePPI-In was determined based on the consistency of the results inferred by two methods: interolog and domain-domain interaction analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Each predicted interaction was given the level of confidence, in terms of confidence value (CV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The confidence value (CV) score was defined as a product of the confidence values from interolog (CV interolog) and DDI (CV DDI) (Equation 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Since our interolog-based PPI prediction was derived from the evidence in plant templates, the CV interolog was formulated to represent the confidence of the prediction, based upon the number of species from which the interaction was inferred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Additionally, this score was also weighted by the method employed to identify the interactions in the source organism, computational prediction or experimental measurements (Equation 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The CV DDI indicated the confidence of prediction based on domain-domain interactions, in which the number of interacting domains between a predicted protein pair was taken into account (Equation 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The formulas were as follows:1\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$CV=C{V}_{interolog}\times C{V}_{DDI}$$\end{document}CV=CVinterolog×CVDDI 2\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$C{V}_{interolog}=\frac{{\sum }_{i=1}^{N}{S}_{i}{M}_{i}}{N}$$\end{document}CVinterolog=∑i=1NSiMiN 3\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$C{V}_{DDI}=dD$$\end{document}CVDDI=dDwhere S ∈ {0, 1} is the existence factor, indicating the presence of an orthologous protein pair in cassava genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In this study, S is always equal to 1 because orthologous protein pairs need to be identified prior to being incorporated in the MePPI-In. M refers to the reliability of the method by which the interactions were identified: 0.5 for computational prediction, and 1 for experimental measurement. N ∈ {1, 2, …, 7} is the number of species from which the protein-protein interactions in cassava were inferred. D = [0, 1] refers to domain enrichment, which is the ratio of the reported DDI pairs to all interactions possibly happening among domains in a protein pair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>For example, D calculated for three and four domain-containing proteins that interact via two DDIs is equal to 2/(3 × 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To compensate the probability bias in calculation of D for the studied protein pairs that contain only one domain, the correction factor (d) = 0.5 was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, d was set to 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Analysis of topology and functional content of MePPI-In </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In network was characterized in terms of topology and biological function relevance (Fig. 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The topology of the network was analyzed using network analysis tools in Cytoscape64. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The topological characteristics of MePPI-In were then compared with those of the cassava random network (simulated by Cytoscape containing the same number of nodes and average number of edges as MePPI-In), Arabidopsis36 and rice9 PPI networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Biological function of the proteins in MePPI-In was examined through AgriGO71, from which GO enrichment analysis was determined using REVIGO72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The results were illustrated in scatterplot graph and compared with the GO enrichment of proteins in Arabidopsis36 and rice9 PPI networks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Protein-protein interaction network of cassava </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The interaction between proteins is a transient phenomenon that allows cells to be regulated at post-translational level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Since experimental investigation of PPIs is difficult and requires huge effort, prediction of protein interactions through computational techniques has, thus, widely been accepted73,74. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In this study, interolog-based method was utilized to construct a genome-scale PPI network of cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Upon the homology-based principle of this method, seven plant species were selected as templates, based on one of the three criteria (the model plant, Arabidopsis, has abundant PPI information; potato, rice and maize are starch-storing crops; castor bean, poplar and soybean are closely related to cassava). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>According to PPI information from various databases (Fig. 1a), Arabidopsis has the most abundant PPI information (235,215 interactions of 17,962 proteins) followed by rice (76,829 interactions of 5,219 proteins), potato (42 interactions of 48 proteins), maize (25 interactions of 29 proteins), soybean (10 interactions of 12 proteins), castor bean (10 interactions of 10 proteins), and poplar (8 interactions of 10 proteins) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>To infer PPI information for cassava from each template plant, BLASTp search of the cassava genome sequence database was carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The cassava orthologous proteins that showed identity percentage ≥60, coverage percentage ≥80 and e-value ≤ 10−10 were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>If these orthologous proteins matched the proteins of template plants that had previously been identified to have protein-protein interaction, such interactions were regarded as orthologous PPIs in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Based on the results obtained, majority of the inferred PPIs were from Arabidopsis (90,069 interactions) followed by rice (212 interactions), potato (19 interactions), soybean (7 interactions), maize and poplar (5 interactions each) and castor bean (2 interactions) (Table 1).Table 1Protein-protein interactions in plant templates and MePPI-In.PlantsGenome Information60 PPI InformationMePPI-InNumber of genesNumber of proteinsNumber of PPIsNumber of proteinsSourcesInfered PPIs in cassavaOrthologs in casssavaArabidopsis27,41635,386235,21517,962ref.36 – ref.39 90,0697,193ref.62 – ref.63 Rice55,986154,31076,8295,219ref.9, ref.62 21284Potato35,11959,6994248ref.62 1915Maize32,54088,3832529ref.62 58Soybean54,17583,7951012ref.62 77Poplar41,33583,796810ref.62 57Castorbean25,87831,5761010ref.62 2290,1737,209 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The resulting interolog-based PPI network of cassava, or MePPI-In, is comprised of 90,173 interactions interconnecting 7,209 proteins, which accounted for c.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>21 percent of proteins in the whole genome (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The overall predicted PPIs are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi">http://bml.sbi.kmutt.ac.th/ppi</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 illustrates the overview of MePPI-In within which subnetwork demonstrated partial set of protein interaction, metabolism and sub-metabolism with specific group of proteins of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>It is important to note here that different colors were given to both interactions (edges) and proteins (nodes) to indicate whether their existence could be supported by other evidences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Edge colors represented interactions from interolog-based method with or without co-expression or DDI support (black or grey), while node colors denoted the proteins with or without expression data (blue or orange) (see more details in the Supporting the interactions section below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Approximately 99 percent of the PPIs in MePPI-In were inferred from Arabidopsis and rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>None of the interactions included in our network was presented in all seven template plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>These results implied that availability of data was the main limitation in inference-based PPI network construction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To improve the confidence of the network derived originally from interolog-based prediction method, other available types of data, such as expression or domain-domain interaction, could be incorporated in the newly constructed MePPI-In. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Supporting the interactions of proteins with expression data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Our MePPI-In was constructed using interolog-based method, which could only project the known PPIs in other plants to cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, it might be helpful if collective information could be incorporated to support the occurrence of such predictions in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In this study, expression of the proteins included in MePPI-In was examined using information from seven protein expression50–53,56,57,59 and four gene expression datasets45,65–67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, co-expression of each interacting protein pair was also determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>This was based on the fact that interaction between two proteins occurs only if both proteins are presented at the same time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>From eleven expression datasets exploited here, 4,698 proteins expression were detected, from the total number of 7,209 proteins in MePPI-In, (Fig. 3a, Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, different colors were given to nodes (or proteins) shown in Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The blue color nodes highlighted the proteins with supporting expression data, while the orange ones had no supporting expression data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Since expression of the proteins from eleven expression datasets indicated their presence in cassava, these proteins were then considered available for the interactions among them to occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>From the total of 90,173 interactions in MePPI-In, 35,146 interactions (or 39 percent) were observed to connect the proteins with supporting expression data.Figure 3MePPI-In with supporting expression evidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>(a) Overview of the number of proteins in MePPI-In and expression information45,50–53,56,57,59,65–67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The numbers in parenthesis represented the total number of genes or proteins in each cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(b) The list of PPIs between proteins with co-expression profiles derived from time-series expression datasets of Yang et al.45 (cassava fibrous, intermediate and storage roots at 4 months), Li et al.65 (cassava leaves, stems and roots harvested at 2nd, 4th, 7th and 10th month), An et al.66 (cassava apical shoots subjected to cold at 7 °C for 0, 4 and 9 h) and Naconsie et al.52 (cassava storage roots harvested at 3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th months). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The resulting interactions were classified into three groups based on the number of proteins and their topologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Each protein was presented as a circle in the color that corresponds to the graph of its expression profile (see more information in Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Among the eleven expression datasets, the time-series datasets of Naconsie et al.52, Yang et al.45, Li et al.65 and An et al.66 were utilized to observe the correlation of expression between two proteins (Pearson correlation coefficient score (PCC) &gt; 0.9 and p-value &lt; 0.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>From the results obtained, there were 16 interactions that were identified to interconnect the proteins with co-expression pattern (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We further classified these PPIs into three groups based on the number of protein members and the types of interactions (Fig. 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>First, the heterodimeric interactions represented interactions between two proteins, for example, an interaction between methionine adenosyltransferase 3 (M3) and small ubiquitin-like modifier 1 (SUMO1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The second group represented linear multimeric interactions, which probably exhibited the sequential functional relationship between proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The third was circular multimeric interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The interactions between nucleolar complex protein 2 (NOC2P), ribosomal RNA processing brix domain protein (RRB) and pescadillo-like protein (PES) potentially suggested functional relationship of these proteins in rRNA processing and cell proliferation control75. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Supporting the interaction of proteins with DDI data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>From our MePPI-In, reliability of each PPI was determined by incorporating the information on domain-domain interaction (DDI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This was based upon the observation that the proteins usually interact via specific domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In this work, the domain information of proteins in MePPI-In were obtained from Pfam database69 and the interactions between protein domains were from iPfam database70 (Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>From the total number of proteins proposed in MePPI-In, only 4,963 proteins (or 69 percent) were identified to have at least one domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>From these numbers, only 1,981 proteins (or 27 percent of the proteins proposed in MePPI-In or 40 percent of the proteins with domain information) were indicated, by iPfam, to interact via specific domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, only 6,826 from 90,173 interactions (~seven percent) could be confirmed through DDI information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Even with Pfam and iPfam, the largest universal repositories of protein domain information, only a small fraction of interactions initially proposed in MePPI-In were identified to have supporting DDI information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>However, this did not mean that the DDI information could not provide any insight into the confidence level of PPIs obtained from interolog-based prediction method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Ranking the confidence of PPIs in MePPI-In based on DDI data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In this study, the confidence of the predicted PPIs in MePPI-In was classified into two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The PPIs with high confidence level (High (H), Table 2) represented those with supporting domain information (6,826 PPIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The other class which exhibited basal confidence level (Basal (B), Table 2) included the remaining interactions in MePPI-In (83,347 PPIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Emphases on the class of high confidence level, confidence value (CV) scores, for the 6,826 PPIs, were determined and classified into three sub-groups, based on the percentile rank of the CV scores (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The CV score basically ranges from 0 to 1, from the lowest to the highest level of confidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>However, the distribution of CV scores was observed to be positively skewed, meaning that majority of the PPIs had the CV score ≤ 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>This was because most of the PPIs in MePPI-In were obtained from computational prediction, not experimental measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the factor M for the calculation of CV interolog was set at 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Also, in most cases, the correction factor d for the calculation of CV DDI was set at 0.5 to represent the DDIs between proteins with only one domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The small values of both CV interolog and CV DDI only allowed a maximum final CV scores of 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, percentile calculation was employed to further classify these high confidence PPIs into three sub-classes: H1 (percentile of CV score &gt; 80), H2 (percentile of CV score: 50–80) and H3 (percentile of CV score &lt; 50) (Table 2).Table 2Classification of predicted PPIs based on the confidence level.Confidence levelRange of confidence value (CV)NumberPPIsProteinsTotal MePPI-In——90,1737,209Interolog, no DDI informationBasal (B)—83,3475,228Interolog, DDI - heterodimerHigh (H)[0.00, 1.00]6,8261,981Percentile of CV score: &gt;80H1[0.14, 1.00]1,184733Percentile of CV score: 50–80H2[0.12, 0.14)3,8591,439Percentile of CV score: &lt;50H3[0.01, 0.12)1,783855 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As mentioned above, the current knowledge of protein domain and DDI information can support only up to seven percent of the overall interactions in MePPI-In. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, the confidence level obtained, along with the PPIs, herein, should help contrast the reliability of each prediction for further investigation by experimental approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of the MePPI-In Network </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In proposed in this study is the first genome-wide protein-protein interaction network of cassava consisting of 90,173 interactions and 7,209 proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Here, characteristics of the MePPI-In were described in terms of the global network topology and the functional coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>At last, we discussed how MePPI-In might be used to infer biological regulatory processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Some of these applications include (1) identification of a hub protein in the interactome cascade, (2) functional identification of unknown protein, (3) inference of protein complex formation, and (4) study of protein connections in metabolic pathway as well as connection of various metabolic pathways via protein-protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>These examples showed the contribution of MePPI-In in envisaging cellular communication via crosstalk at protein level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>MePPI-In performs as a biological network </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A protein-protein interaction network, such as MePPI-In, is generally constructed from available proteome and interactome data of reference species and the studied organism itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In proposed here included knowledge of PPIs from both cassava and other plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The constructed network contained a large number of possible interacting protein pairs; nonetheless, it was impossible to determine the exact coverage of the network constituents of the overall PPIs that exist in real living cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The ill-defined network boundary did not allow assessment of its representativeness in the cellular PPI matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In this circumstance, network topology was employed, at least as an alternative, to suggest the plausibility of the proposed network as if it possesses the properties of common biological network system76. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>To investigate topology of MePPI-In, the key global network properties, including node degree distribution, average path length (L) and clustering coefficient (C i), were determined according to graphical analysis method76. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In exhibited the biological network characteristics based upon the two supporting properties; scale-free and small world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>First, the connectivity (k) of the proteins in MePPI-In followed a power-law distribution, P(k)~k −γ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In exhibited scale-free property and showed an explicit deviation from a random network, in which most proteins had relatively the same numbers of interactions as shown in the relationship between degree and number of nodes (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In MePPI-In, most proteins have only a few interactions and only a few proteins, called hub proteins, have a large number of interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The scale-free property is not only observed in MePPI-In, but also occurs in other types of biological networks76, such as metabolic network, and gene regulatory network77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>MePPI-In was analyzed and compared with the PPI networks of Arabidopsis36 and rice9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 described the various features of these PPI networks, including network diameter, average path length and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Although these PPI networks contained different numbers of interactions and proteins, all of them followed a power law distribution, a common behavior of biological networks in living organisms.Figure 4The global network properties of protein-protein interaction networks in cassava, Arabidopsis and rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Second, the MePPI-In possessed a small-world structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>According to the definition given by Watz and Strogatz78, the average path length of a small-world network must be relatively greater than average path length (L) of random network, while the clustering coefficient (C i) of small world network is relatively much higher than C i of random network (L small world ≥ L random but C i small world ≫ C i random). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The average path length (average of shortest paths between all possible pairs of proteins in the network) value of MePPI-In was 3.53, slightly greater than that of the random network with the same number of nodes and average number of edges per node (3.04). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the much higher clustering coeffiecient of MePPI-In, when comparing with random network shown in Fig. 4, also supported the small world property of our network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This property of MePPI-In is considered beneficial, since it can protect cassava from any perturbation caused by endogenous and exogenous stimuli. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, based on the two network properties mentioned above, MePPI-In exhibits a well-presented biological network behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>It is thus presumed that the MePPI-In contains sufficient information, hence, could be utilized as the model PPI network in cassava. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Functional content of MePPI-In </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Besides the network topology, functional content of proteins in MePPI-In was determined to demonstrate some PPI-based regulation in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The functional coverage of proteins in the network was examined by GO analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The results were presented based on three classes of gene ontology79, biological process, molecular function and cellular component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In addition to the basic GO terms, GO enrichment of proteins in MePPI-In was examined and the results were presented in scatterplot (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The node color showed degree of enrichment ranging from low (red) to high (blue), while the node size represented the frequency of proteins in each functional group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>According to the scatterplot of MePPI-In, a large number of proteins, in ‘biological process’ class, were identified to be related to cellular and metabolic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>These corresponded to the result in the ‘molecular function’ class, in which a large number of the proteins were observed to have catalytic activity or binding capacity, probably acting as enzymes in metabolic pathways and transcription factors in cellular regulatory processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>For the last class of gene ontology or the ‘cellular component’, our results provided no information on specific compartments of the cell where the PPIs tend to occur.Figure 5Comparison of the functional content of MePPI-In and the PPI networks of Arabidopsis and rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The scatterplots were derived based on GO enrichment analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The node color showed degree of enrichment ranging from low (red) to high (blue), while the node size represented the frequency of the proteins in each functional group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>By comparing MePPI-In with the Arabidopsis and rice PPI networks, some similarities of the functional content of the proteins were observed (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>These included the proteins that function in cellular processes and cellular metabolism, and possess catalytic or binding capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The functional content of MePPI-In was observed to be more closely related to Arabidopsis than to rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>These differences probably reflect the different nature of the plants as cassava and Arabidopsis are dicots, while rice is a monocot80,81. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Inference of biological regulation from MePPI-In </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The involvement of protein-protein interaction in mediating cellular regulation has been reported in several studies82–84. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>These studies demonstrated key roles of PPIs in post-translational regulation that governs biological processes in cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In similar manner, we propose possible post-translational regulation in cassava using the information acquired from MePPI-In. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Genome-scale network enabled us to access the extensive cooperation of PPIs underlying specific cellular regulatory process, beyond the explanation at an associative protein pair. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>As the first global protein interaction network in cassava, our MePPI-In was able to illustrate the complexity of cellular regulation in cassava, from the highly elaborate topology of the network (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Moreover, our cassava PPI network (MePPI-In) has brought various insights. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>First, it helps in identifying the most important protein whose significance is reflected by its number of interactions with diverse partner proteins (denoted as high node degree in Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Regarding the MePPI-In, heat shock protein 90.1 (HSP90.1; cassava4.1_002708m) showed the highest (620) number of connections (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>HSP90.1 was recognized as a communication hub because it interacts with various types of proteins including transcription factors, signaling proteins, structural proteins and enzymatic proteins (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>HSP90.1 was reported to play roles in various biological processes, including protein folding, intracellular transport, protein degradation and cell signaling85,86, which agrees with our finding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Similar to cassava, Arabidopsis and rice also use heat shock protein as the center of communication, but the hub protein in these two plants was heat shock protein 70 (HSP70)33,36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In MePPI-In, the HSP70 is one of the proteins with many connections (following only HPS90.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>However, partner proteins that interact with cassava HSP70 are different from those that interact with Arabidopsis and rice HSP70. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that cassava, Arabidopsis and rice may use these core proteins to respond to stress, but how these plants react are different since they use different mechanisms through different protein activities.Figure 6Interaction of the cassava heat shock protein 90.1 (HSP90.1; cassava4.1_002708m) and its partner proteins in MePPI-In. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The nodes represent the proteins; blue for proteins with supporting expression data45,50–53,56,57,59,65–67 and orange for proteins with no supporting data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The edges represent interactions between HSP90.1 and its partners. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Second, the MePPI-In might be used to identify functions of unknown proteins in similar manner to Sharan et al.87. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Proteins involved in same metabolic pathway usually interact to carry out a specific task required by cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>From MePPI-In, the unknown protein, cassava4.1_011746m, was observed to interact with five proteins; cassava4.1_032607m (basic leucine zipper transcription factor protein (bZIP)), cassava4.1_007074m (TGACG motif-binding factor 6), cassava4.1_015896m (response regulator 5), cassava4.1_023865m (response regulator 6), and cassava4.1_022288m (response regulator 9), all of which are transcription factors88,89 (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Based on its interaction with transcription factors, the unknown protein might act as another component in this transcriptional regulation cascade.Figure 7Interaction of an unknown protein (cassava4.1_011746m) with partner proteins with known function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The nodes represent the proteins; blue for proteins with supporting expression data45,50–53,56,57,59,65–67 and orange for proteins with no supporting data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The edges represent interactions between the unknown protein and its partners. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Third, the network could be used to investigate the possibility of proteins to form complexes, as in vivo proteins often work together by forming protein complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>From MePPI-In, interaction between ubiquitin-conjugating protein (E2; cassava4.1_017321m) and ubiquitin ligase proteins (E3; cassava4.1_000004m and cassava4.1_002295m) was observed with high interaction confidence (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>This finding agreed well with the results from previous study which reported that during ubiquitination process, ubiquitin-conjugating proteins form complexes with ubiquitin ligase proteins prior to binding to target proteins90. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>In addition to the proteins that are known to form complexes, our network also indicated additional protein components that might form complex with the ubiquitin-conjugating protein (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>These included the F-box family proteins, which were reported to mediate ubiquitination during protein degradation91, and galactose oxidase/kelch repeat superfamily proteins, which functions as substrate-specific adapter proteins in ubiquitin ligase binding92.Figure 8Protein complex of the cassava ubiquitin-conjugating protein (cassava4.1_017321m). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The nodes represent the proteins; ubiquitin-conjugating protein (yellow); ubiquitin ligases (green); F-box family proteins (purple); galactose oxidase/kelch repeat superfamily proteins (pink); other proteins (orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The edges represent PPIs: black – PPIs with DDI or co-expression support, and grey for – PPIs with no supporting data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Fourth, the network could be used to gain knowledge on a particular metabolic pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>As the value of cassava mainly relies on its capacity to synthesize and store starch, our MePPI-In might provide some insight related to the biosynthesis of starch in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Herein, all proteins involved in the CO2 fixation pathway (Calvin cycle), sucrose biosynthesis pathway and starch biosynthesis pathway (defined as starch proteins)47 as well as their partners, were presented in the form of starch sub-network (Fig. 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>According to Fig. 9, starch proteins interact not only with starch proteins, but with other proteins such as signaling proteins, regulatory proteins, and proteins in other metabolic pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that starch metabolism was tightly regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Since starch proteins connected to proteins in other metabolic processes, its perturbations could eventually affect whole organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This might be the reason why unexpected pleiotropic effects were often observed, even though the mutants in question had already been proven to lack only a single starch gene.Figure 9Cassava starch sub-network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The nodes represent starch proteins (green) and their first neighbors (orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The edges represent interactions between proteins; black for PPIs with DDI or co-expression supporting data, and grey for PPIs with no supporting information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Within the starch sub-network, the arrows indicated where the starch synthases (SS1, SS2, SS3, SS4), starch branching enzymes (SBE2.1, SBE2.2), isoamylase (ISA3) and ADP glucose pyrophosphorylase in large and small subunit (APL1, APS1) resided. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The study of protein-protein interaction allows us to envisage potential post-translational regulation that mediates the cellular processes in cassava. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Our MePPI-In is the first genome-scale protein-protein interaction network of cassava, consisting of 90,173 interactions and 7,209 proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In was constructed from extensive PPI data of seven plants (i.e. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Arabidopsis, rice, potato, maize, castor bean, soybean, and poplar) using interolog-based method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The MePPI-In contained the largest number of PPIs in cassava, which are involved in many biological processes especially cellular process, and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Moreover, confidence value (CV) was calculated to rank the reliability of the prediction, which is beneficial for the discovery of promising PPI for further investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The biological insights gained from the MePPI-In network, hopefully, fill a part of the current gap of knowledge on cassava proteins and their function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec18"><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Supplement Figure S1 Supplement Table S1 Supplement Table S2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-017-17633-2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank The National Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (BIOTEC, NSTDA) for R.T post-graduate scholarship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>We gratefully acknowledge computing facility of Systems Biology and Bioinformatics research group and HPC cluster, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by National Research Council of Thailand (NRCT) and National Science and Technology Development Agency (NSTDA) under Thailand Research Organizations Network (research grant: P-13-50437 and P-16-51275). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>R.T. and T.S. conceived and designed experiments, and performed the computational analysis. R.T., S.K. and T.S. analyzed the results and performed statistical ranking. All authors (R.T., S.K., S.N. and T.S.) discussed the results, wrote the manuscript, and approved the final version.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par34">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>1.SkolnickJFetrowJSFrom genes to protein structure and function: novel applications of computational approaches in the genomic eraTrends Biotechnol.200018343910.1016/S0167-7799(99)01398-0<?supplied-pmid 10631780?>10631780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>2.PhizickyEMFieldsSProtein-protein interactions: methods for detection and analysisMicrobiol Rev.19955994123<?supplied-pmid 7708014?>7708014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>3.CagneyGUetzPFieldsSHigh-throughput screening for protein-protein interactions using two-hybrid assayMethods Enzymol.200032831410.1016/S0076-6879(00)28386-9<?supplied-pmid 11075334?>11075334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>4.HoYSystematic identification of protein complexes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae by mass spectrometryNature.200241518018310.1038/415180a<?supplied-pmid 11805837?>11805837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>5.Rao, V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>S., Srinivas, K., Sujini, G. &amp; Kumar, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Protein-protein interaction detection: methods and analysis. Int J Proteomics. 2014 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>6.De BodtSProostSVandepoeleKRouzéPVan de PeerYPredicting protein-protein interactions in Arabidopsis thaliana through integration of orthology, gene ontology and co-expressionBMC genomics20091028810.1186/1471-2164-10-288<?supplied-pmid 19563678?>19563678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>7.HuangT-WLinC-YKaoC-YReconstruction of human protein interolog network using evolutionary conserved networkBMC bioinformatics2007815210.1186/1471-2105-8-152<?supplied-pmid 17493278?>17493278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>8.WangFPrediction and characterization of protein-protein interaction networks in swineProteome Sci.201210210.1186/1477-5956-10-2<?supplied-pmid 22230699?>22230699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>9.GuHZhuPJiaoYMengYChenMPRIN: a predicted rice interactome networkBMC bioinformatics201112110.1186/1471-2105-12-16121199577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>10.KrishnadevOSrinivasanNPrediction of protein–protein interactions between human host and a pathogen and its application to three pathogenic bacteria. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>JBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Macromolec.20114861361910.1016/j.ijbiomac.2011.01.030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>11.LiZ-GHeFZhangZPengY-LPrediction of protein–protein interactions between Ralstonia solanacearum and Arabidopsis thalianaAmino Acids2012422363237110.1007/s00726-011-0978-z<?supplied-pmid 21786137?>21786137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>12.MulderNJAkinolaROMazanduGKRapanoelHUsing biological networks to improve our understanding of infectious diseasesComput Struct Biotechnol J.20141111010.1016/j.csbj.2014.08.006<?supplied-pmid 25379138?>25379138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>13.BockJRGoughDAPredicting protein–protein interactions from primary structureBioinformatics20011745546010.1093/bioinformatics/17.5.455<?supplied-pmid 11331240?>11331240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>14.GomezSMNobleWSRzhetskyALearning to predict protein–protein interactions from protein sequencesBioinformatics2003191875188110.1093/bioinformatics/btg352<?supplied-pmid 14555619?>14555619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>15.JansenRA Bayesian networks approach for predicting protein-protein interactions from genomic dataScience200330244945310.1126/science.1087361<?supplied-pmid 14564010?>14564010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>16.BurgerLVan NimwegenEAccurate prediction of protein–protein interactions from sequence alignments using a Bayesian methodMol Syst Biol.2008416510.1038/msb4100203<?supplied-pmid 18277381?>18277381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>17.WassMNFuentesGPonsCPazosFValenciaATowards the prediction of protein interaction partners using physical dockingMol Syst Biol.2011746910.1038/msb.2011.3<?supplied-pmid 21326236?>21326236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>18.GuoFDingYLiZTangJIdentification of protein–protein interactions by detecting correlated mutation at the interfaceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Inf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Model.2015552042204910.1021/acs.jcim.5b00320<?supplied-pmid 26284382?>26284382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>19.WangLAn ensemble approach for large-scale identification of protein-protein interactions using the alignments of multiple sequencesOncotarget2017851495159<?supplied-pmid 28029645?>28029645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>20.LiZ-WAccurate prediction of protein-protein interactions by integrating potential evolutionary information embedded in PSSM profile and discriminative vector machine classifierOncotarget201782363823649<?supplied-pmid 28423569?>28423569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>21.LiZ-WYouZ-HChenXGuiJNieRHighly Accurate Prediction of Protein-Protein Interactions via Incorporating Evolutionary Information and Physicochemical CharacteristicsInt J Mol Sci.201617139610.3390/ijms17091396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>22.Li, J.-Q., You, Z.-H., Li, X., Zhong, M. &amp; Chen, X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>PSPEL: In Silico Prediction of Self-interacting Proteins from Amino Acids Sequences using Ensemble Learning. IEEE- ACM T Comput Bi (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>23.GuoYYuLWenZLiMUsing support vector machine combined with auto covariance to predict protein–protein interactions from protein sequencesNucleic Acids Res.2008363025303010.1093/nar/gkn159<?supplied-pmid 18390576?>18390576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>24.XiaJ-FHanKHuangD-SSequence-based prediction of protein-protein interactions by means of rotation forest and autocorrelation descriptorProtein Peptide Lett.20101713714510.2174/092986610789909403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>25.YouZ-HChanKCHuPPredicting protein-protein interactions from primary protein sequences using a novel multi-scale local feature representation scheme and the random forestPLoS One201510e012581110.1371/journal.pone.0125811<?supplied-pmid 25946106?>25946106 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>26.LinXChenXWHeterogeneous data integration by tree-augmented naïve Bayes for protein–protein interactions predictionProteomics20131326126810.1002/pmic.201200326<?supplied-pmid 23112070?>23112070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>27.AnJ-YIdentification of self-interacting proteins by exploring evolutionary information embedded in PSI-BLAST-constructed position specific scoring matrixOncotarget201678244082449<?supplied-pmid 27732957?>27732957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>28.AnJ-YRobust and accurate prediction of protein self-interactions from amino acids sequence using evolutionary informationMol Biosyst.2016123702371010.1039/C6MB00599C<?supplied-pmid 27759121?>27759121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>29.HuangY-AYouZ-HChenXChanKLuoXSequence-based prediction of protein-protein interactions using weighted sparse representation model combined with global encodingBMC bioinformatics20161718410.1186/s12859-016-1035-4<?supplied-pmid 27112932?>27112932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>30.HuangY-AYouZ-HChenXYanG-YImproved protein-protein interactions prediction via weighted sparse representation model combining continuous wavelet descriptor and PseAA compositionBMC Syst Biol.201610485548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>31.RhodesDRProbabilistic model of the human protein-protein interaction networkNat Biotechnol20052395195910.1038/nbt1103<?supplied-pmid 16082366?>16082366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>32.SinghRParkDXuJHosurRBergerBStruct2Net: a web service to predict protein–protein interactions using a structure-based approachNucleic Acids Res.201038W508W51510.1093/nar/gkq481<?supplied-pmid 20513650?>20513650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>33.HoC-LWuYShenH-bProvartNJGeislerMA predicted protein interactome for riceRice201251510.1186/1939-8433-5-15<?supplied-pmid 24279740?>24279740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>34.YueJPTIR: Predicted Tomato Interactome ResourceSci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Rep.201662504710.1038/srep25047<?supplied-pmid 27121261?>27121261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>35.Geisler-LeeJA predicted interactome for ArabidopsisPlant Physiol.200714531732910.1104/pp.107.103465<?supplied-pmid 17675552?>17675552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>36.BrandãoMMDantasLLSilva-FilhoMCAtPIN: Arabidopsis thaliana protein interaction networkBMC bioinformatics200910110.1186/1471-2105-10-45419118496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>37.CuiJAtPID: Arabidopsis thaliana protein interactome data base—an integrative platform for plant systems biologyNucleic Acids Res.200836D999D100810.1093/nar/gkm844<?supplied-pmid 17962307?>17962307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>38.LinMShenXChenXPAIR: the predicted Arabidopsis interactome resourceNucleic Acids Res.201139D1134D114010.1093/nar/gkq938<?supplied-pmid 20952401?>20952401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>39.PrietoCDe Las RivasJAPID: agile protein interaction DataAnalyzerNucleic Acids Res.200634W298W30210.1093/nar/gkl128<?supplied-pmid 16845013?>16845013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>40.SapkotaADIPOS: database of interacting proteins in Oryza sativaMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Biosyst.201172615262110.1039/c1mb05120b<?supplied-pmid 21713282?>21713282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>41.ZhuGPPIM: A protein-protein interaction database for maizePlant physiol.2016170261862610.1104/pp.15.01821<?supplied-pmid 26620522?>26620522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>42.DingY-DPrediction and functional analysis of the sweet orange protein-protein interaction networkBMC Plant Biol.20141421310.1186/s12870-014-0213-7<?supplied-pmid 25091279?>25091279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>43.Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Save and grow: cassava a guide to sustainable production intensification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>FAO <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/3/a-i3278e.pdf">http://www.fao.org/3/a-i3278e.pdf</ext-link> (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>44.SojikulPAFLP-based transcript profiling for cassava genome-wide expression analysis in the onset of storage root formationPhysiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Plant.201014018929810.1111/j.1399-3054.2010.01389.x<?supplied-pmid 20536786?>20536786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>45.YangJAnDZhangPExpression profiling of cassava storage roots reveals an active process of glycolysis/gluconeogenesisfJ Integr Plant Biol.20115319321110.1111/j.1744-7909.2010.01018.x<?supplied-pmid 21205184?>21205184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>46.IhemereUArias-GarzonDLawrenceSSayreRGenetic modification of cassava for enhanced starch productionPlant Biotechnol J.2006445346510.1111/j.1467-7652.2006.00195.x<?supplied-pmid 17177810?>17177810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>47.SaithongTStarch biosynthesis in cassava: a genome-based pathway reconstruction and its exploitation in data integrationBMC Syst Biol.201377510.1186/1752-0509-7-75<?supplied-pmid 23938102?>23938102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>48.SiriwatWTranscriptomic data integration inferring the dominance of starch biosynthesis in carbon utilization of developing cassava rootsProcedia Comput Sci.2012119610610.1016/j.procs.2012.09.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>49.BabaAIProteome analysis of secondary somatic embryogenesis in cassava (Manihot esculenta)Plant Sci.200817571772310.1016/j.plantsci.2008.07.014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>50.LiKProteome characterization of cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) somatic embryos, plantlets and tuberous rootsProteome Sci.20108110.1186/1477-5956-8-120142993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>51.MitprasatMRoytrakulSJiemsupSBoonsengOYokthongwattanaKLeaf proteomic analysis in cassava (Manihot esculenta, Crantz) during plant development, from planting of stem cutting to storage root formationPlanta20112331209122110.1007/s00425-011-1373-4<?supplied-pmid 21327816?>21327816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>52.NaconsieMCassava root membrane proteome reveals activities during storage root maturationJ Plant Res.2016129516510.1007/s10265-015-0761-4<?supplied-pmid 26547558?>26547558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>53.OwitiJiTRAQ-based analysis of changes in the cassava root proteome reveals pathways associated with post-harvest physiological deteriorationPlant J.20116714515610.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04582.x<?supplied-pmid 21435052?>21435052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>54.Batista de SouzaCRPv dos ReisSCastelo Branco CarvalhoLJAn overview of protein identification studies in cassavaCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Protein Pept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Sci.20151621922710.2174/1389203716666150224145407<?supplied-pmid 25707473?>25707473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>55.SchmitzGJde Magalhães AndradeJValleTLLabateCAdo NascimentoJRComparative proteome analysis of the tuberous roots of six cassava (Manihot esculenta) varieties reveals proteins related to phenotypic traitsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Food Chem.2016643293330110.1021/acs.jafc.5b05585<?supplied-pmid 26982619?>26982619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>56.SheffieldJTaylorNFauquetCChenSThe cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) root proteome: protein identification and differential expressionProteomics200661588159810.1002/pmic.200500503<?supplied-pmid 16421938?>16421938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>57.VanderschurenHLarge-scale proteomics of the cassava storage root and identification of a target gene to reduce postharvest deteriorationPlant Cell2014261913192410.1105/tpc.114.123927<?supplied-pmid 24876255?>24876255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>58.Wang, X. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Proteomics profiling reveals carbohydrate metabolic enzymes and 14-3-3 proteins play important roles for starch accumulation during cassava root tuberization. Sci Rep. 6 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>59.ZhaoPAnalysis of different strategies adapted by two cassava cultivars in response to drought stress: ensuring survival or continuing growthJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Bot.20146651477148810.1093/jxb/eru507<?supplied-pmid 25547914?>25547914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>60.GoodsteinDMPhytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomicsNucleic Acids Res.201240D1178D118610.1093/nar/gkr944<?supplied-pmid 22110026?>22110026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>61.UniProt ConsortiumUniProt: a hub for protein informationNucleic Acids Res.201543D204D21210.1093/nar/gku98925348405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>62.KerrienSThe IntAct molecular interaction database in 2012Nucleic Acids Res.201140D841D84610.1093/nar/gkr1088<?supplied-pmid 22121220?>22121220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>63.Chatr-AryamontriAMINT: the molecular interaction databaseNucleic Acids Res.200735D572D57410.1093/nar/gkl950<?supplied-pmid 17135203?>17135203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>64.Kohl, M., Wiese, S. &amp; Warscheid, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Cytoscape: software for visualization and analysis of biological networks. Data mining in proteomics: from standards to applications, 291-303 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>65.LiY-ZAn ordered EST catalogue and gene expression profiles of cassava (Manihot esculenta) at key growth stagesPlant Mol Biol.20107457359010.1007/s11103-010-9698-0<?supplied-pmid 20957510?>20957510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>66.AnDYangJZhangPTranscriptome profiling of low temperature-treated cassava apical shoots showed dynamic responses of tropical plant to cold stressBMC genomics20121316410.1186/1471-2164-13-64<?supplied-pmid 22321773?>22321773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>67.UtsumiYTranscriptome analysis using a high-density oligomicroarray under drought stress in various genotypes of cassava: an important tropical cropDNA Res.20121933534510.1093/dnares/dss016<?supplied-pmid 22619309?>22619309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>68.SchmidMA gene expression map of Arabidopsis thaliana developmentNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Genet.20053750150610.1038/ng1543<?supplied-pmid 15806101?>15806101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>69.FinnRDPfam: the protein families databaseNucleic Acids Res.201342D222D23010.1093/nar/gkt1223<?supplied-pmid 24288371?>24288371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>70.FinnRDMillerBLClementsJBatemanAiPfam: a database of protein family and domain interactions found in the Protein Data BankNucleic Acids Res.201442D364D37310.1093/nar/gkt1210<?supplied-pmid 24297255?>24297255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>71.DuZZhouXLingYZhangZSuZAgriGO: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural communityNucleic Acids Res.201038W64W7010.1093/nar/gkq310<?supplied-pmid 20435677?>20435677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>72.SupekFBošnjakMŠkuncaNŠmucTREVIGO summarizes and visualizes long lists of gene ontology termsPloS one201167e2180010.1371/journal.pone.0021800<?supplied-pmid 21789182?>21789182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>73.ValenciaAPazosFComputational methods for the prediction of protein interactionsCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Biol.20021236837310.1016/S0959-440X(02)00333-0<?supplied-pmid 12127457?>12127457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>74.SkrabanekLSainiHKBaderGDEnrightAJComputational prediction of protein–protein interactionsMol Biotechnol.20083811710.1007/s12033-007-0069-2<?supplied-pmid 18095187?>18095187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>75.TsesmetzisNArabidopsis reactome: a foundation knowledgebase for plant systems biologyPlant cell.2008201426143610.1105/tpc.108.057976<?supplied-pmid 18591350?>18591350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>76.AlbertRScale-free networks in cell biologyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Sci.20051184947495710.1242/jcs.02714<?supplied-pmid 16254242?>16254242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>77.Goll, J. &amp; Uetz, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Analyzing protein interaction networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics-From Genomes toTherapies (ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Lengauer, T.)1121–1177 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>78.WattsDJStrogatzSHCollective dynamics of ‘small-world’ networksNature199839344044210.1038/30918<?supplied-pmid 9623998?>9623998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>79.AshburnerMGene ontology: tool for the unification of biologyNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Genet.200025252910.1038/75556<?supplied-pmid 10802651?>10802651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>80.MorilloSATaxFEfunctional analysis of receptor-like kinases in monocots and dicotsCurr Opin Plant Biol.2006946046910.1016/j.pbi.2006.07.009<?supplied-pmid 16877029?>16877029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>81.NelissenHGonzalezNInzéDLeaf growth in dicots and monocots: so different yet so alikeCurr Opin Plant Biol.201633727610.1016/j.pbi.2016.06.009<?supplied-pmid 27344391?>27344391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>82.KikuchiAKishidaSYamamotoHRegulation of Wnt signaling by protein-protein interaction and post-translational modificationsExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Med.200638111010.1038/emm.2006.1<?supplied-pmid 16520547?>16520547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>83.SchützeKHarterKChabanCPost-translational regulation of plant bZIP factorsTrends Plant Sci.20081324725510.1016/j.tplants.2008.03.002<?supplied-pmid 18424222?>18424222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>84.ZhengZThe protein kinase SnRK2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>6 mediates the regulation of sucrose metabolism and plant growth in ArabidopsisPlant Physiol.20101539911310.1104/pp.109.150789<?supplied-pmid 20200070?>20200070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>85.JakobULilieHMeyerIBuchnerJTransient interaction of Hsp90 with early unfolding intermediates of citrate synthase implications for heat shock in vivoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Chem.19952707288729410.1074/jbc.270.13.7288<?supplied-pmid 7706269?>7706269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>86.PicardDHeat-shock protein 90, a chaperone for folding and regulationCell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Life Sci.2002591640164810.1007/PL00012491<?supplied-pmid 12475174?>12475174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>87.SharanRUlitskyIShamirRNetwork-based prediction of protein functionMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Biol.200738810.1038/msb4100129<?supplied-pmid 17353930?>17353930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>88.JakobyMbZIP transcription factors in ArabidopsisTrends Plant Sci.2002710611110.1016/S1360-1385(01)02223-3<?supplied-pmid 11906833?>11906833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>89.ToJPType-A Arabidopsis response regulators are partially redundant negative regulators of cytokinin signalingPlant Cell200416365867110.1105/tpc.018978<?supplied-pmid 14973166?>14973166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>90.NandiDTahilianiPKumarAChanduDThe ubiquitin-proteasome systemJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Biosci.20063113715510.1007/BF02705243<?supplied-pmid 16595883?>16595883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>91.CraigKLTyersMThe F-box: a new motif for ubiquitin dependent proteolysis in cell cycle regulation and signal transductionProg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Biol.19997229932810.1016/S0079-6107(99)00010-3<?supplied-pmid 10581972?>10581972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>92.RisseeuwEPProtein interaction analysis of SCF ubiquitin E3 ligase subunits from ArabidopsisPlant J.20033475376710.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01768.x<?supplied-pmid 12795696?>12795696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
