<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5959848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">26006</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-26006-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A logic-based method to build signaling networks and propose experimental plans </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rougny</surname><given-names>Adrien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gloaguen</surname><given-names>Pauline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Langonné</surname><given-names>Nathalie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crépieux</surname><given-names>Pascale</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0617-0935</contrib-id><name><surname>Poupon</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><address><email>anne.poupon@inra.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Froidevaux</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2230 7538</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.208504.b</institution-id><institution>Biotechnology Research Institute for Drug Discovery, </institution><institution>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST), Aomi, </institution></institution-wrap>Tokyo, 135-0064 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2182 6141</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12366.30</institution-id><institution>PRC, INRA, CNRS, </institution><institution>Université François Rabelais-Tours, </institution></institution-wrap>37380 Nouzilly, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2182 6141</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12366.30</institution-id><institution>CNRS; Université François-Rabelais de Tours, UMR 7292, </institution></institution-wrap>37032 Tours, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 2558</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5842.b</institution-id><institution>Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique UMR CNRS 8623, </institution><institution>Université Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay, </institution></institution-wrap>Orsay Cedex, 91405 France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>7830</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>With the dramatic increase of the diversity and the sheer quantity of biological data generated, the construction of comprehensive signaling networks that include precise mechanisms cannot be carried out manually anymore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this context, we propose a logic-based method that allows building large signaling networks automatically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Our method is based on a set of expert rules that make explicit the reasoning made by biologists when interpreting experimental results coming from a wide variety of experiment types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>These rules allow formulating all the conclusions that can be inferred from a set of experimental results, and thus building all the possible networks that explain these results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Moreover, given an hypothesis, our system proposes experimental plans to carry out in order to validate or invalidate it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the performance of our method, we applied our framework to the reconstruction of the FSHR-induced and the EGFR-induced signaling networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The FSHR is known to induce the transactivation of the EGFR, but very little is known on the resulting FSH- and EGF-dependent network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We built a single network using data underlying both networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This leads to a new hypothesis on the activation of MEK by p38MAPK, which we validate experimentally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These preliminary results represent a first step in the demonstration of a cross-talk between these two major MAP kinases pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Within a multicellular organism, the behavior of individual cells is partly controlled by hormones that bind to their cognate receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Binding of the ligand triggers conformational changes of the receptor’s spatial structure, resulting in the increase or decrease of its affinity for intracellular partners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In the case of G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs), binding of the extracellular ligand and resulting conformational changes lead to the binding of G proteins and β-arrestins to the intracellular domains of the receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In turn, this leads to a number of intracellular cascades, activating or inhibiting intracellular proteins, such as the ERK cascade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>These cascades lead, among other things, to the activation/inhibition of transcription factors that regulate gene transcription, and to the activation/inhibition of proteins of the translation machinery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Deciphering these networks is done through numerous wet-lab experiments, and in particular the observation of protein phosphorylation, which plays a major role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The representation of these networks is a diagram, usually referred to as the influence graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>As our knowledge of the complexity of signaling pathways has increased, the influence graphs representing them have also grown in size and complexity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>During the past decade, the development of Systems Biology has led to comprehensive reconstructions of large signaling pathways, by gathering results found in the literature1–4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>These reconstructed pathways have two particularities as compared to diagrams found earlier in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>First, rather than simply depicting influences of molecules on each other (e.g. A activates B), these pathways are detailed representations of the molecular mechanisms that come into play (e.g. A phosphorylates B, and phosphorylated B is active). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Second, these pathways are now represented using standards, such as the Systems Biology Graphical Notation (SBGN) Process Description language5 (PD), which helps their understanding6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The construction of such comprehensive networks has become difficult due to the ever-growing amount of biological data and experimental results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these networks are usually not updated with new findings, due to the cost of these updates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Consequently, automated methods to build such networks are highly needed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Some methods that automatically build molecular networks have already been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A first class of methods relies on literature mining7–9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These methods use Natural Language Processing techniques to extract relevant relationships between molecules (such as “A influences the phosphorylation of B”) from scientific papers, either abstracts7 or main text8,9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These extracted relationships are used to build a molecular network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These methods allow building comprehensive networks taking into account the vast amount of available literature; however, they do not permit to infer new unknown relationships. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Other methods build networks directly from experimental data10–12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A number of these methods use statistical inference (e.g. co-expression analysis, Bayesian analysis) to build gene networks from gene expression data13–16 or phosphoproteomic data17–19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Such techniques are powerful to unveil new relationships hidden deep in the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>However, they function as black boxes, and do not allow to identify the precise data used to build a given relation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Finally, a third category, relying on the use of experimental data, adopts a radically different point of view, by using reasoning techniques to interpret qualitative data20,21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Those methods define expert rules that allow interpreting experimental data in order to build gene regulatory networks20 or executable models of signaling pathways21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>These models are reaction networks, as they model different molecular processes (e.g. translocations, state transition processes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, again, the precise biological knowledge underlying a given inferred relation remains implicit22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Hence, such an inference method21 does not aim at building molecular networks that could then be interpreted using different semantics (e.g. Ordinary Differential Equations (ODE)), but rather at building models that already carry a modeling semantics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Another current limitation of this method is the lack of rules to infer relationships from perturbation experiments (such as those involving inhibitors, siRNA, knock-outs or mutants), which are widely used in signaling biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Herein, we introduce a new logic-based method to build networks of biochemical reactions from raw experimental results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We have built a large set of interpretative logic rules that allow mimicking the reasoning biologists apply when interpreting experimental results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Our expert rules are formalized within first-order logic, which allows to capture the deductive nature of the expert’s reasoning using logical implication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this formalism is expressive enough to formalize this reasoning as far as it allows general rules to be instantiated in several ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These rules allow inferring precise biochemical mechanisms from a wide variety of experiments, including perturbation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>They also allow formulating new hypothetical relations that can then be tested experimentally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Using explicit rules, traces of the reasoning used for the inference can be obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Meaning that for any relation within the inferred network, the set of experimental data and rules used to build this relation can be consulted by the expert. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Those are of particular importance when two potentially contradictory pieces of knowledge are inferred, as these originate from contradictory experimental results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In that case, the user is able to go back to these experimental results, and either resolve the contradiction, or choose to ignore some. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Finally, rules were built such that the inference process can be inverted, unveiling an unprecedented feature: the automatic proposition of experimental plans to test given biological hypotheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>We illustrate our method by building the signaling networks triggered by the folliculo-stimulating hormone receptor (FSHR) and the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Given that the binding of the follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) to its receptor is known to transactivate the EGFR, we also deduce an integrated network from experiments conducted in the study of both individual networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>This led us to the hypothesis that, as a result of FSH stimulation, p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (p38MAPK) activates dual specificity mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase (MEK), through the transactivation of EGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We give first experimental evidences that validate this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Explicit interpretative rules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Systems Biology mostly focuses on mechanisms: reactions (e.g. post-translational modifications, complexations) and modulations (e.g. catalyzes, inhibitions) of these reactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>This knowledge is usually represented under the form of graphs, where nodes represent the involved molecules, and arcs represent reactions and modulations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Biologists use implicit deductive reasoning to infer new biological knowledge from experimental results, thus interpreting them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The implicit deductive rules with which they reason follow the generic framework:R1\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{c}\,{\rm{IF}}\,{\rm{an}}\,experimental\,result\,{\rm{is}}\,{\rm{observed}}\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{\rm{some}}\,pieces\,of\,biological\,knowledge\,{\rm{hold}}\\ {\rm{THEN}}\,{\rm{new}}\,pieces\,of\,biological\,knowledge\,{\rm{are}}\,{\rm{established}}\,{\rm{or}}\,{\rm{hypothesized}}\end{array}$$\end{document}IFanexperimentalresultisobservedandsomepiecesofbiologicalknowledgeholdTHENnewpiecesofbiologicalknowledgeareestablishedorhypothesized </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Those rules are general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Of course, a specific experimental result will lead to a specific interpretation, i.e. to an instantiated piece of biological knowledge, but the manner wherewith it is interpreted does not depend on this particular result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Hence rules in the form of (R1) do not apply only to a particular realization of an experiment but rather to some type of experiment, and it is possible to make explicit the general rules used to interpret results obtained from various types of experiments in order to automate the construction of signaling networks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Building the rules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For a given experiment type, we have built one or more interpretative rules by deciphering the molecular processes that come into play while undertaking this experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Let us consider a simple phosphorylation assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In that type of experiment, the quantity of a given target phosphorylated molecule (e.g. phosphorylated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (phospho-ERK)) is compared between a cell lysate obtained from untreated cells (the control), and a cell lysate obtained from cells previously treated with a signal (e.g. an hormone such as FSH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The measurement of the quantity of the target molecule may be carried out by means of an antibody specific to the given phosphorylation or incorporation of radioactive phosphate for example. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The only molecular process that comes into play here is the production of the target molecule from another form of that molecule (e.g. phospho-ERK is produced by the phosphorylation of ERK), which is known to the experimenter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Hence, if ERK is more phosphorylated in the presence of FSH as compared to the control, we can conclude that FSH stimulates the phosphorylation of ERK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Of course, it doesn’t mean that this modulation is direct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Conversely, if the phosphorylation of ERK was weaker, we would conclude that FSH inhibits the phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Finally, if the phosphorylation levels were identical in both conditions, we would conclude that FSH has no effect on the reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>An experimental result obtained from such an experiment can be interpreted by means of the following rule, considering that the detector is an antibody, and that a greater quantity of the target molecule was observed in the treated cells than in the control: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>IF a phosphorylation assay in which the signal is a molecule X, the target molecule Ya being detected by an antibody A and obtained by transformation of a molecule Y, demonstrates a greater quantity of Ya in cells treated by X than in the control cells, THEN X stimulates the process that transforms Y into Ya. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>This interpretative rule can be formalized in first-order logic as follows:R2\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{l}\,{\rm{IF}}\,pa(X,Y,A,increase)\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,antibodyAgainst(A,{Y}^{a})\,and\,{mod}ifiedForm({Y}^{a},Y)\\ {\rm{THEN}}\,{modulates}(X,Y,{Y}^{a},increase,unknown,confirmed)\end{array}$$\end{document}IFpa(X,Y,A,increase)andantibodyAgainst(A,Ya)andmodifiedForm(Ya,Y)THENmodulates(X,Y,Ya,increase,unknown,confirmed) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The left-hand side of the rule (before the “THEN”) is called its premises, while its right-hand side is called its conclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The experimental result is expressed in the premises, while its interpretation is given in the conclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Such deductive rules should be read as follows: IF the premises hold, THEN the conclusion holds. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Lowercase symbols before the opening parenthesis (e.g. pa (phosphorylation assay) or modulates) are predicate symbols that express relations between molecules or parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Their arguments (here, variables and constants) are contained between the associated parentheses: lowercase symbols (e.g. increase, confirmed) are constants that refer to molecules or specific parameters, while uppercase symbols (e.g. X, A) are variables that refer to any molecule or parameter value, and can be instantiated by constants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A fully instantiated predicate (i.e. with all its variables replaced by constants), such as modulates(fsh, erk, perk, increase, unknown, confirmed), is called a fact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The predicate symbol modulates takes six arguments, and modulates (X, Y, Ya, E, D, S) qualifies the modulation by molecule X of the process that transforms molecule Y into molecule Ya. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The three additional arguments are parameters of this modulation:E is the effect parameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>It stands for the effect of the modulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>It can take three values: increase, decrease, or noeffect, depending on whether the modulation is a stimulation, an inhibition or absent, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This parameter is also an argument of predicates that express experimental results such as pa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>For those, increase, decrease and noeffect constants indicate a higher, a lower and an equal quantity of a target molecule in the treated cells than in the control cells, respectively.D is the distance parameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>It stands for the distance with which the modulation takes place: a direct modulation (i.e. with no intermediaries) is represented by the direct constant, and an indirect stimulation by the indirect constant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>As for the unknown constant, it indicates that the distance with which the modulation takes place is unknown.S is the status parameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It can take one of the three values confirmed, hypothesis and infirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The confirmed constant indicates that the modulation has been experimentally validated; the hypothesis constant indicates that the modulation is hypothetical, and should be proved by further experiments; and the infirmed constant indicates that the modulation has been experimentally invalidated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Different interpretative rules for different types of experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Although the number of different experiment types that exist is large, the vast majority of experiments conducted in Systems Biology studies belong to a reduced list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>We have gathered 28 different experiment types that were used to establish a comprehensive map of the FSHR-induced network4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Table 1 shows the different types of experiments taken into account. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A complete description of the various types of experiments is given in Listing of predicates in Supplementary Note.Table 1All types of experiments that can be interpreted by the set of expert rules.Type of the conclusionMethodCategoryDisruptorDetection methodExperiment typeExperimental result predicateConceptual experiment type predicateModulationDosageEnzymatic assayRadio25EAea(X, S1, S2, E)simpleEa(X, S1, S2, E)Antagonist50ACPEAacpea(X, S1, S2, I, E)complexEa(X, S1, S2, I, E)Inhibitor50ICPEAicpea(X, S1, S2, I, E)siRNA75SCPEAscpea(X, S1, S2, I, E)Phosphorylation assayAntibody25PApa(X, Y, A, E)simplePa(X, Y, A, E)Radio25PRApra(X, Y, A, E)AntagonistAntibody50ACPPAacppa(X, Y, A, I, E)complexPa(X, Y, A, I, E)Inhibitor50ICPPAicppa(X, Y, A, I, E)Radio50ICPPRAicppra(X, Y, A, I, E)siRNAAntibody75SCPPAscppa(X, Y, A, I, E)ELISAAntibody25ELISAelisa(X, A, E)simpleElisa(X, A, E)Inhibitor50ICELISAicelisa(X, A, I, E)complexElisa(X, A, I, E)siRNA75SCELISAscelisa(X, A, I, E)Radio-immunology ExperimentRadio25RIAria(X, A, E)simpleRia(X, A, E)Inhibitor50ICRIAicria(X, A, I, E)complexRia(X, A, I, E)Western BlotAntibody25WBwb(X, A, E)simpleWb(X, A, E)Inhibitor50ICWBicWb(X, A, E)complexWb(X, A, I, E)75RIWBriWb(X, A, E)QRTPCR25RTPCRqrtpcr(X, Y, E)simpleQrtpcr(X, Y, E)Inhibitor50ICQRTPCRicqrtpcr(X, Y, I, E)complexQrtpcr(X, Y, I, E)InteractionPrecipitationIP25IPip(X, S1)oneToManyInteractionExp(X, S1)PulldownGSTPulldown25GSTPULLDOWNgstPulldown(X, S1)BDPulldown25BDPULLDOWNbdPulldown(X, S1)FRETFRET50FRETfret(X, Y)oneToOneInteractionExp(X, Y)CristallographyCristallography1003DthreeD(S1)manyInteractionExp(S1)PrecipitationIP125IPDipd(X, Y, S1, E)effectOnOneToManyInteractionExp(X, Y, S1, E)LocalizationFluorescence Coloration25FLUO 25IHCfluo(A, C, E)ihc(A, C, E)detectionExp(A, C, E)Experiments that can be interpreted by the same general rule have the same color. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>All these experiments can be classified into three main groups depending on the kind of biological knowledge they allow to deduce (see first column of Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>All experiment types can be further classified according to different additional criteria, such as the experimental method they bring to play, or the eventual disruptor they use (see Table 1 for more details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This last criterion allows to distinguish between simple assays (e.g. a phosphorylation assay (pa)) and their corresponding complex assays that are realized in presence of a disruptor (e.g. an inhibitor in the case of an icppa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Based on this classification, we generalized the rules related to a number of experiment types taken into account (see Rule generalization in Supplementary Note for some example). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In Table 1, all the experiment types that can be interpreted by the same general rules have the same color. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>All the rules are given in Listing of rules in Supplementary Note. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Simple and complex interpretative rules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In (R2), premises are formed of predicates that cannot be deduced by any other interpretative rule: we call them background knowledge predicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>As for the conclusion, it is formed of a single predicate that provides deduced pieces of knowledge: we call it deduced predicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We distinguish two kinds of rules, depending on whether they only use background knowledge in their premises, and thus do not require any information deduced from another rule (simple rules), or on the contrary cannot be interpreted in the absence of anterior knowledge (complex rules). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Rule (R2) is an example of simple rule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>All the rules built to interpret experiments that involve inhibitors or antagonists are examples of complex rules, as they cannot be interpreted without the results of the same experiment conducted without the inhibitor or antagonist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Let us consider the experiment that consists in comparing the phosphorylation of ERK induced by the FSH between untreated cells and cells treated with an inhibitor of protein kinase A (PKA) (for example, with the H89 inhibitor23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The result of the experiment is that the phosphorylation of ERK induced by FSH is hampered by the inhibitor, from which an expert can make the hypothesis that PKA might be an intermediary of the activation of ERK by FSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This type of experiment is called an icppa, and can be interpreted by the following rule when a decrease effect is observed:R3\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{c}\,\,{\rm{IF}}\,{iccpa}({X}^{a},Y,A,I,{decrease})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{antibodyAgainst}(A,{Z}^{a})\,{\rm{and}}\,{inhibitorAgainst}(I,{Y}^{a})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modifiedForm}({Y}^{a},Y)\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{notModified}({{X}}^{a})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{confirmed})\\ {\rm{THEN}}\,{modulates}({Y}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{confirmed})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Y,{Y}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{hypothesis})\end{array}$$\end{document}IFiccpa(Xa,Y,A,I,decrease)andantibodyAgainst(A,Za)andinhibitorAgainst(I,Ya)andmodifiedForm(Ya,Y)andnotModified(Xa)andmodulates(Xa,Z,Za,increase,unknown,confirmed)THENmodulates(Ya,Z,Za,increase,unknown,confirmed)andmodulates(Xa,Y,Ya,increase,unknown,hypothesis) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In this type of experiment, the signal is the molecule Xa (FSH in our example), and the corresponding rule is triggered only if Xa has no modified form, as the predicate notModified (Xa) appears in its premises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Biologically, this means that Xa is not modified in the reaction, which is the case for an extracellular hormone such as FSH, for example. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>From this type of experiment, we conclude that Ya (activated PKA) stimulates the transformation of Z (ERK) into Za (phospho-ERK), since the quantity of Za is decreased in presence of the inhibitor of Ya (H89). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>From this first conclusion, two alternatives appear: either Ya can influence Za independently from Xa (activated PKA stimulates the phosphorylation of ERK independently of FSH) and no other additional conclusion has to be made, or Ya is an intermediary of the induction of Za by Xa, meaning that additionally, Xa stimulates the transformation of Y into Ya (FSH stimulates the activation of PKA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>As we cannot choose between the two alternatives with only that experiment, both are considered as hypothetical until further confirmation, hence the hypothesis status for the additional conclusion of the second alternative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The following rule allows interpreting the same type of experiment, but leaving the possibility that Xa is the modified form of its inactive counterpart X:R4\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{c}\,\,{\rm{IF}}\,{icppa}({X}^{a},Y,A,I,\mathrm{decrease})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{antibodyAgainst}(A,{Z}^{a})\,{\rm{and}}\,{inhibitorAgainst}(I,{Y}^{a})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modifiedForm}({Y}^{a},Y)\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modifiedForm}({X}^{a},X)\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{confirmed})\\ {\rm{THEN}}\,{modulates}({Y}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{confirmed})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Y,{Y}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{hypothesis})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({Y}^{a},X,{X}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{hypothesis})\end{array}$$\end{document}IFicppa(Xa,Y,A,I,decrease)andantibodyAgainst(A,Za)andinhibitorAgainst(I,Ya)andmodifiedForm(Ya,Y)andmodifiedForm(Xa,X)andmodulates(Xa,Z,Za,increase,unknown,confirmed)THENmodulates(Ya,Z,Za,increase,unknown,confirmed)andmodulates(Xa,Y,Ya,increase,unknown,hypothesis)andmodulates(Ya,X,Xa,increase,unknown,hypothesis) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>This rule has one more conclusion compared to rule (R3):\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${modulates}({Y}^{a},X,{X}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{hypothesis})$$\end{document}modulates(Ya,X,Xa,increase,unknown,hypothesis) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The two alternatives given for the case where Xa has no modified form remain valid, but there is a third one: Xa might be an intermediary of the induction of Za by Ya, and thus Ya might stimulate the process that transforms X into Xa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As for the previous case, we cannot rule out any alternative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 shows the interpretation made from an icppa in the case where the signal has as no modified form (top) and in the case where it has one (bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>For the case where Xa has a modified form, the network on the left represents the alternative where Ya is an intermediary of the induction of Za by Xa, and the network on the right the alternative where it is Xa that is an intermediary between Ya and Za.Figure 1Interpretation of a phosphorylation assay with an inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(A) Case where Xa has no modified form, treated by rule (R3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In the first alternative (left), Ya influences the transformation independently from Xa; in the second alternative (right), Ya is an intermediary of the induction of Za by Xa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>(B) Case where Xa has a modified form X, treated by rule (R4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In the first alternative (left), Ya influences the transformation independently from Xa; in the second alternative (middle), Ya is an intermediary of the induction of Za by Xa; in the last alternative (right), Xa is an intermediary of the induction of Za by Ya. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>For both cases, the confirmed or hypothetical facts that result from the superposition of the different alternatives are represented under the form of a resulting network, on the right of the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Blue modulations represent premises, green modulations conclusions that are confirmed, red ones hypotheses, and dashed ones conclusions that could be indirect and explained by transitivity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Analytical rules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In addition to interpretative rules, we have built a set of analytical rules that do not interpret any experimental result, but allow to either complete the background knowledge, or to deduce new pieces of knowledge or hypotheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>For example, rule (R5) allows generating an hypothetical modulation based on the distance of already known modulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Its meaning is the following: if Xa modulates a process that transforms Z into Za, Ya modulates the same process but with a direct distance (i.e. with no intermediary coming into play), and Ya is the modified form of Y, then Xa might modulate the process that transforms Y into Ya.R5\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{c}\,\,{\rm{IF}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{confirmed})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modulates}({Y}^{a},Z,{Z}^{a},{increase},{direct},{confirmed})\\ \,\,{\rm{and}}\,{modifiedForm}({Y}^{a},Y)\\ {\rm{THEN}}\,{modulates}({X}^{a},Y,{Y}^{a},{increase},{unknown},{hypothesis})\end{array}$$\end{document}IFmodulates(Xa,Z,Za,increase,unknown,confirmed)andmodulates(Ya,Z,Za,increase,direct,confirmed)andmodifiedForm(Ya,Y)THENmodulates(Xa,Y,Ya,increase,unknown,hypothesis)Here, we make the hypothesis that Y is an intermediary of the modulation of Z by X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>We do not hypothesize that it is X that is an intermediary between Y and Z, since we know that Y has a direct effect on Z. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Two tasks: building networks and inferring experimental plans </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Automated construction of cell signaling networks via deduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The set of interpretative and analytical rules we propose allows establishing automatically new pieces of knowledge from a number of given experimental results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>More precisely, given a set of background facts and a set of experimental facts, these rules allow deducing new facts that can then be represented under the form of a signaling network (using the SBGN PD language5 for example). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>A step by step example of such a deductive task is given in Example of deduction in Supplementary Note. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>By using formal explicit rules and facts, one can track the different deduction steps that lead to a particular fact, in a way that is understandable, and thus verifiable, by the biologist. For a deduced relation, the set of experimental results and rules that enabled its deduction is called its trace. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Traces are especially useful when automated reasoning leads to facts that could seem contradictory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>For example, two facts, one qualifying the stimulation of a process by a molecule and the other the inhibition of that same process by the same molecule can sometimes be obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>This is quite possible, for example if two different pathways exist, leading to the same reaction, one being inhibitory and the other activatory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>However, experimental results that lead to such a pair of facts should be carefully verified, since they could also result from erroneous experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In this case, thanks to traces, our system allows the user going back to these two results, and possibly choosing to ignore one. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Automated proposition of experimental plans via abduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Our method also allows to go further. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>It is often the case that a given molecule or reaction is expected to participate in a given signaling network, and the question then arises of choosing experiments that could validate this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Our approach provides a way of answering this question through a method of reasoning called abduction, that can be seen as the inverse process of deduction, and whose goal is to find minimal explanations of an observation, given a background logical theory. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In order to check a given biological hypothesis, we first assume that this hypothesis is true, and formalize this assumption by a fact with the status confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Then, using abductive reasoning, we obtain minimal alternative sets of experimental results, each set alone being sufficient to explain the biological fact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The obtained set of inferred experimental results constitutes an experimental plan, that can be carried out in order to test the input hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A step by step example of such an abductive task is given in Example of abduction in Supplementary Note. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Application to the FSHR-induced and the EGFR-induced signaling networks </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We applied our method to the network induced by the FSHR, and to the network induced by the EGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>FSH is a pituitary hormone of major importance in the control of male and female reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>It acts via its cognate receptor, the FSHR, a Gs-coupled seven transmembrane domain receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In females, FSH participates, inter alia, in the induction of ovarian follicles’ growth and maturation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In males, it participates in the induction of spermatogenesis by stimulating Sertoli cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>When FSH binds to its receptor, the latter triggers several signaling pathways: the G-dependent pathway, leading to the production of second messenger cyclic AMP (cAMP), but also the phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate 3-kinase (PI3K)-dependent and β-arrestin-dependent pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>As for the epidermal growth factor (EGF), it participates in the tissue growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>It acts via its cognate receptor (the EGFR), which belongs to the tyrosine kinase receptors (RTK) family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Activation of EGFR triggers three main signaling pathways: the ERK pathway, the PI3K/protein kinase B (Akt) pathway, and the Jakus kinase (JAK)/signal transducer and activator of transcription protein (STAT) pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Finally, these two networks are not independent of each other: the EGFR is transactivated by the FSHR induced network, via the Rous sarcoma oncogene (Src) (see4 for a review). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We first built the FSHR induced network, by automatically interpreting a set of experimental results linked to this network, which had been used in a previous review4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>We then automatically interpreted this set of experimental results by augmenting it with another set of results related to the EGFR induced network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This last interpretation allowed discovering a new hypothesis, for which we subsequently acquired experimental evidence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Retrieving experimental and background knowledge facts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The set of experimental and background knowledge facts related to both networks was retrieved from the literature (see Methods for further details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For the FSHR induced network, 191 experimental results were retrieved, whereas this number reached 274 for the EGFR induced network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In total, 1448 background facts were also retrieved for both networks together. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Automatic inference of the FSHR induced network </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We performed the interpretation of the 191 experimental results related to the FSHR induced network, using the set of expert rules and the set of background knowledge facts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We obtained 1535 new facts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Among them, 1184 facts corresponded to background knowledge facts or modulations with a noeffect parameter status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The remaining 351 pertinent facts (i.e. formalizing a process, the modulation of a process or the localization of a molecule) formed together a molecular network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We compared this network to the FSHR induced network that we previously built manually using the same set of experiments4 (see Supplementary Fig. S1 for an overview of this network), which will be considered as the reference network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We give an overview of the result of this comparison for the G protein pathway in Comparison for the G protein pathway Supplementary Note. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Most differences observed between the two networks can be explained, either by the fact that in graphical representations some details are omitted for the sake of clarity, or by the presence of knowledge in the reference network transferred from other networks, mostly from signaling networks triggered by other GPCRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>This tends to show that our expert rules are complete enough to deduce all the main processes and modulations of a given network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We conducted a similar work on the signaling network of the EGFR (Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In that case, our reference was the network of the Pathway Interaction Database (PID)24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Similar to the FSHR case, we extracted the experimental facts from the literature cited in the PID network, and ran the inference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the inferred and reference networks showed no significant differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Discovering a new hypothesis on the phosphorylation of MEK by p38MAPK </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Because of its complexity, a signaling network is often not studied as a whole, but through the study of individual pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>However, these different pathways are not independent of each other, and the cellular outcome of the stimulation results from the precise timing and intensity of their activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Consequently, new knowledge would certainly arise from the study of the complete network, which is possible only through automated modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>To illustrate this, and because EGFR is known to be transactivated by FSHR, we decided to merge the sets of experimental and background knowledge facts related to the FSHR and the EGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We then used our expert rules to deduce new facts from this set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>As expected, none of the new deduced facts was obtained by using interpretative rules: indeed, all experimental facts had already been used to deduce facts for each of the two networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>However, rule (R5) allowed generating new hypotheses that were not generated by either of the two sets of experimental results alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Eleven such new facts were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Although many of them are not really useful for understanding the biological outcome of the stimulation, one interesting hypothesis emerging from this analysis is that phosphorylated p38MAPK could activate MEK:F1\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$modulates(pp38mapk,mek,pmek,increase,unknown,hypothesis)$$\end{document}modulates(pp38mapk,mek,pmek,increase,unknown,hypothesis) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis is deeply interesting for two main reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>First, p38MAPK is known as the target of stress-activated MAP2K (MAP2K3, MAP2K4 and MAP2K6 in particular), whereas MEK targets MAPK3 (among which ERK) involved in growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Establishing the existence of a cross-talk between the stress and growth MAPK pathways would show that the two systems are not as insulated as generally thought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in signaling cascades, a MAP2K usually activates a MAPK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>But here, the hypothesis is that a MAPK (p38) activates a MAP2K (MEK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Second, validating this hypothesis would allow to validate at the same time a number of other hypotheses also generated using rule (R5), that relate to modulations of the phosphorylation of MEK by molecules upstream of phospho-p38MAPK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This gives more weight to such hypotheses, and illustrates one advantage of automatic reasoning: after a small change in the whole theory (here, the addition of a new modulation), new pieces of knowledge that are a consequence of this change can easily be deduced, even if the new pieces of knowledge are located far from where the change is initially made within the network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Experimental plans to establish the phosphorylation of MEK by phospho-p38MAPK in the FSHR system </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Having deduced the hypothesis that MEK may be phosphorylated by phospho-p38MAPK (fact (F1)), we inferred automatically all experimental plans that would allow validating it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>We obtained six different experimental plans, each containing only one experiment to carry out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Those six plans were derived from the following abduced facts:icpea(pmek, s_1_erk1, s_1_perk1, sb203580, decrease)icpea(pmek, s_1_erk2, s_1_perk2, sb203580, decrease)icria(fsh, r_pmek, sb203580, decrease)icelisa(fsh, a_pmek, sb203580, decrease)pa(pp38mapk, mek, a_pmek, increase)icppa(fsh, mek, a_pmek, sb203580, decrease) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par50"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Experimental plans containing the icria, the icelisa and the icppa predicates proposed to study the effect of an inhibitor of p38MAPK (here, SB203580, which has been shown to be extremely specific, and has no effect on MEK and ERK activities25) on the stimulation of FSH-triggered MEK phosphorylation using a radio-immunologic assay, a phosphorylation assay or an ELISA, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The two icpea plans proposed to study the effect of the exact same inhibitor on the activity of MEK, through the study in vitro of ERK phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Finally, the plan with the pa proposed to test directly the effect of phosphorylated p38MAPK on MEK phosphorylation using a phosphorylation assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par51"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We carried out the simplest plan to implement, which was the icppa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>This plan proposed to inhibit p38MAPK and to observe the phosphorylation of MEK in stimulated cells using an antibody specific to the phosphorylated (active) form of MEK, and to compare with activated cells in the absence of the inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The results (Fig. 2) confirm the hypothesis: p38MAPK stimulates the phophorylation of MEK, and through it, the phosphorylation of ERK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the phosphorylation level of MEK is significantly lower in the presence of SB203580, an inhibitor of p38MAPK, than in the control conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The same phenomenon is observed for the phosphorylation level of ERK.Figure 2(A) Levels of MEK and (B) levels of ERK phosphorylation in HEK293 cells expressing the FSHR 10 min after activation by FSH in the presence or absence of SB203580 (inhibitor of p38MAPK) and presence or absence of tyrphostin (inhibitor of EGFR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Significant differences are labeled with stars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as the % of the maximum response elicited by FSH in the absence of any inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(C) The SBGN AF43 map representing the different pathways triggered by the FSHR, as well as the transactivation of the EGFR via Src. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Our confirmed hypothesis, that p38MAPK stimulates the phosphorylation of MEK, is colored in red. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par52"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>As this hypothesis did not arise from the study of the FSHR signaling network alone, it was also interesting to test whether this modulation arose through the transactivation of EGFR, or was an unknown consequence of the EGFR-independent FSHR signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For this purpose we repeated the experiment in the presence of an inhibitor of the EGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Comparing the levels of MEK or ERK phosphorylation in the presence of Tyrphostin, the inhibitor of EGFR, shows a tendency to decrease, but this effect is not significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Comparing the phosphorylation of ERK is the presence of both Tyrphostin and SB203580 shows a significant decrease as compared to control conditions, but also to the conditions with SB203580 alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this is not observed for MEK phosphorylation levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This could mean that there exists a pathway leading to ERK phosphorylation which depends on EGFR (since the effect is decreased in the presence of Tyrphostin), but neither on p38MAPK (since SB203580 is present in both conditions), nor on MEK (since the effect is not observed for MEK). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par53"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>However, the observed differences could also be due to technical reasons, such as differences in quality or affinity of the antibodies used to detect the phosphorylated forms of MEK and ERK, or differences in the total amounts of both proteins present in the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Drawing more definitive conclusions would require more experiments, using different protocols, which was not the scope of the present paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>From deduced facts to mathematical models </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par54"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The output of our method is a set of logical deduced facts that formalize knowledge on molecular mechanisms, and that form together a molecular network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>These facts can easily be translated to standard graphical or textual languages, such as SBGN PD5/SBGN ER26 or BioPax27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Also, the output networks represent static knowledge and do not carry any dynamics semantics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Hence, they can be used as inputs for (automatic) mathematical model building under a wide variety of semantics and formalisms, such as the rule-based entity-centered semantics and ODEs9,28,29, plain ODEs30, or qualitative semantics29,31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>These mathematical models can in turn be stored and exchanged using standard formats such as the BioNetGen Language format28 for rule-based models, or the Systems Biology Markup Language format32 for ODEs and qualitative models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Scalability and automation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par55"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>One weakness of our framework that clearly appeared during this work is the manual entry of experimental and background facts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Going through scientific papers to extract experimental results and formating them for the inference engine is a tedious and error-prone task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Consequently, scalability of the method, apart from pure computational aspects, will also need the automation of this extraction and formating task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>This led us to start the development of a method, using natural language processing, to automate this task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We have already shown that we can isolate, within a scientific paper, the sentences relative to the results of an experiment33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>We are now developing cascades within the CasSys system34 to format these experimental results as facts that could be used directly within the framework described in the present paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The first tests have shown that we were able to extract and format successfully both background and experimental facts with good precision (76%) and recall (88%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par56"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>This work is still preliminary, and will require many more developments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>However, we already have a proof of concept that such automated extraction and formatting of background and experimental facts from literature is feasible using natural language processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par57"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="?"><plain>Another question is how scalable is the method? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Giving a definitive answer to this question would require a very large dataset of experimental facts, which will be available only after completion of the natural language treatment-based extraction and formatting method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>However, the computation times observed during our first tests seem to depend linearly on the number of experimental facts (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the number of deduced facts seems to depend linearly on the number of experimental facts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Finally, the computation times are very low, and if the linearity is confirmed, the framework could be applied to very large datasets.Table 2Numbers of experimental facts, deduced facts and computation times for the studied networks.NetworkFSHREGFRFSHR + EGFRExperimental facts191274465New facts155224133058Pertinent facts344583993CPU time (s)4.48.712.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Knowledge transfer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par58"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>As discussed above, in the signaling network we built, some relations were missing because they have not been demonstrated in the case of the FSHR and/or the EGFR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, these relations are considered as true by the experts, either because they have been demonstrated using purified proteins, or because they have been demonstrated for many different conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par59"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>As an example, when we reconstructed the EGFR signaling network, we did not obtain the inhibition relation between Tsc2 and Rheb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Indeed, in the scientific paper corpus we have used, this inhibition of Rheb by Tsc2 was not demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>We then searched the literature for such a demonstration, but we could not find an experiment demonstrating that EGF-activated Tsc2 inhibits Rheb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>However, we found many papers demonstrating this inhibition relation, using purified proteins35 or in vivo, following different stimulations such as insulin36, ephrin37 or tissue plasminogen activator38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>More generally, Tsc2 has been shown to be an important hub in the signaling pathways triggered by many different signals such as amino acid availability, growth factors, cytokines, and energy39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Thus, in this particular example, it seems reasonable to consider that in the EGFR pathway Rheb is inhibited by Tsc2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par60"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This raises the question of transferring knowledge between different networks and/or different biological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The example above is a direct action, demonstrated using purified proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In such cases we could consider that in any cell, and under any condition, if the two proteins are present, the conclusion holds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>But many possible cases are more difficult to decide than this one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="?"><plain>For example, can experimental data obtained in a given cell line be used to build a network in another cell line? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="?"><plain>Or when the cell lines are the same, but the experimental conditions, such as growth media, are different? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>These are of course questions that cannot be answered only through computational tools, and it will ultimately be the user’s decision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>However, tools can be designed to guide this decision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In our framework the user can always come back to the experimental data used to deduce a given relation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>This can be such a guiding element, but more will have to be added in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par61"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In this article, we propose a logic-based method to automate the construction of signaling networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Our method tries to reproduce the reasoning made by biologists when interpreting experimental results, by automatically deducing new knowledge using a set of expert rules that make explicit this reasoning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>These rules allow interpreting experimental results coming from a large variety of experiments that are usually employed in cell signaling, and to infer precise mechanisms, at the molecular reaction scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Moreover, they allow formulating a number of biological hypotheses, and experimental plans to validate them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Our method allowed us to successfully reconstruct two large networks: the FSH-triggered and the EGF-triggered networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Using the two sets of underlying data at the same time led us to formulate the hypothesis that p38MAPK would stimulate the phosphorylation of MEK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>In order to validate this hypothesis, we automatically inferred an experimental plan using our method, that we have carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The results obtained show that p38MAPK stimulates the phosphorylation of MEK in an FSHR-induced system, as MEK activation is significantly lower in the presence of p38MAPK inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, ERK phosphorylation is also decreased when p38MAPK is inhibited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>We also observed further inhibition of activity in the presence of the EGFR inhibitor for ERK, but not for MEK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>This could be the effect of another activation mechanism of ERK, depending on EGFR transactivation, but not on p38MAPK or MEK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>This first experimental validation would need to be consolidated, which is not the object of the present paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>However, it constitutes a first step in the discovery of a yet-unknown cross-talk between these two very important signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par62"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Although preliminary, these results demonstrate that our method allows to make high-level hypotheses, based on already known facts, and could be an important driving force for understanding the signaling pathways in their complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Applying our method to large sets of experimental data could be facilitated by new evolutions, and our efforts will take two directions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>First, we need to expand the number of experiments that can be automatically interpreted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In particular, experiments involving the use of mutants (either cells expressing mutant proteins, or even knock-out animals) are often used, but the corresponding rules are delicate to establish, since the driving idea for making a mutation is often implicit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Another important area we have to formalize corresponds to the in vivo experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Second, we have to be able to extract the facts automatically from scientific papers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Indeed, manually gathering the relevant literature, extracting the experimental data, and subsequently writing the facts is a tedious task, and consequently limits the applicability of the method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>A standard format for reporting experimental results would of course greatly facilitate automated extraction, and the work discussed here could be straightforwardly used to design such a format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>However, we do not believe scientific community is ready to format and report experimental results, and not enough results would be gathered by this mean to make the method really powerful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Instead, we are developing a method, based on natural language processing, which should allow to extract and format experimental facts directly from published papers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Retrieving the experimental facts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par63"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Experimental facts relative to both networks have been manually retrieved from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>The corpus of scientific papers considered for FSHR signaling was the exact same one used to build a comprehensive literature network4, so that the inferred network and the literature network could be compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>This corpus was initially assembled by reviewing the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>As for the corpus of scientific papers considered for EGFR signaling, it has been found in the PID24 (data now available through the NDEx database40). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Deduction with answer set programming </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par64"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Deduction was performed by means of answer set programming (ASP) using the clingo software41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Our expert rules were straightforwardly translated into ASP rules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The ASP program consists of a set of background knowledge and experimental facts, and the translated expert rules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>This program has a unique answer set which is exactly the set of facts that can be deduced from the initial facts and the rules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Traces can be obtained at the same time as sets of deduced facts by using a simple transformation of the ASP rules (see Traces in ASP in Supplementary Note for more details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Computations were made on an Intel(R) Xeon(R) CPU E5-1620v4 @ 3.50 GHz. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Inference of experimental plans with SOLAR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par65"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Inference of experimental plans was performed with the software SOLAR42, using abductive reasoning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>As for deduction with ASP, the expert rules were straightforwardly translated into SOLAR’s input language. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Experimental plans for a given hypothesis were then computed using the negation of the hypothesis as the top clause. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Cell Culture and Western-blots </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par66"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Human embryonic kidney (HEK)-293 cells stably expressing mFSH-R were cultured in minimum Eagle’s medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 1% penicillin/streptomycin in 100-mm dishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Slow growing early passage (&lt;10) cells were divided into 12-well plates and, at 50% confluency, serum-starved for 4 h prior to stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Cells were then incubated with SB203580 (10 μM, 30 min) (Sigma, St Louis, MO), Tyrphostin (10 μM, 1 h) (Sigma) or the combination of the 2 inhibitors, before stimulation with 100 ng/ml (3.3 nM) of recombinant human FSH (Merck Serono, Darmstadt, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Cell lysates were done in 2 × SDS-sample buffer (pH 6.8), followed by boiling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Equivalent amounts of proteins were separated by SDS/PAGE on Tris-glycine polyacrylamide gels, transferred to nitrocellulose membranes, and immunoblotted with rabbit polyclonal antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The anti- phospho (T202/Y204, diluted 1:2,000) and total (diluted 1:6,000) ERK 1/2 antibodies were from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA) and Santa Cruz (Dallas, TX), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Rabbit anti-phospho-MEK 1/2 (S217/S221, diluted 1:1,000) and mouse anti-total MEK 1/2 (diluted 1:2,000) antibodies were from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Goat anti-rabbit IRDye® 680 antibody (Licor®, Lincoln, NE) was used for detection with an Odyssey® CLx scanner (Licor®) and signals were quantified using Image Studio software (Licor®). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Normalization was applied as ratio of phospho ERK/total ERK signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using the GraphPad PRISM software and differences between two groups were assessed by a two-tailed paired t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The cut-off for significance is either 0.05 (⋆) or 0.001 (⋆⋆). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Data and scripts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par67"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>All data and scripts that we used to establish the results presented in this document are available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bios.tours.inra.fr/bios_group/sites/bios_group/IMG/zip/archive_article.zip">http://bios.tours.inra.fr/bios_group/sites/bios_group/IMG/zip/archive_article.zip</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec26"><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Supplementary notes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Anne Poupon and Christine Froidevaux contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-26006-2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>A.P., C.F., E.R., P.G. and P.C. designed the framework under the supervision of A.P. A.P., A.R., C.F. and P.G. built and formalized the set of expert rules. P.G. extracted the facts from the literature for the reconstruction of both networks. A.R. performed the reconstruction of the networks. A.R. and P.G. performed the comparison of the reconstructed networks to those of the literature. N.L. and P.C. performed the wet-lab experiments. All authors participated in the redaction of the manuscript.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par68">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>1.Oda, K., Matsuoka, Y., Funahashi, A. &amp; Kitano, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive pathway map of epidermal growth factor receptor signaling. Molecular Systems Biology1(1), 010 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>2.Calzone, L., Gelay, A., Zinovyev, A., Radvanyi, F. &amp; Barillot, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive modular map of molecular interactions in rb/e2f pathway. Molecular Systems Biology4(1), 0174 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>3.Caron, E. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive map of the mtor signaling network. Molecular Systems Biology6(1), 453 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>4.GloaguenPCrépieuxPHeitzlerDPouponAReiterEMapping the follicle-stimulating hormone-induced signaling networksFrontiers in endocrinology201124510.3389/fendo.2011.00045<?supplied-pmid 22666216?>22666216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>5.MoodieSLe NovereNDemirEMiHVillegerASystems biology graphical notation: process description language level 1 version 1.3Journal of integrative bioinformatics20151221328010.1515/jib-2015-263<?supplied-pmid 29220962?>29220962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>6.Le NovereNThe systems biology graphical notationNature Biotechnology20092773574110.1038/nbt.1558<?supplied-pmid 19668183?>19668183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>7.ChenHSharpBMContent-rich biological network constructed by mining pubmed abstractsBMC Bioinformatics2004514710.1186/1471-2105-5-147<?supplied-pmid 15473905?>15473905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>8.YuryevAAutomatic pathway building in biological association networksBMC Bioinformatics2006717110.1186/1471-2105-7-171<?supplied-pmid 16563163?>16563163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>9.Gyori, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>M. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>From word models to executable models of signaling networks using automated assembly. Molecular Systems Biology13, 954 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>10.Bansal, M., Belcastro, V., Ambesi-Impiombato, A. &amp; di Bernardo, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>How to infer gene networks from expression profiles. Molecular Systems Biology3, 78 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>11.MarkowetzFSpangRInferring cellular networks–a reviewBMC Bioinformatics20078S510.1186/1471-2105-8-S6-S5<?supplied-pmid 17903286?>17903286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>12.Roy, S. &amp; Guzzi, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Biological network inference from microarray data, current solutions, and assessments. Microarray Data Analysis: Methods and Applications 155–167 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>13.Pe’erDRegevAElidanGFriedmanNInferring subnetworks from perturbed expression profilesBioinformatics200117S215S22410.1093/bioinformatics/17.suppl_1.S215<?supplied-pmid 11473012?>11473012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>14.ZhuDHeroAOChengHKhannaRSwaroopANetwork constrained clustering for gene microarray dataBioinformatics2005214014402010.1093/bioinformatics/bti655<?supplied-pmid 16141248?>16141248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>15.FröhlichHFellmannMSültmannHPoustkaABeißbarthTLarge scale statistical inference of signaling pathways from rnai and microarray dataBMC bioinformatics2007838610.1186/1471-2105-8-38617937790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>16.EloLLJärvenpääHOrešičMLahesmaaRAittokallioTSystematic construction of gene coexpression networks with applications to human t helper cell differentiation processBioinformatics2007232096210310.1093/bioinformatics/btm309<?supplied-pmid 17553854?>17553854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>17.SachsKPerezOPe’erDLauffenburgerDANolanGPCausal protein-signaling networks derived from multiparameter single-cell dataScience200530852352910.1126/science.1105809<?supplied-pmid 15845847?>15845847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>18.XuT-RInferring signaling pathway topologies from multiple perturbation measurements of specific biochemical speciesScience Signaling20103ra20ra20 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>19.HillSMBayesian inference of signaling network topology in a cancer cell lineBioinformatics2012282804281010.1093/bioinformatics/bts514<?supplied-pmid 22923301?>22923301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>20.ZupanBGenepath: a system for automated construction of genetic networks from mutant dataBioinformatics20031938338910.1093/bioinformatics/btf871<?supplied-pmid 12584124?>12584124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>21.Nigam, V., Donaldson, R., Knapp, M., McCarthy, T. &amp; Talcott, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Inferring executable models from formalized experimental evidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>In Computational Methods in Systems Biology, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 90–103 (Springer, 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>22.Eker, S. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Pathway logic: Symbolic analysis of biological signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>In Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing7, 400–412 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>23.CrépieuxPThe erk-dependent signalling is stage-specifically modulated by fsh, during primary sertoli cell maturationOncogene2001204696470910.1038/sj.onc.1204632<?supplied-pmid 11498792?>11498792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>24.SchaeferCFPid: the pathway interaction databaseNucleic acids research200837D674D67910.1093/nar/gkn653<?supplied-pmid 18832364?>18832364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>25.DaviesSPReddyHCaivanoMCohenPSpecificity and mechanism of action of some commonly used protein kinase inhibitorsBiochemical Journal20003519510510.1042/bj3510095<?supplied-pmid 10998351?>10998351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>26.SorokinASystems Biology Graphical Notation: Entity Relationship language Level 1 Version 2J Integr Bioinform20151226410.1515/jib-2015-264<?supplied-pmid 26528562?>26528562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>27.DemirEThe biopax community standard for pathway data sharingNature biotechnology20102893510.1038/nbt.1666<?supplied-pmid 20829833?>20829833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>28.FaederJRBlinovMLHlavacekWSRule-based modeling of biochemical systems with BioNetGenMethods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Biol.200950011316710.1007/978-1-59745-525-1_5<?supplied-pmid 19399430?>19399430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>29.CalzoneLFagesFSolimanSBiocham: an environment for modeling biological systems and formalizing experimental knowledgeBioinformatics2006221805180710.1093/bioinformatics/btl172<?supplied-pmid 16672256?>16672256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>30.BüchelFPath2models: large-scale generation of computational models from biochemical pathway mapsBMC Systems Biology2013711610.1186/1752-0509-7-116<?supplied-pmid 24180668?>24180668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>31.RougnyAFroidevauxCCalzoneLPaulevéLQualitative dynamics semantics for sbgn process descriptionBMC systems biology2016104210.1186/s12918-016-0285-0<?supplied-pmid 27306057?>27306057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>32.HuckaMThe systems biology markup language (sbml): a medium for representation and exchange of biochemical network modelsBioinformatics20031952453110.1093/bioinformatics/btg015<?supplied-pmid 12611808?>12611808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>33.Landomiel, F., Gupta, A., Maurel, D. &amp; Poupon, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Préliminaire à la construction d’un réseau de signalisation en biologie systémique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>In Atelier sur la Fouille de Textes (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>34.FriburgerNMaurelDFinite-state transducer cascades to extract named entities in textsTheoretical Computer Science20043139310410.1016/j.tcs.2003.10.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>35.Inoki, K., Li, Y., Xu, T. &amp; Guan, K.-L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Rheb gtpase is a direct target of tsc2 gap activity and regulates mtor signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Genes &amp; development 17, 1829–1834 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>36.CastroAFRebhunJFClarkGJQuilliamLARheb binds tuberous sclerosis complex 2 (tsc2) and promotes s6 kinase activation in a rapamycin-and farnesylation-dependent mannerJournal of Biological Chemistry2003278324933249610.1074/jbc.C300226200<?supplied-pmid 12842888?>12842888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>37.NieDTsc2-rheb signaling regulates epha-mediated axon guidanceNature neuroscience20101316310.1038/nn.2477<?supplied-pmid 20062052?>20062052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>38.RoccioMBosJZwartkruisFRegulation of the small gtpase rheb by amino acidsOncogene20062565710.1038/sj.onc.1209106<?supplied-pmid 16170341?>16170341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>39.HuangJManningBDThe tsc1–tsc2 complex: a molecular switchboard controlling cell growthBiochemical Journal200841217919010.1042/BJ20080281<?supplied-pmid 18466115?>18466115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>40.PrattDNdex, the network data exchangeCell systems2015130230510.1016/j.cels.2015.10.001<?supplied-pmid 26594663?>26594663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>41.Gebser, M., Kaminski, R., Kaufmann, B. &amp; Schaub, T. Clingo = ASP + control: Preliminary report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>In Leuschel, M. &amp; Schrijvers, T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>(eds) Technical Communications of the Thirtieth International Conference on Logic Programming (ICLP'14), vol.arXiv:1405.3694v1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Theory and Practice of Logic Programming, Online Supplement (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>42.NabeshimaHIwanumaKInoueKRayOSolar: An automated deduction system for consequence findingAI communications201023183203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>43.MiHSystems biology graphical notation: activity flow language level 1 version 1.2Journal of integrative bioinformatics20151234038110.1515/jib-2015-265<?supplied-pmid 29220968?>29220968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
