<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">biolopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biology Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2046-6390</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Company of Biologists Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5278426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875243</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/bio.021519</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BIO021519</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>REV-ERBα regulates Fgf21 expression in the liver via hepatic nuclear factor 6 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>Rohit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Preitner</surname><given-names>Nadia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Strittmatter</surname><given-names>Laureen Mansencal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Cheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ripperger</surname><given-names>Jürgen A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pitteloud</surname><given-names>Nelly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0663-8676</contrib-id><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>Urs</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biology, Unit of Biochemistry</addr-line>, <institution>University of Fribourg, Fribourg CH1700</institution>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Service of Endocrinology</addr-line>, <institution>Diabetology and Metabolism, Lausanne University Hospital, Lausanne CH1011</institution>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence (<email>urs.albrecht@unifr.ch</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017. Published by The Company of Biologists Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium provided that the original work is properly attributed.</license-p></license><?release-delay 0|0?></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="biolopen-6-021519.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>ABSTRACT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The circadian clock contributes to the timing of many body functions including metabolism and reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The hepatokine fibroblast growth factor 21 (FGF21) is a critical metabolic regulator involved in modulation of fertility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here we show that lack of the clock component REV-ERBα elevates FGF21 levels in liver and plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>At the molecular level, REV-ERBα modulates the expression of FGF21 via the liver-specific hepatic nuclear factor 6 (HNF6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We conclude that REV-ERBα regulates metabolism and reproduction, at least in part, via regulation of Fgf21. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Summary: The hepatokine Fgf21 is transcriptionally regulated by the nuclear receptor REV-ERBα with the hepatocyte-specific factor HNF6 to regulate metabolism and fertility. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd>Circadian clock</kwd><kwd>Transcription</kwd><kwd>Physiology</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CRSII3_141960/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The circadian clock allows organisms to predict daily recurring events such as sunrise, emergence of a particular food source and presence of predators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This enables them to optimally time physiological processes to the environment in order to enhance survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>For the survival of the species, successful reproduction is essential and factors enhancing the chance of reproductive success are conserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Since the circadian system not only synchronizes physiology and behavior in an organism, but also is able to adapt to environmental changes such as seasons, it is not surprising that de-synchronization of the circadian system or mutation in clock genes can affect reproductive capacity (Ikegami and Yoshimura, 2012; Boden et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Lack of the clock gene Bmal1 in mice leads to irregular estrous cycles (Ratajczak et al., 2009) and impaired ovulation (Boden et al., 2010) for which Bmal1 in ovarian theca cells appears to be important (Mereness et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, mice with a mutation in the Clock gene also display an irregular estrous cycle (Kennaway et al., 2004; Miller et al., 2004), and Per1/Per2 mutants develop irregular estrous cycles as they age (Pilorz and Steinlechner, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The nuclear receptor and clock component REV-ERBα is expressed with a circadian rhythm and represses Bmal1 (Preitner et al., 2002), encoding a positive regulator of clock output genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>REV-ERBα also represses other genes to regulate metabolism in a tissue-dependent manner (Cho et al., 2012; Bugge et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Hence, REV-ERBα is central to regulate complex interactions between the circadian clock and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Female mice lacking Rev-erbα display reduced fertility while males appear to mate and reproduce normally (Chomez et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Recent studies indicate that the reproductive axis and metabolism are sensitive to fibroblast growth factor 21 (FGF21) (Owen et al., 2013; Nies et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>FGF21 is a member of the endocrine FGF subfamily that is a critical metabolic regulator (Itoh, 2010; Reitman, 2007; Beenken and Mohammadi, 2009) and over-expression of Fgf21 renders female mice infertile (Owen et al., 2013; Inagaki et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Because the Fgf21 promoter contains nuclear receptor response elements and E-boxes (Estall et al., 2009; Tong et al., 2010), we investigated whether Fgf21 is regulated directly or indirectly by clock components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>We find that Fgf21 is regulated indirectly by the nuclear receptors REV-ERBα via HNF6, and the clock protein PER2 modulates the repressive function of REV-ERBα and/or the transcriptional efficiency of PPARα-mediated expression of Fgf21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Thus, FGF21 may be an intermediary between the clock components, metabolism and reproductive fitness. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Rev-erbα knock-out mice display reduced fertility </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Breeding of Rev-erbα−/− animals in our facility revealed reduced fertility of these animals, with the average number of pups per mating pair reduced in Rev-erbα−/− compared to the heterozygous Rev-erbα+/− breeding pairs (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, also the number of litters per mating period was reduced (Fig. 1B) indicating that Rev-erbα−/− breeding pairs took longer to produce offspring (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This observation is consistent with a previous report describing reduced reproduction in Rev-erbα knock-out mice (Chomez et al., 2000). Fig. 1.Female Rev-erbα−/− mice display signs of reduced fertility. (A) Rev-erbα−/− (red bar) mating pairs produce significantly less pups per litter compared to Rev-erbα+/− (black bar) pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Unpaired two-tailed t-test, ***P&lt;0.0001, n=18 for Rev-erbα+/− and n=8 for Rev-erbα−/−, F-test reveals no difference in variance, F=2.41, DFn=17, Dfd=7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>(B) Number of litters per mating period is reduced in Rev-erbα−/− (red bar) mating pairs compared to Rev-erbα+/− (black bar) pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Unpaired two-tailed t-test, ***P&lt;0.0001, n=13 for Rev-erbα+/− and n=8 for Rev-erbα−/−, F-test reveals difference in variance, F=51.38, DFn=12, Dfd=7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>(C) Inter-litter period is significantly longer in Rev-erbα−/− (red bar) compared to Rev-erbα+/− (black bar) mating pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Unpaired two-tailed t-test, ***P&lt;0.0001, n=16 for Rev-erbα+/− and n=6 for Rev-erbα−/−, F-test reveals difference in variance, F=8.793, DFn=5, Dfd=15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>(D) Hepatic Fgf21 mRNA in the liver is increased in Rev-erbα−/− (red line) compared to Rev-erbα+/+ mice (black line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The two curves are significantly different, P=0.0008, n=4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>(E) Plasma FGF21 protein levels are significantly increased in Rev-erbα−/− (red line) compared to Rev-erbα+/+ animals (black line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The two curves are significantly different, P=0.0003, n=4-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>All values are mean±s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Recent studies indicate that the reproductive axis is sensitive to fibroblast growth factor 21 (FGF21) (Owen et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The phenotype displayed by Rev-erbα−/− mice is reminiscent of animals overexpressing Fgf21 (Owen et al., 2013), therefore, we tested whether Fgf21 expression is altered in Rev-erbα−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We found that Fgf21 mRNA was diurnally expressed in the liver of wild-type mice in a similar fashion as Bmal1 mRNA, a REV-ERBα target gene (Preitner et al., 2002) and in an inverted diurnal pattern compared to the E-box-driven Per1 gene (Preitner et al., 2002) (Fig. 1D). Fgf21 mRNA expression was increased in Rev-erbα−/− mice at all time points over the day compared to controls (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Similarly, FGF21 protein levels were also increased in plasma of Rev-erbα−/− mice with pronounced elevation at Zeitgeber time (ZT)12 and ZT18 (Fig. 1E), but plasma FGF21 levels were not diurnal in wild-type animals (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Since REV-ERBα is a nuclear receptor with repressive potential, we tested whether REV-ERBα can directly regulate the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Fgf21 is regulated by REV-ERBα/HNF6 and PPARα/RXRα </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic analysis of the Fgf21 promoter revealed the presence of E-box elements to which the circadian clock factors BMAL1/CLOCK bind as heterodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we identified REV-ERBα binding sites, so-called putative retinoid orphan receptor elements (ROREs) and PPARα binding sites (PPARE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In a first step we tested activation of the Fgf21 promoter by BMAL1 and CLOCK using a transactivation assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>A 3.1 kB-long fragment of the Fgf21 promoter was linked to a luciferase reporter gene (Fgf21::luc) and transfected into NIH 3T3 cells along with increasing amounts of Bmal1 and Clock expression vectors (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>As expected, BMAL1/CLOCK induced the Per1::luc control reporter in a dose-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the Fgf21::luc reporter was not induced, indicating that BMAL1 and CLOCK are not regulating the Fgf21 promoter and hence are probably not directly responsible for the diurnal expression of Fgf21 mRNA observed in Fig. 1D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Since BMAL1 and CLOCK activate not only Rev-erbα but also Pparα (Canaple et al., 2006), the expected repression of the Fgf21::luc reporter is probably compensated by the activating potential of PPARα (Inagaki et al., 2007). Fig. 2.Regulation of the Fgf21 promoter by clock components. (A) Dose-dependent activation of the Per1::luc promoter by BMAL1 and CLOCK (black bars) and no BMAL1/CLOCK activation of the Fgf21::luc reporter (white bars) in NIH3T3 cells (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>(B) Dose dependent repression by REV-ERBα on the Bmal1::luc reporter (black bars) and the Fgf21::luc reporter (white bars) in NIH3T3 cells (n=4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>(C) Mutation analysis of the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Top left: schematic diagram showing the positions of the four ROREs (R1-R4), the PPAR element (blue) and the HNF6 binding site (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Top right: diagram of the mutations in R1 and R4, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Bottom: panels of fold change of the various constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Black bars: reference value for the Bmal1::luc and Fgf21::luc reporters, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>White bars: relative repression by Rev-erbα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Hatched bars: reduced repression by Rev-erbα on the mutated Fgf21::luc reporter (n=4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(D) Dose-dependent activating potential of RORα on the Bmal1::luc reporter (black bars) but not on the Fgf21::luc reporter (white bars) in NIH3T3 cells (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(E) Repression of the Bmal1::luc (white bars) and Fgf21::luc (blue bars) reporters in Hepa-1c1c7 cells involves Hnf6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Sc shRNA, scrambled shRNA; Hnf6 shRNA, knockdown of Hnf6 (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>(F) Repressive potential of REV-ERBα in Hepa-1c1c7 cells on the Bmal1::luc, the Fgf21::luc and the Hnf6 site mutated Fgf21::luc (mut Fgf21::luc) reporters (n=3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(G) Fold induction of the Fgf21::luc reporter by Pparα, Rxrα and Per2 in NIH3T3 cells (n=4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All panels: one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post-test. *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001, values are means±s.d. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We tested the repressive potential of REV-ERBα on the 3.1 kB Fgf21 promoter, containing four ROREs and one PPARE, designated as R1-R4 and P in Fig. 2C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>REV-ERBα repressed the Bmal1::luc reporter as expected, and also repressed the Fgf21::luc reporter (Fig. 2B) in a dose-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Mutation of the R1 element in the Fgf21::luc reporter reduced the repressive potential of REV-ERBα (Fig. 2C), which is consistent with previous findings that REV-ERBα may repress Fgf21 expression via this RORE site (Estall et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, however, the repression was not completely reversed by the mutation of R1, suggesting that additional promoter elements are most likely involved in the REV-ERBα-mediated repression of Fgf21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested the R2 and R3 elements as potential REV-ERBα binding sites, but no repression through these two sites was observed (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the R4 element appeared to be involved in the repression of Fgf21 by REV-ERBα, as mutation of this element partially abolished the repressive potential of REV-ERBα (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Hence, the ROREs R1 and R4 may be the sites of REV-ERBα binding at the Fgf21 promoter, regulating its expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Since the classical mechanism of REV-ERBα-mediated repression involves competition with the transcriptional activator RORα, we tested whether RORα activates the Fgf21::luc construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>As expected, RORα could activate the Bmal1::luc reporter in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 2D), however, the Fgf21::luc reporter did not or only poorly respond to RORα (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we suspected that Fgf21 is indirectly regulated by REV-ERBα via hepatic nuclear factor 6 (HNF6), a second mechanism through which REV-ERBα can act (Zhang et al., 2015) (see also the presence of an HNF6 binding site H in Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Transactivation experiments in Hepa-1c1c7 cells revealed that REV-ERBα suppresses the Bmal1::luc reporter in an HNF6 independent manner, because Hnf6 shRNA did not affect this repression (Fig. 2E); although Hnf6 mRNA and protein was strongly repressed with Rev-erbα expression unaffected (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, Hnf6 shRNA induced Fgf21 mRNA expression, indicating that HNF6 is mediating a repressing activity on the Fgf21 promoter (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested the influence of HNF6 on the REV-ERBα repressive function of the Fgf21 promoter observed in Fig. 2B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We found that Hnf6 shRNA, but not scrambled shRNA, increased the luciferase activity in the Fgf21::luc reporter, suggesting that HNF6 is a direct modulator of this promoter, and the lack of it increases baseline expression of Fgf21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the repression by REV-ERBα on this promoter only partially repressed activation and in absence of HNF6, REV-ERBα alone did not repress the Fgf21::luc reporter below baseline levels (Fig. 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This suggests that repression of the Fgf21 promoter is most likely the result of cooperation between HNF6 and REV-ERBα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, there is an HNF6 binding site (Zhang et al., 2015) close to the RORE designated as R1 in Fig. 2C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Mutating this HNF6 binding site abolished REV-ERBα mediated repression of the Fgf21::luc reporter (Fig. 2F), indicating that repression of this reporter by REV-ERBα requires the binding of HNF6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Because we identified a PPAR binding site (P in Fig. 2C) between the RORE R1 and R2, we tested whether PPARα, together with its heterodimerizing partner RXRα, may modulate the Fgf21::luc reporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We observed that PPARα activated this reporter and combined with RXRα this induction was even greater (Fig. 2G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Addition of Per2 increased this activation further (Fig. 2G), indicating that PPARα, RXRα and Per2 have an activating function on the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Binding of REV-ERBα, HNF6 and PPARα to the Fgf21 promoter in liver </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In order to test whether the regulation of the Fgf21 promoter by REV-ERBα, HNF6 and PPARα can occur in liver tissue, we performed chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Chromatin from livers of female mice was isolated and antibodies against REV-ERBα, HNF6 and PPARα were used to identify the promoter sequences in Fgf21 bound by these transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We tested the four RORE-containing regions (R1-R4) in the Fgf21 promoter for binding of REV-ERBα (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>We observed the strongest binding to the R1 element (which included also the HNF6 site) with weaker binding to the R4 element and no binding to the R2 and R3 elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the binding to R1 and R4 was time-of-day dependent with more REV-ERBα binding at ZT10 than ZT22 (Fig. 3A), which is consistent with the expression pattern of Fgf21 (Fig. 1D,E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The pattern of REV-ERBα binding was similar compared to the Bmal1 and Rev-erbα promoter controls (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In contrast, binding of HNF6 to the Fgf21 promoter was not time-of-day dependent and only occurred in the R1 element, which includes the HNF6 binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>R2, R3 and R4 did not show HNF6 binding (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Similar to HNF6, PPARα binding to the Fgf21 promoter was not time-of-day dependent, with strong binding at both ZT8 and ZT20 in both wild-type and Rev-erbα−/− mice (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, PPARα binding to the Bmal1 promoter was time-of-day dependent (Fig. 3C), indicating that the mechanism of regulation by PPARα of the Fgf21 promoter is different from the regulation of the Bmal1 promoter. Fig. 3.Chromatin immunoprecipitation of REV-ERBα, HNF6, PPARα and PER2 on the Fgf21 promoter of liver chromatin. (A) Binding of REV-ERBα to its own promoter and to the Bmal1 and Fgf21 promoters at Zeitgeber time (ZT) 10 (black bars) and ZT22 (white bars), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(B) Binding of HNF6 to the R1-R4 elements on the Fgf21 promoter at ZT10 and ZT22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(C) Binding of PPARα on the Bmal1 and Fgf21 promoters in the liver of wild-type (black bars) and Rev-erbα−/− (red bars) animals at ZT8 and ZT20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(D) Binding of PER2 on the Bmal1 and Fgf21 promoters in the liver of wild-type (black bars) and Rev-erbα−/− (red bars) animals at ZT8 and ZT20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>All panels: two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post-test, n=3, *P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001; values are means±s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Because PER2 can bind to both REV-ERBα and PPARα (Schmutz et al., 2010), we tested PER2 binding to the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We observed that PER2 binds in a time-of-day dependent manner to both the Bmal1 and Fgf21 promoters in wild-type mice, however, only to the Bmal1 promoter in Rev-erbα−/− animals (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>This indicates that binding of PER2 to the Fgf21 promoter depends on the presence of REV-ERBα and/or PPARα. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>There is strong evidence that the circadian clock influences fertility and therefore reproductive fitness in mice (Miller and Takahashi, 2013; Sellix and Menaker, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We observed that Rev-erbα−/− mice produce less pups and have less litters associated with a longer inter-litter period (Fig. 1A-C); however, the mechanisms linking the clock with reproduction are not well understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We provide evidence that FGF21, which regulates metabolism (reviewed in Nies et al., 2016) and modulates fertility (Owen et al., 2013), may be one of the links. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Animals overexpressing FGF21 show reduced fertility, which is similar to the phenotype of Rev-erbα−/− animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This similarity is further highlighted by our finding that expression of Fgf21 mRNA, as well as FGF21 protein, is elevated in Rev-erbα−/− mice (Fig. 1D,E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Hence, Rev-erbα−/− animals can be considered as Fgf21 overexpressors, although they overexpress Fgf21 to a much lesser extent compared to the transgenic mice described by Owen et al. (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The diurnal cycling of Fgf21 mRNA in wild-type liver (Fig. 1D) is similar to the diurnal expression of Bmal1, indicating that BMAL1/CLOCK are most likely not responsible for Fgf21 cycling, despite a previous report that described BMAL1/CLOCK-mediated activation of a 2 kb long Fgf21::luc reporter (Tong et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Our own experiments indicate that our 3.1 kb Fgf21::luc reporter is not activated by BMAL1/CLOCK (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, ChIP-sequencing experiments revealed BMAL1 binding to the Fgf21 promoter, however no evidence of binding for CLOCK or NPAS2 was found (Koike et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the Fgf21 promoter is most likely not activated by BMAL1/CLOCK or BMAL1/NPAS2 heterodimers in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>What the role of BMAL1 binding to the Fgf21 promoter is and whether it has activating potential with an unknown heterodimerization partner remains to be determined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Because Fgf21 expression in liver is increased in Rev-erbα−/− animals (Fig. 1D), reminiscent of the increased expression of Bmal1 (Preitner et al., 2002), we tested whether the Fgf21 promoter could be repressed by REV-ERBα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>We found that Fgf21 was repressed by REV-ERBα in a dose dependent manner, comparable to the Bmal1 promoter (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>This is in line with previous findings that suggested repression of the Fgf21 promoter by REV-ERBα (Estall et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the reported RORE in that work (R1 in Fig. 2) is not the only RORE involved in the regulation of the Fgf21 promoter as revealed by our mutation studies (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>It appears that at least another RORE (R4 in Fig. 2) is involved in REV-ERBα-mediated repression of the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>If REV-ERBα regulates Fgf21 via direct binding to the RORE it would compete with RORα for this binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested whether RORα induces the Fgf21::luc reporter in a dose-dependent manner as it does for the Bmal1::luc reporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>We found no dose-dependent action of RORα on the Fgf21 promoter, in contrast to previous reports that suggested an involvement of RORα in Fgf21 regulation (Wang et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Of note is that no dose response curve for RORα was established in that study, which may lead to a misinterpretation of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>A recent study identified nobiletin as an agonist of ROR nuclear receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Application of nobiletin increased expression of ROR target genes in the liver involved in metabolism, with Fgf21 being unaffected (He et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>This supports our observation that RORα is not involved in the regulation of Fgf21 expression in the liver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>From our data we conclude that REV-ERBα may act on the Fgf21 promoter via another mechanism, different from the competition mechanism between REV-ERBα and RORα. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>A recent study identified a second mode of action for REV-ERBα in the liver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Whereas the direct competition mechanism between REV-ERBα and ROR transcription factors provides a universal mechanism for self-sustained control of the molecular clock across all tissues, REV-ERBα uses lineage-determining factors to convey a tissue-specific rhythm that regulates metabolism tailored to the specific need of that tissue (Zhang et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In the liver, the tissue-specific factor is HNF6 through which REV-ERBα can modulate gene expression in an HNF6-dependent fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In accordance with this hypothesis, we found that REV-ERBα regulates Fgf21 expression involving HNF6 (Figs 2E,F, 3B and Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>This concept is also consistent with the observation that REV-ERBα can regulate FGF21 signaling in an adipose tissue-specific manner by directly regulating βKlotho, an essential co-receptor for FGF21 signaling (Jager et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In addition to HNF6 binding sites (Fig. 3B), we found PPAR elements in the Fgf21 promoter sequence (Figs 2G and 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>We could confirm that PPARα regulates expression of Fgf21 (Figs 2G and 3C) as described previously (Oishi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we observed that PER2 can increase induction of the Fgf21::luc reporter (Fig. 2G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This increase may be partially mediated by binding of PER2 to PPARα, but lack of REV-ERBα abolishes binding of PER2 to the Fgf21 promoter of liver chromatin (Fig. 3D), suggesting a complex regulation of the Fgf21 promoter by PPARα and REV-ERBα with PER2 modulating the transcriptional potential of both of these nuclear receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous observations reporting that PER2 is binding to both PPARα and REV-ERBα (Schmutz et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Hence, PER2 may mediate the formation of a time-of-day dependent super complex containing PPARα and REV-ERBα, most likely along with additional co-factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Taken together, we present evidence that REV-ERBα regulates Fgf21 expression in the liver involving HNF6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This mechanism may be influenced by PER2 and PPARα (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Since FGF21 is released from the liver into the bloodstream to reach the brain influencing fertility via the hypothalamus, REV-ERBα may modulate fertility via this pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>However, the contribution of REV-ERBα to reproductive fitness is most likely not limited to Fgf21 regulation, but may also include additional processes, such as the regulation of ovarian biology and metabolic pathways known to be regulated by REV-ERBα (Bugge et al., 2012; Cho et al., 2012), thereby affecting fertility in an indirect manner. Fig. 4.Schematic representing clock contribution to Fgf21 regulation in the liver. REV-ERBα (R orange circle) represses the Fgf21 promoter involving HNF6 (olive trapezoid). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, PPARα (green oval) with its heterodimerizing partner RXR (light blue oval) activates the Fgf21 promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>PER2 (P2, red circle) most likely modulates one or both of these regulations due to its capacity to bind to PPARα and REV-ERBα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that BMAL1 (B blue circle) and CLOCK (C/N purple oval) are not significantly involved in the regulation of Fgf21. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Animal care and handling were performed in accordance with the guidelines of the Schweizer Tierschutzgesetz (TSchG, SR455) and the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The protocol was approved by the state veterinarian of the Canton of Fribourg. Rev-Erbα−/− mice were obtained from Dr U. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Schibler (University of Geneva, Switzerland) and are on a mixed background 129Sv/C57BL6 (Preitner et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Animals were maintained on 12 h light:12 h dark cycle with food and water ad libitum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Cell culture and luciferase assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>NIH3T3 and Hepa-1c1c7 mouse cells were used for in vitro experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Cells were maintained in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM), high glucose (4.5 g/l) (6429, Sigma, USA) containing 10% fetal calf serum (FCS) and 100 U/ml penicillin/streptomycin at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Expression plasmids pSCT1-PPARα, pSCT1-RXRα, pSCT1-PER2, pSCT1-LacZ (β-galactosidase), pSCT1-REV-ERBα, pSCT1-RORα and Bmal1 luciferase construct (with PPAR regulatory site) are described (Schmutz et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Mouse Fgf21 promoter is harboring four putative retinoid orphan receptor elements (ROREs) and one PPAR response element (PPRE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Five different sizes of mouse Fgf21 promoter fragments were amplified by PCR and cloned into pGL3 basic vector (Promega, USA) using following primers: CGGTACCCTGAAGCCCCAGGTTC (R1_sense primer, KpnI site), GCTCGAGCCAAGGCAGCTGGAATTG (R1_anti-sense primer, XhoI site), CGGTACCCAGGAGGATGGAGAAC (R2_sense primer, KpnI site), GCTCGAGGAACCTGGGGCTTCAG (R2_anti-sense primer, XhoI site), CACGCGTGTCCGGCTTAGTGAAC (R3_sense primer, MluI site), GCTCGAGGTTCTCCATCCTCCTG (R3_anti-sense primer, XhoI site), CACGCGTCTCCTGTCCATTGCCAG (R4_sense primer, MluI site), GCTCGAGGTTCACTAAGCCGGAC (R4_anti-sense primer, XhoI site), CACGCGTCAGATTAAGCCACCGAGTC (sense primer, MluI site), GCTCGAGCTGGTGAACGCAGAAATAC (anti-sense primer, XhoI site). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Generated luciferase reporter plasmids were designated as R1 (+133 to −918 bp), R2 (−919 to −1816 bp), R3 (−1817 to −2892 bp), R4 (−2893 to −4133 bp) and Fgf21: luc (+2 to −3099). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The potential RORE and HNF6 binding elements were mutated by site-directed mutagenesis using the following primers: –90 CCAAGTGGGCCCAGGATCCCGGGCCCGGAGTG –47 (mut_R1), –3058 TGAGATTTTCAGTGGGGCCCGGAGCTATGCAAAT –3023 (mut_R4) and –117 CCTGGCCACGGTGGGCCCCCGGGTCCTGCCAAGTGTG –81 (mut_Hnf6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Luciferase assays were performed in NIH3T3 cells as described (Langmesser et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>An empty pGL3 vector was used as negative control. Bmal1::luc and Per1::luc reporter were used as positive controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Knockdown of HNF6 and western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>24 h after seeding cells, HNF6-shRNA plasmid (HNF-6 sc-37937-SH, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, USA) was used for knocking-down of HNF6, according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Scrambled shRNA plasmid (sc-108060, Santa Cruz Biotechnology) was used as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Knockdown efficiency was assessed 48 h post-transfection by western blotting as well as by real time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Protein of transfected Hepa-1c1c7 cells was extracted using RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate containing protease and phosphatase inhibitors). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Protein samples were subjected to electrophoresis on 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gels and transferred to a nitrocellulose (Amersham Protran Supported 0.45 NC, GE Healthcare). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>After blocking with 0.5% dry milk in PBS-Tween 0.1%, the membranes were probed with anti-HNF6 (1:500, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-376167), and HSP90 (1:1000, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-13119) antibodies overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Anti-rabbit and -mouse HRP conjugated antibody was used as a secondary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Detection of the immune complexes was performed using WesternBright Quantum system (Advansta, K-12042, USA) and quantification was done with the Quantity One analysis software (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from frozen liver using RNA-Bee (AMS Biotechnology, CS-105B, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>RNA samples were treated with DNase I (Roche), and purified by phenol:chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>cDNA synthesis was carried out with SuperScript II (Invitrogen) and SYBR green based real-time PCR was performed for mRNA quantification using KAPA SYBR FAST (KAPA Biosystems, KK-4601, UK) and RotorGene 6000 (Corbett Research, RG-6000, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>All RNA samples were normalized to Gapdh. Primers are: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Gapdh: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>sense: 5′-CATGGCCTTCCGTGTTCCTA-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>antisense: 5′-CCTGCTTCACCACCTTCT TGA-3′; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Fgf21: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>sense: 5′-ACTGCTGCTGGACGGTTA-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>antisense: 5′-GCATCCTGGTTTGGGGAGTCCTT-3′; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Rev-erbα: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>sense: 5′-CAAGGCAACACCAAGAATGTT-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>antisense: 5′-TTCCCAGATCTCCTGCACAGT-3′; </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Hnf6: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>sense: 5′-CCCTGGAGCAAACTCAAGTC-3′ </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>antisense: 5′-GGTCTCTTTCCG TGCTGCTA-3′. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The values were calculated using the double delta Ct method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>81 cycles of 10 s at 55°C with increasing increments of 0.5°C per cycle was performed for melting curve analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>A negative control for each primer pair was included on each plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Melting curve analysis was performed to confirm that only one product was amplified and there were not any products in negative controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>LinRegPCR was used to calculate PCR efficiencies for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The RNA source, Average Ct, working annealing temperature, the average amplification efficiency and coefficients of variation are given for each gene in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>For the chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments, mice were sacrificed at ZT10 and ZT22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The livers of mice were homogenized in 1× phosphate-buffered saline supplemented with 1% formaldehyde, incubated for 5 min at room temperature, and nuclei and chromatin prepared according to (Schmutz et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Briefly, pure liver nuclei form each mouse were obtained by centrifugation through 2.05 M sucrose cushions and the chromatin in 500 μl of 1% SDS, 20 mM Tris pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, and 2 mM EDTA was fragmented by sonication (10×10 s pulses at 50% intensity using a Branson SLPe device equipped with a microtip). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>After a 10-fold dilution with 1.1% Triton X-100, 20 mM Tris pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, and 2 mM EDTA, 200 μl of chromatin were used per reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>DNA fragments precipitated with anti-REV-ERBα antibody (1:50 dilution; SAB2101632; Sigma-Aldrich), with anti-HNF6 (G-10) (1:30 dilution; sc-376167, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), with anti-PPARα (1:25 dilution; 101710; Cayman Chemical Company, USA) or with anti-PER2 (1:25 dilution; No. 611138; BD Transduction Laboratories) were detected with the reverse transcription PCR primers and probes enlisted in Table S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Along the samples, 1% of the input was processed and the % of input calculated as precipitated material/(amount of input ×100). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We thank Drs J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Acierno, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Somm and A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Messina for comments on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><title>Footnotes</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing or financial interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Author contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>U.A. and N.Pi. conceived, designed and interpreted the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>R.C., N.Pr., T.O, L.M.S., C.X. and J.A.R. performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>U.A. wrote the manuscript and all authors reviewed the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a Sinergia Grant from Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung (Swiss National Science Foundation) (CRSII3_141960/1) and the States of Fribourg and Vaud. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information available online at http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/doi/10.1242/bio.021519.supplemental. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="BIO021519C1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>BeenkenA. and MohammadiM. (2009). The FGF family: biology, pathophysiology and therapy. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Drug Discov. 8, 235-253. 10.1038/nrd279219247306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C2"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>BodenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>J., VarcoeT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>J., VoultsiosA. and KennawayD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>J. (2010). Reproductive biology of female Bmal1 null mice. Reproduction 139, 1077-1090. 10.1530/REP-09-052320200203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C3"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>BodenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>J., VarcoeT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>J. and KennawayD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>J. (2013). Circadian regulation of reproduction: from gamete to offspring. Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Biol. 113, 387-397. 10.1016/j.pbiomolbio.2013.01.00323380455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C4"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>BuggeA., FengD., EverettL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>J., BriggsE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>R., MullicanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>E., WangF., JagerJ. and LazarM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>A. (2012). Rev-erbα and Rev-erbβ coordinately protect the circadian clock and normal metabolic function. Genes Dev. 26, 657-667. 10.1101/gad.186858.11222474260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C5"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>CanapleL., RambaudJ., Dkhissi-BenyahyaO., RayetB., TanN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>S., MichalikL., DelaunayF., WahliW. and LaudetV. (2006). Reciprocal regulation of brain and muscle Arnt-like protein 1 and peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor alpha defines a novel positive feedback loop in the rodent liver circadian clock. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. 20, 1715-1727. 10.1210/me.2006-005216556735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C6"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>ChoH., ZhaoX., HatoriM., YuR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>T., BarishG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>D., LamM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>T., ChongL.-W., DiTacchioL., AtkinsA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>R., GlassC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>K.et al. (2012). Regulation of circadian behaviour and metabolism by REV-ERB-α and REV-ERB-β. Nature 485, 123-127. 10.1038/nature1104822460952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C7"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>ChomezP., NeveuI., MansenA., KieslerE., LarssonL., VennstromB. and ArenasE. (2000). Increased cell death and delayed development in the cerebellum of mice lacking the rev-erbα orphan receptor. Development 127, 1489-1498.10704394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C8"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>EstallJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>L., RuasJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>L., ChoiC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>S., LaznikD., BadmanM., Maratos-FlierE., ShulmanG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>I. and SpiegelmanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>M. (2009). PGC-1alpha negatively regulates hepatic FGF21 expression by modulating the heme/Rev-Erbα axis. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>USA 106, 22510-22515. 10.1073/pnas.091253310620018698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C9"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>HeB., NoharaK., ParkN., ParkY.-S., GuilloryB., ZhaoZ., GarciaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>M., KoikeN., LeeC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>C., TakahashiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>S.et al. (2016). The small molecule nobiletin targets the molecular oscillator to enhance circadian rhythms and protect against metabolic syndrome. Cell Metab. 23, 610-621. 10.1016/j.cmet.2016.03.00727076076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C10"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>IkegamiK. and YoshimuraT. (2012). Circadian clocks and the measurement of daylength in seasonal reproduction. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. 349, 76-81. 10.1016/j.mce.2011.06.04021767603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C11"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>InagakiT., DutchakP., ZhaoG., DingX., GautronL., ParameswaraV., LiY., GoetzR., MohammadiM., EsserV.et al. (2007). Endocrine regulation of the fasting response by PPARα-mediated induction of fibroblast growth factor 21. Cell Metab. 5, 415-425. 10.1016/j.cmet.2007.05.00317550777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C12"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>ItohN. (2010). Hormone-like (endocrine) Fgfs: their evolutionary history and roles in development, metabolism, and disease. Cell Tissue Res. 342, 1-11. 10.1007/s00441-010-1024-220730630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C13"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>JagerJ., WangF., FangB., LimH.-W., PeedL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>C., StegerD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>J., WonK.-J., KharitonenkovA., AdamsA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>C. and LazarM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A. (2016). The nuclear receptor rev-erbalpha regulates adipose tissue-specific Fibroblast Growth Factor 21 (FGF21) signaling. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Chem. 291, 10867-10875. 10.1074/jbc.M116.71912027002153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C14"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>KennawayD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>J., BodenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>J. and VoultsiosA. (2004). Reproductive performance in female Clock Delta19 mutant mice. Reprod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Fertil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Dev. 16, 801-810. 10.1071/RD0402315740704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C15"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>KoikeN., YooS.-H., HuangH.-C., KumarV., LeeC., KimT.-K. and TakahashiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>S. (2012). Transcriptional architecture and chromatin landscape of the core circadian clock in mammals. Science 338, 349-354. 10.1126/science.122633922936566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C16"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>LangmesserS., TalloneT., BordonA., RusconiS. and AlbrechtU. (2008). Interaction of circadian clock proteins PER2 and CRY with BMAL1 and CLOCK. BMC Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Biol. 9, 41 10.1186/1471-2199-9-4118430226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C17"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>MerenessA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>L., MurphyZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>C., ForrestelA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>C., ButlerS., KoC., RichardsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>S. and SellixM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>T. (2015). Conditional deletion of Bmal1 in ovarian theca cells disrupts ovulation in female mice. Endocrinology 157, en20151645 10.1210/en.2015-1645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C18"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>MillerB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>H. and TakahashiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>S. (2013). Central circadian control of female reproductive function. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. 4, 195 10.3389/fendo.2013.00195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C19"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>MillerB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>H., OlsonS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>L., TurekF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>W., LevineJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>E., HortonT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>H. and TakahashiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>S. (2004). Circadian clock mutation disrupts estrous cyclicity and maintenance of pregnancy. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Biol. 14, 1367-1373. 10.1016/j.cub.2004.07.05515296754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C20"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>NiesV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>JM., SancarG., LiuW., van ZutphenT., StruikD., YuR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>T., AtkinsA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>R., EvansR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>M., JonkerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>W. and DownesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>R. (2016). Fibroblast growth factor signaling in metabolic regulation. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. 6, 193 10.3389/fendo.2015.00193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C21"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>OishiK., UchidaD. and IshidaN. (2008). Circadian expression of FGF21 is induced by PPARα activation in the mouse liver. FEBS Lett. 582, 3639-3642. 10.1016/j.febslet.2008.09.04618840432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C22"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>OwenB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>M., BookoutA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>L., DingX., LinV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Y., AtkinS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>D., GautronL., KliewerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>A. and MangelsdorfD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>J. (2013). FGF21 contributes to neuroendocrine control of female reproduction. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Med. 19, 1153-1156. 10.1038/nm.325023933983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C23"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>PilorzV. and SteinlechnerS. (2008). Low reproductive success in Per1 and Per2 mutant mouse females due to accelerated ageing? Reproduction 135, 559-568. 10.1530/REP-07-043418367514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C24"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>PreitnerN., DamiolaF., Lopez-MolinaL., ZakanyJ., DubouleD., AlbrechtU. and SchiblerU. (2002). The orphan nuclear receptor REV-ERBα controls circadian transcription within the positive limb of the mammalian circadian oscillator. Cell 110, 251-260. 10.1016/S0092-8674(02)00825-512150932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C25"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>RatajczakC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>K., BoehleK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>L. and MugliaL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>J. (2009). Impaired steroidogenesis and implantation failure in Bmal1-/- mice. Endocrinology 150, 1879-1885. 10.1210/en.2008-102119056819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C26"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>ReitmanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>L. (2007). FGF21: a missing link in the biology of fasting. Cell Metab. 5, 405-407. 10.1016/j.cmet.2007.05.01017550773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C27"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>SchmutzI., RippergerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>A., Baeriswyl-AebischerS. and AlbrechtU. (2010). The mammalian clock component PERIOD2 coordinates circadian output by interaction with nuclear receptors. Genes Dev. 24, 345-357. 10.1101/gad.56411020159955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C28"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>SellixM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>T. and MenakerM. (2010). Circadian clocks in the ovary. Trends Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Metab. 21, 628-636. 10.1016/j.tem.2010.06.00220599392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C29"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>TongX., MuchnikM., ChenZ., PatelM., WuN., JoshiS., RuiL., LazarM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>A. and YinL. (2010). Transcriptional repressor E4-binding protein 4 (E4BP4) regulates metabolic hormone fibroblast growth factor 21 (FGF21) during circadian cycles and feeding. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Chem. 285, 36401-36409. 10.1074/jbc.M110.17286620851878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C30"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>WangY., SoltL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>A. and BurrisT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>P. (2010). Regulation of FGF21 expression and secretion by retinoic acid receptor-related orphan receptor alpha. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Chem. 285, 15668-15673. 10.1074/jbc.M110.10216020332535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="BIO021519C31"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>ZhangY., FangB., EmmettM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>J., DamleM., SunZ., FengD., ArmourS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>M., RemsbergJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>R., JagerJ., SoccioR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>E.et al. (2015). Discrete functions of nuclear receptor Rev-erbα couple metabolism to the clock. Science 348, 1488-1492. 10.1126/science.aab302126044300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
