<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hematol Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Hematol Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Hematology &amp; Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-8722</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5395742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13045-017-0449-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A novel lncRNA uc.134 represses hepatocellular carcinoma progression by inhibiting CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><address><email>wenni_2007@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yuqin</given-names></name><address><email>zhang1987316@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>Zetao</given-names></name><address><email>srandrs@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><address><email>yefeng83869118@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Yonghao</given-names></name><address><email>stephen11@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><address><email>hj841023@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Keli</given-names></name><address><email>wh_drchen@sina.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Longhua</given-names></name><address><email>chenlhsmu@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><address><email>dingyi197980@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8877 7471</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.284723.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Nanfang Hospital, </institution><institution>Southern Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, 510515 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8877 7471</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.284723.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathology, </institution><institution>Southern Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, 510515 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 3078</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410560.6</institution-id><institution/><institution>Cancer Center, Affiliated Hospital of Guangdong Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Zhanjiang, 524001 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>91</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is one of the most common malignancies worldwide, and tumor recurrence and metastasis are major factors that contribute to the poor outcome of patients with HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) are known to regulate different tumorigenic processes, and a growing body of evidence indicates that Hippo kinase signaling is inactivated in many cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, the upstream lncRNA regulators of Hippo kinase signaling in HCC are poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Using a lncRNA microarray, we identified a novel lncRNA, uc.134, whose expression was significantly decreased in the highly aggressive HCC cell line HCCLM3 compared with MHCC97L cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we evaluated uc.134 expression in clinical samples using in situ hybridization (ISH) and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The full-length transcript of uc.134 was confirmed using rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>To investigate the biological function of uc.134, we performed gain-of-function and loss-of-function studies both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The underlying mechanisms of uc.134 in HCC were investigated using RNA pulldown, RNA immunoprecipitation, ubiquitination assays, Western blotting, mRNA microarray analyses, and qRT-PCR analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The ISH assay revealed that uc.134 expression was significantly decreased in 170 paraffin-embedded samples from patients with HCC compared with adjacent tissues and uc.134 expression directly correlated with patient prognosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we defined a 1867-bp full-length transcript of uc.134 using 5′- and 3′-RACE analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The overexpression of uc.134 inhibited HCC cell proliferation, invasion, and metastasis in vitro and in vivo, whereas the knockdown of uc.134 produced the opposite results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we confirmed that uc.134 (1408–1867 nt) binds to CUL4A (592–759 aa region) and inhibits its nuclear export. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we demonstrated that uc.134 inhibits the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 and increases YAPS127 phosphorylation to silence the target genes of YAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Finally, a positive correlation between uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 was confirmed in 90 paraffin-embedded samples by ISH and immunohistochemical staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Our study identifies that a novel lncRNA, uc.134, represses hepatocellular carcinoma progression by inhibiting the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 and increasing YAPS127 phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The use of this lncRNA may offer a promising treatment approach by inhibiting YAP and activating Hippo kinase signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13045-017-0449-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>LncRNA uc.134</kwd><kwd>CUL4A</kwd><kwd>Ubiquitination</kwd><kwd>LATS1</kwd><kwd>pYAP<sup>S127</sup></kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Pearl River Nova Program of Guangzhou, Guangdong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>No. 2014J2200015</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guangdong Natural Science Funds for Distinguished Young Scholar</institution></funding-source><award-id>No. 2015A030306015</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Excellent Young Teachers Program of Higher Education of Guangdong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>No. YQ2015036</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guangdong Program for Support of Top-notch Young Professionals</institution></funding-source><award-id>No. 2015TQ01R279</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yuqin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is one of the most common causes of cancer mortality worldwide [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Currently, surgical treatment for HCC is only available in the initial stage of the disease, but most patients present with advanced disease upon diagnosis, at which point the efficacy of radiotherapy and chemotherapy is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The high rate of tumor recurrence and metastasis are major factors that contribute to the poor prognosis of patients with HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Therefore, novel insights into the mechanism of HCC are urgently needed to identify novel prognostic molecular markers and potential effective therapeutic targets to improve patient survival [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) are RNA transcripts that are longer than 200 nt and exhibit limited or no protein-coding capacity, and many lncRNAs are uniquely expressed in differentiated tissues or specific cancer types [5–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Recent discoveries indicate that lncRNAs drive many important cancer phenotypes by interacting with other cellular macromolecules, including DNA, RNA, and protein [9–12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Advanced studies have found that aberrant lncRNA expression plays critical roles in hepatocarcinogenesis and metastasis [13–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Moreover, MALAT1 is associated with tumor metastasis and can predict recurrence after liver transplantation [16, 17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, UFC1 promotes HCC cell proliferation by inhibiting cell apoptosis and inducing cell cycle progression [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Long noncoding RNA low expression in tumor (lncRNA-LET) reduces hepatic invasion and abdominal metastases via the degradation of NF90 [19], and MEG3 is a predictive biomarker for monitoring epigenetic therapy [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In addition, ultraconserved noncoding RNAs (ucRNAs) are noncoding RNAs transcribed from regions that are highly conserved across many species, so-called ultraconserved regions [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Evf-2, a ucRNA in the intergenic region between the Dlx-5 and Dlx-6 genes, activates transcriptional activity by directly interacting with Dlx-2 in a target- and homeodomain-specific manner [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, the molecular mechanisms of lncRNAs remain poorly understood and warrant further study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>A growing number of studies have focused on the widespread Hippo kinase signaling inactivation and nuclear localization of YAP in epithelial malignancies [23–25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Specifically, a gene expression analysis of HCC identified YAP as an important “driver oncogene” [26], and the Hippo pathway is a highly conserved protein kinase chain that plays a pivotal role in restricting tumor cell proliferation and promoting apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>By phosphorylating YAP, the serine/threonine-protein kinase LATS1 inhibits the translocation of YAP into the nucleus and decreases the expression of its downstream target genes, which are important for cell proliferation and migration [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>However, the mechanism by which lncRNAs regulate Hippo kinase signaling in HCC remains largely unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used a lncRNA microarray to identify that the expression of the ultraconserved lncRNA uc.134 was significantly decreased in the highly aggressive HCC cell line HCCLM3 compared with MHCC97L cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>We then first confirmed the full-length transcript of uc.134 using 5′- and 3′-rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) analysis (GenBank accession no. KY355383). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The high conservation of uc.134 implicates that its aberrant expression may play a critical role in HCC progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in situ hybridization (ISH) and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) results showed that uc.134 expression significantly decreased in HCC and uc.134 expression directly correlated with patient survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we demonstrated that the overexpression of uc.134 suppresses HCC cell proliferation and invasion by inhibiting CUL4A to ubiquitinate LATS1 and increasing pYAPS127 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We also confirmed that uc.134 inhibits the expression of YAP downstream target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Finally, a positive relationship among uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 was also confirmed in 90 paraffin-embedded clinical samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our study reveals that the novel lncRNA uc.134 represses HCC progression by inhibiting the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 and increasing pYAPS127 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Thus, this lncRNA may offer a promising treatment approach by inhibiting YAP and activating Hippo kinase signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Microarray assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from cells using TRIzol Reagent (Takara, Dalian, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Sample labeling and array hybridization were performed according to the Arraystar microarray-based gene expression analysis protocol (Arraystar, Rockville, MD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The Arraystar human lncRNA microarray is designed for the global profiling of human lncRNAs and protein-coding mRNA transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The array detects a total of 40,173 lncRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The lncRNAs were carefully constructed using the most highly respected public transcriptome databases (RefSeq, UCSC Known Genes, Ensembl, etc.), as well as landmark publications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The Arraystar mRNA microarray provided a global view of all known genes and transcripts in the human genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>A total of 27,958 Entrez Gene RNAs were detected by this microarray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The content was sourced from RefSeq, Ensembl, UniGene Build, and GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Quantile normalization and subsequent data processing were performed using the GeneSpring GX v12.1 software package (Agilent Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>After quantile normalization of the raw data, the lncRNAs and mRNAs that were detected in at least three out of six samples were chosen for further data analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed lncRNAs and mRNAs with statistical significance between the two groups were identified through P value/FDR filtering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>KEGG pathway analysis and gene ontology (GO) analysis were applied to determine the roles of these differentially expressed mRNAs in the corresponding biological pathways or GO terms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The microarray data were uploaded in the Additional files 1, 2, and 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Tissue samples, ISH, immunohistochemical staining (IHC), and fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>From January 2009 to December 2013, 170 human HCC samples were collected at Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University (Guangzhou, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>None of these patients had been pretreated with chemotherapy or radiotherapy before undergoing surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the Nanfang Hospital Institutional Ethical Review Board, and informed consent was obtained from each patient. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134 expression was measured in paraffin-embedded samples using an ISH optimization kit (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The locked nucleic acid (LNA)-modified oligonucleotide probe targeting uc.134 was designed and synthesized at Exiqon (Vedbaek, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Briefly, HCC samples were treated with pepsin for 10 min at room temperature and incubated with 500 nM of probe at 55 °C for 4 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The samples were incubated with blocking solution for 30 min, anti-digoxigenin (anti-DIG) reagent was applied for 60 min and the samples were incubated with AP substrate 4-nitro-blue tetrazolium and 5-bromo-4-chloro-3′-indolylphosphate (NBT-BCIP) for 2 h at 30 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The samples were then mounted with Nuclear Fast Red™ (BOSTER, Wuhan, China), and a blue stain in the nucleus indicated a positive signal by NBT-BCIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>IHC was performed as we previously described [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>For FISH, the signals representing the expression of LNA probes were determined using the tyramide signal amplification (PerkinElmer, USA) system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In brief, the signal was detected by incubation with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated anti-DIG antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Then, the signals were amplified using tetramethylrhodamine (TRITC)-conjugated tyramide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The images were acquired with a fluorescence microscope (IX70, Olympus, Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The ISH and IHC results were evaluated by two individuals in a blinded fashion; the evaluators scored the samples using a quick scoring system from 0 to 12 by combining the intensity and percentage of the positive signal (signal: “0,” no staining; “1,” weak staining; “2,” intermediate staining; and “3,” strong staining; percentage: “0,” 0%; “1,” 1–25%; “2,” 26–50%; “3,” 51–75%; and “4,” &gt;75%), and this was in good agreement with the initial quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>An optimal cutoff value was identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>If the evaluated uc.134 score was higher than the average score, the uc.134 expression in those HCC samples was classified as high; otherwise, it was classified as low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>To account for inconsistencies in the percentage of the ISH signals, an ImageJ software (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) was used for scoring signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The data were statistically analyzed using t test to determine the differences in uc.134 expression levels between different groups of tissues. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In vivo model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>All animal studies were performed with the approval from the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Nanfang Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Male BALB/c nude mice (age, 4–6 weeks; Guangdong Medical Laboratory Animal Center, China) were raised under specific pathogen-free conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>All in vivo experiments were performed according to our institution’s guidelines for the use of laboratory animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For the subcutaneously injected tumor model, 3 × 106 cells were subcutaneously injected into the left flanks or right flanks of mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>After 4 weeks, the tumors were embedded in paraffin for ISH or IHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>For the lung metastasis model, 2 × 106 cells were injected into the tail veins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We monitored lung metastasis at 6 weeks to quantify lung colonization by histology examination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>RACE analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The 5′ and 3′-RACE experiments were performed using the SMARTer® RACE 5′/3′ Kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Briefly, at least two sets of primers were designed and synthesized for the nested PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The RACE PCR products were separated on a 1.5% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The results of electrophoresis were confirmed, and the amplified bands were sequenced bi-directionally using the indicated primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The gene-specific RACE primers used for mapping each end are listed in Additional file 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation and qRT-PCR analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Cytoplasmic and nuclear RNA fractionation was performed using the PARIS™ Kit (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, California) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The yield and quality of the RNA samples were evaluated prior to qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>For qRT-PCR analysis, total RNA was isolated from the cells using TRIzol Reagent (Takara) following the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>First-strand cDNA synthesis from 1 μg of total RNA was performed using a reverse transcriptase cDNA synthesis kit (Takara). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The resulting cDNA was then analyzed by qRT-PCR using a SYBR Green PCR Kit (Takara) and a 7500 Fast real-time PCR system (AB Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In brief, the reaction mixture containing 500 ng cDNA, the forward primer and the reverse primer, was used to amplify the PCR product corresponding to the human gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The experiments were repeated at least three times independently to ensure the reproducibility of the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Human GAPDH gene was amplified as an internal control. β-actin and U6 were used as cytoplasmic and nuclear controls, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Comparative quantification was done by using the 2−ΔΔCt method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in Additional file 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>RNA immunoprecipitation (RIP) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A RIP assay was performed using the Magna RIP RNA-Binding Protein Immunoprecipitation Kit (Millipore, MA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Briefly, whole-cell extracts prepared in lysis buffer containing a protease inhibitor cocktail and RNase inhibitor were incubated on ice for 5 min, followed by centrifugation at 10,000g and 4 °C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Magnetic beads were preincubated with 5 ug of IP-grade antibody for 30 min at room temperature with rotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was added to bead-antibody complexes in immunoprecipitation buffer and incubated at 4 °C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Finally, the RNA was purified and quantified by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Input controls and normal rabbit IgG controls were assayed simultaneously to ensure that the signals were detected from RNA that was specifically bound to protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>RNA pulldown assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Biotin-labeled RNA uc.134 was transcribed in vitro with the Biotin RNA Labeling Mix (Roche) and T7 RNA polymerase (Roche) and then treated with RNase-free DNase I (Roche) and 0.2 M EDTA to stop the reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Biotinylated RNAs were mixed with streptavidin agarose beads (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD) at 4 °C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Total cell lysates and RNase inhibitor were added to each binding reaction and incubated on ice for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The RNA–protein binding mixture was boiled in SDS buffer, and the eluted proteins were detected by Western blotting or mass spectrometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The full-length transcript of uc.134 is 1867 bp in length; Δ1, Δ2, and Δ3 correspond to the 1–718 bp, 719–1407 bp, and 1408–1867 bp sequence fragments of uc.134 until the end of the uc.134 sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>CUL4A was cloned into the eukaryotic expression vector pcDNA3.1(+) with a C-terminal Myc tag and translated a 87.7-kilodalton (kDa) protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>CUL4A lacking the 55–401 amino acid (aa) region was cloned into pcDNA3.1(+) to afford the pcDNA3.1(+)-Cul4a-△1-myc construct, which translated a 46.94-kDa protein; CUL4A lacking the 400–671 aa region encoding a cullin homolog was cloned into pcDNA3.1(+) to afford the pcDNA3.1(+)-Cul4a-△2-myc construct, which translated a 56.53-kDa protein; CUL4A lacking the 688~753 aa region, which encodes a neddylation domain, was cloned into pcDNA3.1(+) to afford the pcDNA3.1(+)-Cul4a-△3-myc construct, which translated a 79.81-kDa protein; CUL4A lacking the 592–759 aa region, which encodes the winged helix-turn-helix DNA-binding domain (WHDD), was cloned into pcDNA3.1(+) to afford the pcDNA3.1(+)-Cul4a-△4-myc vector, which translated a 68.03-kDa protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Cycloheximide (CHX) chase measurements of LATS1 half-life </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The CUL4A and uc.134 plasmids were transiently transfected into HCC cells using jetPRIME (Polyplus, Strasbourg, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>After 24 h, CHX (10 ug/ml) was added to the DMEM culture medium, and incubation was continued for 0, 3, 6, or 9 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The cell lysates were submitted to Western blotting using rabbit anti-LATS1 monoclonal antibody (Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA), and Western blot data were quantified using the ImageJ software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitation (IP) and ubiquitination assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Ubiquitin, LATS1, and uc.134 plasmids were transfected into cells using jetPRIME (Polyplus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Thirty-six hours after transfection, 10 nM MG132 was added to the DMEM culture medium and incubation was continued for 8 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The lysates were immunoprecipitated with the indicated antibodies on protein A/G beads (Life Technologies) overnight at 4 °C with rotation and then boiled in SDS buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The eluted proteins were detected by Western blotting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using the SPSS software (Chicago, IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Survival curves were plotted based on the Kaplan–Meier and log-rank tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Pearson’s chi-square test was used to analyze the relationship between uc.134 expression and the clinicopathologic features of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Student’s t test was used to detect significance differences in data obtained from qRT-PCR experiments and colony formation assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A multi-way classification analysis of variance test was performed to assess data obtained from the CCK8 assays and tumor growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Correlations among uc.134 expression, LATS1, and pYAPS127 were analyzed with a Spearman rank correlation. P &lt; 0.05 was considered to indicate a significant difference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Decreased lncRNA uc.134 expression in HCC patients significantly correlates with poor survival </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that lncRNA expression profiles are significantly altered in HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The authors of a previous study reported that they isolated a parent human HCC cell line MHCC97 and its two derived cell lines with different metastatic potentials (MHCC97-L, with low metastatic potential, and MHCC97-H, with high metastatic potential) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>MHCC97-H was inoculated subcutaneously into nude mice, and the HCCLM3 cell line was established from lung metastasis in the mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>These HCC cell lines have the same genetic background and yet have dramatically different metastatic behavior [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>To identify HCC metastasis-relevant lncRNAs, we compared the expression profiles of lncRNAs between the highly aggressive cell line HCCLM3 and the weakly aggressive cell line MHCC97L using human lncRNAs microarray (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A total of 1050 upregulated lncRNAs and 611 downregulated lncRNAs with significantly differential expression (≥3.0-fold) were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>To validate our findings from the microarray analysis, the top four upregulated and three downregulated known/novel lncRNAs were detected using qRT-PCR in HCC cell lines and the immortalized hepatocyte cell line LO2 and the results demonstrated significant differential expression trends similar to those predicted by the microarray (Additional file 5: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Among these lncRNAs, the ultraconserved noncoding RNA uc.134 whose transcript is located in the intron region of the RSRC1 gene (Fig. 1b) exhibited the greatest downregulation in both tissue samples and HCC cell lines (Fig. 1d, e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>We used 5′- and 3′-RACE analyses to identify a 1867-bp full-length transcript of uc.134 (Fig. 1c, Additional file 5: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>By analysis of cytoplasmic and nuclear RNA fractionation and FISH experiments from HCC cells, we observed that the expression of uc.134 was relatively high in the nucleus (Fig. 1f, Additional file 5: Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>ISH analysis was used to determine expression of uc.134 in 170 paraffin-embedded surgical specimens of HCC from Nanfang Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The expression of uc.134 was significantly downregulated in the tumor tissues compared with the adjacent tissues (P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 1g, Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Forty-nine of tumor tissues (28.8%) exhibited a high expression of uc.134, and the other 121 cases (71.2%) had low expression and the Kaplan–Meier analysis indicated that the lower uc.134 expression was related to poor overall survival in patients with HCC (P &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The median survival time of the HCC patients with low uc.134 expression was 10 months, which was significantly shorter than the survival time of those with high uc.134 expression (20 months) (Fig. 1h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Moreover, an analysis of the clinical follow-up data combined with clinicopathologic parameters demonstrated that the expression of uc.134 significantly correlated with lymph node metastasis (P = 0.005) and tumor node metastasis (TNM) classification (P &lt; 0.001) of patients with HCC (Table 1).Fig. 1Aberrant expression of lncRNA uc.134 in HCC. a Hierarchical clustering analysis of lncRNAs differentially expressed in HCCLM3 and MHCC97L HCC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Upregulated genes are highlighted in yellow, and downregulated genes are in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(fold changes &gt;5; P &lt; 0.05). b Transcript of uc.134. c PCR products from the 5′-RACE and 3′-RACE procedures as shown by agarose gel electrophoresis. d–e The expression of uc.134 was analyzed by qRT-PCR in HCC tissues and HCC cells. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; and ***P &lt; 0.001. f qRT-PCR analysis of RNAs purified from nuclear (red) and cytosolic (black) compartments in Bel7402 cells. ***P &lt; 0.001. g ISH assays of uc.134 expression in HCC paraffin specimens and adjacent nontumor tissues. ***P &lt; 0.001. h The Kaplan–Meier method was used to assess the survival of patients with HCC, and the log-rank test was used to compare survival between the uc.134-low and lncRNAuc.134-high groups (n = 170) Table 1Relationship between lncRNA uc.134 expression and the clinical characteristics of HCC patientslncRNA uc.134 expressionFeatures n LowHigh x 2  P valueAll cases17012149Age0.1690.412 &lt;50564115 ≥501148034Gender0.3320.377 Man14510243 Female25196Histological grade2.4880.288 Well1385 Moderately795326 Poorly786018HBsAg status0.0010.566 Negative483414 Positive1198435Serum AFP (ng/ml)3.8850.037 &lt;25674225 ≥251037924Tumor size (cm)0.0420.487 &lt;51138132 ≥5574017Tumor number4.0440.032 Single1459946 Multiple25223Lymph node metastasis6.8510.005 Negative1399346 Positive26242TNM stage51.3930.000 I and II672740 III and IV103949 P value &lt;0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The P values were calculated in SPSS 17.0 using Pearson’s chi-square test </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134 inhibits HCC cell proliferation, invasion, and metastasis in vitro and in vivo </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>To investigate the biological significance of uc.134 in the progression of HCC, we performed gain-of-function and loss-of-function studies in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The results of CCK8 proliferation assays and colony formation assays showed that the stable overexpression of EGFP-LV-uc.134 (Additional file 5: Figure S4A) significantly reduced the proliferative capacity of HCC cells and that cells overexpressing uc.134 formed fewer colonies than control cell lines containing the empty vector (Fig. 2a, b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Transwell and scratch wound-healing assays showed that the upregulation of uc.134 markedly reduced cell invasion compared with control cells (Fig. 2c, d), whereas the knockdown of uc.134 by EGFP-LV-shRNA (Additional file 5: Figure S4B) promoted HCC cell growth and invasion (Additional file 5: Figure S5A–S5D).Fig. 2LncRNA uc.134 suppresses the proliferation, migration, and invasion of HCC in vitro and in vivo. a Growth curves of indicated HCC cells that overexpressed uc.134 compared with those of negative control cells and untransfected cells were determined with a CCK8 proliferation analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The mean ± SD is shown for five independent experiments. ***P &lt; 0.001. b Representative images of colony formation assays (left panels); analysis of the number of colonies (right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. c Invasion ability of the indicated cell lines by Transwell assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. d Representative images of the scratch wound-healing assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The wound-healing percentage was analyzed with the ImageJ software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.001. e Representative images of tumors formed in nude mice (n = 6). *P &lt; 0.05. f Lung metastasis model generated by injecting tumor cells into the tail veins of mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>HE staining showing the number and volume of lung metastases in each group (n = 6); **P &lt; 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>01 and ***P &lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>For in vivo studies, we generated a xenograft tumor model by subcutaneously injecting HCC cells in which uc.134 was stably overexpressed or knocked down into the flanks of nude mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The overexpression of uc.134 markedly decreased the tumor growth rate and mean tumor volume compared with the negative control group (Fig. 2e), whereas silencing uc.134 produced the opposite results (Additional file 5: Figure S5E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Moreover, ISH, IHC, and hematoxylin-eosin (HE) staining were performed on paraffin-embedded samples of xenograft tumors formed by cells overexpressing EGFP-LV-uc.134 or EGFP-LV-shRNA and the negative control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The results showed that in the xenograft tumors overexpressing uc.134, the level of KI67 expression was lower than that in the negative control, whereas in the uc.134 silenced tumors, the level of KI67 expression was higher (Additional file 5: Figure S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We further generated a tail vein xenograft tumor model by injecting the indicated cells into the tail veins of nude mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>At the end of the experiment, the lungs of the mice were removed for HE staining to histologically examine lung metastases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134-overexpressing cells showed reduced lung colonization ability compared with controls, whereas the knockdown of uc.134 produced the opposite results (Fig. 2f, Additional file 5: Figure S5F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Briefly, our studies confirmed that uc.134 can inhibit HCC cell proliferation and invasion, whereas uc.134 knockdown promotes HCC growth and metastasis, suggesting that lncRNA uc.134 may have a critical role in suppressing the development of HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Association of lncRNA uc.134 with CUL4A </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Recently, several studies have focused on the molecular regulation networks between lncRNAs and proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>To explore the molecular mechanisms of uc.134 in HCC progression, we performed RNA pulldown assays to identify proteins associated with uc.134. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>After 10% SDS polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and silver staining, the differentially expressed bands were identified by comparison with the antisense control and excised and subjected to mass spectrometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>An analysis of RNA-associated proteins in three independent RNA pulldown assays followed by mass spectrometry detected the E3 ubiquitin ligase CUL4A, and subsequent Western blot analyses confirmed these results (Fig. 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We also performed RIP to verify the candidate proteins pulled down with uc.134 using antibodies against CUL4A, and a nonspecific antibody (IgG) was used as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The data showed that CUL4A directly bound to uc.134 (Fig. 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results confirmed that uc.134 and CUL4A can form an RNP complex in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that lncRNAs can function as unstructured sequences and the functions of these RNAs may depend more on their linear sequences than their conserved secondary structures [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>To identify the unique binding sites, we took advantage of a series of deletion mutants of uc.134 to map the CUL4A-binding region: Δ1 corresponds to the region between nucleotides 1–718 of uc.134, which is the truncated 5′ end; Δ2 corresponds to the region between nucleotides 719–1407; and Δ3 corresponds to the region between nucleotides 1408–1867 of uc.134, which is the truncated 3′ end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The results from in vitro binding assays indicated that CUL4A interacted with a 460-nt region at the 3′ end of uc.134 (Δ3-1408–1867) (Fig. 3c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Protein domain mapping studies demonstrated that uc.134 binds the 592–759 amino acid (aa) region of CUL4A (Fig. 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The 592–759 aa region of CUL4A encodes a domain known as the winged helix-turn-helix DNA-binding domain (WHDD), which has been suggested to bind DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This suggestion is consistent with our observation that the WHDD of CUL4A may serve as the RNA-binding domain for uc.134. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results demonstrate that uc.134 directly interacts with CUL4A to form uc.134-CUL4A RNPs.Fig. 3LncRNA uc.134 binds CUL4A and inhibits CUL4A nuclear export. a LncRNA uc.134-associated proteins identified by RNA pulldown and mass spectrometric analyses in HEK293T cells (upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis of pulldown product (bottom panel). b RIP assays in HEK293T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>qRT-PCR analysis of RIP (upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Agarose electrophoresis of PCR products (bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Experiments were performed in triplicate, and data are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. c Immunoblot (IB) detection of CUL4A retrieved by in vitro transcribed biotinylated RNAs corresponding to different fragments of uc.134 or its antisense sequence (dotted line) in HEK293T cells. d IB detection of Myc-tagged CUL4A (WT versus domain truncation mutants) precipitated by in vitro transcribed biotinylated uc.134 in HEK293T cells. Upper panel: graphic illustration of the domain structure of CUL4A. e–f LncRNA uc.134 inhibits CUL4A nuclear export as demonstrated by immunofluorescence staining (e) and Western blotting (f) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>CUL4A is amplified in various cancers, which suggests its role in regulating cell cycle progression, transcription, and embryonic development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>At present, numerous proteins have been reported to be ubiquitinated by CUL4A including p53, p21, p27, DICER, and LATS1 [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that inflammation-induced Jak-STAT3 signaling triggers the ubiquitination of DICER1 in cytoplasm by CUL4A to promote the development of colon cancer [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Although CUL4A is predominantly located in the cytoplasm, a fraction of CUL4A protein resides in the nucleus and mediates nucleosome reassembly [34–36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Thus, we performed Western blotting and immunofluorescence analyses to investigate the mechanism by which uc.134 regulates CUL4A expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The knockdown or upregulation of uc.134 did not change total CUL4A protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, an analysis of immunofluorescence staining suggested that CUL4A protein accumulated in the nucleus when uc.134 was overexpressed, whereas uc.134 knockdown arrested CUL4A protein in the cytoplasm (Fig. 3e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The cytoplasmic and nuclear protein fractions from HCC cells revealed the same phenomenon (Fig. 3f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134 inhibits the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 to regulate Hippo kinase signaling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The data from the mRNA microarray and GO analyses showed that the overexpression of uc.134 significantly repressed ubiquitin protein ligase and RNA polymerase activity compared with the negative control (Fig. 4a, b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Previous studies showed that the Hippo pathway core component LATS1 contains an N-terminal ubiquitin-binding domain that can bind in cis or trans to C-terminal ubiquitinated sequences, inducing conformational changes that disturb kinase activity [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Since CUL4A is an E3 ligase that targets LATS1 protein for ubiquitination and degradation, we performed an immunoprecipitation assay using either anti-LATS1 antibody or anti-CUL4A antibody to precipitate CUL4A or LATS1, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The results confirmed the interaction between endogenous LATS1 and CUL4A protein in HCC cells (Fig. 4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Although a large number of studies demonstrate that LATS1 plays essential roles in the Hippo pathway, which suppresses tumorigenesis and stem cell differentiation, the association between LATS1 and lncRNA molecular regulators remains largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Thus, we also performed a CHX chase assay to assess the ability of uc.134 to enhance LATS1 protein stability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The results showed that LATS1 protein was much more stable in cells transfected with both CUL4A and uc.134 compared with cells transfected with CUL4A alone (Fig. 4d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>We subsequently performed a ubiquitination assay, which showed a significant decrease in polyubiquitinated LATS1 protein in uc.134-transfected cells, whereas the knockdown of uc.134 increased LATS1 ubiquitination (Fig. 4e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Previous studies indicated that polyubiquitylation promotes LATS1 protein degradation and blocks its kinase activity to phosphorylate YAP [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we performed a Western blot analysis, which showed that uc.134 overexpression reversed the CUL4A-mediated decrease in LATS1 expression and inactivation of Hippo kinase signaling (Fig. 4f).Fig. 4LncRNA uc.134 inhibits the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 to regulate Hippo kinase signaling. a–b Hierarchical clustering analysis (a) and GO analysis (b) of microarray data for HCC cells overexpressing uc.134 and control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Upregulated genes are highlighted in yellow, and downregulated genes are in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(fold changes &gt;3; P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The top ten most significantly enriched GO terms in differentially expressed genes relative to all other genes in the genome are shown. c IP experiment. d The overexpression of uc.134 prolonged the half-life of LATS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Immunoblot detection of LATS1 (left); IB data were quantified using the ImageJ software (right). Error bars indicate the mean ± SD. **P &lt; 0.01. e Ubiquitination assays of cells transfected with uc.134 plasmid in Bel7402 cells (left) or siRNA in QGY7701 cells (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The bottom panels depict the input of the cell lysates. f Western blotting in Bel7402 cells showed that uc.134 reversed the CUL4A-mediated inhibition of Hippo kinase activity. g Western blots showed that the overexpression of uc.134 activates Hippo kinase signaling (left), whereas silencing of uc.134 yielded opposite results (right). h qRT-PCR analysis of cells overexpressing uc.134 or co-transfected with YAP plasmids compared with vector controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Experiments were performed in triplicate, and data are presented as the mean ± SD. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; and ***P &lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, microarray analysis and qRT-PCR indicated that the overexpression of uc.134 did not significantly affect the mRNA levels of members of the Hippo signaling pathway, such as Mob1, MST1/2, LATS1, and YAP, whereas the mRNA levels of YAP target genes, such as cysteine-rich angiogenic inducer 61 (CYR61), c-Myc, drosophila inhibitor of apoptosis 1 (diap1), and E2F1, were significantly reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>In addition, we have performed the rescue experiment to test whether the uc.134-mediated changes in the tumorigenesis genes are dependent on YAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The Bel7402 cells were transfected with the uc.134 overexpressing plasmid alone or together with the YAP overexpressing plasmid for 48 h, and the expression of target genes was evaluated by qRT-qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The results showed that there was no reduction in the expression of CYR61, c-Myc, diap1, and E2F1 induced by uc.134 overexpression in the YAP-upregulated cells, indicating that YAP is responsible for the uc.134-mediated gene regulation (Fig. 4h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a Western blot analysis demonstrated that the overexpression of uc.134 upregulated LATS1 protein expression and YAP phosphorylation at Ser127 but had no effect on other critical proteins of the Hippo kinase signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the LATS1 and pYAPS127 levels were decreased in specimens in which uc.134 expression was silenced, indicating that LATS1 and pYAPS127 are downstream effectors of uc.134 (Fig. 4g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these studies suggest that lncRNA uc.134 inhibits CUL4A translocation from the nucleus to the cytoplasm to disrupt polyubiquitin chains, which activates the Hippo kinase signaling and silences target genes of YAP by increasing the stability of LATS1 protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134 represses HCC proliferation and metastasis via the uc.134-CUL4A-Hippo axis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>A Western blot analysis demonstrated that the overexpression of uc.134 upregulated LATS1 protein expression and YAP phosphorylation at Ser127, indicating that LATS1 and pYAPS127 are downstream effectors of uc.134. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We then assessed the ability of CUL4A to overcome the uc.134-mediated activation of Hippo kinase signaling in HCC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Notably, Western blotting showed that the overexpression of CUL4A inhibited the uc.134-mediated increases in LATS1 and YAPS127 phosphorylation, whereas the knockdown of CUL4A reversed the si-uc.134-mediated repression of LATS1 and inactivation of Hippo kinase signaling (Fig. 5a, Additional file 5: Figure S4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The biological function analysis showed that CUL4A overexpression abrogated the uc.134-mediated repression HCC cell proliferation and invasion, whereas CUL4A knockdown yielded the opposite results (Fig. 5b, c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data demonstrate that lncRNA uc.134 plays a key role in suppressing the proliferation, invasion, and metastasis of HCC by blocking CUL4A nuclear export to ubiquitinate LATS1 and increasing YAPS127 phosphorylation, which implicates the lncRNA uc.134-CUL4A-Hippo axis as a potential therapeutic target for the treatment of HCC.Fig. 5LncRNA uc.134 represses HCC proliferation and metastasis via the uc.134-CUL4A-Hippo axis. a Western blot showing that CUL4A abrogated the uc.134-mediated activation of Hippo kinase signaling (left), whereas the knockdown of CUL4A reversed the si-uc.134-mediated repression of LATS1 and inactivation of YAP (right). b A Transwell analysis showed that CUL4A overexpression abrogated the uc.134-mediated repression of HCC cell invasion (upper), whereas CUL4A knockdown yielded the opposite results (lower). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. c A CCK8 proliferation analysis showed that the transfection of CUL4A plasmid or LATS1-specific siRNA abolished the uc.134-mediated growth inhibition (left), whereas the transfection of siCUL4A or LATS1 plasmid yielded opposite results (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The mean ± SD is shown for five independent experiments. **P &lt; 0.01; and ***P &lt; 0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>LncRNA uc.134 expression positively correlates with LATS1 and pYAPS127 levels in HCC patient samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We studied correlations among uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 expression by ISH and IHC in paraffin-embedded samples from patients with HCC (Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>IHC analysis was used to determine the expression of LATS1 or pYAPS127 in 90 paraffin-embedded surgical specimens of HCC from Nanfang Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The expression of LATS1 was significantly downregulated in the tumor tissues compared with the adjacent tissues (P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 6a, Additional file 5: Figure S7A), and the Kaplan–Meier analysis indicated that the lower LATS1 expression was related to poor overall survival in patients with HCC (P = 0.032). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The median survival time of the HCC patients with low LATS1 expression was 16 months, which was significantly shorter than those with high LATS1 expression (49 months) (Additional file 5: Figure S7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In addition, the expression of pYAPS127 was also significantly downregulated in the tumors compared with the adjacent tissues (P &lt; 0.01) (Fig. 6a, Additional file 5: Figure S7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>By the Kaplan–Meier analysis, it was observed that the low pYAPS127 protein level was a significant prognostic factor for poor overall survival in patients with HCC (P = 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The median survival time of the HCC patients with low pYAPS127 expression was 16 months, which was significantly shorter than those with high pYAPS127 expression (50 months) (Additional file 5: Figure S7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Together, these results clearly show that the expressions of LATS1 and pYAPS127 are reduced in the HCC tissues compared with the adjacent tissues, and low LATS1 or pYAPS127 expression is associated with worse prognosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In addition, correlations among the expression of uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 were analyzed with a Spearman’s rank correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The scatter plot showed positive relationships among uc.134, LATS1 (r 2 = 0.509; P &lt; 0.001), and pYAPS127 (r 2 = 0.435; P &lt; 0.001) and a positive relationship between LATS1 and pYAPS127 (r 2 = 0.614; P &lt; 0.001) in 90 HCC specimens (Fig. 6b–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Collectively, our data indicate that a 460-nt region of uc.134 (Δ3-1408–1867) binds to the WHDD (592–759 aa region) domain of CUL4A to inhibit CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1 and activate Hippo kinase signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Thus, the lncRNA uc.134-CUL4A-Hippo axis may offer a promising approach for the treatment of HCC (Fig. 6e).Fig. 6Expression levels of lncRNA uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 positively correlated in samples from patients with HCC. a The ISH and IHC staining of HCC paraffin-embedded samples showed that the expression levels of uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 were significantly downregulated in HCC (200× magnification, n = 90). b–d A scatter diagram showed positive correlations among uc.134 and LATS1 or pYAPS127. e A model for the regulatory mechanisms of uc.134 in HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>HCC is a leading cause of cancer-related death worldwide, and tumor recurrence and metastasis are major factors that contribute to the poor prognosis of patients with HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Moreover, recent research has greatly advanced our understanding of the essential role of lncRNAs in HCC [10, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Although thousands of lncRNAs have been functionally characterized, the vast majority of members of this RNA class have not been thoroughly described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>UcRNAs are noncoding RNAs transcribed from regions that are highly conserved across humans, mice, and rats, so-called ultraconserved regions (UCRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>UCRs are usually located at genomic regions that are involved in cancer and differentially expressed in carcinomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Here, we used lncRNA microarrays to identify that the expression of an ultraconserved lncRNA, uc.134, was significantly decreased in the highly aggressive HCC cell line HCCLM3 compared with MHCC97L cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>We first confirmed the full-length transcript of uc.134 using 5′- and 3′-RACE analyses, and qRT-PCR showed that uc.134 expression was reduced in both tissue samples and HCC cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Thus, the decreased expression of uc.134 in HCC, especially in highly aggressive cell lines, indicates that uc.134 may be a promising marker for HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>ISH results showed that the expression of uc.134 was significantly downregulated in 170 paraffin-embedded HCC specimens and decreased uc.134 expression was related to poor survival in patients with HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Moreover, an analysis of clinical follow-up data and clinicopathologic parameters demonstrated that the expression of uc.134 significantly correlated with lymph node metastasis (P = 0.005) and TNM classification (P &lt; 0.001) in patients with HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Cancer is fundamentally a genetic disease with numerous alterations in DNA, RNA, and proteins that support tumor growth and development [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The molecular and cellular characteristics of cancer-associated lncRNAs are under distinct regulatory regimes that are different from physiological conditions [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Although numerous studies have used gene overexpression plasmids or lentiviral vectors to evaluate the functions of tumor-suppressor genes, the cellular toxicities of these gene carriers are inevitable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a knockdown model such as RNAi is necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In our study, we performed gain-of-function and loss-of-function studies both in vitro and in vivo to demonstrate that uc.134 plays a critical role in the inhibition of cell proliferation, invasion, and metastasis in HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Ideally, Tet-Off and Tet-On systems will fulfill the requirements for the quantitative and temporal control of gene expression via nontoxic effector molecules, and these will be used in the future [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>A growing number of studies confirm that the Hippo kinase signaling, which is critical for tumor progression and invasion, is inactivated in many cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The core components of Hippo kinase signaling pathway are conserved in mammals and have a complex network of crosstalk with other important signaling pathways, such as the TGFβ/SMAD, WNT/β-catenin, PI3-kinase/AKT, Hedgehog, Jak/Stat, and Notch pathways [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>A previous study confirmed that YAP increases resistance to RAF- and MEK-targeted cancer therapies [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the serine/threonine kinase LATS1 is a core kinase of Hippo kinase signaling pathway and plays important roles in tumor proliferation, apoptosis, and stem cell differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>A previous study showed that Merlin activates Hippo kinase signaling by inhibiting CRL4DCAF1, an E3 ubiquitin ligase of the CRL4 complex [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>CUL4A is a core component of the CRL4 complex, and its N-terminus associates with a cullin-specific adaptor protein to recruit a large number of substrate proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>CUL4A can interact with LATS1 protein and enhance its proteasomal degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Another study demonstrated that the de-repression of CRL4DCAF1 inhibited the activation of the Hippo pathway by directly binding to and ubiquitinating LATS1/2 in NF2-mutant tumors in the nucleus [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>However, the mechanism that regulates LATS1 at the lncRNA level remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>We performed RNA pulldown and RIP assays, which showed that uc.134 bound the E3 ligase CUL4A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Protein domain mapping and deletion mutation analyses identified a 592–759 aa region of CUL4A, which encodes a WHDD domain, that binds a 460-nt region at the 3′ end of uc.134 (Δ3-1408–1867). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>In addition, we demonstrated that uc.134 inhibited the translocation of CUL4A from the nucleus to the cytoplasm, which inhibits the CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination and degradation of LATS1 in the cytoplasm and increases YAPS127 phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>LncRNAs regulate many important activities in cancer through their interactions with DNA, RNA, and proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms through which lncRNAs interact with proteins to regulate protein-protein interactions or modulate the subcellular transport of proteins are largely unknown [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>It remains to be investigated whether the uc.134-CUL4A RNP can be retained in the nucleus through binding with other nuclear proteins or by forming an RNA–DNA triplex. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>As a co-activator of transcription, YAP binds to the TEAD complex and elevates the levels of numerous target genes to promote tumor proliferation and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>CYR61 is overexpressed in various cancers and has been reported to be involved in tumor growth and vascularization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Previous reports showed that the YAP-dependent expression of CYR61 increased the invasive activity of the glioblastoma cells [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Inactivation of c-Myc results in tumor dormancy and pluripotent differentiation of tumor cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>YAP has been reported to promote the transcriptional activity of c-Myc via interaction with c-Abl in HCC [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>diap1 directly binds to and inhibits caspases to suppress apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Activation of YAP increased the transcription of diap1, cell proliferation, and tissue overgrowth [46, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>A previous study has shown that Yorkie promotes the overgrowth of drosophila neuroepithelial cells and delays their differentiation through the regulation of the cell cycle regulator E2F1, which plays key roles in cell cycle progression and cell differentiation in HCC [48, 49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We performed microarray analysis and qRT-PCR indicated that overexpression of uc.134 significantly decreased the expression of YAP target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>In addition, when we co-transfected the HCC cells with plasmids expressing YAP and those expressing uc.134, the decrease in the mRNA level of CYR61, c-Myc, diap1, and E2F1 was reversed by YAP, indicating that YAP is responsible for the uc.134-mediated gene regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Finally, a positive correlation between uc.134, LATS1, and pYAPS127 was confirmed in 90 paraffin-embedded samples by ISH and IHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our results suggest that uc.134 increased Hippo kinase activity and repressed the downstream target genes of YAP by inhibiting CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination and degradation of LATS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to investigate the critical role of lncRNAs in the regulation of LATS1 in HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Thus, this lncRNA may offer a promising approach for HCC therapy by inhibiting YAP and activating Hippo kinase signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have clarified that the major risk factor for HCC in China is hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection, although hepatitis C virus infection and exposure to toxic chemical substances also contribute to the incidence of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The lncRNA MEG3 is regulated by miR-29a in a methylation-dependent, tissue-specific manner, and it contributes to the growth of HCC [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3) is involved in the suppression of HCC-related lncRNA-LET [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The aberrant expression of lncRNA uc.134 in HCC may be mediated by HBV infection at the transcriptional level, post-transcriptional level, or by epigenetic regulations such as DNA methylation or histone deacetylation [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In our study, we report that the ultraconserved lncRNA uc.134 suppressed the progression of HCC by inhibiting CUL4A-mediated ubiquitination of LATS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Hippo kinase signaling is highly conserved among diverse species and regulates tissue overgrowth and development [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The classic tumor suppressor miRNA let-7 is also conserved among species and promotes cell cycle exit and cell differentiation both during normal development and in cancer [52, 53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="?"><plain>However, does uc.134 have a similar developmental expression pattern as the miRNA let-7? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>It will be interesting to unravel the underlying mechanisms that control the expression of uc.134 in both cancer and normal development in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data indicated that the expression of a novel lncRNA, uc.134, was repressed in HCC specimens and the expression of uc.134 was significantly correlated with the overall survival of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Notably, our results showed that the overexpression of uc.134 suppressed HCC cell proliferation, invasion, and metastasis in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>In addition, we demonstrated that uc.134 plays a crucial role in activating Hippo kinase signaling by inhibiting CUL4A ubiquitination of LATS1 and increasing YAPS127 phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we confirmed that uc.134 repressed the downstream target genes of YAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Finally, ISH and IHC showed positive relationships among uc.134, LAST1, and pYAPS127 in 90 paraffin-embedded samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Consequently, these results identified that lncRNA uc.134 activates Hippo kinase signaling by blocking CUL4A, suggesting that it may serve as a tumor suppressor and prognostic biomarker in HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Additional files </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec22"><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1:Supplementary raw data 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>LncRNA expression profiling data analysis by lncRNA microarray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>(XLS 2275 kb) Additional file 2Supplementary raw data 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Differentially mRNA expression profiling by mRNA microarray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 5963 kb) Additional file 3:Supplementary raw data 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>The full GO data of mRNA microarray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>(XLS 336 kb) Additional file 4:Oligonucleotide sequences and primers for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>(PDF 100 kb) Additional file 5: Figure S1.Expression levels of six lncRNAs by qRT-PCR in HCC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>(A) nc-HOXA11-86 (B) ENST00000426547 (C) ENST00000442971 (D) NR_027250 (E) ENST00000400856 (F) ENST00000394079. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; and ***P &lt; 0.001. Figure S2. Full-length of human lncRNA uc.134 gene cloning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>(A) The sequencing of PCR products from the 5′-RACE and 3′-RACE procedures showed the boundary between the universal anchor primer and lncRNA uc.134 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>(B) Nucleotide sequence of the full-length human lncRNA uc.134 gene. Figure S3. Representative images of FISH detecting endogenous lncRNA uc.134 molecules (green) in HCC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Nucleus (blue) was stained with DAPI. Figure S4. Transfection efficiency in HCC cells was assessed by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, and ***P &lt; 0.001. Figure S5. Knockdown of uc.134 promotes the progression and invasion of HCC in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>(A) Growth curves of HCC cells generated by CCK8 proliferation analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>The mean ± SD is shown for five independent experiments. ***P &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>(B) The colony formation assays (left panels); analysis of the number of colonies (right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(C) Transwell assay for the indicated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>(D) Representative images of the scratch wound-healing assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in triplicate, and results are presented as mean ± SD. ***P &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>(E) Tumors formed by cells transfected with EGFP-LV-shRNA targeting uc.134 were markedly larger and grew faster than tumors formed by control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>(n = 5) *P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>(F) Lung metastasis model generated by injecting cancer cells into the tail veins of mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>HE staining shows the number and volume of lung metastases in each group (n = 6) **P &lt; 0.01. Figure S6. The histologic examination of tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Upper panels: ISH staining, middle panels: KI67 staining, lower panels: HE staining. Figure S7. LATS1 and pYAPS127 expression levels in HCC specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>(A, B) IHC analysis in 90 primary clinical specimens showed that the expression levels of LATS1 and pYAPS127 were significantly depressed in tumors compared with adjacent tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>(C, D) Lower expression levels of LATS1 and pYAPS127 were related to the poor survival of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>(PDF 5721 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CHX</term><def><p>Cycloheximide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCC</term><def><p>Hepatocellular carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ISH</term><def><p>In situ hybridization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>lncRNAs</term><def><p>Long noncoding RNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p>Mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RACE</term><def><p>Rapid amplification of complementary DNA ends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIP</term><def><p>RNA-binding protein immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHDD</term><def><p>Winged helix-turn-helix DNA-binding domain</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to all laboratory members of the Department of Pathology of Southern Medical University for their support and comments.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Pearl River Nova Program of Guangzhou, Guangdong Province (Grant No. 2014J2200015); Guangdong Natural Science Funds for Distinguished Young Scholar (Grant No. 2015A030306015); Excellent Young Teachers Program of Higher Education of Guangdong Province (Grant No. YQ2015036); and Guangdong Program for Support of Top-notch Young Professionals (Grant No. 2015TQ01R279).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materialS</title><p>All authors ensure that all data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article (and its supplementary information files).</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>WN and YD designed the study. LHC and YD supervised the study. WN, YQZ, ZTZ, and FY jointly performed the experiments. JH contributed to the clinical sample collection and pathological analysis. YHL contributed to immunohistochemistry analysis. KLC helped with the animal study. WN, LHC, and YD analyzed and interpreted the data and drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Consent to publish has been obtained from all participants.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>This study was approved by the Nanfang Hospital Institutional Ethical Review Board and informed consent was obtained from each patient. All animal studies were performed with the approval from the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Nanfang Hospital.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>1.SiegelRLMillerKDJemalACancer statistics, 2016CA Cancer J Clin201666173010.3322/caac.21332<?supplied-pmid 26742998?>26742998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>2.ChenWZhengRBaadePDZhangSZengHBrayFJemalAYuXQHeJCancer statistics in China, 2015CA Cancer J Clin20166621153210.3322/caac.21338<?supplied-pmid 26808342?>26808342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>3.LlovetJMBustamanteJCastellsAVilanaRAyusoMDCSalaMBrúCRodésJBruixJNatural history of untreated nonsurgical hepatocellular carcinoma: rationale for the design and evaluation of therapeutic trialsHepatology199929162710.1002/hep.510290145<?supplied-pmid 9862851?>9862851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>4.BruixJBoixLSalaMLlovetJMFocus on hepatocellular carcinomaCancer Cell200453215910.1016/S1535-6108(04)00058-3<?supplied-pmid 15050913?>15050913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>5.MercerTRDingerMEMattickJSLong non-coding RNAs: insights into functionsNat Rev Genet2009103155910.1038/nrg2521<?supplied-pmid 19188922?>19188922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>6.PontingCPOliverPLReikWEvolution and functions of long noncoding RNAsCell200913646294110.1016/j.cell.2009.02.006<?supplied-pmid 19239885?>19239885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>7.EstellerMNon-coding RNAs in human diseaseNat Rev Genet201112128617410.1038/nrg3074<?supplied-pmid 22094949?>22094949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>8.IyerMKNiknafsYSMalikRSinghalUSahuAHosonoYBarretteTRPrensnerJREvansJRZhaoSThe landscape of long noncoding RNAs in the human transcriptomeNat Genet201547319920810.1038/ng.3192<?supplied-pmid 25599403?>25599403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>9.WangKCChangHYMolecular mechanisms of long noncoding RNAsMol Cell20114369041410.1016/j.molcel.2011.08.018<?supplied-pmid 21925379?>21925379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>10.GuttmanMRinnJLModular regulatory principles of large non-coding RNAsNature201248273853394610.1038/nature10887<?supplied-pmid 22337053?>22337053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>11.Krol J, Krol I, Alvarez CPP, Fiscella M, Hierlemann A, Roska B, Filipowicz W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>A network comprising short and long noncoding RNAs and RNA helicase controls mouse retina architecture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Nat Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>2015;6:7305. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>12.SchmittAMChangHYLong noncoding RNAs in cancer pathwaysCancer Cell20162944526310.1016/j.ccell.2016.03.010<?supplied-pmid 27070700?>27070700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>13.Li G, Zhang H, Wan X, Yang X, Zhu C, Wang A, He L, Miao R, Chen S, Zhao H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Long noncoding RNA plays a key role in metastasis and prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Biomed Res Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>2014;2014:780521. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>14.LiuY-RTangR-XHuangW-TRenF-HHeR-QYangL-HLuoD-ZDangY-WChenGLong noncoding RNAs in hepatocellular carcinoma: novel insights into their mechanismWorld J Hepatol2015728278110.4254/wjh.v7.i28.2781<?supplied-pmid 26668690?>26668690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>15.Zeisel MB, Baumert TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Translation and protein expression of lncRNAs: impact for liver disease and hepatocellular carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Hepatology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>2016;64(2):671–4. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>16.LinRMaedaSLiuCKarinMEdgingtonTA large noncoding RNA is a marker for murine hepatocellular carcinomas and a spectrum of human carcinomasOncogene2007266851810.1038/sj.onc.1209846<?supplied-pmid 16878148?>16878148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>17.LaiM-cYangZZhouLZhuQ-qXieH-yZhangFWuL-mChenL-mZhengS-sLong non-coding RNA MALAT-1 overexpression predicts tumor recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma after liver transplantationMed Oncol20122931810610.1007/s12032-011-0004-z<?supplied-pmid 21678027?>21678027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>18.CaoCSunJZhangDGuoXXieLLiXWuDLiuLThe long intergenic noncoding RNA UFC1, a target of MicroRNA 34a, interacts with the mRNA stabilizing protein HuR to increase levels of β-catenin in HCC cellsGastroenterology20151482415–426. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>e41810.1053/j.gastro.2014.10.01225449213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>19.YangFHuoX-sYuanS-xZhangLZhouW-pWangFSunS-hRepression of the long noncoding RNA-LET by histone deacetylase 3 contributes to hypoxia-mediated metastasisMol Cell201349610839610.1016/j.molcel.2013.01.010<?supplied-pmid 23395002?>23395002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>20.BraconiCKogureTValeriNHuangNNuovoGCostineanSNegriniMMiottoECroceCPatelTmicroRNA-29 can regulate expression of the long non-coding RNA gene MEG3 in hepatocellular cancerOncogene201130474750610.1038/onc.2011.193<?supplied-pmid 21625215?>21625215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>21.BraconiCValeriNKogureTGaspariniPHuangNNuovoGJTerraccianoLCroceCMPatelTExpression and functional role of a transcribed noncoding RNA with an ultraconserved element in hepatocellular carcinomaProc Natl Acad Sci201110827869110.1073/pnas.1011098108<?supplied-pmid 21187392?>21187392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>22.FengJBiCClarkBSMadyRShahPKohtzJDThe Evf-2 noncoding RNA is transcribed from the Dlx-5/6 ultraconserved region and functions as a Dlx-2 transcriptional coactivatorGenes Dev2006201114708410.1101/gad.1416106<?supplied-pmid 16705037?>16705037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>23.ZhangJSmolenGAHaberDANegative regulation of YAP by LATS1 underscores evolutionary conservation of the drosophila Hippo pathwayCancer Res200868827899410.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-6205<?supplied-pmid 18413746?>18413746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>24.HaoYChunACheungKRashidiBYangXTumor suppressor LATS1 is a negative regulator of oncogene YAPJ Biol Chem20082839549650910.1074/jbc.M709037200<?supplied-pmid 18158288?>18158288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>25.HuangYJYangCKWeiPLHuynhTTWhang-PengJMengTCHsiaoMTzengYMWuATYenYOvatodiolide suppresses colon tumorigenesis and prevents polarization of M2 tumor-associated macrophages through YAP oncogenic pathwaysJ Hematol Oncol20171016010.1186/s13045-017-0421-3<?supplied-pmid 28241877?>28241877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>26.ZenderLSpectorMSXueWFlemmingPCordon-CardoCSilkeJFanS-TLukJMWiglerMHannonGJIdentification and validation of oncogenes in liver cancer using an integrative oncogenomic approachCell2006125712536710.1016/j.cell.2006.05.030<?supplied-pmid 16814713?>16814713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>27.CordenonsiMZanconatoFAzzolinLForcatoMRosatoAFrassonCInuiMMontagnerMParentiARPolettiAThe Hippo transducer TAZ confers cancer stem cell-related traits on breast cancer cellsCell201114747597210.1016/j.cell.2011.09.048<?supplied-pmid 22078877?>22078877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>28.HuangJYeXGuanJChenBLiQZhengXLiuLWangSDingYDingYTiam1 is associated with hepatocellular carcinoma metastasisInt J Cancer201313219010010.1002/ijc.27627<?supplied-pmid 22573407?>22573407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>29.LiYTangZYYeSLLiuYKChenJXueQChenJGaoDMBaoWHEstablishment of cell clones with different metastatic potential from the metastatic hepatocellular carcinoma cell line MHCC97World J Gastroenterol2001756306<?supplied-pmid 11819844?>11819844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>30.TangZYYeSLLiuYKQinLXSunHCYeQHWangLZhouJQiuSJLiYA decade’s studies on metastasis of hepatocellular carcinomaJ Cancer Res Clin Oncol200413041879610.1007/s00432-003-0511-1<?supplied-pmid 14685850?>14685850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>31.RivasEClementsJEddySRA statistical test for conserved RNA structure shows lack of evidence for structure in lncRNAsNat Methods201714145810.1038/nmeth.4066<?supplied-pmid 27819659?>27819659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>32.HannahJZhouPDistinct and overlapping functions of the cullin E3 ligase scaffolding proteins CUL4A and CUL4BGene20155731334510.1016/j.gene.2015.08.064<?supplied-pmid 26344709?>26344709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>33.RenWShenSSunZShuPShenXBuCAiFZhangXTangATianLJak-STAT3 pathway triggers DICER1 for proteasomal degradation by ubiquitin ligase complex of CUL4A(DCAF1) to promote colon cancer developmentCancer Lett201637522092010.1016/j.canlet.2016.02.055<?supplied-pmid 26965998?>26965998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>34.ZhangYMorroneGZhangJChenXLuXMaLMooreMZhouPCUL‐4A stimulates ubiquitylation and degradation of the HOXA9 homeodomain proteinEMBO J2003222260576710.1093/emboj/cdg577<?supplied-pmid 14609952?>14609952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>35.LiuLLeeSZhangJPetersSBHannahJZhangYYinYKoffAMaLZhouPCUL4A abrogation augments DNA damage response and protection against skin carcinogenesisMol Cell20093444516010.1016/j.molcel.2009.04.020<?supplied-pmid 19481525?>19481525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>36.HanJZhangHZhangHWangZZhouHZhangZA Cul4 E3 ubiquitin ligase regulates histone hand-off during nucleosome assemblyCell201315548172910.1016/j.cell.2013.10.014<?supplied-pmid 24209620?>24209620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>37.LiWCooperJZhouLYangCErdjument-BromageHZagzagDSnuderlMLadanyiMHanemannCOZhouPMerlin/NF2 loss-driven tumorigenesis linked to CRL4 DCAF1-mediated inhibition of the Hippo pathway kinases Lats1 and 2 in the nucleusCancer Cell2014261486010.1016/j.ccr.2014.05.001<?supplied-pmid 25026211?>25026211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>38.HanahanDWeinbergRAHallmarks of cancer: the next generationCell201114456467410.1016/j.cell.2011.02.013<?supplied-pmid 21376230?>21376230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>39.DasATZhouXMetzSWVinkMABerkhoutBSelecting the optimal Tet-On system for doxycycline-inducible gene expression in transiently transfected and stably transduced mammalian cellsBiotechnol J201611171910.1002/biot.201500236<?supplied-pmid 26333522?>26333522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>40.MauvielANallet-StaubFVarelasXIntegrating developmental signals: a Hippo in the (path) wayOncogene2012311417435610.1038/onc.2011.363<?supplied-pmid 21874053?>21874053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>41.LinLSabnisAJChanEOlivasVCadeLPazarentzosEAsthanaSNeelDYanJJLuXThe Hippo effector YAP promotes resistance to RAF-and MEK-targeted cancer therapiesNat Genet2015473250610.1038/ng.3218<?supplied-pmid 25665005?>25665005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>42.LiWYouLCooperJSchiavonGPepe-CaprioAZhouLIshiiRGiovanniniMHanemannCOLongSBMerlin/NF2 suppresses tumorigenesis by inhibiting the E3 ubiquitin ligase CRL4 DCAF1 in the nucleusCell201014044779010.1016/j.cell.2010.01.029<?supplied-pmid 20178741?>20178741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>43.ChenLLLinking long noncoding RNA localization and functionTrends Biochem Sci20164197617210.1016/j.tibs.2016.07.003<?supplied-pmid 27499234?>27499234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>44.LeeHHwangSJKimHRShinCHChoiKHJoungJGKimHHNeurofibromatosis 2 (NF2) controls the invasiveness of glioblastoma through YAP-dependent expression of CYR61/CCN1 and miR-296-3pBiochim Biophys Acta20161859459961110.1016/j.bbagrm.2016.02.010<?supplied-pmid 26923924?>26923924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>45.XiaoWWangJOuCZhangYMaLWengWPanQSunFMutual interaction between YAP and c-Myc is critical for carcinogenesis in liver cancerBiochem Biophys Res Commun201343921677210.1016/j.bbrc.2013.08.071<?supplied-pmid 23994632?>23994632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>46.HuangJWuSBarreraJMatthewsKPanDThe Hippo signaling pathway coordinately regulates cell proliferation and apoptosis by inactivating Yorkie, the Drosophila Homolog of YAPCell200512234213410.1016/j.cell.2005.06.007<?supplied-pmid 16096061?>16096061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>47.TaponNHarveyKFBellDWWahrerDCRSchiripoTAHaberDAHariharanIKSalvador promotes both cell cycle exit and apoptosis in drosophila and is mutated in human cancer cell linesCell20021104677810.1016/S0092-8674(02)00824-3<?supplied-pmid 12202036?>12202036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>48.CalvisiDFConnerEALaduSLemmerERFactorVMThorgeirssonSSActivation of the canonical Wnt/beta-catenin pathway confers growth advantages in c-Myc/E2F1 transgenic mouse model of liver cancerJ Hepatol2005426842910.1016/j.jhep.2005.01.029<?supplied-pmid 15885355?>15885355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>49.ReddyBVRauskolbCIrvineKDInfluence of fat-hippo and notch signaling on the proliferation and differentiation of Drosophila optic neuroepitheliaDevelopment201013714239740810.1242/dev.050013<?supplied-pmid 20570939?>20570939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>50.ZhangBHanSFengBChuXChenLWangRHepatitis B virus X protein-mediated non-coding RNA aberrations in the development of human hepatocellular carcinomaExp Mol Med2017492e29310.1038/emm.2016.177<?supplied-pmid 28186085?>28186085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>51.ZengQHongWThe emerging role of the hippo pathway in cell contact inhibition, organ size control, and cancer development in mammalsCancer Cell20081331889210.1016/j.ccr.2008.02.011<?supplied-pmid 18328423?>18328423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>52.BoyerinasBParkSMHauAMurmannAEPeterMEThe role of let-7 in cell differentiation and cancerEndocr Relat Cancer2010171F193610.1677/ERC-09-0184<?supplied-pmid 19779035?>19779035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>53.BussingISlackFJGrosshansHlet-7 microRNAs in development, stem cells and cancerTrends Mol Med2008149400910.1016/j.molmed.2008.07.001<?supplied-pmid 18674967?>18674967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
