<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.4.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art540.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.4.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_YEXER7042 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Exp Eye Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Exp. Eye Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Experimental Eye Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0014-4835</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1096-0007</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5131611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0014-4835(16)30352-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exer.2016.10.014</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>An investigation into corneal enzymatic resistance following epithelium-off and epithelium-on corneal cross-linking protocols </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aldahlawi</surname><given-names>Nada H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>Sally</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brart</surname><given-names>David P.S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brart</surname><given-names>Naomi D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>Keith M.</given-names></name><email>MeekKM@cardiff.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Structural Biophysics Research Group, School of Optometry and Vision Sciences, Cardiff University, Maindy Road, Cardiff, CF24 4HQ, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Keratoconus Research Institute, Department of Ophthalmology, St Thomas Hospital, London, SE1 7EH, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. School of Optometry and Vision Sciences, Cardiff University, Maindy Road, Cathays, Cardiff CF24 4HQ, UK.School of Optometry and Vision SciencesCardiff UniversityMaindy RoadCathaysCardiffCF24 4HQUK <email>MeekKM@cardiff.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>153</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to investigate corneal enzymatic resistance following epithelium off and on riboflavin/UVA cross-linking (CXL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>One hundred and fourteen porcine eyes were divided into four non-irradiated control groups and seven CXL groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The latter comprised; (i) epithelium-off, 0.1% iso-osmolar riboflavin, 9 mW UVA irradiation for 10 min, (ii) disrupted epithelium, 0.1% hypo-osmolar riboflavin, 9 mW UVA for 10 min, (iii) epithelium-on, 0.25% hypo-osmolar riboflavin with 0.01% benzylalkonium chloride (BACS), 9 mW UVA for 10 min, (iv) epithelium-on, 5 min iontophoresis at 0.1 mA for 5 min with 0.1% riboflavin solution, 9 mW UVA for 10 min or (v) 12.5 min, (vi) epithelium-on, prolonged iontophoresis protocol of 25 min with 1.0 mA for 5 min and 0.5 mA for 5 min with 0.25% riboflavin with 0.01% BACS, 9 mW UVA for 10 min or (vii) 12.5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Enzymatic resistance was assessed by daily measurement of a corneal button placed in pepsin solution and measurement of corneal button dry weight after 11 days of digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This study revealed that the enzymatic resistance was greater in CXL corneas than non-irradiated corneas (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Epithelium-off CXL showed the greatest enzymatic resistance (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The prolonged iontophoresis protocol was found to be superior to all other trans-epithelial protocols (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A 25% increase in UVA radiance significantly increased corneal enzymatic resistance (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, although epithelium-on CXL appears to be inferior to epithelium-off CXL in terms of enzymatic resistance to pepsin digestion, the outcome of epithelium-on CXL may be significantly improved through the use of higher concentrations of riboflavin solution, a longer duration of iontophoresis and an increase in UVA radiance. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0015"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Highlights </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>•Epi-off CXL is superior to epi-on CXL in terms of enzymatic resistance.•Epi-on CXL effectiveness can be improved by using a prolonged iontophoresis protocol.•Higher riboflavin concentrations and increased UVA radiance may also enhance epi-on CXL. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Keratoconus</kwd><kwd>Cornea</kwd><kwd>Cross-linking</kwd><kwd>Epithelium-off</kwd><kwd>Epithelium-on</kwd><kwd>CXL</kwd><kwd>Enzymatic digestion</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Over the past decade, riboflavin/UVA corneal cross-linking (CXL) has become an established treatment to halt the progression of keratoconus and other corneal ectasias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Riboflavin is a hydrophilic molecule, with a molecular weight of 340 Da, while, the corneal epithelium is lipophyllic, with a decreasing permeability to molecules over 180 Da (Huang et al., 1989). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Therefore in the “gold-standard” CXL protocol the epithelium is removed from the central corneal to allow adequate stromal absorption of riboflavin prior to UVA irradiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Spoerl et al. confirmed this need for epithelial removal, reporting no changes in corneal biomechanics when CXL was performed with the epithelium intact (Spoerl et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>On this basis, the epithelium was removed in the first published clinical studies (Caporossi et al., 2006, Gkika et al., 2011, O'Brart et al., 2011, Richoz et al., 2013, Wittig-Silva et al., 2014, Wollensak et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, epithelial debridement is associated with a number of adverse events, including severe ocular pain in the immediate post-operative period, delayed visual rehabilitation and the risks of scarring, infectious and non-infectious keratitis (Koller et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>As a result of such considerations, a number of trans-epithelial CXL techniques have been postulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The first epithelium-on CXL (epi-on-CXL) protocols included the use of multiple topical applications of tetracaine 1% to disrupt epithelial tight junctions (Boxer Wachler et al., 2010, Chan et al., 2007) and partial epithelial debridement in a grid pattern (Rechichi et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>More recently, novel formulations of riboflavin have been developed to facilitate epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Laboratory studies have shown that riboflavin preparations in which trometamol (Tris-hydroxymethyl-aminometane) and sodium ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) have been added facilitate stromal absorption when used in conjunction with superficial/grid pattern epithelial trauma (Alhamad et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Similarly, preparations without dextran but with sodium chloride 0.44% and benzalkonium chloride (BAC) have been shown to facilitate trans-epithelial riboflavin stromal absorption (Kissner et al., 2010, Raiskup et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Clinical studies with such formulations have demonstrated equivocal results with some suggesting similar efficacy to epithelium-off CXL (epi-off-CXL) (Filippello et al., 2012, Magli et al., 2013), and others showing less pronounced effects (Buzzonetti and Petrocelli, 2012, Kocak et al., 2014, Koppen et al., 2012, Leccisotti and Islam, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>As riboflavin is negatively charged at physiological pH and soluble in water, iontophoresis as a means of enhancing trans-epithelial absorption has also been postulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In vitro studies of CXL using iontophoresis-assisted delivery (Ion-CXL) of riboflavin 0.1% with a current of 0.5–1 mA for 5–10 min have been encouraging, demonstrating enhanced trans-epithelial riboflavin absorption and corneal tissue biomechanics (Cassagne et al., 2016, Lombardo et al., 2014, Mastropasqua et al., 2014, Touboul et al., 2014, Vinciguerra et al., 2014a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Early clinical studies have reported cessation of progression and improvements in keratometric and visual parameters (Bikbova and Bikbov, 2014, Buzzonetti et al., 2015, Vinciguerra et al., 2014b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In addition to the desire to keep the epithelium intact, the current “gold-standard”, epi-off-CXL protocol, involves a 30 min application of riboflavin followed by a 30 min irradiation with 370 nm UVA light, with an intensity of 3 mW/cm2, necessitating in excess of one hour treatment time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In an attempt to reduce treatment times, the use of accelerated CXL (A-CXL) procedures using the same energy dose but higher UVA intensities and shorter exposure times have been investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Published clinical studies of A-CXL protocols are relatively few. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, those using 7 mW for 15 min or 9 mW for 10 min have reported improvements in corrected distance acuity and a reduction in topographic keratometry at up to 46 months follow-up with no adverse events associated with the high fluences used (Cinar et al., 2014, Cummings et al., 2016, Kanellopoulos, 2012, Kymionis et al., 2014a, Shetty et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>More recently, it has also been demonstrated that the efficacy of A-CXL may be further improved by increasing the UVA exposure time and the overall cumulative dosage (Aldahlawi et al., 2016, Kymionis et al., 2014b, Sherif, 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Increased resistance of the corneal stroma to enzymatic digestion following standard (Hayes et al., 2013, Spoerl et al., 2004) and accelerated (Aldahlawi et al., 2015) epi-off-CXL has been demonstrated by a number of investigators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>It is likely that the improved enzymatic resistance is an important factor in protection against disease progression, since an increase in proteinase activity and a reduction in proteinase inhibitor activity has been identified in keratoconic corneas (Zhou et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate the efficacy of a number of different epi-on-CXL protocols, we compared the enzymatic resistance of corneal tissue cross-linked using epi-off-CXL with that of corneas treated with partially disrupted-epithelium CXL (dis-CXL), existing epi-on-CXL protocols (involving different riboflavin formulations and modes of delivery) and a prolonged iontophoresis CXL protocol with 0.25% riboflavin (TC-ion-CXL) that we have recently developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In addition to this we examined the effect of increasing the cumulative UVA dosage on the enzymatic resistance of corneas treated with iontophoresis-assisted epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Pepsin was selected as the enzyme of choice for this study in favour of collagenase, as it is a non-specific endopeptidase that can break down both collagen and proteoglycan core proteins, both of which are believed to be sites of riboflavin/UVA induced cross-links (Hayes et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Porcine eyes were used as, unlike human cadaver eyes and rabbit eyes which are of limited availability in the UK, they were readily available in the fresh state and in the large numbers required for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, due to the porcine cornea having a thicker epithelium than the human cornea, the results presented herein should be regarded as a conservative assessment of the effectiveness of trans-epithelial CXL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Specimen preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A total of one hundred and fourteen fresh porcine cadaver eyes with clear corneas and intact epithelium were retrieved from a local European Community licensed abattoir within 6–8 h of death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Due to the large number of eyes and treatment groups involved, it was necessary to split the study into two runs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Run 1 examined the effectiveness of dis-CXL and epi-on-CXL protocols at increasing corneal enzymatic resistance to digestion with pepsin, whilst run 2 examined the effect on enzymatic resistance of increasing the UVA dosage by 25% from 5.4 J/cm2 to 6.75 J/cm2 during iontophoretic epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In both runs, the effectiveness of the standard epi-off CXL protocol at increasing enzymatic resistance was also examined for comparative purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The 11 treatment groups are described below and summarised in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Run 1: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Each treatment group consisted of six eyes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>i) Epi-off standard protocol (Group 1: Epi-off-ribo; Group 2: Epi-off-CXL) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Complete corneal epithelial debridement was performed in groups 1 and 2 using a single edged razor blade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>These eyes then received 0.1% riboflavin eye drops containing 20% dextran T-500 solution (Mediocross D®, Peschke Meditrade, Huenenberg, Switzerland) every 5 min for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The central 9 mm region of corneas in group 2 was then exposed to 365 nm UVA light with a fluence of CXL 9 mW/cm2 for 10 min using a CCL-365 Vario™ cross-linking system (Peschkmed, Huenenberg, Switzerland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>During irradiation, riboflavin was re-applied at 5 min intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Group 1 served as a non-irradiated control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>ii) Epi-disrupted protocol (Group 3: Dis-ribo; Group 4: Dis-CXL) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Partial epithelial disruption was performed in groups 3 and 4, by making 64 full-thickness epithelial punctures with a 25 gauge needle in an 8 × 8 grid pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The corneas were then soaked in riboflavin 0.1% dextran-free solution (Vitamin B2 Streuli, Uznach, Switzerland) for 30 min and rinsed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Group 4 was then irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 10 min with PBS applied at 5 min intervals to keep the corneal surface moist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Group 3 served as a non-irradiated control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>iii) Epi-on and high riboflavin concentration protocol (Group 5: Medio-ribo; Group 6: Medio-CXL) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Groups 5 and 6 received 0.25% riboflavin with 1.2% hydroxypropylmethyl cellulose (HPMC) and 0.01% BAC (Mediocross TE®, Peschketrade, Huenenberg, Switzerland) every 5 min for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This was followed by a 5 min rinse with PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Group 6 was then irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 10 min with PBS applied at 5 min intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Group 5 served as a non-irradiated control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>iv) Epi-on, high riboflavin concentration and prolonged iontophoresis (St. Thomas-Cardiff) protocol (Group 7: TC-ion-ribo; Group 8: TC-ion-CXL) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Groups 7 and 8 received iontophoresis assisted delivery of 0.25% riboflavin with 1.2% HPMC and 0.01% BAC (Mediocross TE®, Peschketrade, Huenenberg, Switzerland) using a current of 1 mA for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The corneas were then soaked with this riboflavin solution for 5 min before a further application of iontophoresis with a power of 0.5 mA/min for 5 min and another 5 min riboflavin soak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The iontophoresis delivery system was used to treat ex vivo eyes by connecting the return electrode to a needle inserted into the vitreous chamber; the negative electrode was a steel grid contained in a corneal well applicator which was adhered to the eye by means of a vacuum well system (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The steel grid (negative electrode) was completely covered with riboflavin and the power generator set to the desired current and duration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The steel grid remained covered with riboflavin solution for the entire procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After treatment the applicator was removed from the cornea and the corneas were washed with PBS for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Group 8 was then irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 10min with PBS applied at 5 min intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Group 7 served as a non-irradiated control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Run 2: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Each treatment group consisted of 11 eyes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>i) Epi-off standard protocol (Group 1: Epi-off-ribo; Group 2: Epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Corneas were treated as described for groups 1 and 2 in run 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>ii) Epi-on, high riboflavin concentration and prolonged iontophoresis (St. Thomas-Cardiff) protocol (Group 8: TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2; Group 9: TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Groups 8 and 9 received iontophoresis assisted delivery of 0.25% riboflavin with 1.2% HPMC and 0.01% BAC (Mediocross TE®, Peschketrade, Huenenberg, Switzerland) using a current of 1 mA for 5min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The corneas were then soaked with this riboflavin solution for 5 min before a further application of iontophoresis with a power of 0.5 mA/min for 5 min and another 5 min riboflavin soak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Following a 3 min wash with PBS, the corneas in Group 8 were irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 10 min and those in Group 9 were irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 12min and 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>During irradiation, PBS was applied to all corneas at 5 min intervals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>iii) Epi-on basic iontophoresis protocol (Group 10: Ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2; Group 11: Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Groups 10 and 11 underwent iontophoresis assisted riboflavin delivery using an isotonic 0.1% riboflavin solution (Vitamin B2) containing 1.0% HPMC dextran-free solution (Mediocross M®, Peschketrade, Huenenberg, Switzerland) and a 1 mA current (Iontophoresis device, Sooft Italia S.p.A, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>After treatment the corneas were washed with PBS for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Group 10 was then irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 10min and group 11 was irradiated with 9 mW UVA for 12 min and 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>During irradiation, PBS was applied to all corneas at 5 min intervals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Measurements of corneal thickness </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Using a Pachette2™ Ultrasonic Pachymeter (DGH Technology, Exton, USA), the central corneal thickness was measured in all eyes prior to treatment and where applicable after removal of the epithelium, application of riboflavin and UVA irradiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Measurements of enzymatic digestion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A corneo-scleral ring was dissected from each eye immediately following treatment, wrapped tightly in Clingfilm™ (to prevent moisture loss) and refrigerated until all treatments were complete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>An 8 mm corneal button was trephined from the centre of each cornea using a disposable skin biopsy punch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The corneal buttons were then immersed into individual plastic tubes, each containing 5 ml of pepsin solution, and incubated in a water bath at a temperature of 23 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The pepsin solution was made up of 1 g of &gt;500 U/mg pepsin from porcine gastric mucosa (Sigma-Aldrich, Dorset, UK) in 10 ml 0.1 M HCL at pH 1.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The structural integrity of the most anterior layers of the cornea was assessed by means of daily measurements of corneal button diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The measurements, which were made using an electronic digital caliper, continued until the specimen could no longer be distinguished from the surrounding pepsin solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At this point the tissue was considered to have undergone complete digestion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>As an additional means of assessing enzymatic resistance, 5 corneal buttons from each of the 6 treatment groups in run 2 were removed after 11 days in pepsin digest solution and placed in a 60 °C oven until a constant dry weight was obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The dry weight of the tissue represents the total mass of undigested tissue and can therefore be used as an indicator of the effective depth of cross-linking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Statistical evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Measurements of corneal thickness, complete digestion time and tissue dry weight were statistically analysed using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Post hoc Bonferroni comparisons were used to isolate significant interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed with the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (IBM SPSS Statistics 20, New York, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>P &lt; 0.01 was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Data were presented in the results as mean ± standard deviation (SD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Corneal thickness </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Fig. 2 shows the average corneal thickness pre-treatment, post-riboflavin application and post-irradiation for each treatment group in runs 1 and 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Statistical tests revealed that corneas treated using the standard, epi-off protocol and an iso-osmolar riboflavin solution (groups 1 and 2) were significantly thinner than the corneas in all other groups (p &lt; 0.007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Qualitative assessment of riboflavin uptake </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 3, the distinctive yellow colouration of riboflavin was most clearly visible in the epi-off and TC-ion treated corneas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Although riboflavin was also seen in corneas from other treatment groups, the colour was notably less intense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Photographs recorded during the irradiation process in run 2 showed a non-homogenous distribution of riboflavin in Ion-CXL treated corneas and a more uniform distribution following epi-off CXL and TC-Ion-CXL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Pepsin digestion of corneal buttons </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows the number of days required for complete tissue digestion to occur in each irradiated and non-irradiated treatment group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Although the digestion times of equivalent non-irradiated (group 1) and cross-linked treatment groups (group 2) were seen to vary slightly between runs 1 and 2, possibly as a result of differences in the breed and age of the pig eyes, the overall trends were consistent between the two runs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>For this reason the data from each run was normalized against the total digestion time of the standard epi-off CXL group to facilitate comparison between the two runs (Fig. 4, Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Fig. 4, Fig. 5 show cumulative measurements of corneal disk diameter for each irradiated and non-irradiated treatment group throughout the digestion process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In both runs 1 and 2, the cross-linked groups showed a significantly greater resistance to enzymatic digestion than the non-irradiated groups (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In run 1, complete digestion of all non-irradiated corneas had occurred by day 13 (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>At the same time point (normalized digestion time of 0.33), the mean diameter of the epi-off-CXL, dis-CXL, medio-CXL and TC-ion-CXL groups had only decreased by 39%, 62%, 74%, and 40% respectively (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>No significant difference was found between the non-irradiated groups in terms of either the average corneal button diameter at any time point in the digestion process or in the time required for complete digestion to occur (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>There were however significant differences between the cross-linked groups in term of the time taken for complete digestion to occur (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The conventionally treated, epi-off-CXL corneas (group 2) took significantly longer to digest than all other cross-linked corneas (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Although less resistant to enzyme digestion than the epi-off-CXL corneas, the TC-ion-CXL treated corneas (group 8) took significantly longer to digest than corneas treated with other disrupted epithelium (dis-CXL) or epi-on-CXL protocols (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In run 2, the non-irradiated corneas were completely digested by day 10 (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>At this same time point, which corresponds to a normalized digestion time of 0.25, the mean diameter of corneas in the epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2, TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2, TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2, Ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 and Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 treatment groups had reduced by 21.4%, 16.2%, 13.4%, 26.7% and 19.4% respectively (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Significant differences in the mean disk diameter of the CXL treatment groups were only apparent after 24 days of digestion (corresponding to a normalized digestion time of 0.6 in Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The epi-off-CXL group (group 2) took longer to undergo complete digestion than all other cross-linked groups (p &lt; 0.0001) but corneas treated with the prolonged, high riboflavin concentration, iontophoresis protocol (TC-ion-CXL) were found to persist in the pepsin digest solution for significantly longer than those treated with the basic Ion-CXL protocol (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In both the Ion-CXL and TC-ion-CXL treatment groups, an increase in UVA radiance from 5.4 J/cm2 to 6.75 J/cm2 resulted in a significant increase in the time required for complete digestion to occur (P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Undigested tissue mass </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In run 2, only the cross-linked corneas remained after 11 days in pepsin digest solution (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>At this time point, the average stromal dry weight of the epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 treated corneas (group 2) was significantly higher than that of all other treatment groups (groups 8, 10, 11, P &lt; 0.0001; group 9, P &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The stromal dry weight did not differ significantly between the Ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 and Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 treatment groups (p = 0.32) or between the TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 and TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 groups (p = 0.038). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, corneas treated with the TC-Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 protocol had a higher stromal dry weight than corneas treated with basic ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 protocol (p &lt; 0.003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Attaining adequate stromal riboflavin concentration is essential for CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Riboflavin acts as a photo-sensitizer for the production of oxygen free radicals, which drive the CXL process (McCall et al., 2010) and as a result insufficient stromal absorption may result in treatment failure (Wollensak et al., 2003, Wollensak and Iomdina, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>As riboflavin is a hydrophilic molecule which cannot penetrate epithelial cell membranes and tight junctions, the first riboflavin/UVA CXL protocols required complete central corneal epithelial debridement prior to riboflavin application (Spoerl et al., 1998, Wollensak et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Although epi-off-CXL is considered to be the gold standard procedure, with multiple prospective and randomized controlled studies demonstrating its efficacy in terms of cessation of keratoconus progression and improvements in keratometric and visual parameters (Caporossi et al., 2006, Gkika et al., 2011, O'Brart et al., 2011, Richoz et al., 2013, Wittig-Silva et al., 2014, Wollensak et al., 2003), new methods of epi-on-CXL have been postulated to remove the need for epithelial debridement, thereby alleviating post-operative pain and potential risks of infection (Koller et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In addition, to reduce the long treatment times associated with epi-off-CXL with 3mw/cm2 UVA irradiation, the use of A-CXL protocols using the same energy dose but higher UVA intensities and shorter exposure times have been advocated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the efficacy of such differing CXL protocols, multiple methodologies, including extensiometry (Cassagne et al., 2016, Kissner et al., 2010, Vinciguerra et al., 2014a, Wollensak and Iomdina, 2009), shear wave elastography (Touboul et al., 2014), Brillouin microscopy (Scarcelli et al., 2013) and Scheimpflug air pulse tonometry (Mastropasqua et al., 2014) have been employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>However each of these methodologies have their inherent inaccuracies and as yet there is no agreed best practice for assessing biomechanical changes following CXL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Although the precise aetiology of keratoconus is unknown (Davidson et al., 2014), an increased activity of protease enzymes and reduced activity of protease inhibitors has been identified (Spoerl et al., 2004), with the resultant increase in stromal protein digestion liable to be a factor in corneal thinning and secondary biomechanical instability (Andreassen et al., 1980). Spoerl et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>(2004) reported increased resistance of stromal tissue to enzymatic digestion following epi-off CXL with a dose response related to the intensity of UVA irradiance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This increased resistance to protease digestion following CXL has been replicated by others (Hayes et al., 2013, Aldahlawi et al., 2016) and is thought to be an important factor in preventing disease progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In this study we utilized enzymatic resistance to pepsin digestion to evaluate the effects of epi-off-CXL, dis-CXL and epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Although minor differences in the rate of enzymatic digestion were seen between similarly treated corneas in runs 1 and 2, possibly due to variations in the age and breed of the pig eyes in different batches of abattoir tissue, each run showed an increased resistance in all of the cross-linked groups compared to their non-irradiated controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>However, in accordance with the findings of Wollensak and Iomdina (2009), which reported corneal stiffness after epi-on-CXL to be only one fifth of that seen after epi-off-CXL (indicating a reduced crosslinking effect), we found enzymatic resistance to be significantly greater with epi-off-CXL than with dis-CXL or epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Whilst dis-CXL showed a greater resistance to digestion than the non-irradiated controls, it was not as effective as the other epi-on-CXL protocols tested, possibly due to the non-homogeneous uptake of riboflavin that we have documented previously (Alhamad et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Such observations are supported by a recently published, randomized controlled study which showed better corneal flattening with epi-off-CXL than dis-CXL, although interestingly, dis-CXL resulted in better improvement of corrected distance visual acuity at 6 months (Razmjoo et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In this study we showed that corneas cross-linked using Mediocross TE® (Medio-CXL protocol) showed a greater resistance to enzymatic digestion than non-irradiated controls and dis-CXL treated corneas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, the enhanced enzymatic resistance achieved with Medio-CXL was found to be inferior to that of the epi-off and ion-CXL protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE® is a hypo-osmolar riboflavin solution that contains 0.01% BAC, a cationic surfactant that can disrupt epithelial tight junctions to increase corneal permeability to riboflavin (Kissner et al., 2010, Raiskup et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Laboratory studies have shown that preparations with sodium chloride and BAC can facilitate riboflavin transfer through an intact epithelium albeit in a reduced concentration compared to the epi-off-CXL (Touboul et al., 2014), and with significant associated superficial epithelial damage (Uematsu et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Published clinical studies using enhanced riboflavin solutions with epithelial penetration enhancers are limited and have produced equivocal results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Some have reported similar efficacy to epi-off-CXL (Filippello et al., 2012, Magli et al., 2013), while others have demonstrated less pronounced effects with high rates of treatment failure (Buzzonetti and Petrocelli, 2012, Kocak et al., 2014, Koppen et al., 2012, Leccisotti and Islam, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>There are currently only three published randomized, controlled trials comparing epi-off and epi-on-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Two of the studies, with follow-up times of up to 12 months, reported similar outcomes (Nawaz et al., 2015, Rossi et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>However, the third study, showed epi-on-CXL to be safe but demonstrated continued progression of keratoconus in 23% of cases at 12 month follow-up (Soeters et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The latter result is consistent with the less pronounced biomechanical changes observed experimentally following epi-on-CXL (Wollensak and Iomdina, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As riboflavin is negatively charged at physiological pH and soluble in water, the use of iontophoresis has been postulated to enhance trans-epithelial absorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Commercially recommended protocols for iontophoresis utilize 0.1% riboflavin solution and electrical currents of 0.5–1 mA for 5–10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Treatment of rabbit corneas by this means has been shown to reduce the stromal riboflavin uptake achieved with epi-off-CXL by two thirds, but to produce a similar improvement in corneal biomechanics (Cassagne et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Studies on rabbit and human cadaver corneas have demonstrated similar findings, with better riboflavin penetration and increased elastometry measurements obtained with Ion-CXL than with epi-on-CXL (using Ricrolin TE) but less than epi-off-CXL (Vinciguerra et al., 2014a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In a human donor eye model, Mastropasqua et al. demonstrated a corneal stiffening effect following Ion-CXL (Mastropasqua et al., 2014), with Lombardo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>(2014) reporting an almost comparable effect on corneal stiffness to that with epi-off-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>These findings have been confirmed by supersonic shear wave elastography (Touboul et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, initial clinical studies in prospective case series have reported cessation of keratoconus progression with up to 15 month follow-up and some limited improvements in keratometric and visual parameters (Bikbova and Bikbov, 2014, Buzzonetti et al., 2015, Vinciguerra et al., 2014b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, the relative efficacy of this technique compared to epi-off-CXL remains to be determined especially over longer term follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Using spectrophotometry (Hayes et al., 2015) and two-photon fluorescence microscopy (Gore et al., 2014), we have found that stromal riboflavin absorption in epithelium-intact corneas can be improved by increasing riboflavin concentration, epithelial contact time and iontophoresis dosage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Based on this work, we have modified the basic Sooft italia Ion-CXL protocol (Sooft italia S.p.A, Motegiorgio, Italy) and developed the St Thomas's/Cardiff modified iontophoresis protocol (TC-ion-CXL) which uses Mediocross TE® as the iontophoretic solution instead of Ricrolin+®, as the riboflavin concentration of the former is higher (0.25%) and the use of the cationic surfactant BAC has been shown with percutaneous treatment to have synergistic effect with iontophoresis on the transport of anions (Fang et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In addition to using this formulation, the modified protocol employed a riboflavin-epithelial contact period of 5 min after iontophoresis to allow time for the sub-epithelial iontophoretically delivered riboflavin to diffuse homogeneously into the stroma, as well as an increased dosage of iontophoresis with a second treatment 5 min after the first. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Results from the present study demonstrated that both the basic Ion-CXL and modified TC-ion-CXL protocols resulted in a greater resistance to enzymatic digestion than all other dis-CXL and trans-epithelial CXL protocols tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, as we have demonstrated previously for epi-off CXL treated corneas (Aldahlawi et al., 2016), we have now shown that the enzymatic resistance of Ion-CXL and TC-ion-CXL treated corneas can also be enhanced by increasing the cumulative energy dose and allowing additional type I photochemical cross-linking to occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The improvement in enzymatic resistance was evidenced by the Ion-CXL and TC-ion-CXL corneas treated with a total energy dose of 6.75 J/cm2 persisting for longer in enzyme digest solution than those that received a lower energy dose of 5.4 J/cm2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The absence of any difference in their dry weights after 11 days of digestion is likely explained by the fact that at this stage of the digestion process, the rate of digestion was similar for both the high and low energy treatment groups and significant differences in average corneal disk diameter were not observed until day 24. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The enzymatic resistance achieved with the TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 protocol was closest to that of the standard epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 protocol, suggesting that this technique may be the best trans-epithelial alternative for epi-off-CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Its slightly lower efficacy compared to epi-off-CXL, demonstrated by measurements of corneal disk diameter and tissue dry weight, may be due to a reduced riboflavin stromal absorption or due to other factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>These might include absorption of UVA by riboflavin within the epithelium, resulting in shielding of the underlying stroma and a reduced UVA dosage to the stroma, although this is unlikely as a 3 min PBS wash of the ocular surface was performed before UVA exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Another possible cause of the reduced efficacy might be the oxygen consumption by the epithelium itself (Harvitt and Bonanno, 1998), which could reduce the amount of oxygen available to the stroma to drive the CXL process (McCall et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Such problems may be overcome by additional manipulation of the UVA dosage, in terms of its intensity and duration and/or by increasing oxygen availability and require further investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>One further explanation may be the limitation of our porcine model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>As the porcine cornea has a much thicker corneal epithelium than the human cornea (90 μm and 50 μm respectively), the results of the current study should be regarded as a conservative assessment of the effectiveness of trans-epithelial CXL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, human donor corneas are unsuitable for examining the effects of CXL on enzymatic resistance due to the fact that donors are typically over 60 years old, and the naturally occurring cross-links which increase with age, may mask the effects of the CXL treatment under investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>However, it would be interesting to repeat our methodology in the rabbit model which has a thinner epithelium (40 μm) and is closer in thickness to that of the human cornea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Such a study would complement our current findings by providing a more liberal estimate of the effectiveness of trans-epithelial cross-linking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>This study, which shows our St Thomas'/Cardiff modified iontophoresis protocol (TC-ion-CXL) to be more effective than other trans-epithelial CXL protocols at increasing the enzymatic resistance of the cornea supports the concept that iontophoresis-assisted CXL may, with modifications in terms of riboflavin concentration, duration of iontophoretic treatment, riboflavin soak-time and UVA energy dose, be an effective technique to prevent the progression of keratoconus and avoid the postoperative pain associated with epithelial debridement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Such a technique is envisaged to be especially useful for eyes that are not eligible for treatment with epi-off-CXL due to minimum corneal thickness values less than 400 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Further laboratory studies to optimize this protocol and randomized, prospective clinical studies to compare its efficacy with epi-off CXL are indicated and are currently being undertaken (O'Brart D, personal communication, International Standard Randomized Controlled Trials Number: 04451470). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Financial disclosure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>No author has a financial or proprietary interest in any material or method mentioned. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>AldahlawiN.H.HayesS.O'BrartD.P.S.AkhbanbetovaA.LittlechildS.L.MeekK.M.Enzymatic resistance of corneas crosslinked using riboflavin in conjunction with low energy, high energy, and pulsed UVA irradiation modesInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Sci.57420161547155227046119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>AldahlawiN.H.HayesS.O'BrartD.P.S.MeekK.M.Standard versus accelerated riboflavin-ultraviolet corneal collagen crosslinking: resistance against enzymatic digestionJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Surg.41920151989199626603408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>AlhamadT.A.O'BrartD.P.S.O'BrartN.A.L.MeekK.M.Evaluation of transepithelial stromal riboflavin absorption with enhanced riboflavin solution using spectrophotometryJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Surg.385201288488922520311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>AndreassenT.T.SimonsenA.H.OxlundH.Biomechanical properties of keratoconus and normal corneasExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Eye Res.31419804354417449878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>BikbovaG.BikbovM.Transepithelial corneal collagen cross-linking by iontophoresis of riboflavinActa Ophthalmol.9212014E30E3423848196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Boxer WachlerB.S.PinelliR.ErtanA.ChanC.C.K.Safety and efficacy of transepithelial crosslinking (C3-R/CXL)J. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Surg.3612010186188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>BuzzonettiL.PetrocelliG.Transepithelial corneal cross-linking in pediatric patients: early resultsJ. Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Surg.2811201276376723347369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>BuzzonettiL.PetrocelliG.ValenteP.IarossiG.ArdiaR.PetroniS.Iontophoretic transepithelial corneal cross-linking to halt keratoconus in pediatric cases: 15-Month follow-upCornea345201551251525789695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>CaporossiA.BaiocchiS.MazzottaC.TraversiC.CaporossiT.Parasurgical therapy for keratoconus by rib oflavin-ultraviolet type A rays induced cross-linking of corneal collagen - preliminary refractive results in an Italian studyJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Surg.325200683784516765803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>CassagneM.LaurentC.RodriguesM.GalinierA.SpoerlE.GaliacyS.D.SolerV.FournieP.MalecazeF.Iontophoresis transcorneal delivery technique for transepithelial corneal collagen crosslinking with riboflavin in a rabbit modelInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Sci.572201659460324644053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>ChanC.C.K.SharmaM.WachlerB.S.B.Effect of inferior-segment Intacs with and without C3-R on keratoconusJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Surg.3312007758017189797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>CinarY.CinguA.K.TurkcuF.M.YukselH.SahinA.YildirimA.CacaI.CinarT.Accelerated corneal collagen cross-linking for progressive keratoconusCutan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Ocular Toxicol.3322014168171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>CummingsA.B.McQuaidR.NaughtonS.BrennanE.MrochenM.Optimizing corneal cross-linking in the treatment of keratoconus: a comparison of outcomes after standard- and high-intensity protocolsCornea356201681482227055212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>DavidsonA.E.HayesS.HardcastleA.J.TuftS.J.The pathogenesis of keratoconus.”Eye282201418919524357835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>FangJ.Y.LinH.H.ChenH.I.TsaiY.H.Development and evaluation on transdermal delivery of enoxacin via chemical enhancers and physical iontophoresisJ. Control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Release54319982933049766249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>FilippelloM.StagniE.O'BrartD.Transepithelial corneal collagen crosslinking: bilateral studyJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Surg.382201228329122104644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>GkikaM.LabirisG.KozobolisV.Corneal collagen cross-linking using riboflavin and ultraviolet-A irradiation: a review of clinical and experimental studiesInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.314201130931921847678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>GoreD.M.MargineanuA.FrenchP.O'BrartD.DunsbyC.AllanB.D.Two-photon fluorescence microscopy of corneal riboflavin absorptionInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Sci.55420142476248124644056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>HarvittD.M.BonannoJ.A.Oxygen consumption of the rabbit corneaInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Sci.39219984444489478006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>HayesS.Kamma-LorgerC.S.BooteC.YoungR.D.QuantockA.J.RostA.KhatibY.HarrisJ.YagiN.TerrillN.MeekK.M.The effect of riboflavin/UVA collagen cross-linking therapy on the structure and hydrodynamic behaviour of the ungulate and rabbit corneal stromaPlos One812013e5286023349690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>HayesS.MorganS.R.O'BrartD.P.O'BrartN.MeekK.M.A study of stromal riboflavin absorption in ex vivo porcine corneas using new and existing delivery protocols for corneal cross-linkingActa Ophthalmol.9422015E109E11726421680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>HuangA.J.W.TsengS.C.G.KenyonK.R.Paracellular permeability of corneal and conjunctival epitheliaInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Sci.30419896846892703309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>KanellopoulosA.J.Long term results of a prospective randomized bilateral eye comparison trial of higher fluence, shorter duration ultraviolet A radiation, and riboflavin collagen cross linking for progressive keratoconusClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.6201297101(Auckland, N.Z.)22275813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>KissnerA.SpoerlE.JungR.SpeklK.PillunatL.E.RaiskupF.Pharmacological modification of the epithelial permeability by benzalkonium chloride in UVA/riboflavin corneal collagen cross-linkingCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Eye Res.358201071572120673048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>KocakI.AydinA.KayaF.KocH.Comparison of transepithelial corneal collagen crosslinking with epithelium-off crosslinking in progressive keratoconusJ. Fr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>D Ophtalmol.3752014371376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>KollerT.MrochenM.SeilerT.Complication and failure rates after corneal crosslinkingJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Surg.35820091358136219631120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>KoppenC.WoutersK.MathysenD.RozemaJ.TassignonM.-J.Refractive and topographic results of benzalkonium chloride–assisted transepithelial crosslinkingJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Surg.38620121000100522624899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>KymionisG.D.GrentzelosM.A.KankariyaV.P.LiakopoulosD.A.PortaliouD.M.TsoulnarasK.I.KaravitakiA.E.PallikarisA.I.Safety of high-intensity corneal collagen crosslinkingJ. Cataract Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Surg.40820141337134025088634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>KymionisG.D.TsoulnarasK.I.GrentzelosM.A.LiakopoulosD.A.TsakalisN.G.BlazakiS.V.ParaskevopoulosT.A.TsilimbarisM.K.Evaluation of corneal stromal demarcation line depth following standard and a modified-accelerated collagen cross-linking protocolAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.1584201467167525034113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>LeccisottiA.IslamT.Transepithelial corneal collagen cross-linking in keratoconusJ. Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Surg.2612201094294820166621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>LombardoM.SerraoS.RosatiM.DucoliP.LombardoG.Biomechanical changes in the human cornea after transepithelial corneal crosslinking using iontophoresisJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Surg.401020141706171525263041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>MagliA.ForteR.TortoriA.CapassoL.MarsicoG.PiozziE.Epithelium-off corneal collagen cross-linking versus transepithelial cross-linking for pediatric keratoconusCornea325201359760123132450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>MastropasquaL.LanziniM.CurcioC.CaliennoR.MastropasquaR.ColasanteM.MastropasquaA.NubileM.Structural modifications and tissue response after standard epi-off and iontophoretic corneal crosslinking with different irradiation proceduresInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Sci.55420142526253324667859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>McCallA.S.KraftS.EdelhauserH.F.KidderG.W.LundquistR.R.BradshawH.E.DedeicZ.DionneM.J.C.ClementE.M.ConradG.W.Mechanisms of corneal tissue cross-linking in response to treatment with topical riboflavin and long-wavelength ultraviolet radiation (UVA)Investig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Sci.511201012913819643975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>NawazS.GuptaS.GogiaV.SasikalaN.K.PandaA.Trans-epithelial versus conventional corneal collagen crosslinking: a randomized trial in keratoconusOman J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.81201591325709267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>O'BrartD.P.S.ChanE.SamarasK.PatelP.ShahS.P.A randomised, prospective study to investigate the efficacy of riboflavin/ultraviolet A (370 nm) corneal collagen cross-linkage to halt the progression of keratoconusBr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.951120111519152421349938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>RaiskupF.PinelliR.SpoerlE.Riboflavin osmolar modification for transepithelial corneal cross-linkingCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Eye Res.373201223423822335811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>RazmjooH.RahimiB.KharrajiM.KooshaN.PeymanA.Corneal haze and visual outcome after collagen crosslinking for keratoconus: a comparison between total epithelium off and partial epithelial removal methodsAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Biomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Res.3201422125538907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>RechichiM.DayaS.ScorciaV.MeduriA.ScorciaG.Epithelial-disruption collagen crosslinking for keratoconus: one-year resultsJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Surg.39820131171117823796620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>RichozO.MavrakanasN.PajicB.HafeziF.Corneal collagen cross-linking for ectasia after LASIK and photorefractive keratectomy long-term resultsOphthalmology120720131354135923582990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>RossiS.OrricoA.SantamariaC.RomanoV.De RosaL.SimonelliF.De RosaG.Standard versus trans-epithelial collagen cross-linking in keratoconus patients suitable for standard collagen cross-linkingClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.9201550350925834386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>ScarcelliG.KlingS.QuijanoE.PinedaR.MarcosS.YunS.H.Brillouin microscopy of collagen crosslinking: noncontact depth-dependent analysis of corneal elastic modulusInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Sci.54220131418142523361513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SherifA.M.Accelerated versus conventional corneal collagen cross-linking in the treatment of mild keratoconus: a comparative studyClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.820141435144025120349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib44"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>ShettyR.PahujaN.K.NuijtsR.M.M.A.AjaniA.JayadevC.SharmaC.NagarajaH.Current protocols of corneal collagen cross-linking: visual, refractive, and tomographic outcomesAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.1602201524324926008626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib45"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>SoetersN.WisseR.P.L.GodefrooijD.A.ImhofS.M.TahzibN.G.Transepithelial versus epithelium-off corneal cross-linking for the treatment of progressive keratoconus: a randomized controlled trial REPLYAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.16022015400–400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib46"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>SpoerlE.HuhleM.SeilerT.Induction of cross-links in corneal tissueExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Eye Res.6611998971039533835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib47"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>SpoerlE.WollensakG.SeilerT.Increased resistance of crosslinked cornea against enzymatic digestionCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Eye Res.2912004354015370365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib48"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>TouboulD.GennissonJ.-L.NguyenT.-M.RobinetA.RobertsC.J.TanterM.GrenierN.Supersonic shear wave elastography for the in vivo evaluation of transepithelial corneal collagen cross-linkingInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Sci.55320141976198424519426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib49"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>UematsuM.KumagamiT.KusanoM.YamadaK.MishimaK.FujimuraK.SasakiH.KitaokaT.Acute corneal epithelial change after instillation of benzalkonium chloride evaluated using a newly developed in vivo corneal transepithelial electric resistance measurement methodOphthalmic Res.396200730831417957130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>VinciguerraP.MencucciR.RomanoV.SpoerlE.CamesascaF.I.FavuzzaE.AzzoliniC.MastropasquaR.VinciguerraR.Imaging mass spectrometry by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization and stress-strain measurements in iontophoresis transepithelial corneal collagen cross-linkingBiomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Int.201440458725276786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib51"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>VinciguerraP.RandlemanJ.B.RomanoV.LegrottaglieE.F.RosettaP.CamesascaF.I.PiscopoR.AzzoliniC.VinciguerraR.Transepithelial iontophoresis corneal collagen cross-linking for progressive keratoconus: initial clinical outcomesJ. Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Surg.30112014747754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib52"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Wittig-SilvaC.ChanE.IslamF.M.A.WuT.WhitingM.SnibsonG.R.A randomized, controlled trial of corneal collagen cross-linking in progressive keratoconus three-year resultsOphthalmology1214201481282124393351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib53"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>WollensakG.IomdinaE.Biomechanical and histological changes after corneal crosslinking with and without epithelial debridementJ. Cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Refract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Surg.353200954054619251149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib54"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>WollensakG.SpoerlE.SeilerT.Riboflavin/ultraviolet-A-induced collagen crosslinking for the treatment of keratoconusAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol.1355200362062712719068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib55"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>ZhouL.SawaguchiS.TwiningS.S.SugarJ.FederR.S.YueB.Y.J.T.Expression of degradative enzymes and protease inhibitors in corneas with keratoconusInvestig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Sci.3971998111711249620070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">MRC programme grant</funding-source> MR/K000837/1 and <funding-source id="gs2">King Saud University</funding-source> funding KSU1269. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript. The authors indicate no financial disclosures. We wish to thank Veni Vidi (Halifax, UK) for their generous provision of riboflavin for this study. Contributions of authors: design of the study (NA, SH, DO, KM); conduct of the study (NA, SH, NO); management and analysis of the data (NA), interpretation of the data (NA, DO and SH); and preparation, review, or approval of manuscript (NA, SH, DO, KM).</p></ack></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Iontophoresis riboflavin delivery system modified for use in ex-vivo eyes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Corneal thickness measurements are shown for each group in run 1 and run 2 before treatment, after riboflavin application and where applicable, following UVA irradiation. *In groups 1 and 2 the corneal epithelium (measuring ∼90 μm in thickness) was removed as part of the riboflavin application process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Corneal buttons from each group in run 1 and 2 are shown immediately post-treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The characteristic yellow colour of riboflavin can be seen most clearly in the epithelium-removed, riboflavin treated corneas (epi-off) and in the corneas that received riboflavin via the St Thomas's/Cardiff modified iontophoresis protocol (TC-Ion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Photographs recorded during the irradiation process show a non-homogenous distribution of riboflavin in corneas treated with the basic iontophoresis protocol (Ion-CXL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The summed diameter of all corneal disks within each treatment group (n = 6) are shown for run 1 as a function of time in pepsin digest solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>The digestion time for each treatment group has been normalized against the total digestion time of the standard epi-off CXL group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>The summed diameter of all corneal disks within each treatment group (n = 6) are shown for run 2 as a function of time in pepsin digest solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>The digestion time for each treatment group has been normalized against the total digestion time of the standard epi-off CXL group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Corneal button dry weight after 11 days of digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Error bars show standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Treatment groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Epithelium </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Riboflavin formulation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Ionto (1 mA) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Ribo soak </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Ionto (0.5 mA) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Ribo soak </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Saline rinse </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>9 mW UVA </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Applied during irradiation </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>(1)Epithelium-off non-irradiated control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Epi-off-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Off </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Mediocross D: 0.1% Riboflavin, 20% dextran </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>(2) Epithelium-off standard CXL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Off </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Mediocross D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>10 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Mediocross D </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>(3) Disrupted epithelium non-irradiated control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Dis-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Disrupted </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Vitamin B2 Streuli: 0.1% riboflavin, saline </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>(4) Disrupted epithelium CXL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Dis-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Disrupted </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Vitamin B2 Streuli </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>10 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>(5) Epithelium intact non-irradiated control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Medio-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE: 0.25% riboflavin, 1.2% HPMC, 0.01% BACS, Pi-water </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>(6) Epithelium intact high riboflavin concentration CXL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Medio-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>30 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>10 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>(7) Epithelium intact, high riboflavin concentration and prolonged iontophoresis non-irradiated control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>TC-ion-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>(8) Epithelium intact, high riboflavin concentration and prolonged iontophoresis CXL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>10 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>(9) Epithelium intact, high riboflavin concentration, prolonged iontophoresis and high UVA energy dose CXL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Mediocross TE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>3 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>12 min 30 s </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>(10) Epithelium intact, basic iontophoresis protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Mediocross M: 0.1% riboflavin, 1.0% HPMC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>3 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>10 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>(11) Epithelium intact, basic iontophoresis protocol with high UVA energy dose </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>On </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Mediocross M </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>5 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>3 min </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>12 min 30 s </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>PBS </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Time taken for the complete tissue digestion to occur. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Groups </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Time taken for complete digestion (in days) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Minimum </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Maximum </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Average (±SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>RUN 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>(1) Epi-off-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>11.5 ± 0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>(2) Epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>39.5 ± 0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>(3) Dis-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>11.8 ± 0.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>(4) Dis-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>15.6 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>(5) Medio-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>11.6 ± 0.51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>(6) Medio-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>14.6 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>(7) TC-ion-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>11.3 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>(8) TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>32.2 ± 0.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>RUN 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>(1) Epi-off-ribo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>9.5 ± 0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>(2) Epi-off-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>43 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>44 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>43.5 ± 0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>(8) TC-ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>34.3 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>(9) TC-ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>41.7 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>(10) Ion-CXL 5.4 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>27.3 ± 0.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>(11) Ion-CXL 6.75 J/cm2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>34.5 ± 0.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
