<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5920331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29474667</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery065</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery065</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Plant—Environment Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The transcription factor CsbHLH18 of sweet orange functions in modulation of cold tolerance and homeostasis of reactive oxygen species by regulating the antioxidant gene </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Jingjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6686-1629</contrib-id><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ji-Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001">Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology (MOE), College of Horticulture and Forestry Sciences, Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>liujihong@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-02-21"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>69</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2677</fpage><lpage>2692</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery065.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18, a bHLH transcription factor of Citrus sinensis, functions as a positive regulator of cold tolerance due to promoted ROS scavenging, and directly targets a POD gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The basic helix–loop–helix (bHLH) transcription factors (TFs) comprise one of the largest gene families in plants, and participate in various physiological processes, but the physiological role and regulatory function of the majority of bHLHs remain poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, a total of 56 putative CsbHLH genes were identified in sweet orange (Citrus sinensis) based on a genome-wide analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The CsbHLH genes, except four members, were distributed throughout nine chromosomes and divided into 19 subgroups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Most of the CsbHLH genes were responsive to cold stress, with the greatest up-regulation being observed in CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18 is localized in the nuclei and has transcriptional activation activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of CsbHLH18 conferred enhanced cold tolerance in transgenic tobacco. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The transgenic plants accumulated significantly less reactive oxygen species (ROS), concurrent with increased activities and transcript levels of antioxidant enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In contrast, knockdown of bHLH18 by RNAi in trifoliate orange promoted cold susceptibility, accompanied by down-regulation of antioxidant genes and accumulation of more ROS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Protein–DNA interaction assays demonstrate that CsbHLH18 directly and specifically binds to and activates the promoter of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these findings indicate that CsbHLH18 plays a positive role in cold tolerance through, at least partly, modulation of ROS homeostasis by directly regulating the antioxidant gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Basic helix–loop–helix transcription factors</kwd><kwd><italic>Citrus sinensis</italic></kwd><kwd>cold stress tolerance</kwd><kwd>E-box element</kwd><kwd>genome-wide analysis</kwd><kwd>ROS homeostasis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Natural Science Foundation of China</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id>31572100</award-id><award-id>31320103908</award-id><award-id>31521092</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Hubei Provincial Natural Science Foundation for Innovative Group</named-content></funding-source><award-id>2017CFA018</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Plants are routinely exposed to a range of abiotic factors, such as extreme temperatures, drought, and high salinity, which have adverse effects on plant growth and may substantially reduce crop productivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Plants have also evolved a range of complex mechanisms to tolerate the harsh environmental stresses (Huang et al., 2013; Zhu, 2016; Zandalinas et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Stress responses are known to involve numerous signaling pathways that can form intricate networks composed of various genes encoding structural and regulatory proteins that play direct or indirect roles in protecting plants against the abiotic stresses (Lata and Prasad, 2011; Liu et al., 2014; Li et al., 2017; Zhao et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Transcription factors (TFs) are important regulatory proteins that function to control the expression of target genes through binding to specific cis-acting elements within the promoters (Golldack et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Therefore, identification and characterization of stress-responsive TFs is crucial to elucidate the molecular network associated with stress response and has been also widely adopted as a strategy for unraveling valuable candidate genes for improving stress tolerance using genetic engineering (Liu et al., 2014; Zhu, 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The basic helix–loop–helix (bHLH) proteins are one of the largest TF families (Riechmann et al., 2000; Carretero-Paulet et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>They typically consist of 50–60 amino acids that form two functionally distinct parts, the basic region at the N-terminus and the HLH region at the C-terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The basic region contains ~15 amino acids with DNA binding ability, which allows the bHLH proteins to bind to the consensus hexa-nucleotide (5'-CANNTG-3') called the E-box element (Atchley et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The HLH region is composed of two amphipathic helices connected by a divergent loop, and functions in facilitating formation of homo- and/or heterodimeric complexes between proteins (Nair and Burley, 2000; Buck and Atchley, 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The bHLH genes act as regulatory components in transcriptional networks, and are involved in many diverse biological processes, such as fruit dehiscence and flowering (Ito et al., 2012), hormone signaling (Friedrichsen et al., 2002), and trichome and root development (Menand et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In addition, an increasing number of studies demonstrate that the bHLHs also function in responses to a range of stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For example, Arabidopsis thaliana INDUCER OF CBF EXPRESSION1 (ICE1) and ICE2 and their homologs in several different plants are reported to play key roles in mediating cold responses (Chinnusamy et al., 2003; Feng et al., 2012; Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>RERJ1 and OsbHLH148 of rice are proposed to be associated with wounding and drought responses (Kiribuchi et al., 2005; Seo et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition, a few bHLH proteins are reported to be involved in modulation of nutrient homeostasis (Sivitz et al., 2012; Zhao et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, it is worth mentioning that although tremendous progress has been achieved concerning the functional characterization of bHLH genes in a diversity of plant species, the physiological role and regulatory function of many bHLH TFs, particularly those of non-model woody fruit trees, are still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Sweet orange (Citrus sinensis) accounts for more than half of the total citrus production worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, cold sensitivity is a major factor limiting sustainable development of the sweet orange industry, and there is considerable interest in fortifying the cold tolerance in this species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Due to unique reproductive barriers caused by polyembryony, sweet orange germplasm enhancement via traditional cross-breeding is difficult, and genetic engineering offers an alternative approach in the breeding pipeline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The published genome of sweet orange (Xu et al., 2013) provides a valuable resource to investigate bHLH family genes and to examine their potential roles in responses to cold stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we first carried out a genome-wide identification and analyses of bHLH genes in sweet orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Based on time-course expression patterns of the CsbHLH genes under cold stress, we focused on CsbHLH18, the most cold-inducible member. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Our results revealed that CsbHLH18 plays a positive role in cold tolerance, which was attributed, at least partly, to modulation of homeostasis of reactive oxygen species (ROS) by regulating antioxidant genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Our findings shed valuable light on functional elucidation of the bHLH genes in sweet orange, and underpin the exploration of genes of significance for genetic manipulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Plant materials and treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Seven-year-old sweet orange plants were grown in the open field under natural photoperiod conditions and watered twice a week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>For analysis of expression patterns of the CsbHLH genes, uniform and healthy fresh shoots excised from the plants were placed in conical flasks containing sterile deionized water for 24 h and kept in a growth room with a 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod at 25 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>For the cold treatment, the flasks were kept in a low-temperature (4 °C) growth chamber and the leaves were sampled at designated time points (0, 6, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The collected samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at –80 °C until further analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide identification and bioinformatics analysis of CsbHLH genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Putative bHLH genes were retrieved using the released sweet orange genome database (Xu et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Positions of the candidate genes in the chromosomes were determined using the Orange Genome Project database, while the distribution of the CsbHLH genes on the chromosomes was processed using MapInspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Genomic sequences with the same start and stop sites on the same chromosome were considered as one gene, and the longest coding sequence (CDS) was retained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>A gene structure map was constructed using the Gene Structure Display Server Program (Hu et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The online programs SMART (Letunic et al., 2012) and Pfam were used to predict the HLH domains; genes without the conserved HLH domains were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The amino acids of the bHLH domains were aligned using Clustal W (Chenna et al., 2003), while WEBLOGO (Crooks et al., 2004) was used to reveal the conserved motifs in the bHLH domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Based on the conserved domains of bHLH genes in sweet orange and A. thaliana (Toledo-Ortiz et al., 2003), a phylogenetic tree was constructed using the Neighbor–Joining method in MEGA5.0 (Tamura et al., 2011) with 1000 bootstrap replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction, RT–PCR, and qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from the leaves using TRIzol reagent (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions and then reversely transcribed to cDNA using a First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (TaKaRa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative reverse transcription–PCR (RT–PCR) analysis was carried out according to Shi et al. (2010) with the exception of using primers specific to the CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time RT–PCRs (qPCRs; 95 °C, 5 min; 95 °C, 10 s; 56–63 °C 30 s, 45 cycles) were conducted with the QuantStudio 7 Flex system (Applied Biosystems, USA) using the SYBR Premix ExTaq Green PCR Kit (QIAGEN, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The 10 μl qPCR solutions contained 5 μl of SYBR Green PCR Master Mix, 0.25 μM of forward and reverse primers, and 100 ng of cDNA template. Actin and Ubiquitin were used as internal reference genes for sweet orange and tobacco, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Relative expression levels of the examined genes were calculated using the 2−∆∆CT method (Livak and Schmittgen, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Four biological replicates were performed for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Gene-specific primers (Supplementary Table S1) were designed using the online NCBI Primer BLAST. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The CsbHLH18 CDS without the stop codon was cloned into the 101YFP (yellow fluorescent protein) vector at XbaI and SalI restriction sites, under the control of the Cauliflower mosaic virus 35S (CaMV 35S) promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>For transient expression analysis, the fusion construct (bHLH18–YFP) or the control vector (YFP) was co-transformed with a plasmid coding for a nuclear marker VirD2NLS fused to mCherry into tobacco (Nicotiana benthamiana) leaves by Agrobacterium tumefaciens infiltration based on a previous description (Kumar and Kirti, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The infiltrated plants were placed in the dark for 24 h and grown for an additional 2 d under a 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In addition, the infiltrated leaves were subjected to enzymatic digestion for isolation of mesophyll protoplasts as reported by Yoo et al. (2007) with slight modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Yellow (for YFP) and red (for mCherry) signals in the epidermis and protoplasts were observed using a laser scanning confocal microscope (Leica TCS-SP8, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional activation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The full length (FL) or three truncated fragments (F1, F2, or F3) of CsbHLH18 were PCR amplified and cloned into pGBKT7 (Clontech) to generate four constructs (pGBKT7-FL/F1/F2/F3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The fusion vectors and empty vector (pGBKT7), used as a negative control, were separately transformed into the yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) strain AH109 harboring a MEL1 reporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional activation activity of the transformed yeast cells was determined after incubation at 30 °C for 3 d on SD/-Trp or SD/-Trp/-His/-Ade medium supplemented with 4 mg ml–1 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indoxyl-α-d-galacto-pyranoside (X-α-gal, Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Transformation and characterization of transgenic plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The CDS of CsbHLH18 was amplified and ligated into the XbaI/BamHI sites of pBI121 (Clontech) to obtain an overexpression vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For construction of the RNAi vector, a 252 bp fragment was PCR amplified and integrated into the pHELLSGATE vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The constructs were verified by sequencing and introduced into A. tumefaciens strain GV3101 by heat shock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The overexpression vector was used to transform tobacco (N. nudicaulis), while the RNAi vector was transformed into trifoliate orange (Poncirus trifoliata). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Transformation of tobacco and P. trifoliata was carried out as previously reported (Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The transformants were selected on MS (for tobacco; Murashige and Skoog, 1962) or MT (for trifoliate orange; Murashige and Tucker, 1969) medium containing 10 μg ml–1 kanamycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The presence of the transgene was confirmed by genomic PCR according to a procedure reported by Gong et al. (2015), while expression levels of the transgene or endogenous bHLH18 in the positive lines was examined via both RT–PCR and qPCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s9"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cold tolerance assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Seeds of transgenic tobacco lines at the T2 generation and the wild type (WT) were germinated on wet filter papers under a 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod at 25 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Four days later, the seedlings were transferred to soil pots and kept in a growth chamber (16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod, 25 °C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For cold treatment, 2-week-old plants were shifted to a growth chamber set at 4 °C for 10 h, then at 0 °C for 8 h, and finally –2 °C for 2 h, followed by recovery at 25 °C for 15 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>In addition, 6-month-old tobacco plants were subjected to –2 °C for 3 h, and finally recovered for 12 d at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>As for cold tolerance assessment of P. trifoliata, seedlings of 5-month-old WT and RNAi lines were exposed to –4 °C for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Plant performance was monitored before and after the cold treatment, while survival rates (only for tobacco) were calculated after the recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Chlorophyll fluorescence was measured using an IMAGING-PAM chlorophyll fluorimeter (under a single saturating pulse of &gt;1800 μmol photons m–2 s–1), based on which Fv/Fm ratios were calculated using Imaging WinGegE software (Walz, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The leaves were collected after cold treatment for physiological measurement and gene expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s10"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Physiological analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Electrolyte leakage (EL) was analyzed essentially following an earlier report (Dahro et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Malondialdehyde (MDA) levels, expressed as nmol mg–1 protein, were determined based on a thiobarbituric acid (TBA) reaction (Liu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In brief, MDA was extracted by homogenizing 0.1 g of leaf powder in 1 ml of 20% (w/v) trichloroacetic acid (TCA), followed by centrifugation at 5000 rpm for 20 min at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A 1 ml aliquot of the supernatant was mixed with 1 ml of 20% TCA containing 0.5% TBA (w/v) and 100 µl of 4% butylated hydroxyl toluene in ethanol (v/v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The mixture was kept for 30 min in a water bath at 95 oC and then cooled down on ice for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 10 000 rpm for 5 min, absorbance of the supernatant was measured at 532 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>MDA concentration was calculated as described by Heath and Packer (1968). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>For extraction of proline, antioxidant enzymes, and H2O2, ~0.1 g of each frozen sample was homogenized in 1 ml of ice-cold extraction buffer (100 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7.8, containing 1% polyvinylpyrrolidone). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The homogenate was centrifuged at 12 000 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C and the resultant supernatant was collected for assays of proline, H2O2, and antioxidant enzymes, namely superoxide dismutase (SOD; EC 1.15.1.1), catalase (CAT; EC 1.11.1.6), and peroxidase (POD; EC 1.11.1.7), using relevant detection kits (A107 for proline, A064-1 for H2O2, A084-3 for POD, A001-1 for SOD, and A007-1 for CAT, Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Jiangsu, China) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Proline levels (µg g–1 FW) were monitored by reading the absorbance at 520 nm, while the absorbance of H2O2 was determined at a wavelength of 415 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Enzyme activity of the samples was recorded as U mg–1 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>One unit of SOD activity was defined as the amount of enzyme required for 50% inhibition of nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) as monitored at 550 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>One unit of POD activity was defined as an increase of 0.01 min–1 in the absorbance at 470 nm, while one unit of CAT activity was defined as a reduction of 0.01 min–1 in absorbance at 240 nm from the decomposition of H2O2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>O2·– measurement was performed according to Ma et al. (2016) with minor changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In brief, 0.5 g of leaf powder was homogenized in 5 ml of ice-cold 65 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 10 000 rpm for 15 min at 4 oC, 5 ml of the supernatant was mixed with 0.1 ml of 10 mM hydroxylamine hydrochloride and incubated for 20 min at 25 oC, followed by addition of 1 ml of 58 mM p-aminobenzenesulfonic acid and 1 ml of 7 mM α-naphthylamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The mixtures were incubated for 20 min at 25 oC and then centrifuged at 4000 rpm for 10 min, and the absorbance of the supernatant was measured at 530 nm to calculate the O2·– content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Absorbance in all measurements was read on a spectrophotometer (UV-1800, Shimadzu, Japan), and total protein concentrations were analyzed using the Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250 staining method (Bradford, 1976). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Histochemical staining of ROS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In situ accumulation of H2O2 and O2·– was examined by histochemical staining with 3,3'-diaminobenzidine (DAB) and NBT, respectively, according to Wang et al. (2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the leaves were placed in freshly prepared solutions of 1 mg ml–1 DAB (in 50 mM potassium phosphate, pH 3.8) or NBT (in 50 mM potassium phosphate, pH 7.8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After incubation for 12 h in the dark at room temperature, the chlorophyll was removed with 75% ethanol in a boiling water bath and the leaves were then photographed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s12"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The promoters of CsSOD (Cs8g15520.1), CsPOD (orange1.1t02041.1), and CsCAT (Cs3g27290.1) were acquired by genomic PCR with specific primers using sweet orange genomic DNA as template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Eight promoter fragments (S1/2 for CsSOD, P1/2/3 for CsPOD, and C1/2/3 for CsCAT) were amplified and ligated into the pAbAi vector to generate the baits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>mP1 is a mutated version of P1, in which the core sequence (CATTTG) of two E-box elements was mutated to GGCCGC and GATGCC, respectively, according to the method reported by Gong et al. (2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The full-length CsbHLH18 ORF was amplified and fused to the pGADT7-AD vector to create the prey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Y1H assay was performed following the manufacturer’s protocol (Clontech, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s13"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>EMSA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The CsHLH18 CDS was amplified and cloned into the pDONR222 vector (Invitrogen) using the Gateway system, followed by site-specific recombination into the pHMGWA vector (Busso et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The resulting construct (HIS-CsHLH18) was expressed in Escherichia coli strain BL21 (DE3) cells, and the fusion protein was purified using glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>EMSA was performed using the LightShift Chemiluminescent EMSA Kit (Pierce, IL, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The 39 bp biotin-labeled DNA probes containing either WT or mutated E-box elements, and unlabeled competitor DNAs were synthesized by Shanghai Sangon Biotechnology based on P1 sequences of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The binding reaction was performed for 20 min at room temperature in 20 μl of reaction buffer containing 1 μl of poly(dI–dC) (1 μg μl–1), competitor DNA at 150, 100, or 0 nM, 17.6 μg of recombinant protein, and 1 nM biotin-labeled probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Protein–DNA samples were separated in a 6% polyacrylamide gel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s14"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Transient expression assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The CDS of CsbHLH18 was ligated into the transient expression vector pGreen II 62-SK to generate an effector plasmid, while P1 or mP1 fragment were fused into the vector pGreen II 0800-LUC to produce the reporter plasmids (Hellens et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The effector, each of the two reporter constructs, and a helper plasmid pSoup (Vain et al., 2003) were co-transformed into A. tumefaciens GV3101. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Transient expression assay in N. benthamiana leaves was performed based on Espley et al. (2009) with minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The activities of firefly luciferase (LUC) and Renilla luciferase (REN) were measured using the Dual-Luciferase® Reporter Assay System (Promega, WI, USA) on an Infinite 200 Pro microplate reader (Tecan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The promoter activity was expressed as the ratio of LUC to REN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s15"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Cold treatment was repeated at least twice with three replicates for each line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>All the data were statistically evaluated using SPSS software (SPSS Statistics); statistical differences were determined using ANOVA based on Fisher’s LSD test, taking P&lt;0.05 as significantly different. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s16"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s17"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Identification and chromosomal distribution of sweet orange bHLH genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>A total of 96 potential candidates were retrieved when ‘bHLH’ was used as a query to search the sweet orange genome database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Non-redundant sequences were obtained by removing different transcripts from the same gene, and the longest sequences were used to confirm the presence of HLH domains based on analyses by SMART. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Finally, 56 genes were identified as putative bHLH members, of which 52 could be mapped to sweet orange chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>They were named according to their orders in the nine chromosomes (Fig. 1A; Supplementary Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The percentage of CsbHLH genes per chromosome varied from 0.15% on chromosome 6 to 0.37% on chromosomes 9, with an average of 0.24% (Table 1), indicating an uneven distribution of the bHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The greatest number of CsbHLH genes was on chromosome 5 (10 genes), followed by seven on chromosomes 1 and 2, six on chromosomes 3, 7, and 9, four on chromosome 4, and three on chromosomes 6 and 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The distribution ratio of CsbHLH genes among chromosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Chromosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Total number of genes </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Number of CsbHLH genes </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Percentage of CsbHLH genes in the chromosome (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>2403 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>0.29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>2780 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>2509 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>0.24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>1809 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>0.22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>3140 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>0.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>1960 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>0.15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>2926 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>0.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>1828 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>0.16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>1625 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>0.37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-01"><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Total numbers of genes on each of the nine sweet orange chromosome based on the NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Chromosomal distribution, sequence logos, and intron number within the bHLH domains of CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(A) Chromosomal distributions of CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The chromosomal positions of CsbHLH genes are mapped according to the sweet orange genome and named from CsbHLH1 to CsbHLH52 based on their order in the nine chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The chromosome numbers are indicated on the top of each chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>(B) Sequence logos of the bHLH domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The overall height of the stack indicates the sequence conservation of the corresponding amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The upper case letters below the logo indicate &gt;50% consensus amino acids among all CsbHLH domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(C) Intron distribution patterns, designated as Type I–VII, within the conserved bHLH domain of CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Intron positions are marked with inverted triangles and numbered (1–3) based on the reference gene PIF3 from A. thaliana. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The number and percentage of genes in each category are shown on either side of the intron patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(This figure is available in colour at JXB online.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06501"/></fig></sec><sec id="s18"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Sequence features of bHLH domains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment using the bHLH domains was carried out to understand the degree of conservation and relative frequency of corresponding amino acids at each position (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We observed that 22 amino acid residues were highly conserved with at least a 50% consensus ratio; in particular, the residues Arg-13, Arg-14, Leu-24, Pro-29, and Leu-56 had a consensus ratio &gt;90%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>It has been documented that the bHLH proteins can be generally classified into two subgroups according to their DNA binding characteristics: E-box-binding members (including G-box binders and non-G-box binders) and non-E-box-binding members (Toledo-Ortiz et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Among the CsbHLH proteins, 46 contain E-box-binding regions, including 33 G-box binders and 13 non-G-box binders (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In addition, we identified seven putative non-E-box-binding proteins that lack either or both of the two essential amino acids (Glu-12 and Arg-15) in the basic region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Of note, three CsbHLH proteins were categorized in the non-DNA-binding subgroup as they contain less than six amino acids and lack Glu-12 and Arg-15 in the basic regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Predicted DNA binding features based on the conserved bHLH domains of CsbHLH proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Predicted activity </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Predicted motif </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Numbers and percentage of proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>DNA binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain> E-box binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain> G-box binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>bHLH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>33 (58.93%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain> Non-G-box binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>bHLH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>13 (23.21%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain> Non-E-box binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>bHLH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>7 (12.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain> Total </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>53 (94.64%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Non-DNA binding </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>HLH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3 (5.36%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s19"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Intron distribution and phylogenetic relationship of CsbHLHs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>We next analyzed the intron/exon structures in the conserved bHLH domains of the CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>There are seven patterns of intron distribution, with intron number ranging from 0 to 3 (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Of the CsbHLHs, 86% have introns in the conserved domains (patterns I–VI), and 80% had at least one highly conserved intron position (patterns I–IV) compared with the reference gene PIF3 from A. thaliana. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Only 5% of the CsbHLH genes had different intron insertions within the conserved domains (patterns V and VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Family members without intron insertions in their bHLH domains accounted for 14% (pattern VII). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Pattern IV was the most common type (~48%), followed by pattern I (29%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>To get a better understanding of the evolutionary relationship and classification of the CsbHLH members, a Neighbor–Joining phylogenetic tree was generated based on amino acid sequences of the bHLH domains from A. thaliana and sweet orange (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The bHLH proteins can be clustered into 21 subfamilies, but subfamilies 11 and 13 were absent from sweet orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In addition, gene structure analysis revealed that the CsbHLH genes from the same subgroups share similar structures (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of bHLH TFs constructed based on bHLH domains from Arabidopsis thaliana (circles, prefixed by At) and Citrus sinensis (stars, prefixed by Cs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The lines with numbers represent different subfamilies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>(This figure is available in colour at JXB online.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06502"/></fig></sec><sec id="s20"><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Expression profiles of CsbHLHs under cold treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>To gain insights into the potential functions of the CsbHLH genes, we analyzed the expression patterns of all 56 genes under cold stress by semi-quantitative RT–PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Sixteen genes (CsbHLH1, 3, 6, 7, 11, 12, 17, 19, 28, 29, 30, 32, 45, 50, 51, and 56) were not expressed at detectable levels (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>S2), while a total of 40 CsbHLH genes showed alteration of transcript levels in response to the cold treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The expression patterns of the genes varied among different members. CsbHLH2, CsbHLH5, CsbHLH9, CsbHLH15, CsbHLH16, CsbHLH21, CsbHLH24, CsbHLH27, CsbHLH33, CsbHLH35, CsbHLH37, CsbHLH38, CsbHLH39, CsbHLH42, CsbHLH44, CsbHLH47, CsbHLH48, and CsbHLH54 were down-regulated by cold, while CsbHLH4, CsbHLH18, CsbHLH22, CsbHLH26, CsbHLH34, CsbHLH36, CsbHLH41, CsbHLH43, CsbHLH46, and CsbHLH49 showed increased expression levels during the cold treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>To confirm the RT–PCR results, nine up-regulated genes were further analyzed using qPCR, which largely validated the semi-quantitative PCR results, indicating that these genes are truly responsive to the cold stress (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Of the cold-responsive genes, transcript levels of CsbHLH18 were drastically and progressively elevated by the cold stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it was chosen for further functional analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of CsbHLH genes under cold treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR was carried out to examine the relative expression levels of nine CsbHLH genes (CsbHLH2, CsbHLH4, CsbHLH18, CsbHLH22, CsbHLH26, CsbHLH34, CsbHLH36, CsbHLH41, and CsbHLH46) in response to cold stress. Actin was used as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Transcript levels of the tested genes were calculated using the 2−∆∆CT method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Error bars indicated SDs, and each of the samples had three technical replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06503"/></fig></sec><sec id="s21"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18 localizes to the nucleus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>To examine the subcellular distribution of the CsbHLH18 protein, the fusion vector (CsbHLH18–YFP) and the control vector (YFP) were transiently expressed in tobacco leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Confocal imaging of the epidermis showed that the YFP alone was detected throughout the entire cell, while the CsbHLH18–YFP fusion protein localized exclusively in the nucleus (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>To verify the subcellular localization using epidermis, YFP signals in tobacco protoplasts were also detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>As expected, YFP protein was observed in both the nucleus and cytoplasm in the control, whereas CsbHLH18–YFP was only detected in the nucleus (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Localization in the nucleus was confirmed using co-transformation of a nucleus marker gene fused to mCherry in both epidermis and protoplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that CsbHLH18 is a nuclear protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization of CsbHLH18 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(A, B) Confocal images showing yellow (for YFP) and red (for mCherry) fluorescence signals in epidermal cells (A) and protoplasts (B) isolated from the infiltrated tobacco (N. benthamiana) leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Tobacco leaves were agroinfiltrated with YFP (yellow fluorescent protein) empty control or CsbHLH18–YFP fusion protein, along with a nuclear marker gene VirD2NLS fused to mCherry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Scale bars=10 µm </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06504"/></fig></sec><sec id="s22"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18 possesses transcriptional activation activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>To determine whether CsbHLH18 has transcriptional activation activity, we used a heterologous yeast expression system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The FL or three truncated fragments (F1, F2, and F3) of CsbHLH18 were fused to pGBKT7 to generate four effectors, which were separately transferred into the yeast containing a MEL1 reporter (Fig. 5A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>All of the yeast cells grew well on the SD medium lacking tryptophan (SD/-Trp), whereas only yeast cells transformed with the effectors containing FL and F1 grew and displayed GAL4 activity on the medium supplemented with X-α-gal (Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that CsbHLH18 has transcriptional activation activity and the F1 region is necessary for the transactivation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional activity assay of CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic diagrams of the full length (FL) and three truncated fragments (F1, F2, and F3) of CsbHLH18 used for constructing vectors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(B) Effectors and reporter used for transcriptional activation activity assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The FL and the three fragments (F1, F2, and F3) of CsbHLH18 were introduced into the pGBKT7 vector, generating four effectors (pGBKT7-FL/F1/F2/F3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>(C) Growth of yeast cells (strain AH109) transformed with each of the four vectors or pGBKT7 empty vector (used as a negative control) on SD/-Trp or SD/-Trp/-His/-Ade with addition of X-α-gal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The layout of the effectors is shown in the pie chart on the left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>(This figure is available in colour at JXB online.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06505"/></fig></sec><sec id="s23"><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of CsbHLH18 enhances cold tolerance in transgenic tobacco </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the function of CsbHLH18 in cold tolerance, we generated transgenic tobacco plants overexpressing CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Two transgenic lines (#5 and #40), which had different overexpression levels of CsbHLH18 (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>S3), were selected for cold tolerance assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>No phenotypic differences were observed between the WT and transgenic lines without cold stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>When 2-week-old plants were subjected to freezing treatment, the WT exhibited a more severe water-soaking phenotype compared with the transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>After growth recovery at ambient temperature for 15 h, 80–90% of the transgenic plants recovered, whereas the survival rate of the WT was only 29% (Fig. 6A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>In addition, leaf chlorophyll fluorescence imaging of the WT was prominently repressed relative to the transgenic lines after the freezing treatment and after the recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile,The Fv/Fm ratio of the WT was significantly lower than those of the transgenic plants (Fig. 6C, D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of CsbHLH18 confers enhanced cold tolerance to transgenic tobacco. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>(A) Phenotypes of 2-week-old plants of transgenic lines (#5 and #40) and the wild type (WT) before and after freezing treatment (–2 oC for 2 h) and 15 h after growth recovery at ambient temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>(B) Survival rates of WT and transgenic plants after the growth recovery, which is calculated based on the ratio of recovered plants to the total number of tested plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>(C, D) Chlorophyll fluorescence imaging (C) and Fv/Fm ratios (D) of transgenic lines and the WT after the freezing treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>(E) Phenotypes of 6-week-old plants of transgenic lines and the WT before and after freezing treatment, followed by growth recovery for 12 d at ambient temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>(F, G) Electrolyte leakage (F) and proline content (G) of transgenic lines and the WT, measured after the freezing treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent SDs for three independent replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate significant differences between the WT and the transgenic lines (**P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06506"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Likewise, when 6-week-old seedlings were exposed to freezing treatment, the leaves of transgenic lines showed a less severe water-soaking phenotype compared with the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Most of the transgenic plants recovered after being returned to room temperature for 12 d, while only a few WT plants recovered (Fig. 6E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>EL was significantly higher in the WT (90%) than in the transgenic lines (Fig. 6F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>We also measured levels of proline, which has been reported to act as an important stress indicator (Szabados and Savouré, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The transgenic lines had significantly higher proline content than the WT after the cold treatment (Fig. 6G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that overexpression of CsbHLH18 led to enhanced cold tolerance in the transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s24"><title><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The overexpressing plants accumulate less ROS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>ROS are known to be responsible for causing oxidative stress that negatively influences cell integrity (Choudhury et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Since the transgenic lines exhibited greater cold tolerance than the WT, we examined the accumulation of two major ROS, H2O2 and O2·–. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Histochemical staining showed that the WT leaves showed deeper staining by DAB and NBT than those of the transgenic lines (Fig. 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Histochemical detection of ROS was further confirmed by quantitative measurements, which showed that cellular levels of H2O2 and O2·– were lower in the transgenic lines than in the WT (Fig. 7B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Both histochemical staining and measurement demonstrate that the transgenic lines accumulated lower levels of ROS in response to cold stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels in wild-type (WT) plants and transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>(A) Histochemical staining with DAB (upper panels) and NBT (bottom panels) for detection of in situ accumulation of H2O2 and O2·–, respectively, in the transgenic lines (#5 and #40) and the WT after cold treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>(B, C) Quantitative measurement of H2O2 (B) and O2·– (C) in the transgenic and WT plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent SDs for three independent replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate significant differences between the WT and transgenic lines (*P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>(This figure is available in colour at JXB online.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06507"/></fig></sec><sec id="s25"><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The transgenic lines exhibit higher activities and expression levels of antioxidant enzymes and genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Antioxidant enzymes play crucial roles in detoxification of ROS and contribute to ROS scavenging under abiotic stresses (Miller et al., 2010; Huang et al., 2013; Zhang et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Activities of the antioxidant enzymes POD, SOD, and CAT were thus measured after the cold treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Activities of all three enzymes were significantly higher in the transgenic plants than in the WT (Fig. 8A–C), which is consistent with the lower ROS accumulation in the former lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Activities and gene expression levels of antioxidant enzymes in the transgenic lines and the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>(A–C) Activities of POD (A), SOD (B), and CAT (C) in the transgenic lines and WT measured after cold treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>(D–F) Expression levels of NtPOD (D), NtSOD (E), and NtCAT (F) in the transgenic lines and the WT. Ubiquitin was used as an internal reference control, and transcript levels of the tested genes were calculated using the 2−∆∆CT method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent SDs for three independent replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate significant differences between the WT and transgenic lines (*P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06508"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>To further understand molecular mechanisms underlying the enhanced cold tolerance by overexpressing CsbHLH18, mRNA abundance of the antioxidant genes NtSOD, NtPOD, and NtCAT in the WT and transgenic lines was analyzed using qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Transcript levels of the three tested genes were higher in the transgenic lines than in the WT (Fig. 8D–F), indicating that overexpression of CsbHLH18 led to an up-regulation of the antioxidant genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s26"><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Silencing of bHLH18 in trifoliate orange leads to elevated cold susceptibility and excessive accumulation of ROS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>To further elucidate the role of bHLH18 in cold tolerance, we attempted to knock down the bHLH18 of trifoliate orange (P. trifoliata) using RNAi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>We selected trifoliate orange for this study for the following reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>First, trifoliate orange is closely related to sweet orange; CsbHLH18 shares &gt;98% nucleotide sequence identity with its counterpart gene of trifoliate orange (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Secondly, it is easy to obtain seeds for production of in vitro seedlings so as to acquire enough shoot segments for genetic transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>We obtained a number of positive transgenic lines by Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of shoot segments (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>RT–PCR and qPCR analyses indicated that expression levels of bHLH18 were dramatically decreased in two putative RNAi lines (#13 and #71) compared with the WT (Fig. 9A), indicating that bHLH18 was successfully silenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>We then measured transcript levels of the antioxidant genes CAT, SOD, and POD in the RNAi lines, and found that the three genes were prominently down-regulated relative to those of the WT (Fig. 9B–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The RNAi lines were morphologically similar to the WT under normal growth conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>However, when subjected to freezing treatment at –4 °C for 24 h, the two RNAi lines displayed more severe leaf wilting (Fig. 9E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>In the absence of stress, no difference in chlorophyll fluorescence imaging and Fv/Fm ratios was observed between the tested lines, whereas the RNAi lines displayed a noticeable reduction of chlorophyll fluorescence and Fv/Fm ratios relative to the WT upon exposure to cold stress (Fig. 9F–H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>In addition, levels of EL and MDA were significantly higher in the RNAi plants than in the WT (Fig. 9I–J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, histochemical staining with DAB and NBT showed that the RNAi lines accumulated a greater amount of H2O2 and O2·–, respectively, than did the WT (Fig. 9K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that silencing of bHLH18 by RNAi elevated cold sensitivity in trifoliate orange. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Silencing of bHLH18 leads to increased cold sensitivity in trifoliate orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(A) Expression levels of bHLH18 in the two RNAi lines (#13 and #71) and the wild type (WT) based on qPCR and RT–PCR (inset image) analyses. Actin was used as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>(B–D) Transcript levels of trifoliate orange CAT (B), SOD (C), and POD (D) in the RNAi lines and the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>(E, F) Phenotype (E) and fluorescence imaging (F) of WT and RNAi lines before and after freezing treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>(G, H) Fv/Fm ratios of the WT and RNAi lines before (G) and after (H) freezing treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>(I–K) Electrolyte leakage (I), MDA levels (J), and in situ accumulation of H2O2 and O2·– (K) in the RNAi lines and the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Scale bars=1 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate significant differences between the WT and the RNAi lines (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>(This figure is available in colour at JXB online.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06509"/></fig></sec><sec id="s27"><title><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18 directly and specifically binds to and activates the promoter of CsPOD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>As the antioxidant genes were up-regulated in the overexpressing lines but down-regulated in the RNAi lines, we speculate that the antioxidant genes may be regulated by CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>To verify this assumption, we obtained the promoter sequences of CsCAT (Cs3g27290.1), CsPOD (orange1.1t02041.1), and CsSOD (Cs8g15520.1), and found that there were four, three, and eight E-box elements on the promoters of CsCAT, CsSOD, and CsPOD, respectively (Fig. 10A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Interactions between CsbHLH18 and the promoters were investigated by Y1H assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>To this end, full-length cDNA of CsbHLH18 was fused with the GAL4AD to generate the prey vector, while bait vectors were constructed using eight partial fragments containing the E-box elements from the three gene promoters, three for CsCAT, two for CsSOD, and three for CsPOD (Fig. 10B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Y1H assay indicated that all the yeast cells grew well on SD/-Leu/-Ura medium, whereas only the positive control and yeast cells transformed with the effector and the P1 bait grew normally on the medium supplemented with Aureobasidin A (AbA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>However, when the two E-box elements of the P1 fragment were mutated from CATTTG to GGCCGC and GATGCC, growth of the yeast cells was completely inhibited (Fig. 10C), indicating that CsbHLH18 interacted with the P1 region of the CsPOD promoter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 10.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18 binds to and activates the promoter of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic diagrams of the promoters of CsCAT, CsSOD, and CsPOD, in which the E-box elements are denoted using red circles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The segments marked with C1/2/3, P1/2/3, and S1/2 represent the promoter fragments used in the yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>(B) The prey and bait vectors used for Y1H assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>mP1 is a mutated version of P1, in which the two E-box elements were mutated by PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>(C) Growth of yeast cells of positive control (p53-AbAi+pGAD-p53), negative control (bait + pGADT7), and co-transformants (bait+prey) on SD/-Leu/-Ura medium supplemented without (left panels) or with (right panels) AbA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>(D) EMSA assay using the affinity-purified fusion protein HIS-CsbHLH18 incubated with biotin-labeled probe containing the wild-type or mutated E-box element, with or without unlabeled competitor DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The bound DNA–protein complex is shown by an open arrow, while the solid arrow indicates the free probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>(E) Schematic diagrams of effector and reporter constructs used for transient expression assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>(F) Transient expression assay of the promoter activity using the tobacco protoplast system, based on the LUC/REN ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>LUC/REN of the control, in the absence of the effector, was considered as 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate that the value is significantly different from that of the control (***P&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery06510"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>In order to further confirm the Y1H result, EMSA was conducted using HIS-CsbHLH18 fusion protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>There was no band shift when only the labeled probe was added to the reaction, whereas a DNA-binding band was detected when the purified fusion protein was incubated with the probe containing the WT E-box. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Addition of a 100- or 150-fold excess of unlabeled competitor DNA in the reaction could compete with the labeled DNA for binding with the protein in a dosage-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>In addition, band shift was completely abolished when the E-box element in the probe was mutated (Fig. 10D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Y1H assay and EMSA indicate that CsbHLH18 directly and specifically binds to the promoter of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the interaction between CsbHLH18 and the CsPOD promoter, a transient expression assay was performed using CsbHLH18 for creating the effector vector and P1 and mP1 fragments for generating the reporter vectors (Fig. 10E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The LUC/REN ratio of tobacco protoplasts co-transformed with the effector and the P1 reporter containing the WT E-box was drastically elevated relative to the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>In contrast, when the E-box element was mutated in the mP1 reporter, the LUC/REN ratio was returned to the control level (Fig. 10F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that CsbHLH18 could activate the promoter of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s28"><title><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Many plant TF families that participate in stress responses have been identified and characterized, such as the MYB, WRKY, CBF/DREB, and bZIPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>However, relatively little is known about the role of bHLH proteins in stress response when compared with the abundant information garnered from other families of TFs (Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>A genome-wide exploration of bHLH proteins in any species, and functional characterization of some of the family members, can therefore provide a better understanding of this TF family in stress signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>In this study, 56 non-redundant sweet orange bHLH genes were identified from the available sweet orange database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>It has to be mentioned that the number of bHLH proteins in sweet orange is smaller in comparison with that in other plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have revealed the presence of 147 bHLH genes in A. thaliana (Toledo-Ortiz et al., 2003), 167 in rice (Li et al., 2006), and 117 in sacred lotus (Hudson and Hudson, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>The exact explanation is lacking for this phenomenon at this stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>One possibility is due to fewer recent whole-genome duplications in sweet orange, which has been previously reported in earlier studies on other TFs (Hudson and Hudson, 2014; Hou et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Chromosomal distribution analysis indicates that the CsbHLH genes were unevenly distributed among the nine chromosomes, whereas four members could not be definitely placed in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Currently, ~87% of the sweet orange genome has been published; therefore, it is possible that availability of a more detailed genome sequence in the future may help to locate the four genes in the exact chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Alignment of all the bHLH domains, which are necessary for the formation of homodimers or heterodimers, showed that the Leu-24 and Leu-56 residues in the helix regions were completely conserved, compared with 99% and 97% in tomato (Sun et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Dimerization could involve interactions between the bHLH proteins themselves, but also between bHLH proteins and other TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>The heterodimer partners include R2R3-MYBs, BAR1-BES1, and AP2s (Goff et al., 1992; Yin et al., 2005; Dubos et al., 2008; Chandler et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>This type of dimerization has been previously shown to change or expand the diversity of intermolecular interactions and create new functions by recognizing new DNA binding sites (Heim et al., 2003; Toledo-Ortiz et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Gene expression profiles can provide important clues to understand their potential biological functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that genes induced by a given abiotic stress may play a positive role in modulation of tolerance to this stress (J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Li et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>To identify members that are induced by cold stress, the transcriptional patterns of CsbHLHs were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Based on the strong and continuous induction of CsbHLH18 in response to cold, we generated tobacco overexpressing plants, and the transgenic lines showed enhanced tolerance to cold stress when compared with the WT plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, knockdown of the bHLH18 counterpart in trifoliate orange led to enhanced sensitivity of the RNAi lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that CsbHLH18 is a positive regulator of the tolerance to cold stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>It is worth mentioning that the homologous gene of CsbHLH18 in Arabidopsis or other plants has not yet been studied in relation to cold stress, although a few bHLH TFs have been proven to play important roles in abiotic stresses (Seo et al., 2011; Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Hence, our findings provide a new avenue to understand the implication of bHLH18 in cold tolerance and offer a new candidate gene with potential for genetic engineering in an effort to improve abiotic stress tolerance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Cold stress leads to a plethora of physiological effects that may be detrimental to plant cells, one of which is accumulation of ROS that are toxic molecules causing oxidative damages to cellular components, including proteins, lipids, and DNA (Miller et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>ROS may be maintained at a low level under favorable growth conditions, but are dramatically elevated when plants are challenged by abiotic stresses, leading to ROS-associated injuries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>It is thus conceivable that the levels of ROS can be considered as an indicator of the magnitude of stress severity and stress tolerance, and a lower level of ROS following stress exposure is generally regarded as better tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Under this scenario, the ROS level is always used for examining the difference in stress tolerance capacity between various plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>In this study, we found that the transgenic overexpressing lines accumulated prominently less H2O2 and O2·– compared with the WT after the cold treatment, as revealed by both histochemical staining and quantitative measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Of note, the lower ROS levels in the transgenic lines are consistent with their better growth phenotype and less serious membrane damage (indicated by lower EL), implying that accumulation of lower ROS levels constitutes a physiological mechanism partly, if not fully, underlying CsbHLH18-mediated cold tolerance in the transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>This is further supported by concurrent observation of a noticeable elevation of ROS levels and enhanced cold susceptibility in the RNAi lines with knockdown of trifoliate orange bHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>It is well known that the ROS homeostasis during stress is largely dependent on the balance between ROS generation and scavenging (Miller et al., 2010; Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>ROS-scavenging enzymes, such as POD, SOD, and CAT, are indispensable for ROS detoxification so that plants can combat the ROS-associated cellular damage and maintain better survival under stressful conditions (Miller et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Herein, the transgenic lines displayed significantly higher antioxidant enzyme activities than the WT under cold conditions, indicating that the transgenic plants may have a more powerful ROS-scavenging machinery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>The greater enzyme activities may explain the lower accumulation of ROS in the transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, transcript levels of all three antioxidant genes were considerably suppressed in the RNAi lines, consistent with the increase of ROS levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>We thus hypothesize that bHLH18 functions in cold tolerance by controlling ROS accumulation via modulation of the antioxidant-scavenging machinery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>It is known that the bHLHs can function in the transcriptional regulation network by binding to the E-box elements within the prompter region of their target genes (Huang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>For example, MYC2 showed a specific association with the E-box of the PLETHORA gene during jasmonic acid-mediated modulation of the root stem cell niche in Arabidoposis (Chen et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, AtbHLH122 was reported to play a role in abiotic stress tolerance via repressing the expression of CYP707A3 by binding to the E-box elements in its promoter (Liu et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the fact that the three antioxidant genes were noticeably up-regulated in the overexpressing lines but down-regulated in the RNAi lines seems to suggest that they may serve as targets of CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, despite the existence of E-box elements in the promoters of the three antioxidant genes, CsbHLH18 could only bind to and activate the promoter of CsPOD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>This finding indicates that CsPOD is a direct target gene of CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the absence of interaction between CsbHLH18 and promoters of CsSOD and CsCAT genes is intriguing as their transcript levels were altered in the same manner as that of CsPOD in the transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>One of the reasons for this phenomenon is the difference in the nucleotides surrounding the E-box elements, which has been reported to influence the three-dimensional structure of DNA-binding sites (Gordân et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that CsbHLH18 is not directly related to transcriptional control of these two genes, which are otherwise regulated by other unidentified TFs that are under the control of CsbHLH18, thus constituting a complex regulatory cascade; this speculation needs to be verified in the future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>It is worth mentioning that such a phenomenon has been previously reported for other TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>For example, Jiang et al. (2012) showed that overexpression of AtWKRY57 up-regulated RD29A, NCED3, and ABA3, but only two of these genes (RD29A and NCED3) were confirmed to be directly regulated by AtWRKY57. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>To conclude, we identified 56 bHLH proteins in sweet orange using the released genome database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Most of the TFs are responsive to cold treatment, of which CsbHLH18 was particularly induced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of CsbHLH18 led to enhanced cold tolerance, while knock-down of bHLH18 in trifoliate orange promoted cold susceptibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>CsbHLH18-mediated cold tolerance might be due, at least in part, to modulation of the antioxidant system by regulating, directly or indirectly, the antioxidant genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Our study provides new insight into the physiological mechanism and regulatory function of the bHLH family members and also provides valuable knowledge to understand the plant cold response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s29"><title><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Gene structures of the CsbHLH genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of CsbHLH genes in response to cold stress, as analyzed by RT–PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Generation and molecular identification of transgenic tobacco plants overexpressing CsbHLH18. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the nucleotide sequences of bHLH18 from sweet orange and trifoliate orange. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>S5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Transformation and molecular characterization of trifoliate orange expressing an RNAi vector. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Table S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>The list of CsbHLH members identified in the sweet orange genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Data</label><media xlink:href="ery065_suppl_supplementary_data.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31572100, 31320103908, and 31521092), the National Key Research and Development Program of China, and the Hubei Provincial Natural Science Foundation for Innovative Group (2017CFA018). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain> AtchleyWR, TerhalleW, DressA 1999 Positional dependence, cliques, and predictive motifs in the bHLH protein domain. Journal of Molecular Evolution48, 501–516.10198117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain> BradfordMM 1976 A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein–dye binding. Analytical Biochemistry72, 248–254.942051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain> BuckMJ, AtchleyWR 2003 Phylogenetic analysis of plant basic helix–loop–helix proteins. Journal of Molecular Evolution56, 742–750.12911037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain> BussoD, Delagoutte-BussoB, MorasD 2005 Construction of a set Gateway-based destination vectors for high-throughput cloning and expression screening in Escherichia coli. Analytical Biochemistry343, 313–321.15993367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain> Carretero-PauletL, GalstyanA, Roig-VillanovaI, Martínez-GarcíaJF, Bilbao-CastroJR, RobertsonDL 2010 Genome-wide classification and evolutionary analysis of the bHLH family of transcription factors in Arabidopsis, poplar, rice, moss, and algae. Plant Physiology153, 1398–1412.20472752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain> ChandlerJW, ColeM, FlierA, WerrW 2009 BIM1, a bHLH protein involved in brassinosteroid signalling, controls Arabidopsis embryonic patterning via interaction with DORNROSCHEN and DORNROSCHEN-LIKE. Plant Molecular Biology69, 57–68.18830673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain> ChenQ, SunJ, ZhaiQet al 2011 The basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor MYC2 directly represses PLETHORA expression during jasmonate-mediated modulation of the root stem cell niche in Arabidopsis. The Plant Cell23, 3335–3352.21954460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain> ChennaR, SugawaraH, KoikeT, LopezR, GibsonTJ, HigginsDG, ThompsonJD 2003 Multiple sequence alignment with the Clustal series of programs. Nucleic Acids Research31, 3497–3500.12824352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain> ChinnusamyV, OhtaM, KanrarS, LeeBH, HongX, AgarwalM, ZhuJK 2003 ICE1: a regulator of cold-induced transcriptome and freezing tolerance in Arabidopsis. Genes and Development17, 1043–1054.12672693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain> ChoudhuryFK, RiveroRM, BlumwaldE, MittlerR 2017 Reactive oxygen species, abiotic stress and stress combination. The Plant Journal90, 856–867.27801967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain> CrooksGE, HonG, ChandoniaJM, BrennerSE 2004 WebLogo: a sequence logo generator. Genome Research14, 1188–1190.15173120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain> DahroB, WangF, PengT, LiuJH 2016 PtrA/NINV, an alkaline/neutral invertase gene of Poncirus trifoliata, confers enhanced tolerance to multiple abiotic stresses by modulating ROS levels and maintaining photosynthetic efficiency. BMC Plant Biology16, 76.27025596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain> DubosC, Le GourrierecJ, BaudryAet al 2008 MYBL2 is a new regulator of flavonoid biosynthesis in Arabidopsis thaliana. The Plant Journal55, 940–953.18532978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain> EspleyRV, BrendoliseC, ChagnéDet al 2009 Multiple repeats of a promoter segment causes transcription factor autoregulation in red apples. The Plant Cell21, 168–183.19151225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain> FengXM, ZhaoQ, ZhaoLL, QiaoY, XieXB, LiHF, YaoYX, YouCX, HaoYJ 2012 The cold-induced basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor gene MdCIbHLH1 encodes an ICE-like protein in apple. BMC Plant Biology12, 22.22336381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain> FriedrichsenDM, NemhauserJ, MuramitsuT, MaloofJN, AlonsoJ, EckerJR, FuruyaM, ChoryJ 2002 Three redundant brassinosteroid early response genes encode putative bHLH transcription factors required for normal growth. Genetics162, 1445–1456.12454087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain> GoffSA, ConeKC, ChandlerVL 1992 Functional analysis of the transcriptional activator encoded by the maize B gene: evidence for a direct functional interaction between two classes of regulatory proteins. Genes and Development6, 864–875.1577278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain> GolldackD, LükingI, YangO 2011 Plant tolerance to drought and salinity: stress regulating transcription factors and their functional significance in the cellular transcriptional network. Plant Cell Reports30, 1383–1391.21476089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain> GongX, ZhangJ, HuJ, WangW, WuH, ZhangQ, LiuJH 2015 FcWRKY70, a WRKY protein of Fortunella crassifolia, functions in drought tolerance and modulates putrescine synthesis by regulating arginine decarboxylase gene. Plant, Cell and Environment38, 2248–2262. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain> GordânR, ShenN, DrorI, ZhouT, HortonJ, RohsR, BulykML 2013 Genomic regions flanking E-box binding sites influence DNA binding specificity of bHLH transcription factors through DNA shape. Cell Reports3, 1093–1104.23562153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain> HeathRL, PackerL 1968 Photoperoxidation in isolated chloroplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Kinetics and stoichiometry of fatty acid peroxidation. Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics125, 189–198.5655425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain> HeimMA, JakobyM, WerberM, MartinC, WeisshaarB, BaileyPC 2003 The basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor family in plants: a genome-wide study of protein structure and functional diversity. Molecular Biology and Evolution20, 735–747.12679534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain> HellensR, AllanA, FrielE, BolithoK, GraftonK, TempletonM, KarunairetnamS, LaingW 2005 Transient expression vectors for functional genomics, quantification of promoter activity and RNA silencing in plants. Plant Methods1, 13.16359558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain> HouXJ, LiSB, LiuSR, HuCG, ZhangJZ 2014 Genome-wide classification and evolutionary and expression analyses of citrus MYB transcription factor families in sweet orange. PLoS One9, e112375.25375352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain> HuB, JinJP, GuoAY, ZhangH, LuoJC, GaoG 2015 GSDS 2.0: an upgraded gene feature visualization server. Bioinformatics31, 1296–1297.25504850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> HuangXS, WangW, ZhangQ, LiuJH 2013 A basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor, PtrbHLH, of Poncirus trifoliata confers cold tolerance and modulates peroxidase-mediated scavenging of hydrogen peroxide. Plant Physiology162, 1178–1194.23624854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain> HudsonK, HudsonM 2014 The basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor family in the sacred lotus, Nelumbo nucifera. Tropical Plant Biology7, 65–70. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain> ItoS, SongYH, Josephson-DayAR, MillerRJ, BretonG, OlmsteadRG, ImaizumiT 2012 FLOWERING BHLH transcriptional activators control expression of the photoperiodic ﬂowering regulator CONSTANS in Arabidopsis. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA109, 3582–3587. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain> JiangY, LiangG, YuD 2012 Activated expression of WRKY57 confers drought tolerance in Arabidopsis. Molecular Plant5, 1375–1388.22930734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain> KiribuchiK, JikumaruY, KakuHet al 2005 Involvement of the basic helix–loop–helix transcription factor RERJ1 in wounding and drought stress responses in rice plants. Bioscience, Biotechnology, and Biochemistry69, 1042–1044. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain> KumarKR, KirtiPB 2010 A mitogen-activated protein kinase, AhMPK6 from peanut localizes to the nucleus and also induces defense responses upon transient expression in tobacco. Plant Physiology and Biochemistry48, 481–486.20409725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain> LataC, PrasadM 2011 Role of DREBs in regulation of abiotic stress responses in plants. Journal of Experimental Botany62, 4731–4748.21737415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain> LetunicI, DoerksT, BorkP 2012 SMART 7: recent updates to the protein domain annotation resource. Nucleic Acids Research40, D302–D305.22053084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain> LiH, DingY, ShiY, ZhangX, ZhangS, GongZ, YangS 2017 MPK3- and MPK6-mediated ICE1 phosphorylation negatively regulates ICE1 stability and freezing tolerance in Arabidopsis. Developmental Cell43, 630–642.e4.29056553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain> LiJ, LiY, YinZet al 2017 OsASR5 enhances drought tolerance through a stomatal closure pathway associated with ABA and H2O2 signalling in rice. Plant Biotechnology Journal15, 183–196.27420922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain> LiX, DuanX, JiangHet al 2006 Genome-wide analysis of basic/helix–loop–helix transcription factor family in rice and Arabidopsis. Plant Physiology141, 1167–1184.16896230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain> LiuJH, NadaK, HondaC, KitashibaH, WenXP, PangXM, MoriguchiT 2006 Polyamine biosynthesis of apple callus under salt stress: importance of the arginine decarboxylase pathway in stress response. Journal of Experimental Botany57, 2589–2599.16825316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain> LiuW, TaiH, LiS, GaoW, ZhaoM, XieC, LiWX 2014 bHLH122 is important for drought and osmotic stress resistance in Arabidopsis and in the repression of ABA catabolism. New Phytologist201, 1192–1204.24261563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain> LivakKJ, SchmittgenTD 2001 Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method. Methods25, 402–408.11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain> MaL, TianT, LinR, DengXW, WangH, LiG 2016 Arabidopsis FHY3 and FAR1 regulate light-induced myo-inositol biosynthesis and oxidative stress responses by transcriptional activation of MIPS1. Molecular Plant9, 541–557.26714049 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain> MenandB, YiK, JouannicS, HoffmannL, RyanE, LinsteadP, SchaeferDG, DolanL 2007 An ancient mechanism controls the development of cells with a rooting function in land plants. Science316, 1477–1480.17556585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain> MillerG, SuzukiN, Ciftci-YilmazS, MittlerR 2010 Reactive oxygen species homeostasis and signalling during drought and salinity stresses. Plant, Cell and Environment33, 453–467. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain> MurashigeT, SkoogF 1962 A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with tobacco tissue cultures. Physiologia Plantarum15, 473–497. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain> MurashigeT, TuckerDPH 1969 Growth factor requirements of citrus tissue culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>In: ChapmanHD, ed. Proceedings of First International Citrus Symposium, Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>3 Riverside, CA: University of California Press, 1155–1161. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain> NairSK, BurleySK 2000 Functional genomics: Recognizing DNA in the library. Nature404, 715–718.10783871 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain> RiechmannJL, HeardJ, MartinGet al 2000 Arabidopsis transcription factors: genome-wide comparative analysis among eukaryotes. Science290, 2105–2110.11118137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain> SeoJS, JooJ, KimMJet al 2011 OsbHLH148, a basic helix–loop–helix protein, interacts with OsJAZ proteins in a jasmonate signaling pathway leading to drought tolerance in rice. The Plant Journal65, 907–921.21332845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain> ShiJ, FuXZ, PengT, HuangXS, FanQJ, LiuJH 2010 Spermine pretreatment confers dehydration tolerance of citrus in vitro plants via modulation of antioxidative capacity and stomatal response. Tree Physiology30, 914–922.20462936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain> SunH, FanHJ, LingHQ 2015 Genome-wide identification and characterization of the bHLH gene family in tomato. BMC Genomics16, 9.25612924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain> SivitzAB, HermandV, CurieC, VertG 2012 Arabidopsis bHLH100 and bHLH101 control iron homeostasis via a FIT-independent pathway. PLoS One7, e44843.22984573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain> SzabadosL, SavouréA 2010 Proline: a multifunctional amino acid. Trends in Plant Science15, 89–97.20036181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain> TamuraK, PetersonD, PetersonN, StecherG, NeiM, KumarS 2011 MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Molecular Biology and Evolution28, 2731–2739.21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain> Toledo-OrtizG, HuqE, QuailPH 2003 The Arabidopsis basic/helix–loop–helix transcription factor family. The Plant Cell15, 1749–1770.12897250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain> VainP, AfolabiAS, WorlandB, SnapeJW 2003 Transgene behaviour in populations of rice plants transformed using a new dual binary vector system: pGreen/pSoup. Theoretical and Applied Genetics107, 210–217.12677408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain> WangJ, SunPP, ChenCL, WangY, FuXZ, LiuJH 2011 An arginine decarboxylase gene PtADC from Poncirus trifoliata confers abiotic stress tolerance and promotes primary root growth in Arabidopsis. Journal of Experimental Botany62, 2899–2914.21282323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain> XuQ, ChenLL, RuanXet al 2013 The draft genome of sweet orange (Citrus sinensis). Nature Genetics45, 59–66.23179022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain> YinY, VafeadosD, TaoY, YoshidaS, AsamiT, ChoryJ 2005 A new class of transcription factors mediates brassinosteroid-regulated gene expression in Arabidopsis. Cell120, 249–259.15680330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain> YooSD, ChoYH, SheenJ 2007 Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts: a versatile cell system for transient gene expression analysis. Nature Protocols2, 1565–1572.17585298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain> ZandalinasSI, MittlerR, BalfagónD, ArbonaV, Gómez-CadenasA 2018 Plant adaptations to the combination of drought and high temperatures. Physiologia Plantarum162, 2–12.28042678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain> ZhangX, WangW, WangM, ZhangHY, LiuJH 2016 The miR396b of Poncirus trifoliata functions in cold tolerance by regulating ACC oxidase gene expression and modulating ethylene–polyamine homeostasis. Plant and Cell Physiology57, 1865–1878.27402968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain> ZhaoC, WangP, SiTet al 2017 MAP kinase cascades regulate the cold response by modulating ICE1 protein stability. Developmental Cell43, 618–629.e5.29056551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain> ZhaoQ, RenYR, WangQJ, WangXF, YouCX, HaoYJ 2016 Ubiquitination-related MdBT scaffold proteins target a bHLH transcription factor for iron homeostasis. Plant Physiology172, 1973–1988.27660166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain> ZhuJK 2016 Abiotic stress signaling and responses in plants. Cell167, 313–324.27716505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
