<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Diabetes Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Diabetes Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JDR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Diabetes Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2314-6745</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2314-6753</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5227166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/9145673</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Pilot Study to Assess the Feasibility of the Spanish Diabetes Self-Management Program in the Basque Country </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6194-4406</contrib-id><name><surname>Gamboa Moreno</surname><given-names>Estibaliz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ochoa de Retana Garcia</surname><given-names>Lourdes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0810-6689</contrib-id><name><surname>del Campo Pena</surname><given-names>Maria Emma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez Perez</surname><given-names>Álvaro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez Carazo</surname><given-names>Catalina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arbonies Ortiz</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rua Portu</surname><given-names>Maria Angeles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piñera Elorriaga</surname><given-names>Koldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zenarutzabeitia Pikatza</surname><given-names>Amaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Urquiza Bengoa</surname><given-names>Miren Nekane</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Méndez Sanpedro</surname><given-names>Tomás</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I9">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oses Portu</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorostidi Fano</surname><given-names>Lourdes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre Sorondo</surname><given-names>Miren Bakarne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vrotsou</surname><given-names>Kalliopi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rotaeche Del Campo</surname><given-names>Rafael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I12">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Active Patient Program, Donostialdea Integrated Health Organisation, Osakidetza, Pasajes San Pedro Health Center, Guipuzcoa, Spain</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Donostialdea Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Pasajes San Pedro Health Center, C/Marinos No. 1, Pasajes, San Pedro, 20110 Guipuzcoa, Spain</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Research Unit, Primary Care-Organization of Integrated Health Services of Vizcaya, Osakidetza, Bilbao, Spain</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Donostialdea Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Beraun Health Center, Renteria, Guipuzcoa, Spain</aff><aff id="I5"><sup>5</sup>Donostialdea Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Bidebieta Health Center, San Sebastián, Spain</aff><aff id="I6"><sup>6</sup>O + Berri, Basque Institute for Healthcare Innovation, Barakaldo, Vizcaya, Spain</aff><aff id="I7"><sup>7</sup>Family Medicine and Community Teaching Unit of Vizcaya, Osakidetza, Bilbao, Spain</aff><aff id="I8"><sup>8</sup>Araba Area, Osakidetza, Olaguibel Health Center, Vitoria-Gasteiz, Spain</aff><aff id="I9"><sup>9</sup>Ezkerraldea Enkarterri Cruces Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Ortuella Health Center, Ortuella, Vizcaya, Spain</aff><aff id="I10"><sup>10</sup>Bidasoa Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Hondarribia Health Center, Hondarribia, Guipuzcoa, Spain</aff><aff id="I11"><sup>11</sup>Research Unit, Primary Care-Organization of Integrated Health Services of Guipuzcoa, Osakidetza, San Sebastián, Spain</aff><aff id="I12"><sup>12</sup>Donostialdea Integrated Health Organization, Osakidetza, Alza Health Center, San Sebastián, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Maria Emma del Campo Pena: <email>mariaemma.delcampopena@osakidetza.eus</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Gill Rowlands </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>2016</volume><elocation-id>9145673</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 Estibaliz Gamboa Moreno et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Purpose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this study was to assess the feasibility of the Spanish Diabetes Self-Management Program (SDSMP) in the primary care setting of the Basque Health Service and offer initial estimations of the randomized controlled trial (RCT) effects. Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Ten health centers (HCs) participated in a single-arm pilot study with a 6-month follow-up period between February 2011 and June 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Recruitment was performed via invitation letters, health professionals, and the local media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Each intervention group consisted of 8–15 people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The ability of each HC in forming up to 2 groups, participants' compliance with the course, and coordination and data collection issues were evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) was the main outcome variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcomes were cardiovascular risk factors, drugs consumption, medical visits, quality of life, self-efficacy, physical exercise, and diet. Results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Two HCs did not organize a course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A total of 173 patients initiated the program, 2 dropped out without baseline data, and 90% completed it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>No pre-post HbA1c differences existed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Certain improvements were observed in blood pressure control, self-efficacy, physical activity, and some dietary habits. Conclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The SDSMP is feasible in our setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Our experience can be of interest when planning and conducting this program in similar health settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The trial is registered with ClinicalTrials.gov identifier <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01642394">NCT01642394</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Kronikgune, International Center of Excellence in Chronicity</funding-source><award-id>KRONIK11/036</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Government of the Basque Country</funding-source><award-id>2011111054</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Health Research Fund</funding-source><award-id>PI12/02738</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>European Fund for Regional Development</funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Diabetes is one of the most prevalent chronic diseases, with 422 million people worldwide having diagnosed diabetes in 2014 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is estimated that the prevalence of diagnosed and undiagnosed type 2 diabetes (T2DM) in Spain may reach as high as 12% in people above 30 years of age [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>T2DM is associated with an increased morbidity and mortality and it is thought to be responsible for 1.5 million deaths in 2012 [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>What is more, the direct and indirect costs of the disease between 2011 and 2030 will reach US $ 1.7 trillion [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It is estimated that diabetes accounts for between 6.3 and 7.4% of the costs in our health system [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Above all, T2DM is associated with cardiovascular system conditions, such problems being the cause of death in three-quarters of the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In the Basque Country, 44% of people with diabetes are obese [4] and 22% have diabetic macroangiopathy [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The diabetes control is improving in our setting, although 64% of patients have HbA1c levels below 7% and only 50% have blood pressure readings under 140/80 mmHg [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Patients' education can play an important role in improving glycemic control and reducing cardiovascular risk [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The current Basque Country clinical practice guideline (GPC) for T2DM recommends offering a structured educational program in order to empower the patients and encourage their active participation in the management of their condition [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Patient activation is defined as understanding one's own role in the care process and having the knowledge, skills, and confidence to take on that role [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Research indicates that activated patients are more likely to adhere to treatment regimens, get preventive care, and participate to a greater degree in decisions about their care [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>They are also more likely to engage in healthy lifestyle behaviors, to seek out health information, and to make less use of healthcare services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Interventions that provide peer support for patients and improve their problem-solving skills have also been shown to increase patient activation and improve health outcomes [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Like other chronic illnesses, diabetes requires patients to take responsibility for their own health (self-care) to minimize long-term complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Among programs on patient self- management, the most widely used structured approach is the Chronic Disease Self-Management Program (CDSMP) [9] developed at Stanford University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The CDSMP has different versions, among which is the Diabetes Self-Management Program (DSMP), specifically adapted for T2DM patients and its Spanish language version (SDSMP) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>These self-management programs are based on Albert Bandura's self-efficacy theory of behavioral change [11], which states that the key predictive variables for successful change are confidence (self-efficacy) in the capacity for carrying out an action and the expectation of achieving a particular goal (outcome expectation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Many studies support that self-efficacy and changes seen in the latter are associated with changes in health behavior and health status [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Successive systematic reviews have been published on the efficacy of various educational models in self-care and patient activation [13–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>These reviews indicate great variety in the results of the interventions attributable to differences in the length of the follow-up, the modality of the interventions, and the target populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In Spain, the few data available on self-management programs suggest favorable results, but the latter have not been assessed through prospective studies or compared with usual care [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The Department of Health of the Basque Country has launched a new strategy for providing care to chronic patients based on the Chronic Care Model [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>One of the cornerstones of this model is the promotion of self-care and population education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In this context, one of the trainings that offers the Active Patient Program (“Paciente Activo”) follows the SDSMP methodology and has been proposed as an instrument to promote self-care in people with T2DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In our health system, these educational interventions take place in the primary care health centers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These centers mainly host general practitioners, pediatricians, and nurses, with the latter bearing the responsibility of most educational activities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A single-arm pilot study was conducted for assessing the feasibility of this educational intervention in our context [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Acceptability, participation, and satisfaction with the educational intervention were studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the obtained data served to estimate the subsequent clinical trial sample size [19], while offering initial estimations of the expected effects for the main and secondary outcomes [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Finally, the experiences and lessons learned during this phase helped the investigators to better prepare, organize, and control all aspects of the subsequent clinical trial [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Objectives </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The feasibility aspects assessed by the pilot study were the interest of the target population in the proposed educational program and the enrollment rate; compliance with the program's schedule; adequacy of the battery of the administered questions, and finally participation and coordination of several health centers (HCs). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In addition, the main and secondary outcome pre-post effects were estimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The standard deviation (SD) estimation of the main outcome of interest (HbA1c) was implemented in the sample size estimation of the clinical trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All primary and secondary derived effects offer an initial idea of the results that may be expected in the clinical trial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>This preliminary research was a prospective pre-post pilot study without a control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Recruitment took place in 10 participating HCs across 4 healthcare organizations (i.e., primary care districts of Araba, Gipuzkoa, Ezkerraldea-Enkarterri, and Bidasoa Integrated Healthcare Organization) in the Basque Country (Spain) from February 2011 to June 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Between 2 and 9 health professionals (HPs) participated per center. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Patients with T2DM between the ages of 18 and 79 years were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Individuals with mental health problems (bipolar disorder, psychosis, schizophrenia, Alzheimer's disease, or other forms of dementia) or other health problems, that might have affected their ability to participate in the study, were excluded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Recruitment was carried out in several ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Invitations letters were sent to 120 T2DM subjects of each participating HC, fulfilling the age criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>These subjects were selected via a computer generated random numbers sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In addition, the participating HPs were instructed to inform and invite patients to the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Finally, awareness about the program was also spread in the local media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All the patients who agreed to participate gave written informed consent, after receiving information about the purpose of the research project. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic and baseline clinical data were collected on age, sex, years since diagnosis, and comorbidities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Assessed comorbidities were hypertension, heart disease, macroangiopathy (coronary, cerebrovascular, or peripheral artery disease), microangiopathy (renal, retinopathy, or neuropathy), depression, asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Description of the Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Self-efficacy enhancement was the key element of the applied educational intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The teaching process was structured to include the following four self-efficacy components: performance mastery, which shows participants how to make specific action plans; modeling, which can be accomplished by involving peers as instructors of self-management programs; symptom interpretation, helping patients to form alternative interpretations of their physiological symptoms, as such interpretations can subsequently lead to new self-management behaviors; and, finally, social persuasion, which refers to the positive effect experienced by the majority of the group members and the way in which this can influence other group members [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the content of the self-management program addressed three tasks, medical or behavioral management, role management, and emotional management, and five core skills, problem solving, decision-making, resource utilization, forming a patient/healthcare provider partnership, and taking action [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The intervention consisted of 6 group sessions lasting 2.5 hours each, once a week for 6 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Sessions were structured with the objective of enabling participants to acquire knowledge and skills related to the disease and its management, placing emphasis on tools for enhancing proactive self-care to achieve healthier lifestyle behaviors (improvements in diet, physical activity patterns, emotional management, and medication adherence among others). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Patients were trained to set their own targets, solve problems related to their condition, and communicate more effectively, with their relatives and healthcare professionals, by sharing their feelings, in order to enable them to play a more active role in the management of their disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The final goal of all this was to promote changes towards healthier lifestyles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>All sessions were supported by educational material specifically developed for the program: books, leaflets, and CDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Each group was supervised by two leaders previously trained and certified in the SDSMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>At least one of the leaders was required to be a T2DM patient or a caregiver for a person with this condition, while the other was allowed to be a HP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These leaders introduced themselves to participants as SDSMP leaders, not referring to their professional position, promoting the concept of peer-learning, as recommended in the implementation manual of the SDSMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Patients not attending at least four sessions were considered not to have completed the program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec5.1"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>5.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Feasibility Assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The recruitment capacity of the centers and their ability in forming up to 2 intervention groups each was assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Each center was asked to recruit between 8 and 30 subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For the needs of this study, 8 and 15 were the minimum and maximum acceptable number of participants in any group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>At least 65% of the participants initiating the intervention were expected to complete it [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Each center was responsible for and should be successful at managing all program related aspects and data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The actual educational intervention was delivered by the same investigators across all centers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Finally, the principal investigators attended interested patients, corresponding to nonparticipating HCs, organized the details related to baseline data information, and referred those subjects to the most convenient participating HC for receiving the educational intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The adequacy and understanding of the battery of questions would be judged by the frequency of missing data, while at the same time this would also inform about appropriate patient follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A manual with detailed instructions related to the pilot study project was given to all participating HPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>5.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Clinical Outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec5.2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>5.2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Primary Outcome Variable </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) level was a primary outcome variable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>5.2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Secondary Outcome Variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Cardiovascular-Related Factors. The factors are body mass index (BMI), systolic and diastolic blood pressure (SBP and DBP), and total and HDL cholesterol levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Cardiovascular risk was assessed with the Registre Gironí del COR (REGICOR) score, an adaptation of the original Framingham risk score for Mediterranean populations, calculated for persons between 35 and 74 years of age [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Use of Medications. Antidiabetes, antihypertensives, and antiplatelets were studied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Quality of Life. The Spanish version of the self-administered instrument, Audit of Diabetes-Dependent Quality of Life (ADDQoL-19), was used [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>This scale is specific for patients with diabetes and consists of 19 items assessing leisure activities, relationships, and living conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>All items are addressed from two perspectives: the way diabetes affects the patient's life and what a patient's life might be like if they did not have diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Replies range from 1 (excellent) to 7 (very poor). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Self-Efficacy. The Spanish Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale developed at Stanford University [24] was administered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>It consists of 8 items assessing diet, physical activity, and control of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Items are rated on a Likert-type scale from 1 to 10 (minimum to maximum). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>A total score and scores for the three aforementioned areas were obtained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Physical Exercise. Physical exercise was assessed with the 7-Day Physical Activity Recall (PAR) interview [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This is a semistructured interview concerning the intensity of physical activity performed in the previous week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Exercise intensity in metabolic equivalents (METs) in hours/week is estimated considering the hours of moderate, intense, and very intense exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>PAR also assesses whether the exercise reported by the patients is suitable for their age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Diet. Diet quality was examined using the food frequency questionnaire of the PREDIMED study [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>This questionnaire assesses frequency consumption of olive oil, fruit, vegetables, dairy products, cereal, red and white meat, fish, pasta or rice, legumes, commercial sweets, and beverages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Patient Satisfaction with the Program. It was measured with an anonymous specific satisfaction survey consisting of 10 questions related to sociodemographic and process variables, 20 satisfaction questions rated on 5-point Likert-type scale ranging from 1 = minimum to 5 = maximum and 3 open questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Questions were divided into three sections referring to the material presented, organization of the program, and behavior change (see Supplementary Material available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2016/9145673">http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2016/9145673</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Use of Healthcare Services. Number of visits to the general practitioner and nurse, number of visits to the emergency department, and number of times of hospitalization are compared during a 6-month period before and after the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Only cardiovascular morbidity and diabetes-related complications (e.g., renal insufficiency, hypoglycemia, and ketoacidosis) were considered for the emergency department visits and hospital admissions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Patients were assessed twice, 1 month before starting the intervention and 6 months after the end of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic and self-report questionnaires were given to patients to fill in, in their own homes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>All participating HPs, previously trained by the research team, were in charge of collecting the following data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Medication consumption and clinical visits were assessed from the electronic clinical history files and corroborated by the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Body mass index (BMI) and systolic (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) were recorded, while HbA1c and cholesterol levels were assessed by blood samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These samples were extracted in participants' HCs and were analyzed in the reference laboratories of the four participating health districts of the Basque Health System (Osakidetza). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>When necessary, the referring HP helped the participants complete the questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Finally, the 7-Day PAR and PREDIMED questionnaires were administered over the telephone by trained interviewers from a centralized call center. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Categorical variables were expressed as frequencies (n) and percentages (%) and continuous variables as means and standard deviations (SD) when normally distributed or as medians and interquartile ranges (Q1, Q3) when they did not follow a normal distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The comparisons between categorical variables before and after the intervention were carried out with McNemar's test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Comparisons between continuous variables were performed with Student's t test for paired samples or the nonparametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>All the differences were calculated as postintervention minus preintervention values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>For normally distributed variables, differences are presented as means with 95% confidence intervals (CI), while, for nonnormally distributed variables, such as the number of visits, differences are expressed as medians and their corresponding 95% CI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Comparisons were considered as statistically significant when p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>For the needs of this study, all results are based on available data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were carried out using the SAS v.9.3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Ethical Considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The research protocol was approved by the Clinical Research Ethics Committee of the Basque Country (Ref. number: 11/2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec8.1"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>8.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Feasibility Assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The participating HCs recruited between 3 and 27 patients each, while 5 patients corresponded to nonparticipating HCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Five of the centers obtained two program groups; three centers obtained one group, while patients recruited in two centers (i.e., n = 3 and 5) had to follow the program in a different HC, for being less than the required minimum for a course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The 5 additional subjects were absorbed without affecting the respective number of program groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Of the 1200 invitation letters sent, 46 were undelivered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Many patients visited their corresponding HP with an invitation letter and requested more details on the program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, frequency of patients who responded to the letter's invitation, of patients who showed initial interest, and of patients informed exclusively by the HP was not registered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A total of 174 patients signed an informed consent, 173 initiated the program, and 2 dropped out after the first session, without providing baseline data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>One hundred and fifty-five patients (90%) completed the training program (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Between 1 and 9% of the self-reported questions were not answered at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>At the postintervention assessment, the main outcome of interest, along with other cardiovascular data, was missing for 5 of the 171 participants, while the amount of missing data of the self-reported variables had increased. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec8.2"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>8.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Baseline Characteristics of Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Overall, 52% of the sample were male, with mean (SD) age of 63.4 (8.1) years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Among the most common comorbidities were hypertension (57%) and heart disease (26%), while 25% and 14% of the participants had a history of macro- and microangiopathy, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Baseline data are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec8.3"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>8.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Pre-Post Differences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>HbA1c levels at the two pilot study moments were 7.3% (1.1) and 7.4% (1.3), respectively, with the mean difference between the measurements being 0.1% (95% CI: −0.1 to 0.2; p = 0.348) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>It was additionally assessed whether patients with poorer initial control, defined as a baseline HbA1c ≥ 7%, presented greater reductions in this variable, but no differences were observed neither in patients with HbA1c ≥ 7% (diff: 0.01 (95% CI: −0.21 to 0.22); p = 0.960; n = 94) nor in patients with HbA1c ≥ 8% (diff: −0.06 (95% CI: −0.54 to 0.42); p = 0.791; n = 38) between the two time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Further, no differences in BMI, total cholesterol levels, or cardiovascular risk were found (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In terms of blood pressure, a reduction was seen after the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The mean changes in SBP and DBP were −3.3 mmHg (95% CI: −5.4 to −1.3; p = 0.002) and −1.3 mmHg (95% CI: −2.5 to −0.1; p = 0.032), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These reductions were also reflected in an increased percentage of patients who simultaneously achieved good control of both SBP and DBP (SBP &lt; 140 and DBP &lt; 90 mmHg) after the intervention, with 10% (95% CI: 3 to 18; p = 0.010) of the participants improving the control of their blood pressure during the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>However, this improvement was not reflected in a coronary risk reduction (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In addition, the pilot study participants reduced by 1 both general practitioner (p = 0.005) and primary nurse visits (p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Frequency of emergency department visits and hospitalization remained 0 at both time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Finally, no differences were seen neither in the total number of medications per patient nor in the percentage of patients taking antidiabetics, antihypertensives, or antiplatelets drugs (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>When replying to the general item of the ADDQoL-19 “In general, my present quality of life is…” participants rated their quality of life as being better 6 months after the pilot study (p = 0.027). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, no differences were observed in the general item, “If I did not have diabetes, my quality of life would be…” (p = 0.263) or in the total ADDQoL-19 score (p = 0.877) between the two moments (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Self-efficacy significantly improved both overall and in the different areas, namely, diet, physical activity, and control of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The observed changes ranged from 0.5 (95% CI: 0.1 to 0.9) to 0.8 (95% CI: 0.5 to 1.2) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The percentage of participants who reached the recommended levels of physical activity for their age increased 6 months after the intervention by 12% (95% CI: 4 to 21%; p = 0.007), while this improvement was not captured when physical activity was measured in minutes and METs (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Regarding dietary habits, a 10% increase was observed in the percentage of patients eating five or more portions of fruit and vegetables after the intervention (p = 0.020) and cold cured meats consumption was reduced (p = 0.035). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>However, none of the other main dietary habits was altered (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>As far as satisfaction with the course was concerned, a total of 149 patients replied to these questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In 19 of the 20 questions, the median score was 5 (95% CI: 4-5), with only one item “This course is going to help me to manage my emotions better,” having a lower median score of 4 (95% CI: 4-5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS,CONCL"><sec id="sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Discussion and Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec9.1"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>9.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Based on the current pilot study, we concluded that performing a randomized clinical trial (RCT) for evaluating the effectiveness of an educational program for diabetic patients was feasible in our context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Results were acceptable as far as overall recruitment, course participation, and patients' satisfaction and collaboration across various centers was concerned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>However, several important observations were also made. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Two of the participating centers, with 3 HPs collaborators each, did not manage to fulfill the minimum number of required participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The number of involved staff, their motivation, and understanding of the study goals were important aspects to consider in the future RCT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>This was seen as a key aspect for the successful RCT fulfillment, especially considering that the latter would involve a great number of centers dispersed over the whole Basque Country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it was decided that at least 5 or 6 HPs per center should be achieved for the future study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In addition, during the RCT informative sessions for capturing participating HPs, more effort should be made on highlighting the positive aspects of the educational intervention; this was expected to improve patients' health control and relieve, in the long term, the workload of the professionals themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>It was also thought that the HP motivation would increase, if pilot study patients participated actively in those informative sessions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>During the pilot study many participating HPs complained that their workload did not allow them to devote any time to the current project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>For this reason, HPs participating in the RCT were going to be allowed (by Osakidetza) a certain amount of working hours devoted exclusively to the needs of that study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>It was also observed that missing information, especially on subjective and patient self-reported data, increased at six months postintervention, compared to baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This fact was taken into consideration when estimating the RCT sample size, but also it indicated the need for a closer patient follow-up during the RCT data collection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The pre-post differences obtained in the current single-arm study may offer an initial estimation of the expected RCT results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The baseline characteristics of the current sample were comparable to those of the average diabetic patient in the Basque Country [4], except in that they were slightly younger and had lower levels of total cholesterol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Changes in several dimensions including improvements in the self-efficacy scale, levels of exercise, and diet were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>However, these changes were not accompanied by a greater glycaemic control in terms of HbA1c levels or changes in other variables, related to vascular morbidity, like coronary risk for example. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The good initial control of the local T2DM population and the short follow-up of the pilot study could be possible explanations of this lack of difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>It is recognized that diabetic people with poorer HbA1c levels have a greater room for improvement and tend to respond better to any type of intervention [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>However, this phenomenon has not been observed consistently in the context of the Stanford Self-Management Programs [28–31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>This very hypothesis will be tested in the RCT study, where a greater number of subjects will be followed for a longer period of time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that although the target HbA1c level is the most widely used variable to date for assessing diabetes interventions, its use as the only method is currently being questioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Recent evidence has shown that lower HbA1c levels are not always accompanied by a decrease in cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, especially in older patients or those with comorbidities [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Hence, it may be necessary to adapt the selection of variables to assess diabetes control to baseline levels of HbA1c, the length of time since diagnosis of the disease, and the presence of risk factors and cardiovascular morbidity [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The following RCT study of this group will explore the HbA1c level as its main outcome, in order to confirm or refute the prior theories, after a 2-year follow-up period, in our context. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The pilot study results suggested a reduction in blood pressure, similar to that obtained using nondrug approaches, such as a salt-free diet and physical exercise, and this was reflected to a significant increase in the percentage of patients with good blood pressure control, without changing the prescription of antihypertensives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The effect on blood pressure has not been included in any of the evaluations of the DSMP we identified in our review of the literature [28, 34, 35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Given the high prevalence of hypertension in people with diabetes and the importance of decreasing blood pressure for reducing cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, this potentially promising finding should be confirmed in future prospective studies, while the influence of a blood pressure reduction in the cardiovascular risk should also be further explored [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>An improvement in scores on the specific self-efficacy questionnaire is a common finding in all evaluations on diabetes self-management [15, 36, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, in many occasions, the significant progress achieved was not followed by an improvement in quality of life [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, people with diabetes, who improve their disease knowledge and self-management skills, are more independent and use fewer healthcare resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>This well-documented finding [15, 36, 37] was also observed in our sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The effects seen in the current study cannot be generalized and no causal relationship can be claimed between those effects and the applied educational intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The fact that the DSMP has been assessed in other populations and contexts, resulting in modest short-term positive results in outcomes such as depression, dietary habits, exercise, medication adherence, symptoms of hypoglycemia, communication with physicians, and health status [34–36], make us believe that the RCT findings will be in line with the a priori positive expectations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This pilot study has certain limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Firstly, its single-arm nature was not a replicate of the future RCT study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>However, its design permitted testing the feasibility of the educational program, in terms of participation and multiple-sites coordination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Even though the minimum number of participants was met overall, great variability was seen among participating HCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Motivation and time availability of participating HPs are issues that will be treated more carefully in the follow-up RCT study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>What is more, exact patient participation rates cannot be calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>On one hand, the invitation letters were sent to T2DM patients, irrespective of whether or not they were fulfilling any other inclusion criteria than the age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>This was due to the data confidentially, which did not permit access to further medical information of the population of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, no records of interested patients and patients informed exclusively by the HPs were kept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>However, given the number of the participating centers, health professional and recruitment approaches, such a record would have been very difficult to manage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Finally, missing data information, especially at 6 months, is another important limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Patients that were not satisfied may have been more reluctant to reply after the intervention and thus the initially obtained and presented results may have been biased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Given the importance of missing and the effect they can have on the study's conclusions, a closer patient follow-up, at all stages, should be assured in the RCT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec9.2"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>9.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The Spanish Diabetes Self-Management Program is feasible in our health system and well accepted by patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The single-arm pilot study results suggest that the program may induce improvements in self-efficacy and blood pressure, but its effectiveness will have to be confirmed by a RCT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Practice Implications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The current pilot study could contribute to the debate on the most adequate outcome variables, for evaluating diabetic patients' interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In addition, the experiences and lessons learned during this phase will serve for better coordinating the future RCT study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Avoiding organizational and communicational flaws, motivating HPs, improving patients' follow-up, and refining the study manual will result in enhancing the RCT quality at all levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Finally, the experience and lessons learned may be beneficial to similar health settings for planning and conducting diabetes self-management programs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplementary-material-sec"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f1"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Satisfaction survey questions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="9145673.f1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e816" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The members of the Active Patient Research Group are M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Barrena Guijarro, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Izar de la Fuente, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Cascante Gómez, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>M. Ávila Rodríguez, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Galardi Andonegui, L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Albizuri Amillategi, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>García Arévalo, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Ledo Parrondo, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Orduna Catalán, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>González de Zarate Ruiz, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Vicinay Ruilope, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Mendigutxia Luzuriaga, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Fernandez Olmeda, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Calvo Diaz, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Sunsundegui Loinaz, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Carracedo Arrastio, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Galo Anza, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Lecertua Arrieta, O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Dorronsoro Barandiaran, X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Sanz Cascante, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>González Babiano, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Aranceta Gaztelu, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Matias González, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Lasa Galparsoro, L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Iriondo Maiztegi, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Goiburu Iparraguirre, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Fdez. de Barrena Alvarez, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Arsuaga Bilbao, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Alonso Alonso, T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Chico Gonzalez, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Leiva Martin, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Berazadi Aldabaldetreku, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Aizpurua Lasa, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Rico Gamarra, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Montejo Garcia, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Trigueros Manzano, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Alvarez Hidalgo, Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Gobantes Otaola, X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Velasco Saiz-Ezkerra, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Sacristán Sainz-Aja, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Bermejo Calvo, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Ibarra Carcomo, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Areitio Ortega, and J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Mendoza Diaz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the Research Unit, Primary Care-Organization of Integrated Health Services of Bizkaia and Gipuzkoa, for their valuable help throughout the process, the management teams of the Osakidetza health districts participating in the pilot study for their support for launching and developing the program, and Basque Foundation for Health Innovation and Research (BIOEF) for supporting the translation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The study was carried out as part of the 2010-2011 Primary Care Research Program, organized by the Research Unit, Primary Care-Organization of Integrated Health Services of Bizkaia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>This research project has been funded by a grant from Kronikgune, International Center of Excellence in Chronicity (Ref. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>KRONIK11/036), a grant from the Department of Health and Consumer's Affairs of the Government of the Basque Country (Ref. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>2011111054), and a Health Research Fund (FIS) Grant (Ref. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>PI12/02738) and cofinanced by the European Fund for Regional Development. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>1NCD Risk Factor CollaborationWorldwide trends in diabetes since 1980: a pooled analysis of 751 population-based studies with 4·4 million participantsThe Lancet2016387100271513153010.1016/s0140-6736(16)00618-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>2Ministerio de Sanidad y ConsumoEstrategia en Diabetes del Sistema Nacional de Salud2012Madrid, SpainMinisterio de Sanidad y Consumo Centro de Publicaciones </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>3World Health OrganizationGlobal Report on Diabetes2016Geneva, SwitzerlandWorld Health Organization </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>4Alonso-MoránE.OruetaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>F.EstebanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>F.Prevalence and quality of care indicators of type 2 diabetes in the population of the Basque Country (Spain)Avances en Diabetología2015312727910.1016/j.avdiab.2015.01.0022-s2.0-84928372668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>5ArteagoitiaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>M.LarrañagaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>I.RodriguezJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>L.FernandezI.PiniésJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>A.Incidence, prevalence and coronary heart disease risk level in known Type 2 diabetes: a sentinel practice network study in the Basque Country, SpainDiabetologia200346789990910.1007/s00125-003-1137-12-s2.0-004216449012830379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>6Grupo de Trabajo para la elaboración de la Guía de Práctica Clínica sobre Diabetes tipo 2, Guía de Práctica Clínica Diabetes tipo 2 [Internet] Vitoria-Gasteiz, 2014, Osakidetza, Editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Disponible en: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.osakidetza.euskadi.eus/r85-phgpc00/es">http://www.osakidetza.euskadi.eus/r85-phgpc00/es</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>7HibbardJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>H.StockardJ.MahoneyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>R.TuslerM.Development of the Patient Activation Measure (PAM): conceptualizing and measuring activation in patients and consumersHealth Services Research2004394, part 11005102610.1111/j.1475-6773.2004.00269.x2-s2.0-314266898415230939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>8HibbardJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>H.GreeneJ.OvertonV.Patients with lower activation associated with higher costs; Delivery systems should know their Patients' ‘Scores’Health Affairs201332221622210.1377/hlthaff.2012.11332-s2.0-8487476797723381513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>9LorigK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>R.SobelD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>S.RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>L.LaurentD.HobbsM.Effect of a self-management program on patients with chronic diseaseEffective Clinical Practice2001462562622-s2.0-003551499511769298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>10ErdemE.KordaH.Self-management program participation by older adults with diabetes: chronic disease self-management program and diabetes self-management programFamily and Community Health201437213414610.1097/fch.00000000000000252-s2.0-8489464155924569159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>11BanduraA.Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavioral changePsychological Review197784219121510.1037/0033-295x.84.2.1912-s2.0-0017472917847061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>12BanduraA.Self-Efficacy: The Exercise of Control1997New York, NY, USAW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Freeman </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>13BolenS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>D.ChandarA.Falck-YtterC.Effectiveness and safety of patient activation interventions for adults with type 2 diabetes: systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regressionJournal of General Internal Medicine20142981166117610.1007/s11606-014-2855-424733301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>14BuryM.NewbouldJ.TaylorD.A Rapid Review of the Current State of Knowledge Regarding Lay-Led Self-Management of Chronic Illnes: Evidence Review2005London, UKNational Institute for Helath and Clinical Excellence </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>15FosterG.TaylorS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>J.EldridgeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>E.RamsayJ.GriffithsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>J.Self-management education programmes by lay leaders for people with chronic conditionsCochrane Database of Systematic Reviews20074CD0051082-s2.0-38449084230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>16GordonC.GallowayT.Review of Findings on Chronic Disease Self-Management Program (CDSMP) Outcomes: Physical, Emotional &amp; Health-Related Quality of Life, Healthcare Utilization and Costs2008Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and National Council on Aging </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>17Nuño-SolinisR.Rodríguez-PereiraC.Piñera-ElorriagaK.Zaballa-GonzálezI.Bikandi-IrazabalJ.Panorama de las iniciativas de educación para el autocuidado en EspañaGaceta Sanitaria201327433233710.1016/j.gaceta.2013.01.00823465729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>18Departamento de Sanidad y Consumo del Gobierno VascoEstrategia para Afrontar el Reto de la Cronicidad en Euskadi2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>19EldridgeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>M.LancasterG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>A.CampbellM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>J.Defining feasibility and pilot studies in preparation for randomised controlled trials: development of a conceptual frameworkPLoS ONE2016113e015020510.1371/journal.pone.0150205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>20Gamboa MorenoE.Sánchez PerezÁ.VrotsouK.Impact of a self-care education programme on patients with type 2 diabetes in primary care in the Basque CountryBMC Public Health2013131, article 52110.1186/1471-2458-13-5212-s2.0-84878223611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>21LorigK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>R.HolmanH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>R.Self-management education: history, definition, outcomes, and mechanismsAnnals of Behavioral Medicine2003261172-s2.0-004209061512867348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>22MarrugatJ.SubiranaI.ComínE.Validity of an adaptation of the Framingham cardiovascular risk function: the VERIFICA StudyJournal of Epidemiology &amp; Community Health2007611404710.1136/jech.2005.03850517183014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>23BradleyC.ToddC.GortonT.SymondsE.MartinA.PlowrightR.The development of an individualized questionnaire measure of perceived impact of diabetes on quality of life: the ADDQoLQuality of Life Research199981-2799110.1023/a:10264851301002-s2.0-003280578710457741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>24RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>L.LorigK.The English and Spanish self-efficacy to manage chronic disease scale measures were validated using multiple studiesJournal of Clinical Epidemiology201467111265127310.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.06.0092-s2.0-8490829316425091546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>25GrandesG.SanchezA.Sanchez-PinillaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>O.Effectiveness of physical activity advice and prescription by physicians in routine primary care: a cluster randomized trialArchives of Internal Medicine2009169769470110.1001/archinternmed.2009.232-s2.0-6524912267919364999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>26ZuazagoitiaA.MontoyaI.GrandesG.Reliability and validity of the 7-day physical activity recall interview in a Spanish populationEuropean Journal of Sport Science201414supplement 1S361S36810.1080/17461391.2012.7053322-s2.0-8489306261624444230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>27Martínez-GonzálezM. Á.CorellaD.Salas-SalvadóJ.Cohort profile: design and methods of the PREDIMED studyInternational Journal of Epidemiology201241237738510.1093/ije/dyq25021172932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>28LorigK.RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>L.VillaF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>J.ArmasJ.Community-based peer-led diabetes self-management: a randomized trialDiabetes Educator200935464165110.1177/01457217093350062-s2.0-6964909415819407333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>29MauldonM.MelkusG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>D.CagganelloM.Tomando control: a culturally appropriate diabetes education program for Spanish-speaking individuals with type 2 diabetes mellitus—evaluation of a pilot projectDiabetes Educator200632575176010.1177/01457217062919992-s2.0-3374842320716971708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>30McEwenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>M.PasvogelA.GallegosG.BarreraL.Type 2 diabetes self-management social support intervention at the U.S.-Mexico borderPublic Health Nursing201027431031910.1111/j.1525-1446.2010.00860.x2-s2.0-7795508186320626831<?supplied-pmid 20626831?>20626831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>31QiL.LiuQ.QiX.WuN.TangW.XiongH.Effectiveness of peer support for improving glycaemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsBMC Public Health2015151, article 47110.1186/s12889-015-1798-y2-s2.0-84929170734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>32BoussageonR.Bejan-AngoulvantT.Saadatian-ElahiM.Effect of intensive glucose lowering treatment on all cause mortality, cardiovascular death, and microvascular events in type 2 diabetes: meta-analysis of randomised controlled trialsBritish Medical Journal20113437817d416910.1136/bmj.d41692-s2.0-79960959816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>33MontoriV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>M.Fernández-BalsellsM.Glycemic control in type 2 diabetes: time for an evidence-based about-face?Annals of Internal Medicine20091501180380810.7326/0003-4819-150-11-200906020-000082-s2.0-6664910088719380837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>34LorigK.GonzalezV.Community-based diabetes self-management education: definition and case studyDiabetes Spectrum2000134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>35LorigK.RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>L.TurnerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>M.EnglishK.LaurentD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>D.GreenbergJ.Benefits of diabetes self-management for health plan members: a 6-month translation studyJournal of Medical Internet Research2016186p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>e16410.2196/jmir.5568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>36LorigK.RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>L.VillaF.PietteJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>D.Spanish diabetes self-management with and without automated telephone reinforcement: two randomized trialsDiabetes Care200831340841410.2337/dc07-13132-s2.0-4444914108318096810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>37LorigK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>R.RitterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>L.DostA.PlantK.LaurentD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>D.McNeilI.The expert patients programme online, a 1-year study of an Internet-based self-management programme for people with long-term conditionsChronic Illness20084424725610.1177/17423953080988862-s2.0-5814911774419091933<?supplied-pmid 19091933?>19091933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Flowchart of pilot study participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JDR2016-9145673.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics of participating patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Baseline information </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>N = 171 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Age in years; mean (SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>63.4 (8.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Sex; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain> Male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>89 (52) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain> Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>82 (48) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Years with diabetes; mean (SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>9.7 (7.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Smoking status; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain> Smoker </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>30 (18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain> Nonsmoker </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>141 (82) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Comorbidities; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain> Hypertension </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>97 (57) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain> Heart disease </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>44 (26) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain> Macroangiopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>43 (25) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain> Microangiopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>24 (14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<italic>n </italic>(%) = frequency (percentage) and SD = standard deviation. Comorbidity data indicate frequency of the “yes” category.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Cardiovascular clinical variables and number of medical visits and times of hospitalization at baseline and 6 months after the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Variables </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>n </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Preintervention </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Mean difference (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>p value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Cardiovascular data </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>HbA1c level </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>166 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>7.3 (1.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>0.1 (−0.1, 0.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>0.348 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain> HbA1c &lt; 7%; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>72 (43) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>3 (−4, 9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>0.465 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>BMI </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>167 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>30.4 (5.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>−0.1 (−0.3, 0.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>0.461 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Total cholesterol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>164 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>197.8 (37.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>−3.2 (−7.6, 1.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>0.158 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>REGICOR score </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>145 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>7.2 (3.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>−0.2 (−0.6, 0.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>0.466 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>SBP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>166 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>137.1 (16.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>−3.3 (−5.3, −1.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>0.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>DBP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>166 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>79.2 (9.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>−1.4 (−2.5, −0.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>0.024 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Good blood pressure control SBP &lt; 140 &amp; DBP &lt; 90; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>166 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>88 (53) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>10 (3, 18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>0.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Medication consumption </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>171 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Antidiabetics; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>133 (78) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>1 (−2, 4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>0.479 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Antihypertensives; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>98 (57) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>0 (−4, 4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>1.000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Antiplatelet drugs; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>56 (33) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>1 (−5, 2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>0.527 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Number of medications; median (Q1, Q3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>3 (1, 4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>0 (0, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>0.763 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Number of medical visits;   median (Q1,Q3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>165 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>General practitioner </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>3 (2, 5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>−1 (−1, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>0.005 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Primary care nurse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>4 (2, 5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>−1 (−1, −1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.0001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Emergency department </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>0 (0, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>0 (0, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>0.815 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Hospital admissions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>0 (0, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>0 (0, 0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>0.278 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are mean (standard deviation), unless otherwise stated. <italic>n</italic> (%) = frequency (percentage). The “<italic>n</italic>” column reports frequencies of available data at both time points. REGICOR estimates cardiovascular risk for patients between 35 and 74 years of age. Differences were calculated as postintervention minus preintervention values. CI: confidence interval. Q1, Q3: 25th and 75th percentiles. HbA1c: glycated haemoglobin. BMI: body mass index. SBP: systolic blood pressure; DBP: diastolic blood pressure. Mean difference for categorical variables corresponds to differences in paired proportions and their respective 95% CI and for ordinal variables (i.e., total number of medications and medical visits) to median differences with their respective 95% CI. Reported <italic>p</italic> values are based on paired <italic>t</italic>-tests for continuous variables, McNemar's test for binary variables, and the Wilcoxon signed-rank test for ordinal variables. Medical visits were assessed for the intervals of 6 months before and after intervention. Only diabetes-related complications were considered for the emergency department visits and hospital admissions.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Variables related to self-efficacy, quality of life, diet, and physical exercise at baseline and 6 months after the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>n </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Preintervention </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>Mean difference (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>p value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Spanish Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain> Diet </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>131 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>6.5 (2.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>0.5 (0.2, 0.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>0.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain> Physical activity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>6.7 (2.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>0.7 (0.3, 1.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>0.0003 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain> Disease control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>136 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>6.2 (2.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>0.8 (0.5, 1.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.0001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Total score </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>128 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>6.5 (1.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>0.6 (0.3, 0.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.0001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Quality of life, physical activity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>ADDQoL score </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>145 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>−1.4 (1.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>−0.02 (−0.2, 0.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>0.877 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>Moderate and vigorous activity minutes/week </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>539 (776) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>−13 (−144, 117) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>0.840 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>Moderate and vigorous activity MET hours/week </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>5.5 (7.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>0.01 (−1.4, 1.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>0.984 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Met physical activity recommendations for their age; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>79 (58) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>12 (4, 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>0.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>Dietary habits; n (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>Fruit &amp; vegetables: ≥5 pieces p/d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>141 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>37 (26) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>10 (2, 18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>0.020 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>Olive oil: ≥3 soup spoons p/d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>142 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>28 (20) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>−4 (−12, 5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>0.398 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>Red meat: &lt;2 portions p/w </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>139 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="592" pm="."><plain>47 (34) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>3 (−6, 11) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>0.505 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>Cold cured meat: &lt;2 portions p/w </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>131 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>64 (49) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>11 (1, 20) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>0.035 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>Legumes: ≥2 plates p/w </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>139 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>97 (70) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>−4 (−13, 4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>0.304 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>Commercial sweets: &lt;2 pieces p/w </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>125 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>87 (70) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>3 (−5, 12) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>0.465 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>Beverages: &lt;1 can p/d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>124 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>107 (86) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>−2 (−8, 3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>0.405 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are mean (standard deviation), unless otherwise stated. <italic>n</italic> (%) = frequency (percentage). The “<italic>n</italic>” column reports frequencies of available data at both time points. ADDQol: Audit of Diabetes-Dependent Quality of Life. MET: metabolic equivalent. Meat portions were 100–150 grams for red meat and 4-5 slices or 80 grams for cold cured meat. p/w and p/d indicate per week and per day, respectively. Differences were calculated as postintervention minus preintervention values. Mean difference for categorical variables corresponds to differences in paired proportions and their respective 95% CI. Reported <italic>p</italic> values are based on paired <italic>t</italic>-tests for continuous variables and McNemar's test for binary variables.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
