<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Geriatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2318</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5307887</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">440</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-017-0440-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Persistent use of psychotropic drugs in nursing home residents in Norway </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Helvik</surname><given-names>Anne-Sofie</given-names></name><address><phone>+47 73597565</phone><email>anne-sofie.helvik@ntnu.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Šaltytė Benth</surname><given-names>Jūratė</given-names></name><address><email>jurate.saltyte-benth@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Bei</given-names></name><address><email>bei.wu@nyu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Engedal</surname><given-names>Knut</given-names></name><address><email>knut.engedal@aldringoghelse.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selbæk</surname><given-names>Geir</given-names></name><address><email>geir.selbaek@aldringoghelse.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1516 2393</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5947.f</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health and General Practice, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Norwegian University of Science and Technology (NTNU), </institution></institution-wrap>Postboks 8905, NO-7491 Trondheim, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0627 3560</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.52522.32</institution-id><institution/><institution>St Olavs University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Trondheim, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Norwegian National Advisory Unit on Ageing and Health, Vestfold Health Trust, Tønsberg, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Institute of Clinical Medicine, Campus Ahus, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9637 455X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411279.8</institution-id><institution>HØKH, Research Centre, </institution><institution>Akershus University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Lørenskog, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412929.5</institution-id><institution/><institution>Centre for Old Age Psychiatric Research, Innlandet Hospital Trust, </institution></institution-wrap>Ottestad, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8753</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.137628.9</institution-id><institution>Rory Meyers College of Nursing, </institution><institution>New York University, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, NC USA </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label>Institute of Health and Society, Faculty of Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>52</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of psychotropic drug (PTD) use in NH residents is high, but few have explored prevalence and persistency in PTD in NH residents and factors associated with persistency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This at the same time as we know that risk of side events may be higher with long- term use in older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Thus, the aim of this study was to describe the prevalence and persistence in use of PTD and to explore factors associated with persistence in use of PTD at two consecutive time points in nursing home (NH) residents. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We included 1163 NH residents in a 72-month longitudinal study with five assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Use of PTD, neuropsychiatric symptoms (NPS), severity of dementia and physical health were assessed each time. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The prevalence over time and persistent use of antipsychotic drugs, antidepressants, anxiolytics and sedatives at two consecutive time points were high in residents with and without dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>There was an association between greater NPS at the first time point, and persistent use of these drugs, but changes in NPS between time points, did not explain such use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A longer NH stay increased the odds for persistent use of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Psychotropic drugs are frequently used as a long-term treatment among NH residents and are associated with severity of neuropsychiatric symptoms, but not with severity of dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Closer attention should be paid to follow-up of psychotropic drug treatment, and especially for long –term use of antipsychotics, since the duration of such treatment should be as short as possible. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>ATC</kwd><kwd>Dementia</kwd><kwd>Older adults</kwd><kwd>Geriatrics</kwd><kwd>Long-term-use</kwd><kwd>Neuropsychiatric symptoms</kwd><kwd>Old age</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The use of psychotropic drugs in European nursing homes (NH) is reported to be quite common. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of use of any psychotropic drug (PTD) varied between 42 and 80% in studies published from 2005 to 2013 [1–6] and varied between countries [7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Among NH residents with dementia or cognitive impairment, the prevalence of any PTD use is similar or even higher than among those with normal cognition (48–90%) [9–14] and also higher than in community living older adults with dementia [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In NHs in Scandinavia, the use of any PTD is also high (57–80%) [15–19], especially in studies that only include residents with dementia (68–85%) [12, 15, 17, 20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Over the years there has been an increase in use of PTD in NH [12, 18, 22–28] except for antipsychotic drugs, where a decrease has been observed in recent years [18, 27, 29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Thus, the prevalence of antipsychotic drug use in Scandinavian NH residents with dementia is among the lowest in Europe (pooled estimates 24%) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Antidepressants are the most commonly used PTD in Norwegian NH residents [16, 18, 22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Antipsychotic drugs are often used to treat neuropsychiatric symptoms, such as aggression, agitation or psychotic symptoms in NH residents with dementia, although non-pharmacological interventions should be the first choice of treatment for these symptoms [32, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, in demanding clinical situations, antipsychotic drugs may be unavoidable, but there is no evidence that long-term use of antipsychotic drugs in the management of neuropsychiatric symptoms is effective [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Older NH residents with dementia can be withdrawn from long-term antipsychotics without detrimental effects on their behavior, but caution is required in residents with severe neuropsychiatric symptoms [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the duration of antipsychotic drug treatment should be as short as possible, because of the high risk of side effects [32], such as more rapid progression of dementia [9] or cognitive decline [35], higher risk of cerebrovascular events [36] and increased risk of falling [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Use of antipsychotic drugs is also associated with increased mortality risk [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>While the side effects of antipsychotics have received the most attention, studies show that there are serious short- and long-term side effects such as falls and fall-related fractures associated with use of antidepressants and with use of benzodiazepines [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of antidepressants on depression in persons with dementia was not confirmed in a meta-analysis summarizing many randomized control trials [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>A recent study of discontinuation of antidepressants in NH residents with dementia and neuropsychiatric symptoms in Norway found that most residents (85%) tolerated discontinuation [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, when antidepressants are discontinued in residents with dementia they should be monitored carefully to identify those with worsening depressive symptoms [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Authors who studied retrospectively discontinuation of long-term use of benzodiazepines in older adults with and without dementia in care institutions found limited evidence of adverse outcomes due to discontinuation of benzodiazepines, but close attention should be paid to the possibility of emergent agitation and in patients with anxiety caution should be practiced [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Discontinuation of long-term use of Benzodiazepines in older adults without dementia has been found to increase handgrip strength, balance and cognitive function [42–44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Of the approximately 75 studies on PTD in NH facilities published after 2004, only a small fraction have examined use of PTD in a longitudinal design [21, 45–54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>About half of the longitudinal studies have studied the prevalence of different types of PTD over time or persistent use at two time points [21, 45–48, 50, 52], but very few have studied factors associated with the persistent use of PTD, such as antipsychotic drugs [46, 52], antidepressants, anxiolytics or sedatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, as the risk of side events may be higher with long-term use [32, 33] and is decreased after discontinuation of PTD in older adults [34, 55] it is of vital importance to study the persistent use of PTD and its associated factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to describe the prevalence and persistence of PTD use and to explore factors associated with the persistence in use of PTD at two consecutive time points in a Norwegian sample of NH residents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This was a 72-month longitudinal study with five assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Baseline assessment (A1) took place between November 2004 and January 2005 [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The follow-up assessments took place after 12, 31 and 52 and 72 months (A2–A5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Setting and participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In total, Norway has 40,000 NH places (beds) [57] for a population of about five million, with about 14% (700,000) of those aged 65 years or older [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The jurisdiction for public health care services lies with local municipalities, and local authorities offer social services (such as housing and home services), in-home nursing and institutional care (mainly in NHs), and provide both long- and short-term care and rehabilitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This study recruited participants from 26 NHs in 18 municipalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The selection of small, medium, and large municipalities was made to obtain a wide variety of NH-settings in the sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>NH residents with a stay of at least 14 days were eligible for inclusion, no other inclusion or exclusion criteria were used [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In all, 1165 residents were eligible for inclusion and only two declined to participate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Psychotropic drugs were grouped according to the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) Classification System into the following groups: antipsychotics (N05A except lithium), antidepressants (N06A), anxiolytics (N05B), hypnotics/sedatives (N05C), and anti-dementia medication (N06D) (yes versus no) [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Combination drugs outside ATC NO5B and NO5Cwere not included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The information was collected from the medical record of each resident [56]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Dementia and severity of dementia was assessed using the Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) scale, covering six domains (memory; orientation; judgment and problem solving; community affairs; home and hobbies; and personal care) with five response categories (0, 0.5, 1, 2, 3) [60, 61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The total score was calculated using an algorithm that gives priority to memory [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Residents with a total score of one or higher were regarded as having dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The cut-off CDR ≥1 in defining dementia has been found adequate in previous Norwegian and international studies [62–64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The categorical scores indicate the severity of dementia: a CDR score of 1 represents mild dementia, a CDR score of 2 represents moderate dementia, and a CDR score of 3 represents severe dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The sum-score of the six domains (sum of boxes), ranging from zero to 18, can also be used to measure the severity of dementia, as the categorical and continuous scores correlate highly ≥ 0.9 [65, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The Spearman correlation between the categorical CDR score and the CDR sum of boxes score in the present study was 0.93. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Due to a wider range of values, the CDR sum of boxes offers important advantages when analyzing the data [66]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We used the CDR score (CDR ≥1) as an indication of dementia, as it was not possible to perform a standardized dementia work-up for all residents because many were too frail or mentally impaired to take part in examinations such as CT or MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A large number of residents with a CDR score of 3 could not be tested with any dementia tests such as the Mini Mental Status Examination [67] or the Clock Drawing Test [68]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Physical health was assessed using the General Medical Health Rating (GMHR) scale [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>This is a one-item global rating scale with four categories: good, fairly good, poor, and very poor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The rating was based on all available information on physical health and use of drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The scale has been used in large studies including older people with and without dementia [70] and has been translated and used in several studies [71, 72]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The Personal Activities of Daily Living (P-ADL) score was assessed with the Physical Self-Maintenance Scale (PSMS), including six items, with a total score ranging from 6 to 30 [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>High scores indicate a lower level of functioning. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Neuropsychiatric symptoms (NPS) were assessed using the Neuropsychiatric Inventory Nursing Home version (NPI-NH) [74, 75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The 10-item inventory covers the following symptoms: delusion, hallucination, euphoria, agitation/aggression, disinhibition, irritability/lability, depression/dysphoria, anxiety, apathy/indifference, and aberrant motor behavior (no/yes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>For each symptom, severity (score 1–3) multiplied by frequency (score 1–4) provides a score from zero to 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Based on a previous principal component analysis, psychosis (delusions, hallucination), agitation (agitation/aggression, disinhibition, irritability), and affective (depression, anxiety) sub-syndrome scores were formed by summing the score of the included items [76–79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The apathy/indifference was analyzed as a single symptom. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Demographic information such as age, gender, marital status, and length of stay in the NH at the time of inclusion was collected from medical records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The type of unit was also recorded from among the following options: regular units (RU), special care unit for people with dementia (SCU), rehabilitation unit (REU), and other units (OU), mainly psychogeriatric wards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The length of stay in a NH before study inclusion was measured in days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Nurses with extensive clinical experience collected the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Prior to data collection, all assessors participated in a 2-day course on how to apply the standardized questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>A 1-day training program was carried out prior to each follow-up assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The project leader (GS) was available for consultation throughout the data collection period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The nurses collected data from medical records and via a standardized interview with the residents’ primary caregivers, all of whom were registered nurses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>All assessment scales used were standard translated Norwegian versions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>A pilot study including 41 NH residents was carried out to test inter-rater reliability of CDR prior to the first data collection and the inter-rater reliability was very good. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The kappa statistics for the global CDR score were 1 (between geriatric psychiatrist and registered nurse specialized in psychiatry) and 0.86 (between geriatric psychiatrist and registered nurse). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>More detailed information of the inter-rating reliability test has been published elsewhere [56]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Study information was given to the residents and their family members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The residents and their next of kin were informed that they could refuse to participate at any stage of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>This procedure was recommended and approved by the Regional Ethics Committee in the south east of Norway, the Data Inspectorate and the Directorate for Health and Social Affairs in 2004 before data collection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Sample characteristics at baseline were described as means and standard deviations (SD) or frequencies and percentages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Residents with CDR ≥ 1 and CDR &lt; 1 were compared by Independent samples t-test for continuous and χ2-test for categorical variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Prevalence and persistence of PTD use among those with and without dementia were compared by Z-test for proportions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The persistence in outcomes, use of antipsychotics, antidepressants, anxiolytics and sedatives were assessed with a logistic regression model for hierarchical data (SAS GLIMMIX procedure). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Random effects for type of unit nested in a NH were included into the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The dependent variable was current use of a specific type of PTD drug, while the independent variable was either use of the same drug at the previous time point (lag 1), two time points previously (lag 2) or three time points previously (lag 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>All models were adjusted for a number of relevant covariates measured at the same time point as the independent variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A similar model was estimated to assess variables associated to persistent use of drugs, where the outcome was defined as 1 in the case of use of drugs at two adjacent time points and 0 otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In addition, exploratory analyses assessing association between change in NPI sub-syndromes and persistent use of drugs were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>All multivariate models were reduced using Akaike’s Information Criteria, where a lower value means a better model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The results were tabulated as odds ratios (ORs) with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CI) and presented graphically. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>All analyses were performed in SPSS version 22 and SAS v9.3. P-values below 0.05 were considered statically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>All tests were two-sided. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Sample characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>At baseline, the mean (SD) age of the residents was 84.4 (7.8) years and 846 (72.7%) of them were women (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The mean (SD) baseline CDR sum of boxes was 11.2 (5.3) and 932 (80.1%) residents had CDR ≥ 1 indicating dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The mean length of stay at baseline was 938.3 (1013.1) days and the mean (SD) number of prescribed drugs taken regularly was 6.0 (3.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Of the 1163 residents at baseline, 98 (8.4%) were still alive and available at the fifth follow-up (see Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Mean (SD) time of follow-up was 829.5 (690.0) days.Table 1Sample characteristics at baselineA1CDR ≥ 1CDR &lt; 1 P-valuesa 1163932Socio-demographics AgeMean (SD)84.4 (7.8)84.5 (7.5)83.8 (9.0)0.223 FemalesN (%)846 (72.7)686 (73.6)156 (68.7)0.139 Education &lt; 10 yearsN (%)847 (74.8)673 (74.1)170 (76.9)0.390 MarriedN (%)221 (19.0)185 (19.8)36 (15.9)0.178Health condition GMHR  Good  Fairly good  Poor  Very PoorN (%)N (%)N (%)N (%)194 (17.2)386 (34.1)378 (33.4)173 (15.3)142 (15.7)291 (32.2)322 (35.6)150 (16.6)52 (23.4)94 (42.3)53 (23.9)23 (10.4)&lt;0.001 PSMS scoreMean (SD)18.1 (5.4)18.8 (5.3)15.4 (4.8)&lt;0.001 NPI Agitation sub-syndromeMean (SD)5.8 (8.0)6.5 (8.2)2.9 (6.1)&lt;0.001 NPI Psychosis sub-syndromeMean (SD)2.8 (5.1)3.2 (5.3)1.3 (3.8)&lt;0.001 NPI Affective sub-syndromeMean (SD)3.5 (5.3)3.7 (5.4)2.9 (4.9)0.041 NPI ApathyMean (SD)2.2 (3.7)2.4 (3.8)1.1 (2.9)&lt;0.001 No of drugsMean (SD)6.0 (3.1)5.8 (3.0)6.9 (3.3)&lt;0.001 Days in NHMean (SD)938.3 (1013.0)928.9 (910.1)975.5 (1359.3)0.534 CDR Clinical Dementia Rating scale GMHR General Medical Health rating PSMS Physical Self-Maintenance Scale NPI Neuropsychiatric Inventory NH Nursing home aCalculated by using t-test for Independent samples for continuous or χ2-test for categorical variables Fig. 1Flow chart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Mean (SD) time between accessions were 11.1 (0.5) months for A1–A2, 18.6 (1.3) months for A2–A3, 20.5 (1.7) months for A3–A4 and 20.8 (2.8) months for A4–A5 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of psychotropic drugs over time </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of PTD use at baseline and each of the follow-up time points are presented in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Antidepressants were most frequently used (38.3% at baseline, 32.7% at last follow-up); while anti-dementia drugs were least frequently used (11.3% at baseline, 0% at last follow-up). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of use of any PTD was high throughout the period; at baseline the prevalence was 72.9%, but had fallen to 63.3% at the last follow-up.Table 2Prevalence and persistence of PTD use according to the presence of dementia at each assessment (%)Prevalence in percentagesA1 A2 A3 A4 A5 All(n = 1163)D/nD(n = 932/227)All(n = 789)D/nD(n = 628/159)All(n = 395)D/nD(n = 300/94)All (n = 209)D/nD(n = 160/48)All (n = 98)D/nD(n = 75/22)Antipsychotics (AP)24.126.0/15.9***25.226.4/20.820.522.0/16.020.622.5/14.620.420.0/22.7 Trad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>AP11.311.5/11.012.211.6/14.59.49.0/10.68.69.4/6.312.212.0/13.6 Atypical AP13.214.9/5.7***13.815.6/6.9***11.913.7/6.4**12.613.1/8.38.28.0/9.1Antidepressants38.339.1/34.837.337.9/34.036.735.3/40.435.433.1/41.732.729.3/40.9Anxiolytics24.223.8/26.424.222.9/29.6*25.121.3/37.2***28.726.9/35.422.421.3/27.3Sedatives29.026.4/39.6***26.623.4/38.4***24.121.0/33.0*23.919.4/37.5**23.520.0/31.8Antidementia drug11.313.5/2.2***9.811.8/1.9***5.36.3/2.1*2.93.1/2.100/0Any PTD72.974.5/66.5*71.471.5/70.470.467.7/78.7*69.466.9/77.163.357.3/81.8**Persistence at two consecutive time points in percentagesA1–A2 A2–A3 A3–A4 A4–A5 AllD/nDAllD/nDAllD/nDAllD/nDAntipsychotics (AP)76.775.2/88.9*64.967.6/55.069.667.5/83.370.068.8/75.0 Trad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>AP73.670.8/84.261.463.3/57.173.773.3/75.080.075.0/100 Atypical AP74.574.7/80.061.563.0/50.062.159.3/100***60.062.5/50.0Antidepressants80.479.8/82.876.573.1/87.9*72.266.1/89.5**75.776.9/70.0Anxiolytics76.973.6/89.5**69.262.7/84.4**86.882.1/100**66.766.7/66.7Sedatives70.965.8/82.8**64.869.1/55.669.664.9/77.868.058.8/85.7Antidementia drug66.065.3/100***38.136.6/100***27.327.3/000/0Any PTD89.888.7/94.3*85.382.4/94.2**89.386.6/97.3**78.475.5/85.0A1–A5: Assessment 1–5 D Dementia CDR ≥ 1; nD No dementia CDR &lt; 1CDR ratings were missing for 4 people at A1, 2 people at A2 and 2 people at A3  CDR Clinical Dementia Rating scale Trad Conventional PTD Psychotropic drugs*p &lt; 0.05, **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001 (Z-test for proportions used) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>At baseline, the use of any PTD occurred more frequently in residents with dementia, while at the last follow-up any PTD was more often used in residents without dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Atypical antipsychotics were used more frequently in residents with dementia at A1–A3, whereas residents without dementia used anxiolytics more frequently at A2 and A3 and sedatives more frequently at A1–A4, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Persistent use of psychotropic drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The proportion of PTD use at two consecutive time points was high (&gt;50%) throughout the period for all types of PTD, except for use of anti-dementia drugs (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Persistent use of anxiolytics at two consecutive time points was higher for residents without dementia than those with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Among those who completed all assessments (n = 98), 10.4% used antipsychotic drugs, 19.8% used antidepressants, 11.5% used anxiolytics and 9.4% used sedatives at all assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Unadjusted and adjusted odds for use of PTD at one time point, given use of the same type of PTD at an earlier time point was estimated for all types of PTD except for anti-dementia drug use (Table 3 and Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Both in unadjusted and adjusted analyses, the odds for persistent use of antipsychotics, antidepressants, anxiolytics and sedative were high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The odds for persistent use of these PTD were highest when compared with use at the closest earlier assessment time point (Lag 1) and fell successively when the distance between the assessment time points increased (Lags 2 and 3), with one exception for antipsychotics where the odds slightly increased when there were three time points between assessments (Lag 3) compared to two time points (Lag 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>All results were highly significant (p &lt; 0.001).Table 3Odds ratios for use of each category of psychotropic drugs at one time point given use of the same category of the psychotropic drug at an earlier time point (the distance between time points is called lag), unadjusted and adjusted analyses where relevant covariates adjusted for were measured at the same earlier timeVariablesUnadjustedAdjustedOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueLag 1, N = 1406 observations Antipsychoticsa 30.7 (21.8; 43.1)&lt;0.00128.8 (20.31; 40.8)&lt;0.001 Antidepressantsb 32.6 (23.8; 44.8)&lt;0.00134.1 (24.6; 47.4)&lt;0.001 Anxiolyticsc 33.1 (23.7; 46.2)&lt;0.00132.2 (23.1; 45.0)&lt;0.001 Sedativesd 22.6 (15.6; 30.8)&lt;0.00123.1 (16.8; 31.7)&lt;0.001Lag 2, N = 654 observations Antipsychoticse 13.3 (8.3; 21.4)&lt;0.00113.5 (8.1; 22.3)&lt;0.001 Antidepressantsf 15.5 (9.9; 24.2)&lt;0.00116.0 (10.2; 25.3)&lt;0.001 Anxiolyticsg 21.4 (12.8; 35.7)&lt;0.00123.4 (13.9; 39.6)&lt;0.001 Sedativesh 9.3 (5.9; 14.4)&lt;0.0019.4 (5.9; 14.8)&lt;0.001Lag 3, N = 288 observations Antipsychoticsi 16.5 (7.5; 36.3)&lt;0.00117.9 (7.5; 42.4)&lt;0.001 Antidepressantsj 10.0 (4.9; 20.4)&lt;0.00112.6 (5.8; 27.2)&lt;0.001 Anxiolyticsk 14.4 (6.5; 32.1)&lt;0.00114.3 (7.0; 29.2)&lt;0.001 Sedativesl 7.0 (3.6; 13.9)&lt;0.0016.4 (3.2; 12.6)&lt;0.001Lag 1: two consecutive assessment time pointsLag 2: one time point between selected time pointsLag 3: two time points between selected time points aAdjusted for: PSMS score, NPI Agitation sub-syndrome, NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome, NPI Affective sub-syndrome, NH size age and duration in NH bAdjusted for: PSMS score, NPI- Affective sub-syndrome, NPI Apathy and duration in NH cAdjusted for CDR sum of boxes, NPI- Affective sub-syndrome and level of education dAdjusted for PSMS score, NPI Apathy and duration in NH eAdjusted for PSMS score, NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome, NPI Apathy, Type of nursing home and age fAdjusted for: CDR sum of boxes, PSMS score and NPI- Affective sub-syndrome gAdjusted for CDR sum of boxes, PSMS score and level of education hAdjusted for CDR sum of boxes, PSMS and age iAdjusted for PSMS score and age jAdjusted for: CDR sum of boxes, NPI- Affective sub-syndrome and NPI Apathy kAdjusted for NPI Agitation sub-syndrome, NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome, NPI Affective sub-syndrome, NPI Apathy, level of education and Type of nursing home unit lAdjusted for CDR sum of boxes, NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome and Nursing home size Fig. 2Illustration of OR for use of each category of psychotropic drugs at one time point given use of the same category of psychotropic drug at an earlier time point by distance (Lag) between the time points, unadjusted and adjusted. a Antipsychotics; b Antidepressants; c Anxiolytics; and d Sedatives </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Factors associated with use of psychotropic drugs at two consecutive time points </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The adjusted risk for persistent use of antipsychotics at two consecutive time points was elevated when residents had higher psychosis sub-syndrome score or were younger, were male or had a longer NH stay at baseline (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The adjusted risk for persistent use of antidepressants was elevated when residents had higher P-ADL functioning (lower PSMS score) or higher affective sub-syndrome score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The adjusted risk for persistent use of anxiolytics was elevated when residents had higher P-ADL functioning (lower PSMS score) or higher affective sub-syndrome score or stayed in a larger NH (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The adjusted risk for persistent use of sedatives was elevated when residents had better cognitive functioning (lower CDR sum of boxes) or higher affective sub-syndrome score or lower apathy symptom score.Table 4Odds of use of Antipsychotics or Antidepressants at one time point given use of Antipsychotics or Antidepressants at the previous time point, covariates measured at the “previous” time point, N = 1406 observationsVariablesAntipsychoticsAntidepressantsUnadjustedAdjustedUnadjustedAdjustedOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueAssessed at previous time point CDR sum of boxes1.04 (1.002; 1.07)0.0360.97 (0.95; 0.995)0.020 GMHR  Good1.25 (0.66; 2.37)0.4980.98 (0.59; 1.63)0.9340.63 (0.35; 1.12)3 0.111  Fairly good1.11 (0.63; 1.98)0.7151.29 (0.82; 2.02)0.2730.92 (0.56; 1.51)8 0.745  Poor1.53 (0.86; 2.72)0.1511.62 (1.03; 2.56)0.0381.34 (0.83; 2.16)5 0.229  Very Poor1-1-1- PSMS score1.03 (0.997; 1.06)0.0730.96 (0.94; 0.98)0.0010.94 (0.91; 0.97)2 &lt;0.001 NPI Agitation sub-syndrome1.05 (1.03; 1.07)&lt;0.0011.02 (0.997; 1.04)6 0.0930.997 (0.98; 1.01)0.714 NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome1.09 (1.06; 1.12)&lt;0.0011.06 (1.03; 1.10)2 0.0011.00 (0.98; 1.03)0.9150.97 (0.95; 1.00)4 0.060 NPI Affective sub-syndrome1.06 (1.03; 1.09)&lt;0.0011.03 (0.999; 1.07)5 0.0601.08 (1.05; 1.10)&lt;0.0011.08 (1.05; 1.11)1 &lt;0.001 NPI Apathy1.07 (1.03; 1.12)&lt;0.0010.99 (0.96; 1.03)0.732Assessed at baseline Age0.95 (0.93; 0.97)&lt;0.0010.95 (0.93; 0.97)1 &lt;0.0010.99 (0.98; 1.01)0.3170.98 (0.97; 1.00)6 0.056 Females0.56 (0.40; 0.80)0.0010.64 (0.44; 0.93)4 0.0191.38 (1.02; 1.87)0.0351.33 (0.97; 1.82)7 0.078 Education (&lt;=10 years)0.97 (0.68; 1.39)0.8650.88 (0.66; 1.17)0.385 Duration in NH (LN)1.21 (1.06; 1.40)0.0071.21 (1.05; 1.40)3 0.0110.98 (0.88; 1.09)0.654 Nursing home size0.998 (0.993; 1.003)0.3821.00 (0.998; 1.01)0.347 Type of nursing home unit  RU1-1-  REU0.57 (0.10; 3.41)0.5391.03 (0.30; 3.51)0.959  SCU1.24 (0.78; 1.97)0.3670.80 (0.55; 1.17)0.248  OU3.25 (0.63; 16.81)0.1601.13 (0.28; 4.61)10.865 RU Regular units REU rehabilitation unit SCU special care unit for people with dementia OU other unitsThe relative importance of each covariate in the adjusted models is included with a number after the 95% CI; lowest number has highest importance Table 5Odds of use of Anxiolytics or Sedatives or at one time point given use of Anxiolytics or Sedatives at a previous time point, covariates measured at the “previous” time point, N = 1406 observationsVariablesAnxiolyticsSedativesUnadjustedAdjustedUnadjustedAdjustedOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueOR (95% CI) P-valueAssessed at previous time point CDR sum of boxes0.96 (0.94; 0.99)0.0150.97 (0.94; 1.01)4 0.1250.94 (0.91; 0.97)&lt;0.0010.94 (0.91; 0.97)1 &lt;0.001 GMHR  Good1.31 (0.68; 2.54)0.4211.20 (0.65; 2.23)  Fairly good1.56 (0.87; 2.81)0.1381.42 (0.82; 2.47)0.560  Poor1.83 (1.01; 3.30)0.0461.43 (0.82; 2.49)0.209  Very Poor1-10.212 PSMS score0.96 (0.93; 0.98)0.0020.96 (0.93; 0.99)3 0.0160.95 (0.93; 0.98)- NPI Agitation sub-syndrome1.00 (0.98; 1.02)0.9640.99 (0.97; 1.01)0.001 NPI Psychosis sub-syndrome1.01 (0.98; 1.04)0.4511.00 (0.97; 1.04)0.358 NPI Affective sub-syndrome1.08 (1.05; 1.11)&lt;0.0011.09 (1.06; 1.12)1 &lt;0.0011.04 (1.01; 1.07)0.8780.0051.06 (1.03; 1.09)2 &lt;0.001 NPI Apathy1.01 (0.97; 1.05)0.6620.94 (0.90; 0.99)0.0120.95 (0.90; 0.996)4 0.034Assessed at baseline Age0.997 (0.98; 1.02)0.7751.002 (0.98; 1.02)0.812 Females1.01 (0.71; 1.44)0.9671.28 (0.89; 1.83)0.182 Education (&lt;=10 years)1.16 (0.81; 1.66)0.4160.82 (0.59; 1.15)0.2530.77 (0.54; 1.08)5 0.125 Duration in NH (LN)1.07 (0.94; 1.22)0.2921.12 (0.98; 1.28)5 0.1010.91 (0.81; 1.04)0.164 Nursing home size1.01 (1.002; 1.01)0.0041.007 (1.002; 1.011)2 0.0021.00 (0.999; 1.01)0.1091.004 (1.00; 1.008)3 0.072 Type of nursing home unit  RU1-1-  REU0.18 (0.02; 1.83)0.1462.35 (0.63; 8.79)0.2060.7540.62 (0.39; 0.98)0.041  SCU0.93 (0.58; 1.49)  OU2.96 (0.54; 16.13)0.2091.67 (0.34; 8.19)0.526 RU Regular units REU rehabilitation unit SCU special care unit for people with dementia OU other unitsThe relative importance of each covariate in the adjusted models is included with a number after the 95% CI; lowest number has highest importance </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In a subsequent analysis where sub-syndrome scores of NPS at the first time point were replaced by change in sub-syndrome score between the two assessments, we found no association between change in the sub-syndrome scores of NPS and persistent use of antipsychotic drugs, antidepressants, anxiolytics or sedatives. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In this Norwegian NH study, the prevalence and persistent use of PTD at two consecutive time points was high, both for residents with and without dementia, except for use of an anti-dementia drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Close to three-quarters of the dementia and two-thirds of non-dementia residents used PTD at baseline of the data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Persistent use of anxiolytics was more common in residents without dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The persistent use decreased gradually when the distance between the assessment time points increased (Lags 2 and 3), with the exception of the use of antipsychotics drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>More severe NPS were associated with persistent use of antipsychotics drugs, antidepressants, anxiolytics and sedatives at the next time point, but change in NPS between the time points was not associated with persistent use of PTD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Better P-ADL functioning (lower PSMS score) was associated with persistent use of antidepressants and anxiolytics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, less severe dementia was associated with persistent use of sedatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Of the organizational variables included in the analysis, we found that a longer stay in NH increased the odds for persistent use of antipsychotics at two consecutive time points and staying in a larger-sized NH increased the odds for persistent use of anxiolytics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Use of antipsychotics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The study found that the prevalence of atypical antipsychotics was higher in residents with dementia than in residents without, but only for the first three time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Use of conventional antipsychotics did not differ between residents with or without dementia at any time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The persistence in use of both atypical and conventional antipsychotics at two consecutive time points was high (&gt;50%) during the entire follow-up period of 72 months for both groups of residents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A small 6-month follow-up study of newly arrived NH residents in Australia has previously reported the persistence of antipsychotics to be equally high [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Given the strong evidence on the increased mortality risk associated with use of conventional antipsychotics in people with dementia it is rather surprising to see that they are still used to that extent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>These findings are alarming, since the duration of such treatment should be as short as possible [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In the present adjusted logistic regression analysis for persistent use of antipsychotic drugs at two consecutive time points, higher severity of psychosis increased the risk for persistent use of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>However, it is surprising that in the exploratory analysis, a change in NPS was not associated with persistent use of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Clinical recommendations have highlighted the need for clinicians to monitor NPS closely and consider discontinuing treatment with antipsychotics when an obvious treatment effect does not occur or the residents have side effects due to the treatment [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>It could be that people receiving PTD had more severe symptoms prior to drug initiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Also, it could be that antipsychotics were described as unspecific sedatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Very few studies have examined variables associated with persistent use of antipsychotics in NH residents [46, 52], but none of these studies have explicitly explored the importance of NPS in the persistent use of antipsychotic drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>However, cross-sectional studies have explored the association between NPS and use of antipsychotic drugs and found that higher total symptom load [80] and more severe psychosis sub-syndromes symptoms were associated with use of antipsychotics [11, 14, 81, 82]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In the adjusted logistic regression analysis of use of antipsychotics, younger age and male gender increased the risk for persistent use of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In contrast, a small Swedish 6-month follow-up study in NH residents with dementia did not find age, gender or other personal characteristics of the residents such as P-ADL or cognitive functioning important for persistent use of antipsychotics [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Our finding may partly be explained by age and gender-based expressions of behavioral symptoms [80] not captured by the NPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Male and younger residents may be experienced as more threatening in their verbal or physical expressions and are physically stronger compared to women and older residents, and for this reason may be put on antipsychotic drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In line with our results, cross-sectional studies of use of antipsychotics in NH residents have found that younger residents [4, 8, 15, 22, 80, 82, 83] and male residents [5, 80, 84] are more likely to receive antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Persistent use of antipsychotics has been reported to be more frequent in regular care units than in SCU [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In the present study we did not find an association between the type of care unit and persistent use of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In Norway, SCUs have residents with more severe NPS than other units, which could explain our result [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, we found that residents with a longer stay in NH at baseline had an increased likelihood of being persistent users of antipsychotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We do not have a firm explanation for this, but it may be that newly arrived NH residents receive more attention from the staff or respond better to care that is intended to reduce stress, strain and symptoms related to dementia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Use of antidepressants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>We found, in line with other studies, that antidepressants were the most frequently used PTD in NH residents [48, 49] and that the frequency did not differ between residents with or without dementia [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The persistence of use of antidepressants was also high [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>As we could expect, those with more severe affective symptoms had higher odds for persistent use of antidepressants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This result is in line with cross-sectional studies of associations for use of antidepressants [11, 15, 81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Even so, the efficacy of antidepressants in treating depression in persons with dementia is uncertain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The high prevalence and persistence of antidepressants use may indicate that these drugs also are used for the treatment of agitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Better performance in P-ADL was more likely to be associated with persistent antidepressant users. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We do not have a firm explanation for this, but it may be that those with better P-ADL also have a better ability to express their emotional state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Use of anxiolytics, sedatives and anti-dementia drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of anxiolytics in the NH residents varied between 20 and 40%, and was significantly higher in residents without dementia, while the persistent use of anxiolytics in adjusted analysis was not explained by the severity of dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>As for antidepressants, persistent use of anxiolytics was explained by more severe affective symptoms and better P-ADL functioning, but not by change in affective sub-syndrome symptoms between time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The size of the NH was associated with persistent use of anxiolytics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>We speculate that staff distress [81], registered nursing hours per resident [86] and other organizational factors [5] that we have not measured may be related to NH size, quality of care and use or persistent use of anxiolytics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Use of sedatives was higher among residents without dementia than residents with dementia and varied between 19 and 26% in residents with dementia and between 32 and 40% in residents without dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A possible explanation may be that residents without dementia are more vulnerable to disturbances in the NH environment and at the same time may be more able to ask for sedatives than residents with dementia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of anti-dementia drugs use was at baseline 11.3% for all residents and as expected the prevalence of such use declined at each of the follow-ups and at the fifth assessment no one used anti-dementia drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>At the four first assessment time points between 1.9 to 2.2% of residents with CDR less than 1 were prescribed anti-dementia drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This may indicate that the NH physicians have prescribed the anti-dementia drugs without having a dementia diagnosis (P70), but the physicians may have used the diagnosis cognitive problems (P20) as an indication for prescribing the drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This is quite common in Norway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>However, in a recent Norwegian study it was found that a substantial number of persons who purchased anti-dementia drugs had no diagnosis of dementia or cognitive problems registered in the primary health care service system [87]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Strength and limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The study has significant strengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Firstly, all nurses participating in the data collection participated in a 2-day educational course to ensure that they had adequate knowledge prior to collecting data for this study and participated in a 1-day educational course before the follow-up data collections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This ensured high data quality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Secondly, a large sample size allowed us to adjust for many potentially important variables, such as health and demographic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, this study benefits from the inclusion of NHs located in a large part of the country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot guarantee that the sample is representative for Norwegian NH residents since inclusion was not based on random selection from all NHs in Norway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The study has some limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the data from the present study is quite old since data collection started in 2004, and thus, may not represent medication use patterns in Norwegian NHs of today. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Secondly, a high drop-out rate mainly due to death might have introduced some bias into the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>However, this methodological problem is inherent to most longitudinal NH studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Also, we used linear mixed models that include all available data (data from drop-outs as well) in the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Due to the low number of participants at the end of the follow-up period, the analysis of persistence was limited to three lags only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Thirdly, the time intervals between the assessments varied somewhat among participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>However, this affects the results only minimally, since the time intervals between assessments were quite long and not used in the models explicitly, only as lags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In the present study the time intervals between the assessments were 1 year or more and due to the study design, we do not know whether there were changes in PTD use between assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Fourthly, there is a limitation on the accuracy of dementia diagnoses, since dementia and degree of dementia are based on the CDR rating of several assessors and the fact that a CDR assessment was used, and not a standardized dementia diagnosis, including neuropsychological tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>A large number of residents with a CDR score of 3 could not be tested with any dementia tests such as the Mini Mental Status Examination or the Clock Drawing Test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>However, CDR is an accepted assessment tool and is commonly used in epidemiological NH studies to identify dementia and measure the severity of dementia [65, 88], and the agreement between CDR and a diagnostic assessment according to the ICD-10 is high [62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Psychotropic drugs were frequently used as a long-term treatment among NH residents and were associated with severity of neuropsychiatric symptoms, but not with severity of dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The high prevalence and persistence of psychotropic drug use may indicate that the treatment is not in line with current treatment recommendation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>It is important that clinicians monitor effects and side effects of PTD treatment closely and stop treatment when the risk is not balanced by considerable benefits to the NH resident. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CDR</term><def><p>Clinical Dementia Rating</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>Confidence intervals</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GMHR</term><def><p>General Medical Health Rating</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NH</term><def><p>Nursing home</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NPI</term><def><p>Neuropsychiatric Inventory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NPS</term><def><p>Neuropsychiatric symptoms</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>Odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OU</term><def><p>Other units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P-ADL</term><def><p>Personal Activities of Daily Living</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSMS</term><def><p>Physical Self-Maintenance Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTD</term><def><p>Psychotropic drugs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>REU</term><def><p>Rehabilitation unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RU</term><def><p>Regular units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCU</term><def><p>Special care unit for people with dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>Standard deviation</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>Data collection was funded by unrestricted grants from the Eastern Norway Regional Health authorities.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p>The datasets analyzed during the current study are not publicly available due access limitations given by the Regional Ethics Committee in the south east of Norway, the Data Inspectorate and the Directorate for Health and Social Affairs in 2004.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>GS and KE designed the study. GS was responsible for the data collection and quality assurance of the study results. JSB analyzed the majority of the data for this manuscript, and ASH did some analysis and drafted the manuscript. All authors participated in interpreting the study results, editing the manuscript, as well as reading and approving the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The study was recommended and approved by the Regional Ethics Committee in the south east of Norway, the Data Inspectorate and the Directorate for Health and Social Affairs in 2004 before data collection.</p><p>Study information in written and oral form was given to the residents and in case of limited capacity to understand the information, to their closest family proxy. The responsible health worker at the nursing home decided whether the resident had capacity to understand the information. No explicit consent was required and the participants were included on an opt-out basis. Furthermore, the residents or their next of kin were informed that they could refuse to participate at any stage of the study. This procedure was approved by the Regional Ethics Committee in the south east of Norway and the Data Inspectorate and the Directorate for Health and Social Affairs.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>1.HuberMAntipsychotic drugs predominate in pharmacotherapy of nursing home residents with dementiaPharmacopsychiatry2012451828<?supplied-pmid 22430201?>22430201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>2.Hosia-RandellHPitkalaKUse of psychotropic drugs in elderly nursing home residents with and without dementia in Helsinki, FinlandDrugs Aging20052279380010.2165/00002512-200522090-00008<?supplied-pmid 16156683?>16156683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>3.GobertMD'HooreWPrevalence of psychotropic drug use in nursing homes for the aged in Quebec and in the French-speaking area of SwitzerlandInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2005207122110.1002/gps.1349<?supplied-pmid 16035123?>16035123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>4.AzermaiMElseviersMPetrovicMvan BortelLSticheleRVAssessment of antipsychotic prescribing in Belgian nursing homesInt Psychogeriatr2011231240810.1017/S104161021100024X<?supplied-pmid 21418723?>21418723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>5.Petek SterMCedilnik GorupEPsychotropic medication use among elderly nursing home residents in Slovenia: cross-sectional studyCroat Med J201152162410.3325/cmj.2011.52.16<?supplied-pmid 21328716?>21328716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>6.MannEPrevalence and associations of potentially inappropriate prescriptions in Austrian nursing home residents: secondary analysis of a cross-sectional studyWien Klin Wochenschr2013125180810.1007/s00508-013-0342-2<?supplied-pmid 23536016?>23536016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>7.RichterTMannEMeyerGHaastertBKopkeSPrevalence of psychotropic medication use among German and Austrian nursing home residents: a comparison of 3 cohortsJ Am Med Dir Assoc201213187.e7187.e1310.1016/j.jamda.2011.03.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>8.FengZUse of physical restraints and antipsychotic medications in nursing homes: a cross-national studyInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2009241110810.1002/gps.2232<?supplied-pmid 19280680?>19280680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>9.EggermontLHde VriesKScherderEJPsychotropic medication use and cognition in institutionalized older adults with mild to moderate dementiaInt Psychogeriatr2009212869410.1017/S1041610209008552<?supplied-pmid 19243660?>19243660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>10.ZuidemaSUDerksenEVerheyFRKoopmansRTPrevalence of neuropsychiatric symptoms in a large sample of Dutch nursing home patients with dementiaInt J Geriatr Psychiatry200722632810.1002/gps.1722<?supplied-pmid 17136713?>17136713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>11.NijkRMZuidemaSUKoopmansRTPrevalence and correlates of psychotropic drug use in Dutch nursing-home patients with dementiaInt Psychogeriatr2009214859310.1017/S1041610209008916<?supplied-pmid 19368752?>19368752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>12.LovheimHSandmanPOKarlssonSGustafsonYChanges between 1982 and 2000 in the prevalence of behavioral symptoms and psychotropic drug treatment among old people with cognitive impairment in geriatric careInt Psychogeriatr200921941810.1017/S1041610209990329<?supplied-pmid 19586566?>19586566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>13.BalalleCJayalathDShankarKAshayeKPrevalence and management of behavioural and psychiatric symptoms on a continuing care unit for patients with dementiaInt J Psychiatry Med2010404253810.2190/PM.40.4.f<?supplied-pmid 21391413?>21391413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>14.Int J Geriatr PsychiatryPsychotropic use and associated neuropsychiatric symptoms among patients with dementia in the USA. . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>2016(Maust DT, Langa KM, Blow FC, Kales HC). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>15.GustafssonMSandmanPOKarlssonSGustafsonYLovheimHAssociation between behavioral and psychological symptoms and psychotropic drug use among old people with cognitive impairment living in geriatric care settingsInt Psychogeriatr20132514152310.1017/S1041610213000859<?supplied-pmid 23782794?>23782794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>16.SelbaekGKirkevoldOEngedalKPsychiatric and behavioural symptoms and the use of psychotropic medication in Special Care Units and Regular Units in Norwegian nursing homesScand J Caring Sci2008225687310.1111/j.1471-6712.2007.00576.x<?supplied-pmid 18801019?>18801019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>17.OlssonJQuality of drug prescribing in elderly people in nursing homes and special care units for dementia: a cross-sectional computerized pharmacy register analysisClin Drug Investig20103028930010.2165/11534320-000000000-00000<?supplied-pmid 20384385?>20384385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>18.RuthsSTrends in psychotropic drug prescribing in Norwegian nursing homes from 1997 to 2009: a comparison of six cohortsInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2013288687610.1002/gps.3902<?supplied-pmid 23147389?>23147389 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>19.NurminenJPuustinenJKukolaMKivelaSLThe use of chemical restraints for older long-term hospital patients: a case report from FinlandJ Elder Abuse Negl2009218910410.1080/08946560902779860<?supplied-pmid 19347712?>19347712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>20.BerghSEngedalKRoenISelbaekGThe course of neuropsychiatric symptoms in patients with dementia in Norwegian nursing homesInt Psychogeriatr2011231231910.1017/S1041610211001177<?supplied-pmid 21729409?>21729409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>21.SelbaekGKirkevoldOEngedalKThe course of psychiatric and behavioral symptoms and the use of psychotropic medication in patients with dementia in Norwegian nursing homes--a 12-month follow-up studyAm J Geriatr Psychiatry2008165283610.1097/JGP.0b013e318167ae76<?supplied-pmid 18591573?>18591573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>22.NygaardHARuthsSStraandJNaikMNot less but different: psychotropic drug utilization trends in Norwegian nursing homes during a 12-year period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The Bergen District Nursing Home (BEDNURS) StudyAging Clin Exp Res2004162778210.1007/BF03324552<?supplied-pmid 15575121?>15575121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>23.ConnellyPJLawEAngusSPrenticeNFifteen year comparison of antipsychotic use in people with dementia within hospital and nursing home settings: sequential cross-sectional studyInt J Geriatr Psychiatry201025160510.1002/gps.2313<?supplied-pmid 19513989?>19513989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>24.CastleNGHanlonJTHandlerSMResults of a longitudinal analysis of national data to examine relationships between organizational and market characteristics and changes in antipsychotic prescribing in US nursing homes from 1996 through 2006Am J Geriatr Pharmacother200971435010.1016/j.amjopharm.2009.05.001<?supplied-pmid 19616182?>19616182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="?"><plain>25.GabodaDLucasJSiegelMKalayECrystalSNo longer undertreated? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Depression diagnosis and antidepressant therapy in elderly long-stay nursing home residents, 1999 to 2007J Am Geriatr Soc2011596738010.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03322.x<?supplied-pmid 21410441?>21410441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>26.HanlonJTHandlerSMCastleNGAntidepressant prescribing in US nursing homes between 1996 and 2006 and its relationship to staffing patterns and use of other psychotropic medicationsJ Am Med Dir Assoc201011320410.1016/j.jamda.2010.01.007<?supplied-pmid 20511098?>20511098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>27.VasudevATrends in psychotropic dispensing among older adults with dementia living in long-term care facilities: 2004-2013Am J Geriatr Psychiatry20152312596910.1016/j.jagp.2015.07.001<?supplied-pmid 26525997?>26525997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>28.Simoni-WastilaLRyderPTQianJZuckermanIHShafferTZhaoLAssociation of antipsychotic use with hospital events and mortality among medicare beneficiaries residing in long-term care facilitiesAm J Geriatr Psychiatry2009174172710.1097/JGP.0b013e31819b8936<?supplied-pmid 19390299?>19390299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>29.AlanenHMFinne-SoveriHNoroALeinonenEUse of antipsychotic medications among elderly residents in long-term institutional care: a three-year follow-upInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2006212889510.1002/gps.1462<?supplied-pmid 16477588?>16477588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>30.HelvikASSeverity of neuropsychiatric symptoms in nursing home residentsDement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra20166284210.1159/000442250<?supplied-pmid 26933438?>26933438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>31.Janus SI, van Manen JG, IJzerman MJ, Zuidema SU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Psychotropic drug prescriptions in Western European nursing homes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Int Psychogeriatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>2016;1–16. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>32.JesteDVACNP White Paper: update on use of antipsychotic drugs in elderly persons with dementiaNeuropsychopharmacology2008339577010.1038/sj.npp.1301492<?supplied-pmid 17637610?>17637610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>33.SinkKMHoldenKFYaffeKPharmacological treatment of neuropsychiatric symptoms of dementia: a review of the evidenceJama200529359660810.1001/jama.293.5.596<?supplied-pmid 15687315?>15687315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>34.Declercq T, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Withdrawal versus continuation of chronic antipsychotic drugs for behavioural and psychological symptoms in older people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Cochrane Database Syst Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>2013. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD007726.pub2. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>35.PuustinenJCNS medications as predictors of precipitous cognitive decline in the cognitively disabled aged: a longitudinal population-based studyDement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra20122576810.1159/000336710<?supplied-pmid 22619661?>22619661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>36.DouglasIJSmeethLExposure to antipsychotics and risk of stroke: self controlled case series studyBMJ2008337a122710.1136/bmj.a1227<?supplied-pmid 18755769?>18755769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>37.HartikainenSLonnroosELouhivuoriKMedication as a risk factor for falls: critical systematic reviewJ Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci20076211728110.1093/gerona/62.10.1172<?supplied-pmid 17921433?>17921433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>38.SchneiderLSDagermanKSInselPRisk of death with atypical antipsychotic drug treatment for dementia: meta-analysis of randomized placebo-controlled trialsJama200529419344310.1001/jama.294.15.1934<?supplied-pmid 16234500?>16234500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>39.NelsonJCDevanandDPA systematic review and meta-analysis of placebo-controlled antidepressant studies in people with depression and dementiaJ Am Geriatr Soc2011595778510.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03355.x<?supplied-pmid 21453380?>21453380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>40.BerghSSelbaekGEngedalKDiscontinuation of antidepressants in people with dementia and neuropsychiatric symptoms (DESEP study): double blind, randomised, parallel group, placebo controlled trialBMJ201234410.1136/bmj.e1566<?supplied-pmid 22408266?>22408266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>41.YokoiYMisalMOhEBellantoniMRosenbergPBBenzodiazepine discontinuation and patient outcome in a chronic geriatric medical/psychiatric unit: a retrospective chart reviewGeriatr Gerontol Int2014143889410.1111/ggi.12113<?supplied-pmid 24666628?>24666628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>42.NurminenJHandgrip strength and balance in older adults following withdrawal from long-term use of temazepam, zopiclone or zolpidem as hypnoticsBMC Geriatr20141412110.1186/1471-2318-14-121<?supplied-pmid 25416480?>25416480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>43.TsunodaKUchidaHSuzukiTWatanabeKYamashimaTKashimaHEffects of discontinuing benzodiazepine-derivative hypnotics on postural sway and cognitive functions in the elderlyInt J Geriatr Psychiatry20102512596510.1002/gps.2465<?supplied-pmid 20054834?>20054834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>44.TveitoMChanges in cognitive function during psychogeriatric treatment in relation to benzodiazepine cessationPharmacopsychiatry2014471455010.1055/s-0034-1381982<?supplied-pmid 24936805?>24936805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>45.LakeySLGraySLSalesAESullivanJHedrickSCPsychotropic use in community residential care facilities: a prospective cohort studyAm J Geriatr Pharmacother200642273510.1016/j.amjopharm.2006.09.010<?supplied-pmid 17062323?>17062323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>46.NobiliAAlzheimer special care units compared with traditional nursing home for dementia care: are there differences at admission and in clinical outcomes?Alzheimer Dis Assoc Disord2008223526110.1097/WAD.0b013e31818207d0<?supplied-pmid 18978601?>18978601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>47.LustenbergerISchupbachBvon GuntenAMosimannUPsychotropic medication use in Swiss nursing homesSwiss Med Wkly2011141w13254<?supplied-pmid 21971698?>21971698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>48.BarcaMLEngedalKLaksJSelbaekGA 12 months follow-up study of depression among nursing-home patients in NorwayJ Affect Disord2010120141810.1016/j.jad.2009.04.028<?supplied-pmid 19467560?>19467560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>49.O'ConnorDWGriffithJMcSweeneyKChanges to psychotropic medications in the six months after admission to nursing homes in Melbourne, AustraliaInt Psychogeriatr20102211495310.1017/S1041610210000165<?supplied-pmid 20199701?>20199701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>50.WetzelsRBZuidemaSUde JongheJFVerheyFRKoopmansRTPrescribing pattern of psychotropic drugs in nursing home residents with dementiaInt Psychogeriatr20112312495910.1017/S1041610211000755<?supplied-pmid 21682938?>21682938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>51.ParsonsCSedative load of medications prescribed for older people with dementia in care homesBMC Geriatr2011115610.1186/1471-2318-11-56<?supplied-pmid 21958366?>21958366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>52.GustafssonMKarlssonSLovheimHInappropriate long-term use of antipsychotic drugs is common among people with dementia living in specialized care unitsBMC Pharmacol Toxicol2013141010.1186/2050-6511-14-10<?supplied-pmid 23391323?>23391323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>53.van de Ven-VakhteevaJBorHWetzelsRBKoopmansRTZuidemaSUThe impact of antipsychotics and neuropsychiatric symptoms on the quality of life of people with dementia living in nursing homesInt J Geriatr Psychiatry201328530810.1002/gps.3858<?supplied-pmid 22886912?>22886912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>54.VerbeekHZwakhalenSMvan RossumEAmbergenTKempenGIHamersJPEffects of small-scale, home-like facilities in dementia care on residents' behavior, and use of physical restraints and psychotropic drugs: a quasi-experimental studyInt Psychogeriatr2014266576810.1017/S1041610213002512<?supplied-pmid 24411467?>24411467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>55.van der CammenTJRajkumarCOnderGSterkeCSPetrovicMDrug cessation in complex older adults: time for actionAge Ageing20144320510.1093/ageing/aft166<?supplied-pmid 24222659?>24222659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>56.SelbaekGKirkevoldOEngedalKThe prevalence of psychiatric symptoms and behavioural disturbances and the use of psychotropic drugs in Norwegian nursing homesInt J Geriatr Psychiatry200722843910.1002/gps.1749<?supplied-pmid 17193341?>17193341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>57.Statsbudsjettet 2013 Finansdepartementet, Editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>2013, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.statsbudsjettet.no/Statsbudsjettet-2013/Budsjettsporsmal/Bevilgningssporsmal/Fremskrittspartiet779/?parti=#hopp">http://www.statsbudsjettet.no/Statsbudsjettet-2013/Budsjettsporsmal/Bevilgningssporsmal/Fremskrittspartiet779/?parti=#hopp</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>58.BoltzMResnickBChippendaleTGalvinJTesting a family-centered intervention to promote functional and cognitive recovery in hospitalized older adultsJ Am Geriatr Soc2014622398407<?supplied-pmid 25481973?>25481973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>59.2015 WCCfDSM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>WHO Collaborating Centre for Drug Statistics Metodology ATC/DDD Index, 2015, Oslo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>2015 26.08.2015]. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>60.HughesCPBergLDanzigerWLCobenLAMartinRLA new clinical scale for the staging of dementiaBr J Psychiatry19821405667210.1192/bjp.140.6.566<?supplied-pmid 7104545?>7104545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>61.MorrisJCThe Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR): current version and scoring rulesNeurology1993432412410.1212/WNL.43.11.2412-a<?supplied-pmid 8232972?>8232972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>62.EngedalKHaugenPThe prevalence of dementia in a sample of elderly NorwegiansInt J Geriatr Psychiatry199385657010.1002/gps.930080706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>63.NygaardHANaikMRuthsSMental impairment in nursing home residentsTidsskr Nor Laegeforen200012031136<?supplied-pmid 11109355?>11109355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>64.WaiteLInformant-based staging of dementia using the clinical dementia ratingAlzheimer Dis Assoc Disord19991334710.1097/00002093-199903000-00005<?supplied-pmid 10192640?>10192640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>65.MjorudMKirkevoldMRosvikJSelbaekGEngedalKVariables associated to quality of life among nursing home patients with dementiaAging Ment Health20141810132110.1080/13607863.2014.903468<?supplied-pmid 24911813?>24911813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>66.O'BryantSEStaging dementia using clinical dementia rating scale sum of boxes scores: a Texas Alzheimer's research consortium studyArch Neurol2008651091510.1001/archneur.65.8.1091<?supplied-pmid 18695059?>18695059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>67.FolsteinMFFolsteinSEMcHughPR"Mini-mental state". </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinicianJ Psychiatr Res1975121899810.1016/0022-3956(75)90026-6<?supplied-pmid 1202204?>1202204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>68.ShulmanKIClock-drawing: is it the ideal cognitive screening test?Int J Geriatr Psychiatry2000155486110.1002/1099-1166(200006)15:6&lt;548::AID-GPS242&gt;3.0.CO;2-U<?supplied-pmid 10861923?>10861923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>69.LyketsosCGThe General Medical Health Rating: a bedside global rating of medical comorbidity in patients with dementiaJ Am Geriatr Soc1999474879110.1111/j.1532-5415.1999.tb07245.x<?supplied-pmid 10203127?>10203127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>70.LyketsosCPopulation-based study of medical comorbidity in early dementia and “cognitive impairment, no dementia (CIND)”: association with functional and cognitive impairment: the cache county studyAm J Geriatr Psychiatry20041365664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>71.HelvikASHealth-related quality of life in older depressed psychogeriatric patients: one year follow-upBMC Geriatr20161613110.1186/s12877-016-0310-6<?supplied-pmid 27388445?>27388445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>72.WergelandJNSelbaekGBerghSSoederhamnUKirkevoldOPredictors for nursing home admission and death among community-dwelling people 70 years and older who receive domiciliary careDement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra20155320910.1159/000437382<?supplied-pmid 26483831?>26483831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>73.LawtonMPBrodyEMAssessment of older people: self-maintaining and instrumental activities of daily livingGerontologist196991798610.1093/geront/9.3_Part_1.179<?supplied-pmid 5349366?>5349366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>74.CummingsJLthe neuropsychiatric inventory: assessing psychopathology in dementia patientsNeurology199748S10610.1212/WNL.48.5_Suppl_6.10S<?supplied-pmid 9153155?>9153155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>75.SelbaekGKirkevoldOSommerOHEngedalKThe reliability and validity of the Norwegian version of the Neuropsychiatric Inventory, nursing home version (NPI-NH)Int Psychogeriatr2008203758210.1017/S1041610207005601<?supplied-pmid 17559707?>17559707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>76.ColomboMVitaliSCairatiMVaccaroRAndreoniGGuaitaABehavioral and psychotic symptoms of dementia (BPSD) improvements in a special care unit: a factor analysisArch Gerontol Geriatr200744Suppl 11132010.1016/j.archger.2007.01.017<?supplied-pmid 17317443?>17317443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>77.ZuidemaSUde JongheJFVerheyFRKoopmansRTNeuropsychiatric symptoms in nursing home patients: factor structure invariance of the Dutch nursing home version of the neuropsychiatric inventory in different stages of dementiaDement Geriatr Cogn Disord2007241697610.1159/000105603<?supplied-pmid 17641527?>17641527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>78.Selbaek G, Engedal K, Benth JS, Bergh S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The course of neuropsychiatric symptoms in nursing-home patients with dementia over a 53-month follow-up period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Int Psychogeriatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>2013;1–11. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>79.SylliaasHSelbaekGBerglandADo behavioral disturbances predict falls among nursing home residents?Aging Clin Exp Res201224251610.1007/BF03325253<?supplied-pmid 23114551?>23114551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>80.KamblePChenHShererJAparasuRRAntipsychotic drug use among elderly nursing home residents in the United StatesAm J Geriatr Pharmacother200861879710.1016/j.amjopharm.2008.10.002<?supplied-pmid 19028374?>19028374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>81.ZuidemaSUde JongheJFVerheyFRKoopmansRTPsychotropic drug prescription in nursing home patients with dementia: influence of environmental correlates and staff distress on physicians' prescription behaviorInt Psychogeriatr2011231632910.1017/S1041610211001438<?supplied-pmid 21813036?>21813036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>82.GelladWFUse of antipsychotics among older residents in VA nursing homesMed Care2012509546010.1097/MLR.0b013e31825fb21d<?supplied-pmid 23047785?>23047785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>83.ShahSMCareyIMHarrisTDewildeSCookDGAntipsychotic prescribing to older people living in care homes and the community in England and WalesInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2011264233410.1002/gps.2557<?supplied-pmid 20878663?>20878663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>84.ChenYBriesacherBAFieldTSTjiaJLauDTGurwitzJHUnexplained variation across US nursing homes in antipsychotic prescribing ratesArch Intern Med2010170899510.1001/archinternmed.2009.469<?supplied-pmid 20065204?>20065204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>85.van AschIFNuyenJVeerbeekMAFrijtersDHAchterbergWPPotAMThe diagnosis of depression and use of antidepressants in nursing home residents with and without dementiaInt J Geriatr Psychiatry201328312810.1002/gps.3830<?supplied-pmid 22588705?>22588705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>86.KimHWhallALFactors associated with psychotropic drug usage among nursing home residents with dementiaNurs Res200655252810.1097/00006199-200607000-00005<?supplied-pmid 16849977?>16849977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>87.DiazEKumarBNEngedalKImmigrant patients with dementia and memory impairment in primary health care in Norway: a national registry studyDement Geriatr Cogn Disord2015393213110.1159/000375526<?supplied-pmid 25823461?>25823461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>88.LeoutsakosJMEffects of general medical health on Alzheimer's progression: the cache county dementia progression studyInt Psychogeriatr20122415617010.1017/S104161021200049X<?supplied-pmid 22687143?>22687143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
