<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5462789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03420-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The dynamic functional core network of the human brain at rest </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kabbara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><address><email>aya.kabbara7@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>EL Falou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wendling</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0307-5086</contrib-id><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>INSERM, U1099, F-35000 Rennes, France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.463996.7</institution-id><institution/><institution>University of Rennes 1, LTSI, </institution></institution-wrap>F-35000 Rennes, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2324 3572</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411324.1</institution-id><institution>Azm Center for Research in Biotechnology and its Application, EDST, </institution><institution>Lebanese University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beirut, Lebanon </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2324 3572</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411324.1</institution-id><institution>CRSI research center, Faculty of Engineering, </institution><institution>Lebanese University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beirut, Lebanon </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>2936</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The human brain is an inherently complex and dynamic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Even at rest, functional brain networks dynamically reconfigure in a well-organized way to warrant an efficient communication between brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, a precise characterization of this reconfiguration at very fast time-scale (hundreds of millisecond) during rest remains elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used dense electroencephalography data recorded during task-free paradigm to track the fast temporal dynamics of spontaneous brain networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Results obtained from network-based analysis methods revealed the existence of a functional dynamic core network formed of a set of key brain regions that ensure segregation and integration functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Brain regions within this functional core share high betweenness centrality, strength and vulnerability (high impact on the network global efficiency) and low clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>These regions are mainly located in the cingulate and the medial frontal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In particular, most of the identified hubs were found to belong to the Default Mode Network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Results also revealed that the same central regions may dynamically alternate and play the role of either provincial (local) or connector (global) hubs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The human brain is a complex network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Even at rest, spatially distributed brain regions are functionally connected, in a very organized way, to continuously share information with each other1–4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The intrinsic connectivity networks (ICNs), also known as Resting State Networks (RSNs), are now widely recognized and found to be quite consistent across subjects1, 5–13 as well as neuroimaging techniques14–17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The most commonly known RSNs are the default mode network (DMN), the dorsal attention network (DAN), the ventral attention network (VAN), the motor network, the visual network (VIS), and the auditory network (AUD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Several studies have reported the existence of few critical regions that may play a key role in establishing and maintaining an efficient brain communication at rest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The presence of central brain regions or ‘hubs’ at rest has been revealed for structural18–27 and functional28–32 connections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In addition to their highly central role, recent studies have shown that these brain hubs tend to be densely interconnected with each other more than expected by chance, forming the so called rich-club organization of the human brain33–35. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Using Magnetoencephalography (MEG) or/and Electroencephalography (EEG), it was shown that these RSNs have an electrophysiological basis16, 36–41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In a preliminary study32, we used dense-EEG recordings to confirm the existence of brain regions playing the role of hubs in a static scenario. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Yet, the main gain of using M/EEG is the excellent temporal resolution that allows the tracking of the temporal dynamics of RSNs at sub-second time scale, not reachable when using fMRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Various MEG studies showed the crucial role of the DMN, and the cingulate cortex in particular, in maintaining efficient temporal communication in the whole brain16, 42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Other studies focused on assessing the temporal transitions between RSNs40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>However, none of them looked at the temporal transition between brain regions, networks and modules over hundreds of millisecond time scale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>To tackle this issue, we collected dense-EEG data from 20 subjects sitting without performing any particular task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We then reconstructed the functional networks using EEG source connectivity approach as described in previous work32, 43, 44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Topologies of the identified networks were characterized in terms of node’s strength, vulnerability, betweenness centrality and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we extend our previous static analysis32 toward the study of the dynamic interactions between resting state networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We have also explored the dynamic modularity and classified brain regions into provincial (intra-community) and connector (inter-community) hubs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Our results revealed the existence of a dynamic core network located mainly in the cingulate and the medial frontal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We found that a large proportion of the brain hubs belong to the DMN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Results also revealed that the same brain hubs might dynamically change their actions and play the role of either provincial (segregation) or connector (integration) hubs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The functional networks were estimated using dense EEG source connectivity method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>As recommended in Hassan et al.44, we combined the weighted Minimum Norm Estimate (wMNE) and the Phase Locking Value (PLV) to reconstruct the dynamic of the cortical sources and compute the functional connectivity between these sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This produced a fully connected, undirected and weighted networks (see Materials and Methods for details about the construction of the functional networks). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In order to explore the advantages of the dynamic analysis, we performed our study in two ways: ‘static’ and ‘dynamic’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>For the static approach, the functional connectivity was computed over the entire noise-free epoch duration (40 seconds). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To examine the dynamics of the RSNs, we used a sliding window of 300 milliseconds in which PLV was calculated over its data points (see Materials and Methods for more details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This value was chosen as it represents the minimal time window size required to adequately compute PLV as recommended by Lachaux et al.45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Other time window sizes (1 s, 2 s, 10 s and 40 s) were also explored and results are reported in Figures S2 and S4 in the Supplementary Materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We then identified the brain hubs by computing the centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient measures of the different brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These measures have been evaluated here since they represent the most commonly used metrics to detect brain hubs4, 21, 22, 28, 31, 34, 42, 46–54. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In this context, Sporns et al.54 showed that a node can be defined as hub if it has an unusually high strength (a large number of connections) and centrality (the node lies on a high number of shortest paths) and a low clustering coefficient (the neighbours of a hub are not directly connected with each other). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We also speculate, based on previous studies19, 33, 48, 55, 56, that adding the vulnerability metric to the spectrum of network measures can provide new insights into the definition of the hubness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a node with high vulnerability is supposed to have a high influence on the global efficiency of the network55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In addition, we have classified hubs into provincials and connectors based on a combination between the participation coefficient and the within-degree module24, 33, 54, 57–60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The full pipeline of our study is summarized in Fig. 1.Figure 1Structure of the investigation. left: Pre-processing of the dense-EEG data by interpolating channels and removing artifactual epochs, middle: Estimation of the EEG cortical sources using the weighted norm estimation method (wMNE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This step was followed by a projection of the source signals on the Desikan-killiany atlas, right: Quantification of the functional connectivity between the regional time series using the phase locking value (PLV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Two analyses were performed: (i) the static analysis in which PLV was computed over a segment of 40 s and (ii) the dynamic analysis in which PLV was computed over a 300 ms sliding window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The networks were then characterized by different graph measures (centrality, strength, vulnerability, clustering coefficient and modularity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The temporal transitions between networks/node’s characteristic across time were also performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Static analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In this analysis, we computed the graph metrics (centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient) using the entire signal length (40 s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We then quantified the difference between nodes distributions of each graph metric using a Wilcoxon test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Only nodes showing significant difference (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected) were retained, see Materials and Method section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Figure 2A presents the results obtained for all subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>It shows four circular barplots reflecting from the outside inward: centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The outermost ring shows the 68 brain regions (obtained from the anatomical parcellation based on Desikan-Killiany atlas)61 arranged by their assigned resting state network (see Table 1 in Supplementary Materials). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The figure also shows that the central nodes are L/R iCC, L/R PCC, L/R paraH, L/R MOF, L/R rACC, L/R LOF, L pTRI, L pORB and R ENT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The vulnerable nodes are R iCC, L/R paraH, L/R MOF, L/R rACC, L LOF, L pTRI, L pORB and R ENT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The L/R iCC, L/R PCC, R paraH, L/R MOF, L/R rACC, L LOF are the regions with highest strength while L/R ITG and L/R rMFG are the regions with highest clustering coefficients.Figure 2Static analysis: graph metrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(A) The distribution of the four measures across the 68 brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The circular barplots reflect from the outside inward: centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The outermost ring shows the 68 brain regions obtained from the anatomical parcellation based on Desikan-Killiany atlas61, arranged by their assigned resting state networks: default mode network (DMN), dorsal attentional network (DAN), salience network (SAN), auditory network (AUD), visual network (VIS), see Table S1 in Supplementary Materials for more details about these assignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We only showed the bars for significant nodes (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(B) The location of the significant brain regions on the cortical surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The color of the node corresponds to which RSN is assigned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Names and abbreviations of the brain regions are listed in Table S1. Table 1A comparison between the identified brain hubs in our study with structural and functional previous studies.Detected as hub in our studyDetected as hub in literatureRegionGraph measureGraph measureTechniqueiCCStr, BC, Vuln: static, dynamicDeg: 18, 47, Str: 27 DTIP, Z: static, dynamicBC: 27, 53, PL: 47 fMRIPCCBC, Vuln: staticDeg: 22, 27, 47, Str: 27, 29 DTIP, Z: static, dynamicBC: 21, 22, 27, 31, 42 fMRIRC: 23, PL: 47 MEGrACCStr: static, dynamicDeg: 22, 47 DTIBC, Vuln: staticBC: 22, 31, 49, 53 fMRIP, Z: static, dynamicRC: 23, 24, P, Z: 27 MOFStr, BC, Vuln: static, dynamicDeg: 22, 47 DTIP, Z: static, dynamicBC: 21, 22, 31, 42, 49 fMRIP, Z: 27, PL: 47 MEGLOFStr, Vuln: static, dynamicDeg: 22, 47 DTIBC: staticBC: 21, 22 fMRIP, Z: static, dynamicMEGParaHStr, BC, Vuln: static, dynamicBC: 53, RC: 52 DTIP, Z: static, dynamicP, Z: 53 fMRIFUSStrength: dynamicDeg: 47 fMRIP, Z: dynamicBC: 53 PL: 47 PCUNP, Z: static, dynamicDeg: 18, 19, 22, 58 DTIStr: 29, BC: 18, 19, 22 fMRIRC: 23, 24, 52, PL: 47 Vuln: 18 P, Z: 27, 52, 58–60 LINGP, Z: dynamicDeg: 47, PL: 47 fMRIParaCP, Z: staticDeg, Str, BC: 27 DTIP, Z: 27 CunuesP, Z: dynamicDeg: 47, PL: 47 DTIP, Z: 24, RC: 24 fMRIperiCalP, Z: staticDeg, Str, BC: 27 DTIP, Z: 27 ENTStr: dynamic××BC, Vuln: staticpORBStr: static, dynamic××P, Z: static, dynamicpTRIStr, Vuln: static, dynamic××P, Z: staticAbbreviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Deg: degree, Str: strength, PL: path length, BC: betweenness centrality, P: participation coefficient, Z: within degree module and Vuln: vulnerability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Results also demonstrated that a large proportion of the identified brain regions in terms of centrality (12/13), vulnerability (10/11) and strength (8/8) belong to the DMN (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In contrast, one can notice that the nodes that have the highest clustering coefficients were distributed across the DAN and the SAN, while no significant node was belonging to the DMN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Brain regions were also classified into provincial hubs, connector hubs and non-hubs by computing the participation coefficient combined with the within-degree z-score of the association matrix obtained for all subjects (Fig. 3A), refer to Materials and Methods section for more details about the modularity analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Figure 3B illustrates the spatial locations of the resultant hubs on the cortical surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We observe that a large number of hubs belong to the DMN (9/12) with the presence of one node belonging to the DAN and two nodes not belonging to any of the five analyzed RSNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The PCUN region was depicted as a provincial hub, while L PCC, R MOF, L/R paraH, L/R rACC, R paraC, R periCal, R iCC, L pORB and L LOF regions are classified as connector hubs.Figure 3Static analysis: modularity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>(A) The scatter plot of the participation coefficient and the within module degree for the 68 brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Based on57, three main areas can be identified: Non-hubs, provincial and connector hubs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>(B) The spatial locations of the identified hubs on the cortical surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Names and abbreviations of the brain regions are listed in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Dynamic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>To investigate importance of the dynamic analysis, we applied the same above procedure for each sliding window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The centrality histogram depicts L/R iCC, R PCC, L MOF, and L/R paraH as significant regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Concerning the vulnerability, the significant nodes are R iCC, R paraH, L/R MOF and L LOF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The nodes having the highest strength values are L/R iCC, L/R rACC, L/R paraH, L/R MOF, R ENT, L/R LOF and L FUS regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Concerning the clustering parameter, L/R LOF, L/R ITG, L pTRI, L/R pORB, LFP, L/R postC, L FUS and L IPL regions showed the highest values (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Very similar results were obtained using different time windows and thresholds (see Supplementary Materials, Figures S1 and S2).Figure 4Dynamic analysis: graph metrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>(A) The distribution of the four measures across the 68 brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The four circular barplots reflect (from the outside inward): centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The outermost ring shows the 68 brain regions (obtained from the anatomical parcellation based on Desikan-Killiany atlas61), arranged by their assigned resting state networks: default mode network (DMN), dorsal attentional network (DAN), salience network (SAN), auditory network (AUD), visual network (VIS) (see Table S1 in Supplementary Materials). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We only retain the bars for significant nodes (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>(B) The temporal transitions between the 68 brain regions in terms of centrality, strength, vulnerability and clustering coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Only significant columns are shown (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Names and abbreviations of the brain regions are listed in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>We then investigated how the brain regions characteristics are fluctuating during time, and which regions are more frequently involved in the segregation/integration than others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To do that, we extracted at each time window the nodes with the highest centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering coefficient values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We then computed the transition matrix which represents the number of changing times from one region to another for each of the graph metrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The transition matrices illustrated in Fig. 4B demonstrate the significant (color-coded) columns (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>One can state that the transition to nodes assigned to the DMN is very frequent compared to other RSNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Importantly, results show that that there is a high probability of transition to L/R iCC according to centrality, vulnerability and strength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>According to vulnerability, the columns corresponding also to L pCC and R paraH are significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the transitions to L LOF, the L/R MOF, L/R paraH are higher in the strength transition matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>However, there is no significant transition to any of the DMN nodes concerning the clustering coefficient, and the single remaining column corresponding to L ITG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>We have also evaluated the fractional occupancy of RSNs during time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Initially we extracted the significant nodes at each time window and then we associated the considered window to the RSN that contains the majority of these nodes (see Table S1 for nodes affiliations). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>After that, we computed the occurrence rates of each RSN across all segments and all participants for the four measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The statistical test using Wilcoxon demonstrates a significant difference between DMN and other RSNs with regard to centrality and strength (p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>However, no significant difference was found between DMN and AUD according to the vulnerability measure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>For the clustering coefficient, other RSNs occupancy rate is significantly different from that of DMN, DAN, SAN, AUD and VIS (Fig. 5A).Figure 5Dynamic analysis: networks transition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>(A) The occurrence rates of the DMN, SAN, DAN, VIS, AUD and Other RSNs across time windows for all participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>(B) The temporal transitions between all networks across time windows for all participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Only significant columns are shown (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, inspection of the transition matrices between RSNs reveals that there is a preference for the brain to move the centrality, vulnerability and strength characteristic to DMN rather than other networks (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We also note that the vulnerability transition from the DMN to the AUD network is significantly considerable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the previous results, the clustering coefficient transition to the DAN and ‘Other’ is the highest among the five known RSNs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Finally, we have explored how a brain region can change its functional role (segregation/integration) over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assigned each of the 68 brain regions to one of the three classes (non-hub, provincial hub, connector hub) at each time window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Figure 6A illustrates the results for all subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A selected row in the matrix presents the role variations of a specific brain region across time windows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>A simple examination of this figure reveals that the same node can change its type (provincial/connector) from one time to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>To extract the brain regions that are significantly behaving as connector or/and provincial hubs, we performed a chi-squared test and retained the significant nodes (p &lt; 0.01, Bonferroni corrected). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Ten out of the thirteen significant provincial hubs were found to be in the DMN, two are in the DAN and one was assigned to the VIS network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>We also found a large proportion of connector hubs included in the DMN with the presence of two nodes in the DAN, three nodes in the VIS and three nodes assigned to none of the five RSNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>A considerable observation here is that some nodes may change their function by dynamically alternating between provincial and connector hubs in the resting network across time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Among these nodes, we cite L/R iCC, L/R paraH, L FUS, L LOF, L/R MOF, L/R PCC, L pORB, and L pTRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Results of significant provincial and connector nodes using different time windows are presented in Supplementary Materials, Figure S3.Figure 6Dynamic analysis: modularity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(A) left: The variations of the node’s type (provincial vs. connector) across time for each of the 68 brain regions, right: The bar plots represent the number of times a node is considered as provincial hub (blue color) and as connector hub (red color). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(B) The spatial distributions of significant provincial hubs, and significant connector hubs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Names and abbreviations of the brain regions are listed in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>There is growing evidence suggesting that the brain is a complex system of interacting functional units. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This complex network was shown to be dynamic and network’s behaviour changes over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In this context, the recent past years have seen a significant increase of interest for dense-EEG analysis of functional brain networks at the level of cortical sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>This approach, called EEG source connectivity, is conceptually very attractive as high spatiotemporal resolution networks can be directly identified in the cortical source space. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This method was recently evaluated for its capacity to reveal relevant networks in the context of cognitive tasks44 and brain disorders62. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>It was then extended to track the spatiotemporal dynamics of functional brain networks43. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>More recently, we have performed a preliminary study using this technique combined with graph theory to explore the brain network architecture during rest in a static way32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>However, the dynamic reconfiguration of resting brain network and its associated brain regions over short time scale (hundreds of millisecond) remains elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used the dense-EEG data combined with graph theory analysis to characterize the fast dynamic reconfiguration of the brain networks at rest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In this paper, we have investigated the dynamic behaviour of the functional brain networks during rest over a very short time scale (&lt;second). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This has never been done before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We have also quantified the modular architecture of the dynamic brain networks and have extracted the local (provincial) and global (integrator) brain regions that play a key role in maintaining the communication between brain regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We also showed that the same regions can play the same role (provincial or integrator) during a given time period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Again, these methodological aspects and the results are novel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The main originality of this work is the combination of source connectivity analysis with graph theoretical study to explore the dynamics of node’s characteristics (centrality, vulnerability, strength and clustering), networks and modules over hundreds of milliseconds time scale which cannot be reached when using fMRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the source connectivity method is a recently developed method used to identify functional networks at the cortical level from scalp dense-EEG recordings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Our results showed mainly that the dynamic analysis of the RSNs at few hundreds of milliseconds time scale revealed valuable characteristics of the brain regions centrality and ‘hubness’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We showed that the human brain holds a dynamic functional core network of a set of central brain regions that dynamically ensure both segregation and integration processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>By classifying the brain regions into local and global hubs using the participation coefficient and the within-module degree, we showed for the first time that same brain region can dynamically switch its function between provincial (segregation) and connector (integration) hubs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Results are further discussed hereafter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Network hubs in the brain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Identifying brain regions that have a strong influence on information segregation and integration in the brain network is a key issue to characterize the brain functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt to identify functional hubs based on EEG source connectivity using graph theory approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>It is therefore essential to substantiate its usefulness by comparing the obtained results to prior studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>For this end, we have selected all the nodes detected here as hubs in terms of centrality, vulnerability, strength and/or modularity-based method, and compared them to those detected previously using other neuroimaging techniques (DTI, fMRI, and MEG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>We found considerable overlapping between our results and previous results for most brain regions, while three brain regions were only detected as hubs in our study (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The Table 1 shows the brain regions identified as hubs in our study in both static and dynamic approach and the corresponding graph measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The table shows also if these regions were identified as hubs previously using other neuroimaging techniques. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>To identify brain hubs, many graph measures have been used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The simplest commonly used way is the detection of highest-degree nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This approach has been used by several studies13, 30, 63, 64. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Others proposed to combine the degree and path length metrics31, 47, 53, 65, 66. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Here, we evaluated the most commonly used graph measures in order to obtain a possible convergence between several measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, Table 1 shows that the iCC, paraH and MOF regions are detected in both static and dynamic analysis independently of the graph measure used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that a consistent hub node has a high centrality (the node lies a high number of shortest paths), high strength (the hub has a large number of connections), high vulnerability (the removal of the hub has a dramatic effect on the efficiency of the network) and low clustering coefficient (the neighbors of a hub are not directly connected with each other). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Based on this definition of “hubness”, the R iCC, L/R MOF and R paraH regions are shown to be the strongest hubs as demonstrated in our static and dynamic analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Several previous studies have also combined the participation coefficient and the within module degree to identify brain hubs24, 33, 54, 58–60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>This method also allows the classification of hubs into two categories: provincial and connector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Using this approach, most of the hubs obtained in our study were intersecting with the already defined hubs using centrality, vulnerability and strength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Among these nodes, we list the L/R iCC, L/R paraH, L/R MOF, L/R PCC, L/R rACC, L/R pORB, L/R LOF, L/R FUS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Moreover, combining empirical results from structural and functional studies demonstrated a strong agreement between these hubs and the previously defined connector/provincial hubs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The PeriCal has also been detected as a provincial hub in Hagmann et al.27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The paraH was shown to play the role of connector hub in He et al.53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the rACC region was identified as a connector in various studies27, 53 and paraC was detected as a connector as reported in Hagmann et al.27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Additionally, while the PCUN was considered as a provincial hub in some studies58, 60, it was identified as a connector hub in others27, 34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The MOF was identified as provincial in Hagmann et al.27 and as connector hub in Meunier et al.59. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Hubs and RSNs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>There is a current debate whether the brain hubs are included in a single functional network, or are distributed among multiple RSNs serving as inter-links between these functional networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>While many studies support the first hypothesis16, 41, 58, others suggest that hubs form an infrastructure for communication between RSNs24, 33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Our results show that the brain hubs are distributed among the DMN (the cingulate, parahippocampal and prefrontal cortex regions), the DAN (parsorbitalis, and parstriangularis regions) and the VIS (cunues, lingual and fusiform). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>However, one can notice that the DMN regions provide the largest contribution to the network segregation/integration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This is revealed by a high fractional occupancy associated to the DMN compared to other RSNs, suggesting a frequent transition to this network in the centrality, vulnerability and strength temporal transition analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Having the majority of hubs included in the DMN corroborates with the fact that DMN is the most dominating RSN1, 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Similar results were reported in the literature10, 67, 68, where an important overlap between hubs and the DMN was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a study that explored the rich club organization of the human brain showed that the rich club nodes cross-link with the majority of RSNs and that the largest proportion belong to the DMN33. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Dynamic core network </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Most studies in RSNs were performed in a static way i.e. networks were identified over the entire recording (called also ‘stationary’ analysis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The assumption that the connectivity between brain regions is static throughout the resting recording was criticized in several studies38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In particular, Allen et al.39 reported that the functional connectivity states derived at rest from the dynamic analysis strongly differ from the patterns obtained using the static approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, Calhoun et al.69 introduced the term “chronnectome” to describe that the patterns of coupling among brain regions are dynamic and consistent over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Performing the analysis over the entire segment (40 s window length in our analysis) offered a global view about the characteristics of the RSNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>However, the sole static analysis prevents the exploration of how the brain regions/networks are reconfiguring at sub-second time scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Moreover, examining the transition between nodes in terms of graph metrics allowed us to investigate how brain hubs are alternating between each other with time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Importantly, a unique finding has also been offered by tracking the dynamics, is the study of the hub’s type variations over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In fact, a hub node has been usually considered as either provincial or connector hub23, 27, 34, 53, 58–60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, we revealed that the same brain region can play the role of provincial hub or connector hub at two different times for same subject at rest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>These findings are expected since the same regions have been detected as provincial hubs in some previous studies, and as connector hubs in others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>For example, the PCUN was found to be a provincial hub in refs 60, 58 and a connector hub in refs 27, 34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Similarly for the MOF that was identified as provincial in ref. 27 and as connector hub in ref. 59. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A possible explanation of these results is that these hub regions may participate in both the local segregation of the information and the global integration over the whole network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Methodological considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used a proportional threshold (highest 10% of the edge’s weights) to remove weak connections of the functional connectivity matrices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Garisson et al.70 showed that network measures are stable across proportional thresholds contrary to absolute thresholds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless and in order to ensure that the obtained results are not sensitive to the threshold value, we performed our analysis across a range of proportional thresholds (ranging from 5 to 20%) and realized the stability of our results across thresholds (see Supplementary Materials Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Results showed slight differences between the several threshold values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>However, the overall conclusion of the study remains intact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The time window used in the dynamic analysis corresponds to the minimal length that can be used to adequately compute PLV, as recommended by Lachaux et al.45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>In order to verify the reproducibility of the obtained results, we repeated our analysis while changing the size of the selected window (300 ms - 1 s - 2s-10s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A high degree of agreement among these analyses was found, see Supplementary Materials Figures S2, S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>One can notice that most brain hubs were always located in the DMN for all time window sizes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Here, we presented the results obtained by performing the study on beta rhythms based on previous findings16, 17, 71, 72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To verify the importance of beta band, we performed the same analysis on the broad-band (3–45 Hz), theta (3–7 Hz), alpha (7–13 Hz) and beta (14–25 Hz) frequency bands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We have evaluated the influence of the frequency band on the DMN occurrence, see Supplementary Materials Figure S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The statistical test using Wilcoxon shows a significant difference between the DMN occurrences in beta, compared to theta and alpha (p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>However, no significant difference was found between DMN’s occupancy in beta compared to the broad-band. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>From a methodological point of view, several issues should be discussed when reconstructing the sources from scalp EEG signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In fact, the number of source dipoles is much larger than the number of electrodes, making the inverse problem ill-posed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This required adding several physical and mathematical constraints to solve the inverse problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In the case of choosing the wMNE as an inverse solution, the main assumption was to find a solution with lowest energy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This assumption is generally explained by the economic energy cost of the brain during information processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, compared to other inverse solutions, the wMNE implies relatively few hypotheses, (see review in Becker et al.73 for more detailed comparison between inverse solution’s assumptions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the lead-field matrix is underdetermined, and an accurate description of the head model will positively affect the quality of solutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Here, we reduced the effect of this problem by computing a realistic subject-specific head model using each individual anatomical MRI image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>In addition, the networks identified using EEG source connectivity are limited to the cortex as the sub-cortical regions are not easily accessible from scalp EEG recordings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>As an emerging technique, the evaluation of EEG source connectivity method is crucial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The question is to determine to what extent the functional brain networks identified from EEG source connectivity correspond to those that are actually activated during considered brain processes (resting state, cognitive task). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, we used (i) real data recorded during a cognitive task43, 44 and (ii) simulated data using biophysical/physiological modelling and real epileptic data62. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In Hassan et al.44, the method was used to estimate the networks involved during a picture naming task for which a solid background was available regarding activated brain regions and networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In brief, we performed a comprehensive literature review on these networks mainly obtained from neuroimaging techniques such as fMRI, MEG, depth EEG and PET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>From this review, a “reference” network could be determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>It was used as a ground truth to define a performance criterion about the accuracy of networks obtained from EEG source connectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we tested a large number of combinations between the inverse solution and functional connectivity measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>For one combination (wMNE/PLV), the estimated network, activating during the cognitive task (500–700 ms), was found to spatially match the reference network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The above described work was then extended from static to dynamic analysis during the same cognitive task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>We showed that the EEG source connectivity method was able to track the spatiotemporal dynamics of activated brain networks from the onset (presentation of the visual stimuli) to the reaction time (articulation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Estimated dynamic networks were also found to match previously-reported regions/networks, as identified with other techniques such as depth-EEG and MEG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>More recently, a study was performed in the context of epilepsy where a physiologically-plausible computational model of epileptogenic networks was used as a ground truth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Simulated scalp-EEG signals were used to evaluate the performance of EEG source connectivity methods in term of “re-estimating” reference large-scale networks modelled at neocortical level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Again, the combination that showed the highest similarity between reference and estimated networks was the wMNE/PLV, used in the present paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Regarding the resting state data analyzed in the current paper, the only ‘ground-truth’ that could be considered are the fMRI recordings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Although fMRI data was not available for the healthy volunteers of our study, we didn’t ignore this issue and we have compared our results with those reported in literature using fMRI and DTI (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Qualitative comparison showed strong matching between brain hubs identified from our EEG-based methods, on the one hand, and brain hubs reported elsewhere and based on fMRI/DTI, on the other hand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we assumed that by taking into account the whole atlas regions without any prior selection of particular region may give more straightforward results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Here, we used 68 anatomical ROIs to define the nodes in the brain network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>There is no clear consensus about how to select the appropriate number of nodes that represent the large-scale networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>On one hand, choosing finer segmentation may increase the spatial resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, keeping a reduced number of ROIs may help removing the spurious links that occur between spatially adjacent sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In this regard, we assume that 68 regions were sufficient to investigate the global characteristics of the resting state networks while minimizing the problem of spurious connections between ‘very close sources’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Although the functional connectivity at the source level reduces the effect of the field spread, they do not suppress its effects completely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In this context, few strategies have been proposed to remove zero-lag correlations before performing any connectivity analyses72, 74. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Others suggest only keeping the long-range connections16, 41, 42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, these methods suppress important correlations that may occur at zero-lag37 or even among close regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>In our study, we evaluated the possible effects of the field spread on our results by assessing the relationships between the average Euclidian distance of brain regions and their centrality, strength, clustering coefficient, participation index, and the within-module degree values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>For each measure, the Euclidian distance of a node was calculated by averaging the distance between the node and all other nodes that affect the measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that a large proportion of nodes have long connections with high metrics values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, there was neither significant correlation between the betweenness centrality of a node and its average distance (ρ = −0.0627, p &gt; 0.05), neither for the clustering coefficient (ρ = −0.0374, p &gt; 0.05), the participation coefficient (ρ = −0.076, p &gt; 0.05) and the within degree module (ρ = 0.013, p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The correlation between the strength and the distance was statistically significant with a positive correlation value (ρ = 0.5, p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>This implies that the used metrics were not affected by the spurious short connections and that a high number of long-range connections were presented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Data acquisition and pre-processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The full pipeline of our study is summarized in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Data were recorded from twenty participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations of the National Ethics Committee for the Protection of Persons (CPP), (BrainGraph study, agreement number 2014-A01461- 46, promoter: Rennes University Hospital), which approved all the experimental protocol and procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Written informed consents were obtained from all participants in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Structural MRI and EEG dense recordings (256 channels, EGI, Electrical Geodesic Inc.) were collected for each subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>During the acquisition, the subjects were asked to relax for 10 minutes with their eyes closed without falling asleep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Electrodes impedances were kept below 10 kΩ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>EEGs were sampled at 1000 Hz, band-pass filtered within 3–45 Hz, and segmented into non-overlapping 40 s long epochs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>After visual inspection, the segments that have substantial noise not due to brain activity (amplitudes over ± 80 μV) have been marked and excluded from the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>For some subjects, few electrodes with poor signal quality have been identified and interpolated using the surrounding channels activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The artifact-free segments (four segments per subject on average) were then used for source estimation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The preprocessing steps were performed using EEGLAB75 and Brainstorm76 open source toolboxes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>A realistic head model was constructed by segmenting the MRI using Freesurfer software package77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The individual MRI anatomy and EEGs data were co-registered through the identification of the same anatomical landmarks (left and right pre-auricular points and nasion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The lead field matrix was then computed for a cortical mesh with 15000 vertices using OpenMEEG78. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The regional time series were filtered in the beta band [14–25 Hz], in which many previous studies have reported its importance in driving large-scale spontaneous neuronal interactions16, 17, 71, 72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>An atlas-based approach was used to project EEG signals onto an anatomical framework consisting of 68 cortical regions identified by means of the Desikan-Killiany61 atlas using Freesurfer77, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://freesurfer.net/">http://freesurfer.net/</ext-link>, see Table S1 for more details about the names and abbreviations of these regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Brain networks construction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Functional networks were computed using a recently proposed approach called ‘dense-EEG source connectivity’43, 44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>It included two main steps: (i) solving the EEG inverse problem to reconstruct the temporal dynamics of the cortical regions at source level and (ii) measuring the functional connectivity between these reconstructed regional time series. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Source estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>According to the linear discrete equivalent dipole model, EEG signals X(t) recorded from Q channels (Q = 256 in our case) can be expressed as linear combination of P time-varying current dipole sources S(t):1\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$X(t)=G.S(t)+N(t)\,$$\end{document}X(t)=G.S(t)+N(t)where G is the lead field matrix and N(t) is the additive noise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>G was computed from a multiple layer head model (volume conduction) and from the position of the Q electrodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Here we used the Boundary Element Method (BEM) as a numerical method to compute realistic head models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>We computed the lead field matrix using OpenMEEG78. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In addition, the noise covariance matrix was calculated over a long segment of the resting recordings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>After calculating G and N(t), the inverse problem consists of estimating the parameters of the dipolar sources \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\hat{{\rm{S}}}$$\end{document}Sˆ(t) (notably the position, orientation and magnitude). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>As this problem is ill-posed (P ≫ Q), physical and mathematical constraints have to be added to find a single solution among the many solutions that minimize the residual term in the fitting of dense EEG signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Using segmented MRI data, the source distribution can be constrained to a field of current dipoles homogeneously dispersed over the cortex and normal to the cortical surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Precisely, in the source model, the electrical contribution of each macro-column to scalp electrodes can be represented by a current dipole located at the center of gravity of each triangle of the 3D mesh and oriented normally to the triangle surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Using this source space, the weighted Minimum Norm Estimate (wMNE) method only estimates the moment of dipole sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The wMNE compensates for the tendency of classical MNE to favor weak and surface sources (Hämäläinen and Ilmoniemi 1994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>This is done by introducing a weighting matrix WX:2\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\hat{{\rm{S}}}}_{{\rm{wMNE}}}={({{\rm{G}}}^{{\rm{T}}}{{\rm{W}}}_{{\rm{X}}}{\rm{G}}+\lambda {\rm{I}})}^{-1}{{\rm{G}}}^{{\rm{T}}}{{\rm{W}}}_{{\rm{X}}}{\rm{X}}$$\end{document}SˆwMNE=(GTWXG+λI)−1GTWXXwhere matrix WX adjusts the properties of the solution by reducing the bias inherent to MNE solutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Classically, WX is a diagonal matrix built from matrix G with non-zero terms inversely proportional to the norm of the lead field vectors. λ is a regularization parameter computed relatively to the signal to noise ratio (λ = 0.2 in our analysis). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Functional connectivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>We used the phase locking value metric to compute the functional connectivity between the 68 reconstructed regional time-series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The combination of wMNE/PLV was shown to be very efficient to precisely identify cortical brain networks from scalp EEG during cognitive activity43, 44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>As described in Lachaux et al.45, the phase locking value between two signals x and y is defined as:3\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$PLV(t)=|\frac{1}{\delta }{\int }_{t-\delta /2}^{t+\delta /2}exp(j({\phi }_{y}(t)-{\phi }_{x}(t))d\tau |$$\end{document}PLV(t)=|1δ∫t−δ/2t+δ/2exp(j(ϕy(t)−ϕx(t))dτ|where \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\phi }_{y}(t)$$\end{document}ϕy(t) and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\phi }_{x}(t)$$\end{document}ϕx(t) are the unwrapped phases of the signals x and y at time t. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The Hilbert transform was used to extract the instantaneous phase of each signal. δ denotes the size of the window in which PLV is calculated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>To explore the advantage of the dynamic analysis, we performed our study in both ‘static’ and ‘dynamic’ ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>For the static way, the functional connectivity was computed over the entire noise-free epoch duration (40 seconds). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>To examine the dynamics of the RSNs, we used a sliding window in which PLV was calculated over its data points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>As recommended by Lachaux et al.45, the window length should be larger than \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\frac{6}{central\,frequency}$$\end{document}6centralfrequency where 6 is the number of ‘cycles’ at the given frequency band. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Having a central frequency of 19.5 Hz for the beta band, the smallest window length can be used is 300 milliseconds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Other frequency bands and other time window size will also described in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Network analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Networks can be illustrated by graphs, which are sets of nodes (brain regions) and of edges (connectivity values) between those nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>We constructed graphs of 68 nodes (i.e. the 68 previously identified cortical regions) and used all information from the functional connectivity (phase locking value) matrix79, 80. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>This gave fully connected, weighted and undirected networks, in which the connection strength between each pair of vertices (i.e. the weight) was defined as their connectivity value. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>We quantified the network’s nodes using several graph metrics: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Betweenness Centrality </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The importance of a node is proportional to the number of paths in which it participates51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Thus, a way to find the critical nodes is to calculate the betweenness centrality of each node:4\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$B{C}_{i}=\sum _{i,j}\frac{\sigma (i,u,j)}{\sigma (i,j)}$$\end{document}BCi=∑i,jσ(i,u,j)σ(i,j)where \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sigma (i,u,j)$$\end{document}σ(i,u,j) is the number of shortest paths between nodes i and j that pass through node u, \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sigma (i,j)$$\end{document}σ(i,j) is the total number of shortest paths between i and j, and the sum is over all pairs i, j of distinct nodes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Vulnerability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The vulnerability of a specific node can be defined as the reduction in performance when the node and all its edges are removed:5\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${V}_{i}=\frac{E-{E}_{i}}{E}$$\end{document}Vi=E−EiEwhere E is the global efficiency of the network before any attach, and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${E}_{i}$$\end{document}Ei is the global efficiency of the network after attacking the node i 50. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Strength </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The strength of a node is the sum of the weights of its corresponding edges:6\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${S}_{i}=\sum _{j}{w}_{ij}$$\end{document}Si=∑jwijwhere \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${w}_{ij}$$\end{document}wij is the weight of the edge linking the node i to the node j 81. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Clustering coefficient </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>The clustering coefficient of a node in a graph quantifies how close its neighbors are to being a clique82. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>The network measures and visualization were performed using BCT83 and BrainNet viewer84, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The above-mentioned network measures were normalized, that is, they were expressed as a function of measures computed from random networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>We generated 500 surrogate random networks derived from the original networks by randomly reshuffling the edge weights. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>The normalized values were computed by dividing the original values by the average of the values computed on the randomized graphs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Modularity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Several algorithms have been proposed to decompose a network into modules or communities of high intrinsic connectivity and low extrinsic connectivity (Simon 1962). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Due to the so-called degeneracy problem85, the modules of a same network differ from a run to another and from a module detection algorithm to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>With the aim to assess the consistency of modules affiliation, we applied the consensus clustering process as follows:Generate a set of partitions of the same network using three community detection methods 100 times (Newman algorithm86, Louvain algorithm87 and Infomap algorithm88).Compute the association matrix for all possible partitions89–91. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>This step results in a 68*68 matrix where the element \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${A}_{i,j}$$\end{document}Ai,j represents the number of times the nodes i and j are assigned to the same module across the runs and algorithms.Compare the consensus matrix to a null model association matrix generated from a permutation of the original partitions92 and keeping its significant values92.Re-cluster the resultant association matrix using Louvain method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Once a network has been partitioned, we classify the 68 nodes into three main categories (non hubs, provincial and connector hubs) by considering the variations of two measures used to quantify nodes connectivity within and between modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The first one is the within-module degree z-score that express the number of links a node makes to other nodes in the same module:7\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${Z}_{i}=\frac{{K}_{i}({m}_{i})-\overline{K({m}_{i})}}{{\sigma }_{k({m}_{i})}}$$\end{document}Zi=Ki(mi)−K(mi)¯σk(mi)where \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${K}_{i}({m}_{i})$$\end{document}Ki(mi) is the within-module degree of the node i, \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\overline{K({m}_{i})}$$\end{document}K(mi)¯ is the mean of within module degree of nodes assigned to the same community as node i, and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\sigma }_{k({m}_{i})}$$\end{document}σk(mi) is the standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Positive z-scores indicate that a node is highly connected to other members of the same community; negative z-scores indicate the opposite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>In our study, nodes with \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${Z}_{i} &gt; 1.5\,\,$$\end{document}Zi&gt;1.5were considered as hubs, and nodes with \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${Z}_{i} &lt; 1.5$$\end{document}Zi&lt;1.5 were considered as non-hubs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>We then focused on discriminating provincial and connector hubs based on a second metric known as participation coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>This metric characterizes how edges of a given node are distributed across modules:8\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${P}_{i}=1-\sum _{m=1}^{M}\,{(\frac{{K}_{i}(m)}{{K}_{i}})}^{2}$$\end{document}Pi=1−∑m=1M(Ki(m)Ki)2where M is the number of modules, \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${K}_{i}(m)$$\end{document}Ki(m) is the number of edges between node i and nodes in module m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Based on the criteria proposed by ref. 57, a provincial hub having most of its links inside its own module has a P i value lower than 0.3; while a connector hub has a P i value greater than 0.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>This criterion was used in our study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>In addition to the evaluation of the difference between brain regions according to their hubness, we were also interested in examining the difference between RSNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>To do so, we associated each brain region in the Desikan-Killiany atlas to its corresponding RSN based on the study described by Shirer et al.93 in which authors identified fourteen functional networks: anterior salience network, auditory network, basal ganglia network, dorsal default mode network, higher visual network, language network, left executive control network, sensorimotor network, posterior salience network, precunues network, primary visual network, right executive control network, ventral default mode network, and visuospatial network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>In our study, we focused on five RSNs: the DMN was obtained by combining the regions of the dorsal and the ventral default mode network, the SAN was obtained by associating all the regions in anterior and posterior salience networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>The combination of the higher and primary visual networks yields to our VIS network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Statistical tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>To statistically identify the significant nodes in terms of each graph metric, we quantified the difference between nodes distributions using a Wilcoxon test for continuous data distribution (metrics distribution, transition matrices) and a chi-squared test for binary data distribution (affiliation of connector/non connector, provincial/non provincial hubs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>All tests were corrected for multiple comparisons using Bonferroni correction method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec22"><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Supplementary materials </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-03420-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Rennes University Hospital (COREC Project named BrainGraph, 2015–17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The work has also received a French government support granted to the CominLabs excellence laboratory and managed by the National Research Agency in the “Investing for the Future” program under reference ANR-10-LABX-07-01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>It was also financed by Azm center for research in biotechnology and its applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Authors would like to thank Olaf Sporns for his helpful discussion and comments that improved this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>We also thank Olivier Dufor for his help in the data acquisition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>This works has been partially funded by the LUMINOUS Project, H2020-FETOPEN-2014-2015-RIA, agreement No. 686764. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: A.K., M.H.; Formal analysis: A.K., M.H., W.E.F.; Writing: A.K., M.H. and F.W.; Funding Acquisition: F.W., M.K.; Resources: F.W., M.H.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>1.FoxMDRaichleMESpontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imagingNat Rev Neurosci2007870071110.1038/nrn2201<?supplied-pmid 17704812?>17704812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>2.RaichleMEA default mode of brain functionProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2001986768210.1073/pnas.98.2.676<?supplied-pmid 11209064?>11209064 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>3.BiswalBYetkinFZHaughtonVMHydeJSFunctional connectivity in the motor cortex of resting human brain using echo-planar MRIMagn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Reson. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Med.19953453754110.1002/mrm.1910340409<?supplied-pmid 8524021?>8524021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>4.Sporns, O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Networks of the Brain: Quantitative Analysis and Modeling. Notes (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>5.BiswalBBVan KylenJHydeJSSimultaneous assessment of flow and BOLD signals in resting-state functional connectivity mapsNMR Biomed.19971016517010.1002/(SICI)1099-1492(199706/08)10:4/5&lt;165::AID-NBM454&gt;3.0.CO;2-7<?supplied-pmid 9430343?>9430343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>6.CordesDFrequencies contributing to functional connectivity in the cerebral cortex in ‘resting-state’ dataAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Neuroradiol.20012213261333<?supplied-pmid 11498421?>11498421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>7.CordesDMapping functionally related regions of brain with functional connectivity MR imagingAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Neuroradiol.20002116361644<?supplied-pmid 11039342?>11039342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>8.DamoiseauxJSConsistent resting-state networks across healthy subjectsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>USA2006103138485310.1073/pnas.0601417103<?supplied-pmid 16945915?>16945915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>9.De LucaMSmithSDe StefanoNFedericoAMatthewsPMBlood oxygenation level dependent contrast resting state networks are relevant to functional activity in the neocortical sensorimotor systemExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Brain Res.200516758759410.1007/s00221-005-0059-1<?supplied-pmid 16284751?>16284751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>10.GreiciusMDKrasnowBReissALMenonVFunctional connectivity in the resting brain: a network analysis of the default mode hypothesisProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>USA2003100253810.1073/pnas.0135058100<?supplied-pmid 12506194?>12506194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>11.LoweMJMockBJSorensonJAFunctional Connectivity in Single and Multislice Echoplanar Imaging Using Resting-State FluctuationsNeuroimage1998711913210.1006/nimg.1997.0315<?supplied-pmid 9558644?>9558644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>12.XiongJParsonsLMGaoJHFoxPTInterregional connectivity to primary motor cortex revealed using MRI resting state imagesHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Brain Mapp.1999815115610.1002/(SICI)1097-0193(1999)8:2/3&lt;151::AID-HBM13&gt;3.0.CO;2-5<?supplied-pmid 10524607?>10524607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>13.van den Heuvel, M., Mandl, R. &amp; Pol, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Normalized cut group clustering of resting-state fMRI data. PLoS One3 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>14.MantiniDPerrucciMGDel GrattaCRomaniGLCorbettaMElectrophysiological signatures of resting state networks in the human brainProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>USA200710413170510.1073/pnas.0700668104<?supplied-pmid 17670949?>17670949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>15.BrookesMJMeasuring functional connectivity using MEG: Methodology and comparison with fcMRINeuroimage2011561082110410.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.02.054<?supplied-pmid 21352925?>21352925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>16.de PasqualeFA Cortical Core for Dynamic Integration of Functional Networks in the Resting Human BrainNeuron20127475376410.1016/j.neuron.2012.03.031<?supplied-pmid 22632732?>22632732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>17.LiuZFukunagaMde ZwartJADuynJHLarge-scale spontaneous fluctuations and correlations in brain electrical activity observed with magnetoencephalographyNeuroimage20105110211110.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.01.092<?supplied-pmid 20123024?>20123024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>18.GongGMapping anatomical connectivity patterns of human cerebral cortex using in vivo diffusion tensor imaging tractographyCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Cortex20091952453610.1093/cercor/bhn102<?supplied-pmid 18567609?>18567609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>19.Iturria-MedinaYSoteroRCCanales-RodriguezEJAleman-GumezYMelie-GarciaLStudying the human brain anatomical network via diffusion-weighted MRI and Graph TheoryNeuroimage2008401064107610.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.10.060<?supplied-pmid 18272400?>18272400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>20.JahanshadNGenome-wide scan of healthy human connectome discovers SPON1 gene variant influencing dementia severityProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>USA201311047687310.1073/pnas.1216206110<?supplied-pmid 23471985?>23471985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>21.LiLMapping putative hubs in human, chimpanzee and rhesus macaque connectomes via diffusion tractographyNeuroimage20138046247410.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.04.024<?supplied-pmid 23603286?>23603286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>22.Nijhuis, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>J., van Cappellen van Walsum, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; Norris, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Topographic Hub Maps of the Human Structural Neocortical Network. PLoS One8 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>23.van den HeuvelMPKahnRSGoñiJSpornsOHigh-cost, high-capacity backbone for global brain communicationProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>USA2012109113727710.1073/pnas.1203593109<?supplied-pmid 22711833?>22711833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>24.van den HeuvelMPSpornsOAn anatomical substrate for integration among functional networks in human cortexJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2013331448950010.1523/JNEUROSCI.2128-13.2013<?supplied-pmid 24005300?>24005300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>25.van Horn, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>D. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Mapping connectivity damage in the case of phineas gage. PLoS One7 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>26.ZaleskyAWhole-brain anatomical networks: Does the choice of nodes matter?Neuroimage20105097098310.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.12.027<?supplied-pmid 20035887?>20035887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>27.HagmannPMapping the structural core of human cerebral cortexPLoS Biol.200861479149310.1371/journal.pbio.0060159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>28.BolaMSabelBADynamic reorganization of brain functional networks during cognitionNeuroimage201511439841310.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.03.057<?supplied-pmid 25828884?>25828884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>29.TomasiDVolkowNDAssociation between Functional Connectivity Hubs and Brain NetworksCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Cortex2011212003201310.1093/cercor/bhq268<?supplied-pmid 21282318?>21282318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>30.TomasiDVolkowNDFunctional connectivity density mappingProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>USA20101079885989010.1073/pnas.1001414107<?supplied-pmid 20457896?>20457896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>31.ZuoXNNetwork centrality in the human functional connectomeCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Cortex2012221862187510.1093/cercor/bhr269<?supplied-pmid 21968567?>21968567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>32.Kabbara, A., Falou, W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>El Khalil, M., Wendling, F. &amp; Hassan, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Graph analysis of spontaneous brain network using EEG source connectivity. arXiv Prepr. arXiv1607.00952 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>33.van den HeuvelMPSpornsORich-Club Organization of the Human ConnectomeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.201131157751578610.1523/JNEUROSCI.3539-11.2011<?supplied-pmid 22049421?>22049421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>34.de ReusMavan den HeuvelMPRich club organization and intermodule communication in the cat connectomeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.201333129293910.1523/JNEUROSCI.1448-13.2013<?supplied-pmid 23926249?>23926249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>35.CollinGSpornsOMandlRCWvan den HeuvelMPStructural and Functional Aspects Relating to Cost and Benefit of Rich Club Organization in the Human Cerebral CortexCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Cortex2013242258226710.1093/cercor/bht064<?supplied-pmid 23551922?>23551922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>36.ChangCLiuZChenMCLiuXDuynJHEEG correlates of time-varying BOLD functional connectivityNeuroimage20137222723610.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.01.049<?supplied-pmid 23376790?>23376790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>37.BrookesMJMeasuring temporal, spectral and spatial changes in electrophysiological brain network connectivityNeuroimage20149128229910.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.12.066<?supplied-pmid 24418505?>24418505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>38.HutchisonRMDynamic functional connectivity: Promise, issues, and interpretationsNeuroimage20138036037810.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.05.079<?supplied-pmid 23707587?>23707587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>39.AllenEATracking whole-brain connectivity dynamics in the resting stateCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Cortex20142466367610.1093/cercor/bhs352<?supplied-pmid 23146964?>23146964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>40.Baker, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>P. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Fast transient networks in spontaneous human brain activity. Elife2014 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>41.de PasqualeFTemporal dynamics of spontaneous MEG activity in brain networksProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>USA20101076040604510.1073/pnas.0913863107<?supplied-pmid 20304792?>20304792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>42.de Pasquale, F. et al.A Dynamic Core Network and Global Efficiency in the Resting Human Brain. Cereb. Cortex bhv185, doi:10.1093/cercor/bhv185 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>43.HassanMDynamic reorganization of functional brain networks during picture namingCortex20157327628810.1016/j.cortex.2015.08.019<?supplied-pmid 26478964?>26478964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>44.Hassan, M., Dufor, O., Merlet, I., Berrou, C. &amp; Wendling, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>EEG source connectivity analysis: From dense array recordings to brain networks. PLoS One9 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>45.LachauxJ-PStudying single-trials of phase synchronous activity in the brainInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Bifurc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Chaos200010242939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>46.AchardSHubs of brain functional networks are radically reorganized in comatose patientsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>USA2012109206081310.1073/pnas.1208933109<?supplied-pmid 23185007?>23185007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>47.AchardSSalvadorRWhitcherBSucklingJBullmoreEA resilient, low-frequency, small-world human brain functional network with highly connected association cortical hubsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.200626637210.1523/JNEUROSCI.3874-05.2006<?supplied-pmid 16399673?>16399673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>48.Alstott, J., Breakspear, M., Hagmann, P., Cammoun, L. &amp; Sporns, O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Modeling the impact of lesions in the human brain. PLoS Comput. Biol. 5 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>49.ColeMWPathakSSchneiderWIdentifying the brain’s most globally connected regionsNeuroimage2010493132314810.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.11.001<?supplied-pmid 19909818?>19909818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>50.Gol’dshteinVKoganovGASurdutovichGIVulnerability and Hierarchy of Complex NetworksPhysics (College. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Park. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Md).2004164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>51.FreemanLCA Set of Measures of Centrality Based on BetweennessSociometry197740354110.2307/3033543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>52.Harriger, L., van den Heuvel, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>P. &amp; Sporns, O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Rich Club Organization of Macaque Cerebral Cortex and Its Role in Network Communication. PLoS One7 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>53.He, Y. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Uncovering intrinsic modular organization of spontaneous brain activity in humans. PLoS One4 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>54.Sporns, O., Honey, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; Kotter, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Identification and classification of hubs in brain networks. PLoS One2 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>55.CostaLFRodriguesFATraviesoGVillas BoasPRCharacterization of complex networks: A survey of measurementsAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Phys.20075616724210.1080/00018730601170527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>56.KaiserMHilgetagCCEdge vulnerability in neural and metabolic networksBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Cybern.20049031131710.1007/s00422-004-0479-1<?supplied-pmid 15221391?>15221391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>57.GuimeràRNunes AmaralLAFunctional cartography of complex metabolic networksNature200543389590010.1038/nature03288<?supplied-pmid 15729348?>15729348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>58.MoussaMNChanges in Cognitive State Alter Human Functional Brain NetworksFront. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2011511510.3389/fnhum.2011.0008321283556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>59.MeunierDAchardSMorcomABullmoreEAge-related changes in modular organization of human brain functional networksNeuroimage20094471572310.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.09.062<?supplied-pmid 19027073?>19027073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>60.PowerJDSchlaggarBLLessov-SchlaggarCNPetersenSEEvidence for hubs in human functional brain networksNeuron20137979881310.1016/j.neuron.2013.07.035<?supplied-pmid 23972601?>23972601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>61.DesikanRSAn automated labeling system for subdividing the human cerebral cortex on MRI scans into gyral based regions of interestNeuroimage20063196898010.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.01.021<?supplied-pmid 16530430?>16530430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>62.Hassan, M. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Identification of Interictal Epileptic Networks from Dense-EEG. Brain Topography 1–17, doi:10.1007/s10548-016-0517-z (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>63.BucknerRLCortical hubs revealed by intrinsic functional connectivity: mapping, assessment of stability, and relation to Alzheimer’s diseaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2009291860187310.1523/JNEUROSCI.5062-08.2009<?supplied-pmid 19211893?>19211893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>64.ColeMWYarkoniTRepovšGAnticevicABraverTSGlobal Connectivity of Prefrontal Cortex Predicts Cognitive Control and IntelligenceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2012328988899910.1523/JNEUROSCI.0536-12.2012<?supplied-pmid 22745498?>22745498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>65.Lohmann, G. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Eigenvector centrality mapping for analyzing connectivity patterns in fMRI data of the human brain. PLoS One5 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>66.Joyce, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>E., Laurienti, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>J., Burdette, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>H. &amp; Hayasaka, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>A new measure of centrality for brain networks. PLoS One5 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>67.RaichleMESnyderAZA default mode of brain function: A brief history of an evolving ideaNeuroimage2007371083109010.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.02.041<?supplied-pmid 17719799?>17719799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>68.MasonMFWandering Minds: The Default Network and Stimulus-Independent ThoughtScience (80-.).200731539339510.1126/science.1131295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>69.CalhounVDMillerRPearlsonGAdaliTThe Chronnectome: Time-Varying Connectivity Networks as the Next Frontier in fMRI Data DiscoveryNeuron20148426227410.1016/j.neuron.2014.10.015<?supplied-pmid 25374354?>25374354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>70.GarrisonKAScheinostDFinnESShenXConstableRTThe (in)stability of functional brain network measures across thresholdsNeuroimage201511865166110.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.05.046<?supplied-pmid 26021218?>26021218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>71.BrookesMJInvestigating the electrophysiological basis of resting state networks using magnetoencephalographyProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>USA201110816783810.1073/pnas.1112685108<?supplied-pmid 21930901?>21930901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>72.HippJFHawellekDJCorbettaMSiegelMEngelAKLarge-scale cortical correlation structure of spontaneous oscillatory activityNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.20121588489010.1038/nn.3101<?supplied-pmid 22561454?>22561454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>73.BeckerHBrain-source imaging: From sparse to tensor modelsIEEE Signal Process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Mag.20153210011210.1109/MSP.2015.2413711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>74.BrookesMJWoolrichMWBarnesGRMeasuring functional connectivity in MEG: A multivariate approach insensitive to linear source leakageNeuroimage20126391092010.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.03.048<?supplied-pmid 22484306?>22484306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>75.DelormeAMakeigSEEGLAB: An open source toolbox for analysis of single-trial EEG dynamics including independent component analysisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>Methods200413492110.1016/j.jneumeth.2003.10.009<?supplied-pmid 15102499?>15102499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>76.Tadel, F., Baillet, S., Mosher, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>C., Pantazis, D. &amp; Leahy, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>Brainstorm: A user-friendly application for MEG/EEG analysis. Comput. Intell. Neurosci. 2011 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>77.FischlBFreeSurferNeuroImage20126277478110.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.01.021<?supplied-pmid 22248573?>22248573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>78.GramfortAPapadopouloTOliviEClercMOpenMEEG: opensource software for quasistatic bioelectromagneticsBiomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>Eng. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>Online201094510.1186/1475-925X-9-45<?supplied-pmid 20819204?>20819204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>79.HamalainenMSIlmoniemiRJInterpreting magnetic fields of the brain: minimum norm estimatesMed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Eng. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Comput.199432354210.1007/BF02512476<?supplied-pmid 8182960?>8182960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>80.Hassan, M., Shamas, M., Khalil, M., Falou, W. &amp; El Wendling, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>EEGNET: An open source tool for analyzing and visualizing M/EEG connectome. PLoS One10 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>81.BarratABarthélemyMPastor-SatorrasRVespignaniAThe architecture of complex weighted networksProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>USA20041013747375210.1073/pnas.0400087101<?supplied-pmid 15007165?>15007165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>82.WattsDJStrogatzSHCollective dynamics of ‘small-world’ networksNature1998393440210.1038/30918<?supplied-pmid 9623998?>9623998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>83.RubinovMSpornsOComplex network measures of brain connectivity: Uses and interpretationsNeuroimage2010521059106910.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.003<?supplied-pmid 19819337?>19819337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>84.Xia, M., Wang, J. &amp; He, Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>BrainNet Viewer: A Network Visualization Tool for Human Brain Connectomics. PLoS One8 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>85.Good, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>H., De Montjoye, Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; Clauset, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Performance of modularity maximization in practical contexts. Phys. Rev. E - Stat. Nonlinear, Soft Matter Phys. 81 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>86.GirvanMNewmanMEJCommunity structure in social and biological networksProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>USA2002997821610.1073/pnas.122653799<?supplied-pmid 12060727?>12060727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>87.BlondelVDGuillaumeJ-LLambiotteRLefebvreEFast unfolding of communities in large networksJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>Mech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>Theory Exp.2008100086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>88.RosvallMAxelssonDBergstromCTThe map equationEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>Spec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>Top.2009178132310.1140/epjst/e2010-01179-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>89.LancichinettiAFortunatoSConsensus clustering in complex networksSci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>Rep.2012233610.1038/srep00336<?supplied-pmid 22468223?>22468223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>90.RubinovMSpornsOWeight-conserving characterization of complex functional brain networksNeuroimage2011562068207910.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.03.069<?supplied-pmid 21459148?>21459148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>91.Sales-PardoMGuimeràRMoreiraAAAmaralLANCorrection for Sales-Pardo et al., Extracting the hierarchical organization of complex systemsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>USA20071041887410.1073/pnas.0703740104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>92.Bassett, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>S. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>Robust detection of dynamic community structure in networks. Chaos23 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>93.ShirerWRRyaliSRykhlevskaiaEMenonVGreiciusMDDecoding subject-driven cognitive states with whole-brain connectivity patternsCereb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>Cortex20122215816510.1093/cercor/bhr099<?supplied-pmid 21616982?>21616982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
