<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Hematol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann. Hematol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Hematology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0939-5555</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0584</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5486778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28623396</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00277-017-3043-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Assessment of the circulating cell-free DNA marker association with diagnosis and prognostic prediction in patients with lymphoma: a single-center experience </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Mao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Yongqian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Xiaomin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Caigang</given-names></name><address><phone>+86 189 806 01083</phone><email>xucg@cd120.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1770 1022</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412901.f</institution-id><institution>Hematology Research Laboratory, Department of Hematology, </institution><institution>West China Hospital, Sichuan University, </institution></institution-wrap>37#, Guoxue Lane, Chengdu, Sichuan 610041 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>96</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1343</fpage><lpage>1351</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Circulating cell-free DNA (ccfDNA) has been shown to be associated with the clinical characteristics and prognosis of cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Our objective was to assess whether the concentration and integrity index of ccfDNA in plasma may be useful for diagnosing and monitoring the progression of patients with lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We included plasma samples from 174 lymphoma patients and 80 healthy individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The total concentration of ccfDNA was determined using a fluorometry method, and the DNA integrity index (DII), which is the ratio of longer to shorter DNA fragments, for the APP gene was detected using real-time quantitative PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The median levels of the ccfDNA concentration and the DII in patients with lymphoma were significantly higher than those in controls (both P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Increases in the ccfDNA concentration and the DII were associated with advanced stage disease, elevated lactate dehydrogenase levels, and a higher prognosis score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In patients with diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL), high levels of ccfDNA (both concentration and the DII) showed an inferior 2-year progression-free survival (PFS) (P = 0.001; P &lt; 0.0001, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Our study provides quantitative and qualitative evidence in favor of using ccfDNA analysis in lymphoma patients for diagnostic and prognostic assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Lymphoma</kwd><kwd>Circulating DNA</kwd><kwd>Integrity</kwd><kwd>Prognosis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Lymphoma, which is a common cancer of the hematopoietic system, represents a heterogeneous collection of diseases with different biological characteristics and clinical outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In China, more than 80,000 new cases of lymphoma and an estimated 52,000 deaths attributed to lymphoma were reported in 2015 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The overall survival of patients with lymphoma tends to be poor primarily because at the time of diagnosis, most patients are already in the late stages and thus lose the opportunity for timely treatment [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there is an urgent need for a noninvasive tool to improve the diagnosis and prognostic evaluation of lymphoma patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Circulating cell-free DNA (ccfDNA) are DNA fragments circulating within the bloodstream and can be obtained by a simple blood collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Mendel and Metais first reported the existence of ccfDNA in 1948 [3], and the presence of ccfDNA has been identified in inflammatory disease [4], autoimmune disease [5], trauma [6], and myocardial infarction [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Recently, quantifying ccfDNA levels has been proposed as a potential biomarker to detect malignant tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>A study by Leon et al. [8] suggested that compared with that of healthy individuals, the concentration of ccfDNA was significantly increased in cancer patients; furthermore, this phenomenon was confirmed by other studies on breast tumors [9], colorectal cancer [10], lung cancer [11], and other cancer types [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The ccfDNA released into the bloodstream is thought to originate from either passive release from apoptotic and necrotic cells or active secretion from nucleated cells such as lymphocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Unlike uniformly truncated DNA released from apoptotic cells, ccfDNA released from necrotic tumor cells varies in size, which may lead to elevated levels of long fragments of DNA in the plasma of patients with malignant diseases [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated that compared to that of healthy individuals, the DNA integrity index (DII), which is calculated as the ratio of longer to shorter DNA fragments, was increased in patients with cancers [14–16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Although the presence of ccfDNA has been widely studied in malignant tumors, there are only few reports regarding ccfDNA in lymphoproliferative diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>It has been hypothesized that ccfDNA may be a good candidate for diagnosis and prognosis of lymphoma because some studies have shown that the concentration of ccfDNA could be a diagnostic and predictive biomarker in lymphoma patients [17, 18]; however, to the best of our knowledge, there are no studies that have investigated the predictive value of ccfDNA integrity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Here, we assessed the value of the concentration and integrity of ccfDNA in diagnosing lymphoma patients and analyzed these parameters to identify associations with clinical characteristics and prognosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>There were 174 lymphoma patients enrolled in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Among the included lymphoma cases, 126 were B cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma (B-NHL), with diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL, n = 98) as the most common subtype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>There were 18, 9, and 21 patients diagnosed with HL, T cell non-HL (T-NHL), and extranodal NK/T cell lymphoma (NK/TCL), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The diagnosis of all patients was histologically confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Patient samples were obtained from West China Hospital of Sichuan University between September 2014 and January 2016. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples were collected at the time of initial diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The median follow-up time was 13.5 months and ranged from 1 to 36 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The main patient characteristics are provided in Table 1.Table 1Main characteristics of patients included in the studyTotalHLB-NHLT-NHLNK/TCLDLBCLOthers(n = 174)(n = 18)(n = 98)(n = 28)(n = 9)(n = 21)Gender Male107106117613 Female678371138Age (range), years ≤60117156116718 &gt;60573371223Stage I–IIA6924211114 IIB–IV10516561787B-symptoms No916601429 Yes83123814712Bulky disease No153138426921 Yes21514200Lactate dehydrogenase Normal9694817814 Elevated789501117IPI Low (0 or 1)56–39836 Intermediate low (2)38–225110 Intermediate high (3)27–13815 High (4 or 5)35–24740IPS 0–2–9–––– ≥ 3–9––––Data were presented as n HL, Hodgkin’s lymphoma; B-NHL, B cell non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma; DLBCL, diffuse large B cell lymphoma; Others group included 9 follicular lymphoma, 7 small cell lymphoma/chronic lymphocytic leukemia, 6 marginal zone lymphoma, 5 mantle cell lymphoma and 1 Burkitt lymphoma; T-NHL, T cell non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma, included in 4 peripheral T cell lymphoma, 3 anaplastic large-cell lymphoma, 2 angioimmunoblastic T cell lymphoma; NK/TCL, extranodal NK/T cell lymphoma; IPI, international prognostic index; IPS, international prognostic score </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A control group consisting of 80 healthy individuals was included to establish the normal range of ccfDNA levels in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from patients and controls according to the institutional guidelines, and the study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of the West China Hospital of Sichuan University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Sample collection and DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood samples were collected into tubes containing EDTA and centrifuged (2000×g, 10 min, 4 °C) within 4 h of collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To prevent cellular DNA contamination, the plasma supernatants were carefully removed and recentrifuged (16,000×g; 10 min at 4 °C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The prepared plasma samples were stored at −80 °C until further analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>ccfDNA was extracted using the MagMAX™ Cell-Free DNA Isolation Kit (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The isolated ccfDNA was eluted in 20 μl of the provided solution and stored at −20 °C prior to quantitative and qualitative analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Quantification of circulating cell-free DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Quantification of ccfDNA was performed by fluorometry using the Qubit® dsDNA HS Assay Kit (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocols, and the plates were read in a Qubit® 3.0 fluorometer (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The ccfDNA concentrations were determined from a standard curve obtained using the standard stock (provided by the manufacturer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Two repeated tests were performed for each set of concentration measurements and the resulting data were averaged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Real-time quantitative PCR of DNA fragments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The integrity of ccfDNA in plasma was determined by quantitative real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The quantitative assay was based on amplification of the APP gene (amyloid beta precursor protein, chromosome 21q21.3, accession NM_000484); the lengths of the two amplicons were 67 and 180 bp and were obtained using two primer pairs as reported previously [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The primer set for APP67 amplified both shorter (truncated by apoptosis) and longer DNA fragments (truncated by nonapoptotic means), whereas the APP180 amplified only the longer DNA fragments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Quantification of ccfDNA fragments was performed using the CFX96 Touch™ Real-Time instrument (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The reaction mixture for each direct quantitative real-time PCR comprised 12.5 μl of SYBR® Premix Ex Taq™ II (TaKaRa, Shiga, Japan), 1 μl (0.4 μM) of each primer, and 2 μl DNA in a total reaction volume of 20 μl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The sequences of the primers are as follows: APP67: forward, 5′-TCAGGTTGACGCCGCTGT-3′ and reverse, 5′-TTCGTAGCCG TTCTGCTGC-3′; and APP180: forward, 5′-TCAGGTTGACGCCGCTGT-3′ and reverse, 5′-TCTATAAATGGACACCGATGGGTAGT-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The real-time PCR protocol included an initial denaturation step at 95 °C for 30 s followed by 40 cycles of denaturation at 95 °C for 5 s and annealing at 64 °C for 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>A melting curve analysis was conducted to confirm PCR product specificity, and the DNA copy number of each sample was determined using a standard curve with serial dilutions (2 × 10−1−2 × 105 ng/ml) of human genomic DNA (Promega, Madison, WI, USA; 200 μg/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All samples were analyzed in duplicate, and a negative control (without template) was included in each plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>All quantitative real-time PCR assays were performed in a blinded fashion without knowledge of the specimen identity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the relative expression levels of ccfDNA (including concentration and the DII) between patients and controls was performed by applying the nonparametric Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Analysis of receiver operating characteristics (ROC) curves and binary logistic regression were performed to evaluate the diagnostic performance of the ccfDNA concentration and the DII in lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The relationship between the levels of ccfDNA and the clinicopathological features of lymphoma patients was estimated as appropriate per variable type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In detail, differences in the ccfDNA levels among the different groups of categorical parameters were analyzed by either the nonparametric Mann-Whitney test for binary variables or the respective Kruskal-Wallis test for the parameters consisting of several independent groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The Kaplan-Meier survival analysis approach and Cox proportional hazard regression analysis were used to determine progression-free survival (PFS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>PFS was defined as the time from initial diagnosis until disease progression/relapse or death from any cause. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>A two-sided P &lt; 0.05 indicated statistical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All analyses were performed using SPSS software version 22.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY) and MedCalc software version 15.10 (MedCalc Software, Ostend, Belgium). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Concentration of circulating cell-free DNA in healthy individuals and lymphoma patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The median concentration of ccfDNA in the 80 healthy individuals tested was 209.0 ng/ml (mean 222.5 ng/ml, range 100.0–456.0 ng/ml); however, in patients with lymphoma (n = 174), this concentration was significantly higher (median 686.0 ng/ml, P &lt; 0.0001) with greater variability among the patients (mean 1407.6 ng/ml, range 100.0–14,180.0 ng/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Elevated ccfDNA concentration levels were observed in patients with HL (n = 18, median 681.0 ng/ml, mean 988.8 ng/ml, P = 0.001), DLBCL (n = 98, median 845.0 ng/ml, mean 1722.2 ng/ml, P &lt; 0.0001), other types of B-NHL (n = 28, median 332.0 ng/ml, mean 1096.3 ng/ml, P &lt; 0.0001), T-NHL (n = 9, median 942.0 ng/ml, mean 1247.0 ng/ml, P &lt; 0.0001), and NK/TCL (n = 21, median 662.0 ng/ml, mean 782.7 ng/ml, P &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 1a).Fig. 1Circulating cell-free DNA levels in the plasma of lymphoma patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Box plots showed circulating cell-free DNA levels of a concentrations and b DII in healthy controls and patients with lymphoma, presented as median value (black line), interquartile range (box), and 5th and 95th percentiles (whiskers) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To assess the diagnostic accuracy of the ccfDNA levels in lymphoma patients, an ROC curve analysis was conducted, and the area under the curve (AUC) was calculated as 0.75 (95% CI 0.66–0.84, P = 0.001) for HL, 0.86 (95% CI 0.80–0.90, P &lt; 0.0001) for DLBCL, and 0.79 (95% CI 0.70–0.87, P &lt; 0.0001) for NK/TCL, suggesting a moderate discriminatory power. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>For HL, the sensitivity and specificity were 61 and 100%, respectively, at a cut-off of 456.0 ng/ml; for DLBCL, 73 and 94% at a cut-off of 340.0 ng/ml, and for NK/TCL, 71 and 96% at a cut-off of 392.0 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Based on these results, elevated levels of ccfDNA were associated with a higher risk of lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>When analyzed as a logistic regression model, a 10.0 ng/ml increase in the ccfDNA concentration increased the lymphoma risk by 7.3% (odds ratio 1.073; 95% CI 1.045–1.102). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Integrity of circulating cell-free DNA in healthy individuals and lymphoma patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The DII was calculated as the ratio of the quantitative real-time PCR results using the two primer sets as follows: QAPP180/QAPP67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Because the annealing sites of APP67 are contained within the APP180 annealing sites, the DII would be 1.0 when the template DNA was not truncated and 0.0 when all of the template DNA was truncated into fragments smaller than 180 bp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The median DII in patients with lymphoma was 0.39 (mean 0.42, range 0.11–0.97), which was significantly higher than that of the normal control subjects (median 0.21, mean 0.22, range 0.07–0.49; P &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Elevated DII values were observed in patients with HL (median 0.37, mean 0.40, P &lt; 0.0001), DLBCL (median 0.43, mean 0.46, P &lt; 0.0001), other types of B-NHL (median 0.34, mean 0.35, P = 0.002), T-NHL (median 0.42, mean 0.41, P = 0.008), and NK/TCL (median 0.33, mean 0.38, P = 0.001), respectively (Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Using the ROC analysis, the AUC of the ccfDNA DII was 0.83 (95% CI 0.74–0.90, P &lt; 0.0001) for HL, 0.90 (95% CI 0.83–0.93, P &lt; 0.0001) for DLBCL, and 0.81 (95% CI 0.72–0.88, P &lt; 0.0001) for NK/TCL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the ROC analysis assessed whether a combination of the raw ccfDNA concentration and the DII could improve the diagnostic ability compared with using the concentration alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The results showed that the AUC was significantly increased after the addition of the DII to the ccfDNA concentration in patients with DLBCL (0.86 vs. 0.91; Z = 2.697, P = 0.007; Fig. 2); whereas in patients with either HL or NK/TCL, there was only a trend of increased AUC observed (0.75 vs. 0.84; Z = 1.714, P = 0.087 and 0.79 vs. 0.88; Z = 1.646, P = 0.0997, respectively).Fig. 2The receiver operating characteristic curves of the circulating cell-free DNA concentration and its combination with DII in patients with DLBCL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The AUC of concentration and model of concentration + DII was 0.86 (95% CI 0.80–0.90) and 0.91 (95% CI 0.86–0.95), respectively (Z = 2.697, P = 0.007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>DII, DNA integrity index; AUC, area under the curve </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Correlation of circulating cell-free DNA and clinicopathological features in lymphoma patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To assess the clinical significance of ccfDNA levels, we analyzed the clinicopathological correlations in the total lymphoma group but restricted the analysis to patients with DLBCL; in this patient subset, the adverse prognostic factors advanced stage disease (stage IIB–IV) and elevated LDH levels were associated with increased ccfDNA levels and DII (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In patients with DLBCL, the presence of B-symptoms was also correlated with increases in both the ccfDNA concentration and the DII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, patients with an adverse prognostic score had higher levels of ccfDNA, which was significant among all lymphoma patients and DLBCL patients [20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, no statistical significance was observed when the ccfDNA concentration and the DII were analyzed with regard to other clinical parameters such as age, gender, and bulky disease.Table 2Plasma circulating cell-free DNA levels and clinicopathologic features in lymphoma patientsAll patientsDLBCLConcentrationDIIConcentrationDIIGender Male660.0 (290.0–1684.0)0.38 (0.29–0.54)764.0 (352.0–1868.5)0.42 (0.33–0.56) Female702.0 (284.0–2000.0)0.42 (0.33–0.53)1118.0 (295.0–3080.0)0.48 (0.35–0.59)  P 0.7690.2340.5070.558Age (range), years ≤60702.0 (260.0–1868.5)0.39 (0.31–0.53)802.0 (287.0–2430.0)0.47 (0.33–0.56) &gt;60656.0 (355.0–1847.0)0.41 (0.30–0.55)888.0 (384.0–2220.0)0.43 (0.34–0.58)  P 0.4140.8560.6680.965Stage I–IIA482.0 (238.5–1081.0)0.34 (0.28–0.47)488.0 (262.8–1048.0)0.35 (0.29–0.48) IIB–IV896.0 (351.0–2330.0)0.43 (0.34–0.56)1395.0 (449.5–2720.0)0.52 (0.41–0.62)  P  0.003  0.0001  0.006  &lt;0.0001 B-symptoms No496.0 (267.0–1426.0)0.39 (0.29–0.52)523.0 (293.0–1672.8)0.41 (0.31–0.54) Yes736.0 (348.0–2240.0)0.41 (0.32–0.54)1657.0 (433.0–3520.0)0.52 (0.39–0.63)  P 0.1040.251 0.034  0.013 Bulky disease No662.0 (287.0–1661.5)0.39 (0.30–0.53)783.0 (320.5–2330.0)0.43 (0.34–0.55) Yes1011.0 (269.0–2434.5)0.42 (0.31–0.59)1148.0 (334.5–2161.8)0.45 (0.35–0.61)  P 0.4310.4060.7410.737Lactate dehydrogenase Normal472.0 (230.8–978.0)0.37 (0.29–0.49)455.0 (248.5–1114.0)0.39 (0.30–0.52) Elevated1200.0 (400.0–3020.0)0.43 (0.33–0.59)1629.5 (517.0–3520.0)0.52 (0.38–0.63)  P  &lt;0.0001  0.006  &lt;0.0001  0.003 Prognostic score Low risk482.0 (248.0–1024.0)0.37 (0.29–0.51)522.0 (267.5–1771.0)0.41 (0.30–0.52) High risk942.0 (402.0–2600.0)0.42 (0.34–0.57)1620.0 (493.0–2870.0)0.52 (0.39–0.66)  P  0.001  0.01  0.002  0.005 Data were presented as median (IQR 25–75); IQR, interquartile range; circulating cell-free DNA analysis included in concentration and DII levels; DII, DNA integrity index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The IPI score was used for patients with non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma and the IPS score for patients with Hodgkin’s lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>IPI scores 0 and 1 were considered low risk, 2 and 3 as high risk, while with IPS scores 0–2 were considered as low risk and 3 as high risk P value, comparison between the two strata of each individual variable. P values below 0.05 were shown in italics </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Prognostic significance of circulating cell-free DNA in diffuse large B cell lymphoma patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The role of the ccfDNA levels at the time of diagnosis as a prognostic marker was analyzed in patients with DLBCL, who constituted the largest diagnostic entity included in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The most discriminatory cut-offs for 2-year PFS were identified by ROC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The ccfDNA concentration and the DII were analyzed as dichotomic variables using 1586 ng/ml and 0.61 as the cut-off points, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>As shown in the Kaplan-Meier curves for the different levels of ccfDNA concentration, patients with a ccfDNA concentration &gt;1586 ng/ml had a 2-year probability of PFS of only 44% (95% CI 15–73%), whereas patients with a ccfDNA concentration ≤1586 ng/ml had significantly higher probability of 2-year PFS at 78% (95% CI 55–99%; P = 0.001; Fig. 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The prognostic value of ccfDNA fragmentation on PFS was also evaluated using the DII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Patients showing a DII &gt;0.61 had a 59% probability of 2-year PFS (95% CI 38–79%), which was significantly shorter than that in patients with a DII ≤0.61 (87%, 95% CI 69–100%, P &lt; 0.0001; Fig. 3b).Fig. 3Survival curves of DLBCL patients stratified by circulating cell-free DNA levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Kaplan-Meier survival curve and log-rank test according to a concentration and b DII determined by ccfDNA analysis were using the cut-offs identified by means of ROC for 2-year progression-free survival (P value noted in the figure). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>ccfDNA, circulating cell-free DNA; DII, DNA integrity index; ROC, receiver operating characteristic </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Following the univariate analysis, we found that both the ccfDNA concentration and the DII were associated with PFS; moreover, advanced stage, B-symptoms, and elevated LDH levels were significant adverse factors (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Thus, these variables were assessed in a multivariate Cox regression model, which showed that the DII appeared to be a statistically independent prognostic factor (HR = 3.04, 95% CI 1.197–7.696; P = 0.019), whereas the ccfDNA concentration was not significant in this multivariate analysis (HR = 1.45, 95% CI 0.490–4.263; P = 0.504).Table 3Univariable Cox regression models for progression-free survival (PFS) in diffuse large B cell lymphoma patientsHR (95% CI) P valueGender (male)1.128 (0.454–2.799)0.796Age (&gt;60 years)1.196 (0.495–2.886)0.692Advanced stage7.977 (1.856–34.29) 0.005 B-symptoms6.639 (2.404–18.33) &lt;0.0001 Bulky disease0.571 (0.133–2.456)0.452Elevated LDH4.545 (1.522–13.57) 0.007 Elevated ccfDNA Concentration4.270 (1.653–11.03) 0.003  DII5.165 (2.187–12.19) &lt;0.0001 Data were presented as HR (95% CI); HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>ccfDNA, circulating cell-free DNA; elevated ccfDNA was included in both concentration and DII levels P values below 0.05 were shown in italics </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>This study reveals that compared to healthy individuals, patients with lymphoma frequently have higher concentrations and longer strands of ccfDNA at the time of diagnosis, which correlates with clinical parameters and was demonstrated to be a negative predictor of DLBCL patients’ outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Recently, studies conducted in various malignancies have shown that ccfDNA levels are significantly increased in cancer [22, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Our work revealed that the ccfDNA concentration and the DII levels were elevated in patients with lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the histological subsets revealed that the ccfDNA concentration and the DII levels varied according to the lymphoma subtype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the B-NHL and T-NHL cohorts were insufficient to perform a significant histological subtype analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>There are only few reports that studied the clinical impact of ccfDNA levels on lymphoma patients and were mainly oriented to analyze the correlation between an increase in the ccfDNA concentration with disease risk and adverse clinical performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, other analytical parameters exhibited by ccfDNA such as the DII have not been studied in lymphoma patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Here, we confirmed the usefulness of detecting the quantity and quality of ccfDNA as a diagnostic tool for lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Data from our ROC analysis showed that the AUC of the concentration to distinguish HL, DLBCL, and NK/TCL patients from normal controls was 0.75, 0.86, and 0.79, respectively; furthermore, the AUC of the DII was higher than that of the concentration (0.83, 0.90, and 0.81 for HL, DLBCL, and NK/TCL, respectively), indicating that the ccfDNA concentration alone appeared to be insufficient for a high-quality diagnostic performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Hohaus et al. [17] conducted a diagnostic analysis of the ccfDNA concentration for patients with HL and DLBCL and found that the maximum sensitivity and specificity did not exceed 75%, making this parameter an unlikely candidate for lymphoma screening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Our study found that for DLBCL patients, there was an added incremental diagnostic value when the ccfDNA concentration was combined with the DII. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Regarding the clinical correlation of ccfDNA levels in lymphoma patients, we observed an association between the ccfDNA levels and a number of clinical parameters that indicate a worse prognosis such as advanced stage disease, the presence of B-symptoms, elevated LDH levels, and high IPI score; these correlations suggest that both the ccfDNA concentration and the DII might reflect actively proliferating disease and lymphoma burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, a literature analysis highlights the confusion regarding these ccfDNA parameters with tumor burden and predicting a therapeutic response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Hohaus et al. [17] also observed significant associations between the ccfDNA concentration and some adverse parameters, whereas a study by Jones et al. [18] found that the ccfDNA concentration was not indicative of lymphoma burden once therapy had commenced; they reported that only lymphoma-specific DNA such as Epstein-Barr virus DNA could be used to monitor the disease response in lymphoma patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In addition, both the ccfDNA concentration and the DII were not significantly different between germinal center B cell type and non-germinal center B cell type DLBCL based on the Hans classification system (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>We assessed the prognostic significance of ccfDNA levels in patients with DLBCL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Our data showed that high concentrations of ccfDNA and an elevated DII were strongly correlated with poor outcome in patients with DLBCL, which has already been reported [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>However, our study data revealed that the ccfDNA concentration was insufficient as an independent prognostic factor compared to other existing and validated adverse factors such as disease stage or elevated LDH levels [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The origin of ccfDNA is still unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In healthy individuals, the ccfDNA concentration is low, which is ascribed to the efficient removal of most nonliving cells from circulation by phagocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Schwarzenbach et al. [25] proposed that ccfDNA could be released by either apoptosis or necrosis and found that the predominant fragment length of ccfDNA frequently occurred in multiples of 180 bp, which is typical of DNA released from apoptotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, the presence of larger fragments such as those found in cancer patients suggested that ccfDNA could also be derived from necrotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Moreover, some studies have attributed a notable fraction of ccfDNA to active release from lymphocytes [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>ccfDNA is not specific to neoplastic conditions as increased levels have also been identified in inflammatory and autoimmune diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>An association between a high concentration of ccfDNA and poor prognosis may be linked to tumor burden [27]; however, changes in the total ccfDNA concentration may reflect not only changes in circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) but also in other conditions that may lead to an increase in ccfDNA, including infection or chemotherapy drug-induced release of normal ccfDNA into the circulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>ctDNA is a specific ccfDNA released by tumor cells, which contains genetic and epigenetic alterations concordant with those of the primary tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This may explain why our data showed the levels of ccfDNA in HL patients were as high as in NHL patients and indicated that the overall concentration of ccfDNA was not an independent significant prognostic factor of survival to some extent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Actually, our results showed the limitations of analyzing only the total ccfDNA levels, as focusing on tumor-specific ccfDNA might serve as a more adequate surrogate biomarker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>For solid tumors, many studies have validated that genetic alterations detected in ctDNA correspond to the primary tumor and that the levels of ctDNA could assess the tumor response and even provide an earlier indication of disease progression [28–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Roschewski et al. [31] reported that monitoring ctDNA could identify patients with DLBCL who are at risk of recurrence before the manifestation of clinical evidence of disease, and interim ctDNA may be a promising biomarker to identify patients at high risk of treatment failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, additional studies on ctDNA are required to prove its value in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Thus, as the ccfDNA levels could still reflect disease progression [32], they remain a useful biomarker to monitor disease status, especially when combined with other parameters such as the DII or ctDNA levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In this study, it should be noted that ccfDNA extraction was performed using the magnetic bead method, which is based on the principle of nucleic acid adsorption and release via magnetic beads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The most commonly used DNA extraction methods include the phenol-chloroform method, sodium iodide method, and magnetic bead method as well as the use of commercial DNA isolation kits [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Pan et al. [34] compared the phenol-chloroform method, commercial kits, and magnetic bead method in the detection of mycobacterium tuberculosis DNA and found that the magnetic bead method had the highest DNA extraction efficiency and the best reproducibility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our study demonstrated that the quantification and integrity analysis of ccfDNA from the plasma of patients with lymphoma might be a useful noninvasive technique for clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In patients with DLBCL, high levels of ccfDNA and an elevated integrity index were associated with poor prognosis, although, based on our results, only the DII was an independent adverse factor for PFS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that additional prospective studies with larger cohorts and a longer follow-up should be initiated to assess the utility of ccfDNA analysis, especially using tumor-specific ccfDNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><p>Informed consent was obtained from patients and controls according to the institutional guidelines, and the study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of the West China Hospital of Sichuan University.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>1.ChenWZhengRBaadePDCancer statistics in China, 2015CA Cancer J Clin20166611513210.3322/caac.21338<?supplied-pmid 26808342?>26808342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>2.ChesonBDFisherRIBarringtonSFRecommendations for initial evaluation, staging, and response assessment of Hodgkin and non-Hodgkin lymphoma: the Lugano classificationJ Clin Oncol2014323059306810.1200/JCO.2013.54.8800<?supplied-pmid 25113753?>25113753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>3.MandelPMetaisPLes acides nucleiques du plasma sanguin chez l'hommeCR Acad Sci Paris1948142241243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>4.FatourosIGDestouniAMargonisKCell-free plasma DNA as a novel marker of aseptic inflammation severity related to exercise overtrainingClin Chem2006521820182410.1373/clinchem.2006.070417<?supplied-pmid 16840584?>16840584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>5.TugSHelmigSMenkeJCorrelation between cell free DNA levels and medical evaluation of disease progression in systemic lupus erythematosus patientsCell Immunol2014292323910.1016/j.cellimm.2014.08.002<?supplied-pmid 25243646?>25243646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>6.LoYMRainerTHChanLYPlasma DNA as a prognostic marker in trauma patientsClin Chem200046319323<?supplied-pmid 10702517?>10702517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>7.ChangCPChiaRHWuTLElevated cell-free serum DNA detected in patients with myocardial infarctionClin Chim Acta20033279510110.1016/S0009-8981(02)00337-6<?supplied-pmid 12482623?>12482623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>8.LeonSAShapiroBSklaroffDMFree DNA in the serum of cancer patients and the effect of therapyCancer Res197737646650<?supplied-pmid 837366?>837366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>9.GalSFidlerCLoYMQuantitation of circulating DNA in the serum of breast cancer patients by real-time PCRBr J Cancer2004901211121510.1038/sj.bjc.6601609<?supplied-pmid 15026803?>15026803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>10.HaoTBShiWShenXJCirculating cell-free DNA in serum as a biomarker for diagnosis and prognostic prediction of colorectal cancerBr J Cancer20141111482148910.1038/bjc.2014.470<?supplied-pmid 25157833?>25157833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>11.SozziGConteDLeonMQuantification of free circulating DNA as a diagnostic marker in lung cancerJ Clin Oncol2003213902390810.1200/JCO.2003.02.006<?supplied-pmid 14507943?>14507943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>12.PerkinsGYapTAPopeLMulti-purpose utility of circulating plasma DNA testing in patients with advanced cancersPLoS One2012710.1371/journal.pone.0047020<?supplied-pmid 23144797?>23144797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>13.JahrSHentzeHEnglischSDNA fragments in the blood plasma of cancer patients: quantitations and evidence for their origin from apoptotic and necrotic cellsCancer Res20016116591665<?supplied-pmid 11245480?>11245480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>14.GaoYJHeYJYangZLIncreased integrity of circulating cell-free DNA in plasma of patients with acute leukemiaClin Chem Lab Med2010481651165610.1515/CCLM.2010.311<?supplied-pmid 20831457?>20831457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>15.HanleyRRieger-ChristKMCanesDDNA integrity assay: a plasma-based screening tool for the detection of prostate cancerClin Cancer Res2006124569457410.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-0130<?supplied-pmid 16899603?>16899603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>16.UmetaniNKimJHiramatsuSIncreased integrity of free circulating DNA in sera of patients with colorectal or periampullary cancer: direct quantitative PCR for ALU repeatsClin Chem2006521062106910.1373/clinchem.2006.068577<?supplied-pmid 16723681?>16723681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>17.HohausSGiacheliaMMassiniGCell-free circulating DNA in Hodgkin’s and non-Hodgkin’s lymphomasAnn Oncol2009201408141310.1093/annonc/mdp006<?supplied-pmid 19465421?>19465421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>18.JonesKNourseJPKeaneCTumor-specific but not nonspecific cell-free circulating DNA can be used to monitor disease response in lymphomaAm J Hematol20128725826510.1002/ajh.22252<?supplied-pmid 22213215?>22213215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>19.SalviantiFPinzaniPVerderioPMultiparametric analysis of cell-free DNA in melanoma patientsPLoS One2012710.1371/journal.pone.0049843<?supplied-pmid 23209607?>23209607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>20.ShippMAHarringtonDPAndersonJRA predictive model for aggressive non-Hodgkin’s lymphomaN Engl J Med199332998799410.1056/NEJM1993093032914028141877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>21.HasencleverDDiehlVA prognostic score for advanced Hodgkin’s disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>International prognostic factors project on advanced Hodgkin’s diseaseN Engl J Med19983391506151410.1056/NEJM199811193392104<?supplied-pmid 9819449?>9819449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>22.HyunKAKimJGwakHIsolation and enrichment of circulating biomarkers for cancer screening, detection, and diagnosticsAnalyst201514138239210.1039/C5AN01762A </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>23.El MessaoudiSMouliereFDu ManoirSCirculating DNA as a strong multimarker prognostic tool for metastatic colorectal cancer patient management careClin Cancer Res2016223067307710.1158/1078-0432.CCR-15-0297<?supplied-pmid 26847055?>26847055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>24.ZiepertMHasencleverDKuhntEStandard international prognostic index remains a valid predictor of outcome for patients with aggressive CD20+ B-cell lymphoma in the rituximab eraJ Clin Oncol2010282373238010.1200/JCO.2009.26.2493<?supplied-pmid 20385988?>20385988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>25.SchwarzenbachHHoonDSPantelKCell-free nucleic acids as biomarkers in cancer patientsNat Rev Cancer20111142643710.1038/nrc3066<?supplied-pmid 21562580?>21562580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>26.GarcRev CanDCRuiz-PiquerasRGarcerasuerDCirculating nucleic acids in plasma and serum (CNAPS) and its relation to stem cells and cancer metastasis: state of the issueHistol Histopathol20041957558315024717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>27.TateishiUTatsumiMTerauchiTPrognostic significance of metabolic tumor burden by positron emission tomography/computed tomography in patients with relapsed/refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphomaCancer Sci201510618619310.1111/cas.12588<?supplied-pmid 25495273?>25495273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>28.De Mattos-ArrudaLWeigeltBCortesJCapturing intra-tumor genetic heterogeneity by de novo mutation profiling of circulating cell-free tumor DNA: a proof-of-principleAnn Oncol2014251729173510.1093/annonc/mdu239<?supplied-pmid 25009010?>25009010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>29.DawsonSJTsuiDWMurtazaMAnalysis of circulating tumor DNA to monitor metastatic breast cancerN Engl J Med20133681199120910.1056/NEJMoa1213261<?supplied-pmid 23484797?>23484797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>30.BalgkouranidouIMatthaiosDKarayiannakisAPrognostic role of APC and RASSF1A promoter methylation status in cell free circulating DNA of operable gastric cancer patientsMutat Res2015778465110.1016/j.mrfmmm.2015.05.002<?supplied-pmid 26073472?>26073472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>31.RoschewskiMDunleavyKPittalugaSCirculating tumour DNA and CT monitoring in patients with untreated diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: a correlative biomarker studyLancet Oncol20151654154910.1016/S1470-2045(15)70106-3<?supplied-pmid 25842160?>25842160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>32.Melani C, Roschewski M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>(2016) Molecular monitoring of cell-free circulating tumor DNA in non-Hodgkin lymphoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Oncol (Williston Park) 30. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>33.MaugerFDularyCDaviaudCComprehensive evaluation of methods to isolate, quantify, and characterize circulating cell-free DNA from small volumes of plasmaAnal Bioanal Chem20154076873687810.1007/s00216-015-8846-4<?supplied-pmid 26123439?>26123439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>34.PanSGuBWangHComparison of four DNA extraction methods for detecting mycobacterium tuberculosis by real-time PCR and its clinical application in pulmonary tuberculosisJ Thorac Dis20135251257<?supplied-pmid 23825755?>23825755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
