<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5260044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4018-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2: Design of a multi-institutional intervention for obesity control and prevention for American Indian adults </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2761-3280</contrib-id><name><surname>Gittelsohn</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><address><phone>410-955-3927</phone><email>jgittel1@jhu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jock</surname><given-names>Brittany</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Redmond</surname><given-names>Leslie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fleischhacker</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eckmann</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bleich</surname><given-names>Sara N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogburn</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gadhoke</surname><given-names>Preety</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pardilla</surname><given-names>Marla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 9311</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.21107.35</institution-id><institution/><institution>Johns Hopkins University, Bloomberg School of Public Health, </institution></institution-wrap>615 N. Wolfe St. Suite W2041, Baltimore, MD 21205 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>National Institute of Diabetes, Digestive and Kidney Diseases Office of Nutrition Research, Bethesda, USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936754X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38142.3c</institution-id><institution/><institution>Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>St. John’s University, Queens, NY USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>105</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Obesity and other nutrition-related chronic disease rates are high in American Indian (AI) populations, and an urgent need exists to identify evidence-based strategies for prevention and treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Multi-level, multi-component (MLMC) interventions are needed, but there are significant knowledge gaps on how to deliver these types of interventions in low-income rural AI communities. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 is a MLMC intervention targeting AI adults living in six rural reservations in New Mexico and Wisconsin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Aiming to prevent and reduce obesity in adults by working at multiple levels of the food and physical activity (PA) environments, OPREVENT2 focuses on evidence-based strategies known to increase access to, demand for, and consumption of healthier foods and beverages, and increase worksite and home-based opportunities for PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 works to create systems-level change by partnering with tribal stakeholders, multiple levels of the food and PA environment (food stores, worksites, schools), and the social environment (children as change agents, families, social media). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Extensive evaluation will be conducted at each level of the intervention to assess effectiveness via process and impact measures. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Novel aspects of OPREVENT2 include: active engagement with stakeholders at many levels (policy, institutional, and at multiple levels of the food and PA system); use of community-based strategies to engage policymakers and other key stakeholders (community workshops, action committees); emphasis on both the built environment (intervening with retail food sources) and the social environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>This paper describes the design of the intervention and the evaluation plan of the OPREVENT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Clinical Trial Registration: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02803853">NCT02803853</ext-link> (June 10, 2016) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Obesity</kwd><kwd>Adults</kwd><kwd>Rural</kwd><kwd>American Indian</kwd><kwd>Multi-level interventions</kwd><kwd>Policy</kwd><kwd>Study design</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000050</institution-id><institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01HL122150</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gittelsohn</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Obesity disproportionately impacts American Indian (AI) populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The Centers for Disease Control estimated that roughly two thirds of AI adults are overweight or obese [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>AI are more than 60% more likely to be obese than non-Hispanic whites [2], and have highest rate of type 2 diabetes of any ethnic population in the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>[3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>AI adults are more than are twice as likely to be diagnosed with heart disease and coronary artery disease [5], 1.3 times more likely to have high blood pressure, and 2.4 times more likely to have a stroke [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>There are multiple causes of higher chronic disease rates among AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Most AI communities are rural, with a high proportion of households at or below the federal poverty level -- at the highest rate (28%) of any ethnic group in the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Rural AI communities tend to have reduced access to paved roads, public transportation and retail food outlets, such as supermarkets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The retail food sources that are present in AI communities tend to carry a limited range of foods [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Many AI communitie﻿s are dependent on gas-station stores, which primarily stock energy dense, high fat, and high sodium items (e.g., sodas, chips, candy) and rarely carry fresh produce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Even when on-reservation stores stock healthier foods, they tend to be at a higher price than unhealthy items [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Accessing affordable, high-quality healthy foods often requires off-reservation travel, and can easily be greater than 30 miles [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The built environment, including land use patterns, is also associated with low physical activity (PA) levels [11] and can be particularly influential in AI communities where resources allocated to the development of recreation facilities and parks are severely limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Physical inactivity is more prevalent among AI adults as compared to non-Hispanic whites, and reports show that 72.8% of AI or Alaska Native adults aged 18 years or older do not meet federal PA guidelines [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Several studies have also found low PA and decreased leisure time activity in AI populations [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Over the last decade, a number of studies have examined the development, implementation and evaluation of policy, systems and environmental changes at the local, state, and federal levels to promote active living and healthy eating [15, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, few policy strategies have focused on AI communities [8, 17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Many AIs live in separate reservation-based communities with tribal sovereignty and are relatively unaffected by mainstream obesity prevention policies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In areas where AIs are impacted by national or regional legislation, these policy approaches may not be sufficiently tailored to the resource constraints, cultural values or tribal sovereignty of the AI community [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As one example, the American Indian Healthy Eating (AIHE) Project was one of the first studies to systematically explore with tribal leaders their potential to utilize policy, systems and environmental change to promote healthy eating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Tribe-driven strategies were developed based on formative research that integrated qualitative, spatial, and policy analyses [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Building on the momentum established through AIHE, a capacity building project known as Healthy, Native North Carolinians (HNNC) was undertaken. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The majority of the obesity prevention trials conducted in AI communities has centered on children in the school setting [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Most of these earlier trials had modest success in changing behavior, with no impact on obesity [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Despite the apparent success of these trials in changing the school food and PA environments, the community and household environments were unchanged, apparently reducing or even erasing overall health impact [21, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In the past decade, multi-level, multicomponent (MLMC) interventions have sought to intervene in multiple settings – and to change multiple aspects of the food and PA environments – in an effort to enhance potential to have health impacts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These studies include the successful Shape Up Somerville (SUS) and Baltimore Healthy Eating Zones (BHEZ) [25, 26] trials aimed at reducing childhood obesity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>To date, only one MLMC trial has centered on reducing and preventing adult obesity in AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT, the precursor to the current trial, was a pilot study that sought to reduce adult obesity in five AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT was a MLMC trial that worked in food stores, worksites, schools and through community media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The results of this trial were also modest, showing no impact on PA, and limited impacts on diet and psychosocial factors (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>No change in body mass inde﻿x (BMI) was found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Limitations of this previous work include: lack of attention to policy, which is needed for sustainability; lack of emphasis on PA; and weaknesses in the delivery of the intervention, such that intensity and exposure were limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 is a full-scale MLMC trial, aimed at adult obesity reduction and prevention in AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 intervention is guided by Bandura’s social cognitive theory (SCT) and Bronfenbrenner’s social ecological model [27, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>SCT and the social ecological model conceptualize the individual as situated within broad family, institutional, community and political networks that influence their perceptions, behavior, and ultimately, their health status (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Psychosocial factors (e.g., knowledge, self-efficacy, behavioral intentions), social and interpersonal factors (e.g., family, peers), and physical-environmental factors (e.g., access to PA resources, food availability, price) interact at various levels to shape health outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>According to the social ecological model, these various levels and components operate as one interacting system within which information and resources flow bi-directionally from one level to another to influence health behaviors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Policy, institutional, and behavioral interventions have the potential to impact multiple levels of the food and PA environments.Fig. 1OPREVENT2 study conceptual framework </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 seeks to develop and test a series of intervention strategies that will function at multiple levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>It will be implemented in collaboration with tribal policymakers, school administrators and teachers, worksites, and retail food stores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Institutional level intervention components will promote healthy food and PA-related behaviors in order to influence the household (e.g., food purchasing, preparation, sedentary behavior) and individual psychosocial factors and behaviors that will ultimately impact obesity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Methods/design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 trial uses a stratified, group randomized study design, where six AI communities have been selected to serve as either intervention (n = 3) or comparison (n = 3, delayed intervention) areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Two communities are located in the Upper Midwest, and four communities in the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Southwestern regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Initially, 37 AI communities in both regions were contacted and invited to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The six participating communities are those who have agreed to participate and provided approvals in the form of tribal/chapter resolutions, as well as school and health board approvals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The research was approved by the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Institutional Review Board (IRB) as well as the Indian Health Service IRB and the Navajo Nation Human Research Review Board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent will be obtained for all participants in the impact evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Formative research </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Prior to the OPREVENT2 intervention in main trial communities, extensive formative research was conducted with two pilot AI communities: one in the Midwest and one in the Southwest region of the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>These communities are not OPREVENT2 main trial communities, though they have similar tribal affiliations and are based in similar regions as the main trial communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The formative research focused on identifying how environmental changes are made throughout the communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>It also aimed to identify the facilitators and barriers these communities face in this process to identify ways to promote and support policy and environmental changes in the OPREVENT2 trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In-depth interviews, observations, and modified talking circles were conducted in each pilot community [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Key participants included: tribal policymakers, health staff, and community member health champions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Theoretical and snowball sampling were used to identify additional participants engaged in the policy and structural change development processes in each community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Following and concurrent to this formative research, a small pilot was conducted in each community, consisting of three Community Action Committee meetings in each community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Participatory methods used in this pilot included talking circles, social mapping, and exploring environmental changes [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Community workshops </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The aim of the community workshops, which are currently underway, is to obtain in-depth input from the OPREVENT2 main trial community members regarding how to adapt previous OPREVENT intervention materials, and to define new materials/approaches that may be needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Three different types of workshops are being conducted in each community: 1) community members focused on general intervention strategies and communications materials; 2) teachers and other school personnel focused on the school program component, and 3) tribal leaders and health staff that will inform structural and policy changes possible in each community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The research team will then review input and make final changes to the OPREVENT2 strategy and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Participants and recruitment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The target group in the OPREVENT2 MLMC intervention is AI adults, ages 18–75 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Participants in the evaluation sample will be randomly recruited from household lists provided by each tribe/community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Due to privacy concerns, in four of the communities, local authorities have agreed to provide us with randomly selected households. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Once consent is received, interviews will be conducted with one person per household until 80 have been completed for each of the six communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Potential participants will be screened for eligibility (e.g., tribal member, adult 18–75 years, no plans to move for next two years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>If a randomly selected household is unable to complete the interview, then the next eligible household will be selected from the recruitment list. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 intervention will involve multiple components at many levels (Fig. 1): policy, schools, fo﻿od stores, worksites, and community media (including social media). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Each component of the OPREVENT2 program will reinforce several other components – either by improving access to or increasing demand for healthy foods and PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 program will be implemented in six 2-month phases, with each phase focusing on different foods, activities, and promotions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Policy-level approaches </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Community Action Committees (CAC) will be established within each community to identify and support structural and environmental changes, in partnership with community partners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Participation in the committee will be open to all community members, and recruitment will be done using mass media communication in each community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Health staff and tribal policymakers will also be invited to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The recruitment goal of this committee will be to bring together participants who are already engaged in making environmental changes in the community – whether formally through health programs and health policy or informally by the actions of existing champions in the community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Forming relationships between stakeholders, aligning existing health programs to support environmental changes, and developing health policies will help to increase sustainability of the OPREVENT2 intervention and promote long-term environmental changes in each community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This committee will meet monthly, and will work to support: sustainability of the OPREVENT2 program and critical reflection of the community environment and its role in shaping behavior, and community member interest in the health fields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>These meetings will be facilitated by an OPREVENT2 interventionist, who will also work to train a new facilitator in the community to enhance sustainability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Changing food access in community food stores </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Our work with food sources will aim to increase access to healthier foods by working in all on-reservation stores that agree to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A central strategy will be increasing the stocking and sales of affordable healthy food options at food stores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For smaller, privately owned stores, we will provide gift cards to their wholesaler, enabling them to purchase a starter stock of promoted foods and beverages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>We will conduct promotional activities at the point of purchase, including shelf labels, posters, interactive sessions such as taste tests and cooking demonstrations, and the provision of flyers, booklets, small gifts and other promotional materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Interactive sessions will occur at least once per week in each participating food store. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Our intervention components at the food source level are based on previous small store interventions conducted in AI communities [31, 32] with additional innovative pieces, including training videos to assist store owners/managers in stocking/marketing healthier foods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Increasing physical activity opportunities in worksites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Physical activity will be a primary focus of the OPREVENT2 intervention worksite component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Intervention materials for worksites will focus on educating community members on recommended type and duration of PA, making a plan and setting goals to exercise, including working out with a partner [33–35], and fueling PA with proper nutrition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Educational materials, including posters, flyers, and educational displays, will be made available at worksites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Interventionists will make several visits to worksites to present on the health benefits of PA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The primary activity to promote PA in worksites will be a FitBit Challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Employees within each worksite will be encouraged to register in teams for the challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Interventionists will distribute free FitBits to registered teams and provide teams with an orientation on proper use, including how to track and monitor their participation in the challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Interventionists will make weekly follow-up visits to each worksite to record daily and weekly steps for challenge participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The members of the team with the highest overall number of steps will be awarded each month with “Team of the Month” certificates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>At the end of the Challenge, the final winning team will receive a free healthy lunch provided by OPREVENT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The top three walkers from each OPREVENT2 community will be awarded a commemorative plaque. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>School curriculum, developing Native youth as household obesity change agents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>A school-to-family curriculum aimed at encouraging children to be household change agents will be a critical component of the OPREVENT2 project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Children influence adults in their households positively for healthier nutrition and PA related habits on multiple levels [36–41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>School-based curricula have reported improved adult household members’ food getting habits, reduced fat intake and consumption, increased fruit and vegetable consumption, and lower BMI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In our precursor study, OPREVENT, we developed a unique, culturally relevant and sensitive school-based curriculum with the partnership of AI curriculum developers and artists for grades 2–6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The grades 2–4 curricula are comprised of weekly in-class curriculum materials that are tailored to each state’s education standards and an AI storybook. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The storybook highlights a poignant story of two young children who learn about healthy lifestyles from their cousin, the change agent in their life, and develops into change agents for their household. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The children travel and experience other tribal cultures, challenges, and strengths of each of the six AI communities participating in OPREVENT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The grades 5–6 curriculum will adapt the “Cooking with Kids” tasting program [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Teachers in each school will be trained in the delivery of the curricula for their grade level, and will be provided with materials needed to implement the program in their classrooms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Community and social media </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Community and social media will be an integral component of the OPREVENT2 intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Community media will be based on OPREVENT, which included use of newsletters and radio announcements within communities to spread intervention messages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Newsletters and radio announcements will be specific to each phase, and produced in the local Native language and delivered by Elders whenever possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In addition to promotion of intervention messages, we will work with tribal health staff to implement community-wide activities, including walking clubs and food store tours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 staff will attend existing community events such as health fairs, community meetings, school activities, and community walks to promote OPREVENT2 activities and to identify key community stakeholders for partnership. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Study communities have a variety of local media, including local radio and cable access channels, bulletin boards, newsletters, and websites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Announcements through local media will be used to promote ongoing activities and products at schools and stores. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Social media and online networks have the capacity to disseminate information widely while promoting social support and reshaping norms [43, 44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 social media component will consist of Facebook, Instagram, and Twitter platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A Social Media Working Group has been formed to explore the best message content for each platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Facebook and Instagram messages will be focused on health information and current events pertinent to our population, such as common health issues and promotional activities in AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Topics will range from exercises tips to healthy recipes incorporating traditional foods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The primary focus of Twitter will be to share recent research related to fitness and nutrition with other community stakeholders as well as with Native tribes/communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Content published on each platform will be promoted and boosted using tools built into each platform for this purpose (e.g., boosting of Facebook posts, creation of Twitter campaigns) in an effort to increase followers and expand the reach of the intervention messages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Standards for intervention delivery, process evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Intervention implementation at each level will be monitored through ongoing process evaluation, with the intention of assuring that set standards are being met (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>These standards are based on our review of the literature, and on our previous experiences implementing MLMC interventions in AI communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 intervention team will meet every two months to review the degree to which intervention standards are being met, and will improve implementation on that basis.Table 1Select process evaluation measures and standards by OPREVENT2 intervention componentIntervention levelProcess evaluation measureHigh standarda Policy# CAC meetings held/community/year# attendees/CAC meeting# different sectors represented/meeting12104Schools% teachers (grades 2–6) trained/school% lessons taught/grade% family packs returned907560Food Stores% promoted healthy foods stocked% shelf labels correctly placed# interactive sessions/store/phase# visitors/interactive session8080620Worksites# participating worksites/community# coffee/water stations made over/participating community% AI staff initially participating in FitBit Challenge% AI staff participating in FitBit Challenge after 2 months557050Community media# radio announcements/week# newsletter/mailed flyers/phase34Social media# Facebook, Instagram, Twitter posts/day/platform# boosts Facebook, Instagram, Twitter/week/platform# likes/follows/week/platform3350 aQuality of implementation based on % high standard met: low = &lt;50%, med = 50–99%, high= &gt; =100% </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Comparison communities (delayed intervention) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The comparison communities will receive the OPREVENT2 intervention following completion of the post-intervention evaluations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Data safety and monitoring </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A Data Safety and Monitoring Board, meeting 1-2 times per year, has been formed to assure the study meets standards of safety and confidentiality, and to deal with possible adverse events. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The OPREVENT2 trial will be evaluated at each intervention level (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Process evaluation measures will assess reach, dose delivered, and fidelity of intervention implementation (Table 1).Table 2Impact evaluation measures for the OPREVENT2 trial by intervention levelIntervention levelImpact/outcome measurePolicy# CAC action items achieved/year# health-related issues put on tribal policymaker’s agenda/yearIncrease in CAC participant collective efficacy scoresSchools# policy changes made to improve the school food and PA environments# structural changes made to improve the school food and PA environments (e.g., removal of vending machines)Food Stores# units of promoted foods sold# units of promoted foods purchased/consumed by OPREVENT2 participantsWorksites# policy changes made to improve the workplace food and PA environments# structural changes made to improve the workplace food and PA environments (e.g., changing what’s in vending machines)Adult/householdHousehold food purchasing (healthy and unhealthy foods)Healthiness of common methods of food preparationChange in psychosocial factors (knowledge, self-efficacy, intentions)Change in dietary patterns (e.g., total calories, total fat, FV servings, HEI scores, etc.)Change in PA (IPAQ, FitBit)Change in weight, BMI, blood pressure, waist and hip circumference </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A sample of adults (100 per community) will be surveyed pre and post intervention to assess impact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The Adult Impact Questionnaire (AIQ) will assess the food getting frequency of our promoted products, household patterns of food acquisition and preparation, adult PA, morbidity history and sociodemographic variables (e.g., age, education, income range). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In addition, the AIQ will evaluate psychosocial constructs including healthy food knowledge, self-efficacy, intentions about food, and community resources/environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The AIQ instrument uses a modified Individual Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) Short Form (IPAQ-SF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The IPAQ-SF specifically asks about walking, moderate-intensity PA, and vigorous-intensity PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>It was determined to be appropriate for this population and study for several reasons: validity studies have been conducted in similar populations; low time burden it was easy to modify to be more culturally acceptable for our target population; and it was piloted in the communities and found to be acceptable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic, family medical history and anthropometric measurements (i.e., height, weight, percent body fat, waist circumference, hip circumference, blood pressure, heart rate) will be collected to assess obesity and other health-related factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>We will be using Tanita 300GS (Tanita Corp., Tokyo, Japan) scales for body weight and percent body fat, and the Omron Fat Loss Monitor (HBF-306) will be used for a second percent body fat estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Blood pressure and heart rate will be measured using an Omron Automatic Wrist Blood Pressure Monitor, Model #BP652 (HEM-6052-Z), and will be assessed pre and post intervention in intervention and comparison respondents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>We worked with NutritionQuest to develop a modified Block Food Frequency Questionnaire (FFQ) specific to our study sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In addition to standard Block FFQ food items, it includes traditional AI foods common in the Southwest and Upper Midwest regions, as well as specific food items promoted and de-promoted within our intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The FFQ was based on the FFQ that was used in the Strong Heart Study Family Study, Cardiovascular Disease in American Indians (Phase V), an instrument used by investigators at the Johns Hopkins Center for American Indian Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The FFQ includes 95 questions pertaining to frequency and portion size of particular foods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Portion sizes will be estimated with the aid of standard portion size illustrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The final section of the FFQ includes 24 questions pertaining to additions to food items (e.g., milk, creamer, etc. to coffee) and type of food items (e.g., low-fat, low-carb, etc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The FFQ will be used to assess dietary intake pre and post intervention in intervention and comparison respondents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>At post intervention data collection, we will collect information on exposure to specific intervention components and materials for all participants which will be used to assess self-reported dose received by our evaluation sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>A series of structured surveys will be conducted pre and post intervention in schools, food stores, and worksites to assess change at the level of these institutions in terms of the food and PA environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>A Community Action Component Impact Questionnaire will be administered to committee participants at their first meeting and at post intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Participant characteristics (e.g., age, occupation) will be gathered, and the instrument will be used to gauge change in collective efficacy, intentions, as well as a free list of community changes and feedback of CAC activities (post intervention only). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Data safety and confidentiality </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Electronically collected data will be encrypted using Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) encryption using REDCap and will be upload to a server at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>All data collectors received a unique user PIN that are ciphered using Secure Hash Algorithm (SHA) cryptography, and all stored REDCAP data and REDCAP application logs are encrypted using advanced encryption standards on tablet PC until the data is uploaded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A separate administrator username and password will prevent data collectors from altering the data and data collection instruments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Sample size and statistical methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Sample size calculations were based on testing the change in mean BMI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Modeling and calculations were based on testing for an effect size d = |μ1–μ2|/σ = 0.5, where μ1 is the mean change in one of the two primary outcome measurements in the treatment group, μ2 is the corresponding mean change in the control group, and σ is the standard deviation of the observed differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The detectable difference (|μ1–μ2|) for the change in mean BMI and daily FV intake was determined using the impact data from OPREVENT and other interventions similar to OPREVENT2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>We used OPREVENT baseline BMI data on 422 AI adults to estimate the standard deviation of the observed differences between pre and post intervention BMIs, assuming that the variances of mean BMI from pre and post intervention are equal and assuming a large correlation between pre- and post-intervention measurements (r = 0.9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We used data from a survey sample of AIs in the Midwest [45] to estimate the standard deviation of the observed differences in mean daily FV under the same assumptions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>For BMI, σ = 3.5 and therefore the detectable change in average BMI is 1.3 kg/m2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>For FV, σ = 1.56 and therefore the detectable change in daily FV servings is 0.78 servings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The power was obtained from a two-sample t-test formula β = 1 ‐ P(t ≤ tα/2) + P(t  ≤ ‐ tα/2), where t is a non-central t-distribution with df = 2(3–1) degrees of freedom and a non-centrality parameter NC = d/[2{1 + (85–1)ρ}/(3*85)]1/2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Here ρ is the within-community correlation between the differences between the primary outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Calculations were based on a ρ equal to 0.01; this value is consistent with the range of correlations reported in the literature [46, 47] and the correlation for baseline BMI and FV found in OPREVENT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>All calculations were done assuming a 20% loss to follow-up from pre to post data collection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>With 80 participants per community and three communities per arm, there is 80% power to detect an effect size of d = 0.5 (which corresponds to a 1.3 kg/m2 change in mean BMI and a 0.78 change in mean daily fruit and vegetable consumption) with a type I error of 5%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We will examine intervention effects by subtracting the pre intervention score/intake from post intervention score/intake and then conduct linear mixed-effect models for confirmatory testing of intervention effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We will conduct t-tests for normally distributed continuous variables and nonparametric Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney tests for non-normal continuous variables; Chi square and Fisher’s exact tests for dichotomous variables; and Mantel trend tests for ordinal variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We will follow this exploratory analysis with multilevel mixed models using the lmer function from the lme4 package for R [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Linear and logistic regression models will be adopted for identifying intervention effects as well as risk factors in regression analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>We will examine multiple primary response variables, including specific indicators of dietary quality (e.g., FV servings, energy intake) and of obesity (e.g. BMI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Fixed effects of the model will be baseline values for these variables, treatment group, age, gender, ethnicity and mediating variables wherever applicable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The community will be treated as a random effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, OPREVENT2 will be one of only two MLMC obesity prevention intervention trials targeting AI adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Substantial formative research and a community engagement process will be used to refine and develop intervention strategies and materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>OPREVENT2 will be a unique trial that integrates stakeholders at multiple critical levels: policy, food retail, worksites, schools, and individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Multiple components of the food and PA environments will be targeted, leading to improved exposure and reinforcement of key messages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>There will be an emphasis on social dimensions of the environment, involving social media and the use of children as change agents in the home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Detailed process and impact evaluations will occur at all intervention levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Tribal leaders, tribal health staff, researchers, and public health practitioners will be greatly interested in OPREVENT2 program findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>MLMC interventions are thought to be required to address the multifactorial causes of obesity, yet few of these large intervention trials have been successfully completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Trials such as OPREVENT2 are required to see if MLMC approaches are indeed more successful, and how they should best be implemented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>One major strength of the OPREVENT2 program will be that it will provide a model of how to work with tribal policymakers and other key stakeholders to improve the community food and PA environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Because of its prolonged and frequent engagement with policymakers and other community leaders, OPREVENT2 may lead to long-term impact, and be sustained through institutionalization of intervention components. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We want to thank tribal authorities, health staff, school administration and staff and food store owners and managers in the six tribal communities in Wisconsin and New Mexico for their agreement to participate in this intervention trial.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>Funding for this study was provided by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (R01HL122150; J. Gittelsohn).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study may be available on request from both the PI (Gittelsohn) and participating tribal communities.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>JG designed the study, developed the protocol, and drafted the manuscript. BJ participated in the design of the study, conducted formative research activities, and developed and coordinated the policy component. LR participated in the design of the study, and developed and coordinated the physical activity component. SF participated in the design of the study, and assisted in the development of the policy component. TE participated in the design of the study, and contributed to sample size and statistical methods. SB participated in the design of the study, and assisted in the development of the policy component. HL participated in the design of the study, and developed and coordinated the social media component. EO participated in the design of the study and supervised the sample size and statistical methods. PG participated in the design of the study, conducted formative research activities, and developed and coordinated the school component. JS and MP participated in the design of the study. All authors assisted in developing process and impact evaluation tools related to their component. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. Funding/assistance was not received from a commercial organization.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Ethics approval was granted from the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Institutional Review Board (7028), the Indian Health Service Institutional Review Board, and the Navajo Nation Human Research Review Board (NNR-16-245). Written informed consent will be received from all study participants.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>1.National Center for Health Statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Health, United States, 2011: With Special Feature on Socioeconomic Status and Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Hyattsville; 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>2.Schiller JS, Lucas JW, Peregoy JA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Summary Health Statistics for U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Adults: National Health Interview Survey, 2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Vital Health Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3.SinghGKSiahpushMHiattRATimsinaLRDramatic increases in obesity and overweight prevalence and body mass index among ethnic-immigrant and social class groups in the United States, 1976–2008J Community Health20113619411010.1007/s10900-010-9287-9<?supplied-pmid 20549318?>20549318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>4.YuCHZinmanBType 2 diabetes and impaired glucose tolerance in aboriginal populations: a global perspectiveDiabetes Res Clin Pract20077821597010.1016/j.diabres.2007.03.022<?supplied-pmid 17493702?>17493702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>5.Barnes PM, Adams PF, Powell-Griner E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Health Characteristics of the American Indian or Alaska Native Adult Population: United States, 2004–2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Hyattsville: US Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>1–23. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>6.Harris R, Nelson LA, Muller C, Buchwald D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Stroke in American Indians and Alaska Natives: A Systematic Review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Am J Public Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>2015;105(8):e16–26. doi:10.2105/AJPH.2015.302698. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>7.U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Census BureauAmerican Community Survey, 2014 American Community Survey 1-Year Estimates2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>8.GittelsohnJRowanMPreventing diabetes and obesity in American Indian communities: the potential of environmental interventionsAm J Clin Nutr20119351179S8310.3945/ajcn.110.003509<?supplied-pmid 21411614?>21411614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>9.Kumar G, Jim-Martin S, Piltch E, Onufrak S, McNeil C, Adams L, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Healthful nutrition of foods in Navajo Nation stores: Availability and pricing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Am J Health Promot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2015 [Epub ahead of print]. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>10.Lee T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>7 foods that cost more on the rez, and one junk food that costs less. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Indian County Media Network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>2016. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://indiancountrymedianetwork.com/culture/health-wellness/7-foods-that-cost-more-on-the-rez-and-one-junk-food-that-costs-less/">https://indiancountrymedianetwork.com/culture/health-wellness/7-foods-that-cost-more-on-the-rez-and-one-junk-food-that-costs-less/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Accessed 17 Jan 2017. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="?"><plain>11.Does the Built Environment Influence Physical Activity? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Washington, D.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>2005. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinepubs.trb.org/onlinepubs/sr/sr282.pdf">http://onlinepubs.trb.org/onlinepubs/sr/sr282.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Accessed 29 Aug 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>12.Foulds HJ1, Warburton DE, Bredin SS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>A systematic review of physical activity levels in Native American populations in Canada and the United States in the last 50 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Obes Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>2013;14(7):593–603. doi:10.1111/obr.12032. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Epub 2013 Apr 11. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>13.YurgalevitchSMKriskaAMWeltyTKGoORobbinsDCHowardBVPhysical activity and lipids and lipoproteins in American Indians ages 45–74Med Sci Sports Exerc1998304543910.1097/00005768-199804000-00012<?supplied-pmid 9565936?>9565936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>14.HoLGittelsohnJSharmaSFood-related behavior, physical activity, and dietary intake in First Nations– a population at high risk for diabetesEthn Health20081343354910.1080/13557850701882936<?supplied-pmid 18701993?>18701993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>15.BowenDJBarringtonWEBeresfordSAIdentifying the effects of environmental and policy change interventions on healthy eatingAnnu Rev Public Health20153628930610.1146/annurev-publhealth-032013-182516<?supplied-pmid 25785891?>25785891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>16.KumanyikaSKSwankMStacheckiJWhitt-GloverMCBrennanLKExamining the evidence for policy and environmental strategies to prevent childhood obesity in black communities: new directions and next stepsObes Rev201415Suppl 417720310.1111/obr.12206<?supplied-pmid 25196413?>25196413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>17.FleischhackerSByrdRRRamachandranGVuMRiesABellRAEvensonKRTools for healthy tribes: improving access to healthy foods in Indian countryAm J Prev Med2012433 Suppl 2S123910.1016/j.amepre.2012.05.015<?supplied-pmid 22898161?>22898161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>18.DavisSMGoingSBHelitzerDLTeufelNISnyderPGittelsohnJPathways: a culturally appropriate obesity-prevention program for American Indian schoolchildrenAm J Clin Nutr1999694 Suppl796S802<?supplied-pmid 10195605?>10195605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>19.RitenbaughCTeufel-ShoneNIAickinMGJoeJRPoirierSA lifestyle interventions improves plasma insulin levels among Native American high school youthPrev Med20033633091910.1016/S0091-7435(02)00015-4<?supplied-pmid 12634022?>12634022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>20.Saksvig BI, Gittelsohn J, Harris SB, Hanley AJG, Valente TW, Zinman B. A pilot school-based health eating and physical activity intervention improves diet, food knowledge, and self-efficacy for native Canadian children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>J Nutr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>2005;135(10):2392–8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>21.GittelsohnJKumarMBPreventing childhood obesity and diabetes: Is it time to move out of the school?Pediatr Diabetes20078Suppl 9556910.1111/j.1399-5448.2007.00333.x<?supplied-pmid 17991134?>17991134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>22.Fleischhacker S, Roberts E, Camplain R, Evenson KR, Gittelsohn J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Promoting Physical Activity Among Native American Youth: a Systematic Review of the Methodology and Current Evidence of Physical Activity Interventions and Community-wide Initiatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>2015 [Epub ahead of print]. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>23.GittelsohnJDavisSMStecklerAEthelbahBClayTMetcalfeLRockBHPathways: lessons learned and future directions for school-based interventions among American IndiansPrev Med200337Suppl 1S1071210.1016/j.ypmed.2003.08.001<?supplied-pmid 14636815?>14636815 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>24.GittelsohnJMerkleSStoryMStoneEJStecklerANoelJBSchool climate and implementation of the Pathways studyPrev Med200337Suppl 1S9710610.1016/j.ypmed.2003.08.010<?supplied-pmid 14636814?>14636814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>25.ShinAHSurkanPJCoutinhoAJSuratkarSKramerRFRowanMTImpact of Baltimore Healthy Eating Zones: An environmental intervention to reduce obesity and obesity-related factors among African-American youthHealth Educ Behav2015421 Suppl97S10510.1177/1090198115571362<?supplied-pmid 25829124?>25829124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>26.EconomicsCDHyattRRMustAGoldbergJPKuderJNaumovaENShape Up Somerville two-year results: a community-based environmental change intervention sustains weight reduction in childrenPrev Med2013574322710.1016/j.ypmed.2013.06.00123756187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>27.BanduraASocial foundations in thought and action1986Englewood Cliffs, NJPrentice Hall </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>28.BronfenbrennerUEcology of the Family as a Context for Human Development: Research PerspectivesDev Psychol19862267234210.1037/0012-1649.22.6.723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>29.FleischhackerSVuMRiesAMcPhailAEngaging tribal leaders in an American Indian healthy eating project through modified talking circlesFam Community Health20113432021010.1097/FCH.0b013e31821960bb<?supplied-pmid 21633212?>21633212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>30.CARE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Embracing Participation in Development: Worldwide experience from CARE’s Reproductive Health Programs with a step-by-step field guide to participatory tools and techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Atlanta: CARE/Health and Population Unit; 1999. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>31.GittelsohnJKimEMHeSPardillaMA food-store based environmental intervention is associated with reduced BMI and improved psychosocial factors and food-related behaviors on the Navajo NationJ Nutr20031439149450010.3945/jn.112.165266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>32.GittelsohnJVijayadevaVDavisonNRamirezVCheungLWKMurphySNovotnyRA food store intervention trial improves caregiver and child food-related psychosocial factors and behaviors in HawaiiObesity2010181supplS849010.1038/oby.2009.436<?supplied-pmid 20107467?>20107467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>33.FeltzDLKerrNLIrwinBCBuddy up: the Köhler effect applied to health gamesJ Sport Exerc Physiol201133450626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>34.FeltzDLIrwinBKerrNTwo-player partnered exergame for obesity prevention: using discrepancy in players’ abilities as a strategy to motivate physical activityJ Diabetes Sci Technol201264820710.1177/193229681200600413<?supplied-pmid 22920808?>22920808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>35.IrwinBCScorniaenchiJKerrNLEisenmannJCFeltzDLAerobic exercise is promoted when individual performance affects the group: a test of the Köhler motivation gain affectAnn Behav Med2012442151910.1007/s12160-012-9367-4<?supplied-pmid 22576339?>22576339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>36.GadhokePStructure, culture, and agency: Framing a child as change agent approach for adult obesity prevention in American Indian households2012BaltimoreThe Johns Hopkins University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>37.BorysJMLafayLNutritional information for children to modify the food habits of the whole familyRev Med Suisse Romande2000921191823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>38.DavisMBaranowskiTHughesMStecklerALinnanUsing children as change agents in increased fruit and vegetable consumption among lower-income African American adults: Process evaluation results of the Bringing It Home ProgramProcess Evaluation in Public Health Interventions2002San FranciscoJossey-Bass </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>39.LarocheHHDavisMMFormanJPalmisanoGReisingerHSTannasCChildren’s roles in parents’ diabetes self-managementAm J Prev Med2009376 Suppl.1S2516110.1016/j.amepre.2009.08.003<?supplied-pmid 19896027?>19896027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>40.LarocheHHHoferTPDavisMMAdult fat intake associated with the presence of children in households. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Findings from NHANES IIIJ Am Board Fam Med200720191510.3122/jabfm.2007.01.060085<?supplied-pmid 17204729?>17204729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>41.GadhokePChristiansenKSchwartzJGittelsohnJ‘Cause it’s family talking to you”: Children as change agents for adult nutrition and physical activity in American Indian households in semi-rural Upper Midwestern United StatesChildhood2014223116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>42.Cunningham-SaboLLohseBImpact of a school-based cooking curriculum for fourth-grade students on attitudes and behaviors is influenced by gender and prior cooking experienceJ Nutr Educ Behav20144621102010.1016/j.jneb.2013.09.007<?supplied-pmid 24268970?>24268970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>43.CobbNKGrahamALByronMJAbramsDBWorkshop ParticipantsOnline Social Networks and Smoking Cessation: A Scientific Research AgendaJ Med Internet Res2011134e11910.2196/jmir.1911<?supplied-pmid 22182518?>22182518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>44.LiJSBarnettTAGoodmanEWassermanRCKemperARApproaches to the prevention and management of childhood obesity: The role of social networks and the use of social media and related electronic technologies: A scientific statement from the American heart associationCirculation20131272260710.1161/CIR.0b013e3182756d8e<?supplied-pmid 23212719?>23212719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>45.BergCJDaleyCMNazirNKinlacheenyJBAshleyAAhluwaliaJSPhysical activity and fruit and vegetable intake among American IndiansJ Community Health2012371657110.1007/s10900-011-9417-z<?supplied-pmid 21630108?>21630108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>46.DonnerAKlarNStatistical considerations in the design and analysis of community intervention trialsJ Clin Epidemiol1996494435910.1016/0895-4356(95)00511-0<?supplied-pmid 8621994?>8621994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>47.FengZGrizzleJECorrelated binomial variates: properties of estimator of intraclass correlation and its effect on sample size calculationStat Med1992111216071410.1002/sim.4780111208<?supplied-pmid 1439364?>1439364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>48.BatesDMaechlerMBolkerBWalkerSFitting Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using lme4J Stat Softw201567114810.18637/jss.v067.i01 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
