<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Fam Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Fam. Cancer</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Familial Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1389-9600</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-7292</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5999171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">39</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10689-017-0039-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of current prediction models for Lynch syndrome: updating the PREMM5 model to identify PMS2 mutation carriers </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3238-4411</contrib-id><name><surname>Goverde</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spaander</surname><given-names>M. C. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nieboer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van den Ouweland</surname><given-names>A. M. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dinjens</surname><given-names>W. N. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dubbink</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tops</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>ten Broeke</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hofstra</surname><given-names>R. M. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><address><phone>+3110 7036913</phone><email>a.wagner@erasmusmc.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Genetics, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC, University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC, University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC, University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathology, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC, University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089452978</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Genetics, </institution><institution>Leiden University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089452978</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Statistics and Bioinformatics, </institution><institution>Leiden University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Genetics, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC, University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Room Ee-2018, P. O. Box 2040, 3000 CA Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Until recently, no prediction models for Lynch syndrome (LS) had been validated for PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>We aimed to evaluate MMRpredict and PREMM5 in a clinical cohort and for PMS2 mutation carriers specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In a retrospective, clinic-based cohort we calculated predictions for LS according to MMRpredict and PREMM5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The area under the operator receiving characteristic curve (AUC) was compared between MMRpredict and PREMM5 for LS patients in general and for different LS genes specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Of 734 index patients, 83 (11%) were diagnosed with LS; 23 MLH1, 17 MSH2, 31 MSH6 and 12 PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Both prediction models performed well for MLH1 and MSH2 (AUC 0.80 and 0.83 for PREMM5 and 0.79 for MMRpredict) and fair for MSH6 mutation carriers (0.69 for PREMM5 and 0.66 for MMRpredict). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>MMRpredict performed fair for PMS2 mutation carriers (AUC 0.72), while PREMM5 failed to discriminate PMS2 mutation carriers from non-mutation carriers (AUC 0.51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The only statistically significant difference between PMS2 mutation carriers and non-mutation carriers was proximal location of colorectal cancer (77 vs. 28%, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Adding location of colorectal cancer to PREMM5 considerably improved the models performance for PMS2 mutation carriers (AUC 0.77) and overall (AUC 0.81 vs. 0.72). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We validated these results in an external cohort of 376 colorectal cancer patients, including 158 LS patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>MMRpredict and PREMM5 cannot adequately identify PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Adding location of colorectal cancer to PREMM5 may improve the performance of this model, which should be validated in larger cohorts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s10689-017-0039-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Lynch syndrome</kwd><kwd>Prediction models</kwd><kwd>Colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>Hereditary cancer</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature B.V. 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Lynch syndrome (LS) is a hereditary predisposition to colorectal cancer, endometrial cancer and other extra-colonic cancers at a young age [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Morbidity and mortality of LS carriers can be significantly reduced by surveillance programs [3–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Therefore identifying LS carriers is of great importance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>LS is caused by a germline mutation in one of the mismatch repair (MMR) genes MLH1, MSH2, MSH6 or PMS2, or in the 3′ end of the EPCAM gene and consequent hypermethylation of the MSH2 promoter region [6–10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>As a result, tumours in LS patients are characterized by microsatellite instability (MSI) and by loss of MMR protein expression in immunohistochemistry (IHC) [11–13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Analysis of MSI and IHC, combined with MLH1 promoter methylation analysis to exclude sporadic MMR deficient tumours, are used to identify patients with tumours likely caused by LS [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A definite diagnosis of LS is made when a pathogenic germline mutation is found. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The revised Bethesda guidelines were based on a set of diagnostic criteria to select patients eligible for LS screening in tumour tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, due to limited sensitivity, many LS patients will likely be missed by these guidelines [14–17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Several prediction models, such as MMRpro, MMRpredict and PREMM5 have also been developed to calculate an individual’s probability of carrying a germline MMR mutation [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These models could aid in the selection of patients at high risk of having LS, for tumour analysis or direct germline mutation analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>MMRpro is less useful in clinical practice since detailed information of all relatives is needed as input for the model [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, MMRpredict and PREMM1,2,6 (a previous version of the newly developed PREMM5 model) both performed well in previous evaluations [21–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>An advantage of PREMM5 is that it can also be used for individuals with extracolonic malignancies and healthy individuals, as opposed to MMRpredict, which can only be used for CRC patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Until recently, all prediction models for LS were developed with cohorts of patients carrying a MLH1, MSH2, or MSH6 mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The recently published PREMM5 model is the only model that included PMS2 mutation carriers in its development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this study we aimed to evaluate MMRpredict and PREMM5 in a clinical cohort and for PMS2 mutation carriers specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we aimed to identify clinical features useful for distinguishing PMS2 mutation carriers from non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In a retrospective, clinic-based cohort we assessed the performance of MMRpredict and PREMM5 in predicting LS mutations in general and for MLH1, MSH2, MSH6 and PMS2 mutations specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we performed a univariate analysis to identify variables that can distinguish PMS2 mutation carriers from patients with no MMR mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Study population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We collected data for all families that were referred for genetic counselling at Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, The Netherlands, and in which colorectal cancer was analysed for MSI and/or IHC between 2000 and 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria were: failed or inconclusive analysis for MSI and IHC, a pathogenic mutation in APC or MUTYH, a variant of unknown clinical significance in one of the MMR genes or APC, and MSI or IHC suspect for LS while no MMR mutation was detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>To increase the number of LS families, 35 LS families outside our cohort, diagnosed after 2010, were also included in the analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Analysis of MSI and IHC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>MSI analysis was carried out with five markers for MSI as described previously; up to 2007 the Bethesda panel [28] was used and from 2007 onwards our center performs Promega pentaplex MSI analysis [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>IHC for MLH1, MSH2, MSH6 and PMS2 protein was performed as described previously [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Tumours without MSI or only a low degree of MSI and with all MMR proteins present, were considered MMR proficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Tumours showing a high degree of MSI and/or absence of one or more MMR proteins, were considered MMR deficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>MLH1 hypermethylation analysis was performed to distinguish between sporadic MMR deficient tumours and MMR deficient tumours suspect for LS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Germline mutation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Patients with MMR deficient tumours suspect for LS underwent germline mutation analysis of the gene indicated by IHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Germline mutation analysis of MLH1, MSH2 and MSH6 was performed by sequencing and multiplex ligation dependent probe amplification analyses. PMS2 mutation analysis was performed as described elsewhere [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Family classification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Tumour characteristics, age at diagnosis, results of molecular diagnostics and germline mutation analysis, and a detailed family history were collected from medical records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In every family the patient in whom MSI and/or IHC was analysed, was labelled the index patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>If more than one family member was screened for LS, the youngest CRC patient analysed was considered the index patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Index patients with MMR proficient tumours or sporadic MMR deficient tumours, were labelled non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Families identified with a pathogenic MMR mutation were labelled LS families. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Prediction models </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For each index patient the probability of carrying a LS mutation according to MMRpredict and PREMM5 was calculated as previously described [18, 20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For PREMM5, the equation was slightly different from the published equation, based on personal communications with F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Kastrinos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>See Supplemental Material (Appendix 1) for the corrected PREMM5 equation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using SPSS statistical software version 21.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Differences between mutation carriers and non-mutation carriers were compared using the Chi square test or Fishers’ exact test for frequencies, and by using the Mann Whitney U test for continuous data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>These analysis were also performed to compare PMS2 mutation carriers with non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>P values &lt; 0.01 were considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Receiver operating characteristic curves were created for MMRpredict and PREMM5 by plotting the true positive rate (sensitivity) against the false positive rate (1- specificity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Performance of MMRpredict and PREMM5 was evaluated by the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We compared the AUC of PREMM5 and MMRpredict for LS patients in general and for the different MMR genes specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity and specificity were calculated for cut-offs previously indicated by the developers of the models (5, 10, 20 and 40%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>These values were compared with the sensitivity and specificity of the revised Bethesda guidelines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Model updating </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Location of CRC is included in MMRpredict, but not in the PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To update the PREMM5 model, we used a previously proposed framework to update multinomial logistic regression models [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We extended the PREMM5 model using recalibration and extension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The PREMM5 model contains four linear predictors, each contributing weights to the probability of carrying a mutation in MLH1, MSH2 (or TACSTD1), MSH6 and PMS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The coefficients of the linear predictors were constrained such that the linear predictor only contributed to the calculation of the corresponding mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Since the original PREMM5 model was developed on a population with no MSH6 mutation carriers with two or more CRCs, we developed two adaptations of the PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>First we recalibrated the PREMM5 model and re-estimated the coefficient of the predictor ‘Two or more CRCs’ in the linear predictor for MSH6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In the second adaptation we also added side of CRC as an additional predictor to the original PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Discriminative ability of the prediction models was quantified using the AUC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Calculations were done using R software (version 3.3.0), with estimation of the coefficients in the updated PREMM5 model using the VGAM package. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Validation of the extended PREMM5 model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For external validation of the extended PREMM5 model, we used a cohort of 376 CRC patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Of these patients, 218 were patients with MMR proficient CRC, that where analysed in the Erasmus Medical Center Rotterdam outside the dates of our initial cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>LS patients (n = 158) in our validation cohort were CRC patients from Leiden University Medical Center in whom an MMR mutation was found and with known location of CRC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>For all patients of the validation cohort we calculated the probability of carrying an MMR mutation according to the original PREMM5 model and the extended model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The performance of both models were evaluated by comparing the AUC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A total of 734 index patients were included in the study; 346 (47%) were male and mean age at time of diagnosis was 53 years (± 13 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Overall, 569 (78%) patients fulfilled the revised Bethesda guidelines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Of the 734 index patients, 83 (11%) were diagnosed with a LS mutation; 23 MLH1, 17 MSH2, 31 MSH6 and 12 PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Patient characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Patient characteristics for mutation-positive and mutation-negative patients are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Significantly more mutation carriers developed multiple CRCs (21 vs. 10%, p = 0.005) and multiple LS-associated cancers in general (13 vs. 4%, p = 0.002) than non-mutation-carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>CRC patients carrying an MMR mutation had a younger age of onset (49 vs. 53 years, p = 0.002) and more often had proximal CRCs (64 vs. 28%, p &lt; 0.001) than non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Among women, the frequency of EC was higher for mutation carriers than for non-mutation carriers (41 vs. 3%, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In the mutation positive group, first and second degree relatives developed CRC at a younger age than in the mutation negative group (50 vs. 64 years, p &lt; 0.001 and 47 vs. 62 years, p = 0.008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>First degree relatives of mutation carriers had higher rates of EC than relatives of non-mutation carriers (19 vs. 5%, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Table 1Index characteristics and family history by mutation status (n = 734)Mutation negative, % (n)Mutation positive, % (n)P valuen65183Revised Bethesda guidelines76% (494)90% (75)0.003Index characteristics Male gender47% (305)49% (41)0.66  CRC   Age CRC (median, IQR)53 years [45–62]49 years [39–59]0.002   Proximal CRC28% (185)64% (53)&lt; 0.001   ≥ 2 CRCs10% (66)21% (17)0.005  Endometrial cancer3% (11)41% (17)&lt; 0.001   Age EC (median, IQR)55 years [50–75]54 years [49–57]0.18 Multiple LS cancers4% (27)13% (11)0.002First degree relatives CRC55% (358)51% (42)0.45  ≥ 2 FDRs with CRC16% (107)17% (14)0.92  Age CRC (median, IQR)64 years [55–71]50 years [43–57]&lt; 0.001 Endometrial cancer5% (35)19% (16)&lt; 0.001  ≥ 2 FDRs with EC0.6% (4)2% (2)0.14  Age EC (median, IQR)55 years [50–64]50 years [45–57]0.25 Other LS cancers22% (142)19% (16)0.60Second degree relatives CRC33% (212)35% (29)0.66  ≥ 2 SDRs with CRC12% (81)12% (10)0.92  Age CRC (median, IQR)62 years [50–74]47 years [38–64]0.008 Endometrial cancer3% (22)7% (6)0.12  ≥ 2 SDRs with EC0.3% (2)2% (2)0.07  Age EC (median, IQR)70 years [50–76]49 years [44–51]0.13 Other LS cancers16% (104)18% (15)0.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Discriminative ability of prediction models </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Overall, PREMM5 predicted higher probabilities of carrying a LS mutation than MMRpredict (median score 0.06 vs. 0.03, Supplemental Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For mutation carriers, risk scores varied from 0.02 to 0.99 for PREMM5 and from 0.002 to 0.99 for MMRpredict. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Both prediction models could fairly discriminate between index patients with and without an MMR mutation.(Fig. 1) PREMM5 and MMRpredict had similar overall performance (AUC 0.72 [95% CI 0.66–0.79] vs. 0.73 [95% CI 0.66–0.79]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>For MLH1 and MSH2 mutation carriers, both prediction models performed well, with AUC of 0.80 [95% CI 0.71–0.89] and 0.83 [95% CI 0.73–0.94] for PREMM5 and AUC of 0.79 [95% CI 0.69–0.89 and 0.67–0.91] for MMRpredict. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Both models had a fair discriminative power for MSH6 mutation carriers (AUC of 0.69 [95% CI 0.58–0.80] for PREMM5 and AUC of 0.66 [95% CI 0.56–0.76] for MMRpredict). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>MMRpredict still had fair performance for PMS2 mutation carriers (AUC of 0.72 [95% CI 0.57–0.87]), while PREMM5 failed to discriminate PMS2 mutation carriers from non-mutation carriers at all with an AUC of 0.51 [95% CI 0.35–0.66]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Fig. 1Performance of PREMM5 and MMRpredict in a clinical setting for all mutation carriers and for individual MMR mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity and specificity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Using a cut-off of 5% for both prediction models, PREMM5 had a higher sensitivity than MMRpredict (78 vs. 70%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This higher sensitivity came at the expense of a lower specificity (46 vs. 67%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>For PREMM5, using a cut-off of 5%, resulted in a sensitivity for MLH1 and MSH2 mutations of 88 and 91%, while the sensitivity for MSH6 mutation carriers was 74% and the sensitivity for PMS2 mutation carriers was only 50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>For MMRpredict, at a 5% cut-off sensitivity for MLH1 and MSH2 mutation carriers were 74 and 77%, while sensitivity for PMS2 as well as MSH6 mutation carriers were 65 and 67%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>For both models, using a cut-off of ≥ 20% failed to identify over 50% of the mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity of the revised Bethesda guidelines decreased from 96% for MLH1 mutation carriers to 83% for PMS2 mutation carriers (Supplemental Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Overall, the revised Bethesda guidelines had a sensitivity of 90% with a specificity of 24%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In order to reach the same sensitivity, PREMM5 and MMRpredict had a similar specificity (25%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>PMS2 mutation carriers versus non-mutation carriers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Mutation carriers differed significantly from non-mutation carriers in many ways (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In contrast, there were almost no significant differences between PMS2 mutation carriers and non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Only one significant difference remained; PMS2 mutation carriers more often had proximal CRC than patients without an MMR mutation (83 vs. 28%, p &lt; 0.001) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Table 2Index characteristics and family history for PMS2 mutation carriers compared with non-mutation carriersMutation negative, % (n)PMS2 mutation positive, % (n)P valuen65112Revised Bethesda guidelines76% (494)83% (10)0.74Index characteristics Male gender47% (305)50% (6)0.83  CRC   Age CRC (median, IQR)53 years [45–62]46 years [40–61]0.21   Proximal CRC28% (185)83% (10)&lt; 0.001   ≥ 2 CRCs10% (66)8% (1)1.0  Endometrial cancer3% (11)0% (0)1.0   Age EC (median, IQR)55 years [50–75]  Multiple LS cancers4% (27)0% (0)1.0First degree relatives CRC55% (358)42% (5)0.36  ≥ 2 FDRs with CRC16% (107)8% (1)0.70  Age CRC (median, IQR)64 years [55–71]62 years [45–90]0.68 Endometrial cancer5% (35)17% (2)0.14  ≥ 2 FDRs with EC0.6% (4)8% (1)0.88  Age EC (median, IQR)55 years [50–64]37 years [–]0.24 Other LS cancers22% (142)8% (1)0.48Second degree relatives CRC33% (212)17% (2)0.35  ≥ 2 SDRs with CRC12% (81)8% (1)1.0  Age CRC (median, IQR)62 years [50–74]39 years [39–]0.12 Endometrial cancer3% (22)8% (1)0.35  ≥ 2 SDRs with EC0.3% (2)8% (1)0.05  Age EC (median, IQR)70 years [50–76]49 years [–]0.67 Other LS cancers16% (104)17% (2)1.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Improvement of the PREMM5 model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Since location of CRC was the only significant difference between PMS2 mutation carriers and non-mutation carriers, we incorporated this variable in the PREMM5 model, aiming to improve the prediction model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For PMS2 mutation carriers, the extended PREMM5 model had considerably better predictions than the original PREMM55 model (AUC 0.77 [95% CI 0.63–0.90] vs. 0.51 [95% CI 0.35–0.66]) (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>At a 5% cut-off, the new PREMM5 model identified 5/6 PMS2 mutation carriers that would have been missed by PREMM5 and 3/4 PMS2 mutation carriers that would have been missed by MMRpredict at the same cut-off. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Fig. 2Performance of PREMM5 and the extended PREMM5 model in a clinical setting for all mutation carriers and for individual MMR mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Adding tumour location also improved the performance of PREMM5 for identifying MLH1 (AUC 0.92 [95% CI 0.88–0.97] vs. 0.80 [95% CI 0.71–0.89]) and MSH6 (AUC 0.75 [95% CI 0.65–0.84] vs. 0.69 [95% CI 0.58–0.80]) mutation carriers (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, performance for MSH2 mutation carriers slightly decreased (AUC 0.80 [95% CI 0.69–0.91] vs. 0.83 [95% CI 0.73–0.94]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Overall, the adjusted PREMM5 model performed better than the original PREMM5 model (AUC 0.81 [95% CI 0.76–0.86] vs. 0.72 [95% CI 0.66–0.79]) and MMRpredict (AUC 0.81 vs. 0.73 [95% CI 0.66–0.79]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The adjusted prediction model can be found as supplemental material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>At a 5% cut-off, sensitivity of the extended PREMM5 model was higher than the sensitivity of the original PREMM5 model (92 vs. 78%) with similar specificity (45 vs. 46%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity and specificity of the extended PREMM5 model at a 5% cut off were both higher than those of the revised Bethesda guidelines (sensitivity 92 vs. 90% and specificity 45 vs. 24%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Validation of the extended PREMM5 model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In our validation cohort, 60% of the patients were male and median age was 55 years (IQR 45–63 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The cohort included 31 MLH1, 26 MSH2, 28 MSH6 and 73 PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Similar to the results in the initial cohort, the extended PREMM5 model had better predictions than the original PREMM5 model for PMS2 mutation carriers (AUC 0.90 [95% CI 0.86–0.94] vs. 0.82 [95% CI 0.76–0.87]) and overall (AUC 0.92 [95% CI 0.89–0.95] vs. 0.87 [95% CI 0.84–0.91]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Performance for MLH1, MSH2 and MSH6 mutation carriers was also slightly better for the extended PREMM5 model than for the original PREMM5 model (AUC 0.97 [95% CI 0.94–1.00] vs. 0.95 [95% CI 0.91–0.99] for MLH1,0.97 [95% CI 0.93–1.00] vs. 0.96 [95% CI 0.92–0.99] for MSH2 and 0.86 [95% CI 0.97–0.93] vs. 0.85 [95% CI 0.77–0.93] for MSH6 mutation carriers). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The results of our study indicate that while the models MMRpredict and PREMM5 can adequately predict whether an individual is likely to have Lynch syndrome, they fail to identify PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The performance of the PREMM5 model improved considerably by adding the location of CRC to the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In our clinical cohort of 734 CRC patients as well as in a validation cohort of 376 CRC patients, this extended PREMM5 model not only identified PMS2 mutation carriers more accurately, its overall performance was also better than the original PREMM5 model and the MMRpredict model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Our results are in line with those of previous studies, where the PREMM1,2,6 model had a slightly better overall performance than MMRpredict [22, 32, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The first PREMM model, PREMM1,2 also performed better than MMRpredict in several studies [23, 24], but had similar [25, 26] or less accurate [21] predictions in other studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>A recent meta-analysis also found pooled AUCs to be higher for the PREMM model than for MMRpredict (AUC 0.84 vs. 0.81) [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Although PREMM5 had better overall predictions, MMRpredict had a better performance for PMS2 mutation carriers specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>An explanation for this could be that the location of CRC is incorporated in the MMRpredict model but not in the PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Proximal location of CRC is a known predictor for Lynch syndrome and in our cohort was the only significant difference between PMS2 mutation carriers and non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>After adding this new variable to the existing PREMM55 model, this new model performed better than MMRpredict for PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The extended PREMM55 model also performed better than the original model for MLH1, MSH2 and MSH6 mutation carriers and had a better overall performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In our validation cohort, all AUCs were much higher than in our original cohort, including those for PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Selection of patients for analysis of MSI and IHC may have been less stringent at the Erasmus Medical Center Rotterdam than at the Leiden University Medical Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Therefore, mutation carriers in our validation cohort, who were all from Leiden University Medical Center, may have had a family history more suspect for Lynch syndrome than family history of the patients in our original cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This could explain the higher AUCs in the validation cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>However, in both cohorts we showed that the extended PREMM5 had better performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Prediction models for Lynch syndrome are not yet regularly used in current clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the US Multi-Society Task Force on Colorectal Cancer recommends genetic evaluation if an individual’s risk of carrying an MMR gene mutation is ≥ 5% according to one of the prediction models MMRpro, MMRpredict or PREMM [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The American guideline recommends that all CRC patients undergo routine screening for LS by analysis of MSI and IHC [34], while current European guidelines recommend such routine screening in at least all CRC patients up to 70 years of age [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>A recent study demonstrated that routine screening for LS without an age cut-off is not cost-effective [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>A strategy using prediction models might lower the cost of screening for LS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In fact, two cost-effectiveness analyses found that strategies including prediction models were more cost-effective than those involving direct tumour testing of all CRC patients, if these prediction models were perfectly implemented [36, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Additionally, prediction models could also be used in cases where no tumour tissue is available or where tumour tissue analysis failed, to assess whether an individual should be analysed for a germline MMR mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The US Multi-Society Task Force on Colorectal Cancer recommends the use of either PREMM, MMRpredict or MMRpro to assess the probability of an individual carrying an MMR mutation [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Since we did not include the MMRpro model in our analysis, we do not know how MMRpro would have performed in our cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>However, MMRpro is less useful in clinical practice since extensive family data is needed as input for the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Collection of this kind of data is very time consuming and therefore not suitable in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>PREMM5 and MMRpredict are web-based models that are easily accessible and therefore much easier to use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Also, multiple studies—including the recent meta-analysis—have shown MMRpro to have similar accuracy to PREMM1,2,6 [21–27, 32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Both PREMM5 and MMRpredict were far more accurate for MLH1 and MSH2 mutation carriers than for LS patients carrying a mutation in MSH6 or PMS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This finding is in line with a previous study that showed that carriers of mutations in MSH6 or PMS2 had lower risk scores than carriers of a mutation in MLH1 or MSH2 [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In our study, discrimination between non-mutation carriers and PMS2 mutation carriers was the least accurate, in line with its more limited penetrance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Around 15% of all Lynch syndrome cases are estimated to be caused by PMS2 mutations [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In our cohort, 14% (12/83) of the Lynch syndrome patients were PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, our study is the first to validate LS prediction models for PMS2 mutation carriers specifically since the development of the PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>At a 5% cut-off, our extended PREMM5 model was able to detect 5/6 PMS2 mutation carriers who would have been missed by the original PREMM5 model at the same cut-off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Identification of Lynch syndrome carriers is highly important, since this allows not only them, but also their family members carrying the same mutation, to undergo intensive surveillance in order to prevent the development of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Our new model would also identify more Lynch syndrome patients overall than the original PREMM5 model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The performance of prediction models can differ between high-risk settings and population-based cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Further validation studies should indicate whether our results can be generalized to settings with patients at low to median risk of having Lynch syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Since patients in our study cohort were all referred for genetic counselling, family histories were obtained in detail and in many cases also verified by medical documents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In other settings where patients are at lower risk of having Lynch syndrome, family history is not verified and might be less reliable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Therefore, prediction models should also be validated in population-based cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, in a meta-analysis, prediction models performed better in population-based cohorts than in clinic-based cohorts [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It is not known whether the current prediction models for Lynch syndrome are useful in non-Western populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In a recent study among Korean patients, PREMM1,2,6 was more accurate than MMRpro and MMRpredict, but still only reached an AUC of 0.71 [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>There was no association between tumour location and mutation status, so our extended PREMM5 model might not improve predictions in populations of non-Western ethnicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>However, germline analysis for PMS2 was not performed in the Korean study, so there might have been more mutation carriers in their cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Another non-Western population has been studied by Khan et al., who analysed the performance of prediction models in 15 African American patients [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In these patients, MMRpredict and PREMM1,2,6 both had a high AUC of 0.89. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>A main strength of our study was the large cohort, which consisted of more than 700 index patient including 83 Lynch syndrome patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Also, our cohort included patients with MSH6 and PMS2 mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Since 12 patients were identified as a PMS2 mutation carrier, we were able to evaluate the prediction models for each MMR mutation specifically, admittedly with considerable uncertainty [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we validated the extended PREMM5 model in a separate cohort of 376 patients including 73 PMS2 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A limitation of our study was that germline mutation analysis was not done for all index patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Patients who had microsatellite stable tumours with normal IHC were assumed to be non-mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, some of these patients might still have an MMR mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Also, the sample size per gene was still relatively small and it is unclear whether our results from a high-risk population apply to a population-based setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we have shown that although MMRpredict and PREMM5 can accurately predict an individual’s risk of carrying a causative MMR mutation, neither model is able to identify patients with PMS2 mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Adding the location of CRC to the PREMM5 model improves the performance of the model for PMS2 mutation carriers as well as its overall performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>These findings should be validated in large cohorts from population-based settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec19"><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Supplementary material 1 (DOCX 14 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Supplementary material 2 (DOCX 15 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Supplementary material 3 (DOCX 19 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s10689-017-0039-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We thank M Nielsen and JT Wijnen for their contribution in the data collection of this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>None of the authors declare a conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>1.LynchHTde la ChapelleAHereditary colorectal cancerN Engl J Med20033481091993210.1056/NEJMra012242<?supplied-pmid 12621137?>12621137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>2.WatsonPLynchHTExtracolonic cancer in hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancerCancer199371367768510.1002/1097-0142(19930201)71:3&lt;677::AID-CNCR2820710305&gt;3.0.CO;2-#<?supplied-pmid 8431847?>8431847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>3.de JongAEHendriksYMKleibeukerJHDecrease in mortality in Lynch syndrome families because of surveillanceGastroenterology2006130366567110.1053/j.gastro.2005.11.032<?supplied-pmid 16530507?>16530507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>4.JarvinenHJAarnioMMustonenHControlled 15-year trial on screening for colorectal cancer in families with hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancerGastroenterology2000118582983410.1016/S0016-5085(00)70168-5<?supplied-pmid 10784581?>10784581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>5.JarvinenHJRenkonen-SinisaloLAktan-CollanKPeltomakiPAaltonenLAMecklinJPTen years after mutation testing for Lynch syndrome: cancer incidence and outcome in mutation-positive and mutation-negative family membersJ Clin Oncol200927284793479710.1200/JCO.2009.23.7784<?supplied-pmid 19720893?>19720893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>6.AkiyamaYSatoHYamadaTGerm-line mutation of the hMSH6/GTBP gene in an atypical hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer kindredCancer Res1997571839203923<?supplied-pmid 9307272?>9307272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>7.BronnerCEBakerSMMorrisonPTMutation in the DNA mismatch repair gene homologue hMLH1 is associated with hereditary non-polyposis colon cancerNature1994368646825826110.1038/368258a0<?supplied-pmid 8145827?>8145827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>8.FishelRLescoeMKRaoMRThe human mutator gene homolog MSH2 and its association with hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancerCell19937551027103810.1016/0092-8674(93)90546-3<?supplied-pmid 8252616?>8252616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>9.NicolaidesNCPapadopoulosNLiuBMutations of two PMS homologues in hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancerNature19943716492758010.1038/371075a0<?supplied-pmid 8072530?>8072530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>10.NiessenRCHofstraRMWestersHGermline hypermethylation of MLH1 and EPCAM deletions are a frequent cause of Lynch syndromeGenes Chromosomes Cancer200948873774410.1002/gcc.20678<?supplied-pmid 19455606?>19455606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>11.AaltonenLASalovaaraRKristoPIncidence of hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer and the feasibility of molecular screening for the diseaseN Engl J Med1998338211481148710.1056/NEJM199805213382101<?supplied-pmid 9593786?>9593786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>12.de la ChapelleAMicrosatellite instabilityN Engl J Med2003349320921010.1056/NEJMp038099<?supplied-pmid 12867603?>12867603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>13.van LierMGWagnerAvan LeerdamMEA review on the molecular diagnostics of Lynch syndrome: a central role for the pathology laboratoryJ Cell Mol Med2010141–218119710.1111/j.1582-4934.2009.00977.x<?supplied-pmid 19929944?>19929944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>14.CrossDSRahmAKKauffmanTLUnderutilization of Lynch syndrome screening in a multisite study of patients with colorectal cancerGenet Med2013151293394010.1038/gim.2013.43<?supplied-pmid 23639899?>23639899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>15.JulieCTresalletCBrouquetAIdentification in daily practice of patients with Lynch syndrome (hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer): revised Bethesda guidelines-based approach versus molecular screeningAm J Gastroenterol2008103112825283510.1111/j.1572-0241.2008.02084.x<?supplied-pmid 18759827?>18759827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>16.Perez-CarbonellLRuiz-PonteCGuarinosCComparison between universal molecular screening for Lynch syndrome and revised Bethesda guidelines in a large population-based cohort of patients with colorectal cancerGut201261686587210.1136/gutjnl-2011-300041<?supplied-pmid 21868491?>21868491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>17.Van LierMGDe WiltJHWagemakersJJUnderutilization of microsatellite instability analysis in colorectal cancer patients at high risk for Lynch syndromeScand J Gastroenterol200944560060410.1080/00365520802706008<?supplied-pmid 19153873?>19153873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>18.BarnetsonRATenesaAFarringtonSMIdentification and survival of carriers of mutations in DNA mismatch-repair genes in colon cancerN Engl J Med2006354262751276310.1056/NEJMoa053493<?supplied-pmid 16807412?>16807412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>19.ChenSWangWLeeSPrediction of germline mutations and cancer risk in the Lynch syndromeJAMA2006296121479148710.1001/jama.296.12.1479<?supplied-pmid 17003396?>17003396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>20.KastrinosFUnoHUkaegbuCDevelopment and Validation of the PREMM5 Model for Comprehensive Risk Assessment of Lynch SyndromeJ Clin Oncol201735192165217210.1200/JCO.2016.69.6120<?supplied-pmid 28489507?>28489507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>21.GreenRCParfreyPSWoodsMOYounghusbandHBPrediction of Lynch syndrome in consecutive patients with colorectal cancerJ Natl Cancer Inst2009101533134010.1093/jnci/djn499<?supplied-pmid 19244167?>19244167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>22.KhanOBlancoAConradPPerformance of Lynch syndrome predictive models in a multi-center US referral populationAm J Gastroenterol2011106101822182710.1038/ajg.2011.200<?supplied-pmid 21747416?>21747416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>23.MonzonJGCreminCArmstrongLValidation of predictive models for germline mutations in DNA mismatch repair genes in colorectal cancerInt J Cancer20101264930939<?supplied-pmid 19653273?>19653273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>24.PouchetCJWongNChongGA comparison of models used to predict MLH1, MSH2 and MSH6 mutation carriersAnn Oncol200920468168810.1093/annonc/mdn686<?supplied-pmid 19164453?>19164453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>25.RamsoekhDvan LeerdamMEWagnerAKuipersEJSteyerbergEWMutation prediction models in Lynch syndrome: evaluation in a clinical genetic settingJ Med Genet2009461174575110.1136/jmg.2009.066589<?supplied-pmid 19541685?>19541685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>26.TresalletCBrouquetAJulieCEvaluation of predictive models in daily practice for the identification of patients with Lynch syndromeInt J Cancer201213061367137710.1002/ijc.26144<?supplied-pmid 21520036?>21520036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>27.WinAKMacinnisRJDowtyJGJenkinsMACriteria and prediction models for mismatch repair gene mutations: a reviewJ Med Genet2013501278579310.1136/jmedgenet-2013-101803<?supplied-pmid 23956446?>23956446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>28.BolandCRThibodeauSNHamiltonSRA National Cancer Institute Workshop on Microsatellite Instability for cancer detection and familial predisposition: development of international criteria for the determination of microsatellite instability in colorectal cancerCancer Res1998582252485257<?supplied-pmid 9823339?>9823339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>29.SuraweeraNDuvalAReperantMEvaluation of tumor microsatellite instability using five quasimonomorphic mononucleotide repeats and pentaplex PCRGastroenterology200212361804181110.1053/gast.2002.37070<?supplied-pmid 12454837?>12454837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>30.van der KliftHMTopsCMBikECQuantification of sequence exchange events between PMS2 and PMS2CL provides a basis for improved mutation scanning of Lynch syndrome patientsHum Mutat2010315578587<?supplied-pmid 20186688?>20186688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>31.Van HoordeKVergouweYTimmermanDVan HuffelSSteyerbergEWVan CalsterBAssessing calibration of multinomial risk prediction modelsStat Med201433152585259610.1002/sim.6114<?supplied-pmid 24549725?>24549725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>32.LeeSYKimDWShinYKValidation of prediction models for mismatch repair gene mutations in KoreansCancer Res Treat2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>33.Kastrinos F, Ojha RP, Leenen C et al. (2016) Comparison of prediction models for Lynch syndrome among individuals with colorectal cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>J Natl Cancer Inst. doi:10.1093/jnci/djv308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>34.GiardielloFMAllenJIAxilbundJEGuidelines on genetic evaluation and management of Lynch syndrome: a consensus statement by the US Multi-Society Task Force on Colorectal CancerGastroenterology2014147250252610.1053/j.gastro.2014.04.001<?supplied-pmid 25043945?>25043945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>35.VasenHFBlancoIAktan-CollanKRevised guidelines for the clinical management of Lynch syndrome (HNPCC): recommendations by a group of European expertsGut201362681282310.1136/gutjnl-2012-304356<?supplied-pmid 23408351?>23408351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>36.Barzi A, Sadeghi S, Kattan MW, Meropol NJ (2015) Comparative effectiveness of screening strategies for Lynch syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>J Natl Cancer Inst. doi:10.1093/jnci/djv005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>37.LadabaumUWangGTerdimanJStrategies to identify the Lynch syndrome among patients with colorectal cancer: a cost-effectiveness analysisAnn Intern Med20111552697910.7326/0003-4819-155-2-201107190-00002<?supplied-pmid 21768580?>21768580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>38.PalomakiGEMcClainMRMelilloSHampelHLThibodeauSNEGAPP supplementary evidence review: DNA testing strategies aimed at reducing morbidity and mortality from Lynch syndromeGenet Med2009111426510.1097/GIM.0b013e31818fa2db<?supplied-pmid 19125127?>19125127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>39.VergouweYSteyerbergEWEijkemansMJHabbemaJDSubstantial effective sample sizes were required for external validation studies of predictive logistic regression modelsJ Clin Epidemiol200558547548310.1016/j.jclinepi.2004.06.017<?supplied-pmid 15845334?>15845334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
