<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Appl Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur. J. Appl. Physiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Applied Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1439-6319</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1439-6327</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5306324</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27815705</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3495</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-016-3495-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Neural, biomechanical, and physiological factors involved in sex-related differences in the maximal rate of isometric torque development </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1583-0782</contrib-id><name><surname>Inglis</surname><given-names>J. Greig</given-names></name><address><phone>1-(905)-688-5550</phone><email>ginglis@brocku.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>Kyle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9318</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411793.9</institution-id><institution>Electromyographic Kinesiology Laboratory, Faculty of Applied Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Brock University, </institution></institution-wrap>1812 Sir Isaac Brock Way, St. Catharines, ON L2S 3A1 Canada </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Communicated by Toshio Moritani. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>117</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Recent research has reported that lower maximal rate of torque development (dτ/dt max) exhibited by females, relative to males, during knee extension can be accounted for by normalization to a maximal voluntary contraction (MVC); however, this was not seen in the upper limb. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Purpose </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The aim of the current work was to examine the contribution of maximum strength (τmax), twitch contraction time (CT), muscle fiber condition velocity (MFCV), and rate of muscle activation (Q30) to sex-differences in the dτ/dt max during maximal isometric dorsiflexion. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Thirty-eight participants (20 males; 18 females) performed both maximal voluntary and evoked isometric contractions of the tibialis anterior across 3 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Ten maximal compound muscle action potentials were elicited and subsequently followed by three, 5-s contractions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>From the recordings, MFCV, dτ/dt max, τmax, CT, electromechanical delay (EMD), root-mean squared (RMS) amplitude, peak-to-peak voltage (Vpp), and Q30 were calculated. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>An ANCOVA showed that τmax accounted for all the sex-differences in dτ/dt max (p = 0.96). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between groups with respect to MFCV, RMS amplitude, Vpp amplitude, or CT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>However, there was a significant sex-difference in dτ/dt max, τmax, and Q30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Females had longer evoked EMD times compared with males (15.69 ± 10.57 ms versus 9.95 ± 3.46 ms; p = 0.01), but the voluntary EMD times were not different. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The current research supports the work by Hannah et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Exp Physiol 97:618–629, (2012) that normalization to MVC in the quadriceps is able to account for all sex-differences in rate of toque development in the lower limb. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Electromechanical delay</kwd><kwd>Muscle activation rate</kwd><kwd>Neural control</kwd><kwd>Strength testing</kwd><kwd>Surface electromyography</kwd><kwd>Muscle fiber conduction velocity</kwd><kwd>Contraction time</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Canadian Network for Research and Innovation in Machining Technology, Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (CA)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The rate of tension development has received increased attention as a critical aspect of dynamic muscle performance during activities of daily living (e.g., balance maintenance) and sport performance (Aagaard et al. 2002; LaRoche et al. 2010; Paasuke et al. 2001; Pijnapples et al. 2008; Schultz et al. 1997; Tillin et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>A number of studies have shown that there is an inextricable link between the ultimate strength of the muscle and its rate of tension development (Andersen and Aagaard 2006; Holtermann et al. 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, neural factors can also play an important role, as training-related increases in the maximal rate of tension development are associated with an increase in muscle activation at the onset of contraction (Van Cutsem et al. 1998; Van Cutsem and Duchateau 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Inglis et al. (2013) recently showed that neural factors also play a role in sex-differences in the maximal rate of tension development in the upper limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Maximum strength was used as a covariate and was only able to account for a portion of the sex-differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The addition of a second variable, the maximum rate of electromyographic (EMG) activity at the onset of contraction (Q30), was able to eliminate statistically significant sex-differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Given the inherent relationship between muscle strength and the maximum rate of tension development, few studies have explored additional mechanisms that would explain sex-differences in the maximal rate of tension development (Aagaard et al. 2002; Andersen and Aagaard 2006; Folland et al. 2014; Van Cutsem et al. 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, sex-differences in lower extremity musculoskeletal injury rates (DiStefano et al. 2015) and falls incidences (Hess and Woollacott 2005; Stevens and Sogolow 2005) may be linked back to this critical aspect of muscle contraction (Bento et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Hannah et al. (2012) explored potential neural and biomechanical factors involved in sex-differences in the maximal rate of tension development in the quadriceps, in addition to maximum strength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Twitch properties, electromechanical delay, and muscle activation using surface EMG (sEMG) were also assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the more general findings for the relationship between maximum strength and the rate of tension development, when the peak rate of tension development was normalized with respect to maximum isometric strength of the muscle, the sex-differences were completely eliminated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The results by Hannah et al. (2012) in the lower limb are contrary to the finding of Inglis et al. (2013) who showed a role for neural factors in the upper limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>It may be hypothesized that since males and females were more comparable in absolute strength in the quadriceps (Δ33%) than the biceps (Δ55.5%; Inglis et al. 2013), strength may entirely explain sex-differences in the rate of tension development in the lower limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the difference in maximum strength between males and females in the upper limb observed by Inglis et al. (2013) was much greater (Δ55.5%), possibly allowing for additional factors, such as the rate of muscle activation, to play a role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Inglis et al. (2013) explored the possibility that the interpretation of the results may differ based on normalization to maximum voluntary strength versus the use of a covariate approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>It was found that normalization to maximum voluntary strength also failed to account for all sex-differences in the maximal rate of tension development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Since there is a strong relationship between maximum strength and the rate of tension development, sex-differences may be accounted for by maximum strength only when the two groups are ‘more’ comparable with respect to maximal strength as exists in the lower limb compared with the upper limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>For example, it has been shown that males and females are more comparable in maximal isometric dorsiflexion strength (Δ28.9%) and identical with respect to root-mean-square (RMS) sEMG magnitude (Heyward et al. 1986; Hoffman et al. 1979; Lenhardt et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, Lenhardt et al. 2009 did not assess the maximum rate of torque development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The 28.9% strength difference between the sexes is consistent with Holmbäck et al. (2003) who concluded that muscle cross-sectional area was the principal determinant of dorsiflexion strength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In general, the muscle cross-sectional area of the TA in males is only 20% larger than that for females (Holmbäck et al. 2003; Jaworowski et al. 2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this paper was to determine if sex-differences in the maximum rate of isometric dorsiflexion torque development are determined by maximum isometric dorsiflexion torque alone or other factors as observed for the upper limb where the strength differences are more pronounced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Based on the work of Hannah et al. (2012), it was hypothesized that maximum isometric strength would account for sex-differences in the maximum rate of torque development in the TA, because males and females are more comparable in maximum isometric strength in the lower limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Studying mechanisms behind sex-differences in distal muscles that are responsible for balance and explosive activity can guide specific training interventions or rehabilitation techniques. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>A power analysis was performed prior to data collection based on research by Lenhardt et al. (2009), showing that a subject pool of 18 males and females was sufficient to show differences in the rate of muscle activation (Q30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>However, to protect against subject drop out, 40 subjects (males and females) were recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Pre-tension on the load cell was observed in two female subjects, so their data was removed from the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Thus, 38 healthy Brock University Kinesiology students (20 males and 18 females) were analyzed in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The participants were free of any orthopedic or neuromuscular disorders, right leg dominant, and provided written informed consent prior to study participation in accordance with the Brock University Research Ethics Board guidelines (REB-02-284). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Each participant was familiarized with the Electromyographic Kinesiology Laboratory prior to the first testing session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Prior to testing, participants were asked about their history of physical activity and weight training (years of experience) as well as the duration (hours per week and per day) and the percentage of weight training focusing on the upper body or lower body. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Experimental setup and scheduling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All testing was performed as the participant sat in a custom built testing chair designed to isolate the dorsiflexors during maximal isometric contractions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Participants sat with their hip and knee joints secured at 90° of flexion and the ankle joint secured at 110° of plantar flexion (Inglis et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Slight plantar flexion was chosen as previous research has shown that a certain degree of plantar flexion produces a maximal torque and 110° may place the TA closer to optimal length for both maximal evoked and voluntary dorsiflexion torque production, which considers the lever arm length (Marsh et al. 1981). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>A load cell (JR3, Woodland, CA, USA) was secured under the foot plate of which the foot was restrained by a minimally padded steel bar located proximal to the metatarsals for all torque recordings (Christie et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>There were 3 days of testing to assess the reliability of the measures as participants can exhibit a learning effect during maximal strength assessment (Green et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>On each day, participants were asked to perform the same tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>These tasks included both voluntary isometric maximal dorsiflexion contractions and maximal evoked isometric torque. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Each of the three testing days was separated by at least 48 h to avoid any complications, which may arise as a result of fatigue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>sEMG recordings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Participants lay supine on a gurney, so that the most prominent TA motor point may be electrically identified using a metallic probe over the skin surface (Christie et al. 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The lowest possible current that produced a minimally visible twitch was taken as the motor point (Calder and Gabriel 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Following motor point identification, the recording areas were shaved, mildly abraded (NuPrep; Weaver and Co., Aurora, CO), and finally cleansed with alcohol to minimize skin–electrode input impedance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The sEMG recording electrode had three parallel stainless steel bars which resulted in two bipolar signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Each stainless steel bar was 1 mm in diameter, 10 mm long, and was mounted with an interbar distance of 5 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The recording electrode was prepared with double-sided adhesive tape, electrolyte gel (Signal Gel; Parker Laboratories, Inc., Fairfield, New Jersey), and placed in line with the muscle fibers, 1 cm distal to the motor point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Alignment and final placement of the electrodes for recording MFCV followed the procedures outlined in McIntosh and Gabriel (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Finally, a ground electrode (CF5000; Axelgaard) was placed on the lateral malleolus (McIntosh and Gabriel 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Electrode–skin input impedance (Grass EZM5, Astro-Med Inc., West Warwick, RI) was assessed before and after the experiment to ensure it remained below 10 kΩ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Skin temperature (Electrotherm TM99A; Cooper Instrument Corp., Middlefield, Connecticut) was also monitored before and after the experiment to verify that there was no change, which could affect the stability of the myoelectric signal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>sEMG was band-pass filtered (between 10 and 1000 Hz) and amplified (Grass P511; Astro-Med) to maximize the resolution on a 16-bit analog-to-digital converter (MI PCI-6052E; National Instruments, Austin, TX). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All signals were collected at 5000 Hz and acquired on a computer-based data acquisition system (DASYLab; DASYTEC National Instruments, Amherst, New Hampshire). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The data were stored on a PC (Celeron; Dell, Round Rock, Texas) for offline analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The data window for the sEMG analysis of the maximal voluntary contraction was 500 ms, terminating before the middle of the contraction (Inglis et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The sEMG signals were up-sampled to 25 kHz prior to calculating the cross-correlation coefficient to increase the time resolution of the action potential propagation (Farina and Merletti 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Muscle fiber conduction velocity calculation was based on the time delay identified by the peak of the cross-correlation function and the known interbar distance of 5 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The root-mean-square (RMS) amplitude of sEMG activity was also calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The rate of muscle activation was calculated by first rectifying the sEMG data and then numerically integrating the first 30 ms starting from the sEMG onset (Q30) that represents the rate of increase in the sEMG over the first 30 ms of muscle activity (Gottlieb et al. 1989). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Electromechanical delay (EMD) comprises an important portion of the rate of tension development phase of the contraction (Gabriel et al. 2001), where changes in motor unit activity patterns have been demonstrated to play a critical role in the maximal rate of torque development (Van Cutsem et al. 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Electromechanical delay was determined from the time lag between the onset of dorsiflexion torque and sEMG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>sEMG onset threshold was identified as the first point of the sEMG signal to rise above the 95% confidence interval for baseline noise and to remain above the 95% confidence interval for 20 ms (Di Fabio 1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Visual inspection was utilized to ensure the accuracy of the established threshold’s ability to detect either torque or sEMG onset (Inglis et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Evoked isometric compound muscle action potentials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Compound muscle action potentials were evoked through a cathode stimulating electrode placed over the fibular nerve along with an anode placed on the medial condyle of the fibula to evoke an isometric dorsiflexion twitch contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The evoked potentials were monitored on an oscilloscope (VC-6525; Hitachi) to ensure that a consistent maximal response had been achieved for ten stimulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The peak-to-peak voltage (Vpp) was extracted from the CMAP, while contraction time (CT) was obtained from the torque-time curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Evoked contraction time (CT) was calculated from the time difference between the CMAP onset to its time to peak tension (Dahmane et al. 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Contraction time is used in this paper to separate differences in the rate of torque development associated with voluntary control versus muscle fibers properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, it was important to determine if potential sex-difference in Q30 could be due to the initial differences in peripheral factors (MFCV, Vpp, or CT) or overall voluntary activation (RMS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Maximal voluntary isometric dorsiflexion contractions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>After the evoked contractions, a 15-min rest period was given. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Participants then performed three voluntary maximal effort isometric dorsiflexion contractions by pulling with the top of their foot against a padded metal plate while minimizing toe extension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>During the MVC’s, each participant was asked to contract “as hard and as fast as possible” with an emphasis on the “hard” (Sahaly et al. 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Each contraction lasted approximately 5 s in duration and was separated by a 5-min rest period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The force data were converted to torque values using the lever arm length, measured from the ankle joint to the metatarsals, where the load cell was located. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A target line was given which represented 110% of the previously determined maximal effort, which was identified in real time on an oscilloscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, during each voluntary contraction, the participants were verbally encouraged to surpass the target line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 shows a representative torque trace, rate of change in torque, and surface electromyographic activity of the tibialis anterior during a maximal effort dorsiflexion contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The manner in which the signals were collected is described below.Fig. 1Torque (τ) (dark grey), surface electromyographic activity (light grey), and the rate of torque development (black) over the first second of a trial for a male representative subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The first vertical line (black) represents the EMG onset; the second vertical line (grey) represents the torque onset </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Maximum rate of torque development was calculated from the equation provided by Andersen and Aagaard (2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The calculation involves determining the slope (Δτ/Δt) over non-overlapping, successive 20 ms intervals, starting from the onset of the torque-time curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The onset was determined as the point in the signal where the rate of change surpassed 1% of the maximal rate of torque development (dτ/dt max). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The dτ/dt max was then the maximum slope, which is synonymous with the ‘peak’ of the dτ/dt curve (Gabriel et al. 2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was conducted in two stages: first, to evaluate the reliability of the criterion measures using the intraclass correlational analysis of variance technique for males and females, separately; second, significant differences between males and females (Sex) in the magnitude of the means, and changes in the means across test sessions (Days), and the interaction (Sex × Days) was evaluated using a repeated-measures analysis of covariance to determine the impact of potential variables that may underlie sex-differences in the rate of torque development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Intraclass correlation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Intraclass correlational analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to evaluate the reliability of the criterion measures for each group, which requires the consideration of both the stability of means and the consistency of scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A one-way repeated-measures ANOVA was used to assess the stability of means across the three test sessions, while the intraclass correlation coefficient (model 2,k) was used to evaluate the consistency of scores within subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>We adopted the convention delineated by Fleiss (1986) where an intraclass correlation coefficient (R) below 0.40 indicates poor reliability, between 0.40 and 0.75 is fair reliability, while values greater than 0.75 represent excellent reliability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The magnitude of the intraclass correlation coefficient was further evaluated using the standard error of measurement (SEM) within an individual (Green et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The SEM was calculated as the square of the mean square error for the ANOVA table using the variables ‘Sex’ and ‘Day’ (Weir and Cockerham 1984). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The intrasubject coefficient of variation was the grand mean across the three test sessions divided by the SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A repeated-measures analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was then used to determine the impact of a covariate on significant differences between males and females with respect to the dτ/dt max development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Maximal torque and Q30 were the primary variables of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>However, EMD, MFCV, and twitch contraction time (CT) were also explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>All statistical procedures were performed using SAS statistical software (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC) with alpha set at the 0.05 probability level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The means ± standard deviations (SD) for each measure are reported below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Participant characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The means and standard deviations for the participant’s characteristics are given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were seen in all anthropometric measurements between males and females (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>However, there were no significant differences in hours per week engaged in physical activity or weight lifting (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The grand means and standard deviations for the criterion measures across the three test sessions for males and females are presented in tables for the voluntary and evoked contractions (see Tables 2, 3).Table 1Demographic characteristics of the study participantsMeasureFemales (N = 18) M ± SDMales (N = 20) M ± SDDifference%Age (years)24 ± 3.324 ± 2.40Height (m)1.6 ± 0.11.8 ± 0.111.1*Mass (kg)56.5 ± 8.579.7 ± 3.929.1*Body mass index (kg/m2)21.4 ± 2.224.4 ± 0.812.3*Foot length (cm)23.7 ± 0.728.5 ± 1.516.8*Leg length (cm)39.2 ± 1.847.3 ± 2.317.1*Leg girth (cm)37.0 ± 1.740.4 ± 1.98.4*Physical activity (hours/week)7.5 ± 3.49.3 ± 2.219.4Weight-lifting (hours/week)4.4 ± 3.75.5 ± 2.820.0Significant differences were set at a p &lt; 0.05 level and are indicated with * Table 2Data under the voluntary condition Female vMFCV (m/s)vEMD (ms)vRTDpk (Nm/s)vTorque (Nm)Q30 (mV x s)RMS (mV)Test Day(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)15.16 ± 1.6137.19 ± 11.0681.15 ± 33.6529.10 ± 7.967.90 ± 5.270.21 ± 0.1025.28 ± 1.4033.86 ± 10.0782.74 ± 36.0229.17 ± 7.788.26 ± 6.970.21 ± 0.1335.33 ± 1.6927.09 ± 5.3091.43 ± 34.8827.10 ± 6.618.20 ± 6.740.17 ± 0.11Grand5.26 ± 1.5532.71 ± 9.94*85.11 ± 34.5128.46 ± 7.398.12 ± 6.260.20 ± 0.11 SEM 0.678.0210.352.763.060.03 R 0.810.350.910.860.760.92 Male Test Day14.92 ± 0.9932.92 ± 12.48160.03 ± 70.2957.31 ± 17.125.80 ± 2.910.18 ± 0.1125.13 ± 1.2532.52 ± 12.08157.04 ± 70.0058.52 ± 21.694.83 ± 3.210.18 ± 0.1334.70 ± 1.0933.08 ± 13.74142.01 ± 82.0156.97 ± 20.545.26 ± 2.730.17 ± 0.08Grand4.92 ± 1.1132.84 ± 12.57153.03 ± 73.4757.60 ± 19.555.30 ± 3.010.18 ± 0.11 SEM 0.556.1230.298.061.880.06 R 0.760.700.830.830.610.72 Percent Difference 6.50.444.4*50.6*34.7*10Means (M) and standard deviations (SD) for voluntary muscle fiber conduction velocity (vMFCV), voluntary electromechanical delay (vEMD), voluntary peak rate of torque development (vRTDpk), voluntary maximum torque (vTorque), voluntary rate of EMG increase over the first 30 ms (Q30), and voluntary root-mean squared amplitude (RMS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were set at a p&lt;0.05 level and are indicated with * Table 3Data under the evoked condition Female eMFCV (m/s)eEMD (ms)eRTDpk (Nm/s)eTorque (Nm)Vpp (mV)CT (ms)Test Day(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)(M ± SD)14.22 ± 1.7616.71 ± 11.2146.07 ± 18.412.59 ± 1.432.17 ± 0.9277.20 ± 17.6324.11 ± 0.9915.38 ± 10.9846.75 ± 18.432.69 ± 1.282.22 ± 0.9180.74 ± 12.1834.34 ± 1.5114.97 ± 10.0246.25 ± 14.432.68 ± 1.102.07 ± 0.9869.21 ± 22.78Grand4.22 ± 1.4315.69 ± 10.5746.36 ± 16.872.66 ± 1.252.16 ± 0.9275.72 ± 18.37 SEM 0.504.254.130.280.364.41 R 0.880.840.940.950.850.91 Male Test Day14.33 ± 1.5010.57 ± 3.30106.48 ± 39.665.89 ± 2.332.59 ± 1.1468.65 ± 7.4724.71 ± 1.6610.17 ± 4.56101.01 ± 41.675.54 ± 2.482.51 ± 1.1379.55 ± 11.9834.17 ± 0.999.12 ± 2.06104.50 ± 35.125.86 ± 1.992.73 ± 1.0176.60 ± 8.09Grand4.40 ± 1.409.95 ± 3.46104.00 ± 38.315.77 ± 2.242.61 ± 1.0874.93 ± 10.33 SEM 0.762.278.570.450.402.32 R 0.710.570.950.960.870.64 Percent Differences 4.136.6*55.4*53.9*17.20.01Means (M) and standard deviations (SD) for evoked muscle fiber conduction velocity (eMFCV), evoked electromechanical delay (eEMD), evoked peak rate of torque development (eRTDpk), evoked maximum torque (eTorque), evoked peak-peak voltage (Vpp), and the evoked contraction time (CT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were set at a p&lt;0.05 level and are indicated with * </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Reliability analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows that the consistency of scores within subjects for the criterion measures obtained during the voluntary contractions for females was excellent (R = 0.76–92) except for EMD which had an intraclass correlation coefficient of R = 0.35 (see Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Female participants exhibited a 27.2% reduction in EMD from session 1 to session 3 (F [2, 51] = 5.83, p = 0.0045). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The lack of stability, as assess by the repeated-measures ANOVA, resulted in a reduced intraclass correlation coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, the intrasubject coefficient of variation (Grand Mean/SEM) was 24.5%, which was deemed acceptable for further analyses (Green et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The means of the criterion measures generated during voluntary contractions as shown in Table 2 were highly stable across test sessions in males, while the consistency of scores within subjects ranged from fair to excellent (R = 0.61–83). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The higher intrasubject variation (56.8%) for males Q30 resulted in a lower intraclass correlation coefficient (R = 0.61), but was still acceptable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The same was true for the criterion measures generated during evoked contractions (R = 0.85–95) and Table 3 shows that consistency of scores within subjects for the criterion measures obtained during the evoked contractions in males ranged from fair to excellent (R = 0.57–96). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The lowest intraclass correlation coefficient was for EMD, but it had an intrasubject coefficient of variation of only 22.8%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>While there was a slight decrease in the means across sessions, a limited range of scores contributed to a decreased intraclass correlation coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Thus, the measure was still deemed acceptable for further analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Between groups analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>A repeated-measures ANOVA revealed a significant difference between groups and across days for voluntary maximal dorsiflexion isometric torque (F [1, 36] = 45.97, p = 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Males had on average a 50.6% greater torque output than females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The difference between males and females with respect to the maximum rate of torque development was similar in magnitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The maximum rate of torque development was 44.6% greater in males than for females (F [1, 36] = 16.46, p = 0.0003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In contrast, females had a 34.7% greater rate of increase in muscle activation as assessed by Q30 (F [1, 36] = 4.30, p = 0.0454). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between males and females with respect to EMD, RMS amplitude, or MFCV (F [1, 36] = 0.00, p = 0.9635; F [1, 36] = 0.31, p = 0.5834; F [1, 36] = 0.86, p = 0.3598, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Similar to the voluntary contractions, maximal evoked dorsiflexion torque was 53.9% greater for males than for females (F [1, 36] = 28.52, p = 0.001), and males also had a comparably greater maximum rate of torque development of 55.4% (F [1, 36] = 13.99, p = 0.0006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The EMD was 36.6% shorter for males than for females during the evoked contractions (F [1, 36] = 7.02, p = 0.0119). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MFCV, evoked CT, and Vpp of the CMAP were not significantly different between groups (F [1, 36] = 0.22, p = 0.6451; F [1, 36] = 0.03, p = 0.8589; F [1, 36] = 2.42, p = 0.1288, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Analysis of covariance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>When maximal torque was used as the covariate in the repeated-measures ANCOVA for the maximum rate of torque development, the difference between means decreased to 1.2% (F [1, 36] = 0.01, p = 0.9264). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The rate of increase in muscle activation (Q30) was not assessed as a covariate, because females were actually greater than males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The only other significant difference between males and females was EMD during evoked contractions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>However, evoked EMD had little impact as a covariate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Sex-related differences in the maximum rate of torque development were reduced to 33.8%, which were still significant (F [1, 36] = 8.27, p = 0.0067). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The main finding of the current work was that maximum torque was able to account for almost all of the sex-related differences in the maximum rate of torque development, as the percent difference in least-square means was reduced to 1.2% when using maximum torque as a covariate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>There also were no significant differences between males and females in sEMG RMS amplitude magnitude as observed by Lenhardt et al. (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The absence of sex-differences in the sEMG signal amplitude, Vpp, and CT may reflect a comparable number of hours per week of training for the two groups (Aagaard et al. 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Contraction time was used in the study to determine if differences in the maximal rate of torque development were associated with either descending voluntary control or peripheral factors associated with muscle composition (Close 1972). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Based on the fact, no sex-related differences in the CT (0.01%) were found suggests that the two groups were also similar with respect to muscle fiber composition, which is consistent with other research (Hicks and McCartney 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Based on the work of Lenhardt et al. (2009), it was expected that males and females would be more comparable in maximum strength in the lower limb than the upper limb, which is consistent with other studies on sex-differences in maximum strength (Heyward et al. 1986; Hoffman et al. 1979). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Instead, a 50.6% difference was observed, which was the same order of magnitude as previously observed for the upper limb (Inglis et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>One reason may be related to differences in the cross-sectional area (CSA) of the TA in the present sample versus that of Lenhardt et al. (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Although CSA was not directly measured, the males and females in this study had a larger difference in lower leg girth (8.4%) than the 5.2% observed by Lenhardt et al. (2009), which may suggest a larger difference in TA CSA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The large difference in maximum strength between males and females was associated with a comparably large difference in the maximum rate of isometric dorsiflexion torque development (44.6%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Greater co-activation of the antagonist muscle group in females could contribute to both lower maximum strength and rate of torque development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Macaluso et al. (2002) showed that females may use greater antagonist co-activation to stabilize the joint due to greater joint laxity, smaller agonist musculature, and potentially lower quality muscle mass (torque/CSA), as has been seen in older versus younger adults (Solomonow et al. 1988; Thelen et al. 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, antagonist co-activation was not measured in this study as it is markedly lower during isometric contractions compared with dynamic contractions and particularly lower when the muscle is placed in a shortened position as in this study (Pasquet et al. 2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>There were several novel findings in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>First, there were no significant differences between males and females with respect to MFCV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This result may be due to comparable muscle fiber diameters between the sexes, which is a large determinant of MFCV (Lange et al. 2002; Lindstrom and Magnusson 1977; Merletti et al. 1995; Nishihara et al. 2005; Zwarts 1989). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that type I (slow twitch) fibers are situated predominately in the anterior portion of the TA (Henriksson-Larsén et al. 1983). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it is a general result that, while males have larger fiber diameters than females, the type I muscle fiber diameters in females are larger than their type II muscle fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The small interelectrode distance (5 mm) will record from a small pick-up volume that encapsulates these superficial type I fibers of the TA, which are comparable in muscle fiber diameter between the sexes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>A second novel finding is that there were pronounced sex-differences in Q30 that were not evident in either the voluntary (RMS) or evoked (Vpp) sEMG magnitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Females were significantly greater than males with respect to the rate of muscle activation as assessed by Q30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The difference increased further (4%) with repeated testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This change was also associated with a significant training-related reduction in voluntary EMD associated with repeated testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>This reduction in voluntary EMG but “not” evoked EMG, and highlights the change in neural control (Gabriel and Boucher 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>We suggest that the greater Q30 and reduction in voluntary EMD for females were associated with a different motor unit activity pattern at the onset of muscle contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, it is not possible to distinguish exact motor unit behavior that may be responsible for the sex-related differences in the rate of increase in surface EMG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Van Cutsem et al. (1998) established a link between the maximum rate of isometric dorsiflexion torque, the rate of increase in sEMG, and the incidence of doublets associated with progressive resistive training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Similarly, Gabriel et al. (2001)found that only three training sessions were sufficient to produce an increase in the maximum rate of isometric elbow extension torque development and mean spike frequency of the sEMG signal during the torque development phase of the contraction in female participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Bojsen-Moller et al. (2005) reported a positive correlation between the rate of torque development and tendon structure stiffness, indicating that 30% of the variation in torque development can be accounted for by the tendons mechanical properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Winter and Brookes (1991) further hypothesized that joint laxity might also play a role in the tension development phase of the contraction as reflected in the EMD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We believe that the greater rate of increase in sEMG activation for females reflects a compensatory mechanism to transmit force to the tendon more effectively, as evident in the observed decrease in voluntary EMD (Kubo et al. 2003; Wilkerson and Mason 2000; Winter and Brookes 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In support of this idea, Rozzi et al. (1999)have shown that females exhibited greater integrated sEMG activity upon landing from a jump as a compensatory mechanism for greater knee joint laxity, which includes both the musculotendinous unit and ligamentous restraint. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>sEMG can only provide an indirect measurement of differences and underlying changes in motor unit activity patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the use of CT to look at fiber composition differences only allows the association of either similarities or differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Although the possible influence of different muscle structures and sizes in males versus females was discussed in the paper, not directly measuring it with ultrasound is a limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>It was also assumed that there were differences in TA tendon stiffness without having actually measured it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Moreover, caution must be applied when extrapolating the results to older adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The use of a healthy college aged population may not account for differences between the sexes with aging, such as the loss of type II fibers, which may render the sexes more similar in the 6th and 7th decades. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The results support the work of Hannah et al. (2012) as maximal strength of the TA as a covariate accounted for nearly all of the sex-differences in the maximum rate of torque development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This was true, even though the difference in maximal strength was quite pronounced (50.6%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Thus, the hypothesis that maximum strength accounts for sex-differences in the maximum rate of tension development in the lower limb due solely to the fact that males and females are more comparable in maximum strength than in the upper limb was not supported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Rather, the maximum strength accounted for sex-difference in the maximum rate of tension development despite a large discrepancy in strength between males and females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, females had a greater rate of increase in sEMG activation, and exhibited a significant reduction in EMD with repeated testing, suggesting that they might utilize a different motor unit activity pattern at the onset of contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Future research may focus on training modalities and rehabilitation techniques that could optimize RTD rather than only focusing on maximum strength to assist an older population in balance maintenance and recovery from imbalance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p>Analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANCOVA</term><def><p>Analysis of covariance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CMAP</term><def><p>Compound muscle action potential</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSA</term><def><p>Cross-sectional area</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p>Contraction time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dτ/d<italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub></term><def><p>Maximum rate of torque development</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMD</term><def><p>Electromechanical delay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MFCV</term><def><p>Muscle fiber conduction velocity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MVC</term><def><p>Maximal voluntary contraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Q<sub>30</sub></term><def><p>Rate of increase in the sEMG over the first 30 ms of muscle activity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>R</term><def><p>Intraclass correlation coefficient</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMS</term><def><p>Root mean square</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RTD</term><def><p>Rate of torque development</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p>Standard error of measurement</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>sEMG</term><def><p>Surface electromyography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>Standard deviations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TA</term><def><p>Tibialis anterior</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>τ<sub>max</sub></term><def><p>Maximum torque</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Vpp</term><def><p>Peak-to-peak amplitude</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>AagaardPSimonsenEBAndersenJLMagnussonPDyhre-PoulsenPIncreased rate of force development and neural drive of human skeletal muscle following resistance trainingJ Appl Physiol2002931318132610.1152/japplphysiol.00283.2002<?supplied-pmid 12235031?>12235031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>AndersenLLAagaardPInfluence of maximal muscle strength and intrinsic muscle contractile properties on contractile rate of force developmentEur J Appl Physiol2006961465210.1007/s00421-005-0070-z<?supplied-pmid 16249918?>16249918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>BentoPCBPereiraGUgrinowitschCRodackiALFPeak torque and rate of torque development in elderly with and without fall historyClin Biomech201025545045410.1016/j.clinbiomech.2010.02.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Bojsen-MollerJMagnussonSPRassmussenLRKjaerMAagaardPMuscle performance during maximal isometric and dynamic contractions is influenced by the stiffness of the tendinous structuresJ Appl Physiol20059998699410.1152/japplphysiol.01305.2004<?supplied-pmid 15860680?>15860680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>CalderKGabrielDAAdaptations during familiarization to resistive exerciseJ Electromyogr Kines20071732833510.1016/j.jelekin.2006.02.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>ChristieADInglisJGBoucherJPGabrielDAReliability of the FCR H-reflexJ Clin Neurophysiol200522204209<?supplied-pmid 15933493?>15933493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>ChristieADInglisJGKamenGGabrielDARelationships between surface EMG variables and motor unit firing ratesEur J Appl Physiol2009107217718510.1007/s00421-009-1113-7<?supplied-pmid 19544067?>19544067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>CloseRIDynamic properties of mammalian skeletal musclesPhysiol Rev197252129197<?supplied-pmid 4256989?>4256989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>DahmaneRDjordjevicSSimunicBValencicVSpatial Fiber type distribution in normal human muscle histochemical and tensiomyographical evaluationJ Biomech2005382451245910.1016/j.jbiomech.2004.10.020<?supplied-pmid 16214493?>16214493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Di FabioRPReliability of computerized surface electromyography for determining the onset of muscle activityPhys Ther19876714348<?supplied-pmid 3797476?>3797476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>DiStefanoLJMartinezJCCrowleyEMatteauEKernerMSBolingMCNguyenA-DTrojianTHMaturation and sex differences in neuromuscular characteristics of youth athletesJ Strength Cond Res20152992465247310.1519/JSC.0000000000001052<?supplied-pmid 26313573?>26313573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>FarinaDMerlettiRMethods for estimating muscle fibre conduction velocity from surface electromyographic signalsMed Bio Eng Comp200442443244510.1007/BF02350984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>FleissJLReliability of measurement: the design and analysis of clinical experiments1986HobokenWiley7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>FollandJPBuckthorpeMWHannahRHuman capacity for explosive force production: neural and contractile determinantsScand J Med Sci Sport201424689490610.1111/sms.12131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>GabrielDABoucherJEffects of repetitive dynamic contractions upon electromechanical delayEur J Appl Physiol199879374010.1007/s004210050470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>GabrielDABasfordJRAnK-NTraining-related changes in the maximal rate or torque development and EMG activityJ Electromyog Kines20011112312910.1016/S1050-6411(00)00041-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>GottliebGLCorcosDMAgarwalGCOrganizing principles for single-joint movements I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A speed-insensitive strategyJ Neurophysiol1989623342357<?supplied-pmid 2769334?>2769334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>GreenLAParroJJGabrielDABeneficial effects of serial contractions on muscle performance after a brief period of restEur J Appl Physiol201411481657166510.1007/s00421-014-2896-8<?supplied-pmid 24817383?>24817383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>GreenLAMcGuireJGabrielDAFlexor carpi radialis surface electromyography electrode placement for evoked and voluntary measuresMuscle Nerve20155281882510.1002/mus.24631<?supplied-pmid 25736453?>25736453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>HannahRMinshullCBuckthorpeMWFollandJPExplosive neuromuscular performance of males versus femalesExp Physiol201297561862910.1113/expphysiol.2011.063420<?supplied-pmid 22308163?>22308163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Henriksson-LarsénKBLexellJSjöströmMDistribution of different fibre types in human skeletal muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Method for the preparation and analysis of cross-sections of whole tibialis anteriorHistochem J198315216717810.1007/BF01042285<?supplied-pmid 6343306?>6343306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>HessJAWoollacottMEffect of high-intensity strength-training on functional measures of balance ability in balance-impaired older adultsJ Man Physiol Ther20052858259010.1016/j.jmpt.2005.08.013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>HeywardVHJohannes-EllisSMRomerJFGender differences in strengthRes Quart Ex Sport198657215415910.1080/02701367.1986.10762192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>HicksALMcCartneyNGender differences in isometric contractile properties and fatigability in elderly human muscleCan J Appl Physiol199621644145410.1139/h96-039<?supplied-pmid 8959311?>8959311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>HoffmanTStaufferRWJacksonASSex difference in strengthAm J Sport Med19797426526710.1177/036354657900700415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>HolmbäckAMPorterMMDownhamDAndersenJLLexellJStructure and function of the ankle dorsiflexor muscles in young and moderately active men and womenJ Appl Physiol20039562416242410.1152/japplphysiol.00517.2002<?supplied-pmid 12949015?>12949015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>HoltermannARoeleveldKVereijkenBEttemaGThe effect of rate of force development on maximal force production: acute and training-related aspectsEur J Appl Physiol200799660561310.1007/s00421-006-0380-9<?supplied-pmid 17219170?>17219170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>InglisJGHowardJMcIntoshKGabrielDAVandenboomRDecreased motor unit discharge rate in the potentiated human tibialis anterior muscleActa Physiol2011201448349210.1111/j.1748-1716.2010.02233.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>InglisJGVandenboomRGabrielDASex-related differences in maximal rate of isometric torque developmentJ Electromyog Kines20132361289129410.1016/j.jelekin.2013.09.005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>JaworowskiÅPorterMMHolmbäckAMDownhamDLexellJEnzyme activities in the tibialis anterior muscle of young moderately active men and women: relationship with body composition, muscle cross-sectional area and fibre type compositionActa Physiol Scand2002176321522510.1046/j.1365-201X.2002.t01-2-01004.x<?supplied-pmid 12392501?>12392501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>KuboKKanehisaHFukunagaTGender differences in the viscoelastic properties of tendon structuresEur J Appl Physiol20038852052610.1007/s00421-002-0744-8<?supplied-pmid 12560950?>12560950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>LangeFvan WeerdenTWvan der HoevenJHA new surface electromyography analysis method to determine spread of muscle fibres conduction velocitiesJ Appl Physiol20029375976410.1152/japplphysiol.00594.2001<?supplied-pmid 12133889?>12133889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>LaRocheDPCreminKAGreenleafBCroceRVRapid torque development in older female fallers and nonfallers: a comparison across lower-extremity musclesJ Electromyog Kines20102048248810.1016/j.jelekin.2009.08.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>LenhardtSAMcIntoshKCGabrielDAThe surface EMG-force relationship during isometric dorsiflexion in males and femalesElectromyog Clin Neurophysiol200949227234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>LindstromLHMagnussonRIInterpretation of myoelectric power spectra: A model and its applications197765653662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>MacalusoANimmoMAFosterJECockburnMMcMillanNCDe VitoGContractile muscle volume and agonist-antagonist coactivation account for differences in torque between young and older womenMuscle Nerve200225685886310.1002/mus.10113<?supplied-pmid 12115975?>12115975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>MarshESaleDMcComasAJQuinlanJInfluence of joint position on ankle dorsiflexion in humansJ Appl Physiol1981511160167<?supplied-pmid 7263411?>7263411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>McIntoshKCGabrielDAReliability of a simple method for determining muscle fiber conduction velocityMuscle Nerve20124525726510.1002/mus.22268<?supplied-pmid 22246883?>22246883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>MerlettiRLo ConteLRSathyanDRepeatability of electrically-evoked myoelectric signals in the human tibialis anterior muscleJ Electromyog Kines199552678010.1016/1050-6411(94)00004-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>NishiharaKFutamiTHosodaKGomiTValidation of estimated muscle fibres conduction velocity with the normalized peak-averaging techniqueJ Electromyog Kines2005159310110.1016/j.jelekin.2004.06.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>PaasukeMErelineJGapeyevaHKnee extension strength and vertical jumping performance in nordic combined athletesJ Sport Med Physical Fit2001413354361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>PasquetBCarpentierADuchateauJSpecific modulation of motor unit discharge for a similar change in fascicle length during shortening and lengthening contractions in humansJ Physiol2006577275376510.1113/jphysiol.2006.117986<?supplied-pmid 16959853?>16959853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>PijnapplesMvan der BurgJCEReevesNDvan DieenJHIdentification of elderly fallers by muscle strength measuresEur J Appl Physiol200810258559210.1007/s00421-007-0613-618071745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>RozziSLLephartSMGearWSFuFHKnee joint laxity and neuromuscular characteristics of male and female soccer and basketball playersAm J Sport Med1999273312319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>SahalyRVandewalleHDrissTMonodHMaximal voluntary force and rate of force development in humans–importance of instructionEur J Appl Physiol2001853–434535010.1007/s004210100451<?supplied-pmid 11560090?>11560090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>SchultzABAshton-MillerJAAlexanderNBWhat leads to age and gender differences in balance maintenance and recovery?Muscle Nerve19975S60S6410.1002/(SICI)1097-4598(1997)5+&lt;60::AID-MUS15&gt;3.0.CO;2-2<?supplied-pmid 9331387?>9331387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>SolomonowMBarattaRZhouBHd’AmbrosiaRElectromyogram coactivation patterns of the elbow antagonist muscles during slow isokinetic movementExp Neurol1988100347047710.1016/0014-4886(88)90032-5<?supplied-pmid 3366200?>3366200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>StevensJASogolowEDGender differences for non-fatal unintentional fall related injuries among older adultsInjury Prevent20051111511910.1136/ip.2004.005835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>ThelenDGSchultzABAlexanderNBAshton-MillerJAEffects of age on rapid ankle torque developmentJ Gerontol A Bio Sci Med Sci1996515M226M23210.1093/gerona/51A.5.M2268808994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>TillinNAPainMTGFollandJExplosive force production during isometric squats correlates with athletic performance in rugby union playersJ Sport Sci2013311667610.1080/02640414.2012.720704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Van CutsemMDuchateauJPreceding muscle activity influences motor unit discharge and rate of torque development during ballistic contractions in humansJ Physiol2005562263564410.1113/jphysiol.2004.074567<?supplied-pmid 15539402?>15539402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Van CutsemMDechateauJHainautKChanges in single motor unit behaviour contribute to the increase in contraction speed after dynamic training in humansJ Physiol199851329530510.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.295by.x<?supplied-pmid 9782179?>9782179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>WeirBSCockerhamCCEstimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structureEvolution19843861358137010.2307/2408641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>WilkersonRDMasonMADifferences in men’s and women’s mean ankle ligamentous laxityIowa Ortho J2000204648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>WinterEMBrookesFBCElectromechanical response times and muscle elasticity in men and womanEuro J Appl Physiol19916312412810.1007/BF00235181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>ZwartsMJEvaluation of the estimation of muscle fibres conduction velocity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Surface versus needle methodElectroencephalog Clin Neurophysiol19897354454810.1016/0013-4694(89)90263-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
