<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5216082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">ncomms13957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28045014</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Death receptor 6 contributes to autoimmunity in lupus-prone mice </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujikura</surname><given-names>Daisuke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ikesue</surname><given-names>Masahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>Tsutomu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>Satoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>Hideaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uede</surname><given-names>Toshimitsu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Division of Infection and Immunity, Hokkaido University Research Center for Zoonosis Control</institution>, North-20, West-10, Kita-ku, Sapporo 001-0020, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Division of Molecular Immunology, Hokkaido University Institute for Genetic Medicine</institution>, North-15, West-7, Kita-ku, Sapporo 060-0815, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Division of Bioresources, Hokkaido University Research Center for Zoonosis Control</institution>, North-20, West-10, Kita-ku, Sapporo 001-0020, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>d-fuji@czc.hokudai.ac.jp</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>uedetoshimitsu@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>13957</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Expansion of autoreactive follicular helper T (Tfh) cells is tightly restricted to prevent induction of autoantibody-dependent immunological diseases, such as systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here we show expression of an orphan immune regulator, death receptor 6 (DR6/TNFRSF21), on a population of Tfh cells that are highly expanded in lupus-like disease progression in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide screening reveals an interaction between syndecan-1 and DR6 resulting in immunosuppressive functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Importantly, syndecan-1 is expressed specifically on autoreactive germinal centre (GC) B cells that are critical for maintenance of Tfh cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 expression level on GC B cells is associated with Tfh cell expansion and disease progression in lupus-prone mouse strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In addition, Tfh cell suppression by DR6-specific monoclonal antibody delays disease progression in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that the DR6/syndecan-1 axis regulates aberrant GC reactions and could be a therapeutic target for autoimmune diseases such as SLE. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Germinal centre (GC) reactions are driven by T follicular helper (Tfh) cells and their dysregulation can cause autoimmune disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Here the authors show that the orphan receptor DR6 is a Tfh cell marker that binds syndecan-1 on GC B cells driving autoimmunity in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a chronic inflammatory disease resulting from autoantibody recognition of self-antigens, with autoantibody production dependent on activation of autoreactive T and B cells1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Although autoreactive T and B cells can be detected in healthy wild-type mice23, the expansion and activation of these cells are tightly controlled by tolerance mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Defects in genes associated with apoptotic cell clearance cause systemic autoimmune disease in familial SLE patients and C57BL/6 (B6) mice456. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Normally, the activation of autoreactive lymphocytes should be regulated at the stage of initial T/B cell interactions789. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The activation and differentiation of peripheral T and B cells requires multiple steps10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Antigen-primed CD4+ T cells migrate from the T cell zone to the B cell follicles after expressing CXCR5, which is a chemokine receptor11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In the lymphoid structure termed the germinal centre (GC), located on the border between the T and B cell zones, the primed CD4+ T cells differentiate into follicular helper T (Tfh) cells and promote B cell maturation, such as proliferation, somatic hyper maturation and immunoglobulin class switching, through its production of cytokines such as interleukin (IL)-4 and IL-21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Tfh cells express the chemokine receptor CXCR4 to migrate from the original follicle to a neighboring follicle and induce new GC formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In these sequential steps, reciprocal signals by antigen-specific GC B cells are important for complete Tfh cell differentiation and maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In promoting complete Tfh cell differentiation, the GC B cells activate T cell receptor (TCR) signalling through antigen presentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The expression of costimulatory ligands such as inducible T cell co-stimulator ligand (ICOSL) and programmed cell death-1 ligand1/2 (PD-L1/2) on GC B cells regulates TCR signal activation, both positively and negatively12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Notably, a functional blockade or defect in negative costimulatory molecules, including programmed cell death 1 (PD1) or cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4 (CTLA4), induces an aberrant GC reaction and systemic autoimmunological disease13141516. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that during T/B cell interactions, costimulatory molecules fine-tune Tfh cell differentiation, thus preventing the induction of systemic autoimmunity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Death receptor 6 (DR6/CD358) is also known as tumour necrosis factor (TNF) receptor superfamily member 21 (TNFRSF21)17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The TNFRSF includes costimulatory molecules such as CD40, CD30, Herpes virus entry mediator (HVEM), 4-1BB, OX40, CD27, DR3, and glucocorticoid-induced TNFR-related protein (GITR)18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In a previous report, mice with a targeted deletion of the Tnfrsf21 gene (encoding DR6) exhibited hyper production of immunoglobulins after antigen stimulation19, and DR6 deficiency in peripheral T cells enhances the production of cytokines for facilitating B cell activation and differentiation, as well as the antigen-dependent activation of transcriptional factors such as the nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT) or nuclear factor-kappa B (NFκB)20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>DR6 is associated with the regulations on T cell function in several immunological diseases, including experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE), asthma, and acute graft versus host disease in animal models212223. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>DR6 is weakly expressed on resting peripheral CD4+ T cells and upregulated in response to TCR stimulation24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the association of TNFRSF21 gene induction with disease progression was reported in SLE patients2526. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Although the molecular mechanism of action, including its immunological ligand, is unknown, DR6 may have a critical role in autoimmune disease progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 is a glycosylated type-I transmembrane protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In in vitro experiments, syndecan-1 binds to various soluble proteins via its attached oligosaccharide chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Therefore, syndecan-1 may act as a scaffold for soluble factors, inducing the accumulation of inflammatory cells in localized inflammation27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>By contrast, several studies suggest that syndecan-1 has a suppressive function on the progression of immunological diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Similar to DR6 deficiency, syndecan-1 deficiency increases the severity of disease, lymphocyte activation, as well as production of antigen-specific plasma cells and immunoglobulins in the peripheral lymphoid organs of EAE, immune complex-mediated murine nephritis, and allergic lung inflammation animal models282930. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest the presence of an undefined regulatory function of syndecan-1 in peripheral lymphocyte activation27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The amount of syndecan-1shed into the peripheral blood has been shown to correlate with disease severity in SLE patients3132. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Although most CD19+ B cells do not express syndecan-1, CD19+ autoreactive pre-plasma cells express syndecan-1 in lupus-prone mice and SLE patients3233. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that syndecan-1 is also engaged in the pathogenesis of autoimmune diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, the details of the suppressive function of syndecan-1, particularly on pathogenic lymphocyte maturation and activation, are unclear27. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Here we show an increase in DR6 expression on Tfh cells in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we identify syndecan-1 as a binding partner for DR6, and we clarify whether and how this dysregulated DR6/syndecan-1 interaction leads to autoimmunity in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Induction of DR6+ CD4+ T cells in lupus-prone mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Recent independent studies have reported that upregulation of the TNFRSF21 gene is associated with disease prognosis by genome-wide gene expression analysis using peripheral mononuclear cells obtained from SLE patients2526. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To explore the details of the association between DR6 and disease, we generated a rat anti-DR6 monoclonal antibody (clone 25-1, IgG1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The specificity of 25-1 antibody (25-1 Ab) is demonstrated in Supplementary Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 25-1 Ab bound DR6 stably expressed on L929 cells (L929-mDR6) (Supplementary Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>25-1 Abs specifically bound to DR6, but not to other TNFRSF molecules that were expressed on the cell surface (Supplementary Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>25-1 Abs could also bind to endogenous DR6, expressed by murine T cell hybridoma (DO11.10-T) cells (Supplementary Fig. 1c, left panel), and this reactivity was lost after Tnfrsf21 gene-specific knockout based on the CRISPR-Cas9 system (G510-8-7 or -10-4) (Supplementary Fig. 1c, middle and right panels), indicating that 25-1 Abs react with endogenous DR6 but not the other proteins expressed on the cell (Supplementary Fig. 1c,d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We used 25-1 Abs to detect mouse DR6 expression hereafter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Splenocytes were obtained from anti-DNA Ab negative (10 weeks of age) and positive (24 weeks of age) female New Zealand Black × New Zealand White F1 (BWF1) mice and age- and sex matched healthy B6 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we identified the induction of DR6-expressing cells in splenocytes obtained from BWF1 but not B6 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The majority of DR6+ cells were CD3+ T cells in all mice that were tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>DR6+ cells were increased in an age-dependent fashion in BWF1 mice (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, a unique CD4+ subset expressing DR6 was observed in autoreactive Ab positive lupus-prone BWF1 (aged 24 weeks) but not in autoreactive Ab negative B6 mice (aged 10 and 24 weeks; Fig. 1b,c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Most of the CD8+ T cells also expressed DR6 in BWF1 mice (Fig. 1d,e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>While CD4+ T cells of BWF1 mice markedly expanded with disease progression, CD8+ T cells were minimally expanded in the mice (Fig. 1f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we decided to further define which subpopulation of CD4+ T cells expressed DR6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>DR6 expression on Tfh cells of lupus-prone mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Follicular helper T (Tfh) cells expand and promote disease progression in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we asked whether DR6 expression was associated with Tfh cells in lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Thus, we characterized Bcl6 expression of DR6+ CD4+ cells by intracellular staining since Bcl6 is a key transcriptional factor for Tfh cells (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we detected anti-Bcl6 antibody specific signal in DR6+ CD4+ splenocytes isolated from 24-week-old BWF1 mice (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>We also analysed DR6 expression among Tfh cells that expanded in lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The expanded Tfh cells were detected by their expression of CXCR5 and PD1 among 7AAD− (live) CD19− CD4+ splenocytes of 24-week-old female BWF1 mice (Fig. 2b, upper panel), but not in age- and sex matched B6 mice (Fig. 2b, lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>By their CXCR5 and PD1 expression levels, the expanded Tfh cells could also be separated into three populations; CXCR5high/PD1high (mature Tfh cells) and CXCR5int/PD1int (pre-Tfh cells) or CXCR5−/PD1− (non-Tfh cells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>To determine Tnfrsf21 gene expression of these three Tfh cell populations, we sorted these cells from splenocytes of 24-week-old BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We then detected expression of the Tnfrsf21 gene in these isolated cells by quantitative PCR (Fig. 2c). Tnfrsf21 mRNA expression was detected in each cell population isolated from BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The expression was highest in Tfh cells; intermediate in pre-Tfh and low in non-Tfh cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We also analysed the DR6 protein expression of these Tfh cell populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In flow cytometrical assays, DR6 expressing cells were observed in each Tfh cell population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The frequency of DR6+ cells was highest in Tfh cells, intermediate in pre-Tfh cells and rare in non-Tfh cells (Fig. 2d, left panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The DR6 expression on Tfh cells correlated with the expression of another Tfh-associated surface molecule, CXCR4, by the cells (Fig. 2d, middle and right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>These findings indicated that DR6 is expressed on Tfh cells that expand in lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Identification of syndecan-1 as a ligand for DR6 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To understand in detail the function of DR6 in immunological events, specific ligand(s) for DR6 required discovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>To identify the DR6 ligand(s), we generated a soluble fusion protein consisting of an extracellular domain of murine DR6 and the Fc portion of human IgG (DR6-Fc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>We observed a small portion of the cells bound to DR6-Fc in total splenocytes obtained from B6 mice (Fig. 3a, red box in left panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Most of the cells bound to DR6-Fc were detected in the lymphocytes gate on a SSC versus FSC dot plot (Fig. 3a, right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We also stained total splenocytes with DR6-Fc and a specific antibody against the indicated cell type marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The cells bound to DR6-Fc were detected with an antibody against a surface marker for B cells, B220, but not for other cell populations tested (Fig. 3b, red coloured box). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The murine A20 B cell line, but not DO11.10-T cell hybridoma, preferentially bound to DR6-Fc (Fig. 3c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Thus, we constructed expression plasmids of full-length complementary DNA (cDNA) library obtained from DR6-Fc-positive A20 cells and retrovirally transfected the plasmids into DR6-Fc-negative DO11.10-T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Then, we isolated the transfectants bound to DR6-Fc during four rounds of sorting and culturing expansions (Fig. 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>After the fifth round, we recovered a single library-specific cDNA fragment (approximately 3,000 bp in length) inserted in genomic DNA of the isolated transfectants (Fig. 3e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the fragment encoded the sequence for the full-length mRNA of murine Syndecan-1 (Sdc1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The binding of syndecan-1 to DR6 was confirmed by human and mouse syndecan-1 ectopically expressed on DO11.10T cells binding to the DR6 ectodomain (Fig. 3f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We then analysed the molecular specificity of the interaction between syndecan-1 and DR6 (Supplementary Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We retrovirally transfected plasmids expressing non-specific (shLuc) or Syndecan-1-specific (shmSdc1) shRNAs into A20 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Using flow cytometry, we confirmed the effective knockdown of syndecan-1 protein expression mediated by shmSdc1, but not shLuc, in A20 cells (Supplementary Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We also confirmed that shmSdc1 treatment did not affect B220 expression of the cells (Supplementary Fig. 2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In a further flow cytometrical assay using DR6-Fc, shmSdc1 but not shLuc treatment dramatically reduced the binding of DR6-Fc to A20 cells (Supplementary Fig. 2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In the same assay using the indicated recombinant Fc proteins, syndecan-1 expressed on A20 cells preferentially bound to DR6-Fc compared with Fc proteins obtained from the other TNFRSF molecules (Supplementary Fig. 2d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This syndecan-1 specific interaction of DR6 was consistent with the observation that the genome-wide screening identified only syndecan-1 as a binding molecule for the DR6-ectodomain (Fig. 3e). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We also analysed binding specificity within the molecular structures of DR6 (Fig. 3g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Four cysteine-rich domains (CRDs) are conserved in the extracellular region of DR6 and are involved in ligand binding17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>We generated recombinant Fc proteins fused with DR6-extracellular domain lacking CRD1 (ΔCRD1), CRD2 (ΔCRD2), CRD3 (ΔCRD3) or CRD4 (ΔCRD4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Then, these recombinant proteins were pulled down with syndecan-1 endogenously expressed on A20 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The precipitated syndecan-1 was detected with an anti-syndecan-1 Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Among the tested Fc proteins, the mutants lacking CRD2 or CRD3 were not capable of precipitating syndecan-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The observed dependence of the interaction on CRD2 and -3 is in agreement with the previous observations that both CRD2 and -3 of DR6 are positively charged for its ligand binding34. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>We further demonstrated a molecular function of syndecan-1/DR6 interaction in T cell activation (Fig. 3h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>DO11.10-T cells were electroporated with the indicated transcription factor-dependent reporter plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Then, the cells were stimulated with or without recombinant syndecan-1 (recSdc1) under activation of TCR signalling mediated by anti-CD3 Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>CD3 cross-linking dramatically activated NFAT in the cells (Fig. 3h, gray in left columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the recSdc1 stimulation suppressed NFAT activation (Fig. 3h, red versus gray in left columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The suppressive effect of recSdc1 was also observed in the reporter assay detecting NFκB activation (Fig. 3h, right columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We also demonstrated the suppressive function of recSdc1 by assessing IL-2 production, which depends on NFAT and NFκB activation (Fig. 3i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Parental DO11.10T cells or their DR6 deficient clones (Supplementary Fig. 1c,d) were stimulated with the indicated combinations of anti-CD3 Ab and recSdc1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Parental DO11.10T cells produced IL-2 in response to anti-CD3 Ab, whereas the cells produced decreased IL-2 in the presence of recSdc1 (Fig. 3i, opened compared with closed column in black coloured columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, DR6 deficient DO11.10T cell clones produced IL-2 in the presence or absence of recSdc1, indicating that the suppressive effect of recSdc1 depends on DR6 expression by the cells (Fig. 3i, opened compared with closed in red or blue columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These findings demonstrate that syndecan-1 is a specific binding partner for DR6 and the interaction negatively regulates NFAT and NFκB activation during TCR activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 on autoreactive germinal centre B cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>We next considered whether syndecan-1 was associated with a specific B cell population, germinal centre (GC) B cells, because the GC B cell provides critical signals for complete maturation and expansion of Tfh cells in lupus-prone mice9103536. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>We isolated spleens from non-immunized 24-week-old female BWF1 and NZB mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>On the splenic cryosections of BWF1 mice, anti-GL7 Ab stained the GC cells, which were markedly expanded on the border between the T- and B-cell zones (Fig. 4a, cyan in left panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the GL7+ GC cells were also stained with anti-syndecan-1 Ab (Fig. 4a, green in right panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In another lupus-prone mouse strain, NZB mice, the GC cells (Fig. 4b, cyan) also expressed syndecan-1 (Fig. 4b, green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The same results were obtained from other sections (Supplementary Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Comparing the observations obtained from BWF1 (Fig. 4a) with NZB mice (Fig. 4b), we found some differences; (1) the level of syndecan-1 expression on GC cells was higher in NZB than BWF1 mice, and (2) the size of expanded GC cells was smaller in NZB than BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>To confirm the former, we assessed the expression level of syndecan-1 on GL7+ CD19+ GC B cells using flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>As expected, the level of syndecan-1 expression on GL7+ CD19+ GC B cells of NZB mice was higher than that of BWF1 mice (Fig. 4c, upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The levels of syndecan-1 expression of GL7− CD19+ non-GC B cells were low and comparable between lupus-prone and healthy B6 mice (Fig. 4c, upper panel), although CD19 expression level was comparable among these cells (Fig. 4c, lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>To confirm the latter, we calculated the numbers and percentages of GC B cells in these mice strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>While GL7+ CD19+ GC B cells hardly developed in healthy non-immunized B6 mice, the cells expanded in lupus-prone NZB and BWF1 mice (Fig. 4d, upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The number of the GC B cells was significantly lower in the spleen of NZB mice compared with BWF1 mice (Fig. 4d, upper panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The percentage of GC B cells was also comparable among these lupus-prone mice strains (Fig. 4d, lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Therefore, lupus-specific expansion of GC B cell should be restricted in NZB, although the GC B cells developed in both NZB and BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Further analysis also showed the NZB specific restriction of the expansion of both pre-Tfh (Fig. 4e, left panels) and Tfh cells (Fig. 4e, right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we wondered whether syndecan-1 was associated with the regulation of Tfh cells in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>To answer this question, we isolated DR6-expressing Tfh cells from BWF1 mice and stimulated the cells with recSdc1 in conjunction with TCR activation in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, recSdc1 stimulation (at 30 nM) suppressed Il-21 production by the Tfh cells during activation (Fig. 4f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The recSdc1-mediated suppressive effect was not due to a cytotoxic effect on the Tfh cells because 30 nM recSdc1 did not stimulate cell death induction in DO11.10T cells (Supplementary Fig. 4) or the Tfh cells (Supplementary Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that syndecan-1 was expressed on GC B cells of lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Suppression of DR6+ Tfh cells delays disease progression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>We found that 25-1 Ab is capable of DR6 cross-linking in in vitro experiments (Supplementary Fig. 6, the details are described in the legend). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In addition, 25-1 Ab suppressed Il-21 production by DR6-expressing Tfh cells isolated from BWF1 mice (Fig. 5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>This effect was not due to cytotoxicity because 25-1 Ab did not affect cell death induction in DO11.10-T (Supplementary Fig. 7) or isolated DR6-expressing Tfh cells (Supplementary Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These observations prompted us to test the effect of 25-1 Ab on disease progression in BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We administered 25-1 Ab (25-1) or nonspecific rat IgG as a control (ctrl-IgG) to 15-week-old BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the 25-1 Ab administrations significantly reduced serum anti-dsDNA Ab production (Fig. 5b), the percentage of mice with proteinuria (as a marker for kidney dysfunction; Fig. 5c), and improved survival (Fig. 5d) compared with the ctrl-IgG administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In addition, 25-1 Ab administration significantly reduced the induction of DR6+ CD4+ cells (Fig. 5e), GC B cells (Fig. 5f) and plasma cells in BWF1 mice (Fig. 5g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The splenic cryosections also showed 25-1 Ab-mediated suppressive effects on GC formation (Fig. 5h,i, the results obtained from the other sections represented in Supplementary Fig. 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In addition, we did not observe a significant effect of 25-1 Ab on antibody dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC, Supplementary Fig. 10a) or complement dependent cytotoxicity (CDC, Supplementary Fig. 10b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that regulation of DR6 delays disease progression in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In this current study, we found a disease-specific induction of DR6+ T cells in lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In particular, the induction of DR6+ CD4+ T cells correlated with age- and genetic background-dependent disease progression and prognosis in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>A large proportion of CD8+ T cells also expressed DR6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>However, the expansion of these CD8+ T cells was suppressed or not promoted in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we further analysed DR6 expressing CD4+ T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>DR6+ CD4+ cells expressed Il-21 and Bcl6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The expression levels were lower than those observed in DR6low Tfh cells (Supplementary Fig. 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The up-regulated expression of DR6 on the T cell surface-regulated the threshold of DR6 activation to suppress activation of TCR signalling in the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>However, the up-regulated DR6 itself is insufficient for complete prevention of Tfh cells in lupus-prone BWF1 mice, because of the low amount of DR6 ligand on the surface of GC B cells that are the direct counter partners of the Tfh cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In addition, recent studies have reported that CD4+ T cell populations exhibit disease-associated characteristics caused by several SLE-associated genetic mutations on murine chromosomes 1, 5, 6, 7 and 18, leading to high activation and expansion of CD4+ T cell populations in lupus-prone mice37383940. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Although the murine Tnfrsf21 gene (on chromosome 17) is not in murine SLE-associated loci, the unique characteristics of the lupus CD4+ T cell populations emphasize the importance of DR6 functions in the regulation of CD4+ T cells in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Upregulation of DR6 expression was observed in Tfh cell populations of lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In contrast to lupus-prone mice, DR6 expression was low in Tfh cells of DNP-KLH- immunized mice (Supplementary Fig. 12a,b, vertical axes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>CXCR4 (Supplementary Fig. 12b, horizontal axes) or Bcl6 (Supplementary Fig. 12c) expression in these cells was also low compared with that in Tfh cells of BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Collectively, Tfh cells of lupus-prone mice manifested their pathological characteristics compared with Tfh cells of healthy mice as expected, considering that lupus CD4+ T cell populations have a high sensitivity to TCR activation3739. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The TCR signal promoted high DR6 induction on Tfh cells of lupus-prone mice (Supplementary Fig. 13a,b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Recently, these pathological characteristics of lupus CD4+ T cells were shown to be caused by aberrant metabolic regulations, and are crucial for spontaneous induction of Tfh cell generation, GC formation, and disease symptoms in lupus-prone mice38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, such aberrant regulation of lupus CD4+ T cells is not associated with humoral responses against foreign antigens38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the pathological cellular characteristics might involve high DR6 induction on auto reactive Tfh cells of severe lupus-prone BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We characterized syndecan-1 as a binding partner for DR6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Recombinant syndecan-1 stimulation was not capable of inducing cell death, except when it was highly concentrated (Supplementary Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This weak apoptotic effect of syndecan-1 stimulation is consistent with the weak apoptotic capability of DR6 compared with that of the other TNFRSF molecules, such as death receptor-4 (DR4)17 and -3 (DR3)41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This weak apoptotic activity of DR6 might depend on its low affinities of binding to Fas-associated protein with death domain (FADD) and TNFR-associated death domain protein (TRADD), which are key components for apoptotic caspase activation17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In addition, DR6 receptor cross-linking did not affect caspase activation in the cultured T-cell line (Supplementary Fig. 14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, syndecan-1/DR6 interaction dramatically suppressed the activation of TCR signalling, which activates NFκB and NFAT in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In addition, DR6 gene deficiency in lymphocytes leads to hyper activation of NFκB or NFAT1920. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These findings and our data suggest that DR6 regulates lymphocyte activation by its negative regulation to NFκB and NFAT signalling rather than apoptotic function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>However, the molecular mechanisms of this DR6-mediated suppression have yet to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 has multiple functions in immunological events and disease progression27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 can attach to several chemokines, growth factors, and cytokines, suggesting that it has a scaffolding function for the accumulation of inflammatory cells in localized inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Several knockout studies also suggest that syndecan-1 regulates antibody production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 deficiency induces pathogenic antigen (myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein)-specific plasma cells in an EAE model28. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Syndecan-1 deficiency also causes high immunoglobulin production in an Ab-dependent nephritis model29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Importantly, DR6 is also associated with negative regulation of peripheral lymphocyte activation in syndecan-1-associated immunological disease models such as EAE21, lung inflammation22, and lupus-like disease (the present study). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest an association of DR6/syndecan-1 interaction with the progression of several immunological diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The 25-1 Ab was capable of DR6 cross-linking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Recombinant syndecan-1, as well as 25-1 Ab treatment, suppressed Il-21 production by Tfh cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the antibody should mimic the function of syndecan-1 that was reduced in BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>IL-21 production by Tfh cells is critical for both maintenance and development of GC B cells42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Although the importance of IL-21 production in Tfh cell development is controversial43, GC B/Tfh cell interaction is important for full-maturation and maintenance of Tfh cells and GC formation94445. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Therefore, 25-1 Ab or syndecan-1 should fine-tune the outcome of GC B/Tfh cell interactions, to prevent autoantibody production and disease progression in BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Moreover, although 25-1 Ab preferentially bound to CD3+ T cells, other cells binding 25-1 Ab were also observed in total splenocytes obtained from BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Several reports have shown DR6 expression on B cells, dendritic cells and macrophages194647. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In addition, these cells are associated with GC reactions after immunization in healthy mice, as well as the disease progression of lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Therefore, further studies will be needed to investigate the role of DR6/syndecan-1 interaction in the regulation of these cells in the immunization as well as the disease progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Taken together, in the current study, we identified a novel regulatory mechanism that depends on the interaction of DR6 with syndecan-1 for preventing expansion and activation of Tfh cells and disease progression in lupus-prone mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the DR6/syndecan-1 axis should be a novel therapeutic target in autoimmune disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Female C57BL/6, New Zealand Black (NZB), or NZB × New Zealand White F1 mice were purchased from SLC Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>(Shizuoka, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>These mice were housed in specific pathogen-free conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>All mice were assigned randomly to experimental groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>We performed animal care and experiments in accordance with the guidelines and approval of the Animal Care and Use Committee of Hokkaido University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Murine fibrosarcoma L929, human embryonic fibroblast (HEK) 293T cells, and retrovirus packaging cells (PLAT-E, kindly provided by Dr Kitamura T) were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium containing 10% fetal calf serum (FCS) at 37 °C in 5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Murine T cell hybridoma DO11.10-T and murine lymphoma A20 were also maintained in RPMI-1640 medium containing 10% FCS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>All cell lines were routinely tested for mycoplasma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Generation of recombinant proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>For construction of DR6-Fc, cDNA encoding the extracellular region of DR6 (mouse: from +1_+350 aa) was fused with the Fc region of human IgG, which was mutated at the amino acid position of E233P, L234A, and L235A for preventing binding with mouse Fc receptors, and inserted into pcDNA3 (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The resulted plasmid was transfected into HEK293T cells with lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The recombinant protein secreted in the cultured supernatant was purified by protein-A sepharose column48. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Biotinylation of the proteins was performed using the EZ-Link NHS-PEO Solid Phase Biotinylation Kit (Life Technologies), according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>For the generation of recombinant mouse syndecan-1 protein (recSdc1), the cDNA encoding ectodomain of mouse syndecan-1 (+1_+251 aa) was inserted into pcDNA3.1 myc/his ver.B (Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The production of recSdc1 that was fused with hexamer His tags was achieved in HEK293T cells as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>RecSdc1 in culture medium was purified using Ni-sepharose column (HisTrap HP, GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Generation of anti-DR6 specific monoclonal antibody </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Hybridomas were generated from splenocytes of Lewis rats immunized with DR6-Fc and L929-mDR6 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Specificity of the antibody produced in the cells was assessed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) using DR6-Fc or human IgG as antigen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Details of antibodies used in the present study are listed in Supplementary Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For analysing cell surface molecules, single-cell suspensions were stained with the indicated antibodies (the concentration of antibody is also listed in Supplementary Table 1), after Fc-block with anti-CD16/32 (clone 2.4G2, 20 μg ml−l, 4 °C, 15 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>After washed twice with ice-cold PBS containing 0.5% bovine serum albumin and 0.1% NaN3, the cells were further stained with 7AAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent intensities of the cells were detected on a LSR Fortessa or Canto (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For identifying lymphocyte cell populations that were indicated in each figure, gate strategies were shown in Supplementary Fig. 15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>For intracellular Bcl6 detection49, Fixable Viability Dye eFluor 780 (eBioscience, San Diego, CA) was used instead of 7AAD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Expression screening </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Expression screening using the retrovirus-based full-length cDNA library was performed as described in our previous report50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the full-length cDNA library was constructed using the In-Fusion SMARTer Directional cDNA Library construction kit (Takara Bio, Shiga, Japan) and inserted into retrovirus vector, pMXs51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The titer of cDNA library was &gt;1 × 106 plaque forming units per ml, and &gt;90% of individual clones contained different cDNA fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>pMXs containing cDNA library was retrovirally packaged in PLAT-E cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>DO11.10-T cell hybridoma (2 × 106 cells) was infected with the virus particles at a multiplicity of infection=0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Two days after the infection, the cells were stained with biotinylated DR6-Fc plus streptavidin-allophycocyanin (APC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>After two-washes, APC-positive cells were sorted by MoFlo Astrios (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The sorted cells were then expanded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>After five-rounds of sorting and culturing, the provirus in the sorted cells was isolated by PCR using pMXs-specific primer set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Stable gene expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>cDNA fragment encoding the indicated gene was cloned into pMXsIG51 at multiple cloning sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The construct was retrovirally transfected into cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Among the cells, enhanced green fluorescent protein positive cells were sorted by Moflo Astrios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The purity of the cells was confirmed as &gt;90% by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Tnfrsf21 knockout single cell clone </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The 23 nucleotide guide sequence (5′-CCACGATGGTCGCCGGCTCTCTT-3′ ) targeting on negative strand genomic DNA locating on exon-1 of murine Tnfrsf21 gene was designed with CRISPR direct software uploaded in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://crispr.dbcls.jp">http://crispr.dbcls.jp</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The DNA fragment was cloned into pSpCas9(BB)-2A-Puro (PX459) ver.2 (ref. 52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The resulted plasmid was electroporated into DO11.10-T cell using Gene Pulser X-cell (Bio-Rad, Hemel Hempstead, UK) at 280 V and 950 μF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Two days after puromycin selection at 3 μg ml−1, single cell clones of the cells were isolated by limiting dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The single cell clones were selected after their re-exhibition of puromycin sensitivity (for validating plasmid exclusion) and sequencing their genomic DNA (for gene editing). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Quantitative PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Quantitative PCR assay was performed using SYBR Premix Ex Taq II (Takara Bio.)41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Briefly, cellular total RNAs were isolated by Trizol method according to the manufacturer's instruction (Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Reverse-transcription was carried out by using ReverTra Ace (Toyobo CO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Ltd., Osaka, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Gene-specific primer sets used in the current study are shown in Supplementary Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Mean of Actb in each sample was used as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Site-directed mutagenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>For generating region specific deletion mutants of DR6 (ΔCRD1; deleted the region from +42 to +105 aa, ΔCRD2; deleted the region from +106 to +145 aa, ΔCRD3; deleted the region from +146 to +185 aa or ΔCRD4; deleted the region from +186 to +212 aa), site-directed deletions were introduced into the plasmid encoding DR6-Fc using PrimeSTAR Mutagenesis kit (Takara Bio.) according to the manufacturer's instruction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Pull down assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>A20 cells (2.5 × 107 cells) were incubated with the indicated Fc fused protein (10 μg ml−1) at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Two hours after the incubation, cells were washed three times with ice-cold culture medium and lysed with the lysis buffer containing 0.2% NP-40, 10% Glycerol, 150 mM NaCl and 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4) at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation (20,000 × g, 30 min, 4 °C), the supernatant was precipitated with protein A sepharose beads (GE Healthcare) at 4 °C for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The beads were washed three times with the lysis buffer and the eluted materials were analysed by dot blot assay using anti-syndecan-1 Ab (clone 281-1, 1/1,000 diluted, Biolegend, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Reporter gene assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Cells (3 × 106 cells per 450 μl of Opti-MEM (Life Technologies) in a 0.4-cm cuvette) were electroporated with 20 μg firefly-luciferase reporter plasmid (pGL4.26, Promega) containing binding motif for the indicated transcriptional factor plus 5 μg reference renilla-luciferase reporter plasmid (phRG-TK, Promega) as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four hours after the electroporation, cells were stimulated with plate-bound anti-CD3 Ab (10 μg ml−1) in the presence or absence of recSdc1 (30 nM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Six hours after the stimulation, the luciferase activities of the cells were assessed by dual-Glo luciferase assay (Promega). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The amount of mouse IL-2 was assessed by mouse IL-2 Quantikine ELISA kit, according to the manufacturer's instruction (M2000, R&amp;D systems, Minneapolis, MN). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Acetone-fixed cryosections (7 μm) were blocked by immunoblock (DS Pharma Biomedical, Osaka, Japan) and then stained with the indicated Abs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The dilution of each antibody is shown in Supplementary Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent images of the sections were captured on a confocal laser scanning system (LSM-780, Carl Zeiss Microscopy GmbH, Göttingen, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>GL7+ area in the field was calculated using ImageJ software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Detection of anti-dsDNA antibody </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Anti-dsDNA Ab in serum sample was detected by ELISA using double-stranded deoxyribonucleic acid coated plate and horse radish peroxidase conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (H+L) antibody (1/5,000 diluted, Jackson Immuno Research, West Grove, PA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Detection of proteinuria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Uropaper III strip (Eiken Chemical Co., Tochigi, Japan) was used for urinalysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Proteinuria was defined as urinary protein excretion exceeding 100 mg dl−1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Two sets of data were compared using two-tailed Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>When variances were not comparable, Welch's correction was applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Sample sizes were selected based on the number of replicates (up to three). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>For survival rate or cumulative incidence, statistical analysis was performed by Log-rank test or Grey test with R software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>). P values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Asterisk or NS means ‘significant' or ‘not significant', respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Each in vitro experiment was performed at least twice with reproducible results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Data availability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the data supporting of the findings of this study are available within the article and its Supplementary Information Files, or from the corresponding authors on reasonable request. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Additional information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Fujikura, D. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Death receptor 6 contributes to autoimmunity in lupus-prone mice. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Commun. 8, 13957 doi: 10.1038/ncomms13957 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d32e18" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Figures, Supplementary Tables, Supplementary Methods and Supplementary References </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We thank all members of Prof Uede's laboratory for discussions and technical help. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>We also thank Dr K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Takada for helpful discussion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by Grants-in-Aid for Young Scientists (to D.F.). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>MohanC., AdamsS., StanikV. &amp; DattaS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>K. Nucleosome—a major immunogen for pathogenic autoantibody-inducing T-cells of lupus. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Med. 177, 1367–1381 (1993).8478612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>CeruttiA., ColsM. &amp; PugaI. Marginal zone B cells: virtues of innate-like antibody-producing lymphocytes. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13, 118–132 (2013).23348416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>EhrensteinM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; NotleyC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>A. The importance of natural IgM: scavenger, protector and regulator. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 10, 778–786 (2010).20948548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Ramirez-OrtizZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>G. . The scavenger receptor SCARF1 mediates the clearance of apoptotic cells and prevents autoimmunity. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 14, 917–926 (2013).23892722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>TaylorP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>R. . A hierarchical role for classical pathway complement proteins in the clearance of apoptotic cells in vivo. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Med. 192, 359–366 (2000).10934224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>BottoM. . Homozygous C1q deficiency causes glomerulonephritis associated with multiple apoptotic bodies. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Genet. 19, 56–59 (1998).9590289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>TangyeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>G., MaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>S., BrinkR. &amp; DeenickE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>K. The good, the bad and the ugly—T-FH cells in human health and disease. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13, 412–426 (2013).23681096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>UenoH., BanchereauJ. &amp; VinuesaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>G. Pathophysiology of T follicular helper cells in humans and mice. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 16, 142–152 (2015).25594465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>CrottyS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>T. Follicular Helper Cell Differentiation, Function, and Roles in Disease. Immunity 41, 529–542 (2014).25367570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>CrottyS. Follicular Helper CD4 T Cells (T-FH). Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 29, 621–663 (2011).21314428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>ForsterR. . A putative chemokine receptor, BLR1, directs B cell migration to defined lymphoid organs and specific anatomic compartments of the spleen. Cell 87, 1037–1047 (1996).8978608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>ChenL. &amp; FliesD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>B. Molecular mechanisms of T cell co-stimulation and co-inhibition. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13, 227–242 (2013).23470321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Good-JacobsonK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>L. . PD-1 regulates germinal center B cell survival and the formation and affinity of long-lived plasma cells. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 11, 535–U107 (2010).20453843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>NishimuraH., NoseM., HiaiH., MinatoN. &amp; HonjoT. Development of lupus-like autoimmune diseases by disruption of the PD-1 gene encoding an ITIM motif-carrying immunoreceptor. Immunity 11, 141–151 (1999).10485649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>WaterhouseP. . Lymphoproliferative disorders with early lethality in mice deficient in Ctla-4. Science 270, 985–988 (1995).7481803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>HamsE. . Blockade of B7-H1 (programmed death ligand 1) enhances humoral immunity by positively regulating the generation of T follicular helper cells. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 186, 5648–5655 (2011).21490158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>PanG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>H. . Identification and functional characterization of DR6, a novel death domain-containing TNF receptor. FEBS Lett. 431, 351–356 (1998).9714541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>AggarwalB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>B. Signalling pathways of the TNF superfamily: A double-edged sword. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 3, 745–756 (2003).12949498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>SchmidtC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>S. . Enhanced B cell expansion, survival, and humoral responses by targeting death receptor 6. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Med. 197, 51–62 (2003).12515813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>LiuJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Q. . Enhanced CD4(+) T cell proliferation and Th2 cytokine production in DR6-deficient mice. Immunity 15, 23–34 (2001).11485735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>SchmidtC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>S. . Resistance to myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein-induced experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis by death receptor 6-deficient mice. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 175, 2286–2292 (2005).16081797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>VenkataramanC., JustenK., ZhaoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Y., GalbreathE. &amp; NaS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Q. Death receptor-6 regulates the development of pulmonary eosinophilia and airway inflammation in a mouse model of asthma. Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Lett. 106, 42–47 (2006).16730379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>LiuJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Q. . Accelerated onset and increased severity of acute graft-versus-host disease following adoptive transfer of DR6-deficient T cells. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 169, 3993–3998 (2002).12244201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>KlimaM., BrouckovaA., KocM. &amp; AnderaL. T-cell activation triggers death receptor-6 expression in a NF-kappaB and NF-AT dependent manner. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 48, 1439–1447 (2011).21501873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>WestraH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>J. . Systematic identification of trans eQTLs as putative drivers of known disease associations. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Genet. 45, 1238–U1195 (2013).24013639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>SanterD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>M., WiedemanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>E., TealT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>H., GhoshP. &amp; ElkonK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>B. Plasmacytoid Dendritic Cells and C1q Differentially Regulate Inflammatory Gene Induction by Lupus Immune Complexes. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 188, 902–915 (2012).22147767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>TengY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>F., AquinoR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>S. &amp; ParkP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>W. Molecular functions of syndecan-1 in disease. Matrix Biol. 31, 3–16 (2012).22033227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>ZhangX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>L., WuC., SongJ., GotteM. &amp; SorokinL. Syndecan-1, a cell surface proteoglycan, negatively regulates initial leukocyte recruitment to the brain across the choroid plexus in murine experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 191, 4551–4561 (2013).24078687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>RopsA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>L. . Syndecan-1 deficiency aggravates anti-glomerular basement membrane nephritis. Kidney Int. 72, 1204–1215 (2007).17805240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>XuJ., ParkP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>W., KheradmandF. &amp; CorryD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>B. Endogenous attenuation of allergic lung inflammation by syndecan-1. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 174, 5758–5765 (2005).15843578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>MinowaK. . Elevated serum level of circulating syndecan-1 (CD138) in active systemic lupus erythematosus. Autoimmunity 44, 357–362 (2011).21320038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>OdendahlM. . Disturbed peripheral B lymphocyte homeostasis in systemic lupus erythematosus. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 165, 5970–5979 (2000).11067960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>CultonD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>A. . Early preplasma cells define a tolerance checkpoint for autoreactive B cells. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 176, 790–802 (2006).16393962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>KuesterM., KemmerzehlS., DahmsS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>O., RoeserD. &amp; ThanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>E. The crystal structure of death receptor 6 (DR6): a potential receptor of the amyloid precursor protein (APP). J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Biol. 409, 189–201 (2011).21463639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>OdegardJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>M. . ICOS-dependent extrafollicular helper T cells elicit IgG production via IL-21 in systemic autoimmunity. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Med. 205, 2873–U2102 (2008).18981236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>BaumjohannD. . Persistent Antigen and Germinal Center B Cells Sustain T Follicular Helper Cell Responses and Phenotype. Immunity 38, 596–605 (2013).23499493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>MohanC., YuY., MorelL., YangP. &amp; WakelandE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>K. Genetic dissection of Sle pathogenesis: Sle3 on murine chromosome 7 impacts T cell activation, differentiation, and cell death. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 162, 6492–6502 (1999).10352264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>YinY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>M. . Normalization of CD4(+) T cell metabolism reverses lupus. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Transl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Med. 7, 274ra18 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>CrispinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>C., KyttarisV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>C., JuangV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>T. &amp; TsokosG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>C. How signals and gene transcription aberrations dictate the systemic lupus erythematosus T cell phenotype. Trends Immunol. 29, 110–115 (2008).18249583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>PerryD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>J. . Murine Lupus Susceptibility Locus Sle1c2 Mediates CD4(+) T Cell Activation and Maps to Estrogen-Related Receptor gamma. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 189, 793–803 (2012).22711888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>FujikuraD. . CLIPR-59 regulates TNF-alpha-induced apoptosis by controlling ubiquitination of RIP1. Cell Death Dis. 3, e264 (2012).22297296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>ZotosD. . IL-21 regulates germinal center B cell differentiation and proliferation through a B cell-intrinsic mechanism. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Med. 207, 365–378 (2010).20142430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>MaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>S., DeenickE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>K., BattenM. &amp; TangyeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>G. The origins, function, and regulation of T follicular helper cells. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Med. 209, 1241–1253 (2012).22753927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>WeinsteinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>S. . B cells in T follicular helper cell development and function: separable roles in delivery of ICOS ligand and antigen. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 192, 3166–3179 (2014).24610013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>QiH., CannonsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>L., KlauschenF., SchwartzbergP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; GermainR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>N. SAP-controlled T-B cell interactions underlie germinal centre formation. Nature 455, 764–U762 (2008).18843362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>DeRosaD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>C., RyanP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>J., OkraglyA., WitcherD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; BenschopR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>J. Tumor-derived death receptor 6 modulates dendritic cell development. Cancer Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Immunother. 57, 777–787 (2008).17962943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>WangZ. . S5a binds to death receptor-6 to induce THP-1 monocytes to differentiate through the activation of the NF-kappa B pathway. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Cell Sci. 127, 3257–3268 (2014).24829148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>FujikuraD. . Type-I interferon is critical for FasL expression on lung cells to determine the severity of influenza. PLoS ONE 8, e55321 (2013).23408968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>BaumjohannD., OkadaT. &amp; AnselK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>M. Cutting edge: distinct waves of BCL6 expression during T follicular helper cell development. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 187, 2089–2092 (2011).21804014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>KurodaM. . Interaction between TIM-1 and NPC1 is important for cellular entry of Ebola virus. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Virol. 89, 6481–6493 (2015).25855742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>NosakaT. . STAT5 as a molecular regulator of proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis in hematopoietic cells. EMBO J. 18, 4754–4765 (1999).10469654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>RanF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>A. . Genome engineering using the CRISPR-Cas9 system. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Protoc. 8, 2281–2308 (2013).24157548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>D.F. and T.U. have filed an application under the Patent Cooperation Treaty (PCT), WO2015076282 A1, ‘Immunosuppressant' regarding the studies in the current paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>The remaining authors declare no competing financial interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Author contributions D.F. and T.U. conceived and designed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>D.F., M.I., T.E. and S.C. performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>D.F. analysed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>H.H. gave technical advice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>D.F. and T.U. wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Disease-specific induction of DR6<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in lupus-prone BWF1 mice.</title><p><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Total splenocytes obtained from the indicated mice were stained with anti-DR6 specific monoclonal antibody (clone 25-1) with anti-CD3, CD8 and CD4 specific Abs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>(a) Total splenocytes (gated as live singlet cells shown in Supplementary Fig. 15a) were analysed on CD3 versus DR6 dot plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Numbers in the dot plots indicates percentage of the cells gated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>(b) CD4+ T cells (CD3+ CD8− CD4+) of the total splenocytes were also analysed on CD4 versus DR6 dot plots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>(c) Quantification of the percentage of DR6+ cells in the CD4+ T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent standard deviation (s.d.) (n=5 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>(d) CD8+ T cells (CD3+ CD8+ CD4−) of splenocytes of the indicated mice were analysed on CD8 versus DR6 dot plots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>(e) DR6 expression (median of fluorescent intensity, MFI) on CD8+ T cells was also quantified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>(f) Actual numbers of total CD4+ T or CD8+ T cells (detected as shown in Supplementary Fig. 15b) were also counted in splenocytes obtained from these mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>(n=5 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistical significance (P&lt;0.05, Student's t-test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>DR6 expression on Tfh cells of lupus-prone BWF1 mice.</title><p><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>(a) DR6+ CD4+ cells of 24-week-old female BWF1 mice were stained with PE-conjugated anti-Bcl6 or isotype matched control Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>The antibody specific signals of the cells are shown in histogram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>(b) 7AAD− CD19− CD4+ splenocytes obtained from the indicated mice were analysed on CXCR5 versus PD1 dot plots for recognizing Tfh (PD1high CXCR5high) and pre-Tfh (PD1int CXCR5int) or non-Tfh (PD1− CXCR5− ) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>(c) The Tfh cell populations of 24-week-old female BWF1 mice were sorted and then Tnfrsf21 mRNA expression in these fractionated cells was analysed by quantitative PCR (qPCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>(n=5 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>(d) Both DR6 and CXCR4 expressions of the indicated Tfh cell populations that were detected as in b are also shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>For detecting Tfh cell populations, gate strategy that was shown in Supplementary Fig. 15c was used in b–d. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Identification of syndecan-1 as a functional binding partner for the DR6 ectodomain.</title><p><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>(a; left panel) Total splenocytes of B6 mice were stained with biotinylated murine DR6-Fc plus allophycocyanin-conjugated streptavidin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>(upper right panel) Cells bound to DR6-Fc among live singlet splenocytes were analysed on FSC versus SSC dot plots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>(lower right panel) The gating shown in the FSC versus SSC dot plot is also schematically explained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>(b) Total splenocytes were also stained with DR6-Fc and antibody for detecting the indicated cell type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>(c) A20 or DO11.10-T cells were stained with DR6-Fc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>DR6-Fc specific fluorescent intensity of these cell lines is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>(d) DO11.10-T cells transfected with a cDNA library derived from A20 cells were stained with DR6-Fc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>The transfectants bound to DR6-Fc were collected by four rounds of sorting and expansion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>(e) After the fifth round of sorting, the cDNA library inserted in genomic DNA of the selected transfectants was isolated as a single cDNA fragment (∼3,000 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>(f) Intensity of DR6-Fc staining on DO11.10-T cells ectopically expressing Syndecan-1 of mouse (mSdc1) or human (hSdc1) or empty plasmid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>(g) Endogenous syndecan-1 of A20 cells was precipitated with the indicated Fc-fusion proteins and detected as described in Methods section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>WT means Fc protein fused with the extracellular region of DR6 wild type, ΔCRD1 means the fusion protein lacking CRD1, ΔCRD2, lacking CRD2, ΔCRD3, lacking CRD3 or ΔCRD4, lacking CRD4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>(h) DO11.10-T cells were transfected with the indicated reporter plasmid with reference plasmid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>The cells were then stimulated with the indicated combination of recombinant syndecan-1 protein (recSdc1, 30 nM) and anti-CD3 Ab (10 μg ml−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>Six hours after the stimulation, reporter activities of the cells were assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>(n=3 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>(i) Parental DO11.10-T or its DR6-knockout clone (G510-8-7 or G510-10-4) was stimulated as described in h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Twelve hours after the stimulation, IL-2 production of the cells was assessed as described in Methods section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>(n=3 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Details of the DR6 knock out single cell clones is also shown in Supplementary Fig. 1c,d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Asterisks or NS in each panel indicate statistical significance (P&lt;0.05, Student's t-test) or not significance, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Syndecan-1 induction on GC B cells in lupus-prone mice.</title><p><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>(a–e) Spleens were isolated from 24-week-old female BWF1, NZB or B6 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Splenic cryosections obtained from the BWF1 (a) or NZB (b) mice were stained by anti-GL7 (left panel) and syndecan-1 (right panel) specific antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Additional anti-CD4 Ab staining was also used for identifying the border between B and T cell zone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>Representative images of at least 3 independent fields per slide are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>B, B cell zone; T, T cell zone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Dashed line indicates the border between each region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>Bar=100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>(c) GL7+ CD19+ and GL7− CD19+ B cell populations obtained from the indicated mice were detected by flow cytometry with the gate strategy that is shown in Supplementary Fig. 15d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of syndecan-1 (upper panel) and CD19 (lower panel) on the detected B cell populations were shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>(n=3 for B6, 5 for NZB, 5 for BWF1 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>(d) Mean number (upper panel) or percentage (lower) of the GL7+ CD19+ GC B cell in live total splenocytes obtained from the indicated mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>(n=3 for B6, 5 for NZB, 5 for BWF1 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>(e) The number (upper panel) or percent (lower) of pre-Tfh (left) or Tfh cells (right) of live total splenocytes from the indicated mice are also analysed with the gate strategy shown in Supplementary Fig. 15c. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>(n=5 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>(f) CD3+ CD4+ PD1high/int CXCR5high/int CXCR4+ cells were isolated from 24-week-old female BWF1 mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>The cells were stimulated with the indicated combinations of recSdc1 (30 nM), anti-CD3 Ab (10 μg ml−1) and anti-CD28 Ab (10 μg ml−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Seventy-two hours after the indicated stimulations, Il-21 mRNA production in the cells was analysed by qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>(n=3 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>ND, not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>Asterisks in each panel indicate statistical significance (P&lt;0.05, Student's t-test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Anti-DR6-specific antibody delays lupus-like syndrome progress in lupus-prone mice.</title><p><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>(a) Effect of 25-1 Ab (25-1) or nonspecific rat IgG (ctrl-IgG; 10 μg ml−1) administration on Il-21 production of CD3+ CD4+ PD1high/int CXCR5high/int CXCR4+ cells was assessed as described in Fig. 4f. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>(b–d) 15-week-old female BWF1 mice were intraperitoneally administered nonspecific control rat IgG (ctrl-IgG) or 25-1 Ab (300 μg per mouse every 2 days, from 15 to 27 weeks old; n=8 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>(b) anti-dsDNA Ab production in sera of these mice was assessed by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>(n=8 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>(c) Percentages of proteinuria positive (&gt;100 mg protein per dl) mice in each group are shown (P=0.0314 by Gray test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>(d) The survival rate of these groups is also shown (P=0.0251 by Log-rank test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>(e–i) Twenty-four-week-old proteinuria-positive female BWF1 mice were treated as described above (until 32 weeks old) (n=4 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Two days after the last administration, frequency of DR6+ cells in CD4+ T cells (e), GL7+ GC B cell in B220+ B cells (f) or syndecan-1high B220− plasma cells in live total splenocytes (g) obtained from these mice was assessed by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>Gate strategies that were used for identifying each cell population were shown in Supplementary Fig. 15a–e. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>Error bar: s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>(n=4 per group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>(h) Splenic cryosections obtained from these mice were stained by GL7 Ab for detecting GCs (magenta). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>The sections were also stained by anti-B220 Ab (green) for detecting B cell area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>Bar, 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>The results obtained from the other sections are also represented in Supplementary Fig. 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>(i) Area of GL7+ in each section was also calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Error bar, s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>(n=4–6 per section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>Asterisks in each panel indicate statistical significance (P&lt;0.05, Student's t-test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms13957-f5"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
