<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5484670</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4606</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-04606-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A novel stress response mechanism, triggered by indole, involved in quorum quenching enzyme MomL and iron-sulfur cluster in Muricauda olearia Th120 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Xinxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiao-Hua</given-names></name><address><email>xhzhang@ouc.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2152 3263</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4422.0</institution-id><institution>College of Marine Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Ocean University of China, </institution></institution-wrap>Qingdao, 266003 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory for Marine Ecology and Environmental Science, Qingdao National Laboratory for Marine Science and Technology, Qingdao, 266071 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>4252</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Indole, as a signal molecule, is involved in multiple physiological behavior including biofilm formation, antibiotic resistance and virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this study, we demonstrated that indole was involved in iron deficient and H2O2 stress response in Muricauda olearia Th120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis showed that totally 206 genes were regulated by exogenous indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Besides, momL-suf gene cluster, consisting of quorum quenching enzyme coding gene momL and iron-sulfur biosynthetic genes suf, were involved in indole-induced stress response pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The result indicated that indole not only up-regulated momL-suf gene cluster, but also enhanced the MomL secretion and the growth rates of MomL-bearing strains in H2O2 stress and iron deficient culture conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Co-incubation of M. olearia Th120 and Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. carotovorum under H2O2 condition revealed that M. olearia Th120 bearing MomL possessed an increased competitive advantage, whereas its competitor had a reduced survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The phenomenon that quorum quenching enzyme is triggered by stress factor has been rarely reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The study also opens a new clue to explore the indole function towards quorum quenching factor in bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Quorum sensing (QS) is a population-dependent behavior that enables bacteria to communicate with each other and to regulate downstream gene expression in response to environmental changes1–5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>During growth, bacteria produce a type of small molecule known as an autoinducer (AI), which can bind to receptor proteins and trigger signal pathway cascades when the AI concentrations reach a threshold value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>At present, several types of AIs have been discovered, such as the N-acyl homoserine lactones (AHLs) common in many Gram-negative bacteria1, 6, oligopeptides in Gram-positive bacteria and AI-2 in both Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria7–9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Indole is another signal molecule which has recently received increased attention as a putative QS signal molecule10, 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Many Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria encode a single copy of the tnaA gene in their chromosome and produce indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>It plays diverse biological roles including biofilm formation, sporulation and virulence10, 12–14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It has also been shown that indole, via two component signal transduction systems, increases antibiotic resistance by inducing exporter and transporter genes in E. coli 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Hence, it is possible that these two-component signal systems can be used as indole sensors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, the indole signaling pathway and its function in stress response have not been comprehensively studied, especially in beneficial microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated that QS systems are closely related to bacterial disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Interfering with QS systems, named quorum quenching (QQ), is a promising control strategy for bacterial diseases because it could decrease the expression of virulence factors of pathogens15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Normally, virulence factor is the weapon for pathogens during adverse situation, so theoretically, QQ could weaken pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The marine bacteria Muricauda olearia Th120 exhibits strong QQ activity, which makes this strain a potential biocontrol agent16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, a novel AHL lactonase, MomL, was identified from M. olearia Th12017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>MomL belongs to the metallo-β-lactamase superfamily and shows the highest identity (56.8%) with Aii20J from Tenacibaculum sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>20J18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Besides, MomL possesses 54.4% and 24.5% identity with FiaL and well-studied AiiA from Flaviramulus ichthyoenteri Th78T and Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>240B1 respectively19–21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>As a novel AHL lactonase in marine isolates, MomL shows promising activity against C6-homoserine lactone (C6-HSL), reaching a catalytic efficiency of 2.9 × 105 s−1M−1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Iron-sulfur (Fe/S) proteins, characterized by the presence of an iron-sulfur cluster, play crucial roles in multiple cellular processes in both prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The biogenesis of iron-sulfur clusters has been extensively studied in Escherichia coli 22, 23, in which there are two iron-sulfur cluster biosynthesis gene operons: the ISC (iron-sulfur cluster) and Suf (sulfur assimilation) systems23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>ISC genes are organized as iscSUA-hscBA-fdx, whereas Suf genes are organized as sufABCDSE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The ISC gene cluster is thought to play housekeeping roles, including the formation of a variety of Fe/S proteins, whereas the Suf system is active under stress conditions, such as iron starvation22, 23. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, momL is located within the stress-response suf operon and is closely linked to sufB and sufC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>This gene organization has not been previously reported in other organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Also, little is known about how the QQ factor momL is regulated by QS in M. olearia Th120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focused on the regulation mechanism of signal molecular indole towards the stress-response genes suf and QQ gene momL, and it firstly described the triggering of the expression of a QQ enzyme by stress factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Material and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Bacterial strains, media and growth conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>M. olearia Th120 was cultured in marine broth 2216 at 28 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The AHL biosensor Chromobacterium violaceum CV026 was cultured in LB medium at 28 °C17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Indole (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, USA) stock solutions were prepared in methanol, and the 2,2′-dipyridyl (Solarbio) stock solution was prepared in ethanol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>H2O2 sensitivity assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>M. olearia Th120 was grown in marine broth 2216 at 28 °C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The cultures were then diluted with fresh medium to a final optical density at 600 nm (OD600) of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The cell suspensions were mixed with H2O2 or H2O2 with 0.2 mM indole at final concentrations of 0.5, 1 or 2 mM and were incubated at 28 °C for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The cells were serially diluted and spread onto marine agar plates, and the colony numbers were counted from each of the plates after 48–72 hours of incubation24. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction, reverse transcription PCR, and real-time-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>M. olearia Th120 cells were collected after reaching an OD600 of 0.8, and the RNA was extracted using an RNA extraction kit (Omega) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For indole treatments, samples with different cultivation conditions were harvested as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>For the H2O2 treatment assay, mid-log-phase cultures of M. olearia Th120 were harvested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After a 30-min treatment with 300 μM H2O2, the RNA was extracted and was reverse-transcribed to cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR was performed in a total reaction volume of 20 μl containing 250 nM primers, 10 μl of SYBR green PCR master mix, 8.5 μl of RNase-free water, and 0.5 μl of a 10-fold-diluted cDNA template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The 16S rRNA was used as a reference gene25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Relative gene expression level was analyzed using 2−ΔΔCt method (ΔΔCt = ΔCt(test) − ΔCt(calibrator), ΔCt(test) = Ct(target, test) − Ct(reference, test) and ΔCt(calibrator) = Ct(target, calibrator) − Ct(reference, calibrator)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The primers for real-time PCR are listed in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed with a StepOne Real-Time PCR System (AB Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The program was designed as follows: pre-incubation at 95 °C for 10 min followed by 35 cycles of 15 seconds at 95 °C, 30 seconds at 55 °C and 30 seconds at 72 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>After 2 hours, cycle threshold (CT) values and melting curves of each reaction were analyzed using StepOne Software v2.2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Extracellular secretion detection of MomL </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>M. olearia Th120 cells were grown for 48 hours, and the OD600 values of the samples (treated and untreated) were measured using a spectrophotometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The cultures were diluted with fresh medium to the same OD600 value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Filter-sterilized (0.22 μm pore size) supernatant and cells were collected, followed by a 10-min centrifugation at 4 °C at 6000 × g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The AHL biosensor Chromobacterium violaceum CV02626, which could produce violacein induced by AHL, was cultured on LB medium at 28 °C to an OD600 of 0.1, and 1 mL of culture and C6-HSL at a final concentration of 0.5 μM were added to solid LB medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The extracellular secretions of samples from different culture conditions were added to the medium, which was placed in an incubator at 28 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>After 24 hours of culture, transparent circles were observed if AHL was degraded and violacein synthesis was inhibited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The area of transparent circle was calculated and the mean value of three repeated experiment was used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Protein domains were analyzed by SMART software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/smart/set_mode.cgi?%20NORMAL=1">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/smart/set_mode.cgi?NORMAL=1</ext-link>) for online analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The suf and momL sequences of the different strains were analyzed by BLAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Annotation and bioinformatic analysis were performed on the flanking genes of momL by genome sequencing and EMBOSS (The European Molecular Biology Open Software Suite) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emboss.open-bio.org/">http://emboss.open-bio.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>DNAMAN software was used to compare the three copies of the OxyR protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Primers for real-time fluorescent quantitative PCR were designed using Primer Premier 527. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Co-cultures of Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. carotovorum (Pcc) and E. coli </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The two types of bacteria were cultured in LB medium separately, and cells were collected by centrifugation when the OD600 reached 0.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The two types of bacteria were mixed and cultured in 10% tryptic soy broth (TSB) medium with 2 mM H2O2 for 6 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The bacterial co-culture was serially diluted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>At each concentration, dilutions were spread onto two LB plates, one of which contained 25 µg/mL Km. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The survival of Pcc was the difference between the bacterial counts of the two LB plates (NumbersLB − NumbersLB+Km). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Co-cultures of P. carotovorum subsp. carotovorum (Pcc) and M. olearia Th120 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Pcc and M. olearia Th120 were cultured in LB and MA media28, 29 separately until the OD600 reached 0.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Cultures of the two bacteria were centrifuged, and the two types of cells were collected and mixed together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Then, the mixture was inoculated into 10% TSB medium containing 2 mM H2O2 and cultured for 6 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>During the culturing, various concentrations of MomL protein were added into the medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>After culturing, the cultures were serially diluted and spread onto MA and LB plates, separately (MA is the regular medium for marine bacterium M. olearia Th120, and LB is for Pcc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Besides, M. olearia Th120 can not survive on LB medium, while, Pcc can not live on MA medium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, changes in the survival of the two bacteria in the different conditions were observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing of M. olearia Th120 (treated with and without indole) was performed by the Biozeron company in Shanghai, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Total RNA of M. olearia Th120 was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) and treated with DNase I (Takara). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>RNA quality was determined using a Bioanalyser 2100 (Agilent), after which the RNA was quantified using a NanoDrop 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>RNA transcriptome libraries were constructed following a TruSeq RNA sample preparation kit from Illumina (San Diego, CA), using 5 μg of total RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>rRNA was removed using a RiboZero rRNA removal kit (Epicenter) and fragmented with fragmentation buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>cDNA synthesis, end repair, A-base addition and ligation of the Illumina-indexed adaptors was performed following Illumina’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Libraries were then size selected for cDNA target fragments of 200–300 bp on 2% Low Range Ultra Agarose followed by PCR amplified using Phusion DNA polymerase (NEB) for 15 PCR cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>After generating the clusters, library sequencing was performed on an Illumina Hiseq platform, to create paired-end reads with lengths of 150 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The raw paired-end reads were trimmed with SeqPrep (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jstjohn/SeqPrep">https://github.com/jstjohn/SeqPrep</ext-link>) and quality controlled with Sickle (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Then, clean reads were aligned to the reference genome using Rockhopper (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cs.wellesley.edu/~btjaden/Rockhopper/">http://cs.wellesley.edu/~btjaden/Rockhopper/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Rockhopper was a user-friendly software for bacterial RNA-seq data anaylsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This software was used to calculate gene expression level as RPKM (reads per kilobase transcriptome per million mapped reads) with default parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>RPKM = (106 * C)/(N * L), with C = Number of reads mapped to a gene; N = Total mapped reads in the experiment; L = gene length in base-pairs for a gene (Kb) EdgeR30 was used for differential gene expression analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/edgeR.html">https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/edgeR.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>To study the functions of the differentially expressed genes, GO functional enrichment and KEGG pathway analysis were carried out by Goatools (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tanghaibao/Goatools">https://github.com/tanghaibao/Goatools</ext-link>) and KOBAS (http://kobas.cbi.pku.edu.cn/home.do) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Gene expression changes higher than 2-fold with P-values less than 0.05 were regarded as reliable and marked differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The sequencing data were deposited in NCBI Sequence Read Archive with accession number PRJNA375720. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Indole improved survival state of M. olearia Th120 in H2O2 stress and iron deficient conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Previous studies indicated that indole is responsible for multiple physiological behaviors, especially in enteric bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Besides, it was reported that indole could leads bacterial persistence formation by activating stress responses31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>However, the indole function towards stress responses in beneficial bacteria M. olearia Th120 is largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Our experiments indicate that indole can improve the survival of M. olearia Th120 in the presence of H2O2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the survival of cells in 0.5, 1, and 2 mM H2O2 were 80%, 70%, and 45%, respectively, in the presence of 200 μM indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>However, the survival of the cells were 60%, 45%, and 15% in the presence of H2O2 but the absence of indole (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Besides, the survival state under iron deficient was also detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The growth rate assay indicated that 200 μM exogenous indole caused M. olearia Th120 to have an improved growth rate in lag and exponential phases under ferric-deficient conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>No obvious difference was observed after stationary phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>What is more, indole did not affect the cell yield of M. olearia Th120 (Fig. 1B and Fig. S1).Figure 1Function of indole for M. olearia Th120 in iron deficient and H2O2 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>(A) The survival of M. olearia Th120 upon H2O2 treatment with or without indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(B) M. olearia Th120 growth rate assay under conditions of ferric infertility (100 μM 2,2′-dipyridyl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the standard deviations of three replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>suf-momL was involved in indole-induced stress responses in a co-transcriptional manner </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In E. coli, the suf operon is responsible for resistance to iron starvation23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We focused on the study of whether suf of M. olearia Th120 was involved in indole-induced iron deficient and H2O2 stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, genome sequencing and bioinformatic studies indicated that the suf genes of M. olearia Th120 is co-localized within the momL gene, an arrangement that has not been reported in similar well-studied genes, such as aiiA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The classic suf locus contains sufA, sufB, sufC, sufD, sufS, and sufE (Fig. S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>SufS and SufE are desulfurase homologs, whereas SufC is an ATPase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>SufS and SufE are responsible for passing the sulfur that dissociates from cysteine to the Fe-S assembly complex, which is composed of two SufC units and single copies of both SufB and SufD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>With the participation of the cofactor FADH2, the Suf proteins assemble iron and sulfate into Fe-S clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>SufA is responsible for transporting Fe-S clusters to the aconitase, AcnB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, suf was always observed as an intact gene cluster with no other unrelated genes among the suf genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In M. olearia Th120, momL is inserted between sufB and sufC, and these three genes are linked closely to each other. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>To analyze the transcriptional features of momL and suf, orfE/orf1/sufA/momL/sufD/orf10 and orfF were chosen for real-time PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In normal condition, the sufA, momL, sufD, orf10 and orfF transcription levels were highly similar, whereas the transcript level of orfE, whose expression was approximately 2-fold higher compared with that of sufA, differed greatly from the expression level of sufA-orfF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the expression level of orf1 was very low: only 20% of that of sufA (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>These differences suggest that suf and momL are co-transcribed, whereas orf1 and orfE are expressed independently of suf-momL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In addition, orf10, which encodes a novel Fe-S cluster synthesis protein, and orfF, which encodes an unknown protein, are also co-transcribed with suf-momL.Figure 2The transcriptional analysis (Ct values) of related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>(A) Transcription levels of genes in the suf-momL operon with (black) or without (gray) the iron-chelating agent 2,2′-dipyridyl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>(B) Transcription levels of suf-momL genes in iron-deficient condition with (black) or without indole (transparent). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(C) indole-induced transcriptional change in H2O2 condition (black, with indole; transparent, without indole). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>(D) The effects of indole on a series of suf regulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the standard deviations of three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>For statistical analysis, ***/**/* means P &lt; 0.001, P &lt; 0.01, and P &lt; 0.05, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>suf-momL was involved in indole-induced stress responses pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The transcription of suf-momL was analyzed under indole-induced iron-deficient and H2O2 condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Without indole, the sufA, sufD, orf10 and orfF expression levels were approximately 2-fold higher in an environment containing the intracellular iron (II) chelator 2,2′-dipyridyl (100 μM), whereas the orfE and orf1 expression levels were not significantly altered in this iron-deficient condition (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>While, with 200 μM indole, the transcription levels of sufA, sufD, and sufE increased 6-, 6-, and 7-fold, respectively, and the transcription level of momL increased nearly 7-fold in this iron-deficient condition (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in H2O2 stress condition, indole up-regulated sufA, sufD, sufE and momL to 3–4 fold changes respectively (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have indicated that three proteins are involved in regulating the suf genes: OxyR, a peroxide-sensing positive regulator; Fur, a ferric uptake regulator; and HimA/D, a bacterial nucleoid DNA-binding protein that induces increased suf expression during oxidative stress23, 32, 33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A bioinformatic analysis of M. olearia Th120 revealed that the genome includes not only the fur and him genes but also three copies of the oxyR gene, designated oxyR1/2/3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>These oxyR genes contain well-conserved DNA-binding sites (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional analysis showed that there were no marked changes in the levels of oxyR2, oxyR3, fur, or himA in the presence of indole, whereas oxyR1 expression increased significantly at 3.2-fold over normal conditions (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>MomL secretion ability in different iron conditions was also studied using the C. violaceum mutant CV026 as an indicator strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>MomL secretion decreased in an environment of adequate iron nutrition, whereas it was enhanced in iron deficient conditions (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In iron deficient condition, MomL secretion increased with the addition of indole, which increased 1.2-fold in the presence of 10 and 50 μM indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>At a concentration of 200 μM indole, MomL secretion increased approximately 2-fold in iron deficient condition (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Besides, under H2O2 condition, indole could also increase MomL secretion significantly (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Because of MomL known as AHL lactonase, to analyze whether the AHL lactonase activity plays role in H2O2 condition, co-cultivation assays of different bacterial species were performed. P. carotovorum subsp. carotovorum (Pcc), once classified as Erwinia carotovorum and regarded as a ubiquitous plant pathogen producing virulence factors through the induction of the signal molecule AHL, was used in this experiment34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In 10% TSB medium with 2 mM H2O2, the survival of Pcc were 43% and 40% when Pcc cells were cultured alone or co-cultured with E. coli-pET24a, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Because the survival of Pcc was calculated by formula NumbersLB − NumbersLB+Km (method part for detailed information), in order to exclude the possibility of spontaneous Km antibiotic resistance of Pcc, control experiment was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The result indicated that Km is completely lethal for Pcc (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>However, the Pcc survival was significantly reduced to 21% when the cells were co-cultured with E. coli-momL, the E. coli strain containing heterologous gene momL (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Pcc and M. olearia Th120 co-culture assays were also performed. Pcc had a similar survival with M. olearia Th120 under H2O2 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>However, adding exogenous purified MomL protein led to a decreased survival of Pcc, and correspondingly, an increased survival of M. olearia Th120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As a control assay, boiled inactived MomL had no function (Fig. 4B and Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional analysis indicated that the exogenous MomL protein can significantly reduce the expression and the production of the pectate lyase gene, the major virulence factor of Pcc (Fig. 4C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>To study the effect of MomL on pectate lyase expression, four related genes (pectate lyase gene pel, pectate lyase precursor 1 gene pelp1, pectate lyase precursor 2 gene pelp2 and pectin lyase regulator gene pelr) were detected by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of pel, pelp1 and pelp2 decreased significantly in the presence of MomL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, the regulator gene pelr was up-regulated, leading to speculation that pelr plays a negative regulatory role in pectin lyase expression (Fig. 4C).Figure 3MomL secretion capacity analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>(A) The secretion capacity of MomL in different iron environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(B) Indole’s function for the MomL secretion capacity in iron deficient condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>(C) Indole’s function for the MomL secretion capacity in H2O2 condition. Figure 4Co-cultivation assays of different bacterial species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(A) P. carotovorum subsp. carotovorum (Pcc) and E. coli-momL co-cultivation. E. coli and E. coli- pET24a are used for the negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(B) Pcc and Muricauda olearia Th120 co-culture on 10% TSB medium containing 2 mM H2O2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>After culturing, the cultures were serially diluted and spread onto MA and LB plates, separately (MA and LB were medium for M. olearia Th120 and Pcc respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>What is more, marine bacterium M. olearia Th120 can not survive on LB medium, while, Pcc can not live on MA medium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(C) Transcriptional analysis of pectate lyase genes of M. olearia Th120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>(D) Detection of pectate lyase production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis of M. olearia Th120 under indole conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>To further analyze the function of indole, we performed transcriptome sequencing of M. olearia Th120 with and without 200 μM exogenous indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Illumina deep sequencing produced approximately 38 M total clean reads from the 5.5 Gbp clean sequence data for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Around 99% of the clean reads had quality scores over the Q20 value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Over 97.9% of the clean reads were mapped to the reference genome (PRJNA244114). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In total, 2,885 genes were detected and quantified among all of the samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>To test the reliability of the transcriptome assay, we randomly chose 20 genes to perform real-time PCR and found that compared with the transcriptome data, the R 2 value (Pearson correlation coefficient) was 0.9185 (Fig. S4), indicating a good correlation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Moreover, consistent with real-time PCR assay, suf-momL gene cluster and oxyR1 were identified as indole-induced genes in the transcriptome assay (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Volcano plots, which integrated both the P value and fold change of each transcript, were constructed to present the general scattering of the transcripts and filter the differentially expressed genes for indole treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Genes regulated by indole were pooled together (Fig. 5, pink and blue color). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>A total of 206 genes were regulated more than 2-fold by exogenous indole (P &gt; 0.05), among which 104 genes were up-regulated and 102 were down-regulated.Figure 5Volcano plots of the overall scatter of gene transcription of M. olearia Th120 (with or without indole treatment). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>P value &lt; 0.05 and |log2 (foldchange)| &gt; 1 were selected as the criteria to filter genes that were significantly regulated (down-regulated genes blue dots, up-regulated genes pink dots). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The differentially expressed genes were functionally annotated after being input into the GO analysis and were divided into three major categories: biological process, molecular function and cellular component (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>For the sample treated by indole, the most affected biological process were associated with cellular process and metabilic process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, multiple genes for response to stimulus and signaling were also affected by indole in M. olearia Th120. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, for cellular component, the significantly regulated part were membrane and membrane-related part. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>For molecular function, transporter and binding activity were mainly affected by indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The KOBAS analysis revealed the enriched KEGG pathways under indole treatement (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Four gene categories, that is, lysine biosynthesis, vancomycin resistance, C5-branched dibasic acid metabolism and two-component system were significantly enriched.Figure 6Functional categories of the regulated genes, broadly separated into ‘biological process’, ‘cellular component’, and ‘molecular function’, based on Gene Ontology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Besides KEGG and GO analysis, our transcriptome results also revealed that five TonB system genes responded to indole, and all of them were up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Among them, four were noted as TonB-dependent receptors, and their changes in expression ranged from 2 to 8 times the expression levels of indole-free samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>One TonB protein-coding gene was up-regulated 6.5-fold (Table S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>TonB systems can function in iron acquisition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 24 membrane proteins, containing transport systems and two component regulatory system proteins, were regulated by indole, among which 21 were up-regulated and only 3 were down-regulated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>M. olearia Th120, which was previously isolated from the body surface mucus of Paralichthys olivaceus, produces enzymes capable of degrading signal molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Located in the genome of M. olearia Th120, momL encodes an AHL lactonase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The location of the momL gene is unique, as it is located within the iron-sulfur protein-coding suf genes, with momL inserted between sufB and sufC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The combination of QQ gene(s) and stress-response gene(s) has not previously been observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The location of the momL gene does not disrupt any of the genes in the operon, suggesting that the momL location is an adaptation mechanism and not a random insertion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In addition, the momL gene is co-transcribed with suf under iron deficient and H2O2 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It is promising to further study whether the AHL lactonase role or other novel function of MomL is needed for the phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Based on this study, one possible reason is that MomL is secreted into extracellular spaces to degrade the AHL signal molecules of competitors and we speculate that this mechanism might possibly damage the competitors’ QS systems, ultimately decrease the virulence factor “weapon” production and the survival of the competitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We are constructing MomL mutant with no enzymatic activity using directed evolution strategy to explore the involved mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the results above also suggest that suf and momL are not combined together randomly, but rather, that this special arrangement allows two otherwise unrelated survival mechanisms to be activated by the same environmental stimuli, enhancing cell survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>However, because of the lack of genetic operation system of M. olearia Th120, we can not deleted momL, and there is currently no direct evidence to prove how momL contributes to increased survival of cells under H2O2 or iron limitation stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Besides, lacking of Pcc genetic operation system at this stage make us unable to delete related genes and unclear about how quorum quenching enzyme MomL decreased the survival of Pcc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We are undergoing these experiments in our group now. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The QQ activity of M. olearia Th120 can be used in biocontrol for the control and prevention of aquatic animal diseases17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>As MomL expression is low in cells, it is important to improve its expression for future applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Signal molecules regulate a series of genes, affecting the physiological activities of a variety of cell types31, 35, 36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a variety of signal molecules have been tested for improving MomL expression levels in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, an well-studied signal molecule, indole, had a notable effect on suf-momL transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Although it is well-studied that indole, as a QS signal molecular, plays important roles in bacteria including biofilm formation, antibiotic resistance and virulence, the mutual regulation between QS and QQ in bacterial is largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrated that indole could not only trigger stress-repsonse genes suf, but also regulate QQ enzyme factor momL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>This is also the first time description that QQ enzyme is triggered by stress factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Experiments suggested that oxyR1, which is regulated by indole, correlated with suf-momL expression and MomL secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Correspondingly, the addition of indole increases the survival of cells during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We speculate that indole may act as a signaling molecule to regulate the oxyR1 gene in an unknown way when it senses changes in environmental conditions (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In addition, it is hypothesized that the three oxyR genes of M. olearia have different functions to allow for more versatile responses to the environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This discovery of a fundamental response system opens new ways to make this strain more useful as a beneficial bacterium for disease control in the future.Figure 7Schematic diagram of the indole and suf-momL signaling cascade pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Through transcriptome analyses, it was found that indole regulated more than 200 genes in M. olearia; these genes displayed a variety of functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>GO analysis indicated that multiple genes for response to stimulus were affected by indole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>It is speculated that these genes were either involved in indole-suf signal cascade pathway or among other stress response pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Besides, for cellular component, the significantly regulated part were membrane-related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, most of the membrane proteins were up-regulated under the regulation of indole, including transporters, permeases and TonB systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Based on this result, we hypothesize that cell membrane proteins play important roles when signaling molecules enter cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In addition, previous studies have shown that indole could affect the resistance of bacteria to antibiotics31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Our transcriptome study showed consistent result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The KOBAS analysis suggested that four KEGG pathways were regulated by indole treatement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Among the four enriched pathways, vancomycin resistance and two-component system were significantly enriched. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>We suggest that indole can either affect the transport capacity of the cell or change cell permeability to alter the resistance to antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec16"><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>supporting information </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-04606-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We are very grateful to Dr. Liangcheng Du and Mr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Stephen Wright in University of Nebraska-Lincoln for making suggestions and language modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Thanks to Mr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Liang Zeng in the Biozeron company in Shanghai for discussion about Transcriptome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Thanks to Dr. Kaihao Tang in Ocean University of China for valuable discussion and information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by projects from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31571970, 41276141 and 41506160) and Natural Science Foundation of Shandong Province (No. 2014ZRE29014). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: Y.W., X.Z., H.L. Performed the experiments: Y.W., H.L., X.C. Analyzed the data: X.Z., Y.W., H.L., X.C. Wrote the paper: Y.W., X.Z., H.L.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>1.NgWLBasslerBLBacterial quorum-sensing network architecturesAnnual review of genetics20094319722210.1146/annurev-genet-102108-134304<?supplied-pmid 19686078?>19686078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>2.WatersCMBasslerBLQuorum sensing: cell-to-cell communication in bacteriaAnnual review of cell and developmental biology20052131934610.1146/annurev.cellbio.21.012704.131001<?supplied-pmid 16212498?>16212498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>3.DaviesDGThe involvement of cell-to-cell signals in the development of a bacterial biofilmScience199828029529810.1126/science.280.5361.295<?supplied-pmid 9535661?>9535661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>4.GambelloMJIglewskiBHCloning and characterization of the Pseudomonas aeruginosa lasR gene, a transcriptional activator of elastase expressionJ Bacteriol19911733000300910.1128/jb.173.9.3000-3009.1991<?supplied-pmid 1902216?>1902216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>5.NealsonKHPlattTHastingsJWCellular control of the synthesis and activity of the bacterial luminescent systemJ Bacteriol1970104313322<?supplied-pmid 5473898?>5473898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>6.BiswaPDobleMProduction of acylated homoserine lactone by gram-positive bacteria isolated from marine waterFEMS microbiology letters2013343344110.1111/1574-6968.12123<?supplied-pmid 23489290?>23489290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>7.SaenzHLInducible expression and cellular location of AgrB, a protein involved in the maturation of the staphylococcal quorum-sensing pheromoneArchives of microbiology200017445245510.1007/s002030000223<?supplied-pmid 11195102?>11195102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>8.JohnsonMRPopulation density-dependent regulation of exopolysaccharide formation in the hyperthermophilic bacterium Thermotoga maritimaMolecular microbiology20055566467410.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04419.x<?supplied-pmid 15660994?>15660994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>9.PereiraCSThompsonJAXavierKBAI-2-mediated signalling in bacteriaFEMS microbiology reviews20133715618110.1111/j.1574-6976.2012.00345.x<?supplied-pmid 22712853?>22712853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>10.LeeJHLeeJIndole as an intercellular signal in microbial communitiesFEMS microbiology reviews20103442644410.1111/j.1574-6976.2009.00204.x<?supplied-pmid 20070374?>20070374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>11.LiXYangQDierckensKMiltonDLDefoirdtTRpoS and indole signaling control the virulence of Vibrio anguillarum towards gnotobiotic sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax) larvaePloS one20149e11180110.1371/journal.pone.0111801<?supplied-pmid 25360804?>25360804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>12.MartinoPDFursyRBretLSundararajuBPhillipsRSIndole can act as an extracellular signal to regulate biofilm formation of Escherichia coli and other indole-producing bacteriaCanadian journal of microbiology20034944344910.1139/w03-056<?supplied-pmid 14569285?>14569285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>13.LeeJJayaramanAWoodTKIndole is an inter-species biofilm signal mediated by SdiABMC microbiology200774210.1186/1471-2180-7-42<?supplied-pmid 17511876?>17511876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>14.HirakawaHInazumiYMasakiTHirataTYamaguchiAIndole induces the expression of multidrug exporter genes in Escherichia coliMolecular microbiology2005551113112610.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04449.x<?supplied-pmid 15686558?>15686558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>15.ClatworthyAEPiersonEHungDTTargeting virulence: a new paradigm for antimicrobial therapyNature chemical biology2007354154810.1038/nchembio.2007.24<?supplied-pmid 17710100?>17710100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>16.TangKEvaluation of a new high-throughput method for identifying quorum quenching bacteriaScientific reports20133293510.1038/srep02935<?supplied-pmid 24121744?>24121744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>17.TangKMomL, a novel marine-derived N-acyl homoserine lactonase from Muricauda oleariaApplied and environmental microbiology20158177478210.1128/AEM.02805-14<?supplied-pmid 25398866?>25398866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>18.MayerCRomeroMMurasAOteroAAii20J, a wide-spectrum thermostable N-acylhomoserine lactonase from the marine bacterium Tenacibaculum sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>20J, can quench AHL-mediated acid resistance in Escherichia coliApplied microbiology and biotechnology2015999523953910.1007/s00253-015-6741-8<?supplied-pmid 26092757?>26092757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>19.MombJMechanism of the quorum-quenching lactonase (AiiA) from Bacillus thuringiensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Substrate modeling and active site mutationsBiochemistry2008477715772510.1021/bi8003704<?supplied-pmid 18627130?>18627130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>20.LiuDMechanism of the quorum-quenching lactonase (AiiA) from Bacillus thuringiensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Product-bound structuresBiochemistry2008477706771410.1021/bi800368y<?supplied-pmid 18627129?>18627129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>21.ZhangYGenome analysis of Flaviramulus ichthyoenteri Th78(T) in the family Flavobacteriaceae: insights into its quorum quenching property and potential roles in fish intestineBMC genomics2015163810.1186/s12864-015-1275-0<?supplied-pmid 25652846?>25652846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>22.RocheBIron/sulfur proteins biogenesis in prokaryotes: formation, regulation and diversityBiochimica et biophysica acta2013182745546910.1016/j.bbabio.2012.12.010<?supplied-pmid 23298813?>23298813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>23.OuttenFWDjamanOStorzGA suf operon requirement for Fe-S cluster assembly during iron starvation in Escherichia coliMolecular microbiology20045286187210.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04025.x<?supplied-pmid 15101990?>15101990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>24.WangYBiosynthetic mechanism for sunscreens of the biocontrol agent Lysobacter enzymogenesPLoS One20138e6663310.1371/journal.pone.0066633<?supplied-pmid 23826105?>23826105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>25.WangYMechanisms involved in the functional divergence of duplicated GroEL chaperonins in Myxococcus xanthus DK1622PLoS genetics20139e100330610.1371/journal.pgen.1003306<?supplied-pmid 23437010?>23437010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>26.McCleanKHQuorum sensing and Chromobacterium violaceum: exploitation of violacein production and inhibition for the detection of N-acylhomoserine lactonesMicrobiology1997143Pt 123703371110.1099/00221287-143-12-3703<?supplied-pmid 9421896?>9421896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>27.SinghVKMangalamAKDwivediSNaikSPrimer premier: program for design of degenerate primers from a protein sequenceBioTechniques199824318319<?supplied-pmid 9494736?>9494736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>28.StanierRYStudies on Marine Agar-Digesting BacteriaJournal of bacteriology194142527559<?supplied-pmid 16560467?>16560467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>29.OppenheimerCHZoBellCEThe growth and viability of sixty three species of marine bacteria as influenced by hydrostatic pressureJournal of Marine Research1952111018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>30.TrapnellCDifferential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seqNat Biotechnol201331465310.1038/nbt.2450<?supplied-pmid 23222703?>23222703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>31.VegaNMAllisonKRKhalilASCollinsJJSignaling-mediated bacterial persister formationNature chemical biology2012843143310.1038/nchembio.915<?supplied-pmid 22426114?>22426114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>32.GranstonAENashHACharacterization of a set of integration host factor mutants deficient for DNA bindingJournal of molecular biology1993234455910.1006/jmbi.1993.1562<?supplied-pmid 8230206?>8230206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>33.FlammELWeisbergRAPrimary structure of the hip gene of Escherichia coli and of its product, the beta subunit of integration host factorJournal of molecular biology198518311712810.1016/0022-2836(85)90206-2<?supplied-pmid 3159903?>3159903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>34.GardanLGouyCChristenRSamsonRElevation of three subspecies of Pectobacterium carotovorum to species level: Pectobacterium atrosepticum sp. nov., Pectobacterium betavasculorum sp. nov. and Pectobacterium wasabiae sp. novInternational journal of systematic and evolutionary microbiology20035338139110.1099/ijs.0.02423-0<?supplied-pmid 12710602?>12710602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>35.HanYIdentification of a small molecule signaling factor that regulates the biosynthesis of the antifungal polycyclic tetramate macrolactam HSAF in Lysobacter enzymogenesApplied microbiology and biotechnology20159980181110.1007/s00253-014-6120-x<?supplied-pmid 25301587?>25301587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>36.GaoMCogginAYagnikKTeplitskiMRole of specific quorum-sensing signals in the regulation of exopolysaccharide II production within Sinorhizobium meliloti spreading coloniesPloS one20127e4261110.1371/journal.pone.0042611<?supplied-pmid 22912712?>22912712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
