<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gerona</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gerona</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journals of Gerontology Series A: Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1079-5006</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1758-535X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5106849</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glv217</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Temporal Development of Autonomic Dysfunction in Heart Failure: Effects of Age in an Ovine Rapid-pacing Model </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>Margaux A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>Elizabeth F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borland</surname><given-names>Samantha J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>Graeme J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Briston</surname><given-names>Sarah J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>Mark A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dibb</surname><given-names>Katharine M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Trafford</surname><given-names>Andrew W.</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><institution>Unit of Cardiac Physiology, Manchester Academic Health Sciences Centre</institution>.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Address correspondence to Andrew W. Trafford, Unit of Cardiac Physiology, Manchester Academic Health Sciences Centre, 3.24 Core Technology Facility, 46 Grafton Street, Manchester, M13 9NT, UK. E-mail: <email>Andrew.W.Trafford@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="fn-100"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Decision Editor: Rafael de Cabo, PHD </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>71</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1544</fpage><lpage>1552</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of The Gerontological Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Heart failure (HF) is predominantly a disease of older adults and characterized by extensive sympatho-vagal imbalance leading to impaired reflex control of heart rate (HR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, whether aging influences the development or extent of the autonomic imbalance in HF remains unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To address this, we used an ovine model of aging with tachypacing-induced HF to determine whether aging affects the chronotropic and inotropic responses to autonomic stimulation and reduction in heart rate variability (HRV) in HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We find that aging is associated with increased cardiac dimensions and reduced contractility before the onset of tachypacing, and these differences persist in HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the chronotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation was markedly attenuated in HF, and this occurred more rapidly in aged animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>By measuring HR during sequential autonomic blockade, our data are consistent with a reduced parasympathetic control of resting HR in aging, with young HF animals having an attenuated sympathetic influence on HR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Time-domain analyses of HR show a reduction in HRV in both young and aged failing animals, although HRV is lowest in aged HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, aging is associated with altered autonomic control and β-adrenergic responsiveness of HR, and these are exacerbated with the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Age-related pathology</kwd><kwd>Animal model</kwd><kwd>Cardiovascular disease</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>British Heart Foundation</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000274</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>FS/12/57/29717</award-id><award-id>FS/09/036</award-id><award-id>PG/11/16</award-id><award-id>PG/10/89</award-id><award-id>PG/09/062</award-id><award-id>FS/07/003</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the healthy heart, stimulation of the sympathetic nervous system via β-adrenergic pathways leads to an increase in heart rate (HR), force of contraction, and rate of relaxation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In general, opposing actions are mediated by the parasympathetic nervous system, with vagal stimulation slowing HR and decreasing contractility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Sympatho-vagal imbalance arising as a result of reduced parasympathetic and increased sympathetic activity is a well-characterized feature of heart failure (HF), contributes to the systolic dysfunction associated with HF, and increasing sympatho-vagal imbalance is associated with progression towards the decompensated state (1,2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>For example, the increased circulating levels of catecholamines and thus elevated sympathetic drive in HF lead to reduced responsiveness to β-adrenergic stimulation and a worsening of clinical symptoms (3,4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Moreover, targeting HF-associated sympatho-vagal imbalance through chronic vagal nerve stimulation appears to have therapeutic benefit in both experimental and clinical HF (5,6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>There is also evidence suggesting that aging leads to sympatho-vagal imbalance and mis-control of HR with impaired cardiac responsiveness to β-adrenergic stimulation noted (7–10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, increased basal levels of circulating catecholamines and decreased β1-adrenoreceptor density have also been found with age (11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Aging is also a major risk factor for the development of HF (12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Despite the clear age dependency of HF, there is presently a paucity of information regarding whether alterations to the neurohormonal axis that occur in aged animals with HF develop to the same degree, or with the same time dependency, as that which occurs in young animals with HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These gaps in the literature exist primarily because the majority of experimental research is carried out using only young animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have used a ventricular tachypacing model of HF in both young and aged sheep to investigate any age dependency in the temporal development of sympatho-vagal imbalance in HF using in vivo techniques on conscious animals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>We find that aging is associated with an increase in resting HR, reduction in heart rate variability (HRV), and a reduced change in cardiac contractility in response to β-adrenergic stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The development of HF increased HR, reduced HRV, attenuated the HR response to β-adrenergic stimulation, and abolished vagal tone in both young and aged sheep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>However, the impairment of β-adrenergic responsiveness occurred earlier in aged sheep following induction of HF by tachypacing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Also, during complete pharmacologically mediated autonomic blockade, the intrinsic HR was found to be increased in aging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We conclude therefore that HF leads to reduced catecholamine responsiveness in both the young and aged, but these effects develop more rapidly in the aged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>All procedures involving the use of animals were performed in accordance with The United Kingdom Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act, 1986 and European Union Directive 2010/63. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Institutional approval was obtained from The University of Manchester Animal Welfare and Ethical Review Board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the study accords with the ARRIVE guidelines (13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Experimental Model of Aging and HF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Female Welsh Mountain sheep (n = 39; 34.8±1.0kg) aged either 18 months (young, n = 23) or 8 years or older (aged, n = 16) were loose housed in groups of 4–5, fed ad libitum hay, and maintained on a 12-hour light, dark cycle at 20±2°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Animals were anesthetized with isoflurane (1%–5% v/v in oxygen), and preoperative analgesia was provided (meloxicom 0.5mg/kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A single active fixation bipolar IS-1 endocardial pacing lead was placed trans-venously into the right ventricle and secured to a single chamber cardiac pacemaker with software modification (High Rate Pacing Patch, Medtronic Inc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>To induce HF, right ventricular tachypacing was initiated at 210 beats per minute (bpm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In two animals, cardiac capture was not immediately consistent at 210 bpm; we therefore paced these animals at 180 bpm for 2–7 days before increasing to 210 bpm for the remainder of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>On presentation of clinical signs of HF (lethargy, dyspnea), tachypacing was stopped and a final “postpacing” set of in vivo experiments performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Animals were humanely killed with pentobarbitone sodium (200 mg·kg−1) with 10,000 units of heparin administered intravenously, and tissues were harvested for additional studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For all in vivo assessments of cardiac function and sympatho-vagal balance following initiation of right ventricular tachypacing, pacemakers were switched off (ODO) for 15 minutes before measurements were taken. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All in vivo experiments were carried out on conscious, nonsedated, and gently restrained animals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Echocardiography and Blood Pressure Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Echocardiograms were analyzed offline using ImageJ (NIH, USA), and 3–20 consecutive cardiac cycles were averaged to obtain measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Left ventricular (LV) end diastolic internal diameter (EDID), end systolic internal diameter (ESID), relative wall thickness (RWT), and fractional shortening measurements were all obtained from m-mode images, whereas the fractional area change was measured from short-axis images as we have described previously (4,14–17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure measurements were recorded by tail cuff plethysmography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Readings were obtained over a 3- to 5-minute period, and the last three consistent values were averaged following European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and European Society of Cardiology (ESC) guidelines (18). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Measurement of HR and HRV </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Surface electrocardiograms (ECGs) were recorded using a five-lead orthogonal configuration, digitized to personal computer (1kHz), and the RR interval and HR were analyzed as described previously using shape recognition algorithms (ECG Auto, EMKA France) (17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Time-domain measures of HRV were quantified as RR interval standard deviation (RRSD) and the coefficient of variance of RRSD (RRSD / mean RR interval). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Assessment of Temporal Development of Sympathetic Dysfunction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The development of sympathetic dysfunction with tachypacing was monitored weekly with intravenous infusions of the sympathetic agonist dobutamine (5–40 µg·kg−1·minute−1, Claris Life Sciences, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Dobutamine concentrations were increased in twofold increments up to a maximum of 40 μg·kg−1·minute−1 or until HR exceeded 150 bpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>ECGs were recorded for 5 minutes at each dobutamine dose, and ECG parameters were calculated from the last 60 seconds of each infusion period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Animals were allowed to recover for at least 30 minutes before tachypacing was recommenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To assess whether sympathetic-mediated enhancement of cardiac contractility was altered with HF and aging, parasternal short-axis echocardiograms were obtained at both baseline and immediately following the final infusion of dobutamine (5 µg·kg−1·minute−1 in control and 10–40 µg·kg−1·minute−1 in HF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Measurements were obtained both prior to tachypacing (control) and once HF had developed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Assessment of Parasympathetic Influence of HR and HRV </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Parasympathetic function in aging and HF was measured using sequential sympathetic (0.5 mg·kg−1 propranolol [PPL]; prepared as propranolol hydrochloride in 0.9% NaCl solution, Sigma-Aldrich, UK) and parasympathetic (0.05 mg·kg−1 atropine; prepared as atropine sulfate in 0.9% NaCl solution; Sigma-Aldrich) blockade via intravenous bolus with an additional 0.05 mg·kg−1·minute−1 atropine infused after 1 minute to maintain complete autonomic block (AB) for the duration of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Measurements were obtained both prior to the start of tachypacing and once HF had developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To determine whether AB was complete, HR responses to dobutamine (5 µg·kg−1·minute−1) and acetylcholine (100 nmol·min−1; prepared as acetylcholine chloride in 0.9% NaCl; Sigma-Aldrich) were assessed in a subset of animals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Quantification of Plasma Noradrenaline </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Blood samples (~ 20mL) were collected into K2EDTA vacutainer blood collection tubes by jugular venipuncture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Samples were stored on ice prior to centrifugation (4,000g, 10 minutes), and plasma were harvested and stored in liquid nitrogen until use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Plasma noradrenaline was quantified using a competitive ELISA according to manufacturer’s instructions (Labor Diagnostika Nord, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All data are presented as the mean ± SEM for n animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All comparisons were made pair-wise on the same animal—that is, control versus HF as well as before and during drug infusions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Differences between groups (age, disease, and drug treatments) were analyzed using either a two-way repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) firstly within each age group (eg, control vs HF; pre and post drug administration) and then between age groups (ie, young control vs aged control) or paired Student’s t test (autonomic blockade vs dobutamine or acetylcholine). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Data that were not normally distributed were transformed by means appropriate to the spread of data, for example, log10 (19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered significant when p value was less than .05; however, p values were adjusted using the Holm-Sidak post hoc test for multiple comparisons using SigmaPlot 11.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Correlational analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s9"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Signs of HF (lethargy and dyspnea) took a median of 35 days to develop (interquartile range = 9) with no age-dependent differences in the duration of tachypacing required to induce HF (p = .56). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Tachypacing was not associated with any instances of sudden death, and all animals completed the study with none being excluded from subsequent data analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>As in our previous studies (4,14–17), aging and tachypacing-induced HF were associated with increased LV dimensions and reduced contractile function (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Of note, aging by itself was associated with a 21% ± 7% increase in EDID, a 50% ± 15% increase in ESID, and a 15% ± 4% decrease in fractional shortening (all p &lt; .01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In both age groups, HF increased (p &lt; .001) EDID (young by 55.6% ± 10%; aged by 34.8% ± 6%) and ESID (young by 232% ± 21%; aged by 152% ± 20%) and resulted in a reduction (p &lt; .001) in fractional shortening (young by 57% ± 2%; aged by 59% ± 3%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, ESID and fractional shortening were worst in the aged HF animals (p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Finally, HF was associated with a decrease in RWT (p &lt; .001; young by 51% ± 5%; aged by 41% ± 5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Systolic, diastolic, and mean blood pressure were decreased similarly with HF in both young and aged animals (all p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Summary of Echocardiographic and Hemodynamic Findings in Aging and Heart Failure </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text></text></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Young </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Aged </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Prepaced </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Postpaced </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Prepaced </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Postpaced </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>EDID (cm) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>2.61±0.10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>3.91±0.07*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>3.15±0.15** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>4.13±0.10††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>ESID (cm) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>0.92±0.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>2.82±0.10*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>1.38±0.11** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>3.17±0.12†††,# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Fractional shortening </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>0.67±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>0.29±0.02*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>0.57±0.02*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>0.23±0.02†††,# </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>RWT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>0.91±0.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>0.39±0.02*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>0.73±0.06* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>0.42±0.05††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Fractional area change </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>0.68±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>0.38±0.02*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>0.63±0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>0.36±0.02††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Systolic BP (mmHg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>127±2.36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>108±2.27*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>133±2.09 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>114±2.62††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Diastolic BP (mmHg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>79±2.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>67±1.64*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>84±2.29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>71±2.36††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Mean BP (mmHg) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>95±1.96 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>81±1.70*** </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>100±1.96 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>85±2.17††† </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-01" fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Notes: Values are mean ± SEM from n = 16–18 young, 10–16 aged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Fractional shortening was calculated as (EDID − ESID) / EDID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>RWT was calculated as (2 × diastolic wall thickness) / EDID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Fractional area change was calculated as (end diastolic area − end systolic area) / end diastolic area. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn-02" fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>BP = blood pressure; EDID = end diastolic internal diameter; ESID = end systolic internal diameter; RWT = relative wall thickness. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn-03" fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>*p &lt; .05 vs young prepaced. **p &lt; .01 vs young prepaced. *** p &lt; .001 vs young prepaced. ††† p &lt; .001 vs old prepaced. # p &lt; .05 vs young postpaced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><sec id="s10"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>HR, HRV, and PR Interval Are Altered in the Ovine Model of Aging and HF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Surface five-lead orthogonal ECGs were measured both prior to tachypacing (control) and once HF was evident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Representative Poincaré plots of successive RR intervals from a young and an aged sheep are shown in Figure 1A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Resting HR was higher in aged than in young animals (Figure 1B. young, 105±4 bpm; aged, 123±7 bpm; p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>HF was associated with an increase in resting HR (122±6 bpm, pacemaker off) only in young animals (p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Changes to baseline heart rate heart rate variability and PR interval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>(A) Representative Poincaré plots of successive RR intervals in young (left) and aged (right) sheep before tachypacing (solid black circles) and in HF (open gray circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>(B–G) Summary data for young control (YC), young HF (YF), aged control (OC), and aged HF (OF) animals showing (B) mean HR, (C) RR standard deviation (RRSD), (D) coefficient of variance of RRSD, (E) instantaneous beat-to-beat HRV (SD1), (F) long-term beat-to-beat HRV (SD2), and (G) ratio of short- to long-term beat-to-beat HRV (SD1:SD2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>(H) Mean values of RRSD as a function of RR interval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The solid line through the data is a best-fit regression of the form y = A + B · eC forced through the origin and having exponent (C) of 2.355. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>(I). Natural log RRSD as a function of mean RR interval with the solid line representing a linear regression to the data (p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In panels (H) and (I) symbols denote: ○, YC; ●, YF; □, OC; and ■, OF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(J) PR interval summary data. *p &lt; .05 vs YC; **p &lt; .01 vs YC; ***p &lt; .001 vs YC; # p &lt; .05 vs OC; ## p &lt; .01 vs OC; ### p &lt; .001 vs OC; $ p &lt; .05 vs YF; $$ p &lt; .01 vs YF. n = 13–18 young, 9–11 aged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gerona_glv217_f0001"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>HRV measured in the time domain as the RRSD (Figure 1C) decreased with the development of HF in both age groups (young: control, 45±6ms; HF, 29±5ms; p &lt; .01; aged: control, 29±3ms; HF, 15±2ms; p &lt; .01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>However, although the observed differences in HRV (RRSD) did not reach significance in aged control animals compared with young control animals (p = .094), it was less in aged failing compared with the young failing sheep (p &lt; .01) and decreased overall with age (control and HF) compared with young (two-way ANOVA; p &lt; .05) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Time-domain measures of HRV such as RRSD are influenced by the underlying HR (20–22), and we also see a strong correlation between RRSD and RR interval in sheep (Figure 1H–I; p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>We have therefore corrected for the age and HF-dependent changes in HR by normalizing the RRSD values to the mean RR interval in each animal (Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>We find that the coefficient of variance of the RRSD (20,21) indicates that the reduction in HRV in HF is not simply due to the increased HR (young: control, 0.074±0.009; HF, 0.054±0.009; p &lt; .05; Aged: control, 0.057±0.006; HF, 0.031±0.005; p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Both measures therefore indicate a reduction of HRV in both young and aged animals with the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the coefficient of variance of RRSD was decreased overall in control and HF aged animals (two-way ANOVA, p &lt; .05) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The final way in which we have assessed HRV in aging and HF is from the short-term (SD1), long-term (SD2), and ratio of short- to long-term variation of successive RR intervals obtained from the Poincaré plots (SD1:SD2; Figure 1E–G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Agreement with the previous assessments of HRV, these measures also show a decrease in HRV with age and HF, with the HF-dependent decrease in SD1:SD2 ratio indicative of loss of parasympathetic influence on HR control being noted in both age groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate whether conduction remodeling occurs in this model of HF, we quantified PR interval from the ECGs (Figure 1J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>HF was associated with an increase in PR interval in both young (128.6±3.3ms vs 95.9±3.2ms) and aged (126.7±4.8ms vs 102.6±3.8ms) sheep (both p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, no difference in PR interval was detected as a result of age (p = .57 by two-way repeated measures ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Attenuated Chronotropic Responsiveness to β-Adrenergic Stimulation Occurs Early in the Development of HF by Tachypacing: An Effect Accelerated by Aging </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>We next sought to determine the time course of development and extent of sympathetic dysfunction in aging and with the onset of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This was assessed weekly by determining the HR responses to dobutamine (5–40 µg·kg−1·minute−1, Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Before the onset of tachypacing to induce HF, dobutamine (5 µg·kg−1·minute−1) increased HR in both young and aged animals by 63% ± 14% in young and 42% ± 14% in aged (Figure 2B and C; p &lt; .001 vs pre-dobutamine; p = .148 between age groups). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Although this dose of dobutamine was still sufficient to increase HR compared with baseline after 1 week (p &lt; .01) and 3 weeks (p &lt; .05) tachypacing in the young, this was not the case for aged animals where, after just 1 week of tachypacing, no change in HR was observed in response to 5 μg·kg−1·minute−1 dobutamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>We also noted that although there was a robust increase in HR in response to 5 μg·kg−1·minute−1 dobutamine in both young and aged animals prior to commencement of tachypacing, at the onset of HF, we found no change in HR response to doses of dobutamine less than 20 μg·kg−1·minute−1 (Figure 2D); thus, the chronotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation is reduced in HF in both age groups although appears to occur earlier in the aged animals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Temporal development of sympathetic dysfunction in heart failure and aging. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>(A) Timeline of experimental protocol used to assess loss of sympathetic responsiveness in HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>White boxes indicate where ECGs were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(B, C) Summary data showing mean HR from animals at baseline (open circles) and in response to intravenous infusion of 5 μg·kg−1·minute−1 dobutamine (DOB, solid circles) in (B) young and (C) aged sheep. *p &lt; .05; **p &lt; .01; ***p &lt; .001 vs baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>(D) Summary data showing HR normalized to predobutamine infusion HR in young prepaced (open bar), aged prepaced (solid bar), young HF (striped bar), and aged HF (checked bar). **p &lt; .01 vs normalized resting HR (ie, 1); ***p &lt; .001 vs pre-DOB infusion HR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(E) LV contractility measured by fractional area change throughout the course of the rapid-pacing protocol in young (solid) and aged (open) sheep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Two-way repeated measures ANOVA detected a significant difference between fractional area change and weeks pacing (p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(F, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>LV contractile function was assessed using 2D short-axis echocardiograms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Histograms showing summary data for mean fractional area change pre (−) and post (+) intravenous dobutamine (DOB) infusion in (F) young, (G) aged, control, and HF animals as indicated. **p &lt; .01 vs Control pre-DOB; ***p &lt; .001 vs Control pre-DOB; # p &lt; .05 vs HF pre-DOB; $ p &lt; .05 vs Control post-DOB; $$$ p &lt; .001 vs Control post-DOB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>(H) Summary data showing plasma noradrenaline concentrations determined by competitive ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>YC, young control; YF, young heart failure; OC, aged control; OF, aged heart failure. # p &lt; .05 vs OC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>For panels (A–D) and (F, G), n = 5 young, 5 aged, for panel (E) n = 7 young, 5 aged, and for panel (H), n = 9 young, 7 aged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gerona_glv217_f0002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s12"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Sympathetic-mediated Inotropic Function Is Attenuated With Aging and HF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>We next assessed whether the inotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation, assessed as LV fractional area change, is attenuated in aging and with the development of HF (Figure 2E–G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In both young and aged animals, cardiac contractility (fractional area change) decreased with the development of HF with no age-dependent temporal differences observed (Figure 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In young prepaced animals, 5 μg·kg−1·minute−1 dobutamine increased fractional area change by 31% ± 10%, whereas in aged control animals, this dose of dobutamine, despite its effect on HR, did not increase LV contractility significantly from baseline (p = .129). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>On development of HF, the contractility response to catecholamine stimulation was assessed with an elevated dose of dobutamine which led to an increase of HR to 150 bpm (“the effective dose”; 20 µg·kg−1·minute−1 in 8 of 10 animals; range 10–40 µg·kg−1·minute−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In young HF animals, the effective dose of dobutamine (10–40 µg·kg−1·minute−1) increased contractility by 31% ± 13% (p &lt; .05) and in aged HF sheep, the effective dose of dobutamine (20 µg·kg−1·minute−1) increased fractional area change by 29% ± 15% (p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In both young and aged HF animals, despite the increased doses of dobutamine, the fractional area changes were considerably less than the 5 µg·kg−1·minute−1 dobutamine responses observed before tachypacing commenced (p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The attenuated chronotropic and inotropic responses to dobutamine in HF were also associated with a significant interaction between HF and plasma noradrenaline levels increasing (Figure 2H; p &lt; .05; two-way RM-ANOVA) with a directly observed increase in the aged cohort (aged control, 557±73 pg·mL−1; aged HF, 1973±937 pg·mL−1; p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s13"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Parasympathetic Control of HR Is Lost With HF in Both Young and Aged Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Assessment of parasympathetic control of HR and HRV was made by sequentially blocking sympathetic and parasympathetic input with PPL and atropine, respectively, to achieve full autonomic blockade (AB, Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Heart failure and aging mediated parasympathetic dysfunction revealed by sequential autonomic blockade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic representation of experimental approach to achieve sympathetic and full autonomic blockade (AB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The white boxes indicate time periods used to analyze data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The horizontal break indicates assessment of responsiveness to dobutamine (DOB) or acetylcholine (ACh) following autonomic blockade performed in a subset of animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>(B) Summary data showing (upper panel) measured HR predrug administration (control, Con), after intravenous bolus of propranolol (PPL) and atropine (AB, full autonomic block) obtained prepacing (open symbols) and HF (closed symbols) in young animals and, (lower panel) tabulated significance values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(C) Summary data (upper panel) and tabulated significance data (lower panel) for aged animals (triangles, right). n = 13 young, 11 aged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>(D) Mean intrinsic HR in aging and HF. *p &lt; .05 vs YC; ***p &lt; .001 vs YC; ### p &lt; .001 vs OC. n = 13 YC, 13 YF, 15 OC, 11 OF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(E, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Absence of heart rate responses to dobutamine infusion (E) or acetylcholine (F) following autonomic blockade (AB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>NS, not significant. n = 4 each group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gerona_glv217_f0003"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>In young prepaced animals (Figure 3B), β-adrenergic receptor antagonism with PPL decreased HR by 29% ± 6% (p &lt; .001) and subsequent full autonomic blockade led to a 60% ± 12% increase in HR (p &lt; .001, compared with PPL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The mean intrinsic HR (ie, outwith autonomic influence) of young prepaced animals was 13% ± 7% faster than the resting HR (predrug administration; p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In young HF animals, PPL still decreased HR (by 20% ± 6%, p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>However, this was a smaller reduction in HR than that seen before tachypacing commenced (p &lt; .01), suggesting reduced sympathetic influence in HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the young HF animals, subsequent autonomic blockade failed to have any additional effect on HR (p = .955) indicating the loss of parasympathetic influence on HR control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>A broadly similar pattern was observed within the aged group (Figure 3C), with PPL slowing HR by 31% ± 6% compared with control conditions (p &lt; .001) and autonomic blockade increasing HR by 53% ± 11% compared with PPL (p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, unlike in the young control animals, the intrinsic HR of aged control animals, that is, during autonomic blockade, was not different to the aged control resting HR (p = .316). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the intrinsic HR in aged control animals is greater than that in young control animals (young, 120.1±4.1 bpm; aged 130.8±3.0 bpm. Figure 3D, p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In aged failing animals, PPL again slowed HR (by 29% ± 4%), but this was to a similar extent to that seen in the prepacing situation (p = .154). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In aged HF animals, autonomic blockade failed to increase HR following PPL administration (p = .88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Thus HF in aged animals was associated with a loss of parasympathetic influence on HR, but sympathetic influence was unaltered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The only age-dependent differences in HR noted were those present at baseline (ie, prior to sympathetic or parasympathetic blockade). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In both prepaced and postpaced time points, aged sheep had a higher HR than in the young sheep (both p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the dosages of PPL and atropine used to achieve autonomic blockade were effective at preventing any HR responses to subsequent doses of dobutamine or acetylcholine (Figure 3E and F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s14"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Parasympathetic Control of HRV Is Lost With the Development of HF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We also measured HRV from the RRSD/RR ratio following β-adrenergic receptor blockade and full autonomic blockade in young (Figure 4A) and aged (Figure 4B) animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In young prepaced animals, no difference in HRV was detectable during β-adrenergic blockade with PPL, but HRV was reduced during full autonomic blockade (control, 0.067±0.007; PPL, 0.069±0.012; AB, 0.017±0.007. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>All comparisons p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>A similar trend in HRV was seen in young failing animals following sequential β-adrenergic and full autonomic blockade (control, 0.056±0.012; PPL, 0.049±0.007; AB, 0.016±0.002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>All comparisons p &lt; .01) such that, in young animals under full autonomic blockade, no differences in HRV exist between the prepaced and HF conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Aging and heart failure mediated reductions in heart rate variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>(A) Summary data (upper panels) showing RRSD covariance values predrug administration (control, con), after propranolol (PPL) and atropine (full autonomic blockade, AB) in young prepaced (open bars) and HF (striped bars) and (lower panels) table of significance values for young animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(B) Data (upper panels) and summary of significance (lower panels) for aged control (solid bars) and HF (checked bars) animals. n = 13 young, 11 aged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gerona_glv217_f0004"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>As with the young prepaced sheep, no difference in HRV was found in aged prepaced animals following PPL, but HRV was less during full autonomic blockade (control, 0.051±0.004; PPL, 0.061±0.01; AB, 0.007±0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>All comparisons p &lt; .001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>However, in aged failing animals, neither PPL nor full autonomic blockade altered the coefficient of variation of RRSD (RRSD/mean RR; control, 0.031±0.005; PPL, 0.025±0.004; AB, 0.015±0.002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The coefficient of variance of RRSD measure of HRV demonstrated that HRV was less at both baseline (no drug infusions) and following β-adrenergic blockade in aged failing sheep compared with the prepacing values (p &lt; .01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The only age-dependent difference in the coefficient of variance of RRSD measurement of HRV following sequential β-adrenergic antagonism and full autonomic blockade was in HF both at baseline and after PPL administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Thus HRV was less in aged HF animals than in young HF animals at baseline (no drug infusion) and following β-adrenergic receptor antagonism (p &lt; .05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Following full autonomic blockade, HRV (coefficient of variance of RRSD) was the same in both young and aged HF animals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s15"><title><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The aims of the present study were to determine whether aging influences the evolution of autonomic dysfunction during the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The major findings were (i) cardiac dimensions are greater and indices of contractility are less in aged HF animals; (ii) chronotropic and inotropic responses to β-adrenergic stimulation are reduced in both aged and young animals with HF but develop earlier in the progression of tachypacing-induced HF in the aged; (iii) time-domain measures of HRV are reduced as a consequence of HF in both young and aged animals, but these are more pronounced in the aged, with some indices showing reduced HRV as a consequence of aging alone; and (iv) following sequential autonomic blockade to assess the sympatho-vagal influence on the control of HR we found subtle age-dependent differences in HF, although before tachypacing commenced the intrinsic HR (ie, during full autonomic blockade) was greater than the resting HR in young animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Together these findings indicate that there are subtle age-dependent effects on (i) the extent of cardiac remodeling, (ii) β-adrenergic responsiveness, and (iii) autonomic control of HR with the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Aging is known to influence a number of cardiac physiological and structural variables including the occurrence of cardiac fibrosis (17,23,24), mitochondrial dysfunction, (25) and in the context of the present study, impaired inotropic reserve and exercise intolerance; the latter being considered hallmarks of aging (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The opposing actions of the sympathetic and parasympathetic innervation of the heart ultimately determine HR and contribute to the beat-to-beat variability of HR, and these controlling factors are known to be altered by aging (26,27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We show that aging also influences these parameters in response to the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Specifically, using an ovine model of aging we show that HR is increased whereas time-domain measures of HRV and the inotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation are reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>These findings are consistent with a diminished responsiveness to catecholamines in aging being observed at the cellular (28,29), tissue (8), and whole heart (30) levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The elevated plasma catecholamine levels noted in some studies of aging [(31,32); Figure 2H] may be directly contributing to the decreased inotropic and chronotropic adrenergic responsiveness of the aged heart due to desensitization and internalization of the β-adrenergic receptors as has been previously noted in both aging (11) and HF (4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A substantial body of evidence demonstrates that the elevated sympathetic drive in HF ultimately leads to a diminished myocardial response to β-adrenergic stimulation, for example, see (3,4,33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have demonstrated that the development of impaired β-adrenergic responsiveness occurs earlier in aged animals during the progression of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>A similar age-dependent attenuation of β-adrenergic influence on HR has been noted following exercise in patients (34). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>However, although the aged HF animals develop impaired inotropic and chronotropic responses to β-adrenergic stimulation earlier than the young HF animals, there are no age-dependent difference in β-adrenergic responsiveness once HF has developed, that is, HF results in a marked attenuation of the chronotropic response in both the young and aged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Thus aging may be an important factor determining the temporal development, rather than ultimate outcome, of, impaired responsiveness to catecholamines as a result of pathological stresses such as HF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Although we were unable to monitor the temporal development of impaired parasympathetic influence on HR control with the onset of tachypacing, we did note that, in both young and aged animals, there was a marked loss of the parasympathetic control of HR once HF had developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Classically, the parasympathetic influence on the heart is to slow sinus node firing rate and thus HR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the parasympathetic input to the heart is also thought to determine the short-term variability of HR, albeit as a saturating function of parasympathetic activity (35,36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The increase in resting HR with age, as well as the unaltered HR following full autonomic block noted in aged animals, suggests that there is a reduced parasympathetic component to the control of HR in aging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Moreover, following tachypacing, there is a dramatic reduction/loss of parasympathetic input to controlling HR in both age groups, as demonstrated by (i) the marked reductions in several time-domain measures of HRV and (ii) the failure of parasympathetic blockade with atropine to influence HR following β-adrenergic blockade with PPL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Such observations are common to numerous studies of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>However, the influence of aging on this response has been less well characterized (37); albeit that, at least in the present study, aging does not appear to influence this outcome once HF has developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Given that reduced parasympathetic activity is generally held to indicate poor outcomes in HF, for example, see (38), the beneficial effects of chronic vagal nerve stimulation in HF may, in part, arise from the improved autonomic control of HR (6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Further studies are required to elucidate other cardioprotective mechanisms that may arise from vagal nerve stimulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s16"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Study Limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Although the tachypacing approaches are considered useful models of dilated cardiomyopathy and tachycardic cardiomyopathy (39), they do not replicate the most common cause of HF occurring as a result of myocardial ischemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>However, the autonomic perturbations noted in the sheep model of aging and tachypacing-induced HF are consistent with those seen in other causes of HF and suggest a common effect on the sympatho-vagal control of HR independent of the underlying cause of this condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Secondly, we did not perform weekly assessments of parasympathetic function (using autonomic blockade), during the development of HF due to the risk of arrhythmias once tachypacing was resumed while animals were still subject to the effects of circulating PPL and atropine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>However, the chronotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation was assessed weekly and demonstrated that sympathetic dysfunction arises very early in the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Finally, due to the orientation of the cardiac apex over the sternum, we were unable to obtain conventional transthoracic long-axis apical views of the heart by echocardiography and are therefore unable to satisfactorily determine a number of indices of cardiac function, for example, E/A ratios, torsion, and ejection fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the long- and short-axis views that we have quantified clearly show a marked deterioration in cardiac function with aging and the development of HF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s17"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we have demonstrated that aging results in cardiac remodeling, reduced contractility, reduced HRV assessed by some time-domain analysis approaches, and reduced response to β-adrenergic stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>With the development of HF, we noted that aging is associated with a more rapid loss of the chronotropic response to β-adrenergic stimulation, greater cardiac dimensions, and impaired contractility, and finally, subtle changes in sympatho-vagal imbalance compared with young HF animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Taken together, given the age dependence of the development of HF in the general population, our findings suggest that aging is an important factor determining the development and extent of autonomic dysfunction in HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The outcomes of current clinical trials targeting the vagal nerve may therefore be influenced by patient age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by grants from The British Heart Foundation (FS/12/57/29717, FS/09/036, PG/11/16, PG/10/89, PG/09/062, and FS/07/003). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>We thank Medtronic Inc and St. Jude Medical for their technical support regarding cardiac pacemaker programming. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>1. TriposkiadisFKarayannisGGiamouzisGSkoularigisJLouridasGButlerJ The sympathetic nervous system in heart failure: physiology, pathophysiology, and clinical implications. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009;54:1747–1762. doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2009.05.015 19874988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>2. PackerM The neurohormonal hypothesis: a theory to explain the mechanism of disease progression in heart failure. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1992;20:248–254. doi:10.1016/0735-1097(92)90167-L 1351488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>3. BorlaugBAMelenovskyVRussellSD Impaired chronotropic and vasodilator reserves limit exercise capacity in patients with heart failure and a preserved ejection fraction. Circulation. 2006;114:2138–2147. doi:10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.632745 17088459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>4. BristonSJCaldwellJLHornMA Impaired beta-adrenergic responsiveness accentuates dysfunctional excitation contraction coupling in an ovine model of tachypacing induced heart failure. J Physiol. 2011;589:1367–1382. doi:10.1113/jphysiol.2010.203984 21242250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>5. HamannJJRubleSBStolenC Vagus nerve stimulation improves left ventricular function in a canine model of chronic heart failure. Eur J Heart Failure. 2013;15:1319–1326. doi:10.1093/eurjhf/hft118  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>6. ZhangYPopoviZBBibevskiS Chronic vagus nerve stimulation improves autonomic control and attenuates systemic inflammation and heart failure progression in a canine high-rate pacing model / clinical perspective. Circ Heart Failure. 2009;2:692–699. doi:10.1161/ CIRCHEARTFAILURE.109.873968 19919995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>7. FarrellSRHowlettSE The age-related decrease in catecholamine sensitivity is mediated by beta(1)-adrenergic receptors linked to a decrease in adenylate cyclase activity in ventricular myocytes from male Fischer 344 rats. Mech Ageing Dev. 2008;129:735–744. doi:10.1016/j.mad.2008.09.017 18973772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>8. LakattaEGGerstenblithGAngellCSShockNWWeisfeldtML Diminished inotropic response of aged myocardium to catecholamines. Circ Res. 1975;36:262–269. doi:10.1161/01.RES.36.2.262 1116236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>9. KendallMJWoodsKLWilkinsMRWorthingtonDJ Responsiveness to beta-adrenergic receptor stimulation: the effects of age are cardioselective. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 1982;14:821–826. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2125.1982.tb02043.x 6129882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>10. HeinsimerJALefkowitzRJ The impact of aging on adrenergic receptor function: clinical and biochemical aspects. J Am Geriatr Soc. 1985;33:184–188. doi:10.1111/j.1532-5415.1985.tb04890.x 2857740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>11. XiaoRPTomhaveEDWangDJ Age-associated reductions in cardiac beta1- and beta2-adrenergic responses without changes in inhibitory G proteins or receptor kinases. J Clin Investig. 1998;101:1273–1282. doi:10.1172/JCI1335 9502768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>12. KannelWB Incidence and epidemiology of heart failure. Heart Failure Rev. 2000;5:167–173. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>13. KilkennyCBrowneWJCuthillICEmersonMAltmanDG Improving bioscience research reporting: the ARRIVE guidelines for reporting animal research. PLoS Biol. 2010;8:e1000412. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1000412 20613859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>14. ClarkeJDCaldwellJLHornMA Perturbed atrial calcium handling in an ovine model of heart failure: potential roles for reductions in the L-type calcium current. J Mol Cell Cardiol. 2015;79:169–179. doi:10.1016/j.yjmcc.2014.11.017 25463272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>15. CaldwellJLSmithCETaylorRF Dependence of cardiac transverse tubules on the BAR domain protein amphiphysin II (BIN-1). Circ Res. 2014;115:986–996. doi:10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.303448 25332206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>16. DibbKMClarkeJDHornMA Characterization of an extensive transverse tubular network in sheep atrial myocytes and its depletion in heart failure. Circ Heart Failure. 2009;2:482–489. doi:10.1161/ CIRCHEARTFAILURE.109.852228 19808379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>17. HornMAGrahamHKRichardsMA Age-related divergent remodeling of the cardiac extracellular matrix in heart failure: Collagen accumulation in the young and loss in the aged. J Mol Cell Cardiol. 2012;53:82–90. doi:10.1016/j.yjmcc.2012.03.011 22516365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>18. ManciaGFagardRNarkiewiczK 2013 ESH/ESC guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension: the Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Eur Heart J. 2013;34:2159–2219. doi:10.1093/eurheartj/eht151 23771844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>19. EnnosR Choosing tests and designing experiments. Statistical and Data Handling Skills in Biology. Essex: Pearson Education; 2000:84–99. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>20. BillmanGE The effect of heart rate on the heart rate variability response to autonomic interventions. Front Physiol. 2013;4:222. doi:10.3389/fphys.2013.00222 23986716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>21. PitzalisMVMastropasquaFMassariFTotaroPPassantinoARizzonP The effect of nadolol on heart rate and the standard deviation of the RR intervals. Eur Heart J. 1995;16:269–275.7744100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>22. MonfrediOLyashkovAEJohnsenAB Biophysical characterization of the underappreciated and important relationship between heart rate variability and heart rate. Hypertension. 2014;64:1334–1343. doi:10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.03782 25225208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>23. KwakHBLeeYKimJHVan RemmenHRichardsonAGLawlerJM MnSOD overexpression reduces fibrosis and pro-apoptotic signaling in the aging mouse heart. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2015;70:533–544. doi:10.1093/gerona/glu090 25016531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>24. WaltonRDJonesSARostronKA Interactions of short-term and chronic treadmill training with aging of the left ventricle of the heart. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2015. doi:10.1093/gerona/glv093  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>25. ColomBOliverJGarcia-PalmerFJ Sexual dimorphism in the alterations of cardiac muscle mitochondrial bioenergetics associated to the ageing process. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2015;70:1360–1369. doi:10.1093/gerona/glu014 24682352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>26. KuoTBLinTYangCCLiCLChenCFChouP Effect of aging on gender differences in neural control of heart rate. Am J Physiol. 1999;277:H2233–H2239.10600841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>27. UmetaniKSingerDHMcCratyRAtkinsonM Twenty-four hour time domain heart rate variability and heart rate: relations to age and gender over nine decades. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1998;31:593–601. doi:10.1016/S0735-1097(97)00554-8 9502641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>28. DaviesCHFerraraNHardingSE Beta-adrenoceptor function changes with age of subject in myocytes from non-failing human ventricle. Cardiovasc Res. 1996;31:152–156. doi:10.1016/S0008-6363(95)00187-5 8849600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>29. SakaiMDanzigerRSXiaoRPSpurgeonHALakattaEG Contractile response of individual cardiac myocytes to norepinephrine declines with senescence. Am J Physiol. 1992;262:H184–189.1370751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>30. YinFCSpurgeonHAGreeneHLLakattaEGWeisfeldtML Age-associated decrease in heart rate response to isoproterenol in dogs. Mech Ageing Dev. 1979;10:17–25. doi:10.1016/0047-6374(79)90067-8 449422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>31. BertelOBühlerFRKiowskiWLütoldBE Decreased Beta-adrenoreceptor responsiveness as related to age, blood pressure, and plasma catecholamines in patients with essential hypertension. Hypertension. 1980;2:130–138. doi:10.1161/01.HYP.2.2.130  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>32. GoldsteinDSLakeCRChernowB Age-dependence of hypertensive-normotensive differences in plasma norepinephrine. Hypertension. 1983;5:100–104. doi:10.1161/01.HYP.5.1.100 6848457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>33. ColucciWSDennissARLeathermanGF Intracoronary infusion of dobutamine to patients with and without severe congestive heart failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Dose-response relationships, correlation with circulating catecholamines, and effect of phosphodiesterase inhibition. J Clin Investig. 1988;81:1103–1110. doi:10.1172/JCI113423 2832444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>34. FlegJLSchulmanSO’ConnorF Effects of acute beta-adrenergic receptor blockade on age-associated changes in cardiovascular performance during dynamic exercise. Circulation. 1994;90:2333–2341. doi:10.1161/01.CIR.90.5.2333 7955191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>35. GoldbergerJJChallapalliSTungRParkerMAKadishAH Relationship of heart rate variability to parasympathetic effect. Circulation. 2001;103:1977–1983. doi:10.1161/01.CIR.103.15.1977 11306527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>36. BloomfieldDMZweibelSBiggerJTJrSteinmanRC R-R variability detects increases in vagal modulation with phenylephrine infusion. Am J Physiol. 1998;274:H1761–H1766.9612388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>37. PlatisaMMGalV Dependence of heart rate variability on heart period in disease and aging. Physiol Meas. 2006;27:989–998. doi:10.1088/0967-3334/27/10/005/meta 16951458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>38. BinkleyPFNunziataEHaasGJNelsonSDCodyRJ Parasympathetic withdrawal is an integral component of autonomic imbalance in congestive heart failure: demonstration in human subjects and verification in a paced canine model of ventricular failure. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1991;18:464–472. doi:10.1016/0735-1097(91)90602-6 1856414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>39. HouserSRMarguliesKBMurphyAM Animal models of heart failure: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circ Res. 2012;111:131–150. doi:10.1161/RES.0b013e3182582523 22595296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
