<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5816796</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00035</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Variation of Functional Neurological Symptoms and Emotion Regulation with Time </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kienle</surname><given-names>Johanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/506975"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rockstroh</surname><given-names>Brigitte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/524125"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiess</surname><given-names>Johanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/497816"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/524166"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>Tzvetan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/43743"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steffen-Klatt</surname><given-names>Astrid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/14531"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Konstanz</institution>, <addr-line>Konstanz</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Kliniken Schmieder</institution>, <addr-line>Konstanz</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Martina De Zwaan, Hannover Medical School, Germany </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Winfried Rief, Philipps University of Marburg, Germany; Claas Lahmann, Universitätsklinikum Freiburg, Germany </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp content-type="corresp" id="cor1">*Correspondence: Astrid Steffen-Klatt, <email>astrid.steffen@uni-konstanz.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Specialty section: This article was submitted to Psychosomatic Medicine, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychiatry </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>35</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 Kienle, Rockstroh, Fiess, Schmidt, Popov and Steffen-Klatt.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kienle, Rockstroh, Fiess, Schmidt, Popov and Steffen-Klatt</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><sec id="ST1"><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The present study addressed the variation of emotion regulation in the context of functional neurological symptom disorder (FNSD) by examining changes of functional neurological symptoms (FNS), general psychological strain, alexithymia, emotion regulation strategies, and cortical correlates of emotion regulation in the context of a standard inpatient treatment program. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="ST2"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods and materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Self-report data on FNS, general psychological strain, alexithymia, emotion regulation strategies, and cortical correlates of an experimentally induced emotion regulation task (participants either passively watched unpleasant and neutral pictures or regulated their emotional response to unpleasant pictures using pre-trained reappraisal, while an electroencephalogram was recorded) were compared between 19 patients with FNSD and 19 healthy comparison participants (HC) before and after a 4-week standard treatment protocol that included a combination of (individual and group) psychotherapies and functional treatments (such as physiotherapy) or a 4-week interval in HC, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="ST3"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>General psychological strain did not decrease significantly in FNSD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Changes in emotion regulation in FNSD patients were constrained to an increase in self-reported use of cognitive reappraisal strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Subjective symptom intensity in FNSD patients varied with alexithymia pretreatment, but did not decrease significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Cortical activity in the time and frequency-domain distinguished passive watching of neutral and unpleasant pictures and regulating emotional responses upon unpleasant pictures from passively watching them without difference between groups and/or time. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="ST4"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Over the investigated time interval, augmented habitual cognitive emotion regulation suggests an alleviation of emotion processing deficits, but no significant symptom decrease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>More controlled and prolonged treatment studies would be needed to determine whether and how a specific contribution of treatment-related changes of emotion regulation and FNS might be inferred. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>functional neurological symptom disorder</kwd><kwd>somatoform dissociation</kwd><kwd>conversion disorder</kwd><kwd>emotion regulation</kwd><kwd>alexithymia</kwd><kwd>electroencephalography</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn01">Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001659</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn01">STE 2263/2-1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="6114"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Functional neurological symptoms (FNS), that is, impaired voluntary motor or sensory function without verified neurological or medical basis (1) cause pervasive suffer and often long-term treatment (2, 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>While the traditional concept of these symptoms as conversion of emotional conflicts and psychological strain into physical expression (4) motivated the assignment of FNS to dissociative disorders [ICD-10 (5)], DSM-5 (1) acknowledges the specific pattern of symptoms and factors contributing to their generation with the distinct category “functional neurological symptom disorder” (FNSD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Hypotheses on symptom generation still consider dissociation and conversion within the concept of aberrant emotion processing consequent upon emotionally upsetting or traumatic experiences and/or emotional conflicts (6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Further clarification of emotion processing in FNSD should inform concepts and therapeutic procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Framing FNSD as dissociative and conversion disorder linked emotion processing primarily to impairments in the perception and verbal expression of one’s own feelings, as conceptualized by alexithymia (7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Framing emotion processing in the context of stress and coping extended emotion regulation to cognitive and behavioral strategies that aimed at (explicit or implicit) control of unpleasant feelings in response to external events; major strategies are described and measured as cognitive reappraisal of the upsetting event or suppression of rising unpleasant sensation (8, 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Both alexithymia and altered emotion regulation have been verified for patients with FNS: elevated levels of alexithymia (10–12) were explained as a transformation of emotional expressions into bodily symptoms or as a misperception of autonomic concomitants of emotion (i.e., increased heartbeat during the experience of fear) as signs of physical illness (10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Altered emotion regulation was verified as stronger tendency for emotion suppression and less cognitive reappraisal in FNSD patients than in healthy controls (13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In addition to self-reported alexithymia and emotion regulation strategies brain dynamics measured in experimental emotion regulation tasks aimed at substantiating the role of emotion regulation in FNSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Hemodynamic and electromagnetic imaging studies confirmed altered processing of emotional stimuli and emotion regulation in FNSD compared to controls in those frontocortical and parietal cortices that have been related to emotion regulation (14, 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition to frontal abnormality, augmented activity in movement-related cortical areas was reported for patients with conversion disorder compared to controls (16–19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Similarly, Fiess et al. (18) reported less frontocortical but augmented sensorimotor electromagnetic activity in FNSD compared to controls in an emotion regulation task, in which participants implemented cognitive reappraisal strategies when watching unpleasant stimuli. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The contribution of emotion processing to FNS generation may be further probed in the context of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Many treatment programs target emotion regulation in conflict situations, considering symptoms as manifestation of dysfunctional emotion regulation or emotional conflict resolution by conversion into physical expression [brief psychodynamic interpersonal therapy (20, 21); enriching cognitive behavior therapy with emotion regulation (22)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Thus, variation with treatment may test hypotheses on the role of emotion regulation in FNSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Moreover, while so far an increasing research body on risk factors and/or comorbid symptoms and other characteristics of FNS(D) can be observed (see above), little is known of their interaction and/or variation over time—or even over treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>To this end, the present study combined self-reported alexithymia and emotion regulation strategies and cortical indices of experimentally induced emotion regulation in the time-domain (via event-related potentials; ERP) and in the frequency-domain between FNSD patients and healthy controls to gain further insight in altered emotion regulation in FNSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In addition, the indices of emotion processing were examined before and after a standard clinical treatment program for FNSD that addressed emotion regulation, emotional conflict awareness, and analysis and resolution of learned stimulus-symptom contingencies as potential contribution to symptom generation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Specific hypotheses were (1) FNSD patients express more alexithymia, psychological strain, and use less cognitive reappraisal and more suppression when downregulating emotions than healthy comparison participants (HC) prior to treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>(2) FNSD patients recruit less frontal and more sensorimotor EEG activity than HC while applying cognitive reappraisal in an experimental emotion regulation task prior to treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>(3) In FNSD, subjective and cortical indices of emotion regulation change across time in parallel to a change in symptom severity and overall psychological strain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Twenty-six patients with FNSD were recruited at the neurological rehabilitation centers Kliniken Schmieder in Konstanz and Gailingen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Patients were diagnosed with ICD-10 diagnoses of a dissociative disorder (ICD-10 code F44.4: dissociative movement disorder, F44.6: dissociative sensibility disorder, F44.7: mixed dissociative disorder), which corresponds to the DSM-5 diagnosis FNSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Individual diagnoses were given by at least two psychiatrists and neurologists according to ICD-10 guidelines (5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Patients with a history of central nervous lesion or disorder were excluded, and at least one core negative FNS (e.g., paresis or hypesthesia) was required for inclusion in the study. N = 5 of the 26 FNSD patients did not complete the study (n = 3 due to early discharge, n = 2 because of a change in diagnosis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In addition, data of two patients were excluded from analyses because of artifact-contaminated EEG data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Table 1 summarizes demographic and clinical data of the remaining sample of n = 19 FNSD patients (n = 11 with diagnosis F44.7, n = 7 with diagnosis F44.4, n = 1 with diagnosis F44.6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Seven FNSD patients suffered from motor weakness or sensory disturbances of left-sided, n = 5 of right-sided limbs, in n = 7 both sides were affected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The average duration of inpatient admission was 4 weeks (33 ± 5.8 range 27–45 days). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>At the time of data assessment, about half of the patients in the present sample (10/19) received analgesic medication (of different active substance groups, only two received the identical drug). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Three patients were unmedicated, 7 out of 19 received medication against hypertension and/or thyroid hypofunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Only 3 out of 19 patients received an antidepressant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Following neurological and neuropsychiatric assessment, patients accomplished a multidisciplinary treatment program to reinstall a functional interaction of body perception and emotion processing [following standards as postulated, e.g., by Dallochio et al. (23) and Carson et al. (24)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This program included psychoeducation (1 h per week), functional therapeutic (i.e., daily physiotherapy, general movement therapy, and depending on individual needs ergotherapy, logotherapy, or neuropsychological training—on average 9.25 h per week) and different psychotherapeutic interventions (on average 7.5 h per week, i.e., once to twice a week individual and four times a week group cognitive behavioral therapy, moreover once or twice a week art and/or bodypsychotherapy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Psychotherapy comprised behavioral therapy with elements of schema-, psychodynamic, and systemic therapies, and addressed emotional regulation within these frameworks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Sociodemographic information of study samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>FNSD patients </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>HC </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>FNSD patients vs. HC </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>N </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Gender (f/m) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>13/6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>12/7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Chi2 = 0.12, p = 0.73 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Age (M ± SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>42.7 ± 14.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>50 ± 17.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>t(36) = 1,38, p = 0.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Years schooling (M ± SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>12.7 ± 4.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>14.3 ± 1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>t(36) = 1,34, p = 0.18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>FNSD, functional neurological symptom disorder; HC, healthy comparison participants; f, female; m, male. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four HC were recruited in the local community by flyer and oral advertisement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria were a central nervous lesion or disorder, and any psychological disorder as screened with the MINI international neuropsychiatric interview (25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>After excluding n = 2 HC, who did not complete the study, and n = 2 with artifact-contaminated EEG, data of n = 19 HC were available for analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Groups did not differ in gender, age distribution, and years of education (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>All participants had normal or corrected to normal vision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Two healthy comparison participants were left-handed, patients diagnosed with FNSD were all right-handed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Study Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The study design was approved by the Ethics committee of the University of Konstanz and by the IRB of the Kliniken Schmieder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>All participants provided written informed consent prior to assessment onset in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The study design addressed the two main hypotheses by comparison of dependent measures (FNS severity, self-rating, and electrocortical emotion regulation indices) between groups (FNSD patients and HC) and across time (before and after the inpatient treatment period in FNSD patients and a respective time interval in HC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Dependent measures were assessed on three separate days: In a first session (for FNSD within 1 week after admission) participants were introduced into the study design and filled in questionnaires on demographic information, FNS severity and general psychological strain, alexithymia and habitual emotion regulation strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Two subsequent assessments involving the experimental emotion regulation task, during which the EEG was monitored, were scheduled before and after completion of the treatment program (patients) or after approximately 4 weeks (HC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The mean time interval between the two laboratory sessions was 23 ± 8.3 days (range 14–45 days) for FNSD patients and 33 ± 5.8 days (range 27–45 days) for HC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The respective time interval was significantly different between groups [T(36) = 4.5, p &lt; 0.001]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Data Acquisition and Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2-3-1"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Functional Neurological Symptoms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Functional neurological symptoms were assessed with the Somatoform Dissociation Questionnaire [SDQ-20 (26), German version by Mueller-Pfeiffer et al. (27)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The SDQ-20 is a 20-item self-report instrument, which assesses the frequency of somatoform dissociation experienced in the preceding 12 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Good internal consistency (Cronbach’s α = 0.92) and test–retest reliability (rtt = 0.89) are reported (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In consideration of the 4-week treatment-interval assessment, a 1-week evaluation period was adopted for the present study, since changes were expected to be most pronounced in this time range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In addition, subjectively experienced symptom intensity was rated on an 11-point Likert scale with a range from 0 “no symptoms” to 10 “maximum intensity” pre and post each EEG session. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-2"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Psychological Strain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Psychological strain was evaluated with the Symptom-Checklist 90R [SCL 90R (28)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The SCL90R includes 90 items that are rated on a five-point Likert scale and combined to nine subscales: somatization, obsessive-compulsiveness, interpersonal sensitivity, depression, anxiety, anger-hostility, phobic anxiety, paranoid ideation, and psychoticism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The mean score of items per subscale represents the respective dimension, while the general psychological strain load is represented by the mean score of all 90 items (global severity index, GSI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Good reliability is approved for subscales [between r = 0.75 and r = 0.87 (29)] and global indices [rtt = 0.68 to rtt = 0.80 (28)]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-3"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Emotion Regulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Emotion regulation covered alexithymia, assessed with the Toronto Alexithymia Scale [TAS-26 (30), German version (31)], and the Emotion Regulation Questionnaire [ERQ (8), German version (32)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The TAS-26 includes 26 self-report items that measure alexithymia on three dimensions: “difficulty identifying feelings,” “difficulty describing feelings,” and “externally oriented thinking.” Internal consistency (α = 0.84) and convergent validity are evaluated as good (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The ERQ includes six items addressing cognitive reappraisal and four items addressing emotion suppression, each rated on a 7-point Likert scale, with good convergent validity and internal consistencies (32). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Differences between groups and assessments (pre-/posttreatment) in FNS- and emotion regulation indices were statistically evaluated by dependent-sample t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Since the assumption of homogeneity of variance was not met, between-group differences were evaluated with non-parametric Mann–Whitney U tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In FNSD patients, the relationships between changes in symptom severity and changes in emotion processing across the treatment period (post-pre difference scores of each scale) were probed using bivariate Pearson correlation analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>To reduce the likelihood of a type I error, we applied a Bonferroni–Holm correction for multiple tests (33) and report only the corrected p-values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-4"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Cortical Correlates of Emotion Regulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Cortical correlates of emotion regulation were measured in an experimental emotion regulation task adopted from Fiess et al. (18) and adjusted to EEG monitoring: 70 high-arousing unpleasant and 70 low-arousing neutral pictures from the International Affective Picture System (34) were presented on a screen about 90 cm from the participant’s eyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The 2-s picture presentation was preceded by a 2-s cue presentation (the capital letters A or R), indicating that participants should passively watch (A for the German word “Anschauen”) the respective picture or downregulate their emotional response to the picture using cognitive reappraisal (R for the German word “Regulieren”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Across the total 210 trials, the three conditions (watch neutral pictures, watch unpleasant pictures, and regulate emotions upon unpleasant pictures) were arranged in pseudorandom order (70 trials per condition). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Intertrial intervals were jittered between 2 and 2.5 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Following standard procedures [e.g., Moser et al. (35)] cognitive reappraisal strategies were practiced prior to the experiment with individually selected examples like “it’s a scene from a movie” or “help is coming.” As manipulation check participants were asked after the experiment, which strategy they had implemented and whether this had been successful. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-5"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>EEG Data Acquisition and Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2-3-5-1"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Data Recording and Preprocessing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The EEG was recorded from 128 electrodes with active shielding placed on a Waveguard cap with equidistant hexagonal layout (ANT Neuro) using a direct-coupled amplifier (ANT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Signals were sampled with 2,048 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>A 40-Hz low pass 0-phase filter was applied offline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Impedances of all electrodes were kept below 20 kΩ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Data were preprocessed using FieldTrip, a matlab-based open-source signal processing toolbox (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Epochs of 9 s length were extracted from the continuous recording (5 s pre-stimulus), time-locked to picture onset and corrected for cardiac, blink and eye-movement artifacts via independent component analysis (37). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-5-2"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>ERP Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>A cluster-based, dependent-sample F-test with Monte-Carlo randomization (38) was calculated for both groups in a time interval of 0.4–1 s after picture onset to identify sensor clusters indicating significant condition differences (NW: passively watch neutral pictures, UW: passively watch unpleasant pictures, UR: regulate emotion upon unpleasant pictures). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Selection of time of interest (TOI) followed evidence on the electroencephalographic late positive potential (LPP) 400 and 700 ms after stimulus onset over posterior regions that distinguishe implementation of cognitive reappraisal strategies upon unpleasant stimuli and passive watching of unpleasant stimuli (35, 39–41). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Regions of interest (ROI) were identified on the basis of this cluster procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Averaged power across those ROI and TOI was analysed in two separate repeated-measures ANOVAs with the within subject factors condition and time (pre/posttreatment) and the between subject factor group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-5-3"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Spectral Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Time-frequency representations of the measured signal were obtained using Hanning-tapered sliding window with a fixed window length of 0.5 s, resulting in a 2 Hz frequency resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Stimulus evoked activity was expressed as change of power (in percent) relative to a cue-preceding baseline (−3 to −2.25 s) and averaged separately for group (HC, FNSD patients), conditions (NW, UW, UR), and time point (pre-/posttreatment or first–second assessment, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Group differences in the modulation of oscillatory activity in a time-window from 0.3 to 2 s after picture onset in the frequency band of 8–12 Hz were evaluated using cluster-based dependent-sample t-tests with Monte-Carlo randomization1 (N = 1000; allowing the control of type 1 error rate in the context of multiple comparisons) with a 5% significance threshold for activity differences between sensor clusters (38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Time-window and frequency band were selected to be comparable to Fiess et al. (18) and Popov et al. (42). Posthoc planned comparisons confirmed the “emotion effect” as UW minus NW contrast, and the regulation effect as UR minus UW contrast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Group and time differences between were evaluated using independent-sample t-test statistics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3-5-4"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Source Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Sources of activity that generated the effects at sensor level were determined by dynamical imaging of coherent sources beamformer on time-frequency windows that were defined based on the results at sensor level [DICS (43)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Cross-spectral density matrices for a time period of 0.3–2 s after stimulus onset were calculated separately for conditions and groups using a multitaper method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The center frequency was set to 10 ± 2 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A standard Montreal Neurological Institute-based (http://www.bic.mni.mcgill.ca/brianweb) boundary element method model (44) was used to create a realistic volume conduction model of the head. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Electrodes were aligned using an ANT-specific template layout of the electrodes, based on averaged digitized electrode positions of 20 volunteers not included in the present report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Within-subjects, differences in source power for the “emotion effect” (NW − UW) and the “regulation effect” (UR − UW), were evaluated for the 0.3- to 2-s interval as defined above using dependent-sample t-tests, and group differences for each effect was examined by independent-sample t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>All analyses were two-sided with an alpha-level set to 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Relationships between changes in symptom severity scores, emotion regulation scores, and cortical emotion regulation indices across time/treatment were probed with bivariate Pearson correlation analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3-1"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Pretreatment Group Comparison </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Functional neurological symptom disorder patients reported higher FNS severity (SDQ-20: U = 48.5, p &lt; 0.00) and higher psychological strain (SCL-90R: U = 22, p &lt; 0.00) than HC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Emotion regulation in FNSD patients differed from HC with respect to more alexithymia than HC (TAS-26: U = 41, p &lt; 0.00), less tendencies to use cognitive reappraisal (ERQ-R: U = 87.5, p &lt; 0.006) but similar tendencies for emotion suppression (ERQ-S: U = 167.5, p = 0.71). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In the entire sample (FNSD patients and HC), symptom and emotion regulation measures were related, in that TAS-26 scores varied with SDQ-20 (r = 0.57, p &lt; 0.001), SCL-90R GSI (r = 0.74, p &lt; 0.001), and subjective level of symptom intensity in FNSD patients (r = 0.64, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Group-specific relationships were confirmed for TAS-26–SCL-90R GSI (r = 0.65, p = 0.003) in FNSD patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-2"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Changes in the Context of Time/Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Bonferroni–Holm adjusted effects confirmed significant changes over time/treatment only for increased use of cognitive reappraisal strategies in FNSD patients [ERQ-R, t(16) = −3.9, p = 0.001, here, the significant alpha-level after Bonferroni–Holm correction should be p &lt; 0.0035], which did not differ from that in HC at the second assessment (U = 129, p = 0.3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>A slight decrease in symptom severity [SDQ-20, t(16) = 0.135, p = 0.9, following Bonferroni–Holm correction p &lt; 0.05 would have been needed to reach significance], and psychological strain [SCL-90R from pre M ± SD.66 ± 0.48 to posttreatment M ± SD = 0.87 ± 0.5; t(16) = 0.14, p = 0.018, Bonferroni–Holm corrected p &lt; 0.004 would have been needed] in FNSD patients did not reach significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Hence, both symptom severity and psychological strain remained higher in FNSD than in HC (SDQ-20: U = 45.5, p &lt; 0.001 SCL-90R: U = 46.5, p &lt; 0.001) at the second assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In FNSD patients, no significant changes can be reported for subjective symptom report [t(16) = 2.1, p = 0.05, Bonferroni–Holm corrected p &lt; 0.007 would have been needed]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Similarly, alexithymia [t(16) = 1.37, p = 0.19, adjusted p, 0.01] and emotion suppression [t(16) = −0.45, p = 0.66, adjusted alpha-level: p = 0.02] did not vary with treatment and changes in symptom severity were not related with changes in emotion processing in FSND patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For an overview on all reported Bonferroni–Holm adjusted alpha-levels please see Table S3 in Supplementary Material in Data Sheet S1 in Supplementary Material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-3"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Cortical Indices of Emotion Regulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 illustrates the identified ROI and corresponding time-course of the ERP during the stimulus–task interval separately for groups and conditions (passive watch, regulate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>An “emotion effect” [F(1,36) = 107,16, p &lt; 0.001] was indicated by the larger LPP in response to unpleasant compared to neutral stimuli in both groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a “regulation effect” was present in both groups [F(1,36) = 8,62, p &lt; 0.01] with larger LPP during the regulation of unpleasant stimuli compared to the passive watching. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>On the left part, sensor clusters indicating significant condition differences (marked by asterics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>On the right part, corresponding time-courses of power of the measured signal averaged seperately over conditions (UW—passively watch unpleasant pictures, UR—regulate emotions upon unpleasant pictures, NW—passively watch neutral pictures) and groups [HC—healthy comparison subjects and functional neurological symptom disorder (FNSD)—patients with FNSD]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-09-00035-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Frequency-domain analyses (see methods) indicated event-related decrease in the 8–12 Hz alpha power in the 0.3- to 2-s time-window after stimulus onset relative to baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 illustrates the time-course of event-related alpha power decrease across a 3-s baseline and 2-s stimulus interval separately for groups and conditions: In the pretreatment assessment, greater alpha power decrease during UW (watch unpleasant stimuli) than NW (watch neutral) trials characterized the “emotion effect” on sensor and source level in both groups (HC: p &lt; 0.001, FNSD patients: p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In the same time interval, the “regulation effect” was evident in both groups in marked alpha power decrease during UR compared to UW condition on sensor level (HC: p &lt; 0.01; FNSD patients: p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Neither “emotion effect” nor “regulation effect” changed over time (p = 0.34), indicating response stability in HC, and no impact of the treatment period on cortical correlates of emotion regulation in patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, within the FNSD sample, changes of the “regulation effect” across time varied with changes in the subjectively rated symptom severity (r = 0.52, p = 0.02) in that larger (post-minus pre treatment) changes in power between the conditions “watch unpleasant” and “regulate unpleasant” varied with larger changes in experienced symptom severity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Grand average time-course of power in the 8–12 Hz band expressed as change (in percent) from pre-stimulus baseline (−3 to −2.25 s) for healthy comparison subjects (HC) and patients with functional neurological symptom disorder (FNSD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Time-courses of power changes during the picture interval (0–2 s) are averaged per group and condition (UW—passively watch unpleasant pictures, UR—regulate emotions upon unpleasant pictures, NW—passively watch neutral pictures). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Light-gray shaded areas mark the emotion effect, dark-gray shaded areas mark the regulation effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-09-00035-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The present study evaluated indices of emotion regulation in relation to FNS by comparing these indices between FNSD patients and healthy controls and their variation with time and/or treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It was hypothesized (1) that groups differed in alexithymia, habitual emotion regulation style, and cortical responses during an experimental emotion regulation task before the treatment period and (2) that in FNSD patients changes in symptom severity and psychological strain after the treatment period varied with changes in emotion regulation indices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In support of the first expectation and in line with previous reports (10–12), FNSD patients exhibited more alexithymia and used less cognitive reappraisal strategies on everyday emotion regulation than controls, Relationships between emotion regulation indices and symptom expression were confirmed for the entire sample, but only for alexithymia and general psychological strain for FNSD patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In addition, cortical correlates of “emotion” and “regulation” effects were replicated (18), whereas frontal and more sensorimotor cortex involvement in emotion regulation in FNSD patients (16, 18) was not replicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The present small sample size and interindividual variability may have resulted in electrocortical responses overlapping between groups, preventing group differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Event-related potential analyses confirmed “emotion” and “regulation effects” in the expected cortical regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In contrast to previous reports of smaller LPP during regulation than during passive watching (45, 46) the LPP was enhanced during the regulation of the emotional response upon unpleasant pictures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Similar evidence of increased LPP under regulation instructions was recently reported by Ellis et al. (47), suggesting that this increase may reflect allocation of attention upon the instruction to actively regulate upcoming emotions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The expected changes over a period that included a standard treatment program for FNSD patients were not confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Robust changes were only confirmed for an increased tendency to use cognitive reappraisal as emotion regulation strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The tendency to use suppressive strategies of emotion regulation did not change over time and did not differ between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>These results are in line with previous evidence of an association between reappraisal but not suppression with physic and psychic health (48, 49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Moreover, results on cortical emotion regulation indices indicated their stability, but did not vary with treatment in FNSD patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Different factors may have contributed to the lack of significant differences between groups and over time: in addition to larger sample sizes for adequate statistical power, the short 4-week treatment program (i.e., following the standard health insurance coverage in Germany) may be insufficient to prompt substantial and sustained changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The present small sample size constrained the comparison of FNSD patients who benefited from treatment or did not change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Treatment effects on emotion regulation strategies and their cortical correlates may emerge only with longer treatment periods or may develop over time even after the end of treatment, as shown by (50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Finally, more specific modules and targeted treatment may be a prerequisite for treatment-induced changes in emotion regulation on the different levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>So far, whether the self-reported increase of cognitive reappraisal to downregulate negative emotion reflects a substantial change in emotion regulation strategies or a trained reproduction of what was learnt in psychotherapy on how to (theoretically) regulate emotion without behavioral effects, remains unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Emotion regulation was just one target in the standard treatment program of the involved neurological rehabilitation center, and thus, the impact of intense treatment procedures focusing on emotion regulation remains to be evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In consideration of these factors, the observed tendencies encourage hypotheses to be verified in future studies with longer, targeted treatment and follow-up assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>To conclude: probing the meaning of emotion regulation, measured on subjective and cortical level, in FNSD in the context of time/treatment offers first clues that need to be substantiated in powered, targeted studies: changes in the subjectively experienced symptom severity and psychological strain may vary with a tendency to adjust everyday emotion regulation toward accentuated use of cognitive strategies, and to reduce alexithymia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>If substantiated, this should be considered in designing the concept of FNS and their generation, as well as for the adjustment of remediation strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The study design was approved by the Ethics committee of the University of Konstanz and by the IRB of the Kliniken Schmieder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>All participants provided written informed consent prior to assessment onset in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>AS-K and BR designed the project and, together with JK, JF, and RS, the study protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>JK and JF collected the data under the supervision of AS-K and RS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>JK, TP, and JF analyzed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>JK, AS-K, and BR drafted the manuscript, and all authors contributed to the final version. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The assistance of Lea Glaser, Martha Hofmann, Anna Döpke, Lisa Wetzel, Celina Hirth-Walter, Vera Gögele, Ursula Lommen, and Barbara Awiszus in data collection is greatly acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we thank the medical and psychotherapeutical teams of the Psychotherapeutic Neurology section, Kliniken Schmieder Konstanz and Gailingen for their support in patient recruitment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Thank you also to the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, the University of Konstanz and the Lurija Institute of the Schmieder Foundation for making this project possible. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Funding. Research was supported by the German Research Council (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft; grant to the senior author, project number STE 2263/2-1) and the University of Konstanz. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>1This procedure begins with a t-test between every combination of time point and channel in the actual data and between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Adjacent time-channel-combinations that showed significant group differences in the t-tests were clustered by summing the t-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>A 1000-fold repetition of this procedure after randomly assigning group associations of each subject can be described as “Monte Carlo permutation,” resulting in a distribution with parallel results that is used for comparison with the original data: For each iteration, the t-value sum from the cluster with the highest t-value sum is added to a distribution reflecting the null hypothesis of no group difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Finally, this hypothesis is evaluated by comparing the t-value sums of the actual data and the calculated distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="S8" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00035/full#supplementary-material">http://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00035/full#supplementary-material</uri>.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="table_2.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="table_3.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>1American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5. Washington, DC: American Psychological Association (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="?"><plain>2CarsonAJRingbauerBStoneJMcKenzieLWarlowCSharpeM. Do medically unexplained symptoms matter? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>A prospective cohort study of 300 new referrals to neurology outpatient clinics. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry (2000) 68(2):207–10.10.1136/jnnp.68.2.207<?supplied-pmid 10644789?>10644789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>3CarsonALehnA. Epidemiology. Handb Clin Neurol (2016) 139:47–60.10.1016/b978-0-12-801772-2.00005-9<?supplied-pmid 27719864?>27719864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>4BreuerJFreudS Studien über Hysterie. Leipzig and Vienna: Deutike (1985). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>5World Health Organization. ICD-10 Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders (The): Diagnostic Criteria for Research. Geneva: World Health Organization (1993). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>6HallettM The most promising advances in our understanding and treatment of functional (psychogenic) movement disorders. Parkinsonism Relat Disord (2017) 46(Suppl 1):S80–2.10.1016/j.parkreldis.2017.07.00228709746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>7GündelH, Ceballos-BaumannAOvon RadM Aktuelle Perspektiven der Alexithymie. Der Nervenarzt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>(2000) 71(3):151–63.10756523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>8GrossJJ. Emotion regulation: affective, cognitive, and social consequences. Psychophysiology (2002) 39(3):281–91.10.1017/S0048577201393198<?supplied-pmid 12212647?>12212647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>9GyurakAGrossJJEtkinA. Explicit and implicit emotion regulation: a dual-process framework. Cogn Emot (2011) 25(3):400–12.10.1080/02699931.2010.544160<?supplied-pmid 21432682?>21432682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>10DemartiniBPetrochilosPRicciardiLPriceGEdwardsMJJoyceE The role of alexithymia in the development of functional motor symptoms (conversion disorder). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry (2014) 85(10):1132–7.10.1136/jnnp-2013-30720324610939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>11GulpekDKelemence KaplanFKesebirSBoraO. Alexithymia in patients with conversion disorder. Nord J Psychiatry (2014) 68(5):300–5.10.3109/08039488.2013.814711<?supplied-pmid 23902128?>23902128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="?"><plain>12KienleJRockstrohBBohusMFiessJHuffzigerSSteffen-KlattA Somatoform dissociation and posttraumatic stress syndrome – two sides of the same medal? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>A comparison of symptom profiles, trauma history and altered affect regulation between patients with functional neurological symptoms and patients with PTSD. BMC Psychiatry (2017) 17(1):24810.1186/s12888-017-1414-z28693577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>13SteffenAFiessJSchmidtRRockstrohB “That pulled the rug out from under my feet!” – adverse experiences and altered emotion processing in patients with functional neurological symptoms compared to healthy comparison subjects. BMC Psychiatry (2015) 15:13310.1186/s12888-015-0514-x26103961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>14EtkinABuchelCGrossJJ. The neural bases of emotion regulation. Nat Rev Neurosci (2015) 16(11):693–700.10.1038/nrn4044<?supplied-pmid 26481098?>26481098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>15López-PérezBAmbronaT The role of cognitive emotion regulation on the vicarious emotional response. Motiv Emot (2015) 39(2):299–308.10.1007/s11031-014-9452-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>16VoonVBrezingCGalleaCAmeliRRoelofsKLaFranceWC Emotional stimuli and motor conversion disorder. Brain (2010) 133(5):1526–36.10.1093/brain/awq054<?supplied-pmid 20371508?>20371508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>17AybekSNicholsonTRO’DalyOZelayaFKanaanRADavidAS. Emotion-motion interactions in conversion disorder: an fMRI study. PLoS One (2015) 10(4):e0123273.10.1371/journal.pone.0123273<?supplied-pmid 25859660?>25859660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>18FiessJRockstrohBSchmidtRSteffenA. Emotion regulation and functional neurological symptoms: does emotion processing convert into sensorimotor activity? J Psychosom Res (2015) 79(6):477–83.10.1016/j.jpsychores.2015.10.009<?supplied-pmid 26652591?>26652591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>19BlakemoreRLSinanajIGalliSAybekSVuilleumierP. Aversive stimuli exacerbate defensive motor behaviour in motor conversion disorder. Neuropsychologia (2016) 93(Pt A):229–41.10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2016.11.005<?supplied-pmid 27842291?>27842291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>20HowlettSReuberM. An augmented model of brief psychodynamic interpersonal therapy for patients with nonepileptic seizures. Psychotherapy (Chic) (2009) 46(1):125–38.10.1037/a0015138<?supplied-pmid 22122575?>22122575 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>21McCormackRMoriartyJMellersJDShotboltPPastenaRLandesN Specialist inpatient treatment for severe motor conversion disorder: a retrospective comparative study. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry (2014) 85(8):895–900.10.1136/jnnp-2013-305716<?supplied-pmid 24124043?>24124043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>22KleinstauberMGottschalkJBerkingMRauJRiefW. Enriching cognitive behavior therapy with emotion regulation training for patients with multiple medically unexplained symptoms (ENCERT): design and implementation of a multicenter, randomized, active-controlled trial. Contemp Clin Trials (2016) 47:54–63.10.1016/j.cct.2015.12.003<?supplied-pmid 26655432?>26655432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>23DallochioCMarangiATinazziM Functional or psychogenic movement disorders: an endless enigmatic tale. Front Neurol (2015) 6:3710.3389/fneur.2015.0003725774148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>24CarsonAJBrownRDavidASDuncanREdwardsMJGoldsteinLH Functional (conversion) neurological symptoms: research since the millenium. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry (2012) 83:842–50.10.1136/jnnp-2011-30186022661497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>25AckenheilMStotzGDietz-BauerRVossenA Deutsche Fassung des Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview. Munich: Psychiatrische Universitätsklinik (1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>26NijenhuisE Development &amp; psychometric characteristics of the SDQ. J Nerv Ment Dis (1996) 184:688–94.10.1097/00005053-199611000-000068955682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>27Mueller-PfeifferCSchumacherSMartin-SoelchCPazhenkottilAPWirtzGFuhrhansC The validity and reliability of the German version of the Somatoform Dissociation Questionnaire (SDQ-20). J Trauma Dissociation (2010) 11(3):337–57.10.1080/15299731003793450<?supplied-pmid 20603767?>20603767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>28DerogatisL Self-report symptom inventory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In: Collegium Internationale Psychiatrie Scalar, editor. Internationale Skalen für Psychiatrie. Weinheim: Beltz (1986). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>29HesselASchumacherJGreyerMBrählerE Symptom-Checkliste SCL-90-R: Testtheoretische Überprüfung und Normierung an einer bevölkerungsrepräsentativen Stichprobe. Diagnostica (2001) 47(1):27–39.10.1026//0012-1924.47.1.27 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>30BagbyRMTaylorGJParkerJDA The twenty-item Toronto alexithymia scale-II. J Psychosom Res (1994) 38(1):33–40.10.1016/0022-3999(94)90005-18126688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>31KupferJBrosigBBrählerE Überprüfung und Validierung der 26-Item Toronto Alexithymie-Skala anhand einer repräsentativen Bevölkerungsstischprobe. Zeitschrift für Psychosomatische Medizin und Psychotherapie (2000) 46(4):368–84.10.13109/zptm.2000.46.4.36811793322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>32AblerBKesslerH Emotion Regulation Questionnaire – eine deutschsprachige Fassung des ERQ von Gross und John. Diagnostica (2009) 55(3):144–52.10.1026/0012-1924.55.3.144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>33HolmS A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure. Scand J Stat (1979) 6:65–70. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>34LangPJBradleyMMCuthbertBN International Affective Picture System (IAPS): Instruction Manual and Affective Ratings (Tech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Rep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>No. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>A-6). Gainesville, FL: University of Florida (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>35MoserJSHajcakGBukayESimonsRF. Intentional modulation of emotional responding to unpleasant pictures: an ERP study. Psychophysiology (2006) 43(3):292–6.10.1111/j.1469-8986.2006.00402.x<?supplied-pmid 16805868?>16805868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>36OostenveldRFriesPMarisESchoffelenJM. FieldTrip: open source software for advanced analysis of MEG, EEG, and invasive electrophysiological data. Comput Intell Neurosci (2011) 2011:156869.10.1155/2011/156869<?supplied-pmid 21253357?>21253357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>37JungT-PMakeigSMcKeownMJBellAJLeeT-WSejnowskiTJ Imaging brain dynamics using independent component analysis. Proc IEEE Inst Electr Electron Eng (2001) 89(7):1107–22.10.1109/5.93982720824156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>38MarisEOostenveldR. Nonparametric statistical testing of EEG- and MEG-data. J Neurosci Methods (2007) 164(1):177–90.10.1016/j.jneumeth.2007.03.024<?supplied-pmid 17517438?>17517438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>39CuthbertBNSchuppHTBradleyMMBirbaumerNLangPJ. Brain potentials in affective picture processing: covariation with autonomic arousal and affective report. Biol Psychol (2000) 52(2):95–111.10.1016/S0301-0511(99)00044-7<?supplied-pmid 10699350?>10699350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>40SchuppHTJunghöferMWeikeAIHammAO. The selective processing of briefly presented affective pictures: an ERP analysis. Psychophysiology (2004) 41(3):441–9.10.1111/j.1469-8986.2004.00174.x<?supplied-pmid 15102130?>15102130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>41HajcakGNieuwenhuisS. Reappraisal modulates the electrocortical response to unpleasant pictures. Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci (2006) 6(4):291–7.10.3758/CABN.6.4.291<?supplied-pmid 17458444?>17458444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>42PopovTSteffenAWeiszNMillerGARockstrohB. Cross-frequency dynamics of neuromagnetic oscillatory activity: two mechanisms of emotion regulation. Psychophysiology (2012) 49(12):1545–57.10.1111/j.1469-8986.2012.01484.x<?supplied-pmid 23074972?>23074972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>43GrossJKujalaJHämäläinenMTimmermannLSchnitzlerASalmelinR. Dynamic imaging of coherent sources: studying neural interactions in the human brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (2001) 98(2):694–9.10.1073/pnas.98.2.694<?supplied-pmid 11209067?>11209067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>44OostendorpTFvan OosteromA. Source parameter estimation in inhomogeneous volume conductors of arbitrary shape. IEEE Trans Biomed Eng (1989) 36(3):382–91.10.1109/10.19859<?supplied-pmid 2921073?>2921073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>45MoserJSKrompingerJWDietzJSimonsRF. Electrophysiological correlates of decreasing and increasing emotional responses to unpleasant pictures. Psychophysiology (2009) 46(1):17–27.10.1111/j.1469-8986.2008.00721.x<?supplied-pmid 18992073?>18992073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>46ParvazMAMacNamaraAGoldsteinRZHajcakG. Event-related induced frontal alpha as a marker of lateral prefrontal cortex activation during cognitive reappraisal. Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci (2012) 12(4):730–40.10.3758/s13415-012-0107-9<?supplied-pmid 22773414?>22773414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>47EllisJDSchroderHSPatrickCJMoserJS. Emotional reactivity and regulation in individuals with psychopathic traits: evidence for a disconnect between neurophysiology and self-report. Psychophysiology (2017) 54(10):1574–85.10.1111/psyp.12903<?supplied-pmid 28580638?>28580638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>48JohnOPGrossJJ. Healthy and unhealthy emotion regulation: personality processes, individual differences, and life span development. J Pers (2004) 72(6):1301–33.10.1111/j.1467-6494.2004.00298.x<?supplied-pmid 15509284?>15509284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>49CutuliD. Cognitive reappraisal and expressive suppression strategies role in the emotion regulation: an overview on their modulatory effects and neural correlates. Front Syst Neurosci (2014) 8:175.10.3389/fnsys.2014.00175<?supplied-pmid 25285072?>25285072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>50GoodmanMCarpenterDTangCYGoldsteinKEAvedonJFernandezN Dialectical behavior therapy alters emotion regulation and amygdala activity in patients with borderline personality disorder. J Psychiatr Res (2014) 57:108–16.10.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.06.020<?supplied-pmid 25285072?>25038629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
