<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1466-1861</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5350351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/8529542</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Human β-Defensin 3 Reduces TNF-α-Induced Inflammation and Monocyte Adhesion in Human Umbilical Vein Endothelial Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>Tianying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Houxuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Can</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yangheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5632-9487</contrib-id><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Fuhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Periodontology, Nanjing Stomatological Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Central Laboratory of Stomatology, Nanjing Stomatological Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Endodontics, Nanjing Stomatological Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Fuhua Yan: <email>fhyan2005@126.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Ulrich Eisel </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>2017</volume><elocation-id>8529542</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 Tianying Bian et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to investigate the role of human β-defensin 3 (hBD3) in the initiation stage of atherosclerosis with human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) triggered by tumor necrosis factor- (TNF-) α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced endothelial injury and inflammatory response were evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Our data revealed that first, hBD3 reduced the production of interleukin-6 (IL-6), IL-8, monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), and macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) in HUVECs in a dose-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In addition, hBD3 significantly prevented intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) production by HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Second, western blot analysis demonstrated that hBD3 dose-dependently suppressed the protein levels of intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1) and vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (VCAM-1) in TNF-α-induced HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>As a result, hBD3 inhibited monocyte adhesion to TNF-α-treated endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Additionally, hBD3 suppressed TNF-α-induced F-actin reorganization in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Third, hBD3 markedly inhibited NF-κB activation by decreasing the phosphorylation of IKK-α/β, IκB, and p65 subunit within 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the phosphorylation of p38 and c-Jun N-terminal protein kinase (JNK) in the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway were also inhibited by hBD3 in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, hBD3 exerts anti-inflammatory and antioxidative effects in endothelial cells in response to TNF-α by inhibiting NF-κB and MAPK signaling. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809">National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>81371152</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Atherosclerosis is a vascular inflammatory disease characterized by the accumulation of lipids and immune cells on the inner face of the arterial wall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory stimulation, even low level endotoxemia, can aggravate the progression of this disease [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A monolayer of endothelial cells, which directly contacts the flowing blood, is easily attacked by various stimulating factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cell dysfunction triggered by such stimulations is believed to be the initiation step and key contributor in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cells at sites of inflammation are not only participants but also regulators of inflammation [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>During inflammation, a large amount of inflammatory mediators are produced by immune cells, such as macrophages, and endothelial cells are the main targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Then, the activated endothelial cells secrete a broad spectrum of cytokines and chemokines, recruiting monocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Enhanced migration and adhesion of monocytes to the endothelium are suggested to play a crucial role in atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In addition, the expression of adhesion molecules required for the firm binding of monocytes is also upregulated on endothelial cell surfaces [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, the results demonstrated that chronic exposure to the endotoxin of Porphyromonas gingivalis can aggravate atherosclerotic lesions in ApoE-deficient mice [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Indeed, compelling evidence has demonstrated the proatherogenic role of inflammatory cytokines in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Elevated levels of several inflammatory markers in the circulation are risk factors for atherosclerotic events [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), one of the most potent inflammatory cytokines, is closely associated with atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It is mainly produced by activated macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>It is a pleiotropic cytokine mediating inflammation, immunity, and apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>For vascular endothelial cells, exposure to TNF-α triggers several signaling cascades in human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs), especially the nuclear factor κB (NF-κB), c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), and p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways, leading to the production of inflammatory cytokines [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In addition, TNF-α can reorganize the F-actin cytoskeleton of endothelial cells, leading to the formation of stress fibers [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>TNF-α can also modulate EC permeability by enlarging intercellular gaps, promoting vascular leakage at sites of inflammation [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>TNF-α stimulation is also associated with increased intracellular levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS) formation, enhancing monocyte recruitment and adhesion to the vascular endothelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This process is mediated mainly by elevated cell adhesion molecules such as intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (VCAM-1), and endothelial cell selectin (E-selectin). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Defensins are naturally occurring peptides with a wide range of antimicrobial, antiviral, and immunomodulatory properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>They are cationic, cysteine-rich, β-sheet, and tridisulfide peptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In humans, defensins are classified into two categories, α- and β-defensins. β-defensins are mainly produced by the mucosa and epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Intraocular tissues and the human endometrium are also reported to express β-defensins [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Several studies have documented the participation of antimicrobial peptides in endothelial immune defense [12, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In addition, β-defensins are beneficial for wound healing of endothelial cells [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Human β-defensin 3 (hBD3) is a member of the β-defensin family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In addition to epithelial cells, hBD3 is also expressed in endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The gene and protein expression of hBD3 are induced in human umbilical vein endothelial cells simulated with TNF-α [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The upregulation of hBD3 by TNF-α in HUVECs illustrates the important role that defensins play in host immune defense against inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, we demonstrated that hBD3 strongly inhibited the progression of early-stage atherosclerotic lesions and inflammation levels in RAW 264.7 cells and human THP-1-derived macrophages [16, 17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>However, the cell types targeted by hBD3 might not be restricted to macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Vascular endothelial cells and monocytes/macrophages are both atherogenic and critical components in the process of atherogenesis [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The interaction between macrophages and endothelial cells is very crucial in atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In normal conditions, resting endothelial cells form an integrated barrier at the blood-tissue interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Upon inflammatory stimulation, quiescent endothelial cells may transform into a proatherogenic phenotype, inducing the infiltration of monocytes [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The recruited monocytes then differentiate into macrophages, contributing to a vicious cycle promoting endothelial dysfunction [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>As the endothelium has already been a therapeutic target, hBD3 might also manifest its protective effects by interacting with vessel endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced endothelial cell activation remain unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Thus, the present study was designed to focus on the effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-stimulated endothelial cell dysfunction, including the enhanced production of inflammatory mediators, monocyte adhesion, and the expression of cell adhesion molecules, all of which are early events in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Cell Culture and Reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Human primary umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) (ScienCell Research Laboratories, San Diego, CA) were maintained in endothelial cell medium (ECM) (ScienCell Research Laboratories) supplemented with 5% FBS, 1% penicillin/streptomycin, and 1% endothelial cell growth supplement (ECGS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>For the present study, cells at passages 3–6 were seeded and grown until confluence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Recombinant human TNF-α and hBD3 were obtained from PeproTech (Rocky Hill, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Anti-ICAM-1 and anti-VCAM-1 antibodies were obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Antiphosphorylated and total IκBα, p65, p38, ERK, and JNK antibodies were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Cell Viability Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The cell viability of HUVECs was determined using a CCK8 assay according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>HUVECs (5000 cells/well) were prepared in 96-well plates and incubated overnight before treatment with various concentrations of hBD3 (20, 10, 5, 2.5, or 1.25 μg/mL) and TNF-α (40 ng/mL) for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, 10 μL of CCK8 solution (Dojindo Laboratories, Kumamoto, Japan) was added to each well, and the cells were incubated for an additional 3 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The optical density of each well was evaluated at a wavelength of 450 nm on a microplate spectrophotometer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were seeded and cultured in a 96-well plate until confluent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The control group was treated with ECM and the other seven groups were treated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) in the presence of various concentrations of hBD3 for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Then the cell supernatants were collected by centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The assay was performed with specific ELISA kits (R&amp;D Systems) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Monocyte Adhesion Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Confluent HUVECs were stimulated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) in the presence or absence of hBD3 for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After that, the cells were washed with RPMI-1640 medium before being cocultured with THP-1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>THP-1 cells were prelabeled with 2 μM calcein-AM (Dojindo Laboratories) in RPMI-1640 medium for 20 min in the cell incubator before being added to each well of HUVECs and further incubated for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>After coincubation, each well was washed gently and thoroughly with RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 1% FBS to remove the nonadherent THP-1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The attached THP-1 cells were examined under a microscope (Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) and fluorescence microplate reader at excitation and emission wavelengths of 490 nm and 515 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Western Blot Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The cells were lysed in RIPA buffer supplemented with protease inhibitors for 30 min, and the whole cell lysates were separated by electrophoresis in sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gels (SDS-PAGE) and then transferred to PVDF membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The membranes were blocked with 5% BSA at room temperature for 2 h before incubation overnight with primary antibodies against the target protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Blots were washed with Tris-buffered saline containing 0.1% Tween 20 three times and then incubated for 2 h with anti-rabbit secondary antibody at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The bands were detected using chemiluminescence detection agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Images were captured with an ImageQuant LAS 4000 digital imaging system (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were seeded onto sterile glass coverslips in a 12-well cell culture plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>After incubation overnight, the cells were treated with the indicated concentrations of hBD3 under TNF-α stimulation for the indicated time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the cells were washed and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min at room temperature and then treated with 0.3% Triton X-100 for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>After that, the cells were blocked with 3% BSA for 1 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Then, the cells were further incubated with the indicated rabbit primary antibody at 4°C overnight, followed by incubation with a goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody conjugated to Alexa Fluor 488 (for NF-κB p65) (1 : 1000, Abcam) or Alexa Fluor 594 (for ICAM-1) (1 : 1000, Abcam) for 2 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The slides were then mounted with one drop of mounting medium that contained DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>NF-κB p65 and ICAM-1 were imaged using a confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>ICAM-1 was visualized as red and NF-κB p65 was visualized as green, with nuclei as blue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Measurement of Intracellular Reactive Oxygen Species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Intracellular ROS formation was determined with DCFH-DA (KeyGEN, Jiangsu, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were seeded in black 96-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the cells were treated with TNF-α with or without indicated concentrations of hBD3 for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The cells were then washed with PBS and incubated with 20 μM DCFH-DA for 30 min at 37°C in the dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence level was determined using a fluorescence microplate reader at an excitation wavelength of 485 nm and an emission wavelength of 530 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>F-Actin Staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Human umbilical vein endothelial cells were cultured and treated with TNF-α as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Then, the cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde at room temperature for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>After that, the actin cytoskeleton was stained with DyLight 488-phalloidin, and the nuclei were stained with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Stained HUVECs were visualized using a confocal microscope (Olympus FV 10i). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>2.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as the means ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Comparison between different treatments was performed using GraphPad PRISM software version 6.0 using one-way ANOVA with Tukey's post hoc test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was set at p values &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on the Viability of TNF-α-Induced Endothelial Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Numerous studies have demonstrated that TNF-α treatment can impair endothelial cell viability and induce apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>First, we evaluated the cytotoxic effects of TNF-α on HUVECs using a CCK8 assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>All data are expressed as the survival percentage of each group relative to the control group, which is defined as 100%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 1, compared with the control group, TNF-α at a concentration of 40 ng/mL could markedly suppress the proliferation of HUVECs by nearly 50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In addition, treatment with hBD3 at 5 μg/mL and 10 μg/mL markedly recovered TNF-α-impaired cell viability to about 79.1% and 101.7%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The results also suggested that hBD3 does not influence the viability of HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on the Production of Proinflammatory Mediators by Endothelial Cells Stimulated with TNF-α </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Next, we examined the effects of hBD3 on endothelial cell activation stimulated by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cells stimulated with TNF-α produce proinflammatory mediators, including interleukin- (IL-) 6, IL-8, and monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), which cause more monocytes to be recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These proinflammatory mediators are reported to aggravate endothelial dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 2(a), when the cells were treated with TNF-α for 24 h, IL-8 production in the supernatant was significantly elevated; however, with hBD3 intervention, IL-8 level was markedly and dose-dependently inhibited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The same trend of IL-6 and MCP-1 was also observed in Figures 2(b) and 2(c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) is a key factor mediating the interactions between macrophages and endothelial cells [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>It is considered to interact with other proinflammatory cytokines during inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>There is evidence showing it is a potent activator of macrophages released by activated endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The release of MIF by HUVECs was markedly inhibited in response to hBD3 treatment (Figure 2(d)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on the Expression of Adhesion Molecules by HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Accumulated evidence supports a role for adhesion molecules in the progression of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 are constitutively expressed on the surface of HUVECs, and E-selectin is only expressed on the activated endothelium [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The interaction of E-selectin and leukocytes mediates the rolling of leukocytes on the activated endothelium, which is the first event in firm adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>TNF-α is known to transiently upregulate the expression of adhesion molecules, such as ICAM-1 and VCAM-1, in HUVECs [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We then evaluated the effects of hBD3 on the expression of adhesion molecules induced by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>As demonstrated in Figure 3(a), treatment with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) significantly enhanced the expression level of ICAM-1 (24 h), VCAM-1 (24 h), and E-selectin (4 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In addition, hBD3 treatment dose-dependently prevented the upregulation of ICAM-1, VCAM-1, and E-selectin levels by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The immunofluorescence staining assay also validated the inhibitory effects of hBD3 (15 μg/mL) on ICAM-1 expression levels triggered by TNF-α (Figure 3(b)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on Monocyte Adhesion to Endothelial Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>During the initiation of atherosclerosis, endothelial cells are activated and upregulate adhesion molecules and chemokine and cytokine secretion, which is beneficial for monocyte recruitment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Due to the significant decrease in cell surface adhesion molecules and proinflammatory mediators in hBD3-treated HUVECs, we investigated whether hBD3 could affect the attachment of immune cells to endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the effects of hBD3 on THP-1 monocyte adhesion to HUVECs in a TNF-α-stimulated proinflammatory environment, HUVECs were seeded and cultured to about 90% confluence and then stimulated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) in the presence or absence of hBD3 (15 μg/mL) for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, HUVECs were cocultured with prelabeled THP-1 cells for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>After removal of nonadherent THP-1 cells by gentle washing, images were captured under a fluorescence microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figures 4(a) and 4(b), we observed that, compared with the control group, TNF-α treatment resulted in a 4-fold increase (p &lt; 0.001) in THP-1 attachment to HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, hBD3 intervention significantly decreased THP-1 adhesion to HUVECs (p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>hBD3 Suppressed Activation of the NF-κB and MAPK Pathways in HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>NF-κB is considered as an important regulator of the proinflammatory process and monocyte adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>To identify the probable molecular mechanism responsible for hBD3 involvement in the modulation of TNF-α-treated HUVECs, we first evaluated the classical NF-κB signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Here, we show that hBD3 strongly inhibits TNF-α-stimulated HUVECs via two distinct signaling pathways, an NF-κB-dependent pathway and the MAPK pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>We examined key factors in the NF-κB pathway with western blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Activation of NF-κB required the phosphorylation and degradation of IκB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5(a), degradation and phosphorylation of IκB were significantly suppressed by the addition of hBD3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The effective role of hBD3 to prevent phosphorylation of p65 subunit was also observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In addition, phosphorylated IKKα, which is the upstream modulator in the NF-κB pathway, was also inhibited by hBD3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>To validate this result, immunofluorescence staining was used to determine NF-κB nuclear translocation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5(b), NF-κB p65 was predominantly located within the cytoplasm in unstimulated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>With TNF-α treatment, p65 translocated to the nucleus within 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, treatment with hBD3 at 15 μg/mL led to retention of the p65 subunit in the cytoplasm of TNF-α-stimulated cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We then investigated the role of the MAPK pathway in this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The key components of the MAPK pathway, p38, ERK, and JNK were evaluated with a western blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5(c), treatment of TNF-α resulted in a significant increase of phosphorylation in the MAPK pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The phosphorylation of p38 and JNK was significantly and concentration-dependently suppressed by hBD3 at 30 min, while the phosphorylation of ERK was not altered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The cell lysates obtained at 45 min also validated this result. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on the Activation of Caspases and Bcl-2 Expression in HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>TNF-α has been reported to stimulate apoptosis in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition, the cleavage of caspase-3 is a key step in TNF-α-induced cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Before activation, caspase-3 exists as an inactive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>After TNF-α-treatment, caspase-3 was cleaved to the active form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The activation of caspases is considered one mechanism of apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we investigated the effects of hBD3 on the activation of caspases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were treated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) for 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of caspase-3 were examined with western blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis revealed that the expression levels of cleaved caspase-3 significantly increased following TNF-α treatment, while hBD3 markedly suppressed this phenomenon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, we examined the expression level of Bcl-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 6, there was a clear decrease in the expression of Bcl-2 after treatment with TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that hBD3 inhibited the apoptosis of HUVECs stimulated by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>hBD3 Suppressed TNF-α-Induced ROS Formation in HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that the enhanced production of intracellular ROS can lead to cell apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>To measure the potential modulation of apoptosis and oxidative stress by hBD3, the production of ROS was evaluated for fluorescence intensity in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>As revealed in Figure 7(a), HUVECs stimulated with TNF-α produced an intracellular burst of ROS (about 3.9-fold change). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The intracellular ROS production in HUVECs was significantly suppressed when treated with hBD3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>However, the basal level of ROS was not altered by treatment with hBD3 alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>hBD3 Repressed TNF-α-Induced F-Actin Reorganization in HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>TNF-α is reported to have the ability to alter the permeability and morphology of endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>To investigate the role of hBD3 in TNF-α-induced endothelial function, HUVECs were treated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) in the presence or absence of hBD3 (15 μg/mL) for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Then, the cells were fixed and stained with phalloidin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 8, stimulating HUVECs with TNF-α resulted in a significant increase in the formation of actin stress fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In addition, hBD3 treatment markedly reduced this alteration in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Atherosclerosis is defined as a chronic inflammatory-fibroproliferative response of the vascular wall to various forms of inflammatory stimuli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Disruption of the endothelial cell barrier induced by proinflammatory cytokines, such as TNF-α, is the initiating step of this disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cells maintain vascular homeostasis via the secretion of several vasoactive factors, and impairment of barrier integrity leads to the development of vascular inflammatory diseases, such as atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>As a monolayer in direct contact with the bloodstream, the vascular endothelium is the principal physiological target of the proinflammatory actions of TNF-α and IL-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Extensive evidence has suggested that the endothelium is not simply the inner cellular lining of blood vessels [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Beyond being passively targeted, endothelial cells are believed to be profoundly involved in this inflammatory process, especially in the regulation of effector cells, such as monocytes and lymphocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the endothelium may act as a therapeutic target due to its critical role in the inflammatory process [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) is one of the most important cytokines produced by endothelial cells to control the accumulation of effector cells [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>It is recognized as an effective activator of macrophages, participating in the process of recruitment and the accumulation of macrophages at local inflammatory sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>As monocyte adhesion to the endothelium is a crucial step in the early stages of atherosclerosis, MIF is considered to be involved in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis and is closely related to plaque stability [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Elevated MIF expression was observed in response to some immunostimulants in HUVECs [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In our experiment, the production of MIF was markedly increased under TNF-α stimulation in HUVECs, while treatment with hBD3 dose-dependently reduced MIF expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>This result was also confirmed by the effect of hBD3 in inhibiting the adhesion of monocytes to endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A prominent feature of TNF-α-induced endothelial cell injury is the excess generation of intracellular ROS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Moderate levels of ROS have been reported to participate in the physiological functions of cells, while the overproduction of intracellular ROS is closely associated with the progression of atherosclerosis [29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress activates endothelial cells, causing cell injury, apoptosis, and enhanced monocyte adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In the present study, treatment with hBD3 attenuated ROS production in HUVECs stimulated with TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The binding of TNF-α to cell surface receptors triggers multiple signaling events, including NF-κB and MAPK pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>NF-κB has been demonstrated to be a key transcription factor in this signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Activation of NF-κB is closely associated with the initiation and progression of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>In resting cells, NF-κB is maintained in an inactive form within the cytoplasm by the inhibitor of κB (IκB) family but enters the nucleus in response to external stimuli, such as TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>IκB kinase- (IKK-) dependent phosphorylation and the subsequent ubiquitination and degradation of IκB make NF-κB free to translocate to the nucleus and induce downstream transcription [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>NF-κB has been identified as an important target in the treatment of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Our data revealed that hBD3 markedly reduced the phosphorylation of IκB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the p65 subunit of NF-κB is constitutively phosphorylated at a low level in unstimulated conditions, and treatment with inflammatory triggers, LPS and TNF-α, for example, results in further phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The total level of phosphorylation of p65 was also suppressed by the addition of hBD3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We also investigated the phosphorylation of IKK-α/β, which is an upstream signaling molecule of NF-κB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrated that hBD3 inhibited IKK-α/β phosphorylation 30 min after TNF-α stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>In addition, the inhibition of ROS generation also contributes to the decrease in NF-κB activation, as NF-κB activation by ROS through the IKK pathway has been suggested [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The downregulation of cell adhesion molecules in HUVECs by hBD3 might be mediated through inhibition of the NF-κB pathway, as the TNF-α-mediated increase in ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 expression is mediated through the NF-κB pathway, not the MAPK pathway [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Ample evidence has documented intensive crosstalk between the NF-κB and MAPK signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The MAPK pathway is required for NF-κB activation in TNF-α-mediated inflammation [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In addition, the JNK pathway was suggested to promote cell apoptosis [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>hBD3 was reported to rapidly enter the cells and impact TLR signaling pathway associated with MyD88 and TRIF [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In this case, there is also possibility that hBD3 inhibits TNF signaling via interaction with the upstream molecules in the signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Further research needs to be done to elucidate this problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Human β-defensin 3 is a multifunctional effector molecule involved in a startling range of cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>First, as an antimicrobial peptide, hBD3 exhibits broad antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria, fungi, and viruses [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Second, it was demonstrated to have immunomodulatory effects due to its biphasic effect in the host immune response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>It can be either proinflammatory or anti-inflammatory, depending on the circumstances [38, 39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In addition, the beneficial effects of hBD3 on wound healing were also reported [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>We previously demonstrated that hBD3 significantly inhibited the progression of early-stage atherosclerotic lesions, and this effect was correlated with downregulation of macrophage inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>To date, there is no study focusing on the effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced endothelial inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In the present study, our data extend the protective effects of hBD3 to TNF-α-induced endothelial cell injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Owing to their strong antimicrobial activity, low molecular weight, and immunogenicity, several researchers and studies are focusing on the clinical use of antimicrobial peptides as a new class of antibiotics [41], and some of them are already in the clinical development stage [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, β-defensins had limited success in clinical application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The reasons include the high synthesis cost and short half-lives in blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Cationic peptides are not stable in the serum due to high susceptibility to enzymatic degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>hBD3 was observed to be completely digested in contact with simulated gastric fluid [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>One solution to the limitations is gene delivery of hBD3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Another way is to develop a structurally modified peptide of hBD3 with certain biological activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Notable examples include a C-terminus peptide and a linear hBD3 peptide with anti-inflammatory and antifungal activities [44–46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>This may provide new therapeutic approaches to harness the pharmaceutical potential of hBD3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>However, the endothelial cells we used in this study were obtained from the human umbilical vein, not aortas, which are the main location forming atherosclerotic plaques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The difference in physiology and shear stress between veins and arteries might contribute to heterogeneity between ECs in veins and aortas [47–49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>In addition, some differences in the immune response to proinflammatory cytokines, such as TNF-α, might exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Further confirmation in animal models should be performed to uncover the underlying molecular mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>In addition, cell density was identified to have an impact on the immune response of HUVECs [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In summary, the results of this study demonstrate that TNF-α-induced endothelial cell activation can be reversed by treatment with hBD3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the anti-inflammatory effects of hBD3 in TNF-α-treated HUVECs seem to be closely related to downregulation of NF-κB pathway and MAPK pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (no. 81371152). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors have no conflict of interests to declare.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>1RiceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>B.StollL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>L.LiW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>G.Low-level endotoxin induces potent inflammatory activation of human blood vessels: inhibition by statinsArteriosclerosis, Thrombosis, and Vascular Biology200323915761582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>2RamjiD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>P.DaviesT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>S.Cytokines in atherosclerosis: key players in all stages of disease and promising therapeutic targetsCytokine and Growth Factor Reviews201526667368510.1016/j.cytogfr.2015.04.0032-s2.0-8494910801326005197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>3LandmesserU.HornigB.DrexlerH.Endothelial function: a critical determinant in atherosclerosis?Circulation200410921, supplement 1II27II3310.1161/01.cir.0000115644.35804.8b2-s2.0-264255624415173060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>4PoberJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>S.SessaW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>C.Evolving functions of endothelial cells in inflammationNature Reviews Immunology200771080381510.1038/nri21712-s2.0-34748914299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>5LaiT.ChungC.ChenB.Gold nanoparticles compromise TNF-α-induced endothelial cell adhesion molecule expression through NF-κB and protein degradation pathways and reduce neointima formation in a rat carotid balloon injury modelJournal of Biomedical Nanotechnology201612122185220110.1166/jbn.2016.2315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>6BianT.LiL.LyuJ.CuiD.LeiL.YanF.Human β-defensin 3 suppresses Porphyromonas gingivalis lipopolysaccharide-induced inflammation in RAW 264.7 cells and aortas of ApoE-deficient micePeptides2016829210010.1016/j.peptides.2016.06.0022-s2.0-8497523039927298203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>7HaddyN.SassC.DroeschS.IL-6, TNF-α and atherosclerosis risk indicators in a healthy family population: the STANISLAS cohortAtherosclerosis2003170227728310.1016/s0021-9150(03)00287-92-s2.0-024266139914612208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>8ChenG.GoeddelD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>V.TNF-R1 signaling: a beautiful pathwayScience200229655731634163510.1126/science.10719242-s2.0-003720494812040173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>9Wójciak-StothardB.EntwistleA.GargR.RidleyA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>J.Regulation of TNF-α-induced reorganization of the actin cytoskeleton and cell-cell junctions by Rho, Rac, and Cdc42 in human endothelial cellsJournal of Cellular Physiology1998176115016510.1002/(sici)1097-4652(199807)176:1&lt;150::aid-jcp17&gt;3.0.co;2-b2-s2.0-26426157529618155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>10McKenzieJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>G.RidleyA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>J.Roles of Rho/ROCK and MLCK in TNF-α-induced changes in endothelial morphology and permeabilityJournal of Cellular Physiology2007213122122810.1002/jcp.211142-s2.0-3454847810017476691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>11HaynesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>J.McElveenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>E.DuaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>S.TigheP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>J.LiversidgeJ.Expression of human beta-defensins in intraocular tissuesInvestigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science20004110302630312-s2.0-003383198610967060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>12BergmanP.JohanssonL.WanH.Induction of the antimicrobial peptide CRAMP in the blood-brain barrier and meninges after meningococcal infectionInfection and Immunity200674126982699110.1128/IAI.01043-062-s2.0-3384548730117030578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>13KawsarH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>I.GhoshS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>K.HirschS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>A.KoonH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>B.WeinbergA.JinG.Expression of human β-defensin-2 in intratumoral vascular endothelium and in endothelial cells induced by transforming growth factor βPeptides201031219520110.1016/j.peptides.2009.12.0082-s2.0-7394912215220006664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>14BaroniA.DonnarummaG.PaolettiI.Antimicrobial human beta-defensin-2 stimulates migration, proliferation and tube formation of human umbilical vein endothelial cellsPeptides200930226727210.1016/j.peptides.2008.11.0012-s2.0-5814952686519041917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>15BurgeyC.KernW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>V.RömerW.SakincT.RiegS.The innate defense antimicrobial peptides hBD3 and RNase7 are induced in human umbilical vein endothelial cells by classical inflammatory cytokines but not Th17 cytokinesMicrobes and Infection201517535335910.1016/j.micinf.2015.01.0052-s2.0-8493899773325637949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>16LiL.BianT.LyuJ.CuiD.LeiL.YanF.Human β-defensin-3 alleviates the progression of atherosclerosis accelerated by Porphyromonas gingivalis lipopolysaccharideInternational Immunopharmacology20163820421310.1016/j.intimp.2016.06.0032-s2.0-8497390243027289299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>17LyuJ.BianT.ChenB. β-defensin 3 modulates macrophage activation and orientation during acute inflammatory response to Porphyromonas gingivalis lipopolysaccharideCytokine201792485410.1016/j.cyto.2016.12.01528092794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>18KoflerS.NickelT.WeisM.Role of cytokines in cardiovascular diseases: a focus on endothelial responses to inflammationClinical Science2005108320521310.1042/cs200401742-s2.0-1484430328115540988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>19GerhardtT.LeyK.Monocyte trafficking across the vessel wallCardiovascular Research2015107332133010.1093/cvr/cvv1472-s2.0-8493852745425990461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>20SwirskiF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>K.LibbyP.AikawaE.Ly-6Chi monocytes dominate hypercholesterolemia-associated monocytosis and give rise to macrophages in atheromataJournal of Clinical Investigation2007117119520510.1172/jci299502-s2.0-3384597019217200719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>21ChengQ.McKeownS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>J.SantosL.Macrophage migration inhibitory factor increases leukocyte-endothelial interactions in human endothelial cells via promotion of expression of adhesion moleculesJournal of Immunology201018521238124710.4049/jimmunol.09041042-s2.0-77955483187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>22JubeliE.MoineL.Vergnaud-GauduchonJ.BarrattG.E-selectin as a target for drug delivery and molecular imagingJournal of Controlled Release2012158219420610.1016/j.jconrel.2011.09.0842-s2.0-8485870313021983284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>23MinJ.-K.KimY.-M.KimS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>W.TNF-related activation-induced cytokine enhances leukocyte adhesiveness: induction of ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 via TNF receptor-associated factor and protein kinase C-dependent NF-κB activation in endothelial cellsJournal of Immunology2005175153154010.4049/jimmunol.175.1.5312-s2.0-21244499298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>24CinesD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>B.PollakE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>S.BuckC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>A.Endothelial cells in physiology and in the pathophysiology of vascular disordersBlood19989110352735612-s2.0-00325252079572988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>25MasonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>C.Cytoprotective pathways in the vascular endothelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Do they represent a viable therapeutic target?Vascular Pharmacology201610.1016/j.vph.2016.08.0022-s2.0-84981718421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>26LinS.-G.YuX.-Y.ChenY.-X.De novo expression of macrophage migration inhibitory factor in atherogenesis in rabbitsCirculation Research200087121202120810.1161/01.RES.87.12.12022-s2.0-003462380211110779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>27SchmeisserA.MarquetantR.IllmerT.The expression of macrophage migration inhibitory factor 1α (MIF 1α) in human atherosclerotic plaques is induced by different proatherogenic stimuli and associated with plaque instabilityAtherosclerosis20051781839410.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2004.08.0382-s2.0-1004422609415585204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>28Burger-KentischerA.GoebelH.SeilerR.Expression of macrophage migration inhibitory factor in different stages of human atherosclerosisCirculation2002105131561156610.1161/01.cir.0000012942.49244.822-s2.0-003700713711927523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>29KanetoH.KatakamiN.MatsuhisaM.MatsuokaT.-A.Role of reactive oxygen species in the progression of type 2 diabetes and atherosclerosisMediators of Inflammation201020101145389210.1155/2010/4538922-s2.0-77952480033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>30TaniyamaY.GriendlingK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>K.Reactive oxygen species in the vasculature: molecular and cellular mechanismsHypertension20034261075108110.1161/01.hyp.0000100443.09293.4f2-s2.0-034810942514581295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>31LiC.-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>H.KornerM.FerrisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>K.ChenE.DaiR.-M.LongoD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>L.NF-κB/Rel family members are physically associated phosphoproteinsBiochemical Journal1994303249950610.1042/bj30304992-s2.0-00281510807980409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>32GloireG.Legrand-PoelsS.PietteJ.NF-κB activation by reactive oxygen species: fifteen years laterBiochemical Pharmacology200672111493150510.1016/j.bcp.2006.04.0112-s2.0-3375052363216723122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>33ZhouZ.ConnellM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>C.MacEwanD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>J.TNFR1-induced NF-κB, but not ERK, p38MAPK or JNK activation, mediates TNF-induced ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 expression on endothelial cellsCellular Signalling20071961238124810.1016/j.cellsig.2006.12.0132-s2.0-3414709956017292586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>34BergheW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>V.PlaisanceS.BooneE.p38 and extracellular signal-regulated kinase mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways are required for nuclear factor-κB p65 transactivation mediated by tumor necrosis factorJournal of Biological Chemistry199827363285329010.1074/jbc.273.6.32852-s2.0-00324888379452444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>35NakanoH.NakajimaA.Sakon-KomazawaS.PiaoJ.-H.XueX.OkumuraK.Reactive oxygen species mediate crosstalk between NF-κB and JNKCell Death and Differentiation200613573073710.1038/sj.cdd.44018302-s2.0-3364596561616341124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>36SempleF.MacphersonH.WebbS.Human β-defensin 3 affects the activity of pro-inflammatory pathways associated with MyD88 and TRIFEuropean Journal of Immunology201141113291330010.1002/eji.2011416482-s2.0-8005492079121809339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>37GursoyU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>K.KönönenE.Understanding the roles of gingival beta-defensinsJournal of Oral Microbiology2012411512710.3402/jom.v4i0.151272-s2.0-84864797071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>38SempleF.WebbS.LiH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>N.Human β-defensin 3 has immunosuppressive activity in vitro and in vivoEuropean Journal of Immunology20104041073107810.1002/eji.20094004120104491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>39FunderburgN.LedermanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>M.FengZ.Human β-defensin-3 activates professional antigen-presenting cells via Toll-like receptors 1 and 2Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200710447186311863510.1073/PNAS.07021301042-s2.0-3674904267118006661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>40ShengQ.LvZ.CaiW.Human β-defensin-3 promotes intestinal epithelial cell migration and reduces the development of necrotizing enterocolitis in a neonatal rat modelPediatric Research201476326927910.1038/pr.2014.932-s2.0-8490735128724956228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>41BomanH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>G.Peptide antibiotics and their role in innate immunityAnnual Review of Immunology199513619210.1146/annurev.iy.13.040195.0004252-s2.0-0028933794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>42JarczakJ.KościuczukE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>M.LisowskiP.Defensins: natural component of human innate immunityHuman Immunology20137491069107910.1016/j.humimm.2013.05.0082-s2.0-8488096450823756165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>43ChenX.YangY.ShiZ.GaoM.-Q.ZhangY.Effects of genetically modified milk containing human beta-defensin-3 on gastrointestinal health of micePLoS ONE2016117e015970010.1371/journal.pone.01597002-s2.0-84979554544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>44TheryT.TharappelJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>C.KraszewskaJ.BeckettM.BondU.ArendtE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>K.Antifungal activity of a synthetic human β-defensin 3 and potential applications in cereal-based productsInnovative Food Science &amp; Emerging Technologies20163816016810.1016/j.ifset.2016.09.018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>45LimS.AhnK.KimC.Antifungal effects of synthetic human β-defensin 3-C15 peptideRestorative Dentistry &amp; Endodontics2016412p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>9110.5395/rde.2016.41.2.9127200276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>46LeeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Y.SuhJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>S.KimJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>M.Identification of a cell-penetrating peptide domain from human beta-defensin 3 and characterization of its anti-inflammatory activityInternational Journal of Nanomedicine2015105423543410.2147/IJN.S900142-s2.0-8494005479126347021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>47AirdW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>C.Phenotypic heterogeneity of the endothelium: I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Structure, function, and mechanismsCirculation Research2007100215817310.1161/01.RES.0000255691.76142.4a2-s2.0-3384679810617272818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>48TopperJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>N.GimbroneM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>A.Jr.Blood flow and vascular gene expression: fluid shear stress as a modulator of endothelial phenotypeMolecular Medicine Today199951404610.1016/s1357-4310(98)01372-02-s2.0-003261307110088131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>49ChistiakovD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>A.OrekhovA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>N.BobryshevY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>V.Effects of shear stress on endothelial cells: go with the flowActa Physiologica2016219238240810.1111/apha.127252-s2.0-8497821540627246807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>50HamadaK.OsakaM.YoshidaM.Cell density impacts epigenetic regulation of cytokine-induced E-selectin gene expression in vascular endotheliumPLoS ONE201494e9050210.1371/journal.pone.00905022-s2.0-84898855074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were treated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) and various concentrations of hBD3 for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>The cell viability of HUVECs was determined with a CCK8 assay according to the instructions of manufacturers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as the survival rate compared to the control group, which is defined as 100%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Values represent the means ± SD (n = 6). ###p &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. ∗∗p &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001 compared with TNF-α group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on IL-8, IL-6, MCP-1, and MIF production in TNF-α-stimulated HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) with or without various concentrations of hBD3 for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Then, the culture supernatants were collected by centrifugation and analyzed by ELISA according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as the mean ± SD (n = 6). ###p &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗p &lt; 0.01, and ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001 compared with TNF-α group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>The effects of hBD3 on the expression of adhesion molecules in TNF-α-activated HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>(a) HUVECs were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) with or without the indicated concentrations of hBD3 for 24 h (ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 analysis) or 4 h (E-selectin analysis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Whole cell lysates were extracted and analyzed by western blot using antibodies specific to VCAM-1, ICAM-1, and E-selectin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>(b) Immunofluorescence analysis for ICAM-1 expression was conducted as mentioned above, and images were obtained using a fluorescence microscope (original magnification: 400x, scale bar 50 μm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced adhesion to THP-1 cells in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were stimulated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) and the indicated concentrations of hBD3 for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>After stimulation, HUVECs were cocultured with calcein-AM-labeled THP-1 cells for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>(a) Images were captured using a fluorescence microscope (original magnification: 100x). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>(b) Adherent cells were measured using a microplate reader at excitation and emission wavelengths of 490 nm and 515 nm, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>The results were expressed as the mean ± SD, n = 3. ###p &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. ∗∗p &lt; 0.01 compared with TNF-α group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced NF-κB and MAPK activation in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(a) HUVECs were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) with or without the indicated concentrations of hBD3 for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Whole cell lysates were centrifuged and analyzed with western blot using specific antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>(b) Immunofluorescence analysis for NF-κB p65 localization was conducted as mentioned above, and images were captured using a confocal laser scanning microscope system (Nikon A1, Japan) (original magnification: 400x, scale bar 50 μm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(c) HUVECs were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) with or without the indicated concentrations of hBD3 for 30 min and 45 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Whole cell lysates were centrifuged and analyzed with western blot using specific antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>hBD3 inhibits HUVEC apoptosis stimulated by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>After incubation with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) and different concentrations of hBD3 for 6 h, the protein levels of cleaved caspase-3 and β-actin in HUVECs were detected with an immunoblot assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Inhibitory effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced ROS formation in HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) and hBD3 (15 μg/mL) for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Intracellular ROS accumulation was determined by observation under a fluorescence microscope (a) or fluorescence measurement with a microplate reader (b) after incubation with the ROS detector DCFH-DA for 30 min (original magnification: 400x). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Values represent the mean ± SD. ###p &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group; ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001 compared with TNF-α alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Effects of hBD3 on TNF-α-induced F-actin rearrangement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were incubated with TNF-α (40 ng/mL) with or without hBD3 (15 μg/mL) for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>After that, cells were washed with PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>F-actin was stained with DyLight 488-phalloidin for 15 min in the dark according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Images were obtained using a confocal microscope (Olympus FV10i) (original magnification: 600x, scale bar 50 μm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MI2017-8529542.008"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
