<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Atypon//DTD Atypon Systems Journal Archiving and Interchange NLM DTD v3.0.5 20110520//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName atypon-archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0.6?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName atyponoasis-oasisns2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Qual Stud Health Well-being</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Qual Stud Health Well-being</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="archive">ZQHW</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">zqhw20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Qualitative Studies on Health and Well-being</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1748-2623</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1748-2631</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5510223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28699394</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1347013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17482631.2017.1347013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Empirical Studies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Stepping out of the shadows of Alzheimer’s disease: a phenomenological hermeneutic study of older people with Alzheimer’s disease caring for a therapy dog </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Swall</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"><sup>*</sup></xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8069-9402</contrib-id></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebbeskog</surname><given-names>Britt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lundh Hagelin</surname><given-names>Carina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fagerberg</surname><given-names>Ingegerd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label><sup>a</sup></label>
<institution><named-content content-type="department">Department of Health Sciences, School of Health and Social Studies</named-content>, <named-content content-type="institution-name">Dalarna University</named-content></institution>, <named-content content-type="city">Falun</named-content>, <country>Sweden</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label><sup>b</sup></label>
<institution><named-content content-type="department">Karolinska Institutet, Department of Neurobiology</named-content>, <named-content content-type="institution-name">Care Science and Society</named-content></institution>, <named-content content-type="city">Stockholm</named-content>, <country>Sweden</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label><sup>c</sup></label>
<institution><named-content content-type="institution-name">Sophiahemmet University</named-content>, <named-content content-type="department">Department of Nursing Science</named-content></institution>, <named-content content-type="city">Stockholm</named-content>, <country>Sweden</country></aff><aff id="AFF0004"><label><sup>d</sup></label>
<institution><named-content content-type="department">Department of Health Care Science</named-content>, <named-content content-type="institution-name">Ersta Sköndal Bräcke University College</named-content></institution>, <named-content content-type="city">Stockholm</named-content>, <country>Sweden</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT Anna Swall <email xlink:href="asw@du.se">asw@du.se</email><institution><named-content content-type="department">Department of Health Sciences, School of Health and Social Studies</named-content>, <named-content content-type="institution-name">Dalarna University</named-content></institution>, <named-content content-type="city">Falun</named-content>, <country>Sweden</country>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id seq="25">1347013</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zqhw-12-1347013.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>ABSTRACT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Purpose: Living with Alzheimer’s disease (AD) can involve a person being unable to recall and convey information in daily life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>There are several ways to provide person-centred care to older people with AD, e.g. by empowering them in a situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The use of animal-assisted therapy (AAT) with a therapy dog in the care of people with dementia is increasing, with the presence of a therapy dog being described as improving, among other things, the well-being and socialization of the person. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to illuminate meanings of care for people with AD in their encounters with a therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Method: The study used video-recorded observations of the person with AD and the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Data were transcribed and analysed using a phenomenological hermeneutic method. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results: The main theme was “Using one’s own resources and abilities as a human being”, which meant being the person one can be and distancing oneself from the symptoms of AD during the time with the dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Conclusions: The feelings evoked in the people with AD included empathy and altruism, which allowed for a sense of joy and tenderness, which may induce a sense of self-worth, of being needed, and of being meaningful. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Alzheimer’s disease</kwd><kwd>caring</kwd><kwd>animal-assisted therapy</kwd><kwd>person-centredness</kwd><kwd>phenomenological hermeneutics</kwd><kwd>life world</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Agria Djurförsäkring</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100008015</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Demensförbundet</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100010773</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Högskolan Dalarna</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100005784</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Sophiahemmet University</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Ragnhild and Einar Lundström Foundation</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Sophiahemmet Reserach Foundation</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Queen Silvia Fund for Education and Research</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Kung Gustav V’s and Queen Victoria’s Foundation</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Svenska Kennelklubben</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100008016</named-content></funding-source><award-id>0</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Agria Djurförsäkring, Demensförbundet, Sophiahemmet University, Sophiahemmet Research Foundation, Queen Silvia Fund for Education and Research, Kung Gustav V’s and Queen Victoria’s Foundation, Ragnhild and Einar Lundström Foundation, and Svenska Kennelklubben and Dalarna University.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="41"/><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A person-centred approach for people with Alzheimer’s disease (AD) and other dementias is beneficial when it comes to reaffirming and empowering the person (Edvardsson, Petersson, Sjogren, Lindkvist, &amp; Sandman, 2013; Edvardsson, Winblad, &amp; Sandman, 2008; Kitwood, 1997; McCormack &amp; McCane, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>There are different methods for promoting person-centredness for people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>A few examples are caregivers singing (Hammar, Emami, Götell, &amp; Engström, 2011), validation therapy (Söderlund, Norberg, &amp; Hansebo, 2012), and person-centred conversations (Hedman, Hansebo, Ternestedt, Hellström, &amp; Norberg, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>These methods are often used as memory triggers, so-called reminiscence (Woods, Spector, Jones, Orrell, &amp; Davies, 2005), and temporary presence of mind in the moment (Normann, Asplund, &amp; Norberg, 1998). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Person-centred methods have been shown to strengthen the sense of “self” and identity among those who have dementia (Crichton &amp; Koch, 2007; Hedman et al., 2012; Hedman, Hellström, Ternestedt, Hansebo, &amp; Norberg, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Loss of identity, or self, as a result of AD is a temporary loss of one’s self (Sabat, 2001), something Edvardsson et al. (2008) describe as being a dormant state of the person’s “personhood”, not a lost one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In addition, living with AD and other dementias can mean living one’s daily life in a nursing home in a state of uncertainty, confusion, and emotional instability, and being unable to recall or convey information (Sabat, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Situations involving vulnerability and difficult symptoms are challenging to manage not only for someone with AD but also for the caregivers (Gates, Fitzwater, &amp; Succop, 2003; Pulsford &amp; Duxbury, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Therefore, being involved in meaningful activities is important for the dignity and identity of people with dementia (Tranvåg, Petersen, &amp; Nåden, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Throughout history, humans and animals have been of value to each other (Birke &amp; Holmberg, 2011; Fine, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In recent years, animals have been introduced into the care of people with dementia (Höök, 2010) and, according to Fine (2010), animals can serve as an extended arm for social interaction between humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The presence of an animal can also help to facilitate contact between caregiver and patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Animal-assisted therapy (AAT) with, for example, cats, fish, and dogs, is used in dementia care to counter emotional and psychological difficulties (Fine, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>AAT with a therapy dog has achieved positive results, such as increased social behaviour, improved quality of life (Bernabei et al., 2013; Marx et al., 2010), reduced aggression and anxiety (Kanamori et al., 2001; Mossello et al., 2011; Perkins Bartlett, Travers &amp; Rand, 2008; Richeson, 2003; Sellers, 2005), and increased physical activity among people with dementia (Nordgren &amp; Engström, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>AAT evokes memories, and there is a sense of physical closeness during the time the person spends stroking the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, interaction with a therapy dog can also evoke sadness that may be difficult for people to handle (Swall et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The involvement of a therapy dog in the care of people with dementia needs to be dealt with individually, and further studies are required (National Board of Health and Welfare, 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>To increase understanding of how the encounter with the therapy dog influenced the self of the person with AD, his or her verbal and non-verbal expressions of care for the dog were studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This adheres to the definition of care given by Martinsen (1994), who defines the concept of caring as follows: “To care for” someone relates to “helping” and “taking care of” and to reducing the amount of “egoism” in each person, and is also related to the giving of oneself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study, therefore, was to illuminate meanings of care for people with AD in their encounters with a therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="S0002"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The lived experience of being in the world has its ontological and epistemological roots in the philosophies of Husserl (2004) and Ricouer (1976). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>What we experience in our daily lives is important for how we experience our life world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The present study aims to allow for a deeper understanding of the participants’ life world and the phenomenon studied, that being the lived experience of people with AD providing care for a dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The life world of people with dementia may sometimes create for them a sense of vulnerability and fear, a result of the symptoms of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In order to better understand the lived experience of old people who have AD, while highlighting the meanings of their lived experience when caring for a therapy dog, the phenomenological hermeneutic research method was used (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Therapy dog team </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The therapy dog team comprises the handler and the handler’s own trained dog, which lives with the handler. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To qualify as a therapy dog team in Sweden, the handler needs to have healthcare training—for example, as a registered nurse, nursing assistant, or occupational therapist—and the handler and dog must have completed an 18 month course at the Swedish therapy dog school. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The dogs are trained to interact effectively in different situations with people with AD and other dementias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The dogs are thoroughly tested to ensure that they can handle different situations and perform well in interaction with older people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>People with AD are prescribed visits from the therapy dog team (the dog and its handler) at the nursing home to cater for their different needs; for example, to decrease anxiety or improve their sense of well-being. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The sessions for each person took place once a week for a total of 10 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The dog handler controlled the dog, talked to the person about the dog, and allowed the person to interact, while observing the situation the whole time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Sometimes the handler withdrew for a moment to give the person and the dog time alone, but was available to control the situation if needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The therapy dog team visited those who had experiences with dogs earlier in their lives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The referrals were made by a registered nurse on the ward and individualized for each person with specific aims. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Each session with the therapy dog was a one-on-one visit between the person with AD and the therapy dog team, and differed according to the circumstances of each person and the aim of the visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The interaction between the person and the therapy dog occurred in a specially adapted room that was equipped with toys, blankets, pictures of dogs, chairs, and tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>There was also a couch where the person could sit down with the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Activities included close contact with the dog, talking, cuddling, and playing—such as throwing balls or searching for hidden sweets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted at a municipal nursing home in a metropolitan area in Sweden that comprised four inpatient wards for older people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Four women and one man between the ages of 89 and 95 years with medium to severe AD were included in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Inclusion criteria for those in the study at the specific nursing home were that they had been diagnosed with AD and that they had never received visits from a therapy dog team before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Those who did not like dogs or who did not have any previous relations to dogs were excluded in accordance with the decision of the dog handlers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The participants had all been prescribed a therapy dog team visit and met the inclusion criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Data consisted of video observations (VIOs) aimed at capturing the behaviour of the people with AD within the context of their interaction with the therapy dog (Barker, Pistrang, &amp; Elliott, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Each visit was recorded (10 visits per person) (in total 50 sessions), and 25 h of video-recorded data were gathered by the first author. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The observations focused on the interaction between the person with AD and the therapy dog, with the first author sitting in the room behind the camera filming the interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>At the end of the visit, the first author asked the participants what they thought of the visit, and the question and the spoken answer, or perhaps no answer at all, were recorded on film. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This enabled the person with AD to express in words his or her experience of interacting with the therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the people with AD communicated about their life world when caring for a therapy dog through verbal and non-verbal communication (bodily movement, speech, and eye contact). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The VIOs from the sessions were viewed and transcribed into text without interpretation (Swall et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The transcribed texts were then separated from the VIOs and, according to Ricoeur (1976), the text then “stands on its own”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>When an interpretation of the text is initiated using phenomenological hermeneutics, there is a circular movement between explanation and understanding, and between the parts and the whole of the text (the hermeneutic circle) (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The alternation between distance from the text and closeness to the text allows the researcher to capture what the text is about (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004; Ricouer, 1976). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A naïve reading is the first step in the analysis phase, followed by a structural analysis and a comprehensive understanding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The naïve reading involved the first author (AS) reading through the text several times to become moved by it and to gain an initial understanding of the whole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The first naïve understanding was then written down to form a coherent text (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The structural analysis was the second step in the analysis process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The transcribed VIO was divided into units of meaning (Table I), followed by a read-through and a reflection against the background of the naïve understanding, all with the aim of the study in mind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The meaning units were then condensed and abstracted into sub-themes, themes and, finally, a main theme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The naïve understanding was validated against the structural analysis and also rewritten once. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The text that developed through the analytical process was translated into English upon completion of the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The sub-themes, themes, and main theme, together with the naïve understanding and the authors’ pre-understanding, were reflected on using suitable literature to form a comprehensive understanding (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>All authors were involved in the analysis process, and the manuscript has been reviewed by other research teams during research seminars.Table I.Meaning units and condensation.Meaning unitsCondensationOh how nice you are, ohh you are so beautiful yes … smiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>And I have no sweets to give you … Oh no.The dog is beautiful, but I have no sweets to give him.The person puts his left hand on the dog and caresses him. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="!"><plain>Says: yeah, you’re so nice! </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The dog goes away, the person following him with his eyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The dog leaves a ball for the dog handler; the dog handler gives the ball to the person. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Says: ha ha ha ha (laughs) looks at the dog, extending his left hand to it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Dog handler: you should sit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Dog handler talks to the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The person says: ohh yes, how nice you are. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Rocking its head sideways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The person says: I cannot sit like that.Leaning towards the dog, caressing, laughing and looking at the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The dog is well behaved when sitting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Smiling and rocking its head.The person smiles and feels the dog’s paw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Says: yeah ha ha ha (laughs), smiles, trying to say something, it becomes unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The person says: I cannot talk … Stops smiling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Dog handler says: yes you can. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The person caresses the dog; the dog lifts its head against the person’s hand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="?"><plain>The person says: Don’t you like it? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Raising her eyebrows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Dog handler: I think he did. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The person continues caressing, smiling a little, caressing, watching the dog.Touches the dog, smiles, says something indistinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Caresses the dog, wondering if the dog does not like it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Continues caressing, smiling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2004"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Ethical considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A therapy dog team was established at the nursing home, and the first author was able to join this team while they visited people with AD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Approval for the study was given by the Regional Board of Research Ethics (2010/220-31/1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The participants were all frail owing to moderate to severe AD, and their next of kin were contacted and informed both orally and in writing about the project, and they then signed a proxy consent (Karlawish et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The information given was that those with AD would be able to receive therapy dog visits without being part of the research project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The first author collected the data (films) of the participants interacting with the therapy dog and looked for signs that might indicate any discomfort on their part; however, there were no such signs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The VIOs were coded and stored in a safe cabinet to which only the authors had access. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="S0003"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The findings will be presented with the naïve understanding first, followed by the main theme and each theme with its sub-themes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>According to the method of phenomenological hermeneutics, the results are written from the position and lived experience of the person with AD encountering a therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="S0003-S2001"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Naïve understanding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The presence of the dog brings joy and closeness for that moment, and also results in a sense of appreciation and moment of happiness in daily life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The dog takes on a value that becomes apparent when one is sharing closeness and warmth, and when talking tenderly to the dog, using skills and knowledge, and taking responsibility for the dog by making the right decisions as to how the dog should be taken care of. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Affection through the creation of a safe, warm environment for the dog is achieved through conversation with and about the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Caring is about being able to express one’s wish to be important to and needed by the therapy dog, which means that one has done one’s best while being aware of one’s limitations when it comes to caring for the dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Caring for the dog is making responsible decisions about what is best for the dog; for example, providing care by being close to the dog, giving it one’s attention, wanting to be useful to the dog, and saying that one always wants to be at the dog’s side as a friend. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Structural analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The structural analysis resulted in one main theme, two themes, and four sub-themes (Table II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In the results, the participants have been given fictitious names.Table II.Sub-themes, themes and main theme that emerged from the text.Sub-themeThemeMain themeBeing affectionate towards the dogBeing concerned for the dogBecoming significant for the dog in the momentDistancing oneself from the dog in the momentLetting one’s feelings lead the way with the dog’s best interests in mindBeing close and at a distanceUsing one’s own resources and abilities as a human being </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="S0003-S2002-S3001"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Main theme: Using one’s own resources and abilities as a human being </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Using hidden resources and abilities, one may become the person one once was before cognitive decline, and also distance oneself from the symptoms of the disease during the time spent with the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Becoming an autonomous person who shows authority and decides what is best for the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Showing one’s inner self, the person one may have been before the symptoms of cognitive decline concealed one’s previous abilities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002-S3002"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Theme I: Letting one’s feelings lead the way with the dog’s best interests in mind </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Caring meant ensuring security and safety for the dog in different situations by giving love and tenderness; using skills based on memories from life and making sure the dog is safe in the situation at that moment, based on one’s own experiences and beliefs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Being affectionate towards the dog means providing care by understanding, respecting, and adapting oneself to the dog and the situation, as well as treating it as a precious living creature. Mrs Anderson: [Sits up and looks at the dog.] Well, you are so cute … Well you are so beautiful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>[She bends down towards the dog: You are so beautiful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>You are so beautiful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>[Takes a sweet from a plastic bag and gives one to the dog.] You are so beautiful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="?"><plain>[The dog eats the sweet.] Was it good? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="?"><plain>[Bends down towards the dog and looks at him.] Did you like the sweet? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>[Still looking at the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The dog comes forward and puts it head in Mrs Anderson’s lap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>She leans against the dog]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Well you are so beautiful …. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>When the dog is close, one acknowledges its presence by showing admiration for it and using calm words like “Yes, you are so good”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In the interaction, one provides care for the dog by appreciating it for being clever and smart when it obeys commands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The dog’s closeness makes one realize that the dog appreciates affection when being stroked since it stays close and falls asleep in one’s presence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Becoming affectionate towards the dog by putting the dog’s needs before one’s own at that moment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>When one is providing care for the dog, the symptoms of one’s disease are less obvious at that moment, and one recalls life memories as a result of protecting the dog and treating it as a fragile creature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Often temporary presence of mind occurs when one is caring for the dog, which also reveals an understanding that one cannot take care of the dog in one’s present condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Instead, there is an understanding about how the dog should be taken care of, as well as how important the dog is. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>One provides care by being responsible and by protecting and expressing worry for the dog about things in the close vicinity that can harm it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>At the same time, one is acknowledging the importance of the dog—that it is a vulnerable and beloved friend that one would like to have visit again. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="?"><plain>Being concerned for the dog by protecting it, such as putting one’s arms around the dog as a shield when realizing that certain situations may be threatening to the dog; providing care by observing and commenting on any health problems in order to be considerate; showing concern for the dog by understanding that it is not behaving as before—realizing perhaps that something is wrong with the dog. Mr Edgar: Are you limping, my friend? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>[He looks at the dog.] Dog handler (DH): Yeah, he has a bit of pain in his front end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Mr Edgar: OK …. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>[He follows the dog with his eyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="?"><plain>His voice becomes somewhat quieter and darker, and his expression becomes serious.] DH: Do you think it will pass? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Mr Edgar: Yes, I hope so … DH: yes … I think so. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Mr Edgar: Yeah, let’s hope so. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>DH: He gets medicine for his limping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Mr Edgar: Ooh well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>DH: So, so the vet thinks so. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Mr Edgar: Yes, yes it appears that he has problems when he walks … Oh, oh, oh poor little chap, yes, yes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Caring for the dog by exhibiting cautious behaviour and by trying to solve any problems with the dog’s best interests in mind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The focus moves from joy and closeness to a serious moment when the dog is not feeling well, and one seeks support and confirmation from the handler to understand how to help with the problem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002-S3003"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Theme II: Being close and at a distance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Caring for the dog meant creating a special relationship with the dog, such as being quiet and close together, understanding each other; at the same time, moving away when the dog comes too close. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="!"><plain>Becoming significant for the dog for the moment meant caring for the dog by reacting to and approving of the dog’s behaviour in words to the dog and in play while having the dog’s attention; understanding that one is important for the dog’s well-being in that shared moment with the dog. Mrs Carlson: Hey you, hey you, little doggy! </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="!"><plain>Hey you, little doggy! </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="?"><plain>[Smiling, she Yes, are you coming to me, are you coming to me …? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Well, well I do not have any sweets you see … [Laughing, looks at the dog and looks at the dog handler.] … ha… ha [laughs]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>[Strokes the dog, smiling.] He wants more pats …. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Becoming significant for the dog meant silently being able to acknowledge the dog by being close to and watching the dog, and attending to the dog’s needs and adapting to the dog; being useful by providing a sense of security to the dog, and at the same time doing something enjoyable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Quietly caring for the dog meant managing to play a game repeatedly as a sign of understanding of the dog and the situation without any verbal commands or control from the handler. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Distancing oneself from the dog at that moment to protect one’s integrity by showing authority and setting limits for both the dog and oneself. Mrs Daniels: Yeah, ha [laughs], you are so beautiful, yesss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>[She caresses and talks to the dog.] I do not … not there, there. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>[She bends her head back when the dog tries to lick her face.] Soo, yes so beautiful, yes, I do not want you in my face. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Noooo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>[The dog turns around.] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Being emotional, and stating to the dog that one wishes to be left alone, and instead observing it quietly from a distance, without any further explanation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="S0004"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S0004-S2001"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Comprehensive understanding and reflections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The people with AD in this study acted affectionately and confidently while demonstrating their ability to lead, decide, and act in ways that they thought benefited the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In Parse’s (1992) theory “Human Becoming”, to be human is the equal right of everyone regardless of background, and the person freely chooses meaning and value in a situation by involving himself or herself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>To experience good health, there needs to be an equilibrium between mental, social, and spiritual well-being; this in turn creates equilibrium of body, mind, and spirit (Parse, 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The participants caring for the therapy dog demonstrated moments that were full of life and confidence based on their resources and abilities to make decisions about the dog in a given situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This required a sense of equilibrium of body, mind, and spirit in the situation when the dog was in the room. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For a person to regain their health when living with a disease, they need to find personal meaning in a situation and to piece together what is real and what brings meaning to them (Parse, 1992, 1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>For the participants in this study, the dog may have helped them to find personal meaning through its bodily proximity which, in turn, may have helped to connect them with their inner life world with memories of caring for their dogs in days gone by. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Provided care is shown through love and responsibility and by being both close and at a distance, the individual appears to be able to act like a healthy human being at that moment with the dog, with the symptoms of the disease, perhaps, being put aside for the moment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The findings show the participants in the present study to be calm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>They expressed sounds of contentment and almost fell asleep when caressing and being close to the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Skovdahl, Sörlie, and Kihlgren (2007) found that when people with dementia in a nursing home received tactile stimulation to their hands and arms from caregivers, they relaxed and fell asleep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This, in turn, reduced symptoms such as aggression and increased their sense of well-being, and they became easier to interact with (Skovdahl et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The dog’s coat may have functioned as tactile stimulation for those in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The act of providing physical care and interacting with the therapy dog may be closely related to receiving tactile stimulation from a caregiver, as described by Skovdahl et al. (2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Levels of oxytocin increase when people have physical contact with a dog for 5–24 min which, in turn, reduces stress and pain and results in lower blood pressure (Beetz, Uvnäs-Moberg, Julius, &amp; Kotrschal, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the level of oxytocin increases in the person with AD during the time spent caressing the dog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These calm moments with the dog may also reveal memories from the person’s past (Swall et al., 2014): memories of dogs and memories of their interactions with dogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>These memories may also, albeit temporarily, result in the person with AD behaving like a confident, healthy person. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The person may manage to be one “person” on the ward when living with the impending conditions of the symptoms of dementia, which may, in turn, create space to be one “kind of person”, where the “true” self may not be the same as before the onset of cognitive decline. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>People with moderate AD have been shown to strengthen their sense of self, their “I”, in relation to the world and to others when interacting with each other in controlled group conversations (Hedman et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In this study, the people appeared to become empowered, more secure, and more confident, and to lead the way and make decisions about what was best for the dog, while still understanding that their own limitations might affect the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The findings show that caring for the dog makes old people who are experiencing cognitive decline more outgoing, social, and interested in and focused on the dog and its needs, while they also become more prepared to express their sense of self (Hedman et al., 2012, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>It appears that the person emerges from the shell created by dementia and may show a fragment of his or her “person” as a result of being empowered in the dog’s presence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Together with the dog, they possibly show their innermost self. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>They liven up and demonstrate the abilities and resources of a whole human being, and know that they are capable of taking care of the dog using their current faculties. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Revealing a sense of self through communion with others in friendship, dialogue, caring, and togetherness has been shown to be important (Hedman, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>People’s inner life and sense of self may come to the fore when they are caring for a friend, the dog, and they may act as if their cognitive decline is not limiting their resources or abilities, thus creating a sense of well-being and optimal health as well as equilibrium of body, mind, and spirit (Parse, 1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Episodes of lucidity are moments of temporary presence of mind in people with AD and other dementias (Normann et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>These moments often occur when the person is cared for in a person-centred way (Edvardsson et al., 2014, 2008; McCormack &amp; McCane, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The dog’s presence seemed to create episodes of lucidity which, in turn, evoked memories and feelings in the individuals, enabling them to show how much the dog meant to them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S0004-S2002"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Methodological considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to increase understanding in terms of the meaning of care for people with AD in their encounter with a therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>AD causes symptoms such as amnesia and aphasia, and therefore it was important to videotape sessions so that the researcher could capture both verbal and non-verbal expressions while the participants interacted with the therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Because of speech difficulties for most of those participating and because the wish was to produce films with rich verbal and non-verbal data, VIOs seemed to be the best option. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Older people with AD can find it intimidating to be filmed; therefore, the first author showed herself in front of the camera to demonstrate that there was nothing to be frightened of in terms of the camera or the author herself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It is possible that directing the focus from the dog to the first author may have influenced the data; however, most of the time the person looked only at the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Any discomfort on the part of the participant was duly observed; however, no such discomfort was noted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Using phenomenological hermeneutics (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004) involves an ongoing movement between the parts and the whole in the text, and between explanation and understanding (Ricoeur, 1976). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The analysis that was required to reach the meaning of the lived experience was not a linear process; instead, it moved back and forth to validate the naïve reading with the structural analysis, and with the aim of the study in mind, a deeper understanding of the phenomenon was attained, as was the way in which it showed itself in front of the text (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>It was important in the VIOs to capture every moment that the participants and the dog were together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Five people with AD participated in the study, and 50 films totalling about 25 h of recorded time were transcribed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The richness and variation of the data can be deemed satisfactory: quality is more important than quantity when it comes to examinations of the life world (Dahlberg, Dahlberg, &amp; Nyström, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The authors’ pre-understanding needed to be checked during the structural analysis to maintain truthfulness to the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>This was achieved by all authors through ongoing commentary on the text and by other research teams contributing during seminars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Through the comprehensive understanding, the results illuminated deeper meanings of the lived experience of older people with AD caring for a therapy dog, which demonstrated the impact the dog may have had on the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The results may also have presented a platform for the further use of trained therapy dogs in the care of older people with AD and other dementias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Meanings of the lived experience for older people with AD in their encounter with a therapy dog have been disclosed (Ricouer, 1998), but the text never has just one meaning or one “truth”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The present study shows one interpretation of the text, but other interpretations are possible (Lindseth &amp; Norberg, 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="S0005"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The present study contributes to knowledge about older people with AD caring for a therapy dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>AAT with a therapy dog is said to affect people with dementia by minimizing agitation and anxiety-induced behaviours such as apathy and aggression, while improving their quality of life and their social interaction with others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>In this study, other behaviours such as empathy and affection that were demonstrated through expressions of feelings of joy and tenderness were noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>These moments possibly gave them momentary empowerment despite the symptoms of the disease, and may have given rise to a sense of being important, needed, and meaningful to the dog in its presence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The study may be seen as a contribution specifically to research into caring for older people with AD who interact with a therapy dog, and more generally into person-centred care for people with dementia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Animals have been living close to humans for many years, for example, both as farm animals and as companions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Therapy dog visits could be used in different parts of the world and in different cultures under controlled conditions that adopt a person-centred approach. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="S0006"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S0007"><title>Implication for practice</title><p>The study contributes to knowledge about AAT with a therapy dog and its different possible applications in the care of people with dementia. Furthermore, AAT with a therapy dog may contribute to a person’s sense of well-being and calm, and may also give meaning to the day for those with dementia. However, there needs to be further research in this area to fully understand the benefits of using AAT with a therapy dog in the care of people with dementia. All authors have contributed differently in the article. However, the first author (AS) collected the data and was leading the analysis process along with the last author (IF). However, all authors have been involved in all parts of the article.</p></sec><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>SwallA., EbbeskogB., Lundh HagelinC. &amp; FagerbergI. (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Can therapy dogs evoke awareness of one’s past and present life in persons with Alzheimer’s disease? Journal of Older people Nursing. doi:10.1111/opn.12053). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>BarkerC., PistrangN., &amp; ElliottR. (2005). Research methods in clinical psychology: An introduction for students and practitioners (2nd ed.). West Sussex: John Wiley &amp; Sons. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>BeetzA., Uvnäs-MobergK., JuliusH., &amp; KotrschalK. (2012). Psychosocial and psychophysiological effects of human-animal interactions: The possible role of oxytocin. Frontiers in Psychology. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2012.00234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>BernabeiV., De RonchiD., La FerlaT., MorettiF., TonelliL., FerrariB.,. . . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Atti, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>(2013). Animal-assisted interventions for elderly patients affected by dementia or psychiatric disorders: A review. Journal of Psychiatric Research, 1, 1–8. doi:10.1016/j.jpsychires.2012.12.014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>BirkeL., &amp; HolmbergT. (2011). Investigating Human/Animal relations in science, culture and work (2nd ed.). Uppsala: University print. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>CrichtonJ., &amp; KochT. (2007). Living with dementia: Curating self-identity. Dementia., 6, 365–381. doi:10.1177/1471301207081570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>DahlbergK., DahlbergH., &amp; NyströmM. (2008). Reflective lifeworld research (2nd ed.). Lund: Studentlitteratur. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>EdvardssonD., PeterssonL., SjogrenK., LindkvistM., &amp; SandmanP.-O. (2013). Everyday activities for people with dementia in residential aged care: Associations with person-centredness and quality of life. International Journal of Older People Nursing., 9, 269–276. doi:10.1111/opn.1203023590628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>EdvardssonD., WinbladB., &amp; SandmanP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>O. (2008). Person-centred care of people with severe Alzheimer’s disease: Current status and ways forward. The Lancet Neurology., 7(4), 362–367. doi:10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70063-218339351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>FineH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>A. (2010). Animal-assisted therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Theoretical foundations and guidelines for practice (3rd ed.). San Diego, CA: Academic Press, Elsevier. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>GatesD., FitzwaterE., &amp; SuccopP. (2003). Relationships of stressors, strain, and anger to caregiver assaults. Issues in Mental Health Nursing, 24, 775–793.13129753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>HammarL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>M., EmamiA., GötellE., &amp; Engstr?MG. (2011). The impact of caregivers? singing on expressions of emotion and resistance during morning care situations in persons with dementia: An intervention in dementia care. Journal of Clinical Nursing., 20, 969–978. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2702.2010.03386.x21309873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>HedmanR. (2014). Striving to be able and included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Expressions of sense of self in people with Alzheimer’s disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(Thesis). Stockholm: Karolinska Institutet. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>HedmanR., HanseboG., TernestedtB.-M., HellströmI., &amp; NorbergA. (2012). How people with Alzheimer’s disease express their sense of self: Analysis using Rom Harre’s theory of selfhood. Dementia: the International Journal of Social Research and Practice. doi:10.1177/1471301212444053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>HedmanR., HellströmI., TernestedtB.-M., HanseboG., &amp; NorbergA. (2014). Social positioning by people with Alzheimer’s disease in a support group. Journal of Aging Studies., 28, 11–21. doi:10.1016/j.jaging.2013.11.00324384363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>HöökI. (2010). Hund på recept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Den professionella vårdhunden [Dogs on prescription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The professional therapy dog]. Stockholm: Gothia Förlag. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>HusserlE. (2004). Ideas to a pure phenomenology and phenomenological philosophy. Riga: Thales. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>KanamoriM., SuzukiM., YamamotoK., KandaM., MatsuiY., KojimaE., … OshiroH. (2001). A day care program and evaluation of animal-assisted therapy (AAT) for the elderly with senile dementia. American Journal of Alzheimer’s Disease and Other Dementias, 16(4), 234–239. doi:10.1177/153331750101600409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>KarlawishJ., KimS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Y., KnopmanD., van DyckC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>H., JamesB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>D., &amp; MarsonD. (2008). The views of Alzheimer disease patients and their study partners on proxy consent for clinical trial enrollment. The American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry, 16, 240–247. doi:10.1097/JGP.0b013e318162992d18310554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>KitwoodT. (1997). The experience of dementia. Journal of Aging &amp; Mental Health, 1(1), 13–22. doi:10.1080/13607869757344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>LindsethA., &amp; NorbergA. (2004). A phenomenological hermeneutical method for researching lived experience. Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences, 18, 145–153. doi:10.1111/scs.2004.18.issue-215147477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>MartinsenK. (1994). Omsorg Sykepleie og Medisin- historisk filosofiske Essays [Caring Nursing and Medicine – historical philosophical Essays]. Otta: Engers Boktrykkeri. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>MarxM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>S., Cohen-MansfieldJ., RegierN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>G., Dakheel-AliM., SrihariA., &amp; TheinK. (2010). The impact of different dog-related stimuli on engagement of persons with dementia. American Journal of Alzheimer’s Disease &amp; Other Dementias? 25, 37–45. doi:10.1177/1533317508326976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>McCormackB., &amp; McCaneT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>V. (2010). Person-centred nursing theory and practice. West Sussex, UK: Wiley-Blackwell. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>MosselloE., RidolfiA., MelloA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>M., LorenziniG., MugnaiF., PicciniC., … MarchionniN. (2011). Animal-assisted activity and emotional status of patients with Alzheimer’s disease in day care. International Psychogeriatrics, 23(6), 899–905. doi:10.1017/S104161021100022621356158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>National Board of Health and Welfare (2014). Therapy dog for older persons in a nursing home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>A systematic review on effects and scientific support. Sweden: National Board on Health and Welfare ISBN 978-91-7555-147-0. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>NordgrenL., &amp; EngströmG. (2012). Effects of Animal-Assisted Therapy on Behavioral and/or Psychological Symptoms in Dementia. American Journal of Alzheimer’s Disease &amp; Other Dementias? 27, 625–632. doi:10.1177/1533317512464117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>NormannH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>K., AsplundK., &amp; NorbergA. (1998). Episodes of lucidity in people with severe dementia as narrated by formal carers. Journal of Advanced Nursing., 28, 1295–1300.9888375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>ParseR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>R. (1992). Human becoming: Parse’s theory of nursing. Nursing Science Quarterly., 5(1), 35–42. doi:10.1177/0894318492005001091538853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>ParseR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>R. (1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The Human becoming theory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>In ParseR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>R. (Eds.), Illuminations the human becoming theory in practice and research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>(1st ed.). New York: National League for Nursing. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>PerkinsJ., BartlettH., TraversC., &amp; RandJ. (2008). Dog-assisted therapy for older people with dementia: A review. Australasian Journal on Ageing, 27, 177–182. doi:10.1111/aja.2008.27.issue-419032618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>PulsfordD., &amp; DuxburyJ. (2006). Aggressive behaviour by people with dementia in residential care settings: A review. Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing., 13, 611–618. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2850.2006.00964.x16965482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>RichesonN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>E. (2003). Effects of animal-assisted therapy on agitated behaviors and social interactions of older adults with dementia. American Journal of Alzheimer’s Disease and Other Dementias, 18, 353–358. doi:10.1177/153331750301800610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>RicoeurP. (1976). Interpretation theory: Discourse and the surplus of meaning. TX, USA: Texas Christian University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>RicoeurP. (1998). Hermeneutics and the human sciences: Essays on language, action and interpretation. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>SabatS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>R. (2001). The experience of Alzheimer’s disease, life through a tangled veil. MA, USA: Blackwell Publisher Inc. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>SellersD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>M. (2005). The evaluation of an animal assisted therapy intervention for elders with dementia in long-term care. Activities, Adaptions and Aging., 30, 61–76. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>SkovdahlK., SörlieV., &amp; KihlgrenM. (2007). Tactile stimulation associated with nursing care to individuals with dementia showing aggressive or restless tendencies: An intervention study in dementia care. International Journal of Older People Nursing., 2(3), 162–170. doi:10.1111/j.1748-3743.2007.00056.x20925872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>SöderlundM., NorbergA., &amp; HanseboG. (2012). Implementation of the validation method: Nurses’ descriptions of caring relationships with residents with dementia disease. Dementia: The International Journal of Social Research and Practice, 11, 569–587. doi:10.1177/1471301211421225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>TranvågO., PetersenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>A., &amp; NådenD. (2013). Relational interactions preserving dignity expereince: Perceptions of persons living with dementia. Nursing Ethics. doi:10.1177/0969733014549882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>WoodsB., SpectorA., JonesC., OrrellM., &amp; DaviesS. (2005). Reminiscence therapy for dementia (review). Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews, 2005(2). doi:10.1002/14651858.CD001120.pub2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
