<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Evol. Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5225553</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-016-0871-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of ionotropic L-glutamate receptor genes in the Bilateria, with special notes on Aplysia californica </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>Justin B.</given-names></name><address><phone>+1-305-421-4728</phone><email>jgreer@rsmas.miami.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khuri</surname><given-names>Sawsan</given-names></name><address><email>s.khuri@miami.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fieber</surname><given-names>Lynne A.</given-names></name><address><email>lfieber@rsmas.miami.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Marine Biology and Ecology, Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science, University of Miami, 4600 Rickenbacker Cswy, Miami, FL 33149 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Center for Computational Science, University of Miami, 1320 S. Dixie Highway, Coral Gables, FL 33146 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Computer Science, University of Miami, P.O. Box 248154, Coral Gables, FL 33124 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>11</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The neurotransmitter L-Glutamate (L-Glu) acting at ionotropic L-Glu receptors (iGluR) conveys fast excitatory signal transmission in the nervous systems of all animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>iGluR-dependent neurotransmission is a key component of the synaptic plasticity that underlies learning and memory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>During learning, two subtypes of iGluR, α-Amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptors (AMPAR) and N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors (NMDAR), are dynamically regulated postsynaptically in vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Invertebrate organisms such as Aplysia californica (Aplysia) are well-studied models for iGluR-mediated function, yet no studies to date have analyzed the evolutionary relationships between iGluR genes in these species and those in vertebrates, to identify genes that may mediate plasticity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We conducted a thorough phylogenetic analysis spanning Bilateria to elucidate these relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The expression status of iGluR genes in the Aplysia nervous system was also examined. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Our analysis shows that ancestral genes for both NMDAR and AMPAR subtypes were present in the common bilaterian ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>NMDAR genes show very high conservation in motifs responsible for forming the conductance pore of the ion channel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The number of NMDAR subunits is greater in vertebrates due to an increased number of splice variants and an increased number of genes, likely due to gene duplication events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>AMPAR subunits form an orthologous group, and there is high variability in the number of AMPAR genes in each species due to extensive taxon specific gene gain and loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>qPCR results show that all 12 Aplysia iGluR subunits are expressed in all nervous system ganglia. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Orthologous NMDAR subunits in all species studied suggests conserved function across Bilateria, and potentially a conserved mechanism of neuroplasticity and learning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Vertebrates display an increased number of NMDAR genes and splice variants, which may play a role in their greater diversity of physiological responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Extensive gene gain and loss of AMPAR genes may result in different physiological properties that are taxon specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest a significant role for L-Glu mediated responses throughout the Aplysia nervous system, consistent with L-Glu’s role as the primary excitatory neurotransmitter. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12862-016-0871-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Kainate</kwd><kwd>Real-time PCR</kwd><kwd>L-glutamate</kwd><kwd>Nervous system</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>P40 OD010952</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Fieber</surname><given-names>Lynne A.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>L-Glu is the most abundant neurotransmitter in the vertebrate brain [1], and exerts most of its effects by binding to different postsynaptic ligand-gated receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>L-Glu receptors are classified into two types, ionotropic and metabotropic receptors [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Metabotropic L-Glu receptors (mGluR) are G-protein-coupled receptors in which binding of L-Glu activates intracellular cascades and modification of intracellular proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Ionotropic L-Glu receptors (iGluR) convey the majority of fast excitatory signal transmission and have been implicated in most aspects of central nervous system (CNS) development and function [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The binding of L-Glu to iGluR opens transmembrane ion channels that allow ions to cross the plasma membrane leading to depolarization of the postsynaptic cell and triggering of action potentials, thereby transmitting synaptic information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>iGluR play important roles in synaptic plasticity, which is the ability of a synapse to strengthen or weaken its interactions with others over time in response to changes in activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This feature of iGluR is believed to be a key mechanism underlying learning and memory [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Several features of iGluR in vertebrates have been revealed using model systems such as rats and mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Vertebrate iGluR are divided into three subtypes according to selective agonists: N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors (NMDAR), kainate, and α-Amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptors (AMPAR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Each subtype of iGluR is composed of four subunits that form a dimer of dimers to create the functional protein [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In a phylogenetic analysis of human, rat, and mouse iGluR subunits, each of the three different subtypes formed a monophyletic clade, with functional iGluR proteins made only with subunits within each individual clade [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Overall amino acid identity of iGluR subunits across the three subtypes in mammals is only 20–30%, but all subtypes contain common structural features that place them together into a single large superfamily [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A fourth iGluR subtype, called delta receptors, show low sequence similarity with other iGluR and do not open ion channels, but are believed to bind D-serine and glycine [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Invertebrate model species such as Aplysia californica (Aplysia), Drosophila melanogaster (Drosophila), and Caenorhabditis elegans (C. elegans) have been used extensively in studies of iGluR mediated transmission in the nervous system since the 1960’s due to several distinct advantages over vertebrate models [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Their nervous systems contain 302–135,000 neurons, compared to 1 × 1011 in the human brain [10–12], and simple neuronal circuits underlying various behaviors have been described [13–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>There is ample evidence suggesting that L-Glu is the major neurotransmitter in many neural circuits in these species [17–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>These advantages have resulted in widespread use of Aplysia, Drosophila, C. elegans, and other models to study iGluR mediated synaptic plasticity, because learned behaviors can be correlated with both molecular and physiological synaptic changes between sensory- and motoneurons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Physiologically, invertebrate model organisms have greatly enhanced our understanding of L-Glu mediated synaptic plasticity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Many plasticity related changes characterized in invertebrate models subsequently have been demonstrated to occur in the more complex vertebrate hippocampus [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>For example, AMPAR and NMDAR have been implicated in learning and memory in vertebrates, Aplysia, and D. malanogaster [22–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Despite the physiological use of invertebrate model species for iGluR-mediated responses, an outstanding question remains as to which iGluR genes are likely to play the functional role of vertebrate NMDAR and AMPAR during plasticity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>To address this question we have conducted a phylogenetic analysis spanning all three Bilateria superclades in order to identify iGluR genes in invertebrate model species that are orthologous with vertebrate iGluR, and thus more likely to be functionally similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Bilateria are organized into three superclades based on embryology, morphology and molecular data: Ecdysozoa (including arthropods like D. melanogaster, nematodes like C. elegans), Lophotrochozoa (including molluscs such as Aplysia), and Deuterostomia (including chordates like rats, mice, humans) [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Lophotrochozoa and Ecdysozoa are sister-clades that together form the Protostomia [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Most studies support the monophyly of these three superclades, and thus a common ancestor for all Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Several recent studies support a monophyletic grouping of Deuterostomia, with Protostomia as a sister clade [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Identification of Protostomia iGluR genes homologous to vertebrate NMDAR and AMPAR subunits can allow for predictions of subunits that may be involved in observed synaptic plasticity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This analysis can also add useful information to our poor understanding of subtype-specific agonists in protostomes [29–31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Aplysia is a model organism with a long history of studies of iGluR-mediated nervous system function, in particular for learning and memory paradigms [9, 32–34]. Aplysia NMDAR subunits have been shown to be expressed throughout the nervous system [35], however most other Aplysia iGluR have been identified through similarity to sequences of other species, and their in vivo expression patterns are unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Subunits within each iGluR subtype form a monophyletic clade in vertebrates, and complete receptors can only be formed with subunits within each of these clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>An Aplysia-only phylogeny was built to identify subunits that form monophyletic clades, and thus may form functional receptors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In this study we clarified the evolution of bilaterian iGluR using phylogenetic analysis, investigated iGluR genes in Aplysia, and determined expression levels in ganglia of the Aplysia nervous system to place this model into an appropriate context with other iGluR model species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>iGluR sequences for phylogenetic analysis were obtained from NCBI for all species except Branchiostoma belcheri (lancelet), which were obtained from the Chinese Lancelet Genome Project (&lt;genome.bucm.edu.cn/lancelet&gt;). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Sequences of all identified canonical iGluR proteins were aligned in MEGA7 [36] using the MUSCLE (multiple sequence comparison by log-expectation) multiple aligner algorithm with default parameters [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Poorly aligned regions of the alignment were removed using trimAl [38] with the –automated1 option to heuristically determine optimal trimming of the alignment, resulting in 473 positions used for phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Unrooted phylogenetic trees were then constructed in MEGA7 using maximum likelihood and 1000 bootstrap replicates with the LG amino acid substitution model [39] with gamma distributed rates and five rate categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The initial tree was obtained by applying the Neighbor-Joining algorithm to a matrix of pairwise distances estimated using a JTT model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Subtype specific trees were built to further clarify the relationships within orthologous groups using the same parameters as the full phylogeny, except 500 bootstrap replicates were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>These same parameters were also used to build the Aplysia-only iGluR tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Trees were visualized using FigTree (v1.4.2) [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Protein accessions for all sequences can be found in Additional file 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Identification of iGluR genes in Aplysia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Previously described iGluR in both Aplysia and chordates were obtained from the NCBI database, and analyzed using tools at the SMART [41] and Interpro [42] protein databases for potential binding sites and transmembrane domains to identify all iGluR subunits in Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>These sites are likely to be highly conserved to maintain L-Glu activation, thus their sequences were extensively searched in both the Aplysia published genome (NCBI) and the freely accessible Aplysia transcriptome database (&lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aplysiagenetools.org/">http://www.aplysiagenetools.org/</ext-link>&gt;). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Candidate genes were then translated to protein sequences and run through a BLAST search as well as scanned in Interpro for verification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Genes were confirmed to be in the Aplysia transcriptome by PCR amplification from cDNA of the abdominal ganglia and cloned in a TA vector (Invitrogen) and subsequently sequenced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobicity analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The Kite/Doolittle hydrophobicity scale was used to determine the hydrophobicity of each amino acid for the last 450 amino acids in both human and Aplysia Grin1 subunits, which contains the ligand binding, transmembrane, and intracellular C-terminal domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>For representative AMPAR and kainate receptor subunits only transmembrane domains were analyzed due to lack of agonist-binding site identification in Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>mRNA extraction and quantification of iGluR gene expression in the nervous system </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To describe quantitative expression of identified iGluR in Aplysia nervous system ganglia, six sexually mature Aplysia californica from a single egg mass of wild-caught animals were obtained from the National Resource for Aplysia at the University of Miami. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Animals were anesthetized in a solution of 50:50 isotonic MgCl2:Artificial sea water (ASW). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>All ganglia were removed, immediately rinsed in ASW, and placed in Trizol (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Tissues were ground in a bead homogenizer to break cells out of the sheath prior to RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Both hemiganglia for each tissue from each animal were pooled into a single sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted following the manufacturer’s protocol and samples were treated with DNAse to remove any contaminating DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>RNA quantities were determined using a Nanodrop (Model ND-1000), and samples were stored at -80 °C until further processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>100 ng of RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using the SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>After dilution of the cDNA (1:5 with H2O) messenger RNA (mRNA) copy number was determined using qPCR on a Stratagene Mx3005P with SYBR Green master mix and the equivalent of 2 ng of starting RNA per well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Primer pairs were designed for each of the 13 iGluR identified in Aplysia to detect expression levels with quantitative real-time PCR (see Additional file 2 for primers). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Efficiencies of each primer pair was tested by generating standard curves based on regression analyses of the Ct and the log value of 10-time dilution of each target gene for each primer pair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>All primers used had efficiencies between 0.9 and 1.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>mRNA copies were then calculated using standard curves and the average of duplicate cycle threshold (Ct) values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Southern blot </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Southern blotting from agarose gels was done onto Hybond-N + membrane (Amersham) in sodium saline citrate buffer (10 × SSC; 1.5 M NaCl; 0.15 M Na citrate pH 7.0) by capillary action. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Hybridization for high stringency blots was conducted in 30% formamide, 5× SSC, 1× Denhardt’s, 0.2% sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS), 10% Dextran sulphate, 20 mM sodium phosphate, pH 6.8 and at 42 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Final washes for high stringency were in 0.1 × SSC, 0.1% SDS at 65 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Each lane contained 4 μg of DNA and was cut with one of the following enzymes: EcoR1, HindIII, BamH1, and PstI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The probe was labeled using a random primed DNA labeling kit with [γ-32P] dCTP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of Bilaterian iGluR subunits </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To investigate the evolutionary relationships of iGluR across the Bilateria, phylogenetic analysis was conducted on full-length protein sequences of all NMDAR, AMPAR, kainate receptor, and delta receptor subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Sequences were included from the three major bilaterian lineages: Deuterostomia (Homo sapiens, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Danio rerio, Branchiostoma lanceolatum, Ciona intestinalis), Ecdysozoa (Limulus polyphemus, Priapulus caudatus, Drosophila melanogaster, Caenorhabditis elegans, Daphnia magna, Tribolium castaneum), and Lophotrochozoa (Aplysia californica, Octopus bimaculoides, Lingula anatina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Additional file 3 contains the multiple sequence alignment of all proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The species tree showing the evolutionary relationships among the species is shown in Fig. 1.Fig. 1Species tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Tree of the evolutionary relationships between species used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The tree was built using the NCBI taxonomy browser [80] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree of bilaterian iGluR is presented in Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Identification of iGluR genes as kainate receptor or AMPAR subtypes is unclear for many protostomes, thus these genes are currently named as “GluR” genes without an AMPA or kainate designation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Deuterostome iGluR genes are named Grin (Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic NMDA), GRIA (Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic AMPA), or GRIK (Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic Kainate) based on selective agonists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Canonical sequences, as determined by Uniprot, were used for genes with more than 1 splice variant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Some deep branches of the tree were poorly supported by bootstrapping due to high divergence of sequences between subtypes and large evolutionary distance between species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>However, most orthologous groups were well resolved with strong bootstrap support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Based on the phylogeny of the iGluR proteins each protostome subunit was classified as NMDAR, AMPAR, kainate receptor or as orphan genes that do not show a clear relationship with vertebrate subtypes (Table 1).Fig. 2Unrooted bootstrap consensus phylogenetic tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>iGluR protein sequences for six deuterostomes and nine protostomes with iGluR information available were aligned using MUSCLE in MEGA7 and the tree was constructed using maximum likelihood and 1000 bootstrap replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>iGluR subtypes are indicated by different colors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Numbers indicate bootstrap support and are displayed for boostrap values &gt;0.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The scale bar represents 0.4 substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>All species contain homologs for Grin1 and Grin2 subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>An ancestral AMPAR and kainate receptor gene was present in the common bilaterian ancestor, but in the case of the kainate receptor, the monophyly is only weakly supported by bootstrap values Table 1Placement of Protostomia iGluR into subtypes based on phylogeniesSpeciesAMPAKainateNMDAOrphans Aplysia californica GluR1GluR2GluR3GluR4GluR5GluR8GluR7KA2Grin1Grin2KA1GluR6 Caenorhabditis elegans GluR1GluR2noneGrin1Grin2GluR3GluR4aGluR5GluR6GluR7 Drosophila melanogaster GluR1AGluR1BGluR1CGluR2DGluRIIEGrin1Grin2GluRIIAGluRIIBGluRIIC Daphnia magna noneGRIK1Grin1GluR1Grin2Grin3GRIK2 Limulus polyphemus GluR1GRIK2GRIK3Grin1Grin2Grin3GRIK1GluR4GluR2 Lingula anatina GluR2GluR4GRIK2Grin1Grin2GluR1 Octopus bimaculoides GluRnoneGrin1Grin3GRIK2 Priapulus caudatus GluR3GluR4noneGrin1Grin2Grin3GRIK3GluR1GluR2GRIK4 Tribolium castaneum noneGRIK1GluR1Grin1Grin2GRIK2GRIK3GRIK5GluR2iGluR genes in each protostome species were categorized into subtypes based on their phylogenetic relationship with chordate iGluR genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Many protostome iGluR genes do not have a clear relationship with chordate subtypes and are thus identified as orphan receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Protostome orphan receptors are divergent from chordate genes and thus unlikely to perform the same subtype specific functions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>NMDAR genes form three orthologous groups corresponding to Grin1, Grin2, and Grin3 subunits, providing evidence that all three ancestral Grin subunits were present in the most recent bilaterian ancestor (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This is a unique feature of NMDAR: they are the only iGluR subtype with more than one orthologous copy present before the divergence of protostomes and deuterostomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In the orthologous group Grin2 each protostome and basal deuterostome has only one ortholog of Grin2, but vertebrates have four Grin2 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Vertebrate Grin2 genes form a highly discrete clade, with four paralogous copies that arose early in the vertebrate lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The Grin2 paralogs in vertebrates are likely best explained by the 2R hypothesis, which postulates that two rounds of whole genome duplication occurred early in the vertebrate lineage after their split from tunicates [43, 44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Thus, the 2R hypothesis predicts that vertebrates are expected to have four copies of each gene in comparison to one copy in invertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In the case of Grin2 all four paralogs have been retained in all vertebrates used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In contrast, both in Grin1 and Grin3 there is only a single orthologous group of vertebrates present in the tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in both cases only one of the four that originated during the 2R genome duplications remained active, whereas three of them have been lost early in vertebrate evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Despite large evolutionary distances among the studied species, all three Grin orthologs are highly conserved suggesting that they are under high functional constraints slowing their divergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>For AMPAR genes there is a monophyletic clade of all vertebrate AMPAR sequences and several orthologous protostome genes, pointing to an AMPAR gene copy present in the common bilaterian ancestor (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The number of AMPAR genes in protostome species is highly variable and appears to be species or taxon specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>For example, in the Lophotrochozoa, Aplysia has 6 paralogous AMPAR genes, Octopus has 1, and Lingula has 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Ecdysozoan species have 2–3 genes in this orthogroup, except Daphnia and Tribolium, which do not have any genes in the AMPAR orthogroup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Most AMPAR genes of protostome species are most closely related to each other (inparalogs) rather than to AMPAR genes, with Lingula as the exception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This implies that gene duplications occurred after the divergence of each lineage in this study, suggesting that there has been extensive gene gain and loss that has acted independently in each protostome taxon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This appears particularly true in Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Six AMPAR genes in Aplysia and 1–2 in other lophotrocozoans, including Octopus, suggests several gene duplication events occurred within the Gastropoda lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The sampled vertebrates have consistent with the 2R genome duplication scenario all four AMPAR genes, in comparison to one AMPAR ortholog in the common bilaterian ancestor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Kainate receptor genes are the only subtype in the tree in which Protostomia and Deuterostomia genes do not form a strongly supported monophyletic clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Only three protostome genes form an orthologous group with chordate kainate receptor subunits: Aplysia KA2, Tribolium GRIK1, and Limulus GRIK2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Identification of kainate receptor genes is unclear for many Ecdysozoan species due to extensive divergence of these subunits from Deuterostomia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Many predicted kainate receptor genes from Limulus, Priapulus, and Tribolium form an independent clade without a clear relationship to chordate kainate receptor genes (to the left of the tree, Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This suggests they have a slightly different function, or that they work through a different mechanism than the kainate genes that have been studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Additionally, Priapulus, Limulus, Daphnia, and Tribolium have several genes that appear to be very distant to all other genes in the tree (to the right of the tree, Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Within vertebrates there are two ancient paralogs with a total of five kainate genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The three paralogs GRIK_A1-3 form one orthologous type and the two paralogs GRIK_B4-5 form together with the lancelet GRIK2 sequence the second type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in comparison to the four paralogs expected under the 2R duplications, GRIK_A1-3 and GRIK_B4-5 were respectively losing one and two paralogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In contrast to Grin and AMPAR genes, extensive divergence of kainate receptor genes in Deuterostomia and Protostomia suggests that they are the least conserved iGluR subtype across Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Orthologous groups of each iGluR subtype were further analyzed in the attempt to obtain a better resolution of the evolutionary relationships in these parts of the tree (see Additional file 3 for alignments, Additional file 4 for trees). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In this analysis the relationship between protostome and chordate iGluR were the same as in the full phylogeny, providing further support for the relationships found in the full phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>An additional phylogenetic tree was built using only Aplysia iGluR to search for subunits that form monophyletic clades and thus may form complete receptors (See Additional file 3 for alignment, Additional file 4 for tree). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The Aplysia-only tree confirms the findings of the full phylogeny, with subunits corresponding to currently predicted NMDAR and AMPAR subunits forming monophyletic clades, while the four predicted kainate receptor subunits do not show a monophyletic relationship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Number of iGluR genes in Aplysia and other Bilaterians </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Through genomic searches, the number of iGluR genes identified in chordates was greater than the number of genes in any protostome (Table 2), although it must be noted that for some protostome species the number of iGluR genes may not be accurate due to limited availability of genomic information and annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>As described in the phylogenetic analysis, extensive gene gain and loss of AMPAR genes in protostomes has also contributed to the variable number of iGluR genes in different protostome species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The increased number of genes in chordates is likely due to retention of many paralogs after 2R genome duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>We found that in both Grin1 and Grin3 orthologous groups three of the four paralogous genes from the 2R genome duplications have not been retained.Table 2Number of iGluR genes in the protostomes and deuterostomesSpeciesTotal iGluR genesSpeciesTotal iGluR genes Homo sapiens 14 Caenorhabditis elegans 9 Mus musculus 14 Ciona intestinalis 6 Rattus norvegicus 14 Daphnia magna 7 Danio rerio 14 Limulus Polyphemus 11 Aplysia california 12 Priapulus caudatus 11 Lingula anatina 6 Tribolium castaneum 10 Octopus bimaculoides 6 Branchiostoma belcheri 10 Drosophila melanogaster 10 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Genomic searches using SMART [45] and InterPro tools [46] revealed 12 unique iGluR genes and one splice variant of Grin1 in Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The translated Aplysia iGluR sequences showed a highly conserved SYTANLAAF motif [47] near the second transmembrane loop, which was used to identify them as iGluR (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This motif contributes to formation of the channel outer pore and its activation gate [48], and amino acid substitutions in this motif are reported to alter channel gating and permeability [49, 50]. Aplysia showed a greater number of iGluR subunits compared to other protostomes, primarily due to several gene duplications of AMPAR genes, as discussed above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>cDNAs corresponding to all 12 Aplysia iGluR were isolated from the nervous system and confirmed to be transcribed in vivo. Fig. 3Conserved motifs in Aplysia and H. sapiens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Boxed region denotes SYTANLAAFL motif vital for formation of the channel pore and activation gate, and in all subunits this high selective pressure has resulted in highly conserved amino acid sequences over large evolutionary distances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This motif is also conserved in all other chordates in this study </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Sequence similarity and conserved domains of Grin1 in Aplysia and vertebrates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Conserved domains of Grin1 proteins in Aplysia and the vertebrates studied were analyzed to elucidate whether similarities in these parts of the sequences might predict conservation of function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The first ~400 amino acids of NMDAR proteins, known as the N-terminal domain (NTD), show high sequence divergence, with only 19% sequence identity in this region within a species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Mutant Grin2 subunits lacking the entire NTD were shown to assemble into receptors functionally similar to complete receptors, thus it is not surprising that this region showed low sequence similarity between species [51, 52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Comparatively, agonist binding domains (ABDs) and transmembrane domains (TMDs) must show greater conservation to maintain iGluR functionality, and indeed, within a species these regions show 63 and 73% identity, respectively [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In comparing the Grin1 subunits of H. sapiens and Aplysia we found 66% sequence identity between these subunits after removal of the NTD, similar to the sequence similarity of ABDs and TMDs within a species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The three TMDs of Grin1 together form the iGluR ion channel and these regions show very high protein sequence similarity throughout the Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>However, Aplysia sequences consistently showed greater sequence similarity to H. sapiens than did either D. melanogaster or C. elegans (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The TMDs of the vertebrate genes compared had close to 100% conservation, on average, and exhibited much greater amino acid similarity than the rest of the protein, suggesting high selective pressure on these sites to maintain function.Table 3Sequence similarities in transmembrane domains of Grin1 between different protostomes and H. sapiens SpeciesTMD1TMD2TMD3 A. californica 85%100%87% D. melanogaster 75%100%61% C. elegans 65%87%48%Compared to H. sapiens, Aplysia had fewer amino acid substitutions in transmembrane domains (TMDs) than did D. melanogaster and C. elegans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This points to a higher likelihood of conserved channel function between vertebrates and Aplysia  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The hydrophobicity of amino acids in a protein influences the folding and structure of the molecule, and protein regions with similar hydrophobicity profiles are predicted to maintain structural stability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>TMDs are well conserved, but substitutions that result in different amino acids occur, as shown in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>A plot of the hydrophobicity of the canonical Grin1 sequences in Aplysia and H. sapiens shows that amino acid substitutions in the TMD’s have been tolerated only when the substituted residue has a similar hydrophobicity, and thus is predicted not to significantly alter protein folding (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that the structure and function of the transmembrane domains and ion channel have been maintained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Conversely, protein sequences for the glycine and NMDA binding sites show high sequence divergence and numerous changes in hydrophobicity compared to H. sapiens sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobicity plays a crucial role in receptor binding domains [54], and this lack of conservation may reflect the diminished role for glycine as a co-agonist in Aplysia NMDAR [55].Fig. 4Hydrophobicity plot of Grin1 in H. sapiens and Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Kite/Doolittle scale was used to determine the hydrophobicity of each amino acid for the last 450 amino acids, containing the ligand binding domain, TMD, and intracellular C-terminal domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Despite large evolutionary distance between Aplysia and H. sapiens, only substitutions with similar hydrophobicity are tolerated in TMDs to maintain proper folding of the ion channel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Predicted NMDA and glycine binding sites show many more substitutions that result in changes in hydrophobicity </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Representative hydrophobicity plots of AMPAR and kainate receptor subunits can be found in Additional file 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For both AMPAR and kainate receptor subunits, hydrophobicity of the TMDs appears to be well conserved with H. sapiens, however, they are not as conserved as the TMDs of Grin1 subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This supports the phylogenetic evidence that AMPAR subunits in Aplysia are closely related to H. sapiens subunits and may perform similar functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In the phylogeny, kainate receptor subunits of the prostostomes were highly divergent from vertebrates, however the TMDs are a notable exception and appeared to be well-conserved with H. sapiens in this analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of Grin2 genes in Aplysia genomic DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>While a search of the recently revised A. californica genome revealed only one gene similar to Grin2 subunits in Chordata, the presence of gaps in this genome sequence raises the possibility that additional genes may have been missed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>A Southern blot analysis of genomic DNA of Aplysia demonstrated only a single band homologous to a conserved region of Grin2 (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This band was at the expected molecular weight for the previously identified Aplysia Grin2, suggesting that no other Grin2 genes are present in this genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This result was not surprising considering that there is only one Grin2 gene found in other Protostomia species [56]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Quantification of iGluR gene expression in the nervous system </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The expression of identified iGluR in all Aplysia nervous system ganglia is shown in Fig. 5 (s﻿ee Additional file ﻿5 for Cts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>All twelve subunits, as well as the splice variant Grin1-2, were expressed in all ganglia, with strong differences both within and between different iGluR subtypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The subtype with the highest expression varied across the different ganglia (Fig. 5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In most tissues the kainate-like receptor genes were expressed at the highest levels, followed by NMDAR-like genes, with AMPAR-like genes expressed at the lowest levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The highest expression of all three iGluR subtypes was found in the pedal ganglion, suggesting that this ganglion has the greatest reliance on L-Glu-mediated neurotransmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The buccal ganglion showed the lowest expression for both NMDAR and AMPAR genes and showed significantly greater (p ≤ 0.05) expression of kainate receptor subunits.Fig. 5iGluR expression levels in Aplysia ganglia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of each subtype of iGluR were determined by quantitative real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Absolute copy number was calculated using standard curves. a Comparisons of total expression of each iGluR subtype in different Aplysia ganglia, with calculated number of transcripts on the y-axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Total kainate receptor subunit expression was significantly greater than other subtypes in both the pleural and buccal ganglia (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s post-hoc, p ≤ 0.05) (b) Pie charts showing each subunit’s contribution to the total expression of its subtype </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Expression of NMDAR genes was primarily due to high expression of Grin1-1, representing &gt;60% of NMDAR expression in nearly all nervous system tissues (Fig. 5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that Grin1 may be the subunit that contributes the most to NMDAR-mediated physiological responses to L-Glu in the nervous system of Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The lone exception was the buccal ganglion, where the splice variant Grin1-2 was the most highly expressed NMDAR subunit gene in the majority of the six animals studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>A similar pattern of high expression of one gene was observed with kainate receptor genes, where the GluR7 subunit comprised the majority of this subtype’s gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The distribution of expression of AMPAR subunits favored no single subunit gene dominating the expression of this subtype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>iGluR mediated responses in the nervous system are of particular interest due to their role in synaptic plasticity associated with learning and memory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Protostomes have a long history of use as model organisms for studies of iGluR mediated synaptic plasticity due to their simple nervous systems and well-defined neural circuits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Many plasticity-related changes in the vertebrate nervous system were first discovered in protostomes, and were subsequently shown to be conserved in chordates [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Further studies in vertebrates have identified the NMDAR and AMPAR subtypes of iGluR underlying these processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Despite the utility of protostomes for iGluR mediated responses in the nervous system, identification of iGluR subunits that are orthologous to chordate iGluR has so far not been thoroughly studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The application of phylogenetic methods to specific protein families is a useful procedure to shed light on their functional status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>We conducted a phylogenetic analysis of iGluR spanning all three superclades of bilaterians; Deuterostomia (including Chordata), and their sisterclade Protostomia, consisting of Ecdysozoa and Lophotrochozoa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We found that the evolutionary history of iGluR in Bilateria is distinct for each iGluR subtype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>It was possible to identify protostome iGluR subunits most closely related to chordate iGluR, with possibly similar functional roles, for both NMDAR and AMPAR genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The best supported conclusion from the analysis presented is that clear orthologous groups are formed for both Grin1 and Grin2 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This is an extension of the previous report that protostome Grin1 and Grin2, including Aplysia, are more closely related to chordate Grin1 and Grin2, respectively, than to each other [35] and further supports the close kinship of all known bilaterian NMDAR subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>This study confirms an ancient duplication that generated two orthologous NMDAR genes present in the common bilaterian ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Both orthogroups have been under high selective constraint that has maintained the function of these genes at least since the divergence of deuterostomes and protostomes, thus making protostome model organisms excellent study systems for NMDAR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The number of NMDAR subunits varies greatly between deuterostomes and protostomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Chordate species in this study express 3–8 Grin1 splice variants, while only 1 Grin1 splice variant was identified in Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The chordates also express a greater number of Grin2 genes and splice variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Two independent rounds of whole genome duplication in the deuterostome lineage since its split from the bilaterian ancestor, that also gave rise to Lophotrochozoa [44], are hypothesized to be the origin of these duplicated Grin2 genes [56, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The regulatory C-terminus contains most of the sequence variability in different vertebrate Grin2 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that the retention of duplicated Grin2 genes is explained by the subfunctionalization model, whereby each duplicate gene copy maintains a subset of its original function [58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The NMDAR subunits involved in receptor assembly have been shown to strongly alter pharmacological and biophysical properties of the channel, including sensitivity to allosteric modulators, single channel conductance, and activation/deactivation kinetics [59–61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The greater number of NMDAR subunits available for complete receptors in chordates increases the different physiological responses possible, and likely underlies the more complex and nuanced signaling capability observed in vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, activation of NMDAR has been shown to be an essential component of synaptic plasticity and memory formation in vertebrates [62], and knockdown of NMDAR can disrupt learning in protostome species [24, 63, 64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>In spite of the greater diversity of NMDAR subunits in chordates, homology of Grin1 and Grin2 across bilaterian animals suggests that a wealth of discovery in the mechanisms of NMDAR-induced plasticity is nevertheless possible in simpler nervous systems such as Aplysia, with relevance to vertebrate NMDAR physiology, including that of humans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>AMPAR subtype genes also form an orthologous group, with evidence of a single ancestral AMPAR gene in the common bilaterian ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Unlike NMDAR, the number of protostome genes in this orthogroup is highly variable and has been subject to extensive lineage and taxon specific gene duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>For example, in the Ecdysozoan superclade, Pripaulus, Drosophila, and C. elegans each have two inparalogous AMPAR genes most closely related to genes in their own species, suggesting that each gene is a paralog that arose independently in each lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the other two Ecdysozoan species studied, Daphnia and Tribolium, do not have any genes within the AMPAR orthogroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In Lophotrochozoans expansion of AMPAR genes is particularly prevalent in Aplysia, where multiple gene duplication events have resulted in six AMPAR genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Whether AMPAR physiology in protostomes will bear the same resemblance to chordate AMPAR, as is the case with NMDAR, is uncertain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The name AMPAR for this subtype is likely inaccurate in protostomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Isolated Aplysia sensory neurons do not respond to exogenously applied AMPA, and AMPAR antagonists do not block whole cell currents elicited by the L-Glu analog D-aspartate (D-Asp; [55]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Yet Aplysia AMPAR have physiological roles with relevance to vertebrate learning, with AMPAR antagonists inhibiting facilitation [65, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Synaptic plasticity in vertebrates is also AMPAR-dependent [67, 68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>AMPAR antagonists such as 6,7-dinitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium (DNQX) and 6-cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium (CNQX) act on sites that are different than the agonist binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Similarity to chordate AMPAR suggests that Aplysia and other protostome AMPAR may bind agonists and antagonists differently than do those of vertebrates, yet operate similarly physiologically once activated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Extensive gene gain and loss of AMPAR suggests less functional constraint compared to NMDAR genes, and may underlie these dissimilarities in AMPAR physiology in different taxonomic groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Different numbers of AMPAR genes in different protostomes may result in unique receptor assemblages conveying different physiological properties in each taxon, thus the exact role of AMPAR may be unique in different lineages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Kainate receptors are the least conserved subtype, with no strongly supported monophyletic group, but were clearly present in the common bilaterian ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Kainate receptors play a minor role in synaptic signaling [69], and are not believed to be as involved in learning and memory as NMDAR and AMPAR [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is unsurprising that there may be less functional constraint on these receptors than there is on AMPAR and NMDAR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Large divergence of kainate receptor genes makes it difficult to predict the functional relevance of these genes to iGluR mediated excitability in the nervous system of protostomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In agreement with previous studies, vertebrate iGluR subunits were arranged into three distinct clades corresponding to the three different agonists [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Our analysis of Aplysia only iGluR genes indicated that NMDAR and AMPAR subunits form well-defined clades and thus may be capable of forming functional iGluR channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the makeup of kainate receptors is less clear, due to the lack of monophyletic groups in the protostomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>All 12 identified iGluR subunits were expressed in all Aplysia ganglia, extending the results of an in situ hybridization study concluding that Grin1 was expressed throughout the nervous system [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This attests to the importance of L-Glu mediated fast synaptic transmission in all parts of the Aplysia nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Grin1 expression was highest in nearly all Aplysia ganglia, with its two splice variants Grin1-1 and Grin1-2 together comprising ~75% of total NMDAR expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>A recent study using a nuclease protection assay showed that expression of Grin1 comprised 67–88% of the total Grin expression in rat brain [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>When combined with homology discussed earlier, this suggests that the regulation and function of NMDAR in Aplysia are highly conserved with those of vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Variable and spatially distinct expression of the three iGluR subtypes was observed in the ganglia of the Aplysia brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Pedal ganglion had the highest iGluR expression, with the glutamatergic nature of pedal motoneuron transmission corroborated by physiological studies [72, 73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Variations in the frequency and amplitude of ionic currents activated by the iGluR agonists L-Glu and D-Asp have been documented in neurons isolated from different ganglia [74, 75], lending support to the non-uniformity of the receptor expression patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Studies in mammalian brains have shown both spatial and developmental variations in patterns of expression of NMDAR and AMPAR subunits, with some subunits specific for certain brain regions, or variable expression dependent on the stage of development [76, 77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>To place bilaterian iGluR into a larger evolutionary perspective, insights about the deep origins of iGluR have recently emerged from discoveries on ctenophores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Studies of candidate iGluR genes in the ctenophore Mnemiopsis leidyi, which is currently thought basal to bilaterian animals [78], revealed that ctenophore iGluR form a monophyletic clade separate from, and ancestral to, chordates [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Thus it appears that subunit types emerged after the ctenophores split, but before the divergence of Deuterostomia, Ecdysozoa, and Lophotrochozoa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>This is suggestive of individual AMPAR and NMDAR subunits evolving prior to the last common bilaterian ancestor, but after divergence from ctenophores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, two studies using expressed sequence tags (EST), genome organization, gene structure and functional content found lower amino acid substitution rates in Lophotrochozoa than Ecdysozoa relative to chordates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that genes in Lophotrochozoa are more likely to have greater sequence similarity to chordates than Ecdysozoan genes, and hence may be more likely to be functional equivalent to chordates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>NMDAR and AMPAR subtypes of iGluR are vital to synaptic plasticity associated with vertebrate learning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>This study confirms the ancestral origins of NMDAR and AMPAR genes and also, but less strongly supported, ancestral kainate receptor genes in Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>These findings underscore the utility of Aplysia and other protostome models for the studies of AMPAR and NMDAR mediated responses in the nervous system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>This is the first analysis of the phylogenetic relationships between subtypes of iGluR genes across Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>For decades, model organisms from the Protostomia have been used as models of nervous system function, and we show that AMPAR and NMDAR subtypes were present in the common bilaterian ancestor and have been maintained as orthologous groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Functional constraint preventing amino acid substitutions in pore regions of NMDAR suggests a highly conserved function of these subunits and potentially a conserved mechanism of learning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Kainate receptor subunits are the least conserved and may not play the same role in protostomes and deuterostomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>qPCR results demonstrate that iGluR are expressed ubiquitously throughout the nervous system of Aplysia, underscoring the importance of this model to understanding iGluR mediated nervous system function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec16"><title>Additional files</title><p>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12862_2016_871_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>iGluR protein accession numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Complete list of protein accession numbers of all iGluR proteins used to create phylogenies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 35 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12862_2016_871_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>qPCR Primer Pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>List of forward and reverse primers used to amplify unique qPCR products for each Aplysia iGluR gene and the Grin1-2 splice variant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>All amplicons were 100–150bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 53 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12862_2016_871_MOESM3_ESM.zip" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Protein alignments used to create phylogenetic trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Protein alignments both before and after sequence trimming with trimAl that were used to create each phylogeny, including: full iGluR phylogeny, NMDAR, AMPAR, and kainate receptor trees, and Aplysia only iGluR tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>(ZIP 292 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12862_2016_871_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Additional phylogenetic trees and hydrophobicity plots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Additional phylogenies were created using trimmed alignments from Additional file 3. Figure S1: Aplysia only phylogeny inferred by the maximum likelihood method to identify subunits that form monophyletic clades in Aplysia and thus may form complete receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>NMDAR and AMPAR subunits form monophyletic clades, while kainate receptor subunits did not form a clade. Figure S2: NMDAR only subtype tree using sequences identified as NMDAR in the full phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Monophyletic relationships are formed between each protostome and chordate NMDAR subunit, as observed in the full phylogeny. Figure S3: AMPAR subtype only tree indicates a single AMPAR gene in the common bilaterian ancestor. Figure S4: Kainate receptor subunits from chordates and protostomes do not form a strongly supported clade, unlike the strongly support clades observed in the NMDAR and AMPAR subtypes. Figure S5: Hydrophobicity plot of H. sapiens GRIA1 and Aplysia GluR1 TMDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Similarity in TMD1 and TMD3 between the sequences suggest similar ion channel structure. Figure S6: Hydrophobicity plot of H. sapiens GRIK1 and Aplysia GluR7 shows high conservation of TMDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>(PDF 131 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12862_2016_871_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Average Ct values from qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Average Ct values of two technical replicates for each iGluR gene in all nervous system ganglia of Aplysia used to calculate copy numbers for each subunit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 43 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
</p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>2R</term><def><p>2 round genome duplication</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ABD</term><def><p>Agonist binding domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMPAR</term><def><p>α-Amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ASW</term><def><p>Artificial sea water</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNQX</term><def><p>6-cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNS</term><def><p>Central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ct</term><def><p>Cycle threshold</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>D-Asp</term><def><p>D-aspartate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dCTP</term><def><p>Deoxycytidine triphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DNQX</term><def><p>6,7-dinitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EST</term><def><p>Expressed sequence tag</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRIA</term><def><p>Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic AMPA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRIK</term><def><p>Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic Kainate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Grin</term><def><p>Glutamate Receptor Ionotropic NMDA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>iGluR</term><def><p>Ionotropic L-Glu receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>L-Glu</term><def><p>L-Glutamate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mGluR</term><def><p>Metabotropic L-Glutamate receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mRNA</term><def><p>Messenger RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MUSCLE</term><def><p>Multiple sequence comparison by log-expectation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMDAR</term><def><p>N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NTD</term><def><p>N-terminal domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p>Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p>Quantitative polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS</term><def><p>Sodium dodecyl sulphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSC</term><def><p>Sodium citrate buffer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TMD</term><def><p>Transmembrane domain</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge the University of Miami Aplysia Resource staff for their assistance. We would also like to thank Ben Silver for his assistance in data mining the transcriptome database, Dr. Patrick Gibbs for his assistance with the Southern Blot and Dr. Ed Mager for his help with primer design for qPCR.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by the National Institutes of Health Grant (P40 OD010952). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article and its additional files.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>JBG and LAF conceived and designed this study. JBG performed the experiments and analyzed the data. SK advised on the bioinformatics analysis. JBG, SK, and LAF wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval</title><p>Not required.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>1.MeldrumBSGlutamate as a neurotransmitter in the brain: review of physiology and pathologyJ Nutr200013041007S15<?supplied-pmid 10736372?>10736372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>2.PetraliaRSWangYXZhaoHMWentholdRJIonotropic and metabotropic glutamate receptors show unique postsynaptic, presynaptic, and glial localizations in the dorsal cochlear nucleusJ Comp Neurol199637233568310.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19960826)372:3&lt;356::AID-CNE3&gt;3.0.CO;2-1<?supplied-pmid 8873866?>8873866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>3.TraynelisSFWollmuthLPMcBainCJMennitiFSVanceKMOgdenKKHansenKBYuanHMyersSJDingledineRGlutamate receptor ion channels: structure, regulation, and functionPharmacol Rev20106234059610.1124/pr.109.002451<?supplied-pmid 20716669?>20716669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>4.DanyszWZajaczkowskiWParsonsCModulation of learning processes by ionotropic glutamate receptor ligandsBehav Pharmacol19956545574<?supplied-pmid 11224354?>11224354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>5.TichelaarWSafferlingMKeinänenKStarkHMaddenDRThe three-dimensional structure of an ionotropic glutamate receptor reveals a dimer-of-dimers assemblyJ Mol Biol200434424354210.1016/j.jmb.2004.09.048<?supplied-pmid 15522296?>15522296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>6.LipskyRHGoldmanDGenomics and Variation of Ionotropic Glutamate ReceptorsAnn N Y Acad Sci200310031223510.1196/annals.1300.003<?supplied-pmid 14684433?>14684433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>7.KewJNKempJAIonotropic and metabotropic glutamate receptor structure and pharmacologyPsychopharmacology2005179142910.1007/s00213-005-2200-z<?supplied-pmid 15731895?>15731895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>8.NaurPHansenKBKristensenASDravidSMPickeringDSOlsenLVestergaardBEgebjergJGajhedeMTraynelisSFIonotropic glutamate-like receptor δ2 binds D-serine and glycineProc Natl Acad Sci200710435141162110.1073/pnas.0703718104<?supplied-pmid 17715062?>17715062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>9.KandelERThe molecular biology of memory storage: a dialogue between genes and synapsesScience200129455441030810.1126/science.1067020<?supplied-pmid 11691980?>11691980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>10.Herculano-Houzel S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The human brain in numbers: a linearly scaled-up primate brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Front Hum Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>2009;3:31. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>11.AlivisatosAPChunMChurchGMGreenspanRJRoukesMLYusteRThe brain activity map project and the challenge of functional connectomicsNeuron2012746970410.1016/j.neuron.2012.06.006<?supplied-pmid 22726828?>22726828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>12.Kosinski R, Zaremba M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Dynamics of the model of the Caenorhabditis Elegans neural network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Acta Phys Pol B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>2007;38(6):2201-10. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>13.WaltersETByrneJCarewTKandelEMechanoafferent neurons innervating tail of Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Response properties and synaptic connectionsJ Neurophysiol1983506152242<?supplied-pmid 6663341?>6663341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>14.SimpsonJHMapping and manipulating neural circuits in the fly brainAdv Genet20096579143<?supplied-pmid 19615532?>19615532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>15.ChalfieMSulstonJEWhiteJGSouthgateEThomsonJNBrennerSThe neural circuit for touch sensitivity in Caenorhabditis elegansJ Neurosci19855495664<?supplied-pmid 3981252?>3981252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>16.PiggottBJLiuJFengZWescottSAXuXSThe neural circuits and synaptic mechanisms underlying motor initiation in C. elegansCell201114749223310.1016/j.cell.2011.08.053<?supplied-pmid 22078887?>22078887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>17.DaleNKandelERL-glutamate may be the fast excitatory transmitter of Aplysia sensory neuronsProc Natl Acad Sci199390157163710.1073/pnas.90.15.7163<?supplied-pmid 8102205?>8102205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>18.LevensonJEndoSKategayaLSFernandezRIBrabhamDGChinJByrneJHEskinALong-term regulation of neuronal high-affinity glutamate and glutamine uptake in AplysiaProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20009723128586310.1073/pnas.220256497<?supplied-pmid 11050153?>11050153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>19.BrockiePJMadsenDMZhengYMellemJMaricqAVDifferential expression of glutamate receptor subunits in the nervous system of Caenorhabditis elegans and their regulation by the homeodomain protein UNC-42J Neurosci2001215151022<?supplied-pmid 11222641?>11222641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>20.MarrusSBPortmanSLAllenMJMoffatKGDiAntonioADifferential localization of glutamate receptor subunits at the Drosophila neuromuscular junctionJ Neurosci200424614061510.1523/JNEUROSCI.1575-03.2004<?supplied-pmid 14960613?>14960613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>21.MalenkaRCBearMFLTP and LTD: an embarrassment of richesNeuron200444152110.1016/j.neuron.2004.09.012<?supplied-pmid 15450156?>15450156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>22.LismanJEFellousJ-MWangX-JA role for NMDA-receptor channels in working memoryNat Neurosci199814273510.1038/1086<?supplied-pmid 10195158?>10195158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>23.LeeH-KTakamiyaKHanJ-SManHKimC-HRumbaughGYuSDingLHeCPetraliaRSPhosphorylation of the AMPA receptor GluR1 subunit is required for synaptic plasticity and retention of spatial memoryCell200311256314310.1016/S0092-8674(03)00122-3<?supplied-pmid 12628184?>12628184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>24.XiaSMiyashitaTFuT-FLinW-YWuC-LPyzochaLLinI-RSaitoeMTullyTChiangA-SNMDA receptors mediate olfactory learning and memory in DrosophilaCurr Biol20051576031510.1016/j.cub.2005.02.059<?supplied-pmid 15823532?>15823532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>25.PhilippeHLartillotNBrinkmannHMultigene analyses of bilaterian animals corroborate the monophyly of Ecdysozoa, Lophotrochozoa, and ProtostomiaMol Biol Evol200522512465310.1093/molbev/msi111<?supplied-pmid 15703236?>15703236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>26.DunnCWHejnolAMatusDQPangKBrowneWESmithSASeaverERouseGWObstMEdgecombeGDBroad phylogenomic sampling improves resolution of the animal tree of lifeNature20084527188745910.1038/nature06614<?supplied-pmid 18322464?>18322464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>27.Halanych KM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The new view of animal phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>2004;35:229-56. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>28.PapsJBaguñàJRiutortMBilaterian phylogeny: a broad sampling of 13 nuclear genes provides a new Lophotrochozoa phylogeny and supports a paraphyletic basal AcoelomorphaMol Biol Evol20092610239740610.1093/molbev/msp150<?supplied-pmid 19602542?>19602542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>29.FoxLELloydPEGlutamate is a fast excitatory transmitter at some buccal neuromuscular synapses in AplysiaJ Neurophysiol1999823147788<?supplied-pmid 10482763?>10482763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>30.KimuraSKawasakiSTakashimaKSasakiKPhysiological and Pharmacological Characteristics of Quisqualic Acid-Induced K + -Current Response in the Ganglion Cells of AplysiaJpn J Physiol20015145112110.2170/jjphysiol.51.511<?supplied-pmid 11564288?>11564288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>31.TrudeauL-ECastellucciVFExcitatory amino acid neurotransmission at sensory-motor and interneuronal synapses of Aplysia californicaJ Neurophysiol1993703122130<?supplied-pmid 7901346?>7901346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>32.BartschDGhirardiMSkehelPAKarlKAHerderSPChenMBaileyCHKandelERAplysia CREB2 represses long-term facilitation: relief of repression converts transient facilitation into long-term functional and structural changeCell19958369799210.1016/0092-8674(95)90213-9<?supplied-pmid 8521521?>8521521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>33.KempsellATFieberLAAging in sensory and motor neurons results in learning failure in Aplysia californicaPLoS One2015105e012705610.1371/journal.pone.0127056<?supplied-pmid 25970633?>25970633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>34.Kempsell AT, Fieber LA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Age-related deficits in synaptic plasticity rescued by activating PKA or PKC in sensory neurons of Aplysia californica. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Front Aging Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>2015;7:173. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>35.HaTJKohnABBobkovaYVMorozLLMolecular characterization of NMDA-like receptors in Aplysia and Lymnaea: relevance to memory mechanismsBiol Bull200621032557010.2307/4134562<?supplied-pmid 16801499?>16801499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>36.Kumar S, Stecher G, Tamura K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Mol Biol Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>2016;33:1870-74. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>37.EdgarRCMUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughputNucleic Acids Res20043251792710.1093/nar/gkh340<?supplied-pmid 15034147?>15034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>38.Capella-GutiérrezSSilla-MartínezJMGabaldónTtrimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analysesBioinformatics (Oxford, England)200925151972310.1093/bioinformatics/btp348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>39.LeSQGascuelOAn improved general amino acid replacement matrixMol Biol Evol200825713072010.1093/molbev/msn067<?supplied-pmid 18367465?>18367465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>40.RambautAFigTree version 1.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>02012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>41.LetunicIDoerksTBorkPSMART 7: recent updates to the protein domain annotation resourceNucleic Acids Res201240D1D302510.1093/nar/gkr931<?supplied-pmid 22053084?>22053084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>42.Hunter S, Jones P, Mitchell A, Apweiler R, Attwood TK, Bateman A, Bernard T, Binns D, Bork P, Burge S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>InterPro in 2011: new developments in the family and domain prediction database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>2012;40:306-12. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>43.PutnamNHButtsTFerrierDEFurlongRFHellstenUKawashimaTRobinson-RechaviMShoguchiETerryAYuJ-KThe amphioxus genome and the evolution of the chordate karyotypeNature2008453719810647110.1038/nature06967<?supplied-pmid 18563158?>18563158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>44.DehalPBooreJLTwo rounds of whole genome duplication in the ancestral vertebratePLoS Biol2005310170010.1371/journal.pbio.0030314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>45.LetunicIDoerksTBorkPSMART: recent updates, new developments and status in 2015Nucleic Acids Res201543D1D2576010.1093/nar/gku949<?supplied-pmid 25300481?>25300481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>46.Mitchell A, Chang H-Y, Daugherty L, Fraser M, Hunter S, Lopez R, McAnulla C, McMenamin C, Nuka G, Pesseat S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>The InterPro protein families database: the classification resource after 15 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>2015;43:D213-D221. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>47.WollmuthLPSobolevskyAIStructure and gating of the glutamate receptor ion channelTrends Neurosci2004276321810.1016/j.tins.2004.04.005<?supplied-pmid 15165736?>15165736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>48.DaiJZhouH-XAn NMDA receptor gating mechanism developed from MD simulations reveals molecular details underlying subunit-specific contributionsBiophys J20131041021708110.1016/j.bpj.2013.04.013<?supplied-pmid 23708357?>23708357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>49.LowC-MLyuboslavskyPFrenchALePWyatteKThielWHMarchanEMIgarashiKKashiwagiKGernertKMolecular determinants of proton-sensitive N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor gatingMol Pharmacol200363612122210.1124/mol.63.6.1212<?supplied-pmid 12761330?>12761330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>50.KohdaKWangYYuzakiMMutation of a glutamate receptor motif reveals its role in gating and δ2 receptor channel propertiesNat Neurosci2000343152210.1038/73877<?supplied-pmid 10725919?>10725919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>51.FayyazuddinAVillarroelALe GoffALermaJNeytonJFour residues of the extracellular N-terminal domain of the NR2A subunit control high-affinity Zn 2+ binding to NMDA receptorsNeuron20002536839410.1016/S0896-6273(00)81070-3<?supplied-pmid 10774735?>10774735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>52.GielenMRetchlessBSMonyLJohnsonJWPaolettiPMechanism of differential control of NMDA receptor activity by NR2 subunitsNature20094597247703710.1038/nature07993<?supplied-pmid 19404260?>19404260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>53.PaolettiPMolecular basis of NMDA receptor functional diversityEur J Neurosci201133813516510.1111/j.1460-9568.2011.07628.x<?supplied-pmid 21395862?>21395862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>54.De LoofHRosseneuMBrasseurRRuysschaertJMUse of hydrophobicity profiles to predict receptor binding domains on apolipoprotein E and the low density lipoprotein apolipoprotein BE receptorProc Natl Acad Sci19868382295910.1073/pnas.83.8.2295<?supplied-pmid 3458195?>3458195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>55.CarlsonSLKempsellATFieberLAPharmacological evidence that D-aspartate activates a current distinct from ionotropic glutamate receptor currents in Aplysia californicaBrain Behav20122439140110.1002/brb3.60<?supplied-pmid 22950043?>22950043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>56.TengHCaiWZhouLZhangJLiuQWangYDaiWZhaoMSunZEvolutionary mode and functional divergence of vertebrate NMDA receptor subunit 2 genesPLoS One2010510e1334210.1371/journal.pone.0013342<?supplied-pmid 20976280?>20976280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>57.Ohno S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Evolution by gene duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Springer Science &amp; Business Media, New York; 1970. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>58.ForceALynchMPickettFBAmoresAYanY-lPostlethwaitJPreservation of duplicate genes by complementary, degenerative mutationsGenetics19991514153145<?supplied-pmid 10101175?>10101175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>59.SternPBehePSchoepferRColquhounDSingle-channel conductances of NMDA receptors expressed from cloned cDNAs: comparison with native receptorsProc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci19922501329271710.1098/rspb.1992.0159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>60.Cull-CandySGLeszkiewiczDNRole of distinct NMDA receptor subtypes at central synapsesSci STKE20042004255re16<?supplied-pmid 15494561?>15494561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>61.RumbaughGPrybylowskiKWangJFViciniSExon 5 and spermine regulate deactivation of NMDA receptor subtypesJ Neurophysiol200083313006<?supplied-pmid 10712457?>10712457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>62.HuntDLCastilloPESynaptic plasticity of NMDA receptors: mechanisms and functional implicationsCurr Opin Neurobiol201222349650810.1016/j.conb.2012.01.007<?supplied-pmid 22325859?>22325859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>63.MüßigLRichlitzkiARößlerREisenhardtDMenzelRLeboulleGAcute disruption of the NMDA receptor subunit NR1 in the honeybee brain selectively impairs memory formationJ Neurosci2010302378172510.1523/JNEUROSCI.5543-09.2010<?supplied-pmid 20534830?>20534830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>64.Esdin J, Pearce K, Glanzman DL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Long-term habituation of the gill-withdrawal reflex in aplysia requires gene transcription, calcineurin and L-type voltage-gated calcium channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Front Behav Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>2010;4:109-17. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>65.LiQRobertsACGlanzmanDLSynaptic facilitation and behavioral dishabituation in Aplysia: dependence on release of Ca2+ from postsynaptic intracellular stores, postsynaptic exocytosis, and modulation of postsynaptic AMPA receptor efficacyJ Neurosci2005252356233710.1523/JNEUROSCI.5305-04.2005<?supplied-pmid 15944390?>15944390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>66.ChitwoodRALiQGlanzmanDLSerotonin facilitates AMPA‐type responses in isolated siphon motor neurons of Aplysia in cultureJ Physiol200153425011010.1111/j.1469-7793.2001.00501.x<?supplied-pmid 11454967?>11454967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>67.SandersonDJGoodMASeeburgPHSprengelRRawlinsJNPBannermanDMThe role of the GluR-A (GluR1) AMPA receptor subunit in learning and memoryProg Brain Res20081691597810.1016/S0079-6123(07)00009-X<?supplied-pmid 18394473?>18394473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>68.ZamanilloDSprengelRHvalbyØJensenVBurnashevNRozovAKaiserKMKösterHJBorchardtTWorleyPImportance of AMPA receptors for hippocampal synaptic plasticity but not for spatial learningScience1999284542118051110.1126/science.284.5421.1805<?supplied-pmid 10364547?>10364547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>69.SongIHuganirRLRegulation of AMPA receptors during synaptic plasticityTrends Neurosci200225115788810.1016/S0166-2236(02)02270-1<?supplied-pmid 12392933?>12392933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>70.ContractorASwansonGTSailerAO’GormanSHeinemannSFIdentification of the kainate receptor subunits underlying modulation of excitatory synaptic transmission in the CA3 region of the hippocampusJ Neurosci20002022826978<?supplied-pmid 11069933?>11069933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>71.GoebelDJPooschMSNMDA receptor subunit gene expression in the rat brain: a quantitative analysis of endogenous mRNA levels of NR1 com, NR2A, NR2B, NR2C, NR2D and NR3AMol Brain Res19996921647010.1016/S0169-328X(99)00100-X<?supplied-pmid 10366738?>10366738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>72.WaltersEByrneJCarewTKandelEMechanoafferent Neurons Innervating Tail of A ~ lysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Response Properties and Synaptic Connections1983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>73.WaltersETByrneJCarewTKandelEMechanoafferent neurons innervating tail of Aplysia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Modulation by sensitizing stimulationJ Neurophysiol1983506154359<?supplied-pmid 6663342?>6663342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>74.KempsellATFieberLABehavioral aging is associated with reduced sensory neuron excitability in Aplysia californicaFront Aging Neurosci201468410.3389/fnagi.2014.00084<?supplied-pmid 24847260?>24847260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>75.CarlsonSLFieberLAPhysiological evidence that D-aspartate activates a current distinct from ionotropic glutamate receptor currents in Aplysia californica neuronsJ Neurophysiol2011106416293610.1152/jn.00403.2011<?supplied-pmid 21753031?>21753031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>76.AkazawaCShigemotoRBesshoYNakanishiSMizunoNDifferential expression of five N‐methyl‐D‐aspartate receptor subunit mRNAs in the cerebellum of developing and adult ratsJ Comp Neurol199434711506010.1002/cne.903470112<?supplied-pmid 7798379?>7798379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>77.MansourMNagarajanNNehringRBClementsJDRosenmundCHeteromeric AMPA receptors assemble with a preferred subunit stoichiometry and spatial arrangementNeuron20013258415310.1016/S0896-6273(01)00520-7<?supplied-pmid 11738030?>11738030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>78.MorozLLKocotKMCitarellaMRDosungSNorekianTPPovolotskayaISGrigorenkoAPDaileyCBerezikovEBuckleyKMThe ctenophore genome and the evolutionary origins of neural systemsNature201451075031091410.1038/nature13400<?supplied-pmid 24847885?>24847885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>79.RyanJFPangKSchnitzlerCENguyenA-DMorelandRTSimmonsDKKochBJFrancisWRHavlakPSmithSAThe genome of the ctenophore Mnemiopsis leidyi and its implications for cell type evolutionScience20133426164124259210.1126/science.1242592<?supplied-pmid 24337300?>24337300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>80.SayersEWBarrettTBensonDABoltonEBryantSHCaneseKChetverninVChurchDMDiCuccioMFederhenSDatabase resources of the national center for biotechnology informationNucleic Acids Res201139suppl 1D385110.1093/nar/gkq1172<?supplied-pmid 21097890?>21097890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
