<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5078810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep35816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep35816</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Responses of the summer Asian-Pacific zonal thermal contrast and the associated evolution of atmospheric circulation to transient orbital changes during the Holocene </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Xiuji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>State Key Laboratory of Severe Weather, Chinese Academy of Meteorological Sciences</institution>, Beijing 100081, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Institute of Climate Systems, Chinese Academy of Meteorological Sciences</institution>, Beijing 100081, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Collaborative Innovation Center on Forecast and Evaluation of Meteorological Disasters, Nanjing University of Information Science and Technology</institution>, Nanjing, 210044, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>State Key Laboratory of Marine Geology, Tongji University</institution>, Shanghai, 200092, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>zhaoping@camscma.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>35816</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>This study investigates the response of large-scale atmospheric circulation over the Asian-Pacific sector and precipitation over eastern China to transient orbital changes during the Holocene summer using an intermediate-complexity climate model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Corresponding to variations in the incoming solar radiation, the eddy sea level pressure (SLP) exhibited an out-of-phase relationship between the North Pacific and the Eurasian landmass that was similar to the present-day Asia-Pacific Oscillation (APO) pattern and was defined as the paleo-APO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Its index presented an increasing trend, which implies the enhancement of a zonal thermal contrast between Asia and the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Associated with the strengthening of the paleo-APO was the westward shift in North Pacific high pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, there was less/more summer precipitation over both the middle reach of the Yangtze River and Southwest China/over North China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The high-resolution stalagmite δ18O records further support this decrease in the model precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Along with the strengthening of paleo-APO from the early Holocene to the present, the eddy SLP anomalies exhibited a decreasing/increasing trend over the Eurasian landmass/the North Pacific, with a phase change of approximately 4.5 ka BP, and they both moved westward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, a less rainfall belt over eastern China exhibited northward propagation from southern China. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The East Asian summer monsoon (EASM) is an important component of global climate systems and plays significant roles in global energy and hydrological cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is viewed as the life blood providing the key precipitation for agriculture1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>However, some extreme variations in the EASM also cause harmful drought and flooding events2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In particular, under recent global warming, the EASM experienced a weakening trend, with severe droughts over northern China and disastrous floods over the Yangtze River valley3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, understanding the natural variability of EASM and predicting its long-term changes in a warming climate are helpful for disaster mitigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The Holocene is another significant warming period that occurred since the last glacial period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Studies of EASM during the Holocene may help us understand the mechanisms responsible for the natural variability of EASM under a warming scenario, which has been of increasing interest during the past decade456789101112. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Some studies of high-resolution and precisely dated contemporaneous speleothem δ18O records from caves have indicated a long-term downward trend of the EASM precipitation during the Holocene1314. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This trend may be a response to the decreasing solar insolation over the Northern Hemisphere (NH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, the associated mechanisms remain unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In the summer, a remarkable tropospheric zonal thermal contrast arises between the warmer Eurasian continent and the cooler North Pacific or Indian Ocean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Some in-depth studies have explored the variations in the thermal contrast and their links with EASM and precipitation on multiple time scales315161718. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Recently, a large-scale summertime teleconnection pattern of the tropospheric temperature over the extratropical NH, with opposite anomalous centers between Asia and the North Pacific, was proposed as the Asian-Pacific Oscillation (APO)19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A higher (lower) APO index often represents a stronger (weaker) thermal contrast between the Eurasian continent and the North Pacific Ocean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The APO index also sufficiently represents the long-term changes in the EASM rainfall over the past century20 and millennium21222324. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Climate models have been widely used to improve our understanding of the mechanisms of Holocene climate changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In particular, the first, second and third phases of the Paleoclimate Modeling Inter-comparison Project (PMIP1, PIMP2, and PIMP3) focused on the Mid-Holocene, 6 ka before the present (ka BP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Some equilibrium simulations (viz., “snapshot”) were applied to compare the characteristics and mechanisms of climate change over China between the Mid-Holocene and the present, in which the concentration of atmospheric CO2 was held at 280 ppm252627282930. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Zhou and Zhao31 examined the APO variation and associated summer precipitation anomalies using the CCSM3 simulation in PIMP2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Their results presented a pattern of northwest-southeast inclination in the Mid-Holocene, which mainly results from the incoming solar radiation differences caused by changes in the orbital parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, to understand climatic evolutions over the entire Holocene period, some transient simulations under the forcing of orbital changes were also performed with different complexity climate models and accelerated schemes323334353637383940. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Although climate simulations for the Holocene have made great progress, a number of questions remain unanswered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="?"><plain>For example, how do large-scale circulations respond to the NH decreasing incoming solar radiation during the Holocene summer? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="?"><plain>Does this response cause a significant difference between land and ocean? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="?"><plain>If so, how do they affect the EASM hydrological climate? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="?"><plain>What are the evolving characteristics of atmospheric circulation in the Holocene? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>With these questions in mind, we use an intermediate-complexity climate model to perform a transient simulation with an acceleration factor of 10 years, under the orbital changes during the past 10 ka BP, and investigate an APO-like large-scale teleconnection over the Asian-Pacific sector and the associated rainfall anomalies over eastern China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, some simulated results are compared with the proxy data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The UVic Model, data, and methods are introduced in the next section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In the result section, the responses of large-scale circulations to orbital changes are analyzed and compared with proxies; and the EASM circulation and hydrological climate evolutions associated with the APO-like large-scale teleconnection during the Holocene are investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A summary and a further discussion are provided in the last section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Model, Experiment, Forcing, Data and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Model and transient experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The UVic Model (version 2.9) developed by the University of Victoria, Canada couples the atmospheric, oceanic, sea ice, and land surface model components, and it has a resolution of 3.6° × 1.8° in longitude and latitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The atmospheric model comprises a single layer (that is, a vertically integrated energy-moisture balance model). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The ocean component comes from version 2.2 of the GFDL Modular Ocean Model, with 19-vertical levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The land surface model employs the MOSES (Met Office Surface Exchange Scheme) model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The UVic Model is often used as a tool for understanding the physical process and feedback in the climate system on long timescales, and is widely used in paleoclimate, present climate, and future climate studies4142434445. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This model could reasonably reproduce temperature, precipitation, and ocean circulation, with relatively small errors, even compared with the coupled General Circulation Model (GCM)42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>However, the internal high-frequency variations of almost all of the variables on interannual and interdecadal timescales in the UVic Model are weaker compared with those of the complex atmospheric models46. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the UVic Model is mainly used to investigate the climate processes and feedback on long timescales42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In this study, we also perform five experiments with different initial fields to test the uncertainty of the model results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>An ensemble mean of variables is used, and the spreads of the time series from the ensemble mean are identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Because of limited computer capabilities, simulations with acceleration factors between 10 and 100 have been applied to long-term climate studies, and they yield similar results47. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In the present study, following Kutzbach et al.35, we begin with orbital parameters at 10 ka BP, and they are advanced by 10 years at the end of each model year (that is, with an acceleration factor of 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The UVic model is spun up for two thousand years before the acceleration and is then integrated for 1001 model years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Sea level air temperature (SLAT), sea level pressure (SLP), and precipitation are used to analyze the climatic variations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>According to the UVic Model, we calculate SLP from the output of SLAT (Ts) as follows42: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>where R is the gas constant of dry air (287 J kg−1 K−1); ρ is the air density; and ρ = a + bTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>This relationship between ρ and Ts has been demonstrated as reasonable by the atmospheric reanalysis data of both the National Centers for Environmental Prediction-National Centers for Atmospheric Research (NCEP-NCAR) and the European Centre for Medium-range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF)42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In this study, we calculate a and b using the air temperature and SLP of the 1981–2010 NCEP-NCAR reanalysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Transient Orbital Forcing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Due to the precession effect, the incoming solar radiation is redistributed over months of a year during the past 10 ka. Figure 1a shows the month-year cross section of the transient incoming solar radiation along 30°N that is used in this study4849. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The incoming solar radiation exhibits a decreasing trend in the warm season (May-August), with a maximum variation exceeding 32.5 W·m−2, an increasing trend in the cold season (October-March), with a maximum variation exceeding 27.5 W·m−2, and an increase (decrease) before 5 ka and a subsequent decrease (increase) in September (April). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The summer incoming solar radiation from June to August along the 30°N (Fig. 1b) presents an obvious declining trend, ranging from 491 to 462 W·m−2 during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A previous study indicated that the application of different calendars in the paleoclimate simulation could induce artificial phase shifts in solar insolation forcing and climatic responses50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Such a “calendar effect” in each month due to the precession might be modified by the fixed angular calendar according to Chen et al.51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focus on the variation in summer (June, July and August, JJA) atmospheric circulation after the above modification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Proxy and Reanalysis Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the simulated SLAT/sea surface temperature (SST) over the Eurasian continent/the North Pacific (a key region of SLAT/SST anomalies associated with orbital forcing), we employ the oxygen isotope record from the Guliya ice cap (at 81.5°E, 35.2°N) of western China525354 and the reconstructed northern California SST (at 124.9°W, 41.7°N) over the North Pacific5556, which have the ability to indicate summer conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Their locations are shown in Fig. 2b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The Guliya temperature proxy over the past 130 ka, drilled from the Guliya ice cap, is recorded as a fluctuation in the concentration of oxygen 18 (δ18O) (hereinafter Guliya δ18O record) in a unit of Vienna Pee Dee Belemnite (VPDB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The monthly concentration of δ18O in Guliya is shown to be highly related to the local monthly surface air temperature57. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Further studies disclosed that the Guliya δ18O record could indicate summer temperatures over the Tibetan Plateau during the past 130 ka4458. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The Northern California SST was reconstructed from the alkenone in the Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Site 1019 (ODP 1019), with a water depth of 980 m55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Generally speaking, the alkenone SST of ODP 1019 represents the annual mean SST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Because the annual mean SST over the region 110°W–120°W, 35°N–45°N in the present-day climate is highly related to the local June–July SST, with a correlation coefficient of 0.82 during 1981–2010 (exceeding the 99.9% confidence level), the annual mean SST over the eastern North Pacific might be used to indicate the equivalent variation in the local June-July averaged SST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the annual mean SST is correlated with the summer North Pacific mean SLP over the region 120°W–180°, 15–60°N, with a correlation coefficient of −0.39 (exceeding the 95% confidence level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This correlation is higher than that between the annual mean SST and the winter North Pacific SLP (−0.25, not significant at the 95% confidence level), which suggests that the annual mean SST over the eastern North Pacific could better indicate the summer North Pacific SLP instead of the winter one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we employ the alkenone SST of ODP 1019 to indicate the summer (June–July) SST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The ODP sites 1014 and 1016, adjacent to the ODP 1019, could indicate the variation of SLP over the North Pacific and their reconstructed SSTs show a similar low-frequency SST variation59. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>It is concluded that the ODP 1019 SST may also represent the variability in the North Pacific high pressure like the ODP sites 1014 and 1016 SST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Due to a low resolution of the reconstructed SSTs in the ODP sites 1014 and 1016 during the Holocene, we use the reconstructed northern California SST in the ODP 1019 for evaluating the simulated SST over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we also use the reconstructed July temperatures with high temporal resolutions over the middle-west part of North America60 and Western Europe (68°22′N, 18°42′E)61 (shown in Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>S1a,b) to further examine the capability of the model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the variation in the model summer precipitation over eastern China, five high-resolution speleothem δ18O records at Dongge Cave (108.08°E, 25.28°N)61, Lianhua Cave (109.53°E, 29.48°N)6, Sanbao Cave (110.43°E, 31.67°N)7, Heshang Cave (110.42°E, 30.45°N)9, and Jiuxian Cave (109.1°E, 30.57°N)5, released on a website from the World Data Center for Paleoclimatology, are employed to compare with the simulated summer precipitation during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>These records were derived from karst caves in the middle reach of the Yangtze River, one of the key regions of EASM where the Meiyu rain belt appears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have argued that the signal of the oxygen isotope composition (δ18O) in speleothem represents precipitation variations63646566. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Caley et al.67 proposed that the speleothem δ18O in South Asia represents a change in hydrology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Their results suggested that the calcite δ18O signal of South Asian speleothem is mainly, but not entirely, controlled by δ18O in precipitation changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, δ18O in precipitation over South Asia is correlated to the northern tropical Indian Ocean which is one of the important moisture sources of East Asian monsoon precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the East Asian speleothem δ18O may relate to the ratio of moisture from the Bay of Bengal (BOB) and the Northwest Pacific68. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In a modern climate, precipitation over eastern China is highly correlated with moisture over the BOB and the Northwest Pacific; that is, a change of δ18O in precipitation is the most important factor affecting the variation of the speleothem δ18O records in eastern China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we use these records as a hydrologic factor and compare them with the most important hydrological factors such as precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we also use monthly mean air temperature and SLP of the NCEP-NCAR reanalysis69 with a horizontal resolution of 2.5° and the monthly Hadley SST with 1° in both longitude and latitude70. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Statistical Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Regression and correlation analyses are used to investigate the relationship between two variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>An Empirical Orthogonal Function (EOF) analysis with area-weighting is employed to examine the leading mode of the eddy SLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A composite analysis between the higher and lower indices is used to analyze variations in a variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The confidence tests in this study are all based on a Student’s t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Response of eddy SLP over the Asian-Pacific sector to incoming solar insolation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Figure 2a shows the regressed model summer eddy SLP () against the incoming solar radiation along 30°N, in which the  is defined as the difference of SLP from the global zonal mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The  anomaly pattern associated with incoming solar radiation presents a zonal dipole, with positive anomalies over Europe, Asia and North Africa and negative anomalies over the North Pacific Ocean and North America, which indicate a large-scale out-of-phase relationship between Eurasia and the extratropical North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The maximum positive center is 8 Pa/W·m−2, larger compared with the absolute value of the negative center (−5 Pa/W·m−2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that when the  over the East Hemisphere landmass is higher (lower), it is lower (higher) over the North Pacific Ocean and the North America landmass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the decrease in the incoming solar radiation is associated with both a decrease of the  over Eurasia and North Africa and an increase over the North Pacific and North America, which corresponds to a strong thermal contrast between the Eurasian-North African region and the North Pacific-North American region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In fact, the out-of-phase relationship presented in Fig. 2a is also a major feature of  variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The EOF analysis on the summer eddy SLP shows that the leading EOF mode (Fig. 2b) of the eddy SLP, accounting for 98.2% of the total variance, depicts a zonal out-of-phase structure with negative anomalies over the Eurasian and North African landmass and positive anomalies over the North Pacific, similar to those shown in Fig. 2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The spatial correlation coefficient between the regressed field (in Fig. 2a) and the leading EOF mode (Fig. 2b) is 0.99 (significant at the 99.9% confidence level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 2c, a decreasing trend of the incoming solar radiation is corresponded to an increasing trend in the PC1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that the summer  over Eurasia/the North Pacific and North America decreases/increases in the Holocene, which may lead to an anomalous zonal contrast of the  between the Eurasian landmass and the North Pacific Ocean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the anomalous pattern of the  during the Holocene is closely associated with the orbital forcing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>To examine the reliability of the simulation, referring to some key regions of the anomalous centers in Fig. 2b, we select reconstructions of the Guliya record and the northern California SST at the ODP 1019. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The reconstructed northern California SST displays a low frequent variation, with a decreasing trend from 10 ka to 6.4 ka BP and an increasing trend during the period from 6.4 ka BP to the present (Fig. 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A high frequent variation on the century-to-millennium scales is superposed over this low frequent variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The simulated June–July averaged Northeast Pacific SST also indicates a decrease during the epoch 10–5 ka BP and then an increase from 5 ka BP to the present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The spread of the ensemble mean June–July Northeast Pacific SST varies within small fluctuation, approximately from 0.05 in the early Holocene to 0.02 °C in the middle and late Holocene, which indicates a small uncertainty in the simulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>It is evident that the simulated and reconstructed SSTs over the Northeast Pacific show similar lower frequency variations during the Holocene. Figure 3b displays the curves of the simulated summer Guliya SLAT and the Guliya δ18O record during the past 10 ka. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The Guliya δ18O record, indicating a summer temperature over the Tibetan Plateau, presents a decrease during the period of 10–4.5 ka BP and an increase from 4.5 ka BP to the present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The simulated summer temperature over the Guliya region also shows a similar lower-frequency variation, with a decrease during 10–4.5 ka BP and an increase from 4.5 ka BP to the present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Uncertainties in the ensemble simulations of the Guliya temperature show little spread, which thereby supports a more stable simulation of the UVic Model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Thus, the simulated Guliya SLAT reproduces well the lower-frequency variation of the Guliya δ18O record (namely, the summer temperature variation over the Tibet Plateau). Figure S1 shows the simulated and reconstructed July temperatures over the mid-western part of the United States and Western Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The simulated July SLAT over the mid-western part of the United States presents a declining trend during the Holocene, which also appears in the reconstructed time series (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>S1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the July temperature variation over the mid-western part of the United States is similar to that of the North Pacific center of the paleo-APO pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the reconstructed July temperature over Western Europe also supports the model simulation on the long-time scales (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>S1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The consistency suggests the reliability of the simulated results over Eurasia and the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that differences in SLP between Asia and the North Pacific may be used to indicate the contrasts in surface air temperature between these two regions15161718. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In fact, the anomalous patterns shown in both Fig. 2a,b are similar to the eddy SLP anomalies associated with APO in the present-day climate (during 1948–2014), in which the APO is a leading mode of the tropospheric eddy temperature and its index is defined as the reference19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In the present day (Fig. 4), negative/positive anomalies of SLP appear over North Africa and Asia/the North Pacific and North America, which indicate weaker than normal Asian landmass low pressure and stronger than normal North Pacific high pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the anomalous pattern of SLP in the UVic Model (shown in Fig. 2a,b) is called the paleo-APO pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Referring to the positions of positive and negative SLP anomalies in Fig. 2a,b, we define the paleo-APO index as a difference in the simulated normalized  between the North Pacific (150°E–110°W, 15°–60°N) and the Eurasian landmass (10°–110°E, 15°–60°N). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The summer paleo-APO index shows an increasing trend, similar to the variability of PC1 (Fig. 5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that the paleo-APO index may reasonably indicate a variation in the leading mode of the eddy SLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the summer solar radiation insolation along 30°N (Fig. 1b) changes from the top to the valley. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Thus, when the NH summer incoming solar radiation decreases during the Holocene, the surface thermal contrast between Eurasia and the North Pacific increases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Figure 5b shows the climatological anomalies of the  over Eurasia and the North Pacific during the summer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The Eurasian  varies from −0.5 hPa to 0.75 hPa and the North Pacific  changes from 0.6 hPa to −1 hPa, which indicates a larger varying range over Eurasia (1.6 hPa) than over the North Pacific (1.25 hPa) and also suggests a larger response of the eddy SLP over Eurasia compared with that over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the  shows a decreasing trend over Eurasia and an increasing trend over the North Pacific during the Holocene, which also leads to an increased trend of the paleo-APO index during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Compared to the North Pacific, therefore, the land response to the orbital forcing possibly plays a more important role in modulating the zonal thermal contrast between Eurasia and the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Figure 6a depicts the composite summer model SLP in the higher and lower paleo-APO indices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The North Pacific high pressure has the central values of 1020 hPa in the higher and lower paleo-APO years, but exhibits a larger domain in the higher paleo-APO years than in the lower paleo-APO years, which suggests a stronger North Pacific high pressure in the higher paleo-APO phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The western boundary of the North Pacific high pressure in the higher paleo-APO phase moves westward along 115°E compared with the lower paleo-APO phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>That is, the increasing (decreasing) trend of the over the North Pacific (Eurasia) implies a stronger and more westward high pressure over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The analyses presented here show that the response of the eddy SLP to orbital forcing displays an APO-like pattern, with positive and negative anomalies of the  in the North Pacific and Eurasia, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Corresponding to the NH’s summer reduced incoming solar radiation during the Holocene, the paleo-APO index shows an increasing trend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The response of the Eurasian landmass plays a more important role due to a (an) decreasing (increasing) trend of the  over Eurasia (the North Pacific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the increasing trend of the  over the North Pacific indicates a stronger and more westward high pressure over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Summer hydrology anomalies over eastern China associated with the paleo-APO at the precession </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Many studies on the present-day climate have shown that the thermal contrasts between the East Asian landmass and its adjacent oceans exerts a strong influence on the hydrological climate in the EASM region and that a strong and westward high pressure over the North Pacific could strengthen the northward transport of water vapor over the EASM region, with more rainfall over North China and less rainfall over the Yangtze River valleys315197172. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>When the paleo-APO index is high, the domain (central intensity) of the North Pacific high pressure is larger (stronger) compared with that in the low paleo-APO index, and the western part of the North Pacific high pressure moves westward (Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>This variation in the North Pacific high pressure favors transport of water moisture toward northern China73. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>As a result, precipitation is often less over the Yangtze River. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>At the precession, the variability of thermal contrasts indicated by the paleo-APO index is also associated with precipitation over eastern China. Figure 6b shows the summer rainfall anomalies over eastern China that are associated with the paleo-APO index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In this figure, the rainfall anomalies present a meridional “positive-negative-positive” anomalous pattern, with negative anomalies along the Yangtze River and over Southwest China and positive rainfall anomalies over North China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>This anomalous pattern is also a major feature of the leading EOF mode of summer rainfall over eastern China during the Holocene (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have suggested that the speleothem δ18O records in eastern China represent the changes in the hydrological climate and are mainly a result of the δ18O changes in precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Hence, we compare the simulated rainfall with five speleothem δ18O records over Southwest China and the middle valley of the Yangtze River (100°–112°E, 22°–32°N), one key region of the EASM precipitation and an important path of moisture transport from the Indian Ocean (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The speleothem δ18O record at Dongge Cave (Fig. 7a) has generally shown a decreasing trend before a slight increase trend since 3.5 ka BP, which indicates the declining precipitation and the obvious decadal- and century-scale fluctuations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the speleothem δ18O records at Lianhua Cave (Fig. 7b), Sanbao Cave (Fig. 7c), Heshang Cave (Fig. 7d), and Jiuxian Cave (Fig. 7e) also exhibit a downward trend during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The simulated summer precipitation similarly presents a decreasing trend before 4 ka and an increasing trend afterwards, indicating wetter conditions in the lower paleo-APO years and drier conditions in the higher paleo-APO years, similar to the variation in the speleothem δ18O records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>This result further supports the reliability of the simulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Atmospheric circulation anomalies associated with the paleo-APO evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In this analysis, we use transient simulation to examine the evolution of the paleo-APO and associated atmospheric circulation and precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It is seen in Fig. 5a that the paleo-APO index exhibits an increasing trend in approximately half of the precession period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>According to the paleo-APO index, we chose 9.0, 6.5, 4.8, 2.5, and 0 ka BP to analyze the evolution of atmospheric circulation. Figure 8 shows the summer eddy SLP anomalies (from the climatological mean) at 9.0, 6.5, 4.8, 2.5 and 0 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>At 9 ka BP (Fig. 8a), there are negative SLP anomalies over the North Pacific, with a maximum negative value of −0.8 hPa, and there are positive SLP anomalies over Eurasia, with a maximum value of 1.5 hPa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>These features suggest a stronger negative phase of the paleo-APO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>At 6.5 ka BP (Fig. 8b), the eddy SLP anomalies depict a similar pattern to that at 9 ka BP, with relatively lower SLP anomalies over both Eurasia and the North Pacific, indicating a moderate negative phase of the paleo-APO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>At 4.8 ka BP (Fig. 8c), small positive eddy anomalies move from Eurasia to West Europe, North Africa, North America, and the tropical eastern Pacific, whereas the other regions are covered by small negative anomalies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This distribution of the eddy SLP anomalies suggests a very weak paleo-APO phase at 4.8 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The eddy SLP anomalies indicate a moderate positive phase of the paleo-APO at 2.5 ka BP (Fig. 8d), which is opposite to the value at 6.5 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>At the present day (Fig. 8e), the paleo-APO further intensifies, with larger anomalies over the North Pacific-North Atlantic region and Eurasia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Thus, the paleo-APO changes from a negative phase to a positive one during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Figure 9 shows the evolution of the eddy SLP anomalies along 30°N during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>There is an anomalous SLP center at the longitudes 30°W–120°E during 10–5.5 ka, with a maximum positive value of 1 hPa along 50°E at 9 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>As time goes on, the positive anomalies of the eddy SLP decrease and turn to the negative ones after 5.5 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The strongest negative anomalies appear along 40°E at the present day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Over the North African and Asian landmasses along 30°N, the anomalous SLP center moves slightly westward during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>During the period 10–5 ka, negative SLP anomalies appears over the longitudes 120°E–30°W, with a center of −0.6 hPa along 140°W–180° and a relatively weak center along 60°W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the negative SLP anomalies decrease, turn to positive values, and reach the present-day largest values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The negative center at 150°W at 10 ka BP turns to a positive one at 170°E at the present day, which suggests a westward shift of SLP anomalies over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>However, no obvious shift in SLP anomalies is seen over the North Atlantic during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>We also display the time-latitude cross section of summer mean precipitation anomalies (from the climatological mean) over eastern China along 110°E (Fig. 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>At 10 ka BP, there is a meridional dipole pattern of rainfall anomalies, with positive anomalies south of 36°N and negative anomalies at higher latitudes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, the positive and negative anomalies gradually weaken and turn to negative and positive values, respectively, in which negative rainfall anomalies from southern China show a northward propagation to 36°N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>An opposite dipole appears between 5.5 ka BP and 2.5 ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>After that, a triple pattern appears over eastern China, with positive precipitation anomalies south of 30°N and north of 36°N and negative precipitation anomalies near the Yangtze River. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that when the paleo-APO pattern moves from a negative phase to a positive one during the Holocene, the rainfall belt exhibits a northward propagation from southern China. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS,CONCL"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Summary and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We employed the intermediate-complexity UVic Model to investigate the response of summer large-scale circulation over Eurasia and the North Pacific and the associated precipitation anomalies over eastern China to the transient orbit forcing during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>A decrease in the NH summer incoming solar radiation is corresponded to an out-of-phase relationship of the summer eddy SLP over the Asian-Pacific region, with positive anomalies over the Asia-Europe-African continent and negative anomalies over the North Pacific and North America, which reflect the leading mode of the eddy SLP during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This anomalous pattern is similar to that associated with the present-day APO, called the paleo-APO. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The paleo-APO index exhibits an upward trend during the Holocene, which indicates an increase in the zonal thermal contrast between the North Pacific and Eurasia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Such a trend is possibly due to a decrease in the  over the Eurasian landmass and an increase in the over the North Pacific, and there is a larger varying range over Eurasia than over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that the response of atmospheric circulation over the Eurasian landmass to orbital forcing is larger than that over the North Pacific, possibly playing a more important role in modulating the zonal thermal contrast between Eurasia and the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A higher paleo-APO index during the Holocene is corresponded to a stronger high-pressure system over the North Pacific that moves more westward, which favors the northward transport of water vapor toward northern China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, there is more precipitation over northern China and less rainfall over the middle and lower reaches of the Yangtze River during the summer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This decrease in the simulated precipitation over the middle and lower reaches of the Yangtze River is supported by the local speleothem proxy data during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The paleo-APO experiences a half-precession cycle during the Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>During the early Holocene, the paleo-APO pattern presents a negative phase with positive SLP anomalies over the Eurasian landmass and negative SLP anomalies over the North Pacific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>These positive (negative) anomalies over the Eurasian landmass (North Pacific and North Atlantic) decrease and turn into negative (positive) anomalies, which indicate a change in the paleo-APO pattern from a negative phase to a positive one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The negative centers over the North Africa-Asian region and the North Pacific move westward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the rainfall belt exhibits a northward propagation from southern China, and a meridional dipole pattern of rainfall anomalies during the early Holocene gradually turns into the present-day triple pattern. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Zhou74 evaluated the performance of 33 models of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) in simulating the summer APO, and projected its variation under warming climate scenarios (RCP4.5 and RCP8.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>His findings suggested that the intensity of APO under a warming climate is weaker than the present day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Similarly, with the reduced trend of incoming solar radiation in the Holocene summer, the paleo-APO index exhibits an increasing trend, which is also supported by Zhou’s results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The summer precipitation anomalies over eastern China associated with the APO were investigated using the reanalysis and gauge data19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The result exhibits more rainfall anomalies over northern China and less rainfall over the Yangtze River. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>This relationship between APO and summer precipitation over eastern China occurs not only during 1900–200920 and past 150 years71 but also throughout the past millennium2122232475. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Summer rainfall anomalies associated with the paleo-APO during the Holocene also exhibit a similar pattern, which implies that this relationship between APO and summer rainfall over eastern China also occurs on a longer precessional scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, variations in the paleo-APO and associated rainfall over eastern China also need more analyses using the General Circulation Model to better understand the underlying mechanisms and processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Ice-sheet changes are often considered as an important external forcing factor of climate change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>They experienced a rapid change in the early Holocene (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>S2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>At that time, the ice-sheet covered the northeast portion of North America (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>S2b) and exerted a strong influence on climate change by changing the surface albedo and the solar insolation76. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Some studies have shown that temperature anomalies caused by ice-sheet forcing represent planetary-scale waves in the extratropical northern hemispheric in winter and annual mean fields77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>However, summer temperature anomalies forced by ice sheets are confined in the northeastern part of North America and the northern part of the North Atlantic, which implies a small effect of the ice-sheet forcing on summer temperature over the extratropical Asian-Pacific sector77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In this study, we further examine the impacts of ice-sheets in the early Holocene on the paleo-APO pattern and its variability by performing a simulation under both orbital and ice-sheet forcings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that the leading mode of the summer eddy SLP under both orbital and ice-sheet forcings (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>S3a) are very similar to that under the orbital forcing alone except that the positive values over the northern part of the North Atlantic become larger compared to the ice-sheet forcing (Fig. 2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The PC of the leading mode (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>S3b) generally exhibits an increasing trend that is consistent with that in Fig. 2c, although with a weak fluctuation in the early Holocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Our simulation further supports that ice sheet changes in the early Holocene have a weak influence on the summer extratropical paleo-APO pattern. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Additional Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Xiao, D. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Responses of the summer Asian-Pacific zonal thermal contrast and the associated evolution of atmospheric circulation to transient orbital changes during the Holocene. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Rep. 6, 35816; doi: 10.1038/srep35816 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d33e53" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Special Foundation for National Science and Technology’s Major Project of China (2011FY120300) [Zhao], the Natural Scientific Foundation of China (41405078 [Xiao] and 91437218 [Zhao]) and the Basic Science Research and Operation Fund of Chinese Academy of Meteorological Sciences (2015Z001) [Xiao]. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>WangB. . Recent Change of the global monsoon precipitation (1979–2008). Clim Dyn. 1123–1135 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>WebsterP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>J. The coupled monsoon system. The Asian Monsoon, WangB. Ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Praxis Publishing Ltd, 3–66, (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>ZhaoP., YangS. &amp; YuR. Long-term changes in rainfall over Eastern China and large-scale atmospheric circulation associated with recent global warming. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Climate 23, 1544–1562 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>AnZ. . Asynchronous Holocene optimum of the East Asian monsoon. Quaternary Science Reviews 19, 743–762 (2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>CaiY. . The variation of summer monsoon precipitation in central China since the last deglaciation. Earth and Planetary Science Letters 291, 21–31 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>CosfordJ. . East Asian monsoon variability since the Mid-Holocene recorded in a high-resolution, absolute-dated aragonite speleothem from eastern China. Earth and Planetary Science Letters 275, 296–307 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>DongJ. . A high-resolution stalagmite record of the Holocene East Asian monsoon from Mt Shennongjia, central China. The Holocene 20, 257–264 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>DykoskiC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>A. . A high-resolution, absolute-dated Holocene and deglacial Asian monsoon record from Dongge Cave, China. Earth and Planetary Science Letters 233, 71–86 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>HuC. . Quantification of Holocene Asian monsoon rainfall from spatially separated cave records. Earth and Planetary Science Letters 266, 221–232 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>HuangJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>B. . The impacts of orbitial parameters on summer precipitation over China in the Holocene. Journal of Tropical Meteorology 17, 103–112 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>LohmannG. &amp; Workshop participants. Workshop on modeling Holocene climate evolution. Pages News 18, 89–90 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>ZhangJ. . Holocene monsoon climate documented by oxygen and carbon isotopes from lake sediments and peat bogs in China: a review and synthesis. Quaternary Science Reviews 30, 1973–1987 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>WangP., WangB. &amp; KieferT. Global monsoon in observations, simulations and geological records. Pages News 17, 82–83 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>WangS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>W. The Holocene Climate Change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Beijing, China: Meteoroolgical Press,, 283 p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>(2011) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>GuoQ. The summer monsoon intensity index in East Asia and its variation. Acta Geographica Sinca 38, 207–217 (1983). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>SunX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>R., ChenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>X. &amp; HeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>H. Interannual variation of index of East Asian land-sea thermal difference and its relation to monsoon circulation and rainfall over China. Acta Meteorologica Sinica 15, 71–85 (2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>SunY., DingY. &amp; DaiA. Changing links between South Asian summer monsoon circulation and tropospheric land-sea thermal contrasts under a warming scenario. Geophys Res Lett 37, L02704, doi: 10.1029/2009GL041662 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>ZhaoP. &amp; ZhouZ. East Asian subtropical summer monsoon index and its relationships to rainfall. Acta Meteorologica Sinica 63, 933–941 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>ZhaoP., ZhuY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>N. &amp; ZhangR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>H. An Asian-Pacific teleconnection in summer tropospheric temperature and associated Asian climate variability. Clim Dyn 29, 293–303 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>ZhaoP., YangS., WangH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; ZhangQ. Interdecadal relationships between the Asian-Pacific Oscillation and summer climate anomalies over Asia, North Pacific, and North America during a Recent 100 years. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Climate 24, 4793–4799 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>FangK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Y., DaviN. &amp; D’ArrigoR. A reconstruction of the Asia-Pacific Oscillation Index for the past 1500 years and its association with the Asian summer monsoon. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Climatol. 34, 2505–2514 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>TanL. . Climate patterns in north central China during the last 1800 yr and their possible driving force. Clim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Past 7, 685–692 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>XuH., HouS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>G. &amp; PangH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>X. Asian-Pacific Oscillation signal from a Qomolangma (Mount Everest) ice-core chemical record. Annals of Glaciology 55, 121–128 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>ZhouX., ZhaoP., LiuG. &amp; ZhouT. Characteristics of decadal-centennial-scale changes in East Asian summer monsoon circulation and precipitation during the Medieval Warm Period and Little Ice Age and in the present day. Chinese Science Bulletin 28, 3303–3311 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>JiangD., LangX., TianZ. &amp; WangT. Considerable Model–Data Mismatch in Temperature over China during the Mid-Holocene: Results of PMIP Simulations. Journal of Climate 25, 4135–4153 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>JiangD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; ZhangZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>S. Paleoclimate modelling at the Institute of Atmospheric Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences. Adv Atmos Sci 23, 1040–1049 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>WangH. The mid-Holocene climate simulated by a grid-point AGCM coupled with a biome model. Adv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Atmos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Sci. 19(2), 205–218 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>WangT., WangH. &amp; JiangD. Mid-Holocene East Asian summer climate as simulated by the PMIP2 models. Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology 288, 93–102 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>ZhengW., WuB., HeJ. &amp; YuY. The East Asian Summer Monsoon at mid-Holocene: results from PMIP3 simulations. Climate of the Past 9, 453–466 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>ZhengW. &amp; YuY. Paleoclimate simulations of the mid-Holocene and last glacial maximum by FGOALS. Advances in Atmospheric Sciences 30, 684–698 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>ZhouB. &amp; ZhaoP. Modeling variations of summer upper tropospheric temperature and associated climate over the Asian Pacific region during the mid-Holocene. Journal of Geophysical Research 115, D20109, doi: 10.1029/2010JD014029 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>BrovkinV. . Carbon cycle, vegetation, and climate dynamics in the Holocene: Experiments with the CLIMBER-2 model. Global Biogeochemical Cycles 16, 1139, doi: 10.1029/2001gb001662 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>CrucifixM. . Climate evolution during the Holocene: a study with an Earth system model of intermediate complexity. Clim Dyn. 19, 43–60 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>FischerN. &amp; JungclausJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>H. Evolution of the seasonal temperature cycle in a transient Holocene simulation: orbital forcing and sea-ice. Climate of the Past 7, 1139–1148 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>KutzbachJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>E., LiuX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>D. &amp; LiuZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Y. Simulation of the evolutionary response of global summer monsoons to orbital forcing over the past 280,000 years. Clim Dyn. 30, 567–579 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>RenssenH. . Simulating the Holocene climate evolution at northern high latitudes using a coupled atmosphere-sea ice-ocean-vegetation model. Climate Dynamics 24, 23–43 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SchmidtG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>A. . General circulation modelling of Holocene climate variability. Quaternary Science Reviews 23, 2167–2181 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>VarmaV. . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Transient Holocene experiments under orbital forcing using the comprehensive global climate model CCSM3 (Community Climate System Model 3) (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>YinQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Z. &amp; BergerA. Insolation and CO2 contribution to the interglacial climate before and after the Mid-Brunhes Event. Nature Geoscience 3, 243–246 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>YinQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Z. &amp; BergerA. Individual contribution of insolation and CO2 to the interglacial climates of the past 800,000 years. Climate Dynamics 38, 709–724 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>FykeJ. . A new coupled ice sheet/climate model: description and sensitivity to model physics under Eemian, Last Glacial Maximum, late Holocene and modern climate conditions. Geosci Model Dev Discuss 4, 117–136 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>WeaverA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>J. . The UVic Earth System Climate Model: Model description, climatology, and applications to past, present and future climates. Atmosphere-Ocean 39, 1–68 (2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>WeberS. . The modern and glacial overturning circulation in the Atlantic ocean in PMIP coupled model simulations. Climate of the Past 3, 51–64 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>XiaoD., ZhaoP., WangY. &amp; ZhouX. Modeling the climatic implications and indicative senses of the Guliya δ18O-temperature proxy record to the ocean-atmosphere system during the past 130 ka. Climate of the Past 9, 735–747, doi: 10.5194/cp-9-735-2013 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>XiaoD., ZhouX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; ZhaoP. Numerical simulation study of temperature change over East China in the past millennium. Sci China Earth Sci. 55, 1504–1517, doi: 10.1007/s11430-012-4422-3 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>ClaussenM. . Earth system models of intermediate complexity: Closing the gap in the spectrum of climate system models. Clim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Dyn. 18, 579–586 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>LorenzS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>J. &amp; LohmannG. Accelerated technique for Milankovitch type forcing in a coupled atmosphere-ocean circulation model: method and application for the Holocene. Clim Dyn. 23, 727–743 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>BergerA. Long-term variations in daily insolation and quaternary climate changes. J Atmos Sci 35, 2362–2367 (1978). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>BergerA., LoutreM.-F. &amp; TricotC. Insolation and Earth’s orbital periods. J Geophys Res. 98, 10341–10362 (1993). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>TimmO. . On the definition of seasons in paleoclimate simulations with orbital forcing. Paleoceanography 23, PA2221, doi: 10.1029/2007PA001461 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>ChenG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>S., KutzbachJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>E., GallimoreR. &amp; LiuZ. Calendar effect on phase study in paleoclimate transient simulation with orbital forcing. Clim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Dyn. 37, 1949–1960, doi: 10.1007/s00382-010-0944-6 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>YaoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>D. . Variations in temperature and precipitation in the past 2000 years on the Xizang (Tibet) Plateau–Guliya ice core record. Science in China (Series D) 26, 348–353 (1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>ThompsonL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>G. . Tropical climate instability: The last glacial cycles from a Qinghai Tibetan ice core. Science 276, 1821–1825 (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>YaoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>D. . Climate variation since the Last Interglaciation recorded in the Guliya ice core. Science in China (Series D) 40, 447–452 (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>BarronJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>A., HeusserL., HerbertT. &amp; LyleM. High-resolution climatic evolution of coastal northern California during the past 16,000 years. Paleoceanography 18, 1020, doi: 10.1029/2002PA000768 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>ChengH. . The Global Paleomonsoon as seen through speleothem records from Asia and the Americas. Climate Dynamics 39, 1045–1062 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>YaoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>D. . Climatological significance of δ18O in the north Tibetan ice cores. J Geophys Res. 101(D23), 29531–29537 (1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>XiaoD. . Millennial-scale phase relationship between North Atlantic deep-level temperature and Qinghai-Tibet Plateau temperature and its evolution since the Last Interglaciation. Chinese Science Bulletin 59, 75–81 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>YamamotoM., YamamuroM. &amp; TanakaY. The California current system during the last 136,000 years: response of the North Pacific High to precessional forcing. Quaternary Science Reviews 26, 405–414 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>ViauA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>E., GajewskiK., SawadaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; FinesP. Millennial-scale temperature variations in North America during the Holocene. Journal of Geophysical Research 111, D09102, doi: 10.1029/2005JD006031 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>LarocqueI. &amp; HallR. Holocene temperature estimates and chironomid community composition in the Abisko Valley, northern Sweden. Quaternary Science Reviews 23, 2453–2465, doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2004.04.006 (2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>WangY. The Holocene Asian Monsoon: Links to Solar Changes and North Atlantic Climate. Science 308, 854–857 (2005).15879216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>ClemensS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>C., PrellW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; SunY. Orbital-scale timing and mechanisms driving Late Pleistocene Indo-Asian summer monsoons: Reinterpreting cave speleothem δ18O. Paleoceanography 25, PA4207, doi: 10.1029/2010PA001926 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>LeeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>E. . Asian monsoon hydrometeorology from TES and SCIAMACHY water vapor isotope measurements and LMDZ simulations: Implications for speleothem climate record interpretation. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Geophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Res. 117, D15112, doi: 10.1029/2011JD017133 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>MaherB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>A. Holocene variability of the East Asian summer monsoon from Chinese cave records: a re-assessment source. the Holocene 18, 861–866 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>PausataF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>R., BattistiD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>S., NisanciogluK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>H. &amp; BitzC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>M. Chinese stalagmite δ18O controlled by changes in the Indian monsoon during a simulated Heinrich event. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Geosci. 4, 474–480 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>CaleyT., RocheD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; RenssenH. Orbital Asian summer monsoon dynamics revealed using an isotope-enabled global climate model. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Commun 5, 5371 doi: 10.1038/ ncomms6371 (2014).25373794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>NanS., TanM. &amp; ZhaoP. Evaluation of the ability of the Chinese stalagmite d18O to record the variation in atmospheric circulation during the second half of the 20th century. Clim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Past 10, 975–985 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>KalnayE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; Coauthors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>The NCEP/NCAR reanalysis project. Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Amer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Meteor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Soc. 77, 437–471 (1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>RaynerN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>A. . Global analyses of sea surface temperature, sea ice, and night marine air temperature since the late nineteenth century. Journal of Geophysical Research 108, D14, 4407, doi: 10.1029/2002JD002670 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>LiuG., ZhaoP. &amp; ChenJ. A 150-year reconstructed summer Asian-Pacific Oscillation index and its association with precipitation over eastern China. Theoretical &amp; Applied Climatology 103, 239–248 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>ZhaoP., WangB. &amp; ZhouX. Boreal summer continental monsoon rainfall and hydroclimate anomalies associated with the Asian-Pacific Oscillation. Clim Dyn, 1197–1207 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>ZhouT. . Why the Western Pacific Subtropical High Has Extended Westward since the Late 1970s. Journal of Climate 22, 2199–2215 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>ZhouB. The Asian–Pacific Oscillation pattern in CMIP5 simulations of historical and future climate. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Climatol. 35, doi: 10.1002/joc.4668 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>ZhouX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>J., ZhaoP. &amp; LiuG. Asian-Pacific Oscillation index and variation of East Asian summer monsoon over the past millennium. Chinese Sci Bull 54, 3768–3771 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>RenssenH. . Simulating the Holocene climate evolution at northern high latitudes using a coupled atmosphere-sea ice-ocean-vegetation model. Climate Dynamics 24, 23–43 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>ZhangY., RenssenH. &amp; SeppäH. Effects of melting ice sheets and orbital forcing on the early Holocene warming in the extratropical Northern Hemisphere. Clim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Past 12, 1119–1135, doi: 10.5194/cp-12-1119-2016 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions D.X. performed the numerical analysis and led the interpretation of the results and writing of the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>P.Z. conceived the idea and designed and revised the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Y.W. and X.Z. contributed to interpreting the results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(a) Annual cycles of the incoming solar radiation anomaly along 30°N relative to the climatological mean over the past 10 ka and (b) the summer incoming solar radiation along 30°N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>The abscissa is time before the present (1950 AD), and the ordinate in (a) is the month of the year. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>(a) Regressed eddy SLP (Unit: Pa/W·m−2) on the JJA incoming solar radiation along 30°N, in which values exceeding the 95% confidence level are plotted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>(b) Leading EOF mode of the eddy SLP, in which the green circle and square indicate the locations of the Guliya ice core and the ODP 1019, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>(c) The PC1 and JJA incoming solar radiation along 30°N during the past 10 ka BP, in which the gray shaded area represents the spread of the ensemble mean PC1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>These figures were generated by the Grid Analysis and Display System (GrADS) Version 2.0.1.oga.1 Copyright (c) 1988–2011 by Brian Doty and the Institute for Global Environment and Society (IGES) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/">ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(a) Reconstructed SST (unit: °C; green) at the ODP 1019 and simulated June-July SST (unit: °C; red) over the northeastern Pacific (110°W–120°W, 35°N–45°N), in which the gray shaded area represents the spread from the model ensemble mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>(b) Same as (a) but for the oxygen isotope record in the Guliya ice core (unit: VPDB; green) and the simulated summer SLAT (unit: °C; red) over 80°E–85°E, 33°N–38°N. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Regression of the eddy SLP (unit: hPa) on the APO index during 1948–2014.</title><p><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>The shaded areas are significant at 95% confidence levels and the green contours are zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>This figure is generated by the Grid Analysis and Display System (GrADS) Version 2.0.1.oga.1 Copyright (c) 1988–2011 by Brian Doty and the Institute for Global Environment and Society (IGES) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/">ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>(a) The paleo-APO index and PC1 in Fig. 2b and (b)  anomaly from climatological mean over the Eurasian continent and the North Pacific Ocean over the past 10 ka. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>(a) Composite SLP filed in the high (during the period 0.09–0 ka BP; orange) and low (during the period 10–9.91 ka BP; blue) paleo-APO index years, in which the contours of 1018 hPa are thickened to denote the domain of the North Pacific high pressure zone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(b) Regression of summer precipitation (unit: mm) over eastern China on the paleo-APO index, in which the locations of stalagmite proxy data at the Jiuxian Cave, Sanbao Cave, Heshang Cave Dongge Cave, and Lianhua Cave are also given and values exceeding significance at the 95% confidence level are plotted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>This figure is generated by the Grid Analysis and Display System (GrADS) Version 2.0.1.oga.1 Copyright (c) 1988–2011 by Brian Doty and the Institute for Global Environment and Society (IGES) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/">ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Stalagmite δ<sup>18</sup>O records and the simulated summer precipitation over the middle reach of the Yangtze River and southwestern China.</title><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>(a) The Dongge Cave δ18O record (red) and the simulated July precipitation over 100°E–112°E, 22°N–32°N (green; mm), (b) the Lianhua Cave δ18O record, (c) the Sanbao Cave δ18O record, (d) the Heshang Cave δ18O record, and (e) the Jiuxian Cave δ18O record. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f7"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Anomalies in the ensemble mean summer eddy SLP (unit: hPa) from the climatological mean at 9 (a), 6.5 (b), 4.8 (c), 2.5 (d), and 0 (e) ka BP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>This figure is generated by the Grid Analysis and Display System (GrADS) Version 2.0.1.oga.1 Copyright (c) 1988–2011 by Brian Doty and the Institute for Global Environment and Society (IGES) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/">ftp://cola.gmu.edu/grads/2.0/old/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f8"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Longitude-time cross-section of the eddy SLP anomalies (unit: hPa) from the climatological mean along 30°N.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f9"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Latitude-time cross-section of summer precipitation anomalies (unit: mm) from the climatological mean along longitude 110°E.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep35816-f10"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
