<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5297700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms18010065</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-18-00065</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Preferential Enhancement of Sensory and Motor Axon Regeneration by Combining Extracellular Matrix Components with Neurotrophic Factors </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-18-00065">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-18-00065">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-18-00065">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>González-Pérez</surname><given-names>Francisco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-18-00065">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-18-00065">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-18-00065">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giudetti</surname><given-names>Guido</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-18-00065">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Micera</surname><given-names>Silvestro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-18-00065">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijms-18-00065">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Udina</surname><given-names>Esther</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-18-00065">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-18-00065">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Del Valle</surname><given-names>Jaume</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-18-00065">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-18-00065">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-18-00065">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-18-00065">2</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-18-00065" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fahnestock</surname><given-names>Margaret</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Martinowich</surname><given-names>Keri</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-18-00065"><label>1</label>Institute of Neurosciences and Department of Cell Biology, Physiology and Immunology, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, E-08193 Bellaterra, Spain; <email>dani.santos.1988@hotmail.com</email> (D.S.); <email>francisco.gzlez@gmail.com</email> (F.G.-P.); <email>esther.udina@uab.cat</email> (E.U.); <email>jaume.delvalle@uab.cat</email> (J.D.V.)</aff><aff id="af2-ijms-18-00065"><label>2</label>Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red sobre Enfermedades Neurodegenerativas (CIBERNED), E-08193 Bellaterra, Spain</aff><aff id="af3-ijms-18-00065"><label>3</label>The BioRobotics Institute, Scuola Superiore Sant’Anna, Viale Rinaldo Piaggio 34, 56025 Pontedera, Italy; <email>g.giudetti@sssup.it</email> (G.G.); <email>micera@sssup.it</email> (S.M.)</aff><aff id="af4-ijms-18-00065"><label>4</label>Bertarelli Foundation Chair in Translational NeuroEngineering, Translational Neural Engineering Laboratory, Center for Neuroprosthetics and Interfaculty Institute of Bioengineering, School of Engineering, Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (EPFL), CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-18-00065"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>xavier.navarro@uab.cat</email>; Tel.: +34-935-811-966; Fax: +34-935-812-986</corresp><fn id="fn1-ijms-18-00065"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>65</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>After peripheral nerve injury, motor and sensory axons are able to regenerate but inaccuracy of target reinnervation leads to poor functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Extracellular matrix (ECM) components and neurotrophic factors (NTFs) exert their effect on different neuronal populations creating a suitable environment to promote axonal growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, we assessed in vitro and in vivo the selective effects of combining different ECM components with NTFs on motor and sensory axons regeneration and target reinnervation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Organotypic cultures with collagen, laminin and nerve growth factor (NGF)/neurotrophin-3 (NT3) or collagen, fibronectin and brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) selectively enhanced sensory neurite outgrowth of DRG neurons and motor neurite outgrowth from spinal cord slices respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>For in vivo studies, the rat sciatic nerve was transected and repaired with a silicone tube filled with a collagen and laminin matrix with NGF/NT3 encapsulated in poly(lactic-co-glycolic acid) (PLGA) microspheres (MP) (LM + MP.NGF/NT3), or a collagen and fibronectin matrix with BDNF in PLGA MPs (FN + MP.BDNF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Retrograde labeling and functional tests showed that LM + MP.NGF/NT3 increased the number of regenerated sensory neurons and improved sensory functional recovery, whereas FN + MP.BDNF preferentially increased regenerated motoneurons and enhanced motor functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Therefore, combination of ECM molecules with NTFs may be a good approach to selectively enhance motor and sensory axons regeneration and promote appropriate target reinnervation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>neurotrophic factors</kwd><kwd>BDNF</kwd><kwd>NGF</kwd><kwd>NT3</kwd><kwd>extracellular matrix</kwd><kwd>motor axons</kwd><kwd>sensory axons</kwd><kwd>nerve regeneration</kwd><kwd>reinnervation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>After peripheral nerve injury, transected axons in the distal stump are disconnected from the neuronal body and undergo Wallerian degeneration, thus leading to denervation of peripheral organs [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Axotomized neurons switch to a growth state, and non-neuronal cells in the distal stump undergo activation and dedifferentiation to sustain nerve regeneration [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Even though axons are able to regenerate after nerve transection, axons grow randomly among the endoneurial tubules in the distal nerve, so that the accuracy of target reinnervation is usually poor, resulting in limited functional recovery [4,5,6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a pro-regenerative environment that selectively guides motor and sensory axons to regenerate into different branches of the injured nerve may be useful to increase the options of specific target reinnervation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Selective regeneration of different axonal populations would be also useful in the field of neuroprosthetics, as separating motor axons from sensory axons in mixed nerves will functionally improve selective recording and stimulation for providing bidirectional communication with the prosthesis [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>After peripheral nerve injury, the generation of a pro-regenerative environment involves the upregulation and secretion of extracellular matrix (ECM) components, such as collagen type IV, laminin and fibronectin, and the secretion of different neurotrophic factors (NTFs), such as nerve growth factor (NGF), brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), neurotrophin-3 (NT3), and glial derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF), among others [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>ECM components interact with integrin heterodimer receptors that are highly expressed in growth cones and non-neuronal cells, both during development and after injury [11,12], promoting axonal guidance, cell adhesion and migration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>For instance, laminin substrates enhance elongation of sensory neurites in vitro when compared to collagen or fibronectin containing scaffolds, whereas fibronectin substrates promote neurite elongation of motor neurons from SC slices in vitro [13,14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the interaction between NTFs and their different receptors, such as Trk/p75 receptors or GDNFR/RET receptors, promotes survival and axonal regeneration of different neuronal populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For example, we found that NGF selectively promotes sensory neurite outgrowth, whereas BDNF or fibroblast growth factor (FGF) preferentially increase motor neurite outgrowth in vitro [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Several reports have demonstrated that the pattern of NTFs expressed in denervated Schwann cells after nerve injury is different between motor and sensory nerve branches, and that motor and sensory axons also express different cell adhesion molecules that may promote differential binding to ECM molecules [16,17,18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Manipulation of some of these differential biomarkers may play a role in promoting selective regeneration of different axonal populations and improving subsequent accurate reinnervation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>However, the majority of the studies have only investigated the effect of these molecules individually, disregarding the synergistic interactions of ECM molecules with NTFs [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in this study, we tested whether the combination of different NTFs and ECM components, that were previously shown to produce a selective although limited stimulus for either sensory or motor axons regeneration [14,21], was able to produce a synergistic and selective pro-regenerative effect on motor and sensory neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Briefly, addition of both LM and NGF/NT3 or FN and BDNF increased the amount of sensory and motor neurite outgrowth, respectively, in culture models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these effects were maintained in vivo in adult animals as sensory and motor axonal regeneration as well as functional recovery was enhanced after treating nerve injuries with a nerve conduit prefilled with the same combinations of NTFs and ECM components. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec2-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2dot1-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In Vitro Effects of Combining Neurotrophic Factors (NTFs) and Extracellular Matrix (ECM) Substrates on Neurite Outgrowth </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>To study the effect of different combinations of NTFs and ECM components on motor and sensory neurons outgrowth, we first performed an in vitro screening using spinal cord (SC) slices and DRG explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In cultures of SC slices (Figure 1), addition of FN to the matrix doubled the maximum neurite length whereas addition of LM did not increase it compared to the control COL matrix (Figure 1J). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Addition of BDNF but not of NGF/NT3 to the different substrates enhanced neurite length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the combination of FN + BDNF significantly enhanced maximum neurite length and density of neurites compared to the other single and combined groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Thus, while groups with either FN or BDNF present an increase in the amount and length of neurites, the combination of the two factors shows a synergistic effect with significant differences with respect to all the other groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, LM or NGF/NT3 alone or combined did not show any improvement (Figure 1J–L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In DRG explants (Figure 2), addition of LM or FN into the collagen matrix similarly enhanced the maximum neurite length (Figure 2J) compared to collagen alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The addition of NGF/NT3 or BDNF into COL, LM and FN substrates enhanced maximum neurite length compared with COL substrate except COL + BDNF cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that only LM + NGF/NT3 group showed differences in maximum neurite length with respect to all the other culture conditions except with LM + BDNF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The addition of NGF and NT3 enhanced significantly the density of neurites in all the substrates, being LM + NGF/NT3 the most prominent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In contrast, addition of BDNF only promoted neurite growth with LM but not when combined with COL or FN (Figure 2L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that combination of FN + BDNF shows synergistic effects on motor neurons promoting neurite elongation and arborization, with weaker effect on sensory elongation, whereas LM + NGF/NT3 is the only condition that exhibits a synergistic effects on sensory but not on motor neurons based on the enhancement observed in neurite elongation and arborization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In Vivo Effects of Combination of NTF and ECM Substrates on Nerve Regeneration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We performed first an in vivo study in which the sciatic nerve was transected and repaired with silicone tubes filled with matrices composed of COL, COL + MP.NGF/NT3, LM, LM + MP.NGF/NT3, COL + MP.BDNF, and FN and FN + MP.BDNF to elucidate if the conditions with a more relevant effect in vitro had a similar effect in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The three NTFs (NGF, NT3 and BDNF) were encapsulated in PLGA microspheres to allow a sustained release during the time that axons regenerate across the tube [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>All rats showed evidence of axonal regeneration, as judged by the retrograde labeling of motor and sensory neurons with Fluorogold (FG) (Figure 3A–F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Regarding the number of regenerated motor neurons, all groups with addition of ECM and NTFs showed significant differences with respect to the COL group (p &lt; 0.001, Figure 3G), being the FN + MP.BDNF group the one with the highest effect, that was also significantly higher compared to all other groups except with FN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For sensory neurons, the group LM + MP.NGF/NT3 showed the highest number of regenerated neurons, and all other groups had better results than the COL control (Figure 3H). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We then tested whether this preferential effect is maintained in a long term study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, we compared groups of rats similar to the short term study but leaving an 8 mm gap between stumps, since this more challenging gap allows to better elucidate differences between groups [22], and applying the FG retrotracer to the tibial nerve at the ankle at 75 dpi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In this case, no significant differences in the number of regenerated motor neurons were observed between groups (Figure 3I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>However, more regenerated sensory neurons were counted in the LM + MP.NGF/NT3 group compared to the other four groups (Figure 3J). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Despite the preferential effects observed in vitro appear less marked in vivo, these results indicate that FN + MP.BDNF mainly favors motor axon regeneration, whereas LM + MP.NGF/NT3 is more effective to promote sensory axon regeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Combination of FN and BDNF Promotes Motor Functional Recovery at Long Term </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We tested if the effects seen on regeneration in the short and long term studies had impact on muscle reinnervation and functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Nerve conduction tests provided first evidence of reinnervation of the TA muscle at 45 dpi in all the groups (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The amplitude of the CMAP increased during the follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>At 60 dpi, the FN + MP.BDNF group showed higher amplitude than all the other groups (p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>FN group also showed significant differences with respect to COL group (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>However, all groups reached similar CMAP amplitude at 75 dpi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In the more distal plantar muscles, reinnervation started later compared to TA muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In this case, the CMAP amplitude at 75 dpi was significantly higher in FN + MP.BDNF group compared to all the other groups (p &lt; 0.001, Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>No differences in the CMAP latency were observed between groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that an intratubular matrix containing FN and BDNF promotes motor axon regeneration and reinnervation of target muscles, whereas LM and LM + NGF/NT3 groups showed values similar to the COL control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The faster muscle reinnervation found in group FN + MP.BDNF is of relevance considering the longer distance that has to be regenerated in injured human nerves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Combination of LM and NGF/NT3 Promotes Sensory Functional Recovery at Long Term </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In parallel, we assessed sensory functional recovery to mechanical and thermal stimuli in the hind paw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For the pinprick test, LM and LM + MP.NGF/NT3 groups presented the first positive response at 30 dpi, whereas no response was observed in the other groups at this time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>At later time points, all groups showed positive responses, being LM + MP.NGF/NT3 the only group with significantly higher scores compared to the control group (p &lt; 0.05; Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Withdrawal responses to heat stimulation in the plantar test showed similar results to the ones observed for the pinprick. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Denervated paws did not respond to the hot stimuli on the lateral region until 45 dpi and at this time point group LM + MP.NGF/NT3 showed a shorter latency compared to control, FN and FN + MP.BDNF groups (p &lt; 0.01; Figure 4D), indicating that more sensory fibers arrived to the plantar skin of the paw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, all groups showed similar latency at 60 and 75 dpi. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To further corroborate the functional results, skin reinnervation of the lateral paw pads was analyzed by immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In all the rats PGP immunolabeling showed regenerated nerve fibers that surrounded the SG tubules, reached the subepidermal nerve plexus, and extended to intraepidermal terminals and Meissner corpuscles at the papillae (Figure 4E–J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Group LM + MP.NGF/NT3 had significantly higher number of IENF than all the other groups (Figure 4K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the number of reinnervated SGs was highest in group LM + MP.NGF/NT3, although only significantly from groups COL and LM (Figure 4L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results indicate that the combination of LM and NGF/NT3 enhances sensory axons regeneration and skin reinnervation by populations of sensory neurons that contribute to thermal and mechanical sensibility, and less markedly of sympathetic fibers innervating the SGs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>NTFs and ECM components both have important roles in nerve regeneration after injury, including effects on Schwann cell migration and differentiation, neuronal survival, cell adhesion and axonal growth [10,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>To corroborate the preferential effect of NGF, NT-3 and LM on sensory neurons and BDNF and FN on motor neurons [15,24,25,26,27], we cultured DRG explants and spinal cord slices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Organotypic cultures are multicellular in vitro models in which neurons and growing neurites share similar differentiation and development patterns with in vivo conditions [28] while they are still in contact with Schwann cells and fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In this way, DRG explants have been long used to study axonal growth and regeneration of the sensory nervous system [29,30] as DRG contain the soma of pseudounipolar sensory neurons that project growing neurites outside the ganglion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, neurites growing from the ventral areas of the spinal cord arise from motoneurons of the ventral horn instead of other interneurons [31] making this 3D culture an useful model for studying regeneration of motor neurites in vitro [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Taking into account that some NTFs show an attractive or repulsive effect depending on the presence of different ECM molecules [33], we performed a screening of possible combinations added to a collagen gel substrate to investigate if the preferential effects of ECM components and NTFs could be synergistically added in DRG and SC postnatal cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We observed an increased effect of LM and NGF + NT3 on sensory neurite outgrowth in DRG explants, whereas this combination did not increase motor neurite length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, BDNF combined with FN promoted a synergic effect on motor neurite outgrowth with small effects on DRG explants, which can be attributed to the effect on regenerating proprioceptive neurites [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The synergistic effect can be exemplified for BDNF, that promotes sensory neurite outgrowth in the presence of LM but not when is added alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>These proregenerative effects may be mediated by the differential expression of integrin and NTF receptors in regenerating neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It has been described that after injury integrin receptors α7β1 and α5β1 are upregulated in both motor and sensory neurons [14,34], whereas high affinity TrkA and TrkC receptors are expressed in sensory neurons and TrKB is mainly expressed in motoneurons and in a low percentage of sensory neurons [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>It can be hypothesized that the partially selective in vitro effects of NTFs may be enhanced by the presence of certain ECM molecules in the substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In fact, it has been reported that the pro-regenerative effects of NGF and NT3 are reduced after blocking the α7 subunit of integrins in sensory neurons [36], and that synergistic actions between integrins and NTF receptors may be attributed to the sustained activation of Src and the downstream signaling Akt intermediate [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, NTFs may also modulate the expression of different integrin receptor subunits, whose upregulation is low in adult compared to their expression in early postnatal animals [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Actually, NGF contributes to enhance ECM signaling by promoting axonal transport and accumulation of β1 integrin in growth cones, thus enhancing neurite outgrowth [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Since the optimal developmental window of regeneration varies from E11–E15 in the chick spinal cord to P7 in rats [40] and the effects of different ECM molecules in vitro are lost when switching from postnatal P7 to weaned P21 rats [14], it was necessary to confirm in a model of peripheral nerve injury and regeneration in vivo the effects observed in cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The in vivo results demonstrated that introduction of a collagen matrix enriched with LM + MP.NGF/NT3 or FN + MP.BDNF within the tube used for nerve repair in adult rats promoted preferential regeneration of sensory and motor axons respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The NTFs were encapsulated in PLGA microspheres as they have been approved by the FDA as a drug delivery system [41] and we have recently demonstrated that they do not interfere with axon regeneration and their slow release over more than 30 days provides more sustained support for nerve regeneration with respect to addition of free NTFs [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>All the treated groups showed an increased number of retrogradely traced motor and sensory neurons that had regenerated their axons to the site of tracer application distal to the tube, compared to the control COL group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This is a positive indication that the design and the concentrations of encapsulated NTFs and ECM components did not cause detrimental effects such as the candy store effect [42] or neuronal death induced by high concentration of NTFs [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>However, the preferential effect mediated by LM + MP.NGF/NT3 and FN + MP.BDNF treatments was more modest compared to the in vitro experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This comparative reduction may be explained because of the more complex environment present in the regenerating nerve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>After nerve injury, ECM components are synthesized and secreted by non-neuronal cells such as Schwann cells and fibroblasts [44], whereas NTFs are expressed by both neuronal and non-neuronal cells [16,45,46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, non-neuronal cells involved in Wallerian degeneration also express integrins and NTF receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the in vivo implant of a matrix containing ECM components and NTFs in the nerve conduit does not only influence the injured neurons, but also acts on the migrating non-neuronal cells inside the intratubular matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Hence, the activation of non-neuronal cells would contribute with proregenerative non-specific cues and decrease the effects of the selective factors introduced in the exogenous matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, although we still found in vivo a significant preferential regeneration of sensory neurons in animals treated with LM + MP.NGF/NT3 and of motor neurons in animals treated with FN + MP.BDNF, the differences in the amount of regenerated neurons were reduced from the short to the long term study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We can discard that this could be related to an inefficient supply of NTFs as we have previously shown that NTF encapsulation in MPs improved regeneration of both motor and sensory axons, and that PLGA MPs are able to sustain release of these NTFs longer than a month [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The most plausible explanation for the reduced effect observed would be that most axons had passed the site of tracer application at 75 dpi, and thus we were not able to detect differences that occurred at earlier time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Although retrolabeling of regenerating neurons is a useful technique to assess the differential effect of local treatments, functional restitution is the most important outcome after nerve injury [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Thus, in the long term in vivo study we evaluated functional recovery of both motor and sensory targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Electrophysiological results demonstrated that muscle reinnervation started earlier and achieved higher levels in the FN + MP.BDNF group than in all the other groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>An increased regeneration rate improves muscle reinnervation, particularly of distal muscles in the limb, as shown in the foot muscles in this study, reducing the detrimental consequences of chronic denervation [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, treatment with LM + MP.NGF/NT3 showed earlier sensory responses to both mechanical and thermal stimuli, confirming the results seen in the retrotracer study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We also demonstrated an increased number of sensory axons reinnervating the epidermis and of sympathetic axons reinnervating the SGs in the skin in the LM + MP.NGF/NT3 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>This parallel effect could be explained by the proregenerative role of NGF on sensory as well as on sympathetic neurons [49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec4-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec4dot1-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In vitro (procedure #1963M) and in vivo (procedure #1162MM) experimental procedures were approved in 30 June 2015 and in 29 May 2015 respectively by the animal and human experimentation ethics committee (CEEAH) of the Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona in accordance with the European Communities Council Directive 2010/63/EU. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In Vitro Study on Organotypic Cultures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Organotypic cultures were prepared as previously described in detail [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Briefly, a 3 mg/mL collagen solution was prepared by mixing rat tail collagen type I (#354236, Corning, Wiesbaden, Germany) with PBS (D8537, Sigma, Tres Cantos, Spain) and sodium bicarbonate at 0.3 mg/mL, and diluting 1:10 with basal Eagle’s medium (10×, Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>NTF enriched substrates were prepared by adding BDNF at 50 ng/mL (Peprotech, London, UK) or NGF and NT3 (Peprotech) at 25 ng/mL each, and fibronectin (BD Bioscences, Vienna, Austria) or laminin type I (Sigma) to a 20% final volume. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Single 30 µL drops of the prepared matrices were deposited on poly-d-lysine (Sigma) coated coverslips, which were placed in Petri dishes or 24-well multidishes (Iwaki, Asahi Technoglass, Chiba, Japan), and kept in the incubator at 37 °C and 5% CO2 for two hours to induce collagen gel formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Collagen gel was mixed with PBS (COL) and used as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Collagen gels were also combined with NGF/NT3 (COL + NGF/NT3) or BDNF (COL + BDNF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Similarly, laminin and fibronectin-enriched gels were combined with PBS (LM and FN, respectively), NGF + NT3 (LM + NGF/NT3 and FN + NGF/NT3, respectively) or BDNF (LM + BDNF and FN + BDNF, respectively) (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The lumbar spinal cord (SC, n = 6–8/group) and dorsal root ganglia (DRG, n = 7–8/group) were harvested from 7-day-old Sprague-Dawley rats, placed in cold Gey’s balanced salt solution (Sigma) enriched with 6 mg/mL glucose and cleaned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>SC 350 µm thick slices and DRG explants were placed on gelled collagen droplets, prepared as indicated above, and covered with a second 30 µL drop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The embedded samples were placed in the incubator for 45 min before adding Neurobasal medium (NB, Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA), supplemented with B27 (Life Technologies), glutamine and penicillin/streptomycin (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>SC slices were cultured for 4 days, and DRG explants for 2 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Then, cultures were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS for 30 min, and incubated for 48 h with primary antibody mouse RT97 (1:200, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa City, IA, USA) at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>After washes, the sections were incubated with secondary antibody AF594 conjugated donkey anti-mouse (1:200, Life Technologies) overnight at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>For DRG and SC visualization, samples were mounted on slides using Mowiol with DAPI (100 ng/mL, Sigma) for nuclear staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Olympus BX51 fluorescence microscope (Olympus, Hamburg, Germany) attached to a DP73 camera was used to obtain images of different areas using cellSens Entry software (version 1.12, Olympus), different parts of each sample were merged using Adobe Photoshop CS3 (Adobe System, San Jose, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>To analyze the length of neurites, ImageJ software (NIH, available on: http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/) resolution parameters were fixed and the three longest neurites were followed from the ventral horn (spinal cord) or ganglion boundary (DRG) to their ending projections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Whole culture images of the DRG and the ventral horn of the SC were analyzed with the Neurite-J plug-in [50] for ImageJ software, and the number of neurites grown at different distances from the explant was compared between sets of cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>To facilitate the visualization of differences between groups, the area under the curve of each group was converted to a bar plot. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In Vivo Study of Peripheral Nerve Regeneration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Female Sprague-Dawley rats weighing between 250–300 g were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Animals had ad libitum access to food and water and were kept under a standard light-dark cycle of 12:12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>All efforts were made to minimize pain and animal distress during surgery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Rats were anaesthetized with ketamine/xylacine (90/10 mg/kg i.p.), the sciatic nerve was exposed at the midthigh and sectioned 90 mm from the tip of the third toe, and a nerve portion resected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A silicone tube was then sutured with 10-0 monofilament sutures to each nerve stump leaving a 6 mm gap between both nerve ends for the short term study or 8 mm gap for the long term study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Animals were kept for 20 days post-injury (dpi) (short term) or 75 dpi (long term) to allow axonal regeneration before testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Each of the three NTFs (NGF, NT3, and BDNF) were encapsulated in microspheres as previously described [51] and added to a collagen solution to reach a final concentration of 2 µg/mL for BDNF and 1 µg/mL for NGF and NT3 respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Each preparation of NTF was then added to ECM solutions prepared as for the cultures, i.e., collagen at 3 mg/mL, collagen supplemented with laminin 20% (v/v), and collagen supplemented with fibronectin 20% (v/v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Silicone tubes 8 or 10 mm long with an internal diameter of 2 mm were filled with one of the mixtures containing different combinations of ECM substrates and encapsulated NTF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In order to promote fibril alignment, the collagen solution was left to gel vertically for 12 h before surgery [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there were 7 experimental groups for short and 5 for long term experiments (n = 6 per group, see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot4-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Retrograde Labeling and Neuronal Counting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To quantify motor and sensory regenerated neurons at short term (20 dpi), rats were anaesthetized with ketamine/xylacine and the sciatic nerve was exposed and transected 8 mm distal to the distal end of the silicone tube to apply Fluorogold (FG; 5%; Fluorochrome Inc., Denver, CO, USA) as a retrotracer [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 5 µL of FG were applied to the end of the nerve for 1 h, then the retrotracer was washed with saline to remove any residues of the tracer and the wound sutured in planes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Similarly, for the long term study (75 dpi) FG was also applied to the tibial nerve at the ankle level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>After tracer application, the rats were allowed to survive for 7 days, then, they were deeply anesthetized and transcardially perfused with 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The lumbar segment (L3–L6) of the SC and the L4 and L5 DRG were removed, postfixed at 4 °C for 1 h and transferred to 30% sucrose in PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Samples were cut in a cryostat longitudinally in 40 and 20 µm thick sections respectively, mounted s severed he tube on slides, heated at 35 °C for 1 h and stored at −20 °C in the dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>DRG and SC sections were observed with an Olympus BX51 fluorescence microscope and the fractionator principle [54] was used to quantify the number of labeled neurons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot5-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Assessment of Muscle Reinnervation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Functional reinnervation of target muscles was assessed at 7, 30, 45, 60 and 75 dpi by means of nerve conduction tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Animals were anesthetized with ketamine/xylacine and the sciatic nerve was stimulated by transcutaneous electrodes placed at the sciatic notch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The amplitudes (M wave) of the compound muscle action potentials (CMAP) of tibialis anterior (TA) and plantar interossei muscles (PL) were recorded (mV) after placing monopolar needle electrodes in the muscle bellies and the reference in the fourth toe [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Values of the contralateral intact limb were used as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>During the tests, the rat body temperature was maintained by means of a thermostated warming flat coil. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Animals were anesthetized with ketamine/xylacine and the sciatic nerve was stimulated by transcutaneous electrodes placed at the sciatic notch. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot6-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>4.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Assessment of Skin Nociceptive Reinnervation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The progression of nociceptive reinnervation of the hind paw was assessed by means of the pinprick test and thermal sensitivity at 7, 30, 45, 60 and 75 dpi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>For the pinprick test, animals were gently kept in a cloth with the sole of the injured paw facing upward, and the skin was stimulated with a needle progressively from proximal to distal at specific sites of the lateral side of the hind paw plantar surface [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Fast withdrawal of the hindpaw after stimulation was identified as a clear pain reaction and thus a sign of functional skin reinnervation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The mean number of positive responses in every tested area was calculated per group at each day of testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Thermal sensitivity was evaluated using a Plantar test algesimeter (Ugo Basile, Comerio, Italy) [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Rats were individually placed in Plexiglas cubicles (20 × 20 × 14 (h) cm) with an elevated Plexiglas floor in a room at constant temperature (24 ± 0.5 °C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The beam of a low intensity lamp (40 mW/cm2) was pointed to the lateral part in the hind paw plantar surface with a heating rate of 1 °C/s to elicit activation of unmyelinated C fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A cutoff time of exposure to limit possible tissue damage was set at 20 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The latency (in seconds) of hindpaw withdrawal from the thermal stimulus was recorded as the mean of 3 tests per paw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>A 5-min resting period was set between each trial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot7-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>4.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of Skin and Sweat Gland Reinnervation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>For assessing skin reinnervation, plantar pads corresponding to the lateral side were removed at the end of the functional follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Cryotome sections 60 µm thick were processed for immunolabeling against protein gene product (PGP) 9.5 (rabbit; 1:1000; UltraClone, Cambridge, UK), a pan-neuronal marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies were conjugated to Cy3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Sections were observed with an Olympus BX51 fluorescence microscope to visualize immunoreactive nerve fibers that had reinnervated the epidermis and the sweat glands (SG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>For analysis, images of three sections of each sample were collected with an Olympus DP73 digital camera, the number of intraepidermal nerve fibers (IENFs) was counted in a 1-mm-long segment of the footpad epidermis and the number of reinnervated SGs in the whole pad was also quantified [58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot8-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>4.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Data Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as mean ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Results were statistically analyzed using GraphPad Prism (version 6.01, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>One- and two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni’s post hoc test for comparison between groups were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was considered when p-value was &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5-ijms-18-00065"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, this study demonstrates that the interaction between FN + BDNF and between LM + NGF/NT3 has synergistic effects to preferentially enhance motor and sensory axon regeneration, respectively, in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these effects are maintained in vivo in adult animals as motor and sensory axonal regeneration and functional recovery was enhanced after treating nerve injuries with a nerve conduit prefilled with the same combinations of NTFs and ECM components. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by the European Union FP7-NMP project MERIDIAN under contract number 280778, and FP7-ICT project NEBIAS under contract number 611687, FEDER funds, and TERCEL and CIBERNED funds from the Instituto de Salud Carlos III of Spain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The authors thank the technical help of Monica Espejo and Jessica Jaramillo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The RT97 antibody was obtained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank developed under the auspices of the NICHD and maintained by the University of Iowa, Department of Biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Daniel Santos, Francisco González-Pérez, Guido Giudetti, Silvestro Micera, Esther Udina, Jaume Del Valle and Xavier Navarro conceived and designed the experiments; Daniel Santos, Francisco González-Pérez, Guido Giudetti and Jaume Del Valle performed the experiments; Daniel Santos, Francisco González-Pérez, Guido Giudetti and Jaume Del Valle, analyzed the data; Silvestro Micera, Esther Udina, Jaume Del Valle and Xavier Navarro contributed with reagents/materials/analysis tool and interpretation of data for the work; Daniel Santos, Francisco González-Pérez, Guido Giudetti, Esther Udina and Jaume Del Valle drafted the manuscript; and Guido Giudetti, Silvestro Micera, Esther Udina, Jaume Del Valle and Xavier Navarro revised the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>1. HallS. The response to injury in the peripheral nervous system J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Bone Jt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Surg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Br. 2005 87 1309 1319 10.1302/0301-620X.87B10.16700 <?supplied-pmid 16189300?>16189300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>2. RichardsonP.M.MiaoT.WuD.ZhangY.YehJ.BoX. Responses of the nerve cell body to axotomy Neurosurgery 2009 65 A74 A79 10.1227/01.NEU.0000352378.26755.C3 <?supplied-pmid 19927082?>19927082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>3. NavarroX.VivóM.Valero-CabréA. Neural plasticity after peripheral nerve injury and regeneration Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2007 82 163 201 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2007.06.005 <?supplied-pmid 17643733?>17643733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>4. AldskogiusH.MolanderC. Specificity in regenerative outgrowth and target reinnervation by mammalian peripheral axons Restor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 1990 1 275 280 <?supplied-pmid 21551567?>21551567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>5. LundborgG. Nerve injury and repair—A challenge to the plastic brain Peripher. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Nerv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Syst. 2003 8 209 226 10.1111/j.1085-9489.2003.03027.x  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>6. Valero-CabréA.NavarroX. Functional impact of axonal misdirection after peripheral nerve injuries followed by graft or tube repair J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Neurotrauma 2002 19 1475 1485 10.1089/089771502320914705 <?supplied-pmid 12490012?>12490012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>7. Valero-CabréA.TsironisK.SkourasE.NavarroX.NeissW.F. Peripheral and spinal motor reorganization after nerve injury and repair J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Neurotrauma 2004 21 95 108 10.1089/089771504772695986 <?supplied-pmid 14987469?>14987469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>8. ClementsI.P.MukhatyarV.J.SrinivasanA.BentleyJ.T.AndreasenD.S.BellamkondaR.V. Regenerative scaffold electrodes for peripheral nerve interfacing IEEE Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Neural Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Rehabil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Eng. 2013 21 554 566 10.1109/TNSRE.2012.2217352 <?supplied-pmid 23033438?>23033438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>9. LotfiP.GardeK.ChouhanA.BengaliE.Romero-OrtegaM. Modality-specific axonal regeneration: Toward selective regenerative neural interfaces Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Neuroeng. 2011 4 11 10.3389/fneng.2011.00011 <?supplied-pmid 22016734?>22016734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>10. AllodiI.UdinaE.NavarroX. Specificity of peripheral nerve regeneration: Interactions at the axon level Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2012 98 16 37 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2012.05.005 <?supplied-pmid 22609046?>22609046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>11. GardinerN.J. Integrins and the extracellular matrix: Key mediators of development and regeneration of the sensory nervous system Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2011 71 1054 1072 10.1002/dneu.20950 <?supplied-pmid 21761574?>21761574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>12. LemonsM.L.CondicM.L. Integrin signaling is integral to regeneration Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2008 209 343 352 10.1016/j.expneurol.2007.05.027 <?supplied-pmid 17727844?>17727844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>13. PlantmanS.PatarroyoM.FriedK.DomogatskayaA.TryggvasonK.HammarbergH.CullheimS. Integrin-laminin interactions controlling neurite outgrowth from adult DRG neurons in vitro Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2008 39 50 62 10.1016/j.mcn.2008.05.015 <?supplied-pmid 18590826?>18590826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>14. González-PérezF.AléA.SantosD.BarwigC.FreierT.NavarroX.UdinaE. Substratum preferences of motor and sensory neurons in postnatal and adult rats Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2016 43 431 442 10.1111/ejn.13057 <?supplied-pmid 26332537?>26332537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>15. AllodiI.Guzmán-LenisM.-S.HernàndezJ.NavarroX.UdinaE. In vitro comparison of motor and sensory neuron outgrowth in a 3D collagen matrix J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Methods 2011 198 53 61 10.1016/j.jneumeth.2011.03.006 <?supplied-pmid 21402104?>21402104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>16. BrushartT.M.AspalterM.GriffinJ.W.RedettR.HameedH.ZhouC.WrightM.VyasA.HökeA. Schwann cell phenotype is regulated by axon modality and central-peripheral location, and persists in vitro Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2013 247 272 281 10.1016/j.expneurol.2013.05.007 <?supplied-pmid 23707299?>23707299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>17. HökeA.RedettR.HameedH.JariR.ZhouC.LiZ.B.GriffinJ.W.BrushartT.M. Schwann cells express motor and sensory phenotypes that regulate axon regeneration J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2006 26 9646 9655 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1620-06.2006 <?supplied-pmid 16988035?>16988035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>18. RobinsonG.A.MadisonR.D. Motor neurons can preferentially reinnervate cutaneous pathways Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2004 190 407 413 10.1016/j.expneurol.2004.08.007 <?supplied-pmid 15530879?>15530879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>19. MartiniR.SchachnerM.BrushartT.M. The L2/HNK-1 carbohydrate is preferentially expressed by previously motor axon-associated Schwann cells in reinnervated peripheral nerves J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 1994 14 7180 7191 <?supplied-pmid 7525896?>7525896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>20. MadlC.M.HeilshornS.C. Matrix interactions modulate neurotrophin-mediated neurite outgrowth and pathfinding Neural Regen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Res. 2015 10 514 517 <?supplied-pmid 26170800?>26170800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>21. SantosD.GiudettiG.MiceraS.NavarroX.del ValleJ. Focal release of neurotrophic factors by biodegradable microspheres enhance motor and sensory axonal regeneration in vitro and in vivo Brain Res. 2016 1636 93 106 10.1016/j.brainres.2016.01.051 <?supplied-pmid 26854135?>26854135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>22. Valero-CabréA.TsironisK.SkourasE.PeregoG.NavarroX.NeissW.F. Superior muscle reinnervation after autologous nerve graft or poly-l-lactide-ε-caprolactone (PLC) tube implantation in comparison to silicone tube repair J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Res. 2001 63 214 223 10.1002/1097-4547(20010115)63:2&lt;214::AID-JNR1014&gt;3.0.CO;2-D 11169632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>23. GordonT. The role of neurotrophic factors in nerve regeneration Neurosurg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Focus 2009 26 E3 10.3171/FOC.2009.26.2.E3 <?supplied-pmid 19228105?>19228105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>24. LeeA.C.YuV.M.LoweJ.B.BrennerM.J.HunterD.A.MackinnonS.E.Sakiyama-ElbertS.E. Controlled release of nerve growth factor enhances sciatic nerve regeneration Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2003 184 295 303 10.1016/S0014-4886(03)00258-9 14637100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>25. KempS.W.P.WebbA.A.DhaliwalS.SyedS.WalshS.K.MidhaR. Dose and duration of nerve growth factor (NGF) administration determine the extent of behavioral recovery following peripheral nerve injury in the rat Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2011 229 460 470 10.1016/j.expneurol.2011.03.017 <?supplied-pmid 21458449?>21458449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>26. VögelinE.BakerJ.M.GatesJ.DixitV.ConstantinescuM.A.JonesN.F. Effects of local continuous release of brain derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) on peripheral nerve regeneration in a rat model Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2006 199 348 353 10.1016/j.expneurol.2005.12.029 <?supplied-pmid 16487516?>16487516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>27. SterneG.D.BrownR.A.GreenC.J.TerenghiG. Neurotrophin-3 delivered locally via fibronectin mats enhances peripheral nerve regeneration Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 1997 9 1388 1396 10.1111/j.1460-9568.1997.tb01493.x <?supplied-pmid 9240396?>9240396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>28. XiangY.DingN.XingZ.ZhangW.LiuH.LiZ. Insulin-like growth factor-1 regulates neurite outgrowth and neuronal migration from organotypic cultured dorsal root ganglion Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2011 121 101 106 10.3109/00207454.2010.535935 <?supplied-pmid 21110707?>21110707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>29. CohenS.Levi-MontalciniR. A nerve growth-stimulating factor isolated from snake venom Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>USA 1956 42 571 574 10.1073/pnas.42.9.571 <?supplied-pmid 16589907?>16589907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>30. Al-AliH.BeckermanS.BixbyJ.L.LemmonV.P. In vitro models of axon regeneration Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2017 287 423 434 10.1016/j.expneurol.2016.01.020 <?supplied-pmid 26826447?>26826447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>31. AllodiI.Casals-DíazL.Santos-NogueiraE.González-PérezF.NavarroX.UdinaE. FGF-2 low molecular weight selectively promotes neuritogenesis of motor neurons in vitro Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2013 47 770 781 10.1007/s12035-012-8389-z <?supplied-pmid 23275175?>23275175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>32. Torres-EspínA.AllodiI.SantosD.González-PérezF.UdinaE.del ValleJ.NavarroX. Analysis of axonal growth in organotypic neural cultures Protoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Exch. 2016 10.1038/protex.2016.014  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>33. HariA.DjoharB.SkutellaT.MontazeriS. Neurotrophins and extracellular matrix molecules modulate sensory axon outgrowth Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2004 22 113 117 10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2003.12.002 <?supplied-pmid 15036386?>15036386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>34. WernerA.WillemM.JonesL.L.KreutzbergG.W.MayerU. Impaired axonal regeneration in α7 integrin-deficient mice J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2000 20 1822 1830 <?supplied-pmid 10684883?>10684883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>35. KarchewskiL.A.KimF.A.JohnstonJ.McKnightR.M.VergeV.M.K. Anatomical evidence supporting the potential for modulation by multiple neurotrophins in the majority of adult lumbar sensory neurons J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 1999 413 327 341 10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19991018)413:2&lt;327::AID-CNE11&gt;3.0.CO;2-3 10524342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>36. GardinerN.J.FernyhoughP.TomlinsonD.R.MayerU.von der MarkH.StreuliC.H. α7 Integrin mediates neurite outgrowth of distinct populations of adult sensory neurons Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2005 28 229 240 10.1016/j.mcn.2004.08.017 <?supplied-pmid 15691705?>15691705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>37. TuckerB.A.MearowK.M. Peripheral sensory axon growth: From receptor binding to cellular signaling Can. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2008 35 551 566 10.1017/S0317167100009331 <?supplied-pmid 19235438?>19235438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>38. CondicM.L. Adult neuronal regeneration induced by transgenic integrin expression J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2001 21 4782 4788 <?supplied-pmid 11425905?>11425905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>39. GrabhamP.W.FoleyM.UmeojiakoA.GoldbergD.J. Nerve growth factor stimulates coupling of β1 integrin to distinct transport mechanisms in the filopodia of growth cones J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Cell Sci. 2000 113 3003 3012 <?supplied-pmid 10934039?>10934039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>40. FilbinM.T. Recapitulate development to promote axonal regeneration: Good or bad approach? Philos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2006 361 1565 1574 10.1098/rstb.2006.1885 <?supplied-pmid 16939975?>16939975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>41. JainR.A. The manufacturing techniques of various drug loaded biodegradable poly (lactide-co-glycolide) (PLGA) devices Biomaterials 2000 21 2475 2490 10.1016/S0142-9612(00)00115-0 11055295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>42. TannemaatM.R.EggersR.HendriksW.T.de RuiterG.C.W.van HeerikhuizeJ.J.PoolC.W.MalessyM.J.A.BoerG.J.VerhaagenJ. Differential effects of lentiviral vector-mediated overexpression of nerve growth factor and glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor on regenerating sensory and motor axons in the transected peripheral nerve Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2008 28 1467 1479 10.1111/j.1460-9568.2008.06452.x <?supplied-pmid 18973572?>18973572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>43. MohiuddinL.DelcroixJ.-D.FernyhoughP.TomlinsonD.R. Focally administered nerve growth factor suppresses molecular regenerative responses of axotomized peripheral afferents in rats Neuroscience 1999 91 265 271 10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00582-X 10336076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>44. González-PérezF.UdinaE.NavarroX. Extracellular matrix components in peripheral nerve regeneration Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2013 108 257 275 <?supplied-pmid 24083438?>24083438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>45. JesurajN.J.NguyenP.K.WoodM.D.MooreA.M.BorschelG.H.MackinnonS.E.Sakiyama-ElbertS.E. Differential gene expression in motor and sensory Schwann cells in the rat femoral nerve J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Res. 2012 90 96 104 10.1002/jnr.22752 <?supplied-pmid 21932366?>21932366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>46. BoydJ.GordonT. Neurotrophic factors and their receptors in axonal regeneration and functional recovery after peripheral nerve injury Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 2003 27 277 324 10.1385/MN:27:3:277 12845152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>47. NavarroX. Functional evaluation of peripheral nerve regeneration and target reinnervation in animal models: A critical overview Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2016 43 271 286 10.1111/ejn.13033 <?supplied-pmid 26228942?>26228942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>48. GordonT.TyremanN.RajiM.A. The basis for diminished functional recovery after delayed peripheral nerve repair J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2011 31 5325 5334 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6156-10.2011 <?supplied-pmid 21471367?>21471367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>49. Levi-MontalciniR. The nerve growth factor: Thirty-five years later Biosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Rep. 1987 7 681 699 10.1007/BF01116861 <?supplied-pmid 3322422?>3322422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>50. Torres-EspínA.SantosD.González-PérezF.del ValleJ.NavarroX. Neurite-J: An Image-J plug-in for axonal growth analysis in organotypic cultures J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Methods 2014 236 26 39 10.1016/j.jneumeth.2014.08.005 <?supplied-pmid 25124852?>25124852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>51. GiudettiG.del Valle MaciaJ.AcebesX.N.MiceraS. NGF-loaded PLGA microparticles for advanced multifunctional regenerative electrodes Proceedings of the 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society, EMBC 2014 Chicago, IL, USA 26–30 August 2014 1993 1995  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>52. VerdúE.LabradorR.O.RodríguezF.J.CeballosD.ForésJ.NavarroX. Alignment of collagen and laminin-containing gels improve nerve regeneration within silicone tubes Restor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. 2002 20 169 179 <?supplied-pmid 12515893?>12515893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>53. SantosD.González-PérezF.NavarroX.del ValleJ. Dose-dependent differential effect of neurotrophic factors on in vitro and in vivo regeneration of motor and sensory neurons Neural Plast. 2016 2016 13 10.1155/2016/4969523 <?supplied-pmid 27867665?>27867665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>54. GundersenH.J. Stereology of arbitrary particles: A review of unbiased number and size estimators and the presentation of some new ones, in memory of William R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Thompson J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Microsc. 1986 143 3 45 10.1111/j.1365-2818.1986.tb02764.x <?supplied-pmid 3761363?>3761363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>55. SantosD.WieringaP.MoroniL.NavarroX.del ValleJ. PEOT/PBT guides enhance nerve regeneration in long gap defects Adv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Healthc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Mater. 2016 10.1002/adhm.201600298 <?supplied-pmid 27973708?>27973708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>56. NavarroX.VerdúE.ButíM. Comparison of regenerative and reinnervating capabilities of different functional types of nerve fibers Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 1994 129 217 224 10.1006/exnr.1994.1163 <?supplied-pmid 7957736?>7957736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>57. GarciaX.del ValleJ.EscribanoE.DomenechJ.QueraltJ. Analgesic and antiallodynic effects of antidepressants after infiltration into the rat Pharmacology 2010 86 216 223 10.1159/000319747 <?supplied-pmid 20829646?>20829646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58-ijms-18-00065"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>58. NavarroX.VerdúE.Wendelscafer-CrabbG.KennedyW.R. Innervation of cutaneous structures in the mouse hind paw: A confocal microscopy immunohistochemical study J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Res. 1995 41 111 120 10.1002/jnr.490410113 <?supplied-pmid 7545760?>7545760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-18-00065-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>(A–I) RT97 stained neurites from spinal cord slices cultured within a 3D collagen matrix alone, and with addition of NGF/NT3 or brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) (A–C); with 20% laminin, plus NGF/NT3 or BDNF (D–F); and with 20% fibronectin, plus NGF/NT3 or BDNF (G–I); plots representing maximum neurite length in the different DRG culture conditions (J); quantification of the number of neurites grown at increasing distance from the DRG body, dashed line represents the values for COL control group (100%) (K); and plots of the quantified area under each curve of K graph (L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Data expressed as mean ± SEM. * p &lt; 0.05 and *** p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-18-00065-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-18-00065-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>(A–I) RT97 stained neurites from DRG neurons cultured within a 3D collagen matrix alone, and with addition of NGF/NT3 or BDNF (A–C); with 20% laminin, plus NGF/NT3 or BDNF (D–F); and with 20% fibronectin, plus NGF/NT3 or BDNF (G–I); (J) plots representing maximum neurite length in the different culture conditions, dashed line represents the values for COL control group (100%); (K) quantification of the number of neurites grown at increasing distance from the cord slice; and (L) plots of the quantified area under each curve of K graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Data expressed as mean ± SEM. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-18-00065-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-18-00065-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>(A–F) Representative micrographs of neurons retrolabeled with FG in the spinal cord (A–C); and DRG (D–F) of rats after sciatic nerve section and repair with a nerve conduit filled: with COL (A,D); LM + MP.NGF/NT3 (B,E); or FN + MP.BDNF (C,F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>(G–H) Histogram of the number of regenerated motor neurons in the spinal cord (G) and sensory neurons in the DRG (H) in the short term (20 days after injury) study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>(I,J) Histogram of the number of regenerated motor neurons in the spinal cord (I) and sensory neurons in the DRG (J) after application of FG retrotracer at the ankle level 75 days after injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Data expressed as mean ± SEM. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-18-00065-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-18-00065-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>FN + MP.BDNF and LM + MP.NGF/NT3 enhance motor and sensory functional recovery, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>(A,B) Mean amplitude of the CMAP in TA (A) and PL (B) muscles during follow-up. ** p &lt; 0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001 FN + MP.BDNF vs. all other groups referenced by the color of the star. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>(C) Pinprick score in the different groups during follow-up; * p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>(D) Latency of withdrawal response to thermal stimuli in the lateral part of the paw during follow-up; ** p &lt; 0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001 LM + MP.NGF/NT3 vs. all other groups referenced by the color of the star. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>(E–J) Representative images of plantar pads immunolabeled against PGP in: an intact rat (E); COL (F); LM (G); LM + MP.NGF/NT3 (H); FN (I); and FN + MP.BDNF (J) treated animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Insets: Detail of axons stained with PGP innervating epidermis and SGs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>(K,L) Percentage of reinnervated IENF (K) and reinnervated SGs (L) vs. intact values. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt;0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Data is presented as mean ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-18-00065-g004a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-18-00065-g004b"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ijms-18-00065-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-18-00065-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Experimental conditions evaluated in the in vitro and in vivo studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>N </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Description </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>In Vitro Condition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Collagen </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>COL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Collagen + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>COL + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel supplemented with NGF and NT3 (25 + 25 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Collagen + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>COL + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel supplemented with BDNF (50 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Laminin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>LM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% laminin type I </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Laminin + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>LM + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% laminin type I and NGF + NT3 (25 + 25 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Laminin + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>LM + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% laminin type I and BDNF (50 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Fibronectin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>FN </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% fibronectin </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Fibronectin + NGF/NT-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>FN + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% fibronectin and NGF + NT3 (25 + 25 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Fibronectin + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>FN + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% fibronectin and BDNF (50 ng/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>In Vivo Condition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Collagen </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>COL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Laminin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>LM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% laminin type I </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Collagen + NGF/NT3 * </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>MP.NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing NGF + NT3 (1 + 1 µg/mL) encapsulated in PLGA microspheres </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Laminin + NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>LM + MP.NGF/NT3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% laminin type I and NGF + NT3 (1 + 1 µg/mL) encapsulated in PLGA microspheres </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Fibronectin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>FN </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% fibronectin </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Collagen + BDNF * </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>MP.BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 2 µg/mL of BDNF encapsulated in PLGA microspheres </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Fibronectin + BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>FN + MP.BDNF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Collagen type I (3 mg/mL) gel containing 20% fibronectin and 2 µg/ml of BDNF encapsulated in PLGA microspheres </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>* Only in the short term study.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
