<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5100220</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27825309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-1917-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Tuberculosis treatment outcomes of six and eight month treatment regimens in districts of Southwestern Ethiopia: a comparative cross-sectional study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>Abyot</given-names></name><address><email>abytoasres@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jerene</surname><given-names>Degu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deressa</surname><given-names>Wakgari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Public Health, College of Health Sciences, MizanTepi University, Mizan Aman, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Management Science for Health, HEAL TB project, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Preventive Medicine, School of Public Health, College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>653</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>A switch of continuation phase tuberculosis (TB) treatment regimen from Ethambutol (E) and Isoniazid (H) combination for 6 months (6EH) to Rifampicin (R) and Isoniazid (H) combination for 4 months (4RH) was recommended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, the effect of the regimen switch in Ethiopian setting is not known. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>A comparative cross-sectional study among 790 randomly selected new cases of TB (395 each treated with 4RH and 6EH during the continuation phase) was conducted in nine health centers and one hospital in three zones in southwestern Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Data were abstracted from the standard unit TB register composed of standard case and treatment outcome definitions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using STATA version 13 where binary logistic regression was fitted to identify independent predictors of unsuccessful treatment outcomes at 5 % significance level. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Over all, 695 (88 %) of the patients had a successful treatment outcome with statistically significant difference (85.3 % vs 90.6 %, p = 0.02) among the 6HE and 4RH regimens, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>After adjusting for confounders, 4RH continuation phase treatment regimen adjusted odds ratio (AOR) [(95 % confidence interval (CI)) 0.55 (0.34,0.89)], age [AOR (95 % CI 1.02 (1.001,1.022)], rural residence [AOR (95 % CI) 2.1 (1.18,3.75)] Human Immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positives [AOR (95 % CI) 2.39 (1.12,5.07)] and increased weight at the end of the second month [AOR (95 % CI 0.28 (0.11,0.72)] independently predicted treatment outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The switch of continuation phase TB treatment regimen from 6EH to 4RH has brought better treatment outcomes which imply applicability of the recommendation in high prevalent and resource constrained settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it should be maintained and augmented through further studies on its impact among the older, rural residents and HIV positives. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12879-016-1917-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd><kwd>Continuation phase</kwd><kwd>treatment regimen</kwd><kwd>Treatment outcome</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Addis Ababa university</institution></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Mizan Tepi University</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In the history of tuberculosis (TB) control, discovery of chemotherapy [1] brought about dramatic changes in patient survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Before the advent of chemotherapy, 30–40 % of TB cases used to die within a year and 50–70 % within 5–7 years after the onset of TB illness [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Introduction of chemotherapy resulted in cure and reduction of mortality for majority of TB cases [1, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, shortly after the therapy, resistance to drug and poor adherence by patients were reported [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the first standard combination therapy for 12 months comprised of Thiacetazone (T), Isoniazid(H) and streptomycin(S) for the first 2 months (2STH) followed by T and H for 10 months(10TH) was issued [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Subsequent to the introduction of rifampicin (R), effective short-course chemotherapy regimens for less than 12 months became standard therapy [2, 5–7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The short-course regimens comprised of an initial, or bactericidal, phase called intensive that aimed to kill bacilli and make patients non infectious and a continuation or sterilizing phase which eliminates persisting mycobacteria to prevent relapse [1, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Thus evidence based combinations of drugs for different categories of cases have been recommended for the two phases across the different regimens [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Introduction of Rifampicin has shortened TB treatment duration [1, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In 1991, an eight months treatment regimen composed of 2 months intensive with Isoniazid(H), Rifampicin (R), Pyrazinamide(Z) and Ethambutol(E) (2RHZE/S) and 6 months continuation (6HE) phases were recommended for all new cases of TB across the world [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>To avoid resistance to the most potent drugs, isoniazid and rifampcin and ensure patient adherence, directly observed treatment short course (DOTS) strategy was launched in 1994 [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Later in 2003, a directly observed intensive phase treatment followed by two continuation phase regimens, 6 months of isoniazid plus ethambutol (6HE) or 4 months of isoniazid plus rifampicin (4HR) were recommended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The 4HR continuation phase treatment regimen needed to be observed throughout the treatment period whereas the 6EH regimen relied on self administered treatment [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>As a result, regimens without rifampicin had been considered safer in developing countries owing to irregular treatments and high absentee rates [1, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, the latest World Health Organization (WHO) guideline recommends 2-month initial phase of (2RHZE) and a 4-month continuation phase (4RH) for the treatment of virtually all forms of new TB cases across the globe [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The government of Ethiopia has adopted the switch of 4HR continuation phase TB treatment for all new cases and accommodated in the latest TB treatment guideline [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Though global strategies are relevant, investigation of the applicability to the local settings is highly required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A continuation phase treatment with 4HR regimen elsewhere has demonstrated lower unsuccessful treatment outcomes and costs as compared to 6EH continuation phase [12–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>But well designed studies evaluating effects of the introduction of 4RH for the continuation phase TB treatment in high TB burden and resource limited settings like Ethiopia are limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Thus, we compared treatment outcomes of TB cases who received 4RH and 6EH continuation phase regimens under routine program condition in high burden and resource limited setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Our objective was to compare baseline patients’ bacteriologic, socio-demographics, clinical characteristics and treatment outcomes among those TB patients treated with the 4RH and 6EH continuation phase treatment regimens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Study setting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We conducted this study in ten health facilities (one hospital and nine health centres) in three remote zones of Southern Nation Nationalities and Peoples Region (SNNPR), one of the nine regions in Ethiopia with about 18million population [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Ethiopia is among the 22 TB High Burden Countries (HBC) where 230,000 incident cases of which 147,592 (64 %) were notified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In the same year, 16100 deaths and 90 % treatment success among the smear positives cases registered in 2011 were reported [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The country has adopted and implemented the DOTS strategy for the treatment of all forms of TB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Accordingly new cases of TB had been treated with directly observed RHZE combinations for the first 2 months (2RHZE) followed by self administered EH combinations for six months (6EH) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>As of the end of 2011, the continuation phase treatment was switched from 6EH to 4RH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus the regimen became directly observed 2RHZE/4RH combinations for all forms of new TB cases throughout the 6 months treatment period [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The three study Zones, Bench Maji, Kaffa and Sheka are located at the southwestern border of the SNNPR where about 2,064,102 peoples reside [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The zones (an administrative unit that liaison weredas with the region) are organized in to four town administrations and 26 weredas (lowest administrative unit closer to the community) those have three hospitals and 65 health centers those provide TB DOTS services for free. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>However, the three hospitals and only 27 health centers were providing TB/Human Immunodeficeincy Virus (HIV) collaborative activities [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Study design and sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A comparative cross-sectional study among TB cases treated with 2RHZE/6EH and 2RHZE/4RH regimens was carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>New cases registered between 2008 and 2014 were eligible of which those aged above 15 years were studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Sample size was estimated using the Stat Calc program of Epi Info version 7 [21] with 95 % confidence level, 80 % power and ratio of 6EH to 4RH (r = 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, 512 cases (256 from each group) was required to detect 7 % difference [12] in the proportion of unsuccessful outcome among the 6EH and 4RH groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Finally, considering the design effect of 1.5 and 10 % missing records, a total of 846 cases were required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The samples were selected through proportional allocation to the three zones followed by selection of weredas and health facilities from the zone using probability proportional to size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The allocation and selection was made based on total number of cases reported from the weredas and health facilities during 2008 through 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Lastly, cases from the selected health facilities were selected randomly using SPSS statistical software using TB unit number of the cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Data were extracted from a standard unit TB register recommended by the WHO [11, 19, 22] using extraction format prepared for the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Thus patients’ baseline attributes (age, gender, residence, sputum smear, type of TB, HIV status) and follow-up measures (sputum smear, weight, drug regimen and treatment outcomes) were extracted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The following standard case and outcome definitions were adopted and used for the study [11, 19]. New case of TB a patient who never had treatment for TB, or had been on anti-TB treatment for less than four weeks in the past Other cases are those patients who do not fulfill the criteria for new, relapse, and return after default or treatment after failure. Cured: a patient whose sputum smear or culture was positive at the beginning of the treatment but who was smear or culture-negative in the last month of treatment and on at least one previous occasion. Treatment completed: completed treatment but does not have a negative sputum smear or culture result in the last month of treatment and on at least one previous occasion. Treatment failure: a patient whose sputum smear or culture is positive at 5 months or later during treatment or patients found to harbor Multidrug Resistant (MDR) TB strain at any point of time during the treatment, whether they are smear-negative or -positive. Died: a patient who dies for any reason during the course of TB treatment. Defaulter/loss to follow-up: a patient who has been on treatment for at least 4 weeks and interrupted treatment for eight or more consecutive weeks. Successful treatment: a treatment that ends up in cure or treatment completion Unsuccessful treatment: a treatment that end up in treatment default or loss to follow up, treatment failure or death. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The extracted data were checked for consistency and completeness and entered in to Epinfo version 7 that later exported to STATA 12 [23] for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Data were described separately for the two groups (6EH and 4RH) using frequencies, mean, standard deviations and tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Besides, crude comparisons of the baseline and follow up measures among the 6EH and 4RH groups were made using chi square (x 2) or t-tests as appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, bivariate and multiple binary logistic regression analysis were made to compute crude and adjusted odds ratios respectively between the explanatory and outcome variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Multiple logistic regression model was fitted with those variables having p ≤ 0.2 on bivariate analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Finally, statistical significance was judged at p &lt; 0.05 and/or 95 % confidence interval (CI) of odds ratio (OR) excluding one. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Ethical considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>We received ethical approval from the institutional review board of the College of Health Sciences at Addis Ababa University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, anonymous patient data were extracted from routine service registry upon permission from the respective institutions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Demographic and baseline clinical characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We retrieved 846 patient records of which 790 (93.4 %) with complete outcome records [395 each treated with 2RHZE/6HE and 2RHZE/4RHregimens respectively] were described and analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The mean age of the patients was 30.8 (31.5 vs 30.9 years, p = 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>5) respectively, for those treated with 6HE and 4HR (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>More than half, 56.6 % and 55.7 % of the patients were male and reside in rural areas, respectively, with no statistically significant difference among the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>With regard to the patient profile, 86.8 % and 77%were registered at health center and had pulmonary TB, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Of the patients, 765 (96.8 %) were new cases (378 treated with 6EH vs387 with 4RH regimen) and the rest ((25 (3.2 %) (17 from 6EH vs 8 from 4RH) were transferred in and other cases treated with new case regimen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Human Immunodeficiency virus (HIV) test result was available for 612 (77.5 %) with statistically significant difference among the two groups [283 (71.6 %) from 6EH and 329 (83.3 %) from 4RH, p &lt; 0.001]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Among those tested HIV positives, 44 (57.1 %) received either Cotrimoxazole Prophylactic Therapy (CPT) or Antiretroviral Therapy (ART) with no statistically significant difference among the regimens 24 (64.9 %) from 6EH and 20 (50 %), p = 0.2.Table 1Demographic and clinical characteristics of the tuberculosis patients registered between, 2008–2014, Southwest EthiopiaVariableContinuation phase treatment regimenTotal P value6EH (n = 395) n (%)4RH (n = 395) n (%)Age (years)Mean ± SDa 31.1 ± 12.930.5 ± 11.930.8 ± 12.40.5GenderMale221 (55.9)226 (57.2)447 (56.6)0.7Female174 (44.1)169 (42.8)343 (43.4)ResidenceUrban175 (44.3)175 (44.3)350 (44.3)1Rural220 (55.7)220 (55.7)440 (55.7)ZoneKaffa106 (26.8)104 (26.3)210 (26.6)0.9Bench Maji206 (52.2)203 (26.3)409 (51.8)Sheka83 (21.0)88 (22.3)171 (21.6)Treatment centerHospital55 (13.9)49 (12.4)104 (13.2)0.5Health center340 (86.1)346 (87.6)686 (86.8)Baseline weightMean ± SDa 47.6 ± 8.648.4 ± 8.548 ± 8.50.2Baseline sputum smearPositive186 (47.1)173 (43.8)359 (45.4)0.6Negative151 (38.2)165 (41.8)316 (40)Unknown58 (14.7)57 (14.4)115 (14.6)Type of TBPulmonary303 (76.7305 (77.2)608 (77.0)0.9Positive186 (47.1)173 (43.8)359 (45.4)Negative117 (30.4)132 (33.4)252 (31.9)Extra pulmonary92 (23.3)90 (22.8)179 (23)HIV statusPositive37 (9.4)40 (10.1)77 (9.7)&lt;0.001Negative246 (62.3)289 (73.2)535 (67.7)Unknown112 (28.4)66 (16.7)178 (22.5)Received CPTb (n = 77)Yes18 (48.6)17 (42.5)35 (45.5)0.6Received CPT or ARTc (n = 77)Yes6 (16.2)6 (15.0)12 (15.6)0.8Received ART (n = 77)Yes12 (32.4)9 (22.5)21 (27.3)0.3Baseline sputum smearPositive186 (47.1)173 (43.8)359 (45.4)0.6Negative151 (38.2)165 (41.8)316 (40)Unknown58 (14.7)57 (14.4)115 (14.6) aStandard deviation,b CPT Cotrimoxazole prophylactic therapy, c ART antiretroviral therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Patient follow-ups and treatment outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A total of 695 (88 %) of the patients had successful treatment outcomes with statistically significant difference (85.3 % vs 90.6 %, p = 0.02) among the 6HE and 4RH groups, respectively (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A total of, 324 (90.3 %), 208 (85.4 %) and 163 (91.1 %) of pulmonary positive, pulmonary negative and extra pulmonary TB cases respectively had successful outcomes with statistically significant difference, P = 0.03. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Besides, statistically significant differences in successful outcomes, 64 (83.1 %), 482 (90.1 %) and 149 (83.7 %, p = 0.005 were also found among HIV positive, HIV negatives and unknown HIV status TB cases, respectively.Table 2Patient follow-up measures and treatment outcomes of TB patients registered during 2008–2014, Southwest EthiopiaVariablesContinuation phase treatment regimen6EH (n = 395) n (%)4RH (n = 395) n (%)Total N (%) P valueWeight at 2nd monthMean ± SD49.9 ± 8.950.8 ± 8.250.4 ± 8.60.2Weight at 5th monthMean ± SD51.4 ± 8.651.3 ± 7.351.3 ± 7.90.9Weight at 6/7th monthMean ± SD51.1 ± 8.952.5 ± 6.551.7 ± 7.90.3Change in weight at 2nd monthNot increased49 (12.4)61 (15.4)110 (13.9)0.4Increased191 (48.4)177 (44.8)368 (46.6)Unknown155 (39.2)157 (39.7)312 (39.5)Sputum smear end of 2nd month (n = 359)Positive4 (2.2)2 (1.2)6 (1.7)0.09Negative130 (69.9)138 (79.8)268 (74.7)Unknown52 (28)33 (19.1)85 (23.7)Sputum smear end of 5th month (n = 359)Positive1 (0.5)0 (0)1 (0.3)0.03Negative83 (44.6)100 (57.8)183 (51)Unknown102 (54.8)73 (42.2)175 (48.7)Sputum smear end of 6/7th month (n = 359)Positive0000.8Negative94 (50.5)85 (49.1)179 (49.9)Unknown92 (49.5)88 (50.9)180 (50.1)Sputum smear done during treatment (n = 359)No44 (23.7)33 (19.1)77 (21.4)0.3At least once142 (76.3)140 (80.9)282 (78.6)Continuation phase visitMean ± SD5.8 ± 1.15.4 ± 3.10.09Treatment outcomeSuccessful337 (85.3)358 (90.6)695 (88)0.02Cured77 (19.5)85 (21.5)162 (20.5)Completed260 (65.8)273 (69.1)533 (67)Unsuccessful58 (14.7)37 (9.4)95 (12)Died28 (7.1)18 (4.6)46 (5.8)Defaulted29 (7.3)19 (4.8)48 (6.1)Failure1 (0.3)01 (0.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Measurements of patient weight at the end of second, fifth and sixth/seventh months of treatment were available for 504 (63.8 %), 145 (18.4 %) and 141 (17.8 %) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Thus, 368 (46.6 %) or (48.4 % from 6EH and 44.8 % from 4RH, p = 0.4) have gained some amount of weight at the end of second month of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, of those initially smear positive pulmonary TB cases, 78.6 % had undergone sputum follow up examination at least once after the diagnosis (76.3 % among 6HE and 80.9 % among 4HR, p = 0.3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Thus sputum smear results at the end of second, fifth and sixth/seventh months of treatment were available for274 (76.3 %), 184 (51.3 %) and 179 (49.9 %) cases respectively with no statistically significant differences among the 6EH and 4RH regimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The majority of the smear positives (69.9 % vs 79.8 % respectively from the 6EH and 4RH regimens, p = 0.4) converted to negative at the end of second month treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Factors associated with unsuccessful treatment outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In bivariate analysis patient age, residence, zone, weight change at the end of the second month of treatment, sputum smear follow-up and continuation phase regimen are associated with treatment success at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>But, in multivariate analysis 4RH continuation phase treatment regimen [AOR (95 % CI) 0.55 (0.34,0.89)], patient age [AOR (95 % CI) 1.02 (1.001,1.022)], rural residence [AOR (95 % CI) 2.1 (1.18,3.75)], treated at health center [AOR (95 % CI) 0.37 (0.14,0.97)], HIV positives [AOR (95 % CI 2.38 (1.12,5.07)], gained weight at the end of the second month [AOR (95 % CI) 0.28 (0.11,0.72)] independently predicted unsuccessful treatment outcome (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The odds of unsuccessful outcome was higher among the older, rural residents, HIV positives and unknown weight change at the end of second month treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The odds of having unsuccessful outcome increase by 2 % for every one year increase in age (AOR = 1.02).On the other hand, treated with 4RH continuation phase regimen, being treated at health center and weight gain at the end of second month have lower likelihood of unsuccessful outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Patients put on 4RH continuation phase of treatment regimen are 45 % less likely to have unsuccessful outcome compared to those put on 6EH regimen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Patients treated at health center have about 63 % lower odds of unsuccessful outcome as compared to those treated at hospitals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>HIV co infected TB patients have more than two fold higher risk of unsuccessful outcomes compared to HIV negatives (AOR = 2.38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Those patients gained weight at the end of the second month of treatment have 72 % lower odds of unsuccessful outcomes compared to those with reduced or unchanged weight (AOR = 0.28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A subgroup analysis among smear positive pulmonary cases showed having a sputum checkup at least once during treatment independently predicted 96 % lower odds of unsuccessful outcomes compared to those unchecked (AOR 0.04 (95 % CI, 0.01–0.12), P &lt; 0.001) (Additional file 1).Table 3Factors associated with unsuccessful treatment outcomes among TB patients registered during 2008–2014, Southwestern EthiopiaVariablesTreatment outcomesOdds ratio (OR)Unsuccessful n (%)Successful n (%)Crude OR95 % CIa Adjusted OR95 % CIAge (years)Mean(SD)33.5 (14)30.4 (12.0)1.02 (1.002,1.03) 1.02 (1.001,1.022) GenderMale60 (13.4)387 (86.6)11Female35 (10.2)308 (89.8)0.73 (0.47.1.14)0.63 (0.38,1.03)ResidenceUrban32 (9.1)318 (90.9)11Rural63 (14.3)377 (85.7)1.66 (1.06,2.61) 2.1 (1.18,3.75) ZoneKaffa34 (16.2)176 (83.8)11Bench Maji50 (12.2)359 (87.8)0.72 (0.45,1.14)1.41 (0.73,2.75)Sheka11 (6.4)160 (93.6)0.36 (0.17,0.73)1.2 (0.44,3.32)Treatment centerHospital17 (16.3)87 (83.7)11HC78 (11.4)608 (88.6)0.66 (0.37,1.16) 0.37 (0.14,0.97) Type of TBPulmonary78 (12.8)530 (87.2)11EPTBb 17 (9.3)165 (90.7)0.70 (0.40,1.22)0.57 (0.32,1.04)HIV statusNegative53 (9.9)482 (90.1)11Positive13 (16.9)64 (83.1)1.85 (0.95,3.57) 2.39 (1.12,5.07) Unknown29 (16.3)178 (83.7)1.77 (1.08,2.88) 2.26 (1.23,4.11) Weight change end of 2nd monthNo increase11 (8.2)357 (91.8)11Increased9 (3)101 (97)0.35 (0.14,0.86) 0.28 (0.11,0.72) Unknown75 (24)237 (76)3.55 (1.71,7.37) 3.48 (1.60,7.54) Continuation phase regimen6EH58 (14.7)337 (85.3)114RH37 (9.4)358 (90.6)0.60 (0.39,0.93) 0.55 (0.34,0.89)  aConfidence interval, bExtra pulmonary Tuberculosis, bold figures indicate statisticaly significant at p&lt;0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Treatment outcomes among TB patients treated with RHZE for the first 2 months, followed by HE for 6 months (2RHZE/6EH) and RH for 4 months (2RHZE/4RH) was compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Both groups of the cases had no statistically significant difference with respect to socio-demographic, baseline clinical, bacteriologic and follow up measures that depict comparability of the groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The comparison was made between regimens used during the continuation phase treatment (4RH vs 6EH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Thus a lower rate of unsuccessful outcomes was reported among those treated with 4RH continuation phase regimen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant difference in treatment outcomes where lower unsuccessful treatment outcome (9.4 % vs 14.7 %) was observed among patients treated with 4RH and 6EH regimen respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a study conducted in Nigeria [14] reported higher odds of unsuccessful outcome among those treated with 6EH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>This could be due to the differences in length and type of drugs used during the continuation phase treatment those influence adherence and ultimate outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Studies reported that reduced continuation phase (from 6EH to 4HR) treatment is associated with lower cost and expected mortality [12] that enhance successful treatment outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, use of rifampcin for longer period of time during the treatment of TB is associated with better outcomes [13] that might be related with efficacy of the drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The finding implies the adoption [11] of the latest WHO recommendation [7] in high prevalent and resource constrained settings is working well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Apart from the treatment regimens, patient attribute like age and residence independently predicted treatment outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We found that age had an inverse relation with unsuccessful outcome where the odds of unsuccessful outcome increase with age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Several studies also reported that older patients were more likely to have unsuccessful outcomes than younger [24–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This could be due to higher risk of age related co morbid situations those lead to poor adherence and outcomes [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Patients residing in rural areas had higher risk of unsuccessful outcomes which could be attributed to the low access to TB care and unfavorable living conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The findings imply need for focused intervention targeted to those older age groups and rural dwellers besides the treatment regimen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Monitoring of patient weight and sputum are among the recommended follow-up measures required for TB patients on treatment [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The results of both weight and sputum monitoring are used to adjust for drug dose and predict outcomes of the treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The proportion of smear positive patients converted to negative at the end of the intensive phase has been taken among indicators of TB programme performance [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>However, only small proportion of patients had documented results of the weight and sputum follow-ups particularly at the later periods of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Consistent to findings from African settings [29] majority of those patients undergone sputum checkup during treatment converted to negative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Patients gained some amount of weight at the end of second month treatment had lower risk of unsuccessful outcomes which is consistent with other studies [30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This could be explained by the fact that weight gain marks some level of improvement from the TB illness including reduced appetite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In addition, changes in weight while on treatment might be an indication of appropriateness of the drug dose to treat the illness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>On the other hand those with unknown weight change at the end of first two months treatment had higher odds of unsuccessful outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This might have occurred due to possible misclassification of cases with reduced or remains unchanged to unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The weight change might be unknown due to patients’ treatment interruption subsequent to treatment default or death those constitute unsuccessful outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>So that patient’s status of weight during treatment might be left undetermined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Having sputum checkup at least once during treatment among initially smear positives predicted lower risk of unsuccessful outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>However, reviews showed low sensitivity and modest specificity of sputum results at the end of intensive phase to predict failure and relapse [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, detection of sputum positive during treatment trigger further patient assessment that influence treatment regimens and ultimate outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Hence, the routine sputum monitoring adopted by the country [11] during treatment should be improved as it is an indicator of program performance and trigger for patient assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Consistent with other studies [33, 34], HIV positive TB patients are more likely to have unsuccessful outcomes compared to those negatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This could be due to multifaceted influences of HIV on TB diagnosis and response to TB treatment those negatively affect the outcomes of TB treatment [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Consequently, collaborative services have been recommended in order to curb the influence of HIV on TB and vice versa [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Evidences from systematic review in African context supported the recommendation and reported better outcomes among concurrently screened and managed TB and HIV infected patients [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, we found no statistically significant difference in treatment success among those infected TB patients provided with CPT and/or ART. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The indifference could be explained by the low uptake of integrated TB/HIV collaborative services among the studied patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In this study, more than three quarter of the patients were offered HIV test which is little higher than the national average of 65 % [18] and 9.7 % TB/HIV co infected patients which is almost similar to the national average of 10 %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, only few HIV co infected patients (45 % on CPT and 27.3 % on ART) were found to have documented service provision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The discrepancies could be due to differences in reporting periods where the national average is a single year attainment but that of this study is over a period of six years including the nationally reported year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Over all, the targets set for the TB/HIV service collaboration has not yet met which calls for in depth understanding and focused intervention that suit local settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, unknown HIV status predicted higher odds of unsuccessful outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>This could be due to possible misclassification of HIV positive cases those predict worse outcome in to unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The study is limited to control for changes in medical resources, polices and quality of care across the study periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Since only few variables were captured on the register, we could not control for possible confounding effect of socioeconomic, lifestyle and co morbid illness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Furthermore resistance pattern of the treatment regimens could not be evaluated which is recommended for the assessment of impact of treatment regimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>On the other hand the random selection of relatively large sample from both groups minimized risk of selection bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The groups treated with 4RH and 6EH had insignificant differences with regard to baseline and follow-up clinical and bacteriologic attributes that enhanced comparability of the groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Besides, we extracted data from a standardized routine programme register that reflect operational reality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In general, our study is valid and can apply in similar settings given the limitations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the switch of continuation phase TB treatment regimen for new cases from 6EH to 4RH has brought better treatment outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The findings verified the applicability of latest WHO recommendation and national adoption to the high prevalent and resource constrained settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the unsuccessful outcome among the older, rural dwellers and HIV positives is higher independent of the treatment regimen that need further investigation and focused intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the recommended switch of treatment regimen should be maintained and progressively assessed for outcomes, including drug resistance survey or surveillance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Moreover, further studies should be carried out on the impact of treatment regimens among older, rural residents and HIV positives. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec12"><title>Additional file</title><p>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12879_2016_1917_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Table 4: Factors associated with unsuccessful treatment outcome among smear positive pulmonary TB cases registered during 2008-2014, southwestern Ethiopia (n=359). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Table 5: Factors associated with unsuccessful outcome among clinically diagnosed (smear negative 10.1186/s12879-016-1917-0 pulmonary and extra pulmonary) TB cases registered during 2008-2014, Southwestern Ethiopia (n=431). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 17 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media>
</p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ART</term><def><p>Antiretroviral therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPT</term><def><p>Cotrimoxazole prophylactic therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DOTS</term><def><p>Directly Observed Treatment Short course</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EH</term><def><p>Ethambutol and Isoniazid combination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HIV</term><def><p>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>Odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RH</term><def><p>Rifampicin and Isoniazid combination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RHZE</term><def><p>Rifampicin, Isoniazid, Pyrazinamide and Ethambutol combination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TB</term><def><p>Tuberculosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We are indebted to Addis Ababa and MizanTepi Universities for financial and material supports for the study. We are also grateful to the staffs of study districts and health facilities for their all rounded supports during the data abstraction.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>Financial and material supports were obtained from Addis Ababa and Mizan Tepi Universities based in Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets analyzed during the current study will be available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>AA conceived, designed the study, analyzed data and prepared manuscript. WD and DJ critically reviewed for intellectual content of the study protocol and manuscript as primary and co-supervisors respectively. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board of the college of health sciences at Addis Ababa University (protocol number 045/14/sph). Since we did not carry out patient interview or examination, consent of participation was not sought as the patients were not on treatment at the time of study. Accordingly an anonymous patient data from routine service registry (unit TB register) were abstracted upon formal permissions of the health facilities.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>1.HillABSuspended judgment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Memories of the British Streptomycin Trial in Tuberculosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The first randomized clinical trialControl Clin Trials1990112777910.1016/0197-2456(90)90001-I<?supplied-pmid 2161313?>2161313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>2.ArandottirTTuberculosis and public health: Policy and principles of Tuberculosis control2009ParisInternational Union Against Tuberculosis and Lung Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>3.British Medical council. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Streptomycin for treatment of pulmonary tuberculosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Br Med J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>1948;2(4582):769–82. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>4.CroftonJMitchisonDAStreptomycin resistance in pulmonary tuberculosisBr Med J1948245881009101510.1136/bmj.2.4588.1009<?supplied-pmid 18100441?>18100441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>5.WHOTreatment of Tuberculosis: Guidelines for National Programmes2003GenevaWorld Health Organization </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>6.WHOGuidelines for tuberculosis treatment in adults and children in national tuberculosis programmes1991GenevaWorld Health Organization </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>7.World Health OrganizationTreatment of tuberculosis: guidelines2010GenevaWorld Health Organization </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>8.Fauce KB, Jameson HL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In: Kasper DL, Fauci AS, Longo DL, Braunwald E, Hauser SL, Jameson JL, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Harrison’s principles of Internal Medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In tuberculosis,16 edn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>USA: McGraw-Hill companies Medical publishing division; 2005. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>2783. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>9.MoriTUchimuraKShimaoTImpact of introducing rifampicin for the treatment of tuberculosis during the 1970's in JapanKekkaku [Tuberculosis]2013884417422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>10.World Health OrganizationWHO tuberculosis control program: Framework for effective tuberculosis control1994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>11.Federal Ministry of Health of EthiopiaGuidelines for clinical and programmatic management of TB, Leprosy and TB/HIV in Ethiopia20125Addis AbabaEthiopian Federal Ministry of Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>12.ManabeYCHermansSMLamordeMCastelnuovoBMullinsCDKuznikARifampicin for continuation phase tuberculosis treatment in Uganda: a cost-effectiveness analysisPLoS One201276e3918710.1371/journal.pone.0039187<?supplied-pmid 22723960?>22723960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>13.MenziesDBenedettiAPaydarAMartinIRoyceSPaiMVernonALienhardtCBurmanWEffect of duration and intermittency of rifampin on tuberculosis treatment outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysisPLoS Med200969e100014610.1371/journal.pmed.1000146<?supplied-pmid 19753109?>19753109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>14.UkwajaKNOshiSNAlobuIOshiDCSix- vs. eight-month anti-tuberculosis regimen for pulmonary tuberculosis under programme conditionsInt J Tuberc Lung Dis201519329530110.5588/ijtld.14.0494<?supplied-pmid 25686137?>25686137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>15.FoxWEllardGAMitchisonDAStudies on the treatment of tuberculosis undertaken by the British Medical Research Council tuberculosis units, 1946–1986, with relevant subsequent publicationsInt J Tuberc Lung Dis1999323127910094325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>16.Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia Central Statistical Agency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Population Projection of Ethiopia for All Regions At Wereda Level from 2014 – 2017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Addis Ababa: CSA; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>17.Federal Ministry of Health of Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Annual performance report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In: Health sector development programme iv. Addis Ababa: Federal Ministry of Health; 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>18.World Health Organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Global tuberculosis report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>France: WHO; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>19.Federal Ministry of Health of EthiopiaTuberculosis, Leprosy and TB/HIV Prevention and Control Programme Manual20084Addis AbabaMinistry of Health of Ethiopia </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>20.Southern Nation Nationalities Peoples Region Health Bureau (2014). "Health profile of Southern Nation Nationalities Peoples Region." Tuberculosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>2015, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.SNNPRHB.gov.et">http://www.SNNPRHB.gov.et</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Accessed 28 Oct 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>21.Centers for Disease Control and Prevention(CDC) (2011). "Epi Info™, a database and statistics program for public health professionals."  7. from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/epiinfo">http://www.cdc.gov/epiinfo</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>22.World Health Organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Definitions and reporting framework for tuberculosis – 2013 revision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Switzerland: WHO Library Cataloguing-in-Publication Data; 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>23.StataCorpStata: Release 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Statistical Software201113College StationStataCorp LP </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>24.TessemaBMucheABekeleAReissigDEmmrichFSackUTreatment outcome of tuberculosis patients at Gondar University Teaching Hospital, Northwest Ethiopia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>A five - year retrospective studyBMC Public Health2009937110.1186/1471-2458-9-371<?supplied-pmid 19799801?>19799801 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>25.Munoz-SellartMCuevasLETumatoMMeridYYassinMAFactors associated with poor tuberculosis treatment outcome in the Southern Region of EthiopiaInt J Tuberc Lung Dis2010148973979<?supplied-pmid 20626941?>20626941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>26.BerheGEnquselassieFAssefaATreatment outcome of smear-positive pulmonary tuberculosis patients in Tigray Region, Northern EthiopiaBMC Public Health20121253710.1186/1471-2458-12-537<?supplied-pmid 22824524?>22824524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>27.Feng J-Y, Su W-J, Chiu Y-C, Huang S-F, Lin Y-Y, Huang R-M, Lin C-H, Hwang J-J, Lee J-J, Yu M-C, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Initial presentations predict mortality in pulmonary tuberculosis patients - a prospective observational study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>PloS One. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>2011;6(9). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>28.WangCSChenHCYangCJWangWYChongIWHwangJJHuangMSThe impact of age on the demographic, clinical, radiographic characteristics and treatment outcomes of pulmonary tuberculosis patients in TaiwanInfection200836433534010.1007/s15010-008-7199-8<?supplied-pmid 18629436?>18629436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>29.Kayigamba FR, Bakker MI, Mugisha V, Gasana M, Schim van der Loeff MF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Sputum completion and conversion rates after intensive phase of tuberculosis treatment: an assessment of the Rwandan control program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>BMC Res Notes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>2012;5(357). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>30.Bernabe-Ortiz A, Carcamo CP, Sanchez JF, Rios J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Weight variation over time and its association with tuberculosis treatment outcome: a longitudinal analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>PLoS One. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>2011;6(4). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>31.HoaNBLauritsenJMRiederHLChanges in body weight and tuberculosis treatment outcome in Viet NamInt J Tuberc Lung Dis2013171616610.5588/ijtld.12.0369<?supplied-pmid 23146565?>23146565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>32.HorneDJRoyceSEGoozeLNaritaMHopewellPCNahidPSteingartKRSputum monitoring during tuberculosis treatment for predicting outcome: a systematic review and meta-analysisLancet Infect Dis201010638739410.1016/S1473-3099(10)70071-2<?supplied-pmid 20510279?>20510279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>33.DanielOJAlausaOKTreatment outcome of TB/HIV positive and TB/HIV negative patients on directly observed treatment, short course (DOTS) in Sagamu, NigeriaNiger J Med2006153222226<?supplied-pmid 17111747?>17111747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>34.ShawenoDWorkuATuberculosis treatment survival of HIV positive TB patients on directly observed treatment short-course in Southern Ethiopia: a retrospective cohort studyBMC Res Notes2012568210.1186/1756-0500-5-682<?supplied-pmid 23234241?>23234241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>35.MaherDHarriesAGetahunHTuberculosis and HIV interaction in sub-Saharan Africa: impact on patients and programmes; implications for policiesTrop Med Int Health200510873474210.1111/j.1365-3156.2005.01456.x<?supplied-pmid 16045459?>16045459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>36.World Health Organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>WHO policy on collaborative TB/HIV activities Guidelines for national programmes and other stakeholders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Italy: WHO Library Cataloguing-in-Publication Data; 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>37.UyeiJCoetzeeDMacinkoJGuttmacherSIntegrated delivery of HIV and tuberculosis services in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic reviewLancet Infect Dis20111185586710.1016/S1473-3099(11)70145-1<?supplied-pmid 22035614?>22035614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
