<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5979449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19041026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-19-01026</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Treatment of Arsenite Intoxication-Induced Peripheral Vasculopathy with Mesenchymal Stem Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Yi-Hung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-19-01026">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-19-01026">2</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-19-01026" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Chai-Chin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-19-01026">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yen-Chung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijms-19-01026">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Oscar K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-19-01026">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-ijms-19-01026">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6-ijms-19-01026">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af7-ijms-19-01026">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af8-ijms-19-01026">8</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-19-01026" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-19-01026"><label>1</label>Institute of Clinical Medicine, National Yang-Ming University, Taipei 11221, Taiwan</aff><aff id="af2-ijms-19-01026"><label>2</label>Department of Orthopaedics, National Yang-Ming University Hospital, Yilan 260, Taiwan</aff><aff id="af3-ijms-19-01026"><label>3</label>Department of Biotechnology and Animal Science, National Yilan University, Yilan 260, Taiwan; <email>Lincc@niu.edu.tw</email></aff><aff id="af4-ijms-19-01026"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, National Yang-Ming University Hospital, Yilan 260, Taiwan; <email>999liquor999@gmail.com</email></aff><aff id="af5-ijms-19-01026"><label>5</label>Stem Cell Research Center, National Yang-Ming University, Taipei 11221, Taiwan</aff><aff id="af6-ijms-19-01026"><label>6</label>Taipei City Hospital, Taipei 10341, Taiwan</aff><aff id="af7-ijms-19-01026"><label>7</label>Department of Medical Research, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei 11217, Taiwan</aff><aff id="af8-ijms-19-01026"><label>8</label>Department of Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei 11217, Taiwan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-19-01026"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>chiang340@gmail.com</email> (Y.-H.C.); <email>DAV47@tpech.gov.tw</email> (O.K.L.); Tel.: +886-2-2559-6131 (O.K.L.)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>1026</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Arsenite (As), a notorious toxic metal, is ubiquitously distributed in the earth and poses a serious threat to human health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Histopathological lesions of As intoxication are known as thromboangiitis obliterans, which are resistant to current treatment and often lead to lower limb amputation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In this study, we attempt to find that treatment with mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) may be effective for As-induced vasculopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We first conducted an in vitro study with a co-culture system containing human MSCs and human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) and treated individual and co-cultured cells with various concentrations of arsenite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We also designed an in vivo study in which Sprague Dawley (SD) rats received periodic intraperitoneal (IP) injections of 16 ppm arsenite for 12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>MSCs were harvested from BALB/c mice that were transplanted via tail vein injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We found that there was significantly higher cellular viability in human mesenchymal stem cells (hMSCs) than in HUVECs under concentrations of arsenite between 15 and 25 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The Annexin V apoptosis assay further confirmed this finding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Cytokine array assay for As-conditioned media revealed an elevated vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) level secreted by MSCs, which is crucial for HUVEC survival and was evaluated by an siRNA VEGF knockdown test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the in vivo study, we demonstrated early apoptotic changes in the anterior tibial vessels of As-injected SD rats with a Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) assay, but these apoptotic changes were less frequently observed upon MSCs transplantation, indicating that the cytoprotective effect of MSCs successfully protected against As-induced peripheral vasculopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The feasibility of MSCs to treat and /or prevent the progression of As-induced vasculopathy is justified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Further clinical studies are required to demonstrate the therapeutic efficacy of MSCs in patients suffering from As intoxication with vasculopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>arsenite</kwd><kwd>peripheral vascular disease</kwd><kwd>mesenchymal stem cells</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Toxic metals pose serious adverse effects to the environment and human health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Among these metals, arsenite (As) is most commonly found due to its ubiquitous distribution in the earth’s crust [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>For decades, most endemic arsenic exposures in humans have come from environmental sources and threatened millions of people in various regions worldwide, including Argentina, Bangladesh, Chile, China, Hungary, the United States and Taiwan [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Recently, the adverse health effects resulting from chronic arsenite exposure are thought to be transmitted through drinking water, worldwide food distribution, smoking and global cosmetics [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Arsenite pollution poses a global threat and is never-ending. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Chronic exposure to arsenite leads to skin lesions, neurological dysfunction, atherosclerosis and cancer [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Those catastrophic insults threaten health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Arsenite often targets the vascular system as an initiation of its toxicity, and the damage to the vascular system plays an important role in mediating pathological changes in specific target organs [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) during arsenic metabolism orchestrates arsenite-induced injury [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Persistent ROS elevation has a deleterious effect on endothelial cells and cells may lose antioxidant defenses, leading to apoptosis [6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The causative effect of arsenite on the peripheral vascular system gives rise to histologic lesions known as thromboangitis obliterans and/or arteriosclerosis obliterans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Clinically, patients are noted with artery insufficiency, chronic ulceration and gangrene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>A majority of lesions are located on lower extremities and thus the condition is called black foot disease, a prevalent endemic disease in Taiwan [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Treatment for such troublesome complications has been researched for decades and toxic metal-induced vascular diseases are still difficult to treat, often eventually leading to amputation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>There are few options for the treatment of arsenite-induced vascular injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Peripheral arterial disease exhibits a similar aggressive clinical presentation and various therapeutic strategies have been established to improve circulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Potential cell therapies are based on the stimulation of angiogenesis with extracellular or cellular components, including endothelial progenitor cells and stem cells [9,10,11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The majority of these treatments have used either bone marrow-derived or peripheral mononuclear cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Those progenitors can restore tissue vascularization after ischemic events in limbs [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, in order to expand stem cell treatment to arsenite intoxication, it is critical to understand whether these cells tolerate the toxicity of arsenite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs), distinct from hematopoietic stem cells, have long been identified in the bone marrow stoma as colony-forming unit-fibroblasts (CFU-F) [13] and have the capability of differentiation into tissues of mesodermal origin [14,15,16,17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>They exhibit characteristics of stem cells and have been expected to bring substantial benefit for the treatment of a variety of diseases and injuries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Potential clinical applications of human MSCs (hMSCs) have been reported in recent years [18,19,20,21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>It is well documented that mechanisms mostly derived from MSCs can orchestrate tissue repair through the secretion of a broad range of bioactive factors and those trophic factors can modulate cellular activity [23,24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>At the same time, as perivascular niche cells, MSCs have a great capability to modulate endothelial function and enhance angiogenesis [25,26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>MSCs may be an ideal candidate for cellular therapy for arsenite-induced vascular disease due to their potential for promoting angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that low concentrations of As (0.1–5 μM) can inhibit CD34+ hematopoietic stem cell proliferation and differentiation into various hematological cell lineages [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, MSCs have been found to tolerate higher concentrations of arsenite and are more resistant to arsenite exposure [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For this reason, we chose MSCs as therapeutic cells in the scenario of arsenite intoxication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We conducted in vitro and in vivo experiments to verify the therapeutic efficacy of MSCs with a co-culture system and a rat animal model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Our hypothesis is that MSCs can recover the damage of endothelial cells caused by As. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec2-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Experimental Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The (3-[4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl]-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromides) MTT assay was used to assess cellular viability after arsenite treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The results showed that there were distinct viability differences between hMSCs and human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) when treated with arsenite for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>By stepping up the dosage of arsenite, we found that there were significantly higher survival rates in hMSCs than in HUVECs at a high concentration of arsenite between 15 to 25 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In addition, the calculated lethal concentration 50% (LC50) was 18.52 μM for hMSCs and 12.79 μM for HUVECs, as shown in Figure 1A. hMSCs can resist more arsenite toxicity than HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>From the morphology of cells under the microscope, hMSCs distributed homogenously and exhibited spindle cell morphology at concentrations as high as 10 μM arsenite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>From the co-culture of hMSCs and HUVECs with transwell plates, differences in the morphology and viability of HUVECs between cultures alone or co-cultured with hMSCs at 20 µM arsenite are shown in Figure 1B and Figure 2A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Under such circumstances, more HUVECs survived when co-cultured with hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Similar effects could also be seen when HUVECs were grown with arsenite-treated conditioned media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis of HUVECs was detected under treated and untreated conditions using Annexin V apoptosis assay and flow cytometric studies (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Data showed that in the untreated group, 51.7% HUVECs underwent apoptosis, as shown with positive Annexin V staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In contrast, when HUVECs were treated with conditioned medium from hMSCs for 48 h, only 33.6% of HUVECs exhibited positive staining for Annexin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>This difference was significant (p &lt; 0.05), as shown in Figure 1B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>From this study, we could characterize the effect of hMSCs, which are capable of preventing apoptosis in HUVECs caused by As intoxication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>By using the cytokine array assay, it was found that the conditioned medium with hMSCs treated with As exhibited a significant increase in vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) levels compared with normal medium, as shown in Figure 2C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Western blot analyses showed the same result when we compared the medium subjected to As treatment with the untreated medium, as shown in Figure 2D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We found that As treatment could trigger the secretion of VEGF from hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate the effect of VEGF, hMSCs were transfected with VEGF siRNA to abrogate VEGF secretion and the knockdown effect was confirmed by an (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay) ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We analyzed the function of VEGF knockdown hMSCs with the Annexin V apoptosis assay and repeated the As treatment experiment as mentioned before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The results showed that when we delivered VEGF siRNA into hMSCs, there was a significant increase in the apoptosis of HUVECs treated with harvested conditioned medium from knocked-down hMSCs, as shown in Figure 2A,B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>From the results of the Annexin V apoptosis assay, we found fewer HUVECs deviating to zone 1 and zone 4 (Annexin V positive) when cultured with conditioned medium from hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon was abolished when we delivered siRNA into hMSCs (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Transfected hMSCs lose their protective and therapeutic effects due to decreases in the secretion of VEGF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>How hMSCs are able to sustain the insults of As was further elucidated based on the investigation of cellular energy metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria dysfunction can contribute to cell apoptosis and cellular oxygen consumption has been recognized as a fundamental measure of mitochondrial function [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Seahorse XF-24 (Seahorse Bioscience Inc., Billerica, MA, USA) was used to measure the maximum oxygen consumption rate (OCR) of hMSCs and HUVECs after treatment with As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The oxygen consumption rate of hMSCs remained constant without significant changes before or after treatment with As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We observed that the decline of functional mitochondria in hMSCs under high concentrations of As (20 μM was not significant (p = 0.061). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the oxygen consumption rate of HUVECs decreased significantly under high concentrations of As (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial mass was checked at the same time and we found that there were also no variances in nonyl acridine orange (NAO) fluorescent density between hMSCs alone and hMSCs treated with 20 μM As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, NAO fluorescence density declined in HUVECs when comparing cells with or without As treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>We concluded that hMSCs could preserve more functional, active mitochondria and withstand a higher dose of arsenite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) generated under high As concentrations often lead to the apoptosis of endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We further investigated whether the toxic ROS could be reduced after HUVECs were treated with hMSCs conditioned media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>After treatment with hMSCs conditioned media for 48 h, an ROS assay with flow cytometry demonstrated that ROS levels (fluorescein isothiocyanate FITC mean) in HUVECs declined slightly compared with those in cells treated with As only (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The antioxidant capacity of HUVECs under conditioned medium treatment was then checked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>We measured superoxidase dismutase (SOD) activity and the results showed that SOD activity increased under conditioned medium treatment, as shown in Figure 3B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>However, the variability was not statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>In the in vivo study, hematoxylin and eosin stain (HE staining) for vessels harvested from the anterior compartment of the lower limbs of Sprague Dawley (SD) rats showed that there were no obvious histological differences in the anterior tibial artery and vein from the mouse mesenchymal stem cells (mMSCs)-injected and control groups (after 12 weeks of treatment). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>However, in the arterioles of the control group, as shown in Figure 4A, mild pathological changes were observed, with a decrease in the diameter of the arteriole lumen and an increase in inflammatory cells infiltrating the smooth muscles of vessel walls when compared with normal specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The diameter of the arteriole decreased from 100 to 65 μm between normal and As-treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Platelet endothelial cell adhesion molecular (CD31) staining for vessels revealed a decrease in staining intensity in control rats compared with that in wild-type SD rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic ratios of tissues were analyzed by a terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling assay (TUNEL assay), which showed that there were significantly more TUNEL-positive tissues induced by As in the control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Compared with the control rat specimens, mMSCs-injected SD rat specimens showed decreases in TUNEL staining, especially in regions containing anterior tibial vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>This finding indicates that mMSCs injection could reverse the early apoptotic changes in vessels induced by As intoxication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To investigate VEGF expression in vivo, serum levels of VEGF were evaluated with an ELISA test and VEGF gene expression levels in the lower limb blood vessels of rats were checked with a qPCR test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Compared to the control group, SD rats injected with arsenite without mMSCs treatment and experimental rats that received serial mMSCs injection for two weeks demonstrated a significant elevation in blood VEGF levels, as shown in Figure 5A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>VEGF levels were elevated significantly in blood samples drawn from SD rats with serial mMSCs injection for two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Similar findings in the VEGF gene expression levels were achieved with the qPCR test (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We also checked oxidative stress in vivo with the measurement of reduced/oxidized glutathione (GSH/GSSG) levels and the detection of antioxidant SOD levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Compared with the experimental rats serially treated with mMSCs for two weeks, SD rats exposed to arsenite without mMSCs treatment exhibited a decline in GSH/GSSG ratio, as shown in Figure 5C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The increase in the GSH/GSSG ratio indicated that injection of mMSCs could decrease oxidative stress in the tissues of experimental groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>During the same time period, levels of SOD were also elevated in the experimental groups, as shown in Figure 5D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Treatment of MSCs could prevent further increase of oxidative stress in arsenite intoxication and could reverse the apoptosis of cells lining the lumen of lower limb vessels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The negative effects of toxic arsenite on human health have been widely studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>However, there are no effective therapies to reverse its pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The paucity of appropriate treatments is part of the grim struggle in the conflict with arsenite intoxication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In this study, we demonstrated that MSCs can recover the early pathological change of small vessels from arsenite intoxication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Vascular tissues are an empirical target of arsenite for both the initiation of injury and disease progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The disruption of the vascular system can lead to a variety of pathologies of tissues in arsenite intoxication and, therefore, we focused on the function of endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>From our studies, MSCs are able to prevent the apoptosis of endothelial cells and can preserve the integrity of small vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We chose MSCs as therapeutic cells because, compared with endothelial cells, they can endure arsenite toxicity and survive under higher concentrations of arsenite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>There have only been a few reports of different responses to arsenite toxicity between progenitor cells and differentiated adult cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Based on our MTT assay, the LD50 for hMSCs under arsenite treatment was 14.52 μM, which is much higher than the LD50 of HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>According to the research of precise As2O3 (iAs) toxicity to CD34+ cells, the author found that iAs with a concentration between 0.1 and 5 can inhibit the proliferation of CD34+ cells and more than 70% of CD34+ cells were detected as necrotic cells when the iAs concentration was more than 5 M [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>So, CD34+ cells cannot be the candidates for cells therapy in As-induced vasculopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In another study on As-induced apoptosis of hMSCs, the author found that with less than 5 M iAs, there was no obvious change in MSCs viability [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The distinct viability differences between adult cells and MSCs during As intoxication are consistent with our results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We tried to verify the mechanism of how hMSCs can survive in high concentrations of As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial function is inextricably linked with cell apoptosis and cellular oxygen consumption is increasingly recognized as a fundamental measurement of mitochondrial function [29,30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In our study, mitochondrial bioenergetics in arsenite exposure, especially at a high concentration of As (20 μM) in hMSCs, was evaluated with the Seahorse extracellular flux analyzer SFX-20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Seahorse XF-20 can provide real-time measurements of cellular oxygen consumption and provide assessments of the cellular bioenergetics function of cells [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Our results show that hMSCs can preserve less dysfunctional mitochondria even in the harsh environment provoked by high As concentration (20 μM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial mass can be a surrogate marker for mitochondrial biogenesis [32,33], as was measured with NAO staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The results of the fluorescent assay show similar results to cellular oxygen consumption rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>According to previous research, prolonged exposure of vascular tissues (vascular smooth muscle cells) to inorganic arsenite (iAsIII) can induce a reduction in mitochondrial content, cause the fragmentation of mitochondria and lead to a decline in mitochondrial respiration [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>From our experimental results, we found that hMSCSs exhibit less of a decline in mitochondrial mass during As intoxication, which may be why hMSCs presented fewer differences in oxygen consumption rate (OCR) in high As concentration in SXF-20 experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>From our experimental results, we found that hMSCs can preserve more functional mitochondria in a high concentration of As and thus escape the toxic effects of As. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>MSCs can secrete various cytokines when confronted with high concentrations of As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>MSCs serve as a reservoir for various cytokines and can secrete cytokines in response to tissue damage [35,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Complex cross talk occurred between injured tissues and MSCs and then MSCs were activated to express various levels of therapeutic protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms underlining MSCs cell therapy demonstrate that the paracrine effects of MSCs are dominant [37,38,39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Due to the complexity of the paracrine effect of MSCs, we choose to investigate the conditioned medium obtained from As-treated MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>From our cytokine array data, when comparing various cytokines exerted by hMSCs with or without As treatment, VEGF was found to play an important role and was most significantly affected after As treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>VEGF has long been recognized as an important factor for endothelial cell proliferation and migration, which can promote angiogenesis [40,41] and inhibit the apoptosis of endothelial cells [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>It also has been reported that VEGF can decrease the level of cellular apoptosis through activating phosphokinase B (Akt) both in renal tubular cells [39] and aortic endothelium cells [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Introducing anti-VEGF antibodies can adversely increase cellular apoptosis [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>We provided further evidence of the anti-apoptotic effect of VEGF by knockdown experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>HUVECs cannot maintain their growth and survival in the same hMSC conditioned medium at the same concentration of As (20 μM), in which VEGF was knocked down. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with a previous report on cisplatin-induced renotoxicity in mice [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The paracrine effects of MSCs that can release various cytokines in response to tissue damage are well known; however, we are the first to demonstrate that MSCs can secrete abundant VEGF under As intoxication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In this study, we generated an animal model of As intoxication through weekly IP injection with As for SD rats for 12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The final blood As concentrations calculated are 108.61 ± 16.25 μg/L which is very similar to the As blood concentration reported in high exposure areas [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We harvest anterior tibial vessels to find early pathological and apoptotic changes with HE staining and TUNEL assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The early pathological changes in small arteriole are consistent with histological pictures of thromboangitis obliterans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>After two weeks of treatment with MSCs harvested from BALB/c mice, we revealed a recovery of vessels from apoptotic changes as proved by TUNEL assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We also demonstrated a significant elevation in blood VEGF levels after two weeks of mMSCs injection by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This finding indicated that allogeneic transplantation with mMSCs in SD rats could reverse the early apoptotic changes of peripheral vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>It is well known that the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) under As exposure contributes to cellular apoptosis [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress leads to mitochondria dysfunction and in turn perpetuates cellular damage, which was found in our in vitro study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the anti-apoptotic effects of growth factors are based on their abilities to prevent oxidative stress by increasing the activity of antioxidant and normalizing mitochondria functions [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In the context of our present in vivo study, GSH/GSSG levels decreased after two weeks of treatment with mouse MSCs and the antioxidant enzyme SOD levels were elevated in the same time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Such effects may come from the contribution of secreted growth factors by mMSCs according to the report of previous research [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A similar phenomenon was also found in the in vitro studies, but the differences were not so significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we believe that repeated treatment and a longer time frame may be required to support the further reinforcement of antioxidant enzyme levels and a solid decrease in ROS levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In this study, human MSCs have been tested and their potential therapeutic efficacy in As-induced vasculopathy has been cleared demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>While this proof-of-concept pre-clinical study showed promising results, other factors, such as the cost and applicability of allogeneic use of hMSCs, must be taken into consideration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>There are still great challenges of manufacturing a ready supply of highly defined transplantable hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A stringent compliance of regulations is essential for successful clinical translation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec4-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec4dot1-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Maintenance and Expansion of Msenchymal Stem Cells (MSCs) and Human Umbilical Vein Endothelial Cells (HUVECs) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Commercially available human MSCs (hMSCs) were used in this study (Steminent Therapeutics Inc., Taipei, Taiwan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Their abilities to differentiate into osteoblasts, chondrocytes and adipocytes were confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The isolation of murine MSCs from the bone marrow of BALB/c mice was performed with our previously reported method [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Commercially available HUVECs, which were isolated from human umbilical veins, were purchased from ScienCell (Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>As adherent cells reached approximately 50% to 70% confluence, they were detached with 0.25% trypsin-EDTA (ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA), washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA), then centrifuged at 1000 rpm (200× g) for 5 min and reseeded at a ratio of 1:3 under the same culture conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Culture Medium </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>hMSC expansion medium consisted of mesenchymal stem cell growth medium (MesenPRO; Gibco), 100 U penicillin, 1000 U streptomycin and 2 mM l-glutamine (Gibco). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Murine MSCs were cultured in low-glucose Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s medium (LGDMEM; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and 1% penicillin-streptomycin-glutamine (PSG; Thermo Fisher Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We used endothelial cell medium (ECM; Sigma-Aldrich) as a HUVEC culture medium and these cells were expanded on fibronectin-coated culture vessels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>(3-[4,5-Dimethylthiazol-2-yl]-2,5-Diphenyltetrazolium Bromides) MTT Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Cell proliferation and viability were determined via an MTT assay (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We suspended HUVECs and MSCs in culture vessels and cell lines were optimized as per the supplier’s suggestions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We then added arsenite with different dosages ranging from 0.3 to 60 μM, incubated the mixture for 48 h and then harvested cells for the MTT assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Procedures were carried out according to the manufacturer’s instructions; we added 10 μL MTT labeling reagent and incubated the mixture for 4 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The resulting solutions were transferred to 96-well plates and absorbance was recorded at 570 nm using a microplate spectrophotometer system (Spectra max190-Molecular Devices). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The results are presented as percentages of control values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot4-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxicity and Apoptosis Assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Direct cytotoxicity tests were performed with a serial elution of arsenite (0, 5, 10, 15, 20 and 25 μm) added to the HUVEC and hMSC cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We also designed a co-culture of HUVECs and hMSCs with Transwell plates and HUVECs with conditioned medium from hMSCs and arsenite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Each included group was inoculated into 6-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>At 24 h, the culture media was removed and different concentrations of arsenite were added with serum-free media and incubated for 24 and 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Cell morphology was examined with a light microscope and the apoptosis rate was evaluated with Annexin V-FITC/PI staining (Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) and analyzed with flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We collected 1 × 105 cells by centrifugation, then suspended cells in 500 μL binding buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Cells were double stained with 5 μL Annexin F_FITC and 5 μL propidium iodide (PI), incubated at room temperature for 5 min and prepared for quantification with flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot5-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Cytokine Array Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A human cytokine antibody array kit (Abcam) was used to measure the cytokine production of hMSCs and HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Both cell lines were cultured alone and treated with 20 μm arsenite for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Supernatant was harvested from media and conditioned media from hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The array was performed according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Detection was carried out with biotin-conjugated antibodies and HRP-conjugated streptavidin, followed by an overnight incubation at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Membranes were transferred to chromatography paper and chemiluminescence imaging was captured by a UVP BioSpectrum 600 System (UVP LLC, Upland, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot6-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>4.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Western Blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Supernatants from conditioned medium of hMSCs with 20 μM arsenite, incubated for 48 h, were collected for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Twenty micrograms of protein were separated on a 12% polyacrylamide gel and transferred to a PVDF membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The membrane was blocked by 5% BSA (bovine serum albumin)/TBST (tris buffered saline with tween) for 1 h and then probed with primary antibodies of VEGF (Abcam) at 4 °C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>After TBST washing, the membrane was incubated with HRP (horseradish peroxidase)-conjugated secondary antibodies at room temperature for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>After TBST washing, protein levels were detected using SuperSignal™ West Femto Maximum Sensitivity Substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Chemiluminescence imaging was captured by a UVP BioSpectrum 600 System (UVP LLC, Upland, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot7-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>4.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Small Interfering (si) RNA Knockdown Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The silencing of human VEGF was achieved by using PepMute™ siRNA transfection reagent (SignaGen Laboratories, Rockville, MD, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Transient transfection was performed in 6-well culture plates and carried out according to the protocol recommended by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Specifically, 5.0 nM siRNA was diluted in 100 μL transfection buffer and then mixed with 3 μL PepMute™ reagent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The mixed transfection complex then was added onto plates containing hMSCs and incubated for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>HUVECs were also seeded on 6-well plates and then incubated for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>A total of 20 μM arsenite, conditioned media from hMSCs, 20 μM As and conditioned media transfected with siRNA against VEGF were added separately to HUVECs, incubated for 48 h and then harvested for morphology and Annexin V apoptosis assays as described in Section 4.4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot8-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>4.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial Test—Oxygen Consumption Rate (OCR) Test and Mitochondrial Mass Detection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial oxygen consumption rates (OCR) were measured with XF24 (Seahorse Bioscience Inc., Billerica, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>hMSCs and HUVECs were seeded on an XF24 culture plate; the experimental groups were treated with 20 μM arsenite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The optimal seeding density was 1 × 104 cells/well and the cells were incubated for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>We then continued the assay using the protocol described by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Oxygen consumption rates (OCR) were detected under basal conditions followed by sequential addition of oligomycin (line B in Figure 3A), carbonyl cyanide p-trifluoromethoxy-phenylhydrazone (FCCP) (line C in Figure 3A), as well as rotenone and antimycin A (line C in Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Maximal respiratory rate was measured after cells were treated with FCCP (blue bar zone 29 in Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Finally, data were calculated and generated automatically; data are presented as wave data for analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial mass was measured with Acridine Orange 10-nonyl bromide (NAO, Sigma-Aldrich, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We prepared cell lines as described in the OCR test above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Cells at a sub-confluent stage were trypsinized and resuspended in 0.5 mL of phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, pH 7.4) containing 2.5 μM NAO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The harvested cells were incubated for 15 min at 25 °C in the dark, then immediately transferred to a tube for analysis on a flow cytometer (Model EPICS XL-MCL, Beckman-Coulter, Miami, FL, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence intensity of 1 × 104 cells was recorded on a flow cytometer with an excitation wavelength at 488 nm and emission wavelength at 535 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot9-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>4.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In Vivo SD Rat Experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>To assess the effect of As intoxication in vivo, we maintained SD rats purchased from the national animal center and maintained them with periodic 16 ppm As intraperitoneal injections once a week for 12 weeks and finally checked their serum As concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>For the experimental group, mouse MSCs harvested from BALB/c mice were injected through the tail vein at the 12th week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Then, 1 × 106 cells dispersed in 1 mL PBS solution were injected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Injections were repeated one week later and the total number of cells injected were 2 × 106 cells over the course of two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>SD rats in the control and experimental groups were sacrificed one week after the last injection and we harvested specimens from the anterior compartment of hind limbs just above the ankle joint. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot10-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>4.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis TUNEL Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Tissues containing the vascular bundle from the anterior lower limbs of SD rats were harvested for the detection of apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>They were fixed in 10% formalin, embedded in paraffin and sectioned at 5 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>After deparaffinization and rehydration, tissue sections were subsequently processed using a TUNEL apoptosis detection kit (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Procedures were carried out according to the manufacturer’s instructions and then observed under a light microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot11-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>4.11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>ELISA Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Blood was drawn from SD rats, which were divided into wild-type, PBS injection only, As IP injection and mMSC injection groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The VEGF concentrations in the blood were measured with a VEGF ELISA Kit (Abcam). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The arrays were performed according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were pipetted into 96-well plates, followed by the addition of biotinylated anti-rat VEGF antibody, HRP-conjugated streptavidin and TMB substrate solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The absorbance levels of proteins were measured on a plate reader at 450 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot12-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>4.12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Glutathione GSH/GSSG Assay and SOD Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>As previously mentioned, blood was drawn from SD rats and was then divided into wild-type, PBS injection only, As IP injection and mMSC injection groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Whole blood was added to a tube and mixed with Bioxytech reduced glutathione and oxidized glutathione (GSH/GSSG) 412-kit (Oxis international Inc., Forster City, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>After centrifuging, the supernatant was extracted and processed for GSH/GSSG analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The absorbance levels of samples were measured on a plate reader at 412 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Activities of superoxide dismutase (SOD) were performed in blood samples by using colorimetric commercial kits, SOD ab65354 (Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Plasma layers from blood were collected and then incubated in order to complete the enzyme reactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The absorbance was measured at 450 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot13-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>4.13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Quantitative Real-Time PCR Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>RNA was prepared from tissue from the vascular bundle of the lower limbs of rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated using TRIzol (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and cleaned using an RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Courtaboeuf, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>We reverse transcribed the messenger RNA to complementary DNA using reagents (Genemark Technology, Taiwan) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of total RNA from cultured cells was performed using the ABI Step One Plus Real-Time PCR System. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>cDNA was amplified using an ABI Step One Plus Real-Time PCR System at 95 °C for 60 s, 56 °C for 45 s and 72 °C for 60 s for 40 cycles, after initial denaturation at 95 °C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot14-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>4.14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Data Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were performed by Student’s t test for two groups of data and by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with post hoc tests for multiple comparisons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as the mean ± SEM from three independent experiments and p &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5-ijms-19-01026"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>A preclinical model of cellular therapy using MSCs for the treatment of As-induced vascular diseases was established in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that adult stem cell MSCs therapy may provide a remarkable, feasible and effective treatment for overwhelming As intoxication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We also demonstrate that hMSCs are more resistant to As toxicity by preserving more functional mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Abundant VEGF secreted by MSCs under arsenite intoxication is of therapeutic efficacy and can support endothelial function and rescue endothelial cells from early apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The paracrine effect of MSCs under arsenite intoxication provides a therapeutic effect and ameliorates vascular abnormalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Together, the translational application of MSCs into the treatment of As-induced vasculopathy deserves further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The authors acknowledge financial support from the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (MOST 106-2321-B-010-008, MOST 106-2911-I-010-502 and MOST 106-3114-B-010-002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>This study was also supported by Aiming for the Top University Plan, a grant from Ministry of Education. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Yi-Hung Chiang carried out all cell-culture, in-vitro and in-vivo experiment and the statistical analyses and drafted the manuscript. Chai-Chin Lin participated in in-vivo animal experiment. Yen-Chung Chen participated in in-vivo study, collected data and statistical analyses. Oscar K. Lee conceived of the study and participated in its design and coordination and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><array orientation="portrait"><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>As </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Arsenite </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>ROS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Reactive oxygen species </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>MSCs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Mesenchymal stem cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>hMSCs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Human mesenchymal stem cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>HUVECs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Human umbilical endothelial cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>LC50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Lethal concentration 50% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>CM </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Condition medium </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Col-Cul </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Co-cultured </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>VEGF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Vascular endothelial growth factor </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Si </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>SiRNA for VEGF </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>OCR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Maximal oxygen consumption rate </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SOD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Superoxidase dismutase </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>CD31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Platelet endothelial cell adhesion molecular </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>GSH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Reduced glutathione </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>GSSG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Oxidized glutathione </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>HE stain </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Hematoxylin and eosin stain </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>SD rat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Sprague Dawley rat </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>TUNEL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></array></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>1.McCartyK.M.HanhH.T.KimK.W.Arsenic geochemistry and human health in South East AsiaRev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Health201126717810.1515/reveh.2011.01021714384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>2.ChungJ.Y.YuS.D.HongY.S.Environmental source of arsenic exposureJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Prev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Public Health20144725325710.3961/jpmph.14.036<?supplied-pmid 25284196?>25284196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>3.TsengC.H.Cardiovascular disease in arsenic-exposed subjects living in the arseniasis-hyperendemic areas in TaiwanAtherosclerosis2008199121810.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2008.02.013<?supplied-pmid 18367191?>18367191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>4.ProzialeckW.C.EdwardsJ.R.NebertD.W.WoodsJ.M.BarchowskyA.AtchisonW.D.The vascular system as a target of metal toxicityToxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Toxicol.200810220721810.1093/toxsci/kfm263<?supplied-pmid 17947343?>17947343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>5.WuM.M.ChiouH.Y.WangT.W.HsuehY.M.WangI.H.ChenC.J.LeeT.C.Association of blood arsenic levels with increased reactive oxidants and decreased antioxidant capacity in a human population of northeastern TaiwanEnviron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Health Perspect.20011091011101710.1289/ehp.011091011<?supplied-pmid 11675266?>11675266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>6.KumagaiY.SumiD.Arsenic: Signal transduction, transcription factor and biotransformation involved in cellular response and toxicityAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Toxicol.20074724326210.1146/annurev.pharmtox.47.120505.105144<?supplied-pmid 17002598?>17002598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>7.LemaireM.LemarieC.A.MolinaM.F.SchiffrinE.L.LehouxS.MannK.K.Exposure to moderate arsenic concentrations increases atherosclerosis in ApoE-/-mouse modelToxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Toxicol.201112221122110.1093/toxsci/kfr097<?supplied-pmid 21512104?>21512104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>8.TsengC.H.Blackfoot disease and arsenic: A never-ending storyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Health C Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Carcinog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Ecotoxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Rev.200523557410.1081/GNC-200051860<?supplied-pmid 16291522?>16291522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>9.AmannB.LuedemannC.RateiR.Schmidt-LuckeJ.A.Autologous bone marrow cell transplantation increases leg perfusion and reduces amputations in patients with advanced critical limb ischemia due to peripheral artery diseaseCell Transplant.20091837138010.3727/096368909788534942<?supplied-pmid 19500466?>19500466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>10.HorieT.OnoderaR.AkamastuM.IchikawaY.HoshinoJ.KanekoE.IwashitaC.IshidaA.TsukamotoT.TeramukaiS.Long-term clinical outcomes for patients with lower limb ischemia implanted with G-CSF-mobilized autologous peripheral blood mononuclear cellsAtherosclerosis201020846146610.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2009.07.050<?supplied-pmid 19720375?>19720375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>11.FranzR.W.ShahK.J.PinR.H.HankinsT.HartmanJ.F.WrightM.L.Autologous bone marrow mononuclear cell implantation therapy is an effective limb salvage strategy for patients with severe peripheral arterial diseaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Vasc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Surg.20156267368010.1016/j.jvs.2015.02.059<?supplied-pmid 26304481?>26304481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>12.RafiiS.LydenD.Therapeutic stem and progenitor cell transplantation for organ vascularization and regenerationNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Med.2003970271210.1038/nm0603-702<?supplied-pmid 12778169?>12778169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>13.FriedensteinA.J.PetrakovaK.V.KurolesovaA.I.FrolovaG.P.Heterotopic of bone marrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Analysis of precursor cells for osteogenic and hematopoietic tissuesTransplantation1968623024710.1097/00007890-196803000-00009<?supplied-pmid 5654088?>5654088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>14.PereiraR.F.HalfordK.W.O‘HaraM.D.LeeperD.B.SokolovB.P.PollardM.D.BagasraO.ProckopD.J.Cultured adherent cells from marrow can serve as long-lasting precursor cells for bone, cartilage and lung in irradiated miceProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>USA1995924857486110.1073/pnas.92.11.4857<?supplied-pmid 7761413?>7761413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>15.HorwitzE.M.ProckopD.J.FitzpatrickL.A.KooW.W.GordonP.L.NeelM.SussmanM.OrchardP.MarxJ.C.PyeritzR.E.Transplantability and therapeutic effects of bone marrow-derived mesenchymal cells in children with osteogenesis imperfectaNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Med.1999530931310.1038/6529<?supplied-pmid 10086387?>10086387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>16.PittengerM.F.MackayA.M.BeckS.C.JaiswalR.K.DouglasR.MoscaJ.D.MoormanM.A.SimonettiD.W.CraigS.MarshakD.R.Multilineage potential of adult human mesenchymal stem cellsScience199928414314710.1126/science.284.5411.143<?supplied-pmid 10102814?>10102814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>17.JiangY.JahagirdarB.N.ReinhardtR.L.SchwartzR.E.KeeneC.D.Ortiz-GonzalezX.R.ReyesM.LenvikT.LundT.BlackstadM.Pluripotency of mesenchymal stem cells derived from adult marrowNature2002418414910.1038/nature00870<?supplied-pmid 12077603?>12077603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>18.SwartJ.F.BackerM.J.G.HofhuisF.PrakkenB.J.KuisW.MartensA.C.M.WulfraatN.M.Mesenchymal stem cell therapy has significant clinical effect in arthritisArthritis Rheum.200858S32S64 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>19.BrookeG.RossettiT.IlicN.MurrayP.HancockS.PelekanosR.AtkinsonK.Points to consider in designing mesenchymal stem cell-based clinical trialsTransfus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Hemother.20083527928510.1159/000143158<?supplied-pmid 21512643?>21512643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>20.NagayaN.OhgushiH.ShimizuW.YamagishiM.NoguchiT.NodaT.DoiK.IshidaY.OhnishiS.KitakazeM.Clinical trial of autologous bone marrow mesenchymal stem cell transplantation for severe chronic heart failureCirculation2007116453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>21.ResnickI.B.BarkatsC.ShapiraM.Y.StepenskyP.BloomA.I.ShimoniA.MankutaD.Varda-BloomN.RheingoldL.YeshurunM.Treatment of severe steroid resistant acute GVHD with mesenchymal stromal cells (MSC)Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Blood Res.20133225238<?supplied-pmid 23997985?>23997985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>22.RamaP.MatuskaS.PaganoniG.SpinelliA.De LucaM.PellegriniG.Limbal stem-cell therapy and long-term corneal regenerationN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Engl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Med.201036314715510.1056/NEJMoa0905955<?supplied-pmid 20573916?>20573916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>23.KeatingA.Mesenchymal stromal cells: New directionsCell Stem Cell20121070971610.1016/j.stem.2012.05.015<?supplied-pmid 22704511?>22704511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>24.CaplanA.I.DennisJ.E.Mesenchymal stem cells as trophic mediatorsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Biochem.2006981076108410.1002/jcb.20886<?supplied-pmid 16619257?>16619257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>25.CrisanM.YapS.CasteillaL.ChenC.W.CorselliM.ParkT.S.AndrioloG.SunB.ZhengB.ZhangL.A perivascular origin for mesenchymal stem cells in multiple human organsCell Stem Cell2008330131310.1016/j.stem.2008.07.003<?supplied-pmid 18786417?>18786417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>26.RoubelakisM.G.TsaknakisG.PappaK.I.AnagnouN.P.WattS.M.Spindle shaped human mesenchymal stem/stromal cells from amniotic fluid promote neovascularizationPLoS ONE20138e5474710.1371/journal.pone.0054747<?supplied-pmid 23359810?>23359810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>27.VernhetL.MorzadecC.van GrevenyngheJ.BareauB.CorolleurM.FestT.FardelO.Inorganic arsenic induces necrosis of human CD34-positive haematopoietic stem cellsEnviron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Toxicol.20082326326810.1002/tox.20334<?supplied-pmid 18214907?>18214907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>28.YadavS.ShiY.WangF.WangH.Arsenite induces apoptosis in human mesenchymal stem cells by altering Bcl-2 family proteins and by activating intrinsic pathwayToxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol.201024426327210.1016/j.taap.2010.01.001<?supplied-pmid 20083129?>20083129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>29.PerryC.G.KaneD.A.LanzaI.R.NeuferP.D.Methods for assessing mitochondrial function in diabetesDiabetes2013621041105310.2337/db12-1219<?supplied-pmid 23520284?>23520284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>30.FerrickD.A.NeilsonA.BeesonC.Advances in measuring cellular bioenergetics using extracellular fluxDrug Discov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Today20081326827410.1016/j.drudis.2007.12.008<?supplied-pmid 18342804?>18342804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>31.Pike WinerL.S.WuM.Rapid analysis of glycolytic and oxidative substrate flux of cancer cells in a microplatePLoS ONE20149e10991610.1371/journal.pone.0109916<?supplied-pmid 25360519?>25360519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>32.JiangW.C.ChengY.H.YenM.H.ChangY.YangV.W.LeeO.K.Cryo-chemical decellularization of the whole liver for mesenchymal stem cells-based functional hepatic tissue engineeringBiomaterials2014353607361710.1016/j.biomaterials.2014.01.024<?supplied-pmid 24462361?>24462361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>33.LambR.BonuccelliG.OzsvariB.Peiris-PagesM.FiorilloM.SmithD.L.BevilacquaG.MazzantiC.M.McDonnellL.A.NaccaratoA.G.Mitochondrial mass, a new metabolic biomarker for stem-like cancer cells: Understanding WNT/FGF-driven anabolic signalingOncotarget20156304533047110.18632/oncotarget.5852<?supplied-pmid 26421711?>26421711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>34.PaceC.BanerjeeT.D.WelchB.KhaliliR.DagdaR.K.AngermannJ.Monomethylarsonous acid, but not inorganic arsenic, is a mitochondria-specific toxicant in vascular smooth muscle cellsToxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>In Vitro20163518820110.1016/j.tiv.2016.06.006<?supplied-pmid 27327130?>27327130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>35.ProckopD.J.KotaD.J.BazhanovN.RegerR.L.Evolving paradigms for repair of tissues by adult stem/progenitor cells (MSCs)J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Med.2010142190219910.1111/j.1582-4934.2010.01151.x<?supplied-pmid 20716123?>20716123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>36.EstradaR.LiN.SarojiniH.AnJ.LeeM.J.WangE.Secretome from mesenchymal stem cells induces angiogenesis via Cyr61J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Physiol.200921956357110.1002/jcp.21701<?supplied-pmid 19170074?>19170074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>37.LineroI.ChaparroO.Paracrine effect of mesenchymal stem cells derived from human adipose tissue in bone regenerationPLoS ONE20149e10700110.1371/journal.pone.0107001<?supplied-pmid 25198551?>25198551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>38.KhubutiyaM.S.VagabovA.V.TemnovA.A.SklifasA.N.Paracrine mechanisms of proliferative, anti-apoptotic and anti-inflammatory effects of mesenchymal stromal cells in models of acute organ injuryCytotherapy20141657958510.1016/j.jcyt.2013.07.017<?supplied-pmid 24113425?>24113425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>39.EliopoulosN.ZhaoJ.BouchentoufM.FornerK.BirmanE.YuanS.BoivinM.N.MartineauD.Human marrow-derived mesenchymal stromal cells decrease cisplatin renotoxicity in vitro and in vivo and enhance survival of mice post-intraperitoneal injectionAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Renal Physiol.2010299F1288F129810.1152/ajprenal.00671.2009<?supplied-pmid 20844023?>20844023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>40.CarmelietP.Angiogenesis in health and diseaseNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Med.2003965366010.1038/nm0603-653<?supplied-pmid 12778163?>12778163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>41.MakinenK.ManninenH.HedmanM.MatsiP.MussaloH.AlhavaE.Yla-HerttualaS.Increased vascularity detected by digital subtraction angiography after VEGF gene transfer to human lower limb artery: A randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blinded phase II studyMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Ther.2002612713310.1006/mthe.2002.0638<?supplied-pmid 12095313?>12095313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>42.GerberH.P.McMurtreyA.KowalskiJ.YanM.KeytB.A.DixitV.FerraraN.Vascular endothelial growth factor regulates endothelial cell survival through the phosphatidylinositol 3′-kinase/Akt signal transduction pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Requirement for Flk-1/KDR activationJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Chem.1998273303363034310.1074/jbc.273.46.30336<?supplied-pmid 9804796?>9804796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>43.HungS.C.PochampallyR.R.ChenS.C.HsuS.C.ProckopD.J.Angiogenic effects of human multipotent stromal cell conditioned medium activate the PI3K-Akt pathway in hypoxic endothelial cells to inhibit apoptosis, increase survival and stimulate angiogenesisStem Cells2007252363237010.1634/stemcells.2006-0686<?supplied-pmid 17540857?>17540857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>44.GebelT.W.Genotoxicity of arsenical compoundsInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Hyg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Health200120324926210.1078/S1438-4639(04)70036-X11279822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-ijms-19-01026"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>45.Garcia-FernandezM.DelgadoG.PucheJ.E.Gonzalez-BaronS.Castilla CortazarI.Low doses of insulin-like growth factor I improve insulin resistance, lipid metabolism and oxidative damage in aging ratsEndocrinology20081492433244210.1210/en.2007-1190<?supplied-pmid 18187555?>18187555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-19-01026-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>(A) MTT assays for human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) and human mesenchymal stem cells (hMSCs) under arsenite treatment show a distinct difference in the survival rate between HUVECs and hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>There are significantly higher survival rates in hMSCs than in HUVECs under high concentrations of arsenite between 15 to 25 μM; (B) An apoptosis flow cytometry study reveals significant differences in apoptosis rates between HUVECs treated with arsenite, HUVECs in conditioned medium and HUVECs and hMSCs co-cultured under an arsenite concentration of 20 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>(* p &lt; 0.05), MTT assay—(3-[4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl]-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromides). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Col-cul—co-cultured HUVEC and hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>CM—conditioned medium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-19-01026-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(A) Microscopic view of a culture dish with 20 µM arsenite treatment for 48 h shows obvious differences in the morphology and viability of HUVECs between cells cultured alone and those co-cultured with hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>The left picture shows that when we delivered VEGF (vascular endothelia growth factor) siRNA into hMSCs, the harvested siRNA conditioned medium could not rescue the HUVECs and more cell death was found compared with the middle picture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>(Scale bar 100 µm) (B) Apoptosis flow cytometry results show fewer HUVECs deviating to zone 1 and zone 4 (Annexin V positive) when cultured with conditioned media from hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon is abolished when we deliver siRNA into hMSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>(* p &lt; 0.05) (C) Cytokine array assay reveals an elevated VEGF level in conditioned media with hMSCs treated with As compared with that in normal medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>(D) Western blot experiments show the same result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>More VEGF was expressed upon As treatment in the conditioned medium than in the normal medium (hMSCs only). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>CM—conditioned medium with HUVECs treated with 20 µm As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>CM+Si—conditioned medium with HUVECs and the addition of VEGF SiRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>hMSCs—human mesenchymal stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>HUSMCs—human umbilical vein smooth muscle cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-19-01026-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>(A) A mitochondrial maximum oxygen consumption rate (OCR) test shows that with Seahorse XF-24, the OCR of hMSCs remains constant without significant changes before or after treatment with As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>However, the OCR of HUVECs decreases significantly at a high concentration of As and the difference is statically significant (* p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Cells were sequentially treated with oligomycin (line B), carbonyl cyanide p-trifluoromethoxy-phenylhydrazone (FCCP) (line C), as well as rotenone and antimycin A (line D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Maximal respiratory rate was measured after cells were treated with FCCP (blue bar zone 29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Dark orange line—HUVEC, Light orange line—HUVEC with As 20 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Red line—MSC, Blue line—MSC with As 20 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>(B) A mitochondrial mass nonyl acridine orange (NAO) fluorescence assay demonstrates that under 20 µM As, the NAO green fluorescent protein (GFP) mean in HUVECs decreased compared with that in normal HUVECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>hMSCs maintain a constant mean before and after treatment with As. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>(C) A reactive oxygen species (ROS) assay demonstrates that ROS levels declined slightly in HUVECs treated with conditioned medium compared with those in cells treated with As for only 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>(D) An antioxidant superoxidase dismutase (SOD) assay shows increased SOD activity in HUVECs treated with conditioned medium compared with that in cells treated with As only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>hMSCs—human mesenchymal stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>HUVECs—human umbilical vein endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g003a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g003b"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-19-01026-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>(A) HE (hematoxylin and eosin) staining for a small arteriole from the anterior lower limb of an SD rat shows a decrease in the lumen diameter of the arteriole (yellow arrow) and an increase in the number of inflammatory cells infiltrating the smooth muscles of vessel walls (green arrow) when compared with a wild-type untreated rat (left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Scale bar 200 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>(B) IHC CD31 staining for vessels reveals a decrease in staining intensity in the As-treated group compared with that in the wild-type SD rat group (yellow arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Scale bar 200 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>(C) A TUNEL assay shows numerous TUNEL-positive tissues induced by As in the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Compared with the control specimens, mMSCs-injected SD rat specimens show a decrease in TUNEL reactions, especially in regions containing anterior tibial vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Scale bar 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>SD rat—Sprague Dawley rat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>IHC—immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>CD31 stain—platelet endothelial cell adhesion molecular stain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>TUNEL assay—terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>mMSCs—mouse mesenchymal stem cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g004a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g004b"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-19-01026-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>(A) An in vivo ELISA VEGF test demonstrates that VEGF levels significantly increase in blood samples drawn from SD rats with serial mMSCs (mouse MSCs) injections for two weeks (* p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>(B) An in vivo VEGF qPCR test shows increasing gene expression in rats after serial mMSCs injections for two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>(* p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>(C) An in vivo GSH/GSSG assay shows that the GSH/GSSG ratio increases in experimental groups subjected to serial mMSCs injections for two weeks compared with that in the As-treated group (* p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>(D) In vivo antioxidant superoxidase dismutase (SOD) assay shows increased SOD activity in experimental groups subjected to serial mMSCs injections for two weeks compared with that in the As-treated group (* p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>VEGF—vascular endothelial growth factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>mMSCs—mouse mesenchymal stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>PBS—phosphate buffered saline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>MSC 1w—mouse MSCs injected for one week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>MSC 2w—mouse MSCs injected for two weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>GSH—reduced glutathione. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>GSSG—oxidized glutathione. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-19-01026-g005"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
