<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5641157</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.20004</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Circulating tumor DNA detection in head and neck cancer: evaluation of two different detection approaches </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Perdomo</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Avogbe</surname><given-names>Patrice H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foll</surname><given-names>Matthieu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abedi-Ardekani</surname><given-names>Behnoush</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Facciolla</surname><given-names>Violeta Lescher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>Devasena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9"><sup>9</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chopard</surname><given-names>Priscilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calvez-Kelm</surname><given-names>Florence Le</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vilensky</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Polesel</surname><given-names>Jerry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holcatova</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simonato</surname><given-names>Lorenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Canova</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lagiou</surname><given-names>Pagona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>James D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), Lyon 69372, France</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Institute of Nutrition, Genetics and Metabolism Research, Faculty of Medicine, Universidad El Bosque, Bogotá 110121, Colombia</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Departamento de Saúde Coletiva, Faculdade de Ciências Médicas da Santa Casa de São Paulo, São Paulo CEP01221-020, Brazil</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Instituto Angel Roffo, Buenos Aires C1417DTB, Argentina</aff><aff id="A5"><sup>5</sup> CRO Aviano National Cancer Institute, Aviano 33081, Italy</aff><aff id="A6"><sup>6</sup> Charles University, 1st Faculty of Medicine, Prague 116 36, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="A7"><sup>7</sup> Laboratory of Public Health and Population Studies, University of Padova, Padova 35122, Italy</aff><aff id="A8"><sup>8</sup> Department of Hygiene, Epidemiology and Medical Statistics, School of Medicine, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens 11527, Greece</aff><aff id="A9"><sup>9</sup> Current present address: Rajiv Gandhi Centre for Biotechnology, Trivandrum 695010, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic>Paul Brennan,</italic><email>BrennanP@iarc.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>42</issue><fpage>72621</fpage><lpage>72632</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2017 Perdomo et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The use of non-invasive biomarkers such as circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) in head and neck tumors may be of relevance in early diagnosis and eventually improved outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>We evaluated two different approaches from two case series in Europe and South America including (i) targeted screening of ctDNA mutations, and (ii) detection of TP53 mutations in plasma and oral rinses without previous knowledge of mutational status in tumor samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Targeted sequencing in 5 genes identified ctDNA mutations in plasma among 42% of HNSCC cases, 67% of who were early stage cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>No association was found between ctDNA mutation detection and overall survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of the entire coding region of the TP53 gene resulted in identification of TP53 mutations in 76% of tumor cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>However, concordance of mutation detection was low between tumor, oral rinses (11%) and plasma (2,7%) samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Identification of 5 pathogenic TP53 mutations in oral rinses from 3 non-cancer controls gives additional evidence of mutation occurrence in individuals without a diagnosed cancer and presents an additional challenge for the development of ctDNA diagnostic assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>ctDNA</kwd><kwd>head and neck</kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd><kwd>mutation</kwd><kwd>detection</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Cell-free DNA (cfDNA) are small nucleic acid fragments released in body fluids and their levels are a reflection of the dynamics between cellular mechanisms of DNA release and DNA clearance, apoptosis and necrosis, cfDNA stability, blood nuclease activity and uptake and degradation by phagocytes [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Among individuals with cancer a fraction of cfDNA is potentially of tumor origin, i.e. cfDNA fragments harboring tumor somatic nucleic acid changes that are also called circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Some studies have correlated the abundance of ctDNA with tumor size and stage, with as much as 40% of ctDNA levels in metastatic cancers but as low as 0.1-1% in premalignant or early stage disease [3–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Clinicopathological characteristics for specific tumor types, such as anatomic location, tumor grade, tumor mucinous features and treatment response [4, 9, 10] might also play an important role in the process of cfDNA release and stability in blood circulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Head and neck squamous cell carcinomas (HNSCC) are the seventh most common cause of death in the world accounting for approximately 375,000 cancer deaths annually. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In 2012, almost 700,000 new head and neck cancer cases were estimated to occur worldwide [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Despite current therapeutic interventions, the prognosis for HNSCC is relatively poor, with a 5-year survival ranging from approximately 25% to 60%, according to cancer subsite [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Diagnostic delay is a recognized challenge for patients with HNSCC, and has also been related to higher risk (30%) of advanced stage tumor diagnosis eventually impacting negatively on prognosis and survival [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>These delays could be shortened in many patients through the examination of clinically suspicious lesions using non-invasive biomarkers such as ctDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In HNSCC patients, besides circulating DNA fragments carrying tumor alterations in plasma, the saliva contains a high fraction of tumor DNA due to its close contact to oral cavity and pharyngeal tumor sites constituting an additional biological source for ctDNA detection and analysis [14–16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Our primary goals were to provide a comprehensive evaluation of the presence of ctDNA in plasma and oral rinses from a series of HNSCC cases at early and late stages and to determine the best approach to use ctDNA analysis in HNSCC early detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>We evaluated two strategies of ctDNA mutation detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>A targeted approach tested for the presence of mutations in plasma samples, previously detected in tumor samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The second approach involved ctDNA screening detection in plasma and oral rinses without prior knowledge of mutation status in tumors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2_1"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>ctDNA targeted detection in plasma samples from the ARCAGE study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>36 HNSCC cases from the ARCAGE study were selected based on carrying one or several mutations in their tumor samples in the 5 screened genes (TP53, NOTCH1, CDKN2A, CASP8, PTEN) (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>All cases were HPV negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Forty-two percent of cases (15/36) had detectable ctDNA mutations in their plasma samples, sixty seven percent of those were early stage (I, II) cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A total of 18 mutations, previously detected in the matched tumor samples, were detected in plasma with allelic fractions (AF) ranging from 0,001-0,12 (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Among those mutations, we were able to detect a TP53 16-nucleotide frameshift deletion in a stage II oropharyngeal case (Supplementary Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Cases with identified plasma mutations showed no differences in overall survival compare to those without ctDNA mutations (Log rank p=0,47). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Targeted mutation detection in plasma of 36 HNSCC cases from the ARCAGE study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Description of clinical and epidemiological characteristics of cases and ctDNA mutation detection in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Cases are organized by stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In red, mutations identified in matched tumor and plasma samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>AF: mutation allelic frequency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-72621-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>TP53 mutation detection in tumor, plasma and oral rinses of HNSCC cases from the LA study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We performed independent TP53 mutation detection analyses for the 37-late stage HNSCC cases in each sample type: tumor, plasma and oral rinses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>A total of 36 TP53 mutations were identified in tumors, 3 in plasma and 26 in oral rinses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Seventy-six percent (28/37) of cases harbored at least one TP53 mutation in the tumor sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>One case (ARG5040) had a mutation (TP53 p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Arg174Trp) found exclusively in plasma (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>We found no association between age, subsite, smoking or alcohol status and the presence of TP53 mutations in tumors (Supplementary Table 1 and Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The proportion of cases with ctDNA TP53 variants in oral rinses was higher in patients with tumors in the oral cavity 46,2% (n=6) and in the oropharynx 60% (n=3) than in the Larynx 16,7% (n=12) (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>More than 80% of overall mutations corresponded to missense variants, all localized in the DNA binding domain (aminoacids 102-292) and 86% were non-functional variants according to the functional classification based on the overall transcription activity [17] (Figure 3B and Supplementary Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The mutational distribution along the coding regions and protein domains was comparable for all three sample types (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Four cases showed concordance in mutation detection between tumor and oral rinses and only in one additional case, we identified the same mutation in tumor, plasma and oral rinses (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Fourteen cases (52%) showed detectable TP53 mutations in tumor but none in plasma or oral rinses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Description of TP53 mutations identified in Tumor, plasma and oral rinses from a series of 37 cases from the LA study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Only cases with TP53 mutations are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In red, mutations identified in matched tumor and oral rinses or plasma samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>AF: average allelic frequency from both libraries. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-72621-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Comparison of TP53 mutations found in tumor, plasma and oral rinses from a series of 37 cases from the LA study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>(A) Proportion of cases harboring TP53 mutations in tumor, plasma and oral rinses by subsite. (B) Diagrams of mutation distribution along the TP53 coding regions and protein domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Mutation colors represent: green: Missense Mutations; black: Truncating Mutations (Nonsense, Nonstop, Frameshift deletion, Frameshift insertion, Splice site). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-72621-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>TP53 mutation detection in non-cancer controls </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>One additional finding was the observation that TP53 mutations could be detected in the plasma and oral rinses of a few non-cancer individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We identified 5 TP53 mutations in oral rinses from 3 individuals without cancer diagnosis with AFs ranging from 0,001-0,004. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>All 5 mutations were classified as pathogenic and located in the DNA binding domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Two of those individuals were both never smokers and non-drinkers (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Description of TP53 mutations found in oral rinses of 3 Argentinian controls with the mutations’ allelic fractions detected in the two libraries </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Control ID </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Disease classification (ICD-10-CM) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Coverage Library 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Coverage Library 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Allelic Fraction Library 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Allelic Fraction Library 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Chr </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Start </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>End </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Ref </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Alt </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Mutation Type </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Cosmic-76 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Hgvs DNA Change </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Hgvs Protein Change </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Transactivation Class </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>ARG553 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Hydrocele and spermatocele </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>35483 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>36558 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>0,001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>0,002 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>7577530 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>7577530 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Missense Mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>COSM43967 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>c.614A&gt;G </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>p.Ile251Phe </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>non-functional </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>ARG410* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>unspecified disorders of male genital organs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>28491 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>38571 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>0,004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>0,003 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>7577548 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>7577548 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Missense Mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>COSM1640833 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>c.661G&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>p.Gly245Ser </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>supertrans </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>ARG594* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Osteoarthritis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>29062 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>27304 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>0,001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>0,001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>7577609 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>7577609 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>G </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Splice Site </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>COSM562645 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>c.673-1G&gt;C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>NA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>NA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>37034 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>21337 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>0,002 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>0,002 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>7578188 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>7578188 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Missense Mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>COSM44853 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>c.733G&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>p.Glu221Lys </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>non-functional </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>39098 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>22393 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>0,004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>0,004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>7578235 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>7578235 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Missense Mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>COSM99631 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>c.751A&gt;T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>p.Tyr205Cys </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>non-functional </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>NA: Not applicable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Chr: Chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>* both non-smokers non-drinkers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>As was reported before by us, 5 TP53 mutations were found in the plasma of 4 of the non-cancer individuals analyzed from Argentina, one being confirmed to be a germline variant [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Targeted ctDNA screening is an increasingly used non-invasive method for mutation detection in human cancer, both for diagnosis and disease monitoring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been shown that screening for specific mutations in plasma and saliva of HNSCC patients is a sensitive and specific approach [4, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In our series of 36 cases from the ARCAGE study, we detected specific tumor-concordant mutations in 5 genes in the plasma of 42% of cases and the majority of those (67%) were early-stage cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>However, our overall mutation detection rate in plasma was low as we were able to detect only 28% of the total number of mutations tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Limitations regarding sample preservation might account in part for the low mutation detection rate in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In particular, cfDNA degradation due to prolonged storage is one of the pre-analytical variables that have an impact on cfDNA recovery and mutation detection, and recent studies recommend the use of plasma samples or cfDNA extracts up to nine months of storage at −20°C or −80°C [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Additionally, preanalytical recommendations for ctDNA analysis indicate that blood samples can be kept up to 4 hrs at room temperature (RT) before plasma preparation without major impact on cfDNA concentration [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The protocols for blood recovery and processing followed by both studies (ARCAGE and LA) allowed a time window for blood processing up to 12 hrs at RT, which could have resulted in a reduction of cfDNA concentration before plasma storage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This is the first study evaluating ctDNA using retrospective HNSCC samples from a case series where plasma samples exceeded 10 years of storage at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Fifty percent of mutation detection in long stored plasma has been only previously reported for KRAS mutations identified by Sanger sequencing in plasma stored up to 6 years from metastatic colorectal patients [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Analysis of ctDNA detection and survival in the ARCAGE cases found no association between ctDNA mutation status and HNSCC survival overall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>No additional studies have previously evaluated the impact in survival of ctDNA detection in head and neck cancer cases limiting the comparability of our results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Association between ctDNA detection at diagnosis and survival is consistent across several metastatic and advanced tumor types [5, 21–23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>However, limited data is available on early stages and while ctDNA detection has been found to be associated with poor overall survival in some early stage pancreatic and colorectal cases [7, 24] no difference was observed in early breast cancer cases [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Future prospective studies are then necessary to evaluate the prognostic clinical significance of ctDNA detection in both early and late stage HNSCC cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>While targeted sequencing might be sufficient for post-diagnosis uses of ctDNA, in the case of early detection it might be necessary to interrogate the whole coding region of the most frequently altered genes in HNSCC rather than focusing on selected targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The mutational profile of HNSCC is characterized by recurrent alterations in tumor suppressor genes (of the 15 most common HNSCC mutated genes only HRAS and PIK3CA are oncogenes) where singular hot spots are infrequent and the mutational spectra covers various exon regions and/or specific functional protein coding domains [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Consistently with previous reports, 76% of the tumor cases from the LA study analyzed harbored a TP53 mutation [25, 26], which makes TP53 one of the suitable biomarkers for non-invasive early detection of HNSCCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Yet, the concordance in TP53 mutation detection between tumor and oral rinses was 11% for tumors located in the oral cavity and overlapping sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The salivary genome consists of various DNAs representing the genome of an individual, oral microbiota and infecting DNA viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Such diversity can undermine tumor DNA detection while increasing the mutational background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>However, the quality and yield of DNA that can be obtained from saliva as well as its stability for long-term storage might compensate this limitation and might make it a robust analyte choice for diagnostics [15, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In this regard, Wang and collaborators identified mutations in 6 commonly mutated genes for HNSCC in both saliva and plasma of 93 patients and reported 100% sensitivity of ctDNA detection in saliva specimens in tumors of the oral cavity [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the authors found that both the sensitivity and the fraction of mutant alleles decreased in HNSCCs distal to the oral cavity which agrees with the higher percentage of mutations we have found in both oral cavity and oropharynx compared to laryngeal cases. TP53 mutations have been previously identified in 23,5% of oral rinses from cases with homogeneous oral leukoplakia (OL) and in 40% of OL cases with an earlier diagnosis of one or several oral squamous cell carcinomas [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>One additional study, based on microsatellite marker detection in tumor and exfoliated oral mucosal cells, detected tumor DNA in 44% of oral rinse samples [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Variations in tumor DNA detection frequencies between these studies might be due to the use of different mutation detection techniques (massive parallel sequencing or Sanger sequencing). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found 22 additional mutations in oral rinses from 11 cases not found in their matched tumor samples but identified in similar coding regions (aminoacids102-292) and with the same pattern of mutational distribution along the TP53 protein domains as those found in tumor samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The additional burden of mutation in oral rinses might reflect tumor heterogeneity (especially in the case of advanced tumors) where sub clonal populations of cells are not necessarily captured by tumor biopsies and/or could reflect genetic alterations in the squamous epithelial cells lining the oral cavity as a result of field cancerization, mostly associated to smoking and alcohol consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Evidence of mutational heterogeneity in the oral epithelium of HNSCC cancer patients has been recently reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Wood and collaborators showed the presence of discordant TP53 mutations in dysplastic tissue and adjacent cancer tissue from the same patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>They also reported the presence of different mutations in other genes at very low allelic frequencies (&lt;0,05-0,2) reflecting sub clonal cell populations present in either adjacent or distant dysplastic tissue but absent in the pair tumor tissue [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Our percentage of mutation detection in plasma in cases from Argentina (LA study) was much lower (8,1%) compared to oral rinses (40,5%, all sites) and restricted to cases in larynx and overlapping sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that the impact on ctDNA detection after long storage of plasma (discussed above) had a higher effect on cases from Argentina (8,1% ctDNA plasma detection) since these samples were collected 4 years before samples from the ARCAGE study (28% ctDNA plasma detection). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Finally, identification of TP53 mutations of non-cancer individuals introduces new questions regarding the biological role of such pathogenic mutations in healthy individuals and challenges the specificity of ctDNA screening in possible diagnostic scenarios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Although detection of TP53 mutations in plasma, human skin and peritoneal fluid of healthy individuals has been reported previously [18, 30–32], we detected for the first time, 5 pathogenic TP53 mutations in oral rinses from 3 non-cancer individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>However, one limitation of our results is that non-independent germline sample (buffy coat) was not available to confirm the somatic origin of these mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In fact, the presence of circulating-mutated fragments resulting from clonal hematopoiesis in healthy individuals has been well documented [33–38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Most recently, in 53105 individuals without a known cancer diagnosis from the Exome Aggregation Consortium, 2,7% germline DNA repair mutations were identified [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Without discarding the plausibility of these mutations being germline alterations, the low allelic fraction in the mutations detected in oral rinses (0,001-0,004) suggests that they may well correspond to somatic changes in the oral mucosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>A recent study has reported a higher somatic mutation burden in 9 head and neck non-malignant tissues compared to 61 benign tissues [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Since we used hospital-based controls as a proxy for healthy individuals, mutations identified might reflect biological processes underlining inflammatory responses (for 2 never smoker, non-drinker controls) and/or the smoking and alcohol accumulated effect in the oral mucosa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Together, our findings confirm the feasibility of ctDNA targeted mutation detection in plasma of HNSCC patients including early stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Blind detection of TP53 mutations in oral rinses or saliva had a low concordance compared to mutations identified in the matched tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Identification of 5 TP53 mutations in oral rinses from healthy controls confirms the presence of a small percentage of pathogenic mutations in healthy individuals, a fact that should be taken into consideration when developing diagnostic ctDNA assays for early HNSCC detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Further prospective studies are necessary in order to define both the diagnostic value and prognostic clinical significance of ctDNA detection in HNSCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4_1"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Study population and mutation detection design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Cases and controls were selected from two multicentre studies: one conducted in South America (LA study) between 1998 and 2002 and the second between 2002 and 2005 in Europe (ARCAGE study), from which biological samples were available in the IARC biorepository, along with complete epidemiological data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Extensive details on data and sample collection from these studies are included elsewhere [41–43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Briefly, all subjects underwent personal interviews to collect information on lifestyle exposures and hospital records were reviewed to obtain clinical and pathological information [41, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Centralized HPV testing was completed for both studies determined on serology testing as described before [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>HPV positivity was defined based on HPV16 E6 status, which has been shown to be a highly sensitive and specific marker of HPV16-related oropharyngeal tumours [43, 45, 46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all participants in the two studies, and the analysis was approved by the Ethical Review Committee of the International Agency for Research on Cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In order to test the targeted ctDNA detection approach, we selected 36 HNSCC fresh tumor samples, including 14 early (stage I and II) cases, from the ARCAGE study with available matched plasma samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Oral rinses were not collected as part of the ARCAGE study [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>DNA from 36 HNSCC tumors had been previously sequenced and found to carry 65 mutations in 5 genes (TP53, NOTCH1, CDKN2A, CASP8, PTEN) from a panel of the 14 most frequently mutated genes (CASP8, CDKN2A, FAT1, FBXW7, HRAS, IRF6, MLL2, NOTCH1, NSD1, PTEN, PIK3CA, RB1, TP53, TP63) (unpublished results). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Gene selection was based on an independent analysis of TCGA data on HNSCC using MutsigCV algorithm complemented with the list of the most frequently mutated genes reported in the literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>To evaluate detection of ctDNA mutations without previous knowledge of tumor mutational status, we decided to sequence the entire coding region of TP53, as it is the most frequently mutated gene in HNSCC [25, 26, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>We selected 37 cases diagnosed as HNSCC from the LA study, all late stage (III and IV), from which tumor, plasma and oral rinse samples were available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>A total of 49 hospital based controls from the same study with plasma and oral rinses were selected and matched by sex, age, smoking and alcohol status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Clinical and epidemiological characteristics for all Argentinian cases and controls are described in Supplementary Table 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Sample preparation and DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>All cases had biological samples collected at diagnosis and before any treatment [41–43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>When feasible, two 10-ml samples of blood were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>A portion of the blood was centrifuged for 10 min at 2000 rpm and white blood cells, red blood cells, and plasma were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>All samples were stored locally at −80°C (or at least −70°C depending on type of freezer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The amount of time between sample collection and freezing did not exceed 12 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Oral rinses were collected by performing gentle strokes in predefined areas including the right and left buccal mucosa, right, left and dorsal side of the tongue, and inside of the upper and lower lip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Cells from brushes were suspended in tubes containing phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Participants subsequently gargled with saline, and the resulting suspension was added to the same tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Samples were centrifuged at 3000 g for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Supernatant was discarded leaving ∼1,0ml to resuspend the pellet in. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Samples were frozen at −70°C until shipment to Lyon (France). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Biopsy specimens were placed in liquid nitrogen or in freezers at −70°C, always within 8 hours of collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Specimens were shipped on dry ice to Lyon, where they were stored at −70°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Fresh tumor tissue underwent pathological review in order to select samples with a minimum of 60% tumor cellularity for DNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Tumor DNA was extracted using the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>cfDNA was extracted from 0,6-2,1 mL of plasma and from 1,6 to 2,0 mL of oral rinses using the QIAamp DNA Circulating Nucleic Acid kit (Qiagen) and following manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>cfDNA was eluted into 100 μL of elution buffer and quantified with the Qubit DNA high-sensitivity assay kit (Invitrogen Corporation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Details regarding plasma and oral rinse volume and amount of cfDNA for all cases are included in the Supplementary Table 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Primer design and amplification of targets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Twenty-one amplicons of 150 bp in size were designed (Eurofins Genomics Ebersberg, Germany) to cover targeted regions from the 5 selected genes, where mutations were identified in HNSCC fresh tumor samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>A validated in-house protocol was used to set up PCRs in 20μL reaction volume, containing 5 ng cfDNA, 60 nM of primer pool and 0,73 μL of High fidelity HotStarTaq enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Amplification was carried out in DNA engine Tetrad 2 Peltier Thermal Cycler (BIORAD) as follows: 15 min at 95°C and 30 cycles of 15 seconds at 95°C and 2 min at specific annealing temperature and 10 min at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences and amplification conditions are described in Supplementary Table 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Primer design and amplification conditions for the TP53 mutation discovery assays followed the procedures previously described [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Library preparation and sequencing in an ion torrentTM proton sequencer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Both targeted and discovery ctDNA sequencing assays followed the same library preparation and sequencing protocol previously described [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The following sequencing quality controls were applied: Reads with a mapping quality below 20 were excluded from subsequent analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>An on-target coverage cut off of 400X for tumor and 3000X for plasma/oral rinses was used to select libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Additionally, libraries for which the on-target median coverage was significantly lower in comparison to the other libraries sequenced in the same batch were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>On-target median coverage for both libraries is shown in Supplementary Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Sequencing data analyses and validation of detected mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>For the calling of variants, we used Needlestack, an ultra-sensitive variant caller, which estimates the distribution of sequencing errors across multiple samples to reliably identify variants present in very low proportion (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/IARCbioinfo/needlestack">https://github.com/IARCbioinfo/needlestack</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>A detail description of the Needlestack variant caller has been previously published [18, 48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Variant calls were annotated using ANNOVAR [49] and only TP53 mutations reported in COSMIC-76 that were indels, nonsense, splicing, or missense variants reported as deleterious in SIFT or Polyphen, were kept for subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>OncoPrinter and MutationMapper tools were used for visualization of mutational data [50, 51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Technical duplication and false positive filtering </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>To account for the sequencing errors and the potential false positive calls in the TP53 discovery assay, additional quality control tests were undertaken: The whole process from PCR amplification, library preparation, and sequencing for each sample (tumor, plasma and oral rinses) was carried out in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Each technical duplicate pair was assessed independently on separate plates to avoid sample contamination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>When calling TP53 mutations in cases and controls, Needlestack models de distribution of recurring sequencing errors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>In some cases, some rare, random errors generated by the DNA polymerase during sequencing will be identified as variants (potential false positives). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>However, such errors will be generally specific to a particular library preparation and/or library sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>To filter out these rare errors, only mutations called in the two independent technical duplicates were considered valid and included in subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we identified and excluded a few genomic positions having a particularly high proportion (&gt;10%) of false positive calls (i.e. ‘variants’ with allelic fractions higher than the estimated sequencing error rates, but not replicable in two independent libraries). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Survival data was available for all 36 ARCAGE cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Overall survival was calculated from cancer diagnosis to death for any cause or end of follow up (last follow up date: 30/01/2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Follow-up was censored at 5 years, given that most cancer related events occur before that time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The Kaplan-Meier estimator was used to estimate the distribution of the 5-year survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Multivariate Cox proportional hazard models were used to estimate hazard ratios (HRs) and their corresponding p values for ctDNA mutation presence using age, subsite, stage, smoking and alcohol status as covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Log-rank test was used to compare the different survival distributions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Clinical characteristics were compared between tumor samples with and without detectable TP53 mutations with Fisher's exact test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY FIGURE AND TABLES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-72621-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1029" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-72621-s002.docx" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1031" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><p>The authors wish to acknowledge Dr. Felipe Vaca for his valuable collaboration in the standardization of the targeted sequencing assays for the ARCAGE cases and Valérie Gaborieau for her contribution in database curation and data homogenization. The authors acknowledge all patients who donated their biological specimens.</p><p>This work was undertaken during the tenure of a Postdoctoral Fellowship to Dr Sandra Perdomo and to Dr Patrice Avogbe from The International Agency for Research on Cancer, partially supported by the European Commission FP7 Marie Curie Actions – People – Co-funding of regional, national and international programmes (COFUND).</p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Author contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>PB and SP conceived and designed the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>DA, MV, IH, JP, LS, CC and PL coordinated the contributing studies, provided samples and associated data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>SP, PA, FLCK, PC and JDM developed and undertook the laboratory procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>SP, PA, and VLF performed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>BAA reviewed pathological specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>MF and JDM developed Needlestack. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>SP and MF performed sequencing analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>SP analysed and interpreted the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>SP and PB wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed and approved the final version for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>CONFLICTs OF INTEREST </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>FUNDING SOURCES </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>This work has been funded by IARC. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>cfDNA</term><def><p>cell free DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ctDNA</term><def><p>circulating tumor DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HNSCC</term><def><p>head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AF</term><def><p>allelic frequency</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>1FleischhackerMSchmidtBCirculating nucleic acids (CNAs) and cancer--a surveyBiochim Biophys Acta2007177518123217137717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>2VolikSAlcaideMMorinRDCollinsCCCell-free DNA (cfDNA): clinical significance and utility in cancer shaped by emerging technologiesMol Cancer Res20161489890827422709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>3ForshewTMurtazaMParkinsonCGaleDTsuiDWKaperFDawsonSJPiskorzAMJimenez-LinanMBentleyDHadfieldJMayAPCaldasCNoninvasive identification and monitoring of cancer mutations by targeted deep sequencing of plasma DNASci Transl Med20124136ra168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>4BettegowdaCSausenMLearyRJKindeIWangYAgrawalNBartlettBRWangHLuberBAlaniRMAntonarakisESAzadNSBardelliADetection of circulating tumor DNA in early- and late-stage human malignanciesSci Transl Med20146224ra224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>5DiehlFSchmidtKChotiMARomansKGoodmanSLiMThorntonKAgrawalNSokollLSzaboSAKinzlerKWVogelsteinBDiazLAJrCirculating mutant DNA to assess tumor dynamicsNat Med20071498599018670422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>6NewmanAMBratmanSVToJWynneJFEclovNCModlinLALiuCLNealJWWakeleeHAMerrittREShragerJBLooBWAlizadehAADiehnMAn ultrasensitive method for quantitating circulating tumor DNA with broad patient coverageNat Med20142054855424705333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>7SausenMPhallenJAdleffVJonesSLearyRJBarrettMTAnagnostouVParpart-LiSMurphyDKay LiQHrubanCAScharpfRWhiteJRClinical implications of genomic alterations in the tumour and circulation of pancreatic cancer patientsNat Commun20156768626154128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>8BeaverJAJelovacDBalukrishnaSCochranRLCroessmannSZabranskyDJWongHYValda ToroPCidadoJBlairBGChuDBurnsTHigginsMJDetection of cancer DNA in plasma of patients with early-stage breast cancerClin Cancer Res2014202643265024504125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>9WangYSpringerSZhangMMcMahonKWKindeIDobbynLPtakJBremHChaichanaKGalliaGLGokaslanZLGrovesMLJalloGIDetection of tumor-derived DNA in cerebrospinal fluid of patients with primary tumors of the brain and spinal cordProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20151129704970926195750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>10SwystunLLMukherjeeSLiawPCBreast cancer chemotherapy induces the release of cell-free DNA, a novel procoagulant stimulusJ Thromb Haemost201192313232121838758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>11FerlayJSoerjomataramIErvikMDikshitREserSMathersCRebeloMParkinDMFormanDBrayF2014GLOBOCAN 2012 v1.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Cancer Incidence and Mortality Worldwide: IARC CancerBase No. 11 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>12GattaGBottaLSanchezMJAndersonLAPierannunzioDLicitraLGroupEWPrognoses and improvement for head and neck cancers diagnosed in Europe in early 2000s: the EUROCARE-5 population-based studyEur J Cancer2015512130214326421817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="?"><plain>13GomezISeoaneJVarela-CentellesPDizPTakkoucheBIs diagnostic delay related to advanced-stage oral cancer? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysisEur J Oral Sci200911754154619758250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>14WangYSpringerSMulveyCLSillimanNSchaeferJSausenMJamesNRettigEMGuoTPickeringCRBishopJAChungCHCalifanoJADetection of somatic mutations and HPV in the saliva and plasma of patients with head and neck squamous cell carcinomasSci Transl Med20157293ra104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>15BonneNJWongDTSalivary biomarker development using genomic, proteomic and metabolomic approachesGenome Med201248223114182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>16SpaffordMFKochWMReedALCalifanoJAXuLHEisenbergerCFYipLLeongPLWuLLiuSXJeronimoCWestraWHSidranskyDDetection of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma among exfoliated oral mucosal cells by microsatellite analysisClin Cancer Res2001760761211297256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>17PetitjeanAMatheEKatoSIshiokaCTavtigianSVHainautPOlivierMImpact of mutant p53 functional properties on TP53 mutation patterns and tumor phenotype: lessons from recent developments in the IARC TP53 databaseHum Mutat20072862262917311302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>18Fernandez-CuestaLPerdomoSAvogbePHLeblayNDelhommeTMGaborieauVAbedi-ArdekaniBChanudetEOlivierMZaridzeDMukeriaAVilenskyMHolcatovaIIdentification of circulating tumor DNA for the early detection of small-cell lung cancerEBioMedicine20161011712327377626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>19El MessaoudiSRoletFMouliereFThierryARCirculating cell free DNA: preanalytical considerationsClin Chim Acta201342422223023727028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>20KopreskiMSBenkoFAKweeCLeitzelKEEskanderELiptonAGockeCDDetection of mutant K-ras DNA in plasma or serum of patients with colorectal cancerBr J Cancer199776129312999374374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>21YangXZhuoMYeXBaiHWangZSunYZhaoJAnTDuanJWuMWangJQuantification of mutant alleles in circulating tumor DNA can predict survival in lung cancerOncotarget201672081020824<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.8021">https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.8021</ext-link>26989078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>22SchwaederleMHusainHFantaPTPiccioniDEKesariSSchwabRBPatelSPHarismendyOIkedaMParkerBAKurzrockRUse of liquid biopsies in clinical oncology: pilot experience in 168 patientsClin Cancer Res2016225497550527185373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>23BidardFCMadicJMarianiPPiperno-NeumannSRampanouAServoisVCassouxNDesjardinsLMilderMVaucherIPiergaJYLebofskyRSternMHLantzODetection rate and prognostic value of circulating tumor cells and circulating tumor DNA in metastatic uveal melanomaInt J Cancer20141341207121323934701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>24TieJWangYTomasettiCLiLSpringerSKindeISillimanNTaceyMWongHLChristieMKosmiderSSkinnerIWongRCirculating tumor DNA analysis detects minimal residual disease and predicts recurrence in patients with stage II colon cancerSci Transl Med20168346ra392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>25The Cancer Genome Atlas NetworkComprehensive genomic characterization of head and neck squamous cell carcinomasNature201551757658225631445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>26StranskyNEgloffAMTwardADKosticADCibulskisKSivachenkoAKryukovGVLawrenceMSSougnezCMcKennaASheflerERamosAHStojanovPThe mutational landscape of head and neck squamous cell carcinomaScience20113331157116021798893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>27FábiánTKFejérdyPCsermelyPSalivary genomics, transcriptomics and proteomics: the emerging concept of the oral ecosystem and their use in the early diagnosis of cancer and other diseasesCurr Genomics20089112119424479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>28LópezMAguirreJMCuevasNAnzolaMVidegainJAguirregaviriaJCastroAMartínez de PancorboMUse of cytological specimens for p53 gene alteration detection in oral squamous cell carcinoma risk patientsClin Oncol200416366370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>29WoodHMDalyCChalkleyRSenguvenBRossLEganPChengotPGrahamJSethiNOngTKMacLennanKRabbittsPConwayCThe genomic road to invasion-examining the similarities and differences in the genomes of associated oral pre-cancer and cancer samplesGenome Med201795328592326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>30GormallyEVineisPMatulloGVegliaFCabouxELe RouxEPelusoMGarteSGuarreraSMunniaAAiroldiLAutrupHMalaveilleCTP53 and KRAS2 mutations in plasma DNA of healthy subjects and subsequent cancer occurrence: a prospective studyCancer Res2006666871687616818665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>31KrimmelJDSchmittMWHarrellMIAgnewKJKennedySREmondMJLoebLASwisherEMRisquesRAUltra-deep sequencing detects ovarian cancer cells in peritoneal fluid and reveals somatic TP53 mutations in noncancerous tissuesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20161360056010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>32MartincorenaICampbellPJSomatic mutation in cancer and normal cellsScience20153491483148926404825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>33GenoveseGKahlerAKHandsakerRELindbergJRoseSABakhoumSFChambertKMickENealeBMFromerMPurcellSMSvantessonOLandenMClonal hematopoiesis and blood-cancer risk inferred from blood DNA sequenceN Engl J Med20143712477248725426838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>34JacobsKBYeagerMZhouWWacholderSWangZRodriguez-SantiagoBHutchinsonADengXLiuCHornerMJCullenMEpsteinCGBurdettLDetectable clonal mosaicism and its relationship to aging and cancerNat Genet20124465165822561519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>35JaiswalSFontanillasPFlannickJManningAGraumanPVMarBGLindsleyRCMermelCHBurttNChavezAHigginsJMMoltchanovVKuoFCAge-related clonal hematopoiesis associated with adverse outcomesN Engl J Med20143712488249825426837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>36LaurieCCLaurieCARiceKDohenyKFZelnickLRMcHughCPLingHHetrickKNPughEWAmosCWeiQWangLELeeJEDetectable clonal mosaicism from birth to old age and its relationship to cancerNat Genet20124464265022561516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>37WongTNRamsinghGYoungALMillerCAToumaWWelchJSLamprechtTLShenDHundalJFultonRSHeathSBatyJDKlcoJMRole of TP53 mutations in the origin and evolution of therapy-related acute myeloid leukaemiaNature201551855255525487151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>38XieMLuCWangJMcLellanMDJohnsonKJWendlMCMcMichaelJFSchmidtHKYellapantulaVMillerCAOzenbergerBAWelchJSLinkDCAge-related mutations associated with clonal hematopoietic expansion and malignanciesNat Med2014201472147825326804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>39PritchardCCMateoJWalshMFDe SarkarNAbidaWBeltranHGarofaloAGulatiRCarreiraSEelesRElementoORubinMARobinsonDInherited DNA-repair gene mutations in men with metastatic prostate cancerN Engl J Med201637544345327433846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>40YadavVKDeGregoriJDeSThe landscape of somatic mutations in protein coding genes in apparently benign human tissues carries signatures of relaxed purifying selectionNucleic Acids Res2016442075208426883632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>41LagiouPGeorgilaCMinakiPAhrensWPohlabelnHBenhamouSBouchardyCSlamovaASchejbalovaMMerlettiFRichiardiLKjaerheimKAgudoAAlcohol-related cancers and genetic susceptibility in Europe: the ARCAGE project: study samples and data collectionEur J Cancer Prev200918768418830131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>42SzymańskaKHungRJWünsch-FilhoVEluf-NetoJCuradoMPKoifmanSMatosEMenezesAFernandezLDaudtAWBoffettaPBrennanPAlcohol and tobacco, and the risk of cancers of the upper aerodigestive tract in Latin America: a case–control studyCancer Causes Control2011221037104621607590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>43HerreroRCastellsagueXPawlitaMLissowskaJKeeFBalaramPRajkumarTSridharHRoseBPintosJFernandezLIdrisASanchezMJHuman papillomavirus and oral cancer: the International Agency for Research on Cancer multicenter studyJ Natl Cancer Inst2003951772178314652239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>44AnantharamanDGheitTWaterboerTAbedi-ArdekaniBCarreiraCMcKay-ChopinSGaborieauVMarronMLagiouPAhrensWHolcatovaIMerlettiFKjaerheimKHuman papillomavirus infections and upper aero-digestive tract cancers: the ARCAGE studyJ Natl Cancer Inst201310553654523503618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>45ReuschenbachMWaterboerTWallinKLEinenkelJDillnerJHamsikovaEEschenbachDZimmerHHeiligBKopitzJPawlitaMDoeberitzMWentzensenNCharacterization of humoral immune responses against p16, p53, HPV16 E6 and HPV16 E7 in patients with HPV-associated cancersInt J Cancer20081232626263118785210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>46KreimerARJohanssonMWaterboerTKaaksRChang-ClaudeJDrogenDTjonnelandAOvervadKQuirosJRGonzalezCASanchezMJLarranagaNNavarroCEvaluation of human papillomavirus antibodies and risk of subsequent head and neck cancerJ Clin Oncol2013312708271523775966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>47MorrisLGChandramohanRWestLZehirAChakravartyDPfisterDGWongRJLeeNYShermanEJBaxiSSGanlyISinghBShahJPThe molecular landscape of recurrent and metastatic head and neck cancers: insights from a precision oncology sequencing platformJAMA Oncol2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>48Le Calvez-KelmFFollMWozniakMBDelhommeTMDurandGChopardPPertesiMFabianovaEAdamcakovaZHolcatovaIForetovaLJanoutVValleeMPKRAS mutations in blood circulating cell-free DNA: a pancreatic cancer case-controlOncotarget201677882778840<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.12386">https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.12386</ext-link>27705932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>49YangHWangKGenomic variant annotation and prioritization with ANNOVAR and wANNOVARNat Protoc2015101556156626379229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>50GaoJAksoyBADogrusozUDresdnerGGrossBSumerSOSunYJacobsenASinhaRLarssonECeramiESanderCSchultzNIntegrative analysis of complex cancer genomics and clinical profiles using the cBioPortalSci Signal20136l1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>51CeramiEGaoJDogrusozUGrossBESumerSOAksoyBAJacobsenAByrneCJHeuerMLLarssonEAntipinYRevaBGoldbergAPThe cBio cancer genomics portal: an open platform for exploring multidimensional cancer genomics dataCancer Discov2012240140422588877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
