<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Qual Life Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Qual Life Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Quality of Life Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9343</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-2649</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5770482</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-017-1704-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Health-related quality of life and its determinants in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><address><phone>+31 10 40 89 189</phone><email>degroot@imta.eur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Redekop</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Versteegh</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sleijfer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oosterwijk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kiemeney</surname><given-names>L. A. L. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uyl-de Groot</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000092621349</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6906.9</institution-id><institution>Erasmus School of Health Policy and Management, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Rotterdam, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 1738, 3000 DR Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000092621349</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6906.9</institution-id><institution>Institute for Medical Technology Assessment, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Rotterdam, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 1738, 3000 DR Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology and Cancer Genomics Netherlands, </institution><institution>Erasmus MC Cancer Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 5201, 3008 AE Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0444 9382</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10417.33</institution-id><institution>Department of Urology, Radboud Institute for Molecular Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Radboud University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 9101, 6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0444 9382</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10417.33</institution-id><institution>Department for Health Evidence, Radboud Institute for Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Radboud University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 9101, 6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Purpose </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Based on improvements of progression-free survival (PFS), new agents for metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC) have been approved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>It is assumed that one of the benefits is a delay in health-related quality of life (HRQoL) deterioration as a result of a delay in progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, little data are available supporting this relationship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This study aims to provide insight into the most important determinants of HRQoL (including progression of disease) of patients with mRCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>A patient registry (PERCEPTION) was created to evaluate treatment of patients with (m)RCC in the Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>HRQoL was measured, using the EORTC QLQ-C30 and EQ-5D-5L, every 3 months in the first year of participation in the study, and every 6 months in the second year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Participation started as soon as possible following a diagnosis of (m)RCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Random effects models were used to study associations between HRQoL and patient and disease characteristics, symptoms and treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Eighty-seven patients with mRCC completed 304 questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The average EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status was 69 (SD, 19) before progression and 61 (SD, 22) after progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the average EQ-5D utility was 0.75 (SD, 0.19) before progression and 0.66 (SD, 0.30) after progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The presence of fatigue, pain, dyspnoea, and the application of radiotherapy were associated with significantly lower EQ-5D utilities. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Key drivers for reduced HRQoL in mRCC are disease symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Since symptoms increase with progression of disease, targeted therapies that increase PFS are expected to postpone reductions in HRQoL in mRCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s11136-017-1704-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Health-related quality of life</kwd><kwd>EQ-5D</kwd><kwd>EORTC QLQ-C30</kwd><kwd>Cost-effectiveness analysis</kwd><kwd>Metastatic renal cell carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Targeted therapy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001826</institution-id><institution>ZonMw</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>152001014</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Uyl-de Groot</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Pfizer BV</institution></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Roche Nederland BV</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer International Publishing AG, part of Springer Nature 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Renal cell carcinoma (RCC) accounts for 90% of all kidney cancers [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>While the prognosis of patients with localised disease treated with surgery is relatively good, the prognosis of patients with advanced or metastatic disease is poor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Median overall survival (OS) ranges from 7.8 months for patients with a poor risk to 43.2 months for patients with a favourable risk according to the Heng criteria [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Besides the impact of metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC) on survival, mRCC can be associated with severe symptoms, such as cachexia and/or anorexia, asthenia and/or fatigue, pain, anaemia, and venous thromboembolism [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Since 2006, several new targeted therapies have been approved for the treatment of mRCC such as sunitinib, sorafenib, pazopanib and everolimus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In phase III studies, these therapies improved progression-free survival (PFS) of patients with mRCC over the diverse comparators [4–11], but the effect on OS was less pronounced, likely (partly) due to treatment crossover. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>It is assumed that one of the benefits of the new therapies is a delay in HRQoL deterioration as a result of a delay in progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Clinicians feel that a better PFS translates into a better HRQoL [12], but little data are available supporting this relationship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In the context of the high prices of targeted therapies which form a strain on health care budgets, it is important to establish whether indeed a delay in progression delays HRQoL deterioration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This study is the first to provide insight into the most important determinants of HRQoL (including progression of disease) of patients with mRCC using data from a patient registry in the Netherlands [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Additionally, this study aims to assess if the association between progression and HRQoL, if one exists, is also captured by measures used in economic evaluations to assess benefit (i.e. EQ-5D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Patients and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Study population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>A patient registry (i.e. PERCEPTION) was created to evaluate treatment of patients with (m)RCC in the Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Patients with RCC (all stages) of any histological subtype diagnosed from 2011 until June 30th 2013 in 25 of 32 hospitals (both general and academic) in three regions in the Netherlands were invited to participate, and fill out HRQoL questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Eligible patients were identified through the hospitals’ registration systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the Netherlands Cancer Registry (NCR), which maintains a cancer registration database of all cancer patients in the Netherlands, was used to ensure that no patients were missed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The research protocol was approved by the medical ethics committee of Radboud university medical center in Nijmegen (CMO Region Arnhem-Nijmegen) in May 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all patients participating in the HRQoL study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Cancer-specific HRQoL was measured using the EORTC (European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer) QLQ-C30 questionnaire (v3.0) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This measure includes five functional scales (physical, role, emotional, social and cognitive), three symptom scales (fatigue, nausea &amp; vomiting and pain), a global health status/QOL scale and six single items (dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhoea and financial difficulties). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In addition to the EORTC QLQ-C30, the EQ-5D-5L was used to measure HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The EQ-5D-5L is a preference-based generic measure, and measures HRQoL on five dimensions, i.e. mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Each dimension includes five severity levels [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Patients were sent a HRQoL questionnaire every 3 months in the first year of participation in the study, and every 6 months in the second year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Participation started as soon as possible following a diagnosis of (m)RCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In addition to data on HRQoL, data on demographics, clinical and laboratory factors (to determine the patient’s risk group [16]) were collected retrospectively from individual patient records using uniform case report forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, data on treatment schemes and treatment endpoints (e.g. survival) were derived from patient records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Data collection stopped at the end of 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For each scale of the EORTC QLQ-C30, the average of the items that contributed to that scale was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>They were then linearly transformed in line with the EORTC QLQ-C30 scoring manual [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>EQ-5D utilities were derived by combining the answers to the EQ-5D-5L with the Dutch EQ-5D- 5L tariff [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Mean EQ-5D utilities and HRQoL based on the EORTC QLQ-C30 were calculated by taking the average of the observations for each patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The proportion of reported problems for each EQ-5D dimension were presented by taking the modus (i.e. the level reported most frequently) across observations for each patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>If two or more modes exist, the highest level was taken. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>HRQoL was evaluated separately for the periods before and after progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In the period before progression of disease, a further distinction was made between wait-and-see and treatment with (first-line) targeted therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Treatment was assumed to last until progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Response including progression of disease was defined based on RECIST (as mentioned in the radiology report). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>As a substitute (if unavailable) data managers were instructed to register the response as indicated by the physician in the medical record. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Patients who did not start therapy within the follow-up period were assumed to wait for therapy during the entire follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Since data on HRQoL were clustered, random effects models [19] were used to study associations between HRQoL (i.e. EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status and EQ-5D utility) and patient and disease characteristics, symptoms and treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Use of random effects models ensured that multiple measurements from the same patient were analysed appropriately and made it possible to distinguish between intraindividual and interindividual variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Backward selection was used to select the covariates for the models; any non-significant covariates were excluded from the models one at a time (significance level of 0.20 for entering and 0.10 for removing the explanatory variables). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>To control for heteroscedasticity, random effects models with robust standard errors were estimated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Additionally, random effects logit models [19] were used to study associations between the individual EQ-5D dimensions and patient and disease characteristics, symptoms and treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>EQ-5D levels were dichotomised into ‘no problems/(i.e. level 1) and ‘problems’ (i.e. levels 2–5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Missing data regarding patient and disease characteristics were handled using multiple imputations by chained equations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>This method generated imputations based on a set of imputation models, one for each variable with missing values [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The significance level was set at α = 0.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Data analyses were conducted using STATA statistical analysis software (StataCorp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Stata Statistical Software: Release 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>College Station, TX: StataCorp LP). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Four hundred eleven (m)RCC patients participating in the study completed 1630 questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The median number of questionnaires per patient was four (range 1–7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The number of questionnaires collected at each time point is provided in the Supplementary material (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>S1), as are the number of questionnaires per patient (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The average EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status of patients diagnosed with localised disease (336 patients, 1326 questionnaires) was 76 (SD, 15), and the average EQ-5D utility was 0.82 (SD, 0.17). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Eighty-seven patients had mRCC (i.e. metastatic disease at initial presentation or after an initial diagnosis with localised disease). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Of these patients, eighty-two percent were male, and the median age at diagnosis was 63 years (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Twenty-six percent of the population did not receive any systemic therapy during follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Of the patients receiving systemic therapy, the majority (80%) was treated with first-line sunitinib. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Twenty-three patients also received a second-line therapy within the follow-up period; the majority of these patients was treated with everolimus (13/23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Thirty-one patients received radiotherapy during follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Table 1Baseline characteristics at diagnosisVariablePatients (n = 87)Male sex, n (%)71 (82)Age, median (range)63 (40–79)Non-clear cell pathology, n (%)17 (20)WHO performance status, n (%) 0–182 (94) 2–45 (6)More than one metastatic site, n (%)48 (55)Liver metastasis, n (%)15 (17)Lung metastasis, n (%)48 (56)Bone metastasis, n (%)21 (24)Brain metastasis, n (%)3 (3)Haemoglobin &lt; LLN, n (%)46 (52)Neutrophil count &gt; ULN, n (%)18 (21)Platelet count &gt; ULN, n (%)19 (22)Corrected serum calcium &gt; ULN, n (%)26 (30)Lactate dehydrogenase &gt;1.5 times ULN, n (%)11 (12)Time since RCC diagnosis &lt;1 year78 (90)MSKCC risk score, n (%) Favourable6 (7) Intermediate54 (62) Poor27 (31) LLN lower limit of normal, ULN upper limit of normal, RCC renal cell carcinoma, MSKCC Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In total, 304 questionnaires were completed by patients with mRCC and the median number of questionnaires per patient was three (range 1–7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows HRQoL during the different stages of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The mean EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status was 67 (SD, 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Patients primarily experienced problems with role functioning (i.e. doing daily activities and pursuing leisure time activities). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Problems with emotional (i.e. feeling tense, irritable, depressed or worrying) and cognitive functioning (i.e. concentrating and remembering) were experienced less often. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Symptoms most commonly reported were fatigue, pain, insomnia and dyspnoea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A statistically significant difference was found between the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status before and after progression of disease, i.e. 69 (SD, 19) and 61 (SD, 22) (p = 0.022). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>All functioning scales significantly decreased, except for emotional and cognitive functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Two symptom scales significantly increased; patients reported more problems regarding dyspnoea (p = 0.031) and diarrhoea (p = 0.057) after progression than before progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Table 2Health-related quality of life based on the EQ-5D and QLQ-C30Total n = 87 patients (304 obs.)Before progression n = 81 patients (246 obs.)After progression n = 27 patients (58 obs.)Mean (SD)Total mean (SD)No systemic therapy n = 47 (125 obs.*)Mean (SD)First-line therapy n = 50 (119 obs.)Mean (SD)Total mean (SD)EQ-5D Utility0.74 (0.19)0.75 (0.19)0.76 (0.21)0.76 (0.18)0.66 (0.30)**EORTC QLQ-C30 Global health status67 (19)69 (19)69 (22)70 (17)61 (22)***Functioning scales Physical functioning69 (23)71 (23)73 (22)69 (23)62 (29) Role functioning59 (28)61 (29)61 (30)62 (29)52 (33) Emotional functioning79 (16)80 (18)77 (19)82 (19)73 (19) Cognitive functioning80 (20)80 (22)81 (21)79 (25)76 (22) Social functioning76 (22)78 (22)77 (20)78 (22)67 (28)Symptom scales Fatigue41 (25)39 (27)36 (27)41 (27)48 (30) Nausea and vomiting12 (17)13 (20)8 (13)17 (24)10 (12) Pain29 (24)27 (24)24 (25)29 (26)34 (30)Single items Dyspnoea24 (24)23 (24)23 (25)26 (28)29 (34) Sleeping28 (26)26 (27)24 (27)27 (30)35 (31) Appetite loss19 (26)18 (25)15 (26)21 (26)22 (32) Constipation10 (17)9 (17)12 (24)5 (10)12 (21) Diarrhoea20 (26)19 (27)13 (27)23 (28)22 (26) Financial difficulties10 (18)9 (18)9 (21)11 (19)8 (21) Obs observations*Observations of patients who died within 90 days after being diagnosed with mRCC were excluded from this subgroup (n = 2), since these measurements would not contribute to the estimation of the HRQoL of a patient awaiting therapy**Mean EQ-5D utility of these patients before progression of disease (n = 21) was 0.76 (0.23)***Mean EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status of these patients before progression of disease (n = 21) was 69 (20) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In the period before progression of disease, a similar HRQoL was found for a period without therapy (i.e. wait-and-see) and a period with therapy; mean EORTC QLQ-C30 global health statuses were 69 (SD, 22) and 70 (SD, 17), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>However, in the period before progression of disease, patients experienced fewer problems with emotional functioning during a period with therapy compared to a period without therapy (p = 0.067). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Additionally, patients reported fewer problems regarding constipation (p = 0.072), but more problems regarding diarrhoea during a period with therapy compared to a period without therapy (p = 0.005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The average EQ-5D utility was 0.74 (SD, 0.19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>As with the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status, a significant difference was found in EQ-5D utility before progression of disease and after progression of disease; the average EQ-5D utility before progression of disease was 0.75 (SD, 0.19), whereas the average EQ-5D utility after progression of disease was 0.66 (SD, 0.30) (p = 0.032). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In the period before progression of disease, no significant difference was found between a period without therapy (i.e. wait-and-see) and a period with therapy; mean utilities were 0.76 (SD, 0.21) and 0.76 (SD, 0.18), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In the Supplementary material, Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>S3 and S4 provide a summary of mean EORTC QLQ-C30 global health statuses and mean EQ-5D utilities by time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Figures 1 and 2 show the proportions of patients reporting levels 1–5 by EQ-5D dimension, before progression of disease and after progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Both before and after progression of disease, most problems were reported on the mobility, usual activities and pain/discomfort dimensions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Fig. 1Proportion of patients reporting levels 1–5 by dimension, before progression of disease </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Fig. 2Proportion of patients reporting levels 1–5 by dimension, after progression of disease </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Univariable analyses show several relationships between disease characteristics, symptoms and treatment, and HRQoL (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Patients with brain metastases and patients with progression of disease reported a lower HRQoL than the other patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Patients with more than one metastatic site or bone metastases reported a lower EQ-5D utility, a relationship that was not seen in the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Additionally, symptoms (i.e. fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation and diarrhoea) were associated with a lower HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Lastly, patients treated with radiotherapy reported a worse HRQoL than patients not treated with radiotherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Table 3Associations between HRQoL and patient and disease characteristics, symptoms and treatmentEQ-5D utilityEORTC QLQ-C30 global health statusUnivariable analysisMultivariable analysisUnivariable analysisMultivariable analysisCoefficientSECoefficientSECoefficientSECoefficientSEPatient characteristics Male sex0.0770.069NS2.7485.198NS Age (per year)−0.0010.002NS−0.2570.223NS WHO performance score  0–1  2–4−0.080.072NS−5.9197.304NSDisease characteristics More than one metastatic site−0.068*0.035NS−5.0483.3424.048*2.276 Presence of liver metastases−0.0270.05NS−3.9924.779NS Presence of lung metastases−0.0210.041NS0.4654.074NS Presence of bone metastases−0.085**0.04NS−3.393.915NS Presence of brain metastases−0.285*0.17NS−21.143*10.239−13.586***2.438 MSKCC risk score  Favourable  Intermediate0.0150.062NS−0.4318.924NS  Poor0.0540.063NS2.4859.22NS Progression of disease−0.082**0.036NS−6.897*3−3.859*2.249 Disease duration (in months)−0.0020.001NS−0.0810.117NSSymptoms Fatigue−0.004***0.001−0.003***0.001−0.451***0.035−0.316***0.042 Nausea and vomiting−0.001*0.0010.001**0.001−0.360***0.05NS Pain−0.004***0−0.002***0−0.324***0.036−0.143***0.035 Dyspnoea−0.003***0−0.001***0−0.222***0.04NS Sleeping−0.002***0NS−0.219***0.035NS Appetite loss−0.002***0NS−0.274***0.034−0.111***0.035 Constipation−0.002***0.001NS−0.186***0.054NS Diarrhoea−0.001*0NS−0.089**0.04NSTreatment Systemic therapy versus no systemic therapy0.0260.027NS−0.4872.408NS Radiotherapy−0.150***0.042−0.115***0.036−10.017***3.306NSModel intercept0.943***0.01685.380***1.903R2 (overall)0.5590.534Wald test (p value)&lt;0.001&lt;0.001Several comorbidities at diagnosis were considered for inclusion in the multivariable analyses, but all appeared to be not significantly associated with HRQoL SE standard error, NS not significant*Significant at α = 0.1**Significant at α = 0.05***Significant at α = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Multivariable analysis showed that the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status decreased with the presence of fatigue, pain and appetite loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the presence of brain metastases and progression of disease were associated with a worse EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>A similar association was found between fatigue and pain, and the EQ-5D utility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, EQ-5D utility scores decreased with the presence of dyspnoea and treatment with radiotherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Although the univariable analyses showed several relationships between disease characteristics (e.g. the presence of bone or brain metastases and progression of disease) and HRQoL, these characteristics were no longer associated with a deterioration of HRQoL in multivariable analyses after correction for symptoms (at a significance level of 0.05 and 0.01, except for the presence of brain metastases in the model with the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status as the dependent variable). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This seems to imply that symptoms might increase due to progression of disease (and/or due to the spread of the cancer to the bone or brain), which explains the reduced HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Table 4 shows that fatigue was associated with all EQ-5D dimensions, except with the mobility dimension; fatigue was associated with a greater frequency of problems regarding self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Patients having pain reported problems with all EQ-5D dimensions more often, with the exception of anxiety/depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Table 4Associations between the EQ-5D dimensions and patient and disease characteristics, symptoms and treatmentMobilitySelf-careUsual activitiesPain/discomfortAnxiety/depressionORSEORSEORSEORSEORSEPatient characteristics Male sex0.149**0.112NS0.095**0.110NSNS Age (per year)1.078**0.032NSNSNSNSDisease characteristics Presence of liver metastases4.427*3.395NSNSNSNS Presence of lung metastasesNSNSNSNS0.300*0.191 Presence of bone metastases4.733**2.961NS15.054***14.768NSNS MSKCC risk score  Favourable  IntermediateNSNSNS0.041***0.049NS  PoorNSNSNS0.1430.176NS Disease durationNS1.073**0.033NSNSNSSymptoms FatigueNS1.044***0.0121.128***0.0281.034***0.0121.021**0.010 Nausea and vomiting0.967**0.015NSNSNSNS Pain1.029***0.0091.030***0.0101.029*0.0151.143***0.023NS Dyspnoea1.025***0.009NS1.024*0.014NSNS SleepingNSNSNSNS1.016*0.009 Appetite loss1.031***0.011NSNSNSNSTreatment RadiotherapyNS6.062***3.971NSNSNSOdds ratios based on models created using multivariable logistic regression OR odds ratio, SE standard error*Significant at α = 0.1**Significant at α = 0.05***Significant at α = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In this study differences were found between the health-related quality of life (HRQoL) of patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC) before and after progression of disease, with a reduced HRQoL after progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Progression of disease was no longer associated with a deterioration of HRQoL in multivariable analyses after correction for symptoms (at a significance level of 0.05 and 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In line with Wilson and Cleary [21], a relationship between disease characteristics and symptoms was expected, which could explain why disease characteristics (such as progression) were no longer statistically significant in the multivariable analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Similarly, bone metastases were no longer associated with a deterioration of HRQoL in multivariable analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Since bone metastases can cause pain, then it is not surprising that bone metastases are not significantly associated with HRQoL once pain is included in the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>This seems to imply that symptoms increase due to progression of disease (and/or due to the spread of the cancer to the bone), which explains the reduced HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Besides the relationship between symptoms and HRQoL, a significant association was found between radiotherapy and HRQoL (in the model with the EQ-5D utility as the dependent variable). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It is possible that this observed association is not due to radiotherapy itself, but to the selection of which mRCC patients are to receive radiotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>That is, radiotherapy is mostly reserved for palliation of local and symptomatic disease or to prevent the progression of metastatic disease in critical sites (i.e. bones and brain) [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Either way, radiotherapy appears to be a significant determinant of HRQoL, even after correction for patient and disease characteristics (including bone and brain metastases) and symptoms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The average EQ-5D utility of patients with mRCC was 0.74 compared to an average of 0.84 (SD, 0.18) in the Dutch population aged 60 to 69 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Most patients (74%) in the study population were treated with a targeted therapy (the majority received sunitinib). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The average EQ-5D utility of these patients was 0.76 before progression of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In a study by Cella et al., a similar EQ-5D utility was reported for patients treated with sunitinib (i.e. 0.75) [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In the economic evaluation of bevacizumab and sunitinib by Thompson-Coon and colleagues [24], a health state utility of 0.78 (95% CI 0.76–0.80) was used for progression-free survival and 0.70 (95% CI 0.66–0.74) for progressive disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>These utilities were derived from the data presented in the sunitinib submission to NICE and are somewhat higher than the utilities that we found in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The economic evaluation of sunitinib by Remák and colleagues [25] was based on the results of a phase II trial of sunitinib as second-line treatment in mRCC [26]; utilities of 0.72 and 0.76 were used for progression-free survival (i.e. during treatment or rest, respectively), whereas utilities of 0.63 and 0.55 were used for progressive disease (i.e. during second-line treatment or after termination of second-line treatment, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The latter utilities are below the utilities found in our study, but this might be explained by differences in the study population, e.g. patients with progression on first-line cytokine therapy were enrolled in the phase II trial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>This study has several limitations that deserve mentioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>First, only 9% of the population (including those patients with RCC but not having metastatic disease) completed the 2-year follow-up period and filled in seven questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This is mainly because data collection stopped before many patients could be followed up for 2 years after diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>That is, data collection stopped at the end of 2013, which meant that patients diagnosed after January 1st 2012 were not able to complete the full follow-up period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>There are no reasons to expect important differences between the patients who did and did not complete the 2-year follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Second, a significant association between WHO performance status and HRQoL, and the MSKCC risk score and HRQoL was not found, although such a relationship would have been expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The MSKCC risk score divides patients into three risk groups, and gives an indication of the life expectancy of patients with mRCC [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Whereas HRQoL was measured several times during the follow-up period, data on patient characteristics (e.g. WHO performance status) and disease characteristics (e.g. laboratory factors, which are part of the MSKCC risk score) were collected once before the start of each new treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, too few observations on patient and disease characteristics might have been available to detect a significant association between WHO performance status and the MSKCC risk score, and HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a significant association between comorbidities and HRQOL might have been expected, but data on comorbidities were only collected once (at diagnosis) which might explain why a significant association was not found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the impact of comorbidities on HRQoL might be captured to some extent through age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Age appeared not to be significantly associated with HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A third limitation is that our study sample was too small to find any difference in EQ-5D utilities between different types of targeted therapies, while these therapies differ in toxicity profiles [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, although adverse events have a high impact on HRQoL, an association between adverse events and HRQoL would not be found if the proportion of patients with grade 3 or 4 adverse events is relatively low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Hypertension and fatigue are the most commonly reported grade 3 or 4 adverse events in the randomised phase 3 trial of sunitinib [4], but these adverse events occurred in only 8 and 7% of the population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a very large sample size is needed to find any difference in EQ-5D utilities between different types of targeted therapies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Additionally, it is unknown whether the improved HRQoL due to prolonged PFS outweighs reductions in HRQoL due to treatment-related adverse events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Importantly, this study did not find differences in HRQoL of patients treated with systemic therapy and patients not treated with systemic therapy, or between periods with or without systemic therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, this study may have been underpowered to find such differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>A fourth limitation is that no data were collected in the PERCEPTION-registry on assistance provided to patients who reported problems on one or more of the functioning scales of the EORTC QLQ-C30, while these patients could have received assistance to relieve their complaints. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>For example, patients could have received care at home to help with dressing and washing or emotional support by a psychologist or another healthcare professional. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, the impact of mRCC on HRQoL as presented in Table 2 might be underestimated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Lastly, the total number of patients with mRCC was 233 in the 2011–2013 Cohort of the PERCEPTION-registry [13], while only 87 patients filled in one or more questionnaires about HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>A comparison of the patient and disease characteristics and outcomes (in terms of overall survival) showed that the patients in the current study had a more favourable prognosis than the other patients in the PERCEPTION-registry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The impact on HRQoL as we estimated in this study is expected to be small, since we presented HRQoL associated with different stages of the disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>To conclude, key drivers for reduced HRQoL in mRCC are symptoms of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Since this study showed that symptoms increase with progression of disease, targeted therapies that increase PFS can help to delay loss in HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>This study also showed that the EQ-5D is able to detect changes in HRQoL of patients with mRCC, as it found associations between well-known symptoms of mRCC and EQ-5D utilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Similar associations were found between these symptoms and the disease-specific EORTC QLQ-C30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Supplementary material 1 (PDF 213 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s11136-017-1704-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the registration team of the Netherlands Comprehensive Cancer Organisation for data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The authors are also grateful to Dr. Jeannette Oosterwijk-Wakka for her help in the collection of data on HRQoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The PERCEPTION registry was financially supported by the Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development (Grant Number: 152001014); Pfizer BV (formerly Wyeth Pharmaceuticals BV); and Roche Nederland BV. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar2"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>MV is a member of the EuroQoL research foundation. SS received speaker honoraria from GlaxoSmithKline. LK received an unrestricted research grant from Pfizer to extend the data collection of the PERCEPTION registry. CU received unrestricted research grants from Pfizer (formerly Wyeth Pharmaceuticals BV) and Roche Nederland BV to support the PERCEPTION registry. All remaining authors declared no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The research protocol was approved by the medical ethics committee of Radboud university medical center in Nijmegen (CMO Region Arnhem-Nijmegen) in May 2010.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Informed consent</title><p>Informed consent was obtained from all patients participating in the HRQoL study.</p></sec></notes></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>1.LjungbergBCampbellSCChoiHYJacqminDLeeJEWeikertSThe epidemiology of renal cell carcinomaEuropean Urology201160461562110.1016/j.eururo.2011.06.049<?supplied-pmid 21741761?>21741761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>2.HengDYXieWReganMMHarshmanLCBjarnasonGAVaishampayanUNExternal validation and comparison with other models of the International Metastatic Renal-Cell Carcinoma Database Consortium prognostic model: A population-based studyThe Lancet Oncology201314214114810.1016/S1470-2045(12)70559-4<?supplied-pmid 23312463?>23312463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>3.LambeaJHinojoCLainezNLazaroMLeonLRodriguezAQuality of life and supportive care for patients with metastatic renal cell carcinomaCancer Metastasis Reviews201231Suppl 1S33S3910.1007/s10555-012-9357-9<?supplied-pmid 22684341?>22684341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>4.MotzerRJHutsonTETomczakPMichaelsonMDBukowskiRMRixeOSunitinib versus interferon alfa in metastatic renal-cell carcinomaThe New England Journal of Medicine2007356211512410.1056/NEJMoa065044<?supplied-pmid 17215529?>17215529 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>5.EscudierBEisenTStadlerWMSzczylikCOudardSSiebelsMSorafenib in advanced clear-cell renal-cell carcinomaThe New England Journal of Medicine2007356212513410.1056/NEJMoa060655<?supplied-pmid 17215530?>17215530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>6.HudesGCarducciMTomczakPDutcherJFiglinRKapoorATemsirolimus, interferon alfa, or both for advanced renal-cell carcinomaThe New England Journal of Medicine2007356222271228110.1056/NEJMoa066838<?supplied-pmid 17538086?>17538086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>7.EscudierBPluzanskaAKoralewskiPRavaudABracardaSSzczylikCBevacizumab plus interferon alfa-2a for treatment of metastatic renal cell carcinoma: A randomised, double-blind phase III trialLancet200737096052103211110.1016/S0140-6736(07)61904-7<?supplied-pmid 18156031?>18156031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>8.RiniBIHalabiSRosenbergJEStadlerWMVaenaDAOuSSBevacizumab plus interferon alfa compared with interferon alfa monotherapy in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma: CALGB 90206Journal of Clinical Oncology: Official Journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology200826335422542810.1200/JCO.2008.16.984718936475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>9.MotzerRJEscudierBOudardSHutsonTEPortaCBracardaSEfficacy of everolimus in advanced renal cell carcinoma: A double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled phase III trialLancet2008372963744945610.1016/S0140-6736(08)61039-9<?supplied-pmid 18653228?>18653228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>10.SternbergCNDavisIDMardiakJSzczylikCLeeEWagstaffJPazopanib in locally advanced or metastatic renal cell carcinoma: Results of a randomized phase III trialJournal of Clinical Oncology: Official Journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology20102861061106810.1200/JCO.2009.23.976420100962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>11.RiniBIEscudierBTomczakPKaprinASzczylikCHutsonTEComparative effectiveness of axitinib versus sorafenib in advanced renal cell carcinoma (AXIS): A randomised phase 3 trialLancet (London, England)201137898071931193910.1016/S0140-6736(11)61613-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>12.HotteSJBjarnasonGAHengDYJewettMAKapoorAKollmannsbergerCProgression-free survival as a clinical trial endpoint in advanced renal cell carcinomaCurrent Oncology (Toronto, Ont.)201118Suppl 2S11S19 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>13.De GrootSSleijferSRedekopWKOosterwijkEHaanenJBKiemeneyLAVariation in use of targeted therapies for metastatic renal cell carcinoma: Results from a Dutch population-based registryBMC Cancer20161636410.1186/s12885-016-2395-x<?supplied-pmid 27286871?>27286871 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>14.AaronsonNKAhmedzaiSBergmanBBullingerMCullADuezNJThe European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30: A quality-of-life instrument for use in international clinical trials in oncologyJournal of the National Cancer Institute199385536537610.1093/jnci/85.5.365<?supplied-pmid 8433390?>8433390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>15.SzendeAOppeMDevlinNEQ-5D value sets: Inventory, comparative review and user guide20071DordrechtSpringer </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>16.MotzerRJBacikJMurphyBARussoPMazumdarMInterferon-alfa as a comparative treatment for clinical trials of new therapies against advanced renal cell carcinomaJournal of Clinical Oncology: Official Journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology200220128929610.1200/JCO.2002.20.1.28911773181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>17.FayersPMAaronsonNKBjordalKGroenvoldMCurranDBottomleyAThe EORTC QLQ-C30 scoring manual20013New YorkWiley </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>18.VersteeghMMVermeulenKMEversSMde WitGAPrengerRStolkEADutch tariff for the five-level version of EQ-5DValue in Health201619434335210.1016/j.jval.2016.01.00327325326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>19.HedekerDGibbonsRDLongitudinal data analysis2006New YorkWiley </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>20.WhiteIRRoystonPWoodAMMultiple imputation using chained equations: Issues and guidance for practiceStatistics in Medicine201130437739910.1002/sim.4067<?supplied-pmid 21225900?>21225900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>21.WilsonIBClearyPDLinking clinical variables with health-related quality of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>A conceptual model of patient outcomesJAMA19952731596510.1001/jama.1995.03520250075037<?supplied-pmid 7996652?>7996652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>22.EscudierBPortaCSchmidingerMAlgabaFPatardJJKhooVRenal cell carcinoma: ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-upAnnals of Oncology: Official Journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology/ESMO201425Suppl 3iii49iii5610.1093/annonc/mdu259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>23.CellaDMichaelsonMDBushmakinAGCappelleriJCCharbonneauCKimSTHealth-related quality of life in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma treated with sunitinib vs interferon-alpha in a phase III trial: Final results and geographical analysisBritish Journal of Cancer2010102465866410.1038/sj.bjc.6605552<?supplied-pmid 20104222?>20104222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>24.Thompson CoonJHoyleMGreenCLiuZWelchKMoxhamTBevacizumab, sorafenib tosylate, sunitinib and temsirolimus for renal cell carcinoma: A systematic review and economic evaluationHealth Technology Assessment2010142118410.3310/hta14020<?supplied-pmid 20028613?>20028613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>25.RemakECharbonneauCNegrierSKimSTMotzerRJEconomic evaluation of sunitinib malate for the first-line treatment of metastatic renal cell carcinomaJournal of Clinical Oncology: Official Journal Of The American Society of Clinical Oncology200826243995400010.1200/JCO.2007.13.266218711190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>26.MotzerRJMichaelsonMDRedmanBGHudesGRWildingGFiglinRAActivity of SU11248, a multitargeted inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor and platelet-derived growth factor receptor, in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinomaJournal of Clinical Oncology: Official Journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology2006241162410.1200/JCO.2005.02.257416330672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>27.MotzerRJHutsonTECellaDReevesJHawkinsRGuoJPazopanib versus sunitinib in metastatic renal-cell carcinomaThe New England Journal of Medicine2013369872273110.1056/NEJMoa1303989<?supplied-pmid 23964934?>23964934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
