<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5993813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">27109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-27109-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies are increased in Plasmodium vivax infection and are associated with anemia </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mourão</surname><given-names>Luiza Carvalho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1806-8260</contrib-id><name><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>Rodrigo de Paula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>Zélia Barbosa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grynberg</surname><given-names>Priscila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pucci</surname><given-names>Maíra Mazzoni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castro-Gomes</surname><given-names>Thiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fontes</surname><given-names>Cor Jesus Fernandes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>Sumit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Yagya D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva-Pereira</surname><given-names>Rosiane A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bemquerer</surname><given-names>Marcelo Porto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5550-7157</contrib-id><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>Érika Martins</given-names></name><address><email>embraga@icb.ufmg.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2181 4888</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8430.f</institution-id><institution>Departamento de Parasitologia, </institution><institution>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, </institution></institution-wrap>Belo Horizonte, MG Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 738X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.213876.9</institution-id><institution>Center for Tropical and Emerging Global Diseases, </institution><institution>University of Georgia, </institution></institution-wrap>Athens, GA USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0541 873X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.460200.0</institution-id><institution>Embrapa Recursos Genéticos e Biotecnologia, </institution></institution-wrap>Brasília, DF Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 0931</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418068.3</institution-id><institution>Centro de Pesquisas René Rachou, </institution><institution>Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, </institution></institution-wrap>Belo Horizonte, MG Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2322 4953</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411206.0</institution-id><institution>Faculdade de Ciências Médicas, Universidade Federal do Mato Grosso, </institution></institution-wrap>Cuiabá, MT Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1767 6103</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413618.9</institution-id><institution>Department of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>New Delhi, India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>8762</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Clearance of non-infected red blood cells (nRBCs) is one of the main components of anemia associated with Plasmodium vivax malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Recently, we have shown that anemic patients with P. vivax infection had elevated levels of anti-RBCs antibodies, which could enhance in vitro phagocytosis of nRBCs and decrease their deformability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Using immunoproteomics, here we characterized erythrocytic antigens that are differentially recognized by autoantibodies from anemic and non-anemic patients with acute vivax malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Protein spots exclusively recognized by anemic P. vivax-infected patients were identified by mass spectrometry revealing band 3 and spectrin as the main targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>To confirm this finding, antibody responses against these specific proteins were assessed by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In addition, an inverse association between hemoglobin and anti-band 3 or anti-spectrin antibodies levels was found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Anemic patients had higher levels of IgG against both band 3 and spectrin than the non-anemic ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>To determine if these autoantibodies were elicited because of molecular mimicry, we used in silico analysis and identified P. vivax proteins that share homology with human RBC proteins such as spectrin, suggesting that infection drives autoimmune responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that band 3 and spectrin are potential targets of autoantibodies that may be relevant for P. vivax malaria-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium vivax accounts for a sizable portion of the global malaria burden and is being increasingly associated to fatal outcomes with anemia as one of the major complications1,2 particularly in young children1–4 and pregnant women5,6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Despite its enormous public health importance, the mechanisms behind vivax malaria-associated anemia are not well known. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Malaria-induced anemia is thought to arrise from hemolysis of infected RBCs, as well as from clearance of nRBCs7,8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Several reasons have been suggested to explain the removal of nRBC8, including impaired RBC production through dyserythropoiesis or bone marrow insufficiency9, exposition of erythrocytes to oxidative stress triggered by parasite rupture or host immune responses10,11, and mechanical ex vivo destruction of non-infected red blood cells (nRBCs), as it has been demonstrated using a splenic sinusoid model12, in addition to other mechanisms that may also be relevant to P. vivax-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In P. falciparum infections, one of the causes underlying malarial anemia is the augmented removal of nRBCs possibly boosted by increased levels of self-antibodies against nRBCs proteins13–15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Evidences in this line are given by studies that have shown an inverse association between hemoglobin levels and anti-phosphatidylserine antibodies in humans with late post-anemia due to P. falciparum infection14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In addition, one may also take into account the expansion of T-bet+ B cells and the production of anti-erythrocyte antibodies in ex vivo cultures of naïve human peripheral blood mononuclear cells exposed to P. falciparum-infected erythrocyte15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the role of autoimmunoglobulins in P. vivax infection is an important field of research that has been mainly explored through clinical studies and case reports16–18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Our group recently demonstrated that in vitro erythrophagocytosis of nRBCs was mediated by anti-erythrocyte antibodies purified from anemic patients with vivax malaria, possibly through a decrease in cell deformability19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Thus, characterization of RBCs targets for autoimmunoglobulins elicited by P. vivax infection may be important for the understanding of vivax malaria-associated anemia as well as for autoimmune diseases due to its clinical and therapeutic potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Herein we used two different strategies to understand the relationship between autoantibodies against nRBCs and P. vivax-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>First, we used an immunoproteomic approach to identify the erythrocytic antigens reactive to IgG from anemic P. vivax-infected patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Then, we confirmed the reactivity of those antigens using ELISA and investigated the possible contribution of molecular mimicry to vivax malaria associated-anemia by searching for P. vivax proteins that share homology with human RBCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Differential RBC protein recognition by IgGs from anemic and non-anemic P. vivax-infected patients with acute malaria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>To determine whether IgG antibodies recognizing nRBC antigens are increased during acute P. vivax malaria, median levels of such immunoglobulins were assessed by ELISA in plasma from patients with patent P. vivax infection presenting (n = 24) or not (n = 24) anemia, as well as in plasma from healthy individuals never exposed to malaria (n = 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Anemic patients infected with P. vivax had higher levels of IgG against erythrocyte proteins (median OD: 0.49; IQR [0.41–0.65]) than the infected non-anemic patients (median OD: 0.21; IQR [0.10–0.39]) or healthy controls (median OD: 0.21; IQR [0.07–0.37]) (Kruskal-Wallis followed Dunn’s post hoc test, p &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 1).Figure 1Levels of IgG against protein extracts of nRBCs in plasma from P. vivax-infected patients with or without anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>IgG antibody responses were evaluated by ELISA using plasma from healthy individuals (n = 8) and anemic (n = 24) or non-anemic P. vivax-infected patients (n = 24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Results are shown as values of mean optical density and standard error of the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Differences between the groups were determined using Kruskal-Wallis test followed by Dunn post hoc test (p value &lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of the immunoproteomes obtained with serum samples of the three experimental groups revealed a different profile of antigenic spots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 shows a representative nRBC 2D-SDS-PAGE map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Sera from the infected groups recognized a greater number of spots than the sera from the healthy control group (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Some of the spots recognized exclusively by the serum antibodies of patients with vivax malaria corresponded to cytoplasmic proteins bound to the cell membrane such as ankyrin, dematin 7, and band 4.2 (Fig. 3, Supplementary Tables 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Several spots corresponded to membrane-cytoskeleton associated proteins, spectrins and actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Spots corresponding to the integral membrane protein band 3 were also identified (Fig. 3, Supplementary Tables 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We also detected other proteins that were recognized by antibodies from P. vivax-infected patients, but which were not confirmed by peptide sequencing: EV15-like protein, kynurenine-oxoglutarate transaminase, long chain fatty acid transport protein 6, FAM45A protein, FAM180A, and TMLHE (Fig. 3, Supplementary Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Spots recognized exclusively by sera from anemic malaria patients included band 3, spectrin (both alpha and beta chains), cytoplasmic actin 1, protein 4.1, protein band 4.2, ankyrin 1, and dematin (Fig. 3, Supplementary Table 1).Figure 2Representative 2D-SDS-PAGE map of RBC protein spots identified by mass spectrometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>100 µg of nRBCs protein extract were focused on pH 4–7 IPG strips (7 cm) and then separated by SDS-PAGE 12%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Gel was stained with colloidal Coomassie Blue G-250. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The molecular masses (kDa) of the protein standards are indicated on the left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All the protein spots that matched to their corresponding spot in the western blotting were excised from the gel and processed for MALDI-ToF/ToF mass spectrometry analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>These protein spots are listed in the Supplementary Tables 1 and 2.Figure 3Comparative analysis of the IgG repertoire against nRBC proteins among subjects with distinct vivax malaria clinical features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The proteins resolved by 2D-SDS-PAGE were blotted onto PVDF membranes and probed with different plasma pools: (A) healthy, (B) patients with vivax malaria and no anemia or (C) P. vivax-infected patients with anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Bound antibodies were detected with HRP conjugated anti-human IgG (1:6000) using an ECL chemiluminescence-based kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Images were analysed using ImageMaster 2D Platinum software (GE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>A representative image of three independent experiments is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Western blots were cropped for easier visualization; uncropped images are available in the supplemental material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All the protein spots detected in the Western blotting that matched to their corresponding spot in 2D-SDS-PAGE gel were processed for MALDI-ToF/ToF mass spectrometry analysis and are listed in the supplementary Tables 1 and 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies correlate with anemia in patients with vivax malaria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Since band 3 and spectrin proteins are involved in RBC clearance, we selected them to validate the findings of the immunoproteomic approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>To detect anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies in plasma from patients with patent P. vivax infection, we used ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>IgG levels were expressed as reactivity index, which was obtained by dividing the mean OD value of each test sample by the cut-off value (threshold of positivity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The cut off value was calculated as the mean OD plus two standard deviations of eight healthy blood donors never exposed to malaria as it will be described in section 4.8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>We observed that anemic patients had significantly higher levels of anti-band 3 antibodies (median: 1.69; ITR: [0.97–3.12]) in comparison to the non-anemic ones (median: 0.39; ITR: [0.21–0.69]) (Mann-Whitney U test p &lt; 0.0001, Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>A similar result was also observed for anti-spectrin antibodies (median of 0.85, ITR [0.68–1.38] for anemic versus median of 0.59, ITR [0.46–0.78] for the non-anemic; Mann-Whitney U test p = 0.0043).Figure 4Anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies correlate with anemia in patients with acute P. vivax infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Levels of anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies were detected by ELISA in plasma samples from patients with patent P. vivax infection presenting or not presenting anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Antibody levels were expressed as reactivity index (RI), which was calculated as the ratio between the mean OD generated by each test sample and the mean OD plus two standard deviations of samples from eight healthy blood donors never exposed to malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>RIs equal or greater than 1.0 were scored as positive (A) Anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies levels were compared between anemic (n = 24) and non-anemic P. vivax-infected patients (n = 24) using Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Scatter plots show the means and standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The dotted lines on each graph represent the threshold above which samples were considered as positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(B) Heat map of IgG antibody profile against band 3 and spectrin in plasma from anemic and non-anemic patients with vivax malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Grey colour indicates that antibody levels are at least greater than the mean plus two standard deviations of the healthy controls whereas white colour denotes the opposite result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Associations between hemoglobin levels and anti-band 3 or anti-spectrin antibodies (C and D, respectively) were analysed by Spearman correlation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>To further understand each patient´s individual immunoreactivity profile against these two erythrocytic antigens, a heatmap was used (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We observed that the spectra of antibody responses varied markedly among P. vivax-infected patients either presenting or not presenting anemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For evaluating whether there is a direct correlation between hemoglobin levels and anti-RBC antibodies, the levels of hemoglobin were correlated with the levels of anti-band 3 or anti-spectrin antibodies (Fig. 4C,D, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The data clearly show that the levels of hemoglobin decreases with the increase in the level of anti-band 3 (Spearman correlation: r = −0.7224; p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A similar association was also found to anti-spectrin antibodies (Spearman correlation: r = −0.3321; p = 0.0211). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In silico identification of cross-reactive proteins between host RBCs and P. vivax </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the observed autoimmune response could be due to molecular mimicry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we performed an in silico analysis comparing P. vivax entire proteome and human RBC proteome to identify putative molecular mimicry candidate proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The final BLAST results indicated that 23 P. vivax proteins were mimetic to human RBC proteins (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Nineteen of them were hypothetical proteins of the parasite and their mimetic human RBC proteins were associated with plasma membranes: ankyrin, actin, and spectrin (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The other four parasite proteins found to be mimetic to human RBC proteins (PVX_123515, PVX_099980, PVX_101610 and PVX_099980) were membrane surface-related proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, most of the candidates were also membrane-associated RBC proteins such as the ones found in the immunoproteomic approach (Fig. 3, Supplementary Tables 1 and 2).Table 1P. vivax proteins mimetic to human proteins. Subject Human ID  P. vivax query ID  Protein description ( P. vivax )  Human protein sp|O60641|AP180_HUMANPVX_092010-AA:777hypothetical protein, conservedClathrin coat assembly protein AP180sp|O94856|NFASC_HUMANPVX_095335-AA:266hypothetical protein, conservedNeurofascinsp|O94988|FA13A_HUMANPVX_123250-AA:290hypothetical protein, conservedProtein FAM13Asp|P07205|PGK2_HUMANPVX_123515-AA:1081MAC/Perforin domain containing proteinPhosphoglycerate kinase 2sp|P35611|ADDA_HUMANPVX_099980-AA:800major blood-stage surface antigen Pv200Alpha-adducinsp|P55209|NP1L1_HUMANPVX_091530-AA:524hypothetical protein, conservedNucleosome assembly protein 1-like 1sp|P78356|PI42B_HUMANPVX_099150-AA:363hypothetical protein, conservedPhosphatidylinositol 5-phosphate 4-kinase type-2 betasp|Q12873|CHD3_HUMANPVX_093655-AA:1234hypothetical protein, conservedChromodomain-helicase-DNA-binding protein 3sp|Q13151|ROA0_HUMANPVX_092895-AA:619hypothetical protein, conservedHeterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein A0sp|Q13637|RAB32_HUMANPVX_123100-AA:280hypothetical protein, conservedRas-related protein Rab-32sp|Q5S007|LRRK2_HUMANPVX_000660-AA:258hypothetical proteinLeucine-rich repeat serine/threonine-protein kinase 2sp|Q6PL18|ATAD2_HUMANPVX_101610-AA:137RAD protein (Pv-fam-e)ATPase family AAA domain-containing protein 2sp|Q6WRI0|IGS10_HUMANPVX_085900-AA:1308hypothetical protein, conservedImmunoglobulin superfamily member 10sp|Q6ZRI8|RHG36_HUMANPVX_114675-AA:140hypothetical protein, conservedRho GTPase-activating protein 36sp|Q9BQ39|DDX50_HUMANPVX_117850-AA:2285hypothetical protein, conservedATP-dependent RNA helicase DDX50sp|Q9BYB0|SHAN3_HUMANPVX_122920-AA:552hypothetical protein, conservedSH3 and multiple ankyrin repeat domains protein 3sp|Q9BZF9|UACA_HUMANPVX_099150-AA:822hypothetical protein, conservedUveal autoantigen with coiled-coil domains and ankyrin repeatssp|Q9H254|SPTN4_HUMANPVX_003755-AA:415hypothetical protein, conservedSpectrin beta chain, brain 3sp|Q9H4A3|WNK1_HUMANPVX_118355-AA:350hypothetical proteinSerine/threonine-protein kinase WNK1sp|Q9NQC3|RTN4_HUMANPVX_099980-AA:809major blood-stage surface antigen Pv200Reticulon-4sp|Q9P0M6|H2AW_HUMANPVX_083455-AA:988hypothetical protein, conservedCore histone macro-H2A.2sp|Q9UPE1|SRPK3_HUMANPVX_123910-AA:330hypothetical protein, conservedSRSF protein kinase 3sp|Q9UPN3|MACF1_HUMANPVX_099150-AA:569hypothetical protein, conservedMicrotubule-actin cross-linking factor 1, isoforms 1/2/3/5 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Comparison between the spectrin sequence of P. vivax and other Plasmodium species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Since autoantibodies from P. vivax-infected patients recognized spectrin and this protein was identified in our mimicry in silico approach, we also verified if spectrin was conserved in other Plasmodium species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The sequence that seemed the most ideal for comparative analysis was the hypothetical P. vivax protein (PVX_003755), which was mimetic to the human spectrin β-chain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We aligned this P. vivax spectrin-like sequence with other Plasmodium species using blastp and verified that all local alignments corresponded to hypothetical proteins (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Our orthology analysis revealed no paralog sequences in the ortholog clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic analysis identified at least two evolutionary groups (P1 and P2) for this protein and showed that P. falciparum was the species whose spectrin sequence appeared to be the most divergent in comparison with the sequences from other Plasmodium species (Fig. 5A).Table 2Plasmodium spectrin-like ortholog sequences.GeneOrganismProductLengthPBANKA_0304100Plasmodium berghei ANKAhypothetical protein, conserved1030PCHAS_0306300 Plasmodium chabaudi chabaudi hypothetical protein, conserved1027PCYB_042380Plasmodium cynomolgi strain Bhypothetical protein, conserved840PF3D7_0206500Plasmodium falciparum 3D7hypothetical protein, conserved1436PKNH_0414500Plasmodium knowlesi strain Hhypothetical protein, conserved1101PY17X_0304700Plasmodium yoelii yoelii 17Xhypothetical protein, conserved983PY00070Plasmodium yoelii yoelii 17XNLhypothetical protein958PYYM_0305000Plasmodium yoelii yoelii YMhypothetical protein, conserved983PVX_003755Plasmodium vivax SaI-1hypothetical protein, conserved1085Figure 5Comparison of the divergence of spectrin-like proteins between different Plasmodium species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>(A) Plasmodium “spectrin-like” maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Two groups are detected: one group containing the Plasmodium falciparum protein (P1) and the other with the P. vivax protein (P2); P1 and P2 represents the two putative phylogenetic groups of spectrin-like sequences between the analyzed Plasmodium species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>(B) P. falciparum protein Pf3D7_0206500 synteny alignment against all other Plasmodium species spectrin-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The figure shows that the C-terminus (red end) is highly conserved in all proteins and the N-terminus (green end) is only conserved in the group B sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Only alignments with more than 75% identity were represented in this figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The conserved C-terminus region among all species is mimetic to the human pleckstrin-like homology domain (PH domain). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We performed a sequence identity comparison of P. falciparum Pf3D7_0206500 against all other Plasmodium species spectrin-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>One may observe two different patterns in our dataset: the C-terminus of all the proteins was highly conserved while the N-terminus region showed identity to P. falciparum only for proteins from the group P2 (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>When using all other Plasmodium sequences as queries we saw that they maintained the same identity pattern in the N-terminus except for P. cynomolgi, which seems to have a smaller size gene, caused by a mutation or by an annotation error. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Our data provide information about autoantibody responses to non-infected RBCs as well as its association with anemia during P. vivax infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Using different approaches, we found that: (1) anemic patients infected with P. vivax have higher levels of IgG against erythrocyte proteins; (2) band 3 and spectrin proteins are the main molecular targets in nRBCs differentially recognized by IgGs from anemic patients with patent P. vivax infection; and (3) a P. vivax protein of unknown function is mimetic to human spectrin suggesting that molecular mimicry may contribute to autoantibody immune responses to nRBCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Many RBC protein spots were recognized by autoantibodies of P. vivax-infected patients rather than by autoantibodies from healthy sera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Previous results of our group revealed that non-infected RBC have reductions in their dynamic membrane fluctuations when incubated with autoantibodies from patients with P. vivax malaria19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The immunoproteomic data presented here show that antibodies from P. vivax-infected subjects recognize proteins such as band 3, spectrin and actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Since the transmembrane band 3 exposes new antigens during Plasmodium infection20,21, it is a more probable target of autoantibodies than the cytoskeletal proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Shibuya et al. (2018) proposed a model for antibody assess to the cytoplasmic domain of band 3 in hereditary spherocytosis, which was attributed to the hydrolysis of spectrin and ankyrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Their proposal is that conformational changes in the extracellular portion of band 3 protein observed in patients with hereditary spherocytosis would lead to the hydrolysis of spectrin and ankyrin in the intracellular milieu, which directly affects cytoskeleton dynamics, leading to RBC clearance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In this scenario, the binding of anti-band 3 autoantibodies to band 3 protein on the surface of RBC during P. vivax infection could induce similar intracellular changes, affecting cytoskeleton and leading to a higher clearance of erythrocytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Although the presence of autoantibodies against RBCs has been previously reported in vivax infection16, only recently we demonstrated that autoantibodies mediate erythrophagocytosis of nRBCs possibly through a decrease in cell deformability19. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>IgG autoantibodies of anemic patients infected by P. vivax recognized a larger number of erythrocytic antigens when compared to non-anemic individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Some spots exclusively recognized by autoantibodies from anemic vivax patients were identified as band 3 protein, an anion transporter that mediates cell flexibility and shape maintenance22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In Plasmodium infections, band 3 acts as a host receptor for interaction with different merozoite proteins such as MSP-123, MSP-924, and tryptophan-rich antigens25,26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In endemic areas where P. falciparum is the prevalent species, band 3 antibodies seem to be protective because children with higher levels of these antibodies had lower parasitemia than nonimmune ones27,28. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>However, the role of autoantibodies against band 3 remains controversial and has never been studied in P. vivax infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We speculate that such autoantibodies may contribute to anemia by interacting with new exposed epitopes followed by C3b deposition on nRBCs21, by promoting erythrocyte clearance29 and by changing cell membrane deformability19. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Band 3 has a cytoplasmic domain, which binds to different proteins involved in RBC structure and function, and a transmembrane domain, which catalyses the chloride and bicarbonate antiporter transport22,30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Also, while one-third of band 3 molecules binds to spectrin and becomes immobile, the other two-thirds freely diffuse into the lipidic bilayer31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>It is known that band 3 pass through molecular conformation modifications during initial immune responses to malaria parasites, which leads to exposure of new epitopes20,21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Thus, since these modifications in band 3 are associated to hemichrome deposition and reactive oxygen species generation, they may persist after parasite clearance giving rise to changes in chloride/bicarbonate transporter activity21, thereby affecting RBC CO2 transport and contributing to anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Also, possibility of enzymatic hydrolysis of spectrin may be taken into account32. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Several mechanisms are involved in the production of self-reactive antibodies in malaria including polyclonal activation of B cells induced by parasite antigens33, dysregulation of B lymphocytes33,34 and stimulation of specific B lymphocytes by molecular mimicry35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To investigate whether molecular mimicry is underlying vivax malaria-associated anemia, we identified P. vivax proteins that share homology at the molecular level with proteins from human RBCs using bioinformatics tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Homologous regions of primary structure were found between P. vivax and human spectrin, a result that may explain the increase in levels of anti-spectrin antibodies detected by ELISA in plasma of patients infected by P. vivax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>In line with this idea is the study by Berti et al.36, who reported that a surge in anti-spectrin antibodies following the intraperitoneal injection of spectrin in rats affected the homeostasis of RBC by accelerating their elimination and stimulating erythropoiesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>It is possible that host spectrin and spectrin-homologous proteins derived from the parasite trigger the generation of autoantibodies that mediate the destruction of nRBCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This anemic scenario leads to increased erythropoiesis, which, in turn, favours reticulocyte infection by P. vivax, thus supporting molecular mimicry as an advantageous host-parasite adaptation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Although little is known about molecular mimicry in P. vivax, this mechanism has been proposed for other Plasmodium species37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The protein candidates include: P. falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 (PfMSP-1), which has human epidermal growth factor-like motifs38; the P. falciparum translationally controlled tumor protein (PfTCTP), which is homologous to the human histamine releasing factor39; and P. falciparum erythrocyte membrane protein 1 (PfEMP1), which shares motifs with human vitronectin40. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis comparing different Plasmodium species showed two groups of spectrin-like proteins, with P. falciparum as an outlier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The C-terminus of spectrin-like Plasmodium orthologue proteins are highly conserved (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>To find a possible biological relevance of spectrin, putative domains were predicted and, curiously, the C-terminus conserved region was predicted to be a pleckstrin homology-like domain (PH-like). Although such predictions do not define the protein function, it is known that increased expression of this domain family in humans is associated with the presence of anemia41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it has been shown that pleckstrin-2, which contains two PH domains, plays a critical role in erythropoiesis42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Altogether, these data may explain how molecular mimicry of spectrin relates with the anemic status induced by Plasmodium infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Since spectrin is present on the intracellular side of the erythrocyte membrane, it remains unclear how anti-spectrin antibodies bind to a cytoplasmic protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Although we do not have an explanation for such observation, this is not the first time that immunoglobulins directed towards an intracellular antigen have been detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The reaction of anti-spectrin antibodies with RBCs has been previously described by studies investigating the clearance of aged erythrocytes43,44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>We suggest that during P. vivax infection, the destruction of erythrocytes releases spectrin in the plasma, where it could bind to circulating anti-spectrin antibodies, thereby eliciting complement deposition onto these complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>RBC engulfment by macrophages is affected by cell stiffness and molecular interactions in cell surface45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Therefore, deposition of those immunocomplexes on the surface of nRBCs through the complement receptor 1 (CR1) could decrease nRBCs deformability thus predisposing them to clearance by phagocytes and contributing to anemia in vivax malaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Immune response against cytoskeletal proteins may contribute to falciparum malaria46,47. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, no studies are available for P. vivax-associated anemia, but since our immunoproteomic data suggest the presence of antibodies for band 3 and for associated cytoskeletal proteins, and also considering that antibodies for those proteins are involved in RBC clearance29, further investigation of contribution of these antibodies to the pathogenesis of vivax-associated anemia is necessary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted according to the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Ethics Committee of the National Information System on Research Ethics Involving Human Beings (SISNEP - CAAE01496013.8.0000.5149). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>All healthy donors and patients were anonymized, and they provided written informed consent for the collection of samples and subsequent analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were collected between February 2006 and January 2008 from adults with patent P. vivax infection who attended and were diagnosed at the Hospital Universitário Júlio Muller, in Cuiabá (Mato Grosso State, Brazil). P. vivax mono-infections were diagnosed by thick blood smear and further confirmed by nested PCR amplification of species-specific sequence of the 18s SSU rRNA gene of Plasmodium, as previously described48. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The clinical history and demographic profile were obtained from all the subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Individuals were assigned according to the results of complete blood count into two groups: (i) malaria patients without anemia (n = 24) and (ii) malaria patients with anemia (n = 24) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Anemia was set as hemoglobin levels less than or equal to 11 g/dL and only patients with normocytic (mean corpuscular volume 80–96 fL) and normochromic (mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration 32–36 g/dL) anemia were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Patients presenting severe malnutrition or infections such as HIV or hepatitis were excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>As control, we included plasma from healthy volunteers who had never been exposed to malaria (n = 8).Table 3Baseline characteristics of the study population.CharacteristicP. vivax anemic(n = 24)P. vivax non-anemic(n = 24)p value(Mann-Whitney test)Age (years)29.5 [27.7–41.2]30.0 [24.0–42.0]0.8954Number of malaria previous episodes2 [1–4]3 [0–10]0.8895Parasitemia (parasites/µL)7,275 [2,418–12,331]2,375 [7,000–16,500]0.0517Hemoglobin (g/dL)9.7 [8.4–10.1]16.1 [15.4–16.8]&lt;0.0001Hematocrit (%)28.0 [25.0–29.4]46.1 [45.4–48.08]&lt;0.0001Platelets (cells/mm3)101,000 [69,000–126,000]160,500 [112,750–193,250]0.0106Leucocytes (cells/mm3)4,900 [3,700–6,000]5,390 [4,633–6,313]0.2930Values are shown as median and interquartile ranges. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>For the immunoproteomics approach, we prepared a pool containing plasma from seven individuals for each studied group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>These individuals were those who presented median levels of IgG against nRBCs detected by ELISA as it will be described below in section 3.4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>It is important to mention that blood samples from P. vivax-infected patients were collected on the onset of diagnosis, during the acute phase of infection and before starting treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The treatment consisted in chloroquine (150 mg/day, 3 days) associated with primaquine (15 mg/day, 7 days) at doses calculated per kilogram of weight, as proposed by the Brazilian Ministry of Health guidelines for P. vivax uncomplicated malaria therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>RBC extract preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Erythrocyte membrane extract was prepared with RBCs obtained from a healthy O+ blood type donor after separation using Ficoll-Paque Plus (GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Hemoglobin-free erythrocyte ghosts were obtained by hypotonic lysis as previously described49. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Membrane proteins were solubilized in 8 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 4% w/v CHAPS, 0.0025% bromophenol blue, 65 mM DTT (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA), 1% v/v BioLyte 3–10 100X buffer (Bio-Rad) and precipitated using 2D Clean-Up Kit (GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Protein concentration was estimated using Bradford assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Detection of IgG against nRBCs proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Serum levels of IgG against nRBCs extracts were determined by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Briefly, each well of a 96-well flat-bottomed polystyrene microplate (Corning Incorporation, Corning, NY, USA) was coated with 0.1 ng of RBC protein extract in 0.1 M carbonate buffer, pH 9.6, and then incubated overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>After five washes with PBS containing 1% (w/v) bovine serum albumin (BSA), the plate was blocked with nonfat powdered milk for two hours at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Next, plates were washed and incubated, in duplicate, with serum samples diluted 1:200 in PBS/BSA for 2 hours at 3 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Wells were rewashed and incubated with horseradish peroxidase conjugated polyclonal anti-human IgG diluted 1:8000 in PBS/BSA for 90 minutes at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Finally, the plates were washed again, and the reaction was revealed using 0.5 mg/mL o-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride substrate in 0.05 M phosphate-citrate buffer, pH 5.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The reaction was stopped with 3M H2SO4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Optical density (OD492 nm) was determined in a Spectra Max 250 microplate reader (Molecular Devices, San Jose, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The levels of specific IgG were expressed as OD492nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Two-dimensional Western blotting and protein identification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>RBC proteins (100 µg) were separated by 2D gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>RBC extract was loaded onto immobilized pH gradient (IPG) strips (7 cm, pH 4–7; Bio-Rad) and subjected to isoelectric focusing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Next, RBC proteins were reduced, alkylated and separated on 12% SDS-polyacrylamide (SDS-PAGE) gel50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>To identify nRBCs antigens recognized by antibodies from the studied groups, two 2D-SDS-PAGE were performed in parallel to each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The preparative 2D-SDS-PAGE gels were stained with Coomassie brilliant blue G-250 (BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The remaining 2D-SDS-PAGE gels were electroblotted onto PVDF membranes (BioRad) in transfer buffer (25 mM Tris-Base, 192 mM glycine, 20% methanol, pH 8.3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Each membrane was probed with each serum pool diluted 1:200 in TBS (20 mM Tris-HCl, 500 mM NaCl pH 7.5) containing 0.05% Tween-20 and 1% BSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>HRP-conjugated goat anti-human IgG (1:6000) and a chemiluminescence-based kit (ECL; GE Healthcare) was used to detect the immunoreactive spots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Three immunoblots were performed for each serum group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>After image analysis (Image Master 2D Platinum 7.0, GE Healthcare), all immunoreactive spots that matched to their homologues in 2D-SDS-PAGE gels were excised, distained and digested with trypsin (Trypsin Gold, Mass Spectrometry Grade, Promega, Madison, WI, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The tryptic peptides obtained were extracted and had their volume decreased under reduced pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>After a desalting step (C18-µZipTip, Merck-Millipore, Bilerica, USA), the peptides were dried, suspended in ultrapure water, spotted onto a MALDI target plate (BrukerDaltonics, Bilerica, MA, USA) and analysed using MALDI-ToF and MALDI-ToF/ToF (Autoflex Speed or Ultraflex III, BrukerDaltonics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>MS and MS/MS spectra were acquired using Flex Control 2.0 (Bruker Daltonics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The external calibration MS mode was performed using Peptide Calibration Standard II (Bruker Daltonics) according to manufacturer instruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Mass analysis ranged from m/z = 500 to m/z = 4000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The ToF operation was conducted in the reflected mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>All mass spectra were obtained in the positive ion reflector mode, using α-cyano-4-hydroxycinnamic acid as matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>For the calibration of the MS/MS mode, parent ions from each of those peptides contained in the calibration mixture were selected and fragmented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The fragmentation was conducted using LIFT™ technology51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>MS/MS spectra were also obtained in the positive mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Theoretical values of [M + H]+ for each precursor ion were calculated by “Isotope-MS” Protein Prospector tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://prospector.ucsf.edu/prospector/mshome.htm">http://prospector.ucsf.edu/prospector/mshome.htm</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Mass spectra were edited and analysed using Flex Analysis 3.3 and Biotools 3.0 (Bruker Daltonics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The lists containing experimentally obtained m/z ratios were compared to theoretical values generated by in silico digestion of all human protein sequences deposited in SwissProt and NCBInr protein databases through Biotools v program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>3.0 (Bruker Daltonics) coupled to the Mascot v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>2.1 and 2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Protein identification was assigned by peptide mass fingerprint (PMF) and by MS/MS Ion Search using the search program Mascot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Searches were performed firstly against the SwissProt database and when it did not lead to identification, they were confronted against the NCBInr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>To avoid random matches, identification was considered valid only for samples whose scores exceeded the identity or extensive homology threshold value that was calculated by MASCOT (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>To confirm the identifications and to identify the proteins that did not present a significant score in those analyses, MS/MS spectra were interpreted by manual inspection taking into consideration the widely accepted mechanisms for the fragmentation of peptides as well as the mechanically favoured or disfavoured cleavage events52,53. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Preparation of RBC antigens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Band 3 protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>To separate erythrocytes from leucocytes, freshly drawn blood collected in heparinized tube was layered on Histopaque and centrifuged at 1000 g for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Packed erythrocytes were washed three times with PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Hemoglobin-free erythrocyte membranes (ghosts) were prepared by osmotic lysis of the washed erythrocyte. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The washed cells were hemolyzed in ten volumes of ice-cold 5 mM phosphate buffer (pH 8.0) containing 0.1 mM PMSF and incubated 30 min at 4 ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The ghosts were centrifuged at 20,000 g for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was carefully aspirated without disturbing ghost pellet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This procedure was repeated until membranes were free of hemoglobin and the pellet become milky white. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Then, the peripheral proteins were stripped from membrane by suspending it in ten volumes of ice-cold 2 mM EDTA (pH 12.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Immediately after dilution, the membrane was pelleted by centrifugation at 48,000 g for 30 min at 4 ºC and washed three times with 5 mM phosphate buffer, (pH 8.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The stripped membrane (15–20 mg protein/mL) was resuspended in 5 mM phosphate buffer, pH 8.0, and five volumes of 1% (v/v) C12E8 in 5mM phosphate buffer, pH 8.0 was added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>This mixture was incubated at 4 ºC for 20 min and centrifuged at 48,000 g for 2 h at 4 ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Band 3 protein was purified by affinity chromatography on aminoethyl-agarose resin (ABT beads, Madrid, Spain). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Amino ethyl-agarose was packed in column and equilibrated with 0.1% C12E8, 5 mM phosphate buffer (pH 8.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The solubilized membrane protein was loaded onto the column and washed with one bed volume of 0.1% C12E8 5 mM phosphate buffer (pH8.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>A linear gradient of 0–300 NaCl in 0.1% (v/v) C12E8 in 5 mM phosphate buffer, pH 8.0, of ten bed volume were applied to column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Band 3 was eluted at 100 mM NaCl and collected in fractions of 1 mL in sterile tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Concentration was determined by spectrophotometry and purity of the preparation was checked by 10% SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Eluted protein was divided in fractions at 1 mg/mL in 5 mM phosphate buffer and lyophilized overnight. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Spectrin protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Spectrin was extracted from RBCs as previously described with some modifications54–56. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Briefly, blood was collected and centrifuged at 1000 g, for 20 minutes at 4 ºC in order to remove plasma and buffy coat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Packed RBCs were washed three times with 20 volumes of 5 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 8.0) containing 0.95% (w/v) NaCl and the cells were collected after each wash procedure by centrifugation at 4000 g for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The cells were then hemolyzed in 5 mM sodium phosphate, pH 8.0, and the membranes collected by centrifugation at 37000 g for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Membranes were washed in the same buffer until a pale yellow colour appears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was removed, and the pellet was suspended in an equal volume of spectrin removal buffer (0.2 mM sodium phosphate, 0.1 mM EDTA, 0.2 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 20 µg/mL phenylmethyl sulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), pH 8.0, 37 ºC for 20–60 minutes for the release of the dimeric spectrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The tetrameric spectrin was purified with the same protocol but the incubation was performed at 4 ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Membranes were removed from the incubated sample by centrifugation at 27000 g for 15 minutes, and the supernatant was concentrated by dialysis against spectrin removal buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Then, vesicles were clarified by centrifugation (27000 X g, 15 minutes) and both dimeric and tetrameric spectrins were purified after concentration by 30% ammonium sulphate precipitation followed by isolation by gel filtration chromatography on a Superose 6 10/300 GL column equilibrated with 10 mM sodium phosphate (pH 7.5) containing 0.1 M NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, and 0.3 mM sodium azide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically, and purity was checked by 7.5% DS-PAGE under reducing condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Before ELISA experiments, spectrin was extensively dialyzed against 5 mM phosphate to remove DTT and EDTA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Detection of anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>For detection of anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodies, ELISA was carried out as previously described with some modifications57. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Briefly, plates were coated overnight at 4 ºC with 5 ng of band 3 or 50 ng of spectrin, blocked with 3% BSA, and incubated with sera samples diluted 1:100 in PBS containing 1% BSA (PBS.1% BSA) for 2 h at 37 ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Peroxidase conjugated anti-human IgG at a dilution of 1:1000 in PBS.1% BSA was added and the plates were incubated at 37 ºC for 90 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Wells were developed with O-phenylenediamine substrate (benzene-1,2-diamine). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Antibody values were expressed as reactivity index (RI), which was calculated as the ratio between the mean OD generated by each duplicate and the mean OD plus two standard deviations of samples from eight healthy blood donors never exposed to malaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>RIs equal or greater than 1.0 were scored as positive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Mimicry candidate detection analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>To identify molecular mimicry candidate proteins between the entire P. vivax proteome and human RBCs, we used a modified Perl version of a local pipeline created by Ludin et al.40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The term mimetic is refereed here as the display of any parasite protein whose primary structure resembles primary structures of the host and possibly confers a benefit to the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Ludin´s pipeline works following several steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>First, a blastp search against free-living eukaryotic organisms unrelated to pathogenicity was performed to eliminate the generally conserved proteins58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Then, specific parasites sequences were masked for possible peptide signal sites using Phobius software59 and divided into 14 length size overlapping fragments, which were aligned against our free-living control proteomes to remove similar peptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Finally, these 14-mers sequences parasite-specific were compared using blast alignment against the RBC human proteome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Only the high-scoring segment pairs (HSPs), e-value ≤ 10−10, from BLAST were selected as final mimicry candidates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Throughout all pipeline, redundancy control filters steps were used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Comparison between P. falciparum and P. vivax sequences orthologous to spectrin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>We searched for amino acid sequence differences that could help to identify the specific aspects that make P. vivax-associated anemia different from the one observed for P. falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>We aligned P. vixax mimetic protein sequences against P. falciparum sequences, using blastp algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the gene disposition over the genus Plasmodium, a search for orthologous sequences was done between all available Plasmodium species in PlasmoDB version 2960. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The mimicry amino acid sequences were submitted to the OrthoMCL program61 using a total of nine isolates from different Plasmodium species: P. falciparum 3D7 (PF3D7_0206500). P. berghei ANKA (PBANKA_0304100), P. yoelli yoelli 17X (PY17X_0304700), P. yoelli yoelli YM (PMY_0305000), P. yoelli yoelli 17XNL (PY00070), P. chabaudi chabaudi (PCHAS_0306300), P. knowlesi strain H (PKNH_0414500), P. vivax Sal-1 (PVX_003755) and P. cynomolgi strain B (PCYB_042380), which were publicly available at this time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The recovered sequences were subjected to a maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis using PhyML62 and visualized using Figtree program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Data Availability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article (and its Supplementary Information files). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec22"><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Original 2D-SDS-PAGE stained with colloidal Coomassie Blue G-250 of 100 µg of RBC protein extract using 7 cm, pH 4-7 IPG strip RBCs immunoreactive proteins identified by peptide mass fingerprint (PMF) RBCs immunoreactive proteins identified by MS/MS peptide fragmentation or by de novo sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-27109-6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank all patients and their families who contributed to the current study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>We are also grateful to health professionals and students from UFMT for all the support given for the present study as well to Jamil Silvano de Oliveira, Adriana Fernandes and Alcina Zitha, who have helped in the laboratory activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnológico [grant numbers: 309202/2013-2; 158045/2015-7; 404365/2016-7]; Fundação de Desenvolvimento da Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais [grant number: APQ000361-16]; Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (PNPD PG/PARASITOLOGIA); Pró-Reitoria de Pesquisa da Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais and Program for Technological Development in Tools for Health-PDTIS-FIOCRUZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: L.C.M., R.A.S.P., M.P.B., E.M.B. Performed the experiments: L.C.M., R.P.B., Z.B.A., T.C.-G., M.M.P. Analyzed the data: L.C.M., R.P.B., Z.B.A., P.G., M.M.P., R.A.S.P., M.P.B., E.M.B. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: C.J.F.F., S.R., Y.D.S., R.A.S.P., M.P.B., E.M.B. Wrote the paper: L.C.M., R.P.B., R.A.S.P., M.P.B., E.M.B.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>1.GentonBPlasmodium vivax and mixed infections are associated with severe malaria in children: A prospective cohort study from Papua New GuineaPLoS Med.200850881088910.1371/journal.pmed.0050127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>2.TjitraEMultidrug-resistant Plasmodium vivax associated with severe and fatal malaria: A prospective study in Papua, IndonesiaPLoS Med.200850890089910.1371/journal.pmed.0050128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>3.Rodríguez-MoralesASánchezEVargasMAnemia and thrombocytopenia in children with Plasmodium vivax malariaJ Trop Pediatr.200652495110.1093/tropej/fmi069<?supplied-pmid 15980019?>15980019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>4.KenangalemEPlasmodium vivax infection: a major determinant of severe anaemia in infancyMalar J.20161532110.1186/s12936-016-1373-8<?supplied-pmid 27306221?>27306221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>5.Bardají, A. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Burden and impact of Plasmodium vivax in pregnancy: A multi-centre prospective observational study. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 11 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>6.NostenFEffects of Plasmodium vivax malaria in pregnancyLancet.199935454654910.1016/S0140-6736(98)09247-2<?supplied-pmid 10470698?>10470698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>7.AnsteyNMDouglasNMPoespoprodioJRPriceRNPlasmodium vivax: Clinical Spectrum, Risk Factors and PathogenesisAdv Parasitol.20128015120110.1016/B978-0-12-397900-1.00003-7<?supplied-pmid 23199488?>23199488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>8.Castro-GomesTPotential immune mechanisms associated with anemia in Plasmodium vivax malaria: a puzzling questionInfect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Immun.2014823990400010.1128/IAI.01972-14<?supplied-pmid 25092911?>25092911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>9.Wickramasinghe, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>N., Looareesuwan, S., nagachinta, B. &amp; White, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Dyserythropoiesis and ineffective erythropoiesis in Plasmodium vivax malaria. Br J Haematol. 72, 91–99, Blood and bone marrow changes in malaria (1989). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>10.ErelOKocyigitAAvciSAktepeNBulutVOxidative stress and antioxidative status of plasma and erythrocytes in patients with vivax malariaClin Biochem.19973063163910.1016/S0009-9120(97)00119-7<?supplied-pmid 9455617?>9455617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>11.BilginRYalcinMSYucebilgicGKoltasISYazarSOxidative stress in vivax malariaKorean J Parasitol.20125375377710.3347/kjp.2012.50.4.375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>12.HandayaniSHigh deformability of Plasmodium vivax-infected red blood cells under microfluidic conditionsJ Infect Dis.20091994455010.1086/596048<?supplied-pmid 19090777?>19090777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>13.RosenbergEBStricklandGTYangS-LWhalenGEIgM antibodies to red cells and autoimmune anemia in patients with malariaAm J Trop Med Hyg.19732214615210.4269/ajtmh.1973.22.146<?supplied-pmid 4631762?>4631762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>14.Fernandez-AriasCAnti-Self Phosphatidylserine Antibodies Recognize Uninfected Erythrocytes Promoting Malarial AnemiaCell Host Microbe.20161919420310.1016/j.chom.2016.01.009<?supplied-pmid 26867178?>26867178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>15.Rivera-CorreaJPlasmodium DNA-mediated TLR9 activation of T-bet+ B cells contributes to autoimmune anaemia during malariaNat Commun.20188128210.1038/s41467-017-01476-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>16.FernandesAAMSimilar cytokine responses and degrees of anemia in patients with Plasmodium falciparum and Plasmodium vivax infections in the Brazilian Amazon regionClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Vaccine Immunol.20081565065810.1128/CVI.00475-07<?supplied-pmid 18256207?>18256207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>17.VenturaAClinical and immunological profiles of anaemia in children and adolescents with Plasmodium vivax malaria in the Pará State, Brazilian AmazonActa Trop.201818112213110.1016/j.actatropica.2018.01.022<?supplied-pmid 29408596?>29408596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>18.GhoshASharmaSChoudhuryJAutoimmune hemolytic anemia in Plasmodium vivax malariaIndian J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Pediatr.20178448348410.1007/s12098-017-2327-z<?supplied-pmid 28290054?>28290054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>19.MourãoLCAnti-erythrocyte antibodies may contribute to anaemia in Plasmodium vivax malaria by decreasing red blood cell deformability and increasing erythrophagocytosisMalar J.20161539710.1186/s12936-016-1449-5<?supplied-pmid 27488382?>27488382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>20.PantaleoAGiribaldiGMannuFAresePTurriniFNaturally occurring anti-band 3 antibodies and red blood cell removal under physiological and pathological conditionsAutoimmun Rev.200874576210.1016/j.autrev.2008.03.017<?supplied-pmid 18558362?>18558362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>21.DeroostKPhamT-TOpdenakkerGVan den SteenPEThe immunological balance between host and parasite in malariaFEMS Microbiol Rev.20164020825710.1093/femsre/fuv046<?supplied-pmid 26657789?>26657789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>22.WangDNBand 3 protein: structure, flexibility and functionFEBS Lett.1994346263110.1016/0014-5793(94)00468-4<?supplied-pmid 8206153?>8206153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>23.GoelVKBand 3 is a host receptor binding merozoite surface protein 1 during the Plasmodium falciparum invasion of erythrocytesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>USA20031005164516910.1073/pnas.0834959100<?supplied-pmid 12692305?>12692305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>24.BaldwinMHuman erythrocyte band 3 functions as a receptor for the sialic acid-independent invasion of Plasmodium falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Role of the RhopH3-MSP1 complexBiochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Acta.201418432855287010.1016/j.bbamcr.2014.08.008<?supplied-pmid 25157665?>25157665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>25.AlamMSInteraction of Plasmodium vivax tryptophan-rich antigen PvTRAg38 with band 3 on human erythrocyte surface facilitates parasite growthJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Chem.2015290202572027210.1074/jbc.M115.644906<?supplied-pmid 26149684?>26149684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>26.AlamMSZeeshanMRathoreSSharmaYDMultiple Plasmodium vivax proteins of Pv-fam-a family interact with human erythrocyte receptor band 3 and have a role in red cell invasionBiochem Biophys Res Commn.20164781211121610.1016/j.bbrc.2016.08.096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>27.HoghBPetersenECrandallIGottschauAShermanIWImmune responses to band 3 neoantigens on Plasmodium falciparum-infected erythrocytes in subjects living in an area of intense malaria transmission are associated with low parasite density and high hematocrit valueInfect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Immun.19946243624366<?supplied-pmid 7927696?>7927696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>28.LuginbühlANikolicMBeckHPWahlgrenMLutzHUComplement factor D, albumin, and immunoglobulin G anti-band 3 protein antibodies mimic serum in promoting rosetting of malaria-infected red blood cellsInfect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Immun.2007751771177710.1128/IAI.01514-06<?supplied-pmid 17261605?>17261605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>29.HornigRLutzHUBand 3 clustering of human erythrocytes promotes binding of naturally occuring anti-band 3 and anti-spectrin antibodiesExper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Geront.2000351025104410.1016/S0531-5565(00)00126-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>30.HamasakiNOkuboKBand 3 protein: physiology, function and structureCell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>(Noisy-le-grand).199642102510398960778 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>31.TomishigeMSakoYKusumiARegulation mechanism of the lateral diffusion of band 3 in erythrocyte membranes by the membrane skeletonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol.1998142989100010.1083/jcb.142.4.989<?supplied-pmid 9722611?>9722611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>32.ShibuyaAKawashimaHTanakaMAnalysis of erythrocyte membrane proteins in patients with hereditary spherocytosis and other types of haemolytic anaemiaHematology.201861710.1080/10245332.2018.1455278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>33.MinoprioPParasite polyclonal activators: new targets for vaccination approaches?Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.20013158859110.1016/S0020-7519(01)00171-0<?supplied-pmid 11334946?>11334946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>34.Daniel-RibeiroCDruilhePMonjourLHombergJCGentiliniMSpecificity of auto-antibodies in malaria and the role of polyclonal activationTrans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Hyg.19837718518810.1016/0035-9203(83)90064-0<?supplied-pmid 6346590?>6346590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>35.GreenwoodBMPossible role of a B-cell mitogen in hypergammaglobulinaemia in malaria and trypanosomiasisLancet (London, England)1974143543610.1016/S0140-6736(74)92386-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>36.BertiGGovoniMVentrelliIAutoantibodies against spectrin in ratsBoll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Ital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Sper.1989652936<?supplied-pmid 2757817?>2757817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>37.AndersRFMultiple cross-reactivities amongst antigens of Plasmodium falciparum impair the development of protective immunity against malariaParasite Immunol.1986852953910.1111/j.1365-3024.1986.tb00867.x<?supplied-pmid 3543808?>3543808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>38.BlackmanMJLingITNichollsSCHolderAAProteolytic processing of the Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein-1 produces a membrane-bound fragment containing two epidermal growth factor-like domainsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.199149293310.1016/0166-6851(91)90127-R<?supplied-pmid 1775158?>1775158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>39.MacDonaldSMImmune mimicry in malaria: Plasmodium falciparum secretes a functional histamine-releasing factor homolog in vitro and in vivoProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>USA200198108291083210.1073/pnas.201191498<?supplied-pmid 11535839?>11535839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>40.LudinPNilssonDMäserPGenome-wide identification of molecular mimicry candidates in parasitesPLoS One20116e1754610.1371/journal.pone.0017546<?supplied-pmid 21408160?>21408160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>41.ChiuS-TClinicopathologic correlation of up-regulated genes identified using cDNA microarray and real-time reverse transcription-PCR in human colorectal cancerCancer Epidemiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Biomarkers Prev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>A Publ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Assoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Cosponsored by Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Prev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Oncol.20051443744310.1158/1055-9965.EPI-04-0396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>42.ZhaoBTargeted shRNA screening identified critical roles of pleckstrin-2 in erythropoiesisHaematologica2014991157116710.3324/haematol.2014.105809<?supplied-pmid 24747950?>24747950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>43.Ghailani, N., Guillemin &amp; C., Vigneron, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Chronology of the formation of vesicles and membrane protein aggregates during erythrocyte aging. Nouv Ver Fr Hematol. 37, 313-319 91995). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>44.GraldiGAccelerated elimination from the circulation of homologous aged red blood cells in rats bearing anti-spectrin antibodiesMech Ageing Dev.1999107213610.1016/S0047-6374(98)00126-2<?supplied-pmid 10197786?>10197786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>45.SosaleNGCell rigidity and shape override CD47’s “self”-signaling in phagocytosis by hyperactivating myosin-IIBlood.201512554255210.1182/blood-2014-06-585299<?supplied-pmid 25411427?>25411427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>46.BansalDIgG autoantibody to brain beta tubulin III associated with cytokine cluster-II discriminate cerebral malariain central IndiaPLoS One.20094e824510.1371/journal.pone.0008245<?supplied-pmid 20011600?>20011600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>47.GitauENKokwaroGOKaranjaHNewtonCRJCWardSAPlasma and cerebrospinal proteomes from children with cerebral malaria differ from those of children with other encephalopathiesJ Infec Dis.20132081494150310.1093/infdis/jit33423888081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>48.ScopelKKGFontesCJFNunesACHortaMFBragaEMLow sensitivity of nested PCR using Plasmodium DNA extracted from stained thick blood smears: an epidemiological retrospective study among subjects with low parasitaemia in an endemic area of the Brazilian Amazon regionMalar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>J.20043810.1186/1475-2875-3-8<?supplied-pmid 15056392?>15056392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>49.PasiniEMIn-depth analysis of the membrane and cytosolic proteome of red blood cellsBlood.200610879180110.1182/blood-2005-11-007799<?supplied-pmid 16861337?>16861337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>50.LudolfFSerological screening of the Schistosoma mansoni adult worm proteomePLoS Negl Trop Dis.20148e274510.1371/journal.pntd.0002745<?supplied-pmid 24651847?>24651847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>51.SuckauDA novel MALDI LIFT-TOF/TOF mass spectrometer for proteomicsAnal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Bioanal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Chem.200337695296510.1007/s00216-003-2057-0<?supplied-pmid 12830354?>12830354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>52.PaizsBSuhaiSFragmentation pathways of protonated peptidesMass Spectromem Rev.20052450854810.1002/mas.20024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>53.MedzlhradszkyKFChalkleyRJLessons in de novo peptide sequencing by tandem mass spectrometryMass Spectrom Rev.201334436310.1002/mas.21406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>54.PatraMMukhopadhyayCChakrabartiAProbing conformational stability and dynamics of erythroid and nonerythroid spectrin: effects of urea and guanidine hydrochloridePLoS One.20152410(1)e011699110.1371/journal.pone.0116991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>55.BeggGERalstonGBMorrisMBA proton nuclear magnetic resonance study of the mobile regions of human erythroid spectrinBiophysical Chemistry.199452637310.1016/0301-4622(94)00066-2<?supplied-pmid 7948712?>7948712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>56.UngewicellEGratzerWSelf-association of human spectrinEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Biochem.19788837938510.1111/j.1432-1033.1978.tb12459.x689023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>57.MourãoLCNaturally acquired antibodies to Plasmodium vivax blood-stage vaccine candidates (PvMSP-119 and PvMSP-3α359-798) and their relationship with hematological features in malaria patients from the Brazilian AmazonMicrobes and Infection20121473073910.1016/j.micinf.2012.02.011<?supplied-pmid 22445906?>22445906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>58.CamachoCBLAST+: architecture and applicationsBMC Bioinformatics20091042110.1186/1471-2105-10-421<?supplied-pmid 20003500?>20003500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>59.KällLKroghASonnhammerELLA combined transmembrane topology and signal peptide prediction methodJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Biol.20043381027103610.1016/j.jmb.2004.03.016<?supplied-pmid 15111065?>15111065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>60.AurrecoecheaCPlasmoDB: a functional genomic database for malaria parasitesNucleic Acids Res.200937D53954310.1093/nar/gkn814<?supplied-pmid 18957442?>18957442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>61.LiLStoeckertCJRoosDSOrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomesGenome Res.2003132178218910.1101/gr.1224503<?supplied-pmid 12952885?>12952885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>62.GuindonSNew algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Biol.20105930732110.1093/sysbio/syq010<?supplied-pmid 20525638?>20525638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
