<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">MBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mBio</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mBio</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2150-7511</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5666160</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29089432</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mBio01628-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01628-17</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Csr System Regulates Escherichia coli Fitness by Controlling Glycogen Accumulation and Energy Levels </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Csr System Controls <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Energy Charge</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">Morin et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>Manon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ropers</surname><given-names>Delphine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cinquemani</surname><given-names>Eugenio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Portais</surname><given-names>Jean-Charles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Enjalbert</surname><given-names>Brice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cocaign-Bousquet</surname><given-names>Muriel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label><addr-line>LISBP, Université de Toulouse, CNRS, INRA, INSA, Toulouse, France</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label><addr-line>Inria, University of Grenoble-Alpes, Grenoble, France</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name><role>Invited Editor</role><aff>University of Florida</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>E. Peter</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>University of Washington</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Delphine Ropers, <email>delphine.ropers@inria.fr</email>, or Brice Enjalbert, <email>brice.enjalbert@insa-toulouse.fr</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="equal"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>B.E. and M.C.-B. contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e01628-17</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 Morin et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Morin et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="mbo005173569001.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>ABSTRACT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In the bacterium Escherichia coli, the posttranscriptional regulatory system Csr was postulated to influence the transition from glycolysis to gluconeogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, we explored the role of the Csr system in the glucose-acetate transition as a model of the glycolysis-to-gluconeogenesis switch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the Csr system influence the reorganization of gene expression after glucose exhaustion and disturb the timing of acetate reconsumption after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Analysis of metabolite concentrations during the transition revealed that the Csr system has a major effect on the energy levels of the cells after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This influence was demonstrated to result directly from the effect of the Csr system on glycogen accumulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Mutation in glycogen metabolism was also demonstrated to hinder metabolic adaptation after glucose exhaustion because of insufficient energy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This work explains how the Csr system influences E. coli fitness during the glycolysis-gluconeogenesis switch and demonstrates the role of glycogen in maintenance of the energy charge during metabolic adaptation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>IMPORTANCE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Glycogen is a polysaccharide and the main storage form of glucose from bacteria such as Escherichia coli to yeasts and mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Although its function as a sugar reserve in mammals is well documented, the role of glycogen in bacteria is not as clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>By studying the role of posttranscriptional regulation during metabolic adaptation, for the first time, we demonstrate the role of sugar reserve played by glycogen in E. coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Indeed, glycogen not only makes it possible to maintain sufficient energy during metabolic transitions but is also the key component in the capacity of cells to resume growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Since the essential posttranscriptional regulatory system Csr is a major regulator of glycogen accumulation, this work also sheds light on the central role of posttranscriptional regulation in metabolic adaptation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Csr system</kwd><kwd>carbon metabolism</kwd><kwd><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>glycogen</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="award1"><funding-source>INRA</funding-source><award-id>CJS INRIA-INRA</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Manon Morin</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award2"><funding-source>INRIA</funding-source><award-id>CJS INRIA-INRA</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Manon Morin</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="49"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="7567"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>September/October 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Metabolic adaptation describes the capacity to switch from one substrate to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This mechanism is essential for the fitness and survival of microorganisms (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In the model bacterium Escherichia coli, metabolic adaptation influences the productivity of bioprocesses and also its persistence in the gut, with major consequences for human health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The persistence of commensal E. coli strains has already been shown to provide a barrier to infection in the intestine (3, 4). E. coli first consumes sugars and sugar derivatives through glycolytic pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In the absence of such substrates, it uses less favorable molecules such as acetate, succinate, or formate by activating the gluconeogenic pathway (1, 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms involved in pathogen exclusion in natural ecosystems are complex but notably involve competitive metabolic interactions with available nutriments (4, 6, 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Since the availability of carbon substrates in the gut is constantly changing, metabolic adaptation and the capacity to switch from glycolysis to gluconeogenesis are essential for colonization and persistence of E. coli and hence for health (8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Although the metabolic organization of E. coli is well described, metabolic adaptation is still not fully understood (9–11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In central carbon metabolism (CCM), the accumulation of several layers of regulatory mechanisms (transcriptional, posttranscriptional, translational, and posttranslational regulatory mechanisms) results in a complex and entangled control of carbon fluxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>At the posttranscriptional level (i.e., control of the stability and translation of mRNA), the main controller of CCM reported so far is the carbon storage regulator (Csr) system (12–16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>This posttranscriptional controller is highly pleiotropic (17, 18) and is involved in the regulation of most adaptive phenomena, including virulence (19), motility (20, 21), stringent response (12), and glycogen synthesis (14, 22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Its main component is the conditionally essential protein CsrA, which is able to bind to target mRNAs, leading to either their degradation or their stabilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>CsrA activity is controlled through sequestration by CsrB and CsrC, two noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs) (23–25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Both of these ncRNAs are targeted by the protein CsrD, which triggers their RNase E-dependent degradation (26), through a molecular mechanism based on CsrD and CsrA antagonism (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Transcription of CsrB and CsrC is activated by the BarA/UvrY two-component system (23, 25, 28) and is repressed by cAMP-CRP (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The Csr system is said to positively regulate glycolysis while inhibiting gluconeogenesis (14–16, 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>It is hypothesized to be involved in the switch between the two metabolisms since the BarA/UvrY two-component system is needed for the efficient transition from glycolytic to gluconeogenic metabolism (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The recently discovered circuitry linking catabolite repression and Csr regulatory systems (29) also suggests the involvement of CsrA in the transition, since the switch to gluconeogenic substrate consumption requires the alleviation of catabolite repression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Here, we investigated the putative role of the Csr system in the metabolic adaptation from glycolysis to gluconeogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Gene expression and metabolite pool analyses were performed with Csr system mutant strains throughout the glucose-acetate transition, which was considered a model of metabolic adaptation (9, 10, 31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate the important role of the Csr system during this metabolic transition through its control of glycogen accumulation and cell energy homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>(Parts of this work were conducted as M.M.’s thesis project.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s1.1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The Csr system influences the dynamics of acetate reconsumption after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The glucose-acetate transition is a model of adaptation from glycolytic to gluconeogenic metabolism (9, 10, 31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Briefly, this transition consists of E. coli cells growing exponentially on a glucose minimal medium and excreting acetate into the medium as a metabolic overflow product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>When the cells run out of glucose, the CCM is reorganized, thereby enabling the cell to consume the acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The behaviors of three strains with modified CsrA activities (csrA51, ΔcsrBC, and ΔcsrD mutant strains) were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Deletions of CsrB and, to a lesser extent, of CsrC ncRNAs are known to increase CsrA activity by preventing its sequestration (24, 25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Deletion of csrD triggers an increase in CsrB and CsrC ncRNA concentrations, which promotes the sequestration of CsrA and reduces its activity (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In the csrA51 mutant strain, the deletion of the last 11 amino acids of CsrA has been reported to dramatically reduce its activity while maintaining strain viability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This construction has been widely used as the gold standard to explore the function of CsrA (17, 32, 33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To investigate the glucose-acetate transition, the three mutants and their wild-type (WT) isogenic control were grown dynamically in controlled bioreactors in M9 minimal medium supplemented with 0.27% glucose (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The biomass and extracellular glucose and acetate concentrations were measured at 30-min intervals (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The growth of all four strains was exponential during glucose consumption (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>As expected from previous work (16), the csrA51 mutant’s growth rate on glucose was lower than that of the WT (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>No significant differences were observed between the WT and the ΔcsrBC and ΔcsrD mutant strains during the growth phase on glucose (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>This was corroborated by the similar glucose consumption profiles of the strains (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The csrA51 mutant strain produced a very low level of acetate during growth on glucose in comparison with the three other strains, whose production rates and final levels of acetate were similar (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The small amount of acetate in the csrA51 mutant strain was completely consumed in the minutes following glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The other three strains also consumed the acetate produced after glucose exhaustion but with different timings, resulting in the ΔcsrD mutant strain consuming its acetate first, followed by the WT and then the ΔcsrBC mutant strain (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, during the acetate consumption phase, higher rates of acetate consumption were observed in the ΔcsrD mutant strain, followed by the WT and then the ΔcsrBC mutant strain (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>To illustrate, at 1 h after glucose exhaustion, these rates were, respectively, −1.50 ± 0.26, −0.82 ± 0.32, and −0.58 ± 0.12 mM ⋅ g of dry weight (gDW)−1 ⋅ h−1 in the ΔcsrD mutant, WT, and ΔcsrBC mutant strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We detected no difference in biomass content that could be related to the differences in the timing of acetate consumption (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 1 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Behavior of Csr system mutants during the glucose-acetate transition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Cultures were monitored from 6 h before to 4 h after glucose exhaustion, which was set as time zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All data concerning the replicates are displayed as dots, and the fitted average value of each strain is displayed as a line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Shaded areas represent ±1 standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>WT, black circles; csrBC mutant, green squares; csrD mutant, orange triangles; csrA51 mutant, red diamonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(A) Changes in the biomass concentration (gDW ⋅ liter−1) and growth rate μ (h−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>(B) Extracellular glucose concentration (mM) and specific glucose production rates (mM ⋅ h−1 ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(C) Extracellular acetate concentration (mM) and specific acetate production rates (mM ⋅ h−1 ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>(D) Glycogen concentration (ggluc ⋅ gDW−1) and specific glycogen production rates (ggluc ⋅ h−1 ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Since the csrA51 mutant strain is reported to overaccumulate glycogen (14, 16, 22), we assessed the concentration of this storage polysaccharide in the cell during the glucose-acetate transition (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>As expected (22), the csrA51 mutant strain accumulated up to 0.28 g of glucose (ggluc) ⋅ gDW of glycogen−1, representing about 30% of the biomass dry weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Glycogen also accumulated in the ΔcsrD mutant cells but to a lesser extent (maximum of 0.07 ggluc ⋅ gDW−1, representing 7% of the cell dry weight) and even less in the WT (4% of the cell dry weight). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the ΔcsrBC mutant cells stored a very small quantity of glycogen (maximum of 0.01 ggluc ⋅ gDW−1, representing about 1% of the biomass). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The glycogen content in the four strains remained mostly stable during the exponential phase of growth on glucose (concentrations and rates remained constant), and all four strains used glycogen after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Overall, glycogen production and consumption rates were high in the csrA51 mutant strain (respectively, 0.078 ± 0.014 and −0.057 ± 0.014 gglc ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1 1 h before and 1 h after glucose exhaustion), medium in the ΔcsrD mutant (0.035 ± 0.004 and −0.018 ± 0.001 gglc ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1), and low in the ΔcsrBC mutant (0.003 ± 0.001 and −0.002 ± 0.001 gglc ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1) compared to those of the WT (0.028 ± 0.001 and −0.012 ± 0.007 gglc ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To conclude, the investigated strains showed a range of phenotypes according to their CsrA activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The csrA51 mutant was the most affected strain, with high glycogen and low acetate contents and a reduced growth rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The ΔcsrD mutant also had a higher glycogen content than the WT and accelerated acetate consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The ΔcsrBC mutant displayed the reverse phenotypes (low to no glycogen content and delayed acetate consumption). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In addition to its effect on growth rates and glycogen accumulation, the Csr system is involved in the dynamics of the glycolysis-gluconeogenesis transition, notably through its impact on acetate consumption after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s1.2"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>CCM gene expression is differently influenced by the Csr system before and after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We assumed that the differences in acetate consumption between the strains could result from differential gene expression in the CCM after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This was assessed by performing quantitative reverse transcription (RT)-PCR analysis of 14 key CCM genes (34) during the metabolic transition from 3 h preceding to 2 h after glucose exhaustion (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>During the glucose consumption phase, massive differences in gene expression were observed between the mutant strains and the WT, especially the csrA51 mutant strain (as previously described by Morin et al. [16]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the differences between the strains were globally reduced after glucose exhaustion, except for the genes involved in acetate and glycogen metabolism (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>For acetate metabolism (ACS, ack, and pta), higher expression was noticed in the csrA51 and ΔcsrD mutant strains than in the WT, which could be consistent with their improved acetate consumption rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The expression of glycogen-related genes (pgm and glgC) was increased, but only in the csrA51 mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We thus conclude that the Csr system controls different sets of genes before and after glucose exhaustion, the later set being devoted to the use of the remaining carbon sources (acetate and glycogen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 2 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Expression of key metabolic genes during the glucose-acetate transition of Csr system mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Gene expression (relative to the idnT RNA reference) was investigated from 3 h before to 2 h after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>WT, black circles; csrBC mutant, green squares; csrD mutant, orange triangles; csrA51 mutant, red diamonds. ptsG, glucose phosphotransferase system permease PtsG subunit (European Bioinformatics Institute European Nucleotide Archive accession no. EG10787); pgm, phosphoglucomutase (accession no. EG12144); glgC, glucose-1-phosphate adenylyltransferase (accession no. EG10379); zwf, glucose 6-phosphate-1-dehydrogenase (accession no. EG11221); pgi, phosphoglucose isomerase (accession no. EG10702); pfkA, phosphofructokinase (accession no. EG10699); eno, enolase (accession no. EG10258); icd, isocitrate dehydrogenase (accession no. EG10489); pck, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (accession no. EG10688); pta, phosphate acetyltransferase (accession no. EG20173); ack, acetate kinase (accession no. EG10027); ACS, acetyl coenzyme A synthetase (accession no. EG11448); pck, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (accession no. EG10688); fbp, fructose 1,6-bisphosphatase (accession no. EG10283). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The values are averages of three replicates with error bars representing standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>PPP, pentose phosphate pathway; TCA, tricarboxylic acid cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s1.3"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the metabolite pools revealed different energy status in the Csr system mutant strains after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We then measured key metabolite pools in the CCM over time in the four strains by using liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The profiles of the metabolites assessed over time were mostly similar in the four strains, with a drop in concentrations after glucose exhaustion, except for the alarmone cAMP and for phosphoenolpyruvate, as previously described in the WT strain (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Before glucose exhaustion, the ΔcsrBC mutant strain had higher concentrations of fructose 1,6-bisphosphate (FBP) and malate, whereas the ΔcsrD pools were mostly comparable to those of the WT (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>As expected (16), the csrA51 mutant strain displayed larger metabolite pools in the upper part of the glycolysis process (glucose-6-phosphate [G6P], fructose-6-phosphate [F6P]) than the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>These pools decreased after glucose exhaustion but, unexpectedly, were maintained in the csrA51 mutant strain at levels equivalent to those measured in the WT strain during the glucose consumption phase (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the nucleotide triphosphate pools remained high in the csrA51 mutant strain even after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 3 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Concentrations of key central carbon metabolites during the glucose-acetate transition of Csr system mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(A) Metabolite concentrations were investigated from 3 h before to 2 h after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>WT, black circles; csrBC mutant, green squares; csrD mutant, orange triangles; csrA51 mutant, red diamonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>PEP, phosphoenolpyruvate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>(B) The AECs of the same four strains during glucose consumption (plain bars) and 1.5 h after glucose exhaustion (striped bars) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A significant difference between a mutant and the WT is represented by an asterisk (P &lt; 0.05 [t test]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The values in both panels are averages of three independent biological replicates with error bars representing standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that the energy level after glucose exhaustion differs between strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We therefore investigated the energy status of the cells by calculating the adenylate energy charge (AEC) as an index of the bacterium metabolic state (35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The AEC on glucose was between 0.87 and 0.91 in all of the strains during the glucose consumption phase (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Such values are expected in exponentially growing cells (35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>At 90 min after glucose exhaustion, the AEC had decreased in all of the strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>However, in the csrA51 mutant strain, the AEC remained significantly higher than in the WT, and the ΔcsrBC mutant AEC collapsed to 0.50, a value previously linked to dying cells (35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the csrA51 mutant strain maintained high energy levels after glucose exhaustion, whereas there was a dramatic drop in the energy status of the ΔcsrBC mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>We thus hypothesize that the energy levels in the Csr system mutant strains could be linked to the observed differences in the kinetics of acetate consumption. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s1.4"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Both glycogen and acetate influence the energy status after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We analyzed the relationship between energy fluxes and acetate consumption rates by investigating the distribution of the energy fluxes after glucose exhaustion in the different strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>During the acetate consumption phase, glycogen is also consumed as an intracellular storage sugar and is thus also likely to be involved in the balance between energy fluxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To examine the influence of glycogen and acetate flux on the growth rate and ATP flux, we used a previously developed constraint-based model of E. coli (16, 36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>These parameters were analyzed in the ranges of acetate and glycogen consumption rates we monitored after glucose exhaustion (Fig. 1; see Materials and Methods for details of the procedure). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We compared the ATP fluxes predicted by the model with cell maintenance that we estimated at 2.9 mmol ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1 from experimental data obtained with the WT strain (32) and considered to be the same in all four strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The results of analysis of the flux balance are shown in Fig. 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Acetate and glycogen uptake rates were insufficient to detect growth (µ &lt; 0.05 h−1) in any of the four strains (Fig. 4A), since ATP production barely covered the maintenance costs (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>At 2.5 h after glucose exhaustion, the WT and ΔcsrBC mutant strains produced ATP from acetate in the absence of glycogen (the ATP fluxes produced ranged between 5 and 12 mmol ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1), while in the csrA51 mutant strain, ATP was produced from glycogen in the absence of acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Although the ΔcsrD mutant strain displayed the greatest ATP flux from a mixture of glycogen and acetate 90 min after glucose exhaustion (Fig. 4A), growth was only barely detectable and stopped 1 h later when both acetate and glycogen were depleted (Fig. 1 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>We thus conclude that both acetate and glycogen can be used to maintain the energy status of the cells after glucose exhaustion but that their consumption rates are too low to ensure observable growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Even in the csrA51 mutant strain, which has the highest energy level AEC and glycogen content (up to 30% of the biomass), the ATP produced is only sufficient to ensure maintenance, i.e., to allow the strain to survive but not to grow efficiently. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 4 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Metabolic capacities of the WT and Csr system mutant strains during growth on glycogen and acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Flux balance analysis of the four strains was performed with glycogen and acetate as carbon sources by using two different objective functions, biomass and ATP production (see Materials and Methods for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(A) Maximum predicted growth rates (μ) for various pairs of glycogen and acetate uptake rates (qs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(B) Maximum flux of ATP predicted by the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Bars to the right of each plot indicate the color code used for the growth rate (A) and ATP flux (B) values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The four strains, the WT (gray circles), the csrBC mutant (green squares), the csrD mutant (orange triangles), and the csrA51 mutant (red diamonds), were assessed at two different times 90 min (*) and 150 min (**). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The values are averages of three replicates with error bars representing standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s1.5"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Suppression of glycogen synthesis hinders the capacity of the csrA51 mutant strain to maintain high energy levels after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>As shown above, both acetate and glycogen can be used to maintain the energy status after glucose exhaustion but the corresponding ATP fluxes did not enable us to distinguish differences in the energy level AEC and fitness related to acetate consumption in the different strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Only glycogen levels appeared to accompany the high energy level of the csrA51 mutant strain and the low energy level of the ΔcsrBC mutant (Fig. 1D and 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>We therefore hypothesized that the impact of Csr on the energy status can only be mediated by the impact of CsrA on glycogen accumulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To confirm this hypothesis, we prevented glycogen synthesis in the WT and csrA51 mutant strains by deleting the glgC gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The same pools of metabolites as those shown in Fig. 3 were then assessed during the glucose-acetate transition in the WT and ΔglgC, csrA51, and csrA51 ΔglgC mutant strains (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Some of the WT and csrA51 mutant metabolite pools, e.g., FBP, differed quantitatively from those shown in Fig. 3A, very likely because these cultures were performed in Erlenmeyer flasks instead of in reactors with regulated pH and monitored oxygenation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, the trends were similar under both conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, the deletion of glgC prevented the maintenance of elevated G6P, F6P, and nucleotide triphosphate in the csrA51 mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Prevention of glycogen synthesis did not affect the AEC before glucose exhaustion (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>After glucose exhaustion, the AEC of the two strains unable to store glycogen dropped drastically in comparison to that of the WT and csrA51 mutant strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We therefore conclude that the maintenance of the energy status after glucose exhaustion in the csrA51 mutant strain results from its high glycogen content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 5 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Concentrations of key central carbon metabolites throughout the glucose-acetate transition of Csr system and/or glycogen-deficient mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(A) Metabolite concentrations were investigated from 3 h before to 2 h after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>WT, black circles; ΔglgC mutant, gray squares; csrA51 mutant, red diamonds; csrA51 ΔglgC mutant, brown triangles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>PEP, phosphoenolpyruvate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(B) The AECs of the same four strains during glucose consumption (plain bars) and 90 min after glucose exhaustion (striped bars) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A significant difference between a mutant and the WT is represented by an asterisk (P &lt; 0.05 [t test]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The values are averages of three independent biological replicates with error bars representing standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s1.6"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The Csr system affects cellular fitness through its control of glycogen synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our results suggest that the Csr system influences the energy status through the control of glycogen synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This affects the ability of the strain to switch to acetate metabolism after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate this scenario, we investigated the dynamics of the metabolic adaptation of the cells when switched to fresh medium containing acetate as the sole carbon source. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The capacity of Csr and/or glycogen mutant cells to resume growth on fresh acetate minimum medium was assessed before and after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The times required to recover full growth on acetate were determined (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>As previously demonstrated (31), the WT strain required 38 min to switch from glucose- to acetate-based growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>This delay was reduced to 21 min when the cells were sampled 1 h after glucose exhaustion, likely because of the induced expression of gluconeogenic enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The delays were similar in the ΔcsrD mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In the csrA51 mutant strain, the delays increased by 40 to 50% but the same relative decrease was observed after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The long delays in the csrA51 mutant strain could be explained by the difficulty in setting up acetate consumption in the presence of highly abundant glycogen, which could be a more favorable substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The delay in the ΔcsrBC mutant strain growing on glucose was similar to that in the WT strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the delay in the ΔcsrBC mutant strain was not reduced after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>This property was also observed in the ΔglgC and csrA51 ΔglgC mutant strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The increase in the delays in the csrA51 mutant strain switched to acetate was also suppressed in the csrA51 ΔglgC mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Since the glycogen level in the csrBC mutant strain was zero after glucose exhaustion (Fig. 1D), we conclude that glycogen is necessary to start acetate uptake 1 h after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the Csr system affects the establishment of metabolic adaptation after glucose exhaustion through its control of glycogen synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 6 </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Delay before the full growth rate was reached on acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For each strain, cells from a mother culture on M9-glucose were transferred to M9-acetate and the time lag until full growth on the new substrate was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Cells were sampled either 60 min before (plain bars) or 60 min after (striped bars) glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The data are averages of three or more independent biological replicates with error bars representing standard deviations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>A significant difference between a mutant and the WT is represented by an asterisk (P &lt; 0.05 [t test]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0051735690006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The Csr system was recently demonstrated to be a major controller of upper glycolysis fluxes (16), but its involvement in metabolic adaptation is less clear in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>CsrA is known to positively regulate glycolytic genes and negatively regulate gluconeogenic genes (15, 16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>A study of the BarA/UvrY two-component system during the metabolic switch suggested that the Csr system is crucial for efficient adaptation between different metabolic pathways (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Here, we showed that gene expression in the CCM (glycolysis, gluconeogenesis, the pentose phosphate pathway, and the tricarboxylic acid cycle) did not present strong discrepancies between the Csr system mutants during the acetate consumption phase, in deep contrast to the situation during glucose consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>It will be awkward to totally rule out any control of these genes by CsrA, since regulation could be at the posttranscriptional level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The control by CsrA could also be counterbalanced by its higher sequestration by CsrB, since the latter level has been reported to increase during the transition (23, 37). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, CsrA was demonstrated to control the expression of genes encoding functions in acetate and glycogen metabolism after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This gene expression profiling, combined with acetate measurements and switch experiments, demonstrated that CsrA influences the timing of acetate and glycogen utilization after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>We proved that glycogen allows the maintenance of a minimal cellular energy level after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The energy related to glycogen and/or acetate catabolism provided the energy required for maintenance but was not sufficient to sustain growth on glycogen alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We also showed that glycogen accumulation increased cell fitness by allowing a rapid restart on acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In the csrA51 mutant strain, the overaccumulation of glycogen was also accompanied by levels of G6P and F6P and energy status after glucose exhaustion matching those of the WT during growth on glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Conversely, a ΔcsrBC mutant strain that accumulates a very low level of glycogen presents phenotypes similar to those of a ΔglgC mutant strain after glucose exhaustion, with a low energy status and a weaker adaptive capacity to use acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>From our work, it is now clear that CsrA regulates the metabolic transition from glycolysis to gluconeogenesis in E. coli. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Most of the elements presented here strengthen the hypothesis that the transition control by the Csr system is exerted through the regulation of glycogen synthesis and its utilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The only clue we observed concerning a glycogen-independent effect of CsrA during the transition is in the production of cAMP, an alarmone that has an important function in the catabolite repression process (38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a csrA51 mutant strain induced cAMP production after glucose exhaustion, but the levels were about five times lower than in the WT (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This could result from the greater availability of G6P, since this substrate indirectly controls adenylate cyclase activity (39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, the csrA51 ΔglgC mutant strain presents the same phenotype, proving that this lower cAMP level does not result from the greater glycogen content and is therefore directly linked to CsrA activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>CsrA could thus affect important metabolic adaption processes, such as catabolite repression, independently of glycogen content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This reinforces the very recently discovered link between Csr and catabolite repression regulatory systems (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This new regulation was shown to be related to the control of the expression of the CsrB and CsrC ncRNAs via the main catabolic repression actors EIIAGluc and cAMP-CRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>There could be another clue to glycogen-independent control; i.e., if glycogen exhaustion hinders metabolic adaptation, glycogen overaccumulation (as in the csrA51 mutant strain) should favor it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>However, the delay before the beginning of acetate anabolism was longer in the csrA51 mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This phenotype is very likely explained by the fact that glycolysis is still supplied in G6P by glycogen after glucose exhaustion in the csrA51 mutant and this could impair/prevent the establishment of gluconeogenic metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Therefore, here again, this phenotype is linked to glycogen accumulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We consequently conclude that CsrA control of metabolic adaptation is mediated mainly through glycogen accumulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Given its structural characteristics and its metabolic regulation, glycogen was hypothesized to be a storage compound providing both carbon and energy for microorganisms (40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>However, no demonstration of this function was previously reported in the literature (41–43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Here, using a metabolomics approach, we proved for the first time that glycogen is essential to maintain the cell energy level after glucose exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>This is especially important since it was postulated that to classify glycogen as an energy storage compound, its use as a supply for energy maintenance had to be demonstrated (40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>With this work, this is now the case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Glycogen metabolism was also linked to environmental survival (43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It was recently hypothesized and backed up by modeling that glycogen is an energy supply for immediate use in the following growth phase of E. coli (42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Here again, we experimentally demonstrated the validity of these in silico-based conclusions by showing that metabolic adaptation of cells depends on glycogen content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Thus, this work also provides significant clues to the function of glycogen in E. coli. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>To conclude, this work is of particular importance in understanding (i) the function of CsrA-mediated posttranscriptional control, (ii) the role of glycogen in bacteria, and (iii) the mechanisms behind metabolic adaptation and fitness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This knowledge is crucial not only for control of the ability of E. coli to efficiently colonize the gut or other microbial communities and environments but also for the optimization of biotechnological processes in which the metabolic flexibility of E. coli is extensively exploited for the use of a broad range of substrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>All of the strains used in this study came from E. coli K-12 MG1655 (WT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The csrA51 mutant strain was built by deleting the last 11 amino acids of the CsrA protein by λ Red system recombination (17, 32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The csrD mutant strain was constructed by completely deleting the csrD gene by λ Red system recombination (17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the csrBC mutant strain was constructed by completely deleting the CsrB and CsrC ncRNAs by λ Red system recombination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The ΔglgC and csrA51 ΔglgC mutants were obtained from the JW3393 strain (Keio collection [44]) by moving the mutation (ΔglgC::Kan) to the WT or the background of the csrA51 mutant strain by bacteriophage P1-mediated transduction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Growth conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Bioreactor cultures were performed with a volume of 500 ml of M9 medium complemented with 2.7 g ⋅ liter−1 glucose with pH and oxygenation controls (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Three biological replicates were produced per strain (two for the csrA51 mutant strain). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The optical density at 600 nm (OD600) of extra- and intracellular samples was measured at 30-min intervals throughout the culture period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Flask cultures were performed with 200-ml baffled Erlenmeyer flasks with a total volume of 50 ml of M9 medium supplemented with 2.7 g ⋅ liter−1 glucose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>All of the cultures were performed at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Extracellular and intracellular metabolites. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The extracellular metabolites were identified and quantified by H+ high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) (Agilent Technologies 1200 Series HPLC and an Aminex HPX-87h column to separate acid and sugar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The analysis was carried out at 48°C with 5 mM H2SO4 as the eluent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Intracellular metabolites were sampled at four different times during culture by the differential method (45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The metabolic intracellular content was assessed by LC-MS/MS as previously described (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The AEC was quantified as previously described (35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Specific growth rates and consumption and production rates were determined as previously described (46). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Gene expression levels were analyzed by quantitative PCR (EvaGreen; Biotium, CA) on a Biomark 96.96 Dynamic Array (Fluidigm, CA) as previously described (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the equivalent of 5 mg of cell dry weight was harvested and directly flash frozen in liquid nitrogen at the same time as the intracellular metabolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and RT were performed as previously described (32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The transcripts levels were normalized to the idnT reference gene used as a constitutive reference (47). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Quantification of intracellular glycogen. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Intracellular glycogen was quantified as previously described (48). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Briefly, cells were lysed and glycogen was hydrolyzed into glucose subunits by an amyloglucosidase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The glucose subunits were then quantified with the Glucose (GO) Assay kit (Sigma-Aldrich, France). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Flux balance analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The genome scale model and constraints used in this study were previously described (16), except for the lower boundary of the non-growth-associated maintenance flux, which was set to 2.9 mmol ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The model is a slightly modified version of the genome scale reconstruction iAF1260-flux2 (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Flux balance analyses were performed with the COBRAv2 toolbox with GLPK as the linear programming solver (49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The glucose uptake rate was set to zero, while the oxygen uptake rate was set to a limiting value of −15 mmol ⋅ gDW−1 ⋅ h−1 to allow growth on acetate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The acetate and glycogen uptake rates were varied within the range of values monitored after glucose exhaustion (see Fig. 1), and for each pair of uptake rates, either the biomass or the ATP flux was optimized (with the lower boundary of the maintenance flux set to zero in the latter case). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3.7"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Switch experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>To investigate the timing of phenotypic adaptation, cell samples were collected from a “mother” culture 60 min before and 60 min after glucose exhaustion as previously described (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Briefly, cell samples were rapidly filtered, rinsed, and used to inoculate 250-ml Erlenmeyer flasks filled with 30 ml of acetate medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Growth of the “daughter” cultures was monitored by measuring the OD600 by spectrophotometry at 0, 15, 80, and 120 min after inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>We made sure that the cells from the daughter cultures reached the maximal growth rate (μmax) by measuring the growth rate between 80 and 120 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The lag time was calculated as previously described (31). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Citation Morin M, Ropers D, Cinquemani E, Portais J, Enjalbert B, Cocaign-Bousquet M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>2017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The Csr system regulates Escherichia coli fitness by controlling glycogen accumulation and energy levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>mBio 8:e01628-17. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01628-17">https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01628-17</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>We thank Sophie Mondeil, Alessandra Fontana, Aurélien Staes, Andrea Belluati, Frédéric Anglès, Thomas Esquerre, and Catherine Turlan for their valuable contributions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique (Department Microbiology of the Food Chain) and the Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique), from which M.M. received a doctoral fellowship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>MetaToul (Metabolomics and Fluxomics Facilities, Toulouse, France, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metatoul.fr">http://www.metatoul.fr</ext-link>) and its staff (Lara Gales and Lindsey Peyriga) are gratefully acknowledged for access to NMR and MS facilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>MetaToul is part of the national infrastructure MetaboHUB-ANR-11-INBS-0010 (the French National Infrastructure for Metabolomics and Fluxomics, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metabohub.fr">http://www.metabohub.fr</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Gene expression data were obtained with the support of the Genomic and Transcriptomic Platform in Auzeville, France. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>1.MirandaRL, ConwayT, LeathamMP, ChangDE, NorrisWE, AllenJH, StevensonSJ, LauxDC, CohenPS 2004 Glycolytic and gluconeogenic growth of Escherichia coli O157:H7 (EDL933) and E. coli K-12 (MG1655) in the mouse intestine. Infect Immun 72:1666–1676. doi:10.1128/iai.72.3.1666-1676.2004.14977974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>2.PernestigAK, GeorgellisD, RomeoT, SuzukiK, TomeniusH, NormarkS, MeleforsO 2003 The Escherichia coli BarA-UvrY two-component system is needed for efficient switching between glycolytic and gluconeogenic carbon sources. J Bacteriol 185:843–853. doi:10.1128/jb.185.3.843-853.2003.12533459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>3.LeathamMP, BanerjeeS, AutieriSM, Mercado-LuboR, ConwayT, CohenPS 2009 Precolonized human commensal Escherichia coli strains serve as a barrier to E. coli O157:H7 growth in the streptomycin-treated mouse intestine. Infect Immun 77:2876–2886. doi:10.1128/IAI.00059-09.19364832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>4.DursoLM, SmithD, HutkinsRW 2004 Measurements of fitness and competition in commensal Escherichia coli and E. coli O157:H7 strains. Appl Environ Microbiol 70:6466–6472. doi:10.1128/AEM.70.11.6466-6472.2004.15528507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>5.ChangDE, SmalleyDJ, TuckerDL, LeathamMP, NorrisWE, StevensonSJ, AndersonAB, GrissomJE, LauxDC, CohenPS, ConwayT 2004 Carbon nutrition of Escherichia coli in the mouse intestine. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 101:7427–7432. doi:10.1073/pnas.0307888101.15123798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>6.KamadaN, KimYG, ShamHP, VallanceBA, PuenteJL, MartensEC, NúñezG 2012 Regulated virulence controls the ability of a pathogen to compete with the gut microbiota. Science 336:1325–1329. doi:10.1126/science.1222195.22582016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>7.KamadaN, ChenGY, InoharaN, NúñezG 2013 Control of pathogens and pathobionts by the gut microbiota. Nat Immunol 14:685–690. doi:10.1038/ni.2608.23778796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>8.FabichAJ, JonesSA, ChowdhuryFZ, CernosekA, AndersonA, SmalleyD, McHargueJW, HightowerGA, SmithJT, AutieriSM, LeathamMP, LinsJJ, AllenRL, LauxDC, CohenPS, ConwayT 2008 Comparison of carbon nutrition for pathogenic and commensal Escherichia coli strains in the mouse intestine. Infect Immun 76:1143–1152. doi:10.1128/IAI.01386-07.18180286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>9.EnjalbertB, LetisseF, PortaisJC 2013 Physiological and molecular timing of the glucose to acetate transition in Escherichia coli. Metabolites 3:820–837. doi:10.3390/metabo3030820.24958151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>10.KotteO, ZauggJB, HeinemannM 2010 Bacterial adaptation through distributed sensing of metabolic fluxes. Mol Syst Biol 6:355. doi:10.1038/msb.2010.10.20212527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>11.WolfeAJ 2005 The acetate switch. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 69:12–50. doi:10.1128/MMBR.69.1.12-50.2005.15755952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>12.EdwardsAN, Patterson-FortinLM, VakulskasCA, MercanteJW, PotrykusK, VinellaD, CamachoMI, FieldsJA, ThompsonSA, GeorgellisD, CashelM, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2011 Circuitry linking the Csr and stringent response global regulatory systems. Mol Microbiol 80:1561–1580. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07663.x.21488981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>13.McKeeAE, RutherfordBJ, ChivianDC, BaidooEK, JuminagaD, KuoD, BenkePI, DietrichJA, MaSM, ArkinAP, PetzoldCJ, AdamsPD, KeaslingJD, ChhabraSR 2012 Manipulation of the carbon storage regulator system for metabolite remodeling and biofuel production in Escherichia coli. Microb Cell Fact 11:79. doi:10.1186/1475-2859-11-79.22694848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>14.RomeoT, GongM, LiuMY, Brun-ZinkernagelAM 1993 Identification and molecular characterization of csrA, a pleiotropic gene from Escherichia coli that affects glycogen biosynthesis, gluconeogenesis, cell size, and surface properties. J Bacteriol 175:4744–4755. doi:10.1128/jb.175.15.4744-4755.1993.8393005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>15.SabnisNA, YangH, RomeoT 1995 Pleiotropic regulation of central carbohydrate metabolism in Escherichia coli via the gene csrA. J Biol Chem 270:29096–29104. doi:10.1074/jbc.270.49.29096.7493933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>16.MorinM, RopersD, LetisseF, LaguerreS, PortaisJC, Cocaign-BousquetM, EnjalbertB 2016 The post-transcriptional regulatory system CSR controls the balance of metabolic pools in upper glycolysis of Escherichia coli. Mol Microbiol 100:686–700. doi:10.1111/mmi.13343.26833659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>17.EsquerréT, BouvierM, TurlanC, CarpousisAJ, GirbalL, Cocaign-BousquetM 2016 The Csr system regulates genome-wide mRNA stability and transcription and thus gene expression in Escherichia coli. Sci Rep 6:25057. doi:10.1038/Srep25057.27112822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>18.SowaSW, GeldermanG, LeistraAN, BuvanendiranA, LippS, PitaktongA, VakulskasCA, RomeoT, BaldeaM, ContrerasLM 2017 Integrative FourD omics approach profiles the target network of the carbon storage regulatory system. Nucleic Acids Res 45:1673–1686. doi:10.1093/nar/gkx048.28126921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>19.BhattS, EdwardsAN, NguyenHT, MerlinD, RomeoT, KalmanD 2009 The RNA binding protein CsrA is a pleiotropic regulator of the locus of enterocyte effacement pathogenicity island of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli. Infect Immun 77:3552–3568. doi:10.1128/IAI.00418-09.19581394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>20.WeiBL, Brun-ZinkernagelAM, SimeckaJW, PrüssBM, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2001 Positive regulation of motility and flhDC expression by the RNA-binding protein CsrA of Escherichia coli. Mol Microbiol 40:245–256. doi:10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02380.x.11298291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>21.YakhninAV, BakerCS, VakulskasCA, YakhninH, BerezinI, RomeoT, BabitzkeP 2013 CsrA activates flhDC expression by protecting flhDC mRNA from RNase E-mediated cleavage. Mol Microbiol 87:851–866. doi:10.1111/mmi.12136.23305111 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>22.YangH, LiuMY, RomeoT 1996 Coordinate genetic regulation of glycogen catabolism and biosynthesis in Escherichia coli via the CsrA gene product. J Bacteriol 178:1012–1017. doi:10.1128/jb.178.4.1012-1017.1996.8576033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>23.GudapatyS, SuzukiK, WangX, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2001 Regulatory interactions of Csr components: the RNA binding protein CsrA activates csrB transcription in Escherichia coli. J Bacteriol 183:6017–6027. doi:10.1128/JB.183.20.6017-6027.2001.11567002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>24.LiuMY, GuiG, WeiB, PrestonJFIII, OakfordL, YükselU, GiedrocDP, RomeoT 1997 The RNA molecule CsrB binds to the global regulatory protein CsrA and antagonizes its activity in Escherichia coli. J Biol Chem 272:17502–17510. doi:10.1074/jbc.272.28.17502.9211896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>25.WeilbacherT, SuzukiK, DubeyAK, WangX, GudapatyS, MorozovI, BakerCS, GeorgellisD, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2003 A novel sRNA component of the carbon storage regulatory system of Escherichia coli. Mol Microbiol 48:657–670. doi:10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03459.x.12694612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>26.SuzukiK, BabitzkeP, KushnerSR, RomeoT 2006 Identification of a novel regulatory protein (CsrD) that targets the global regulatory RNAs CsrB and CsrC for degradation by RNase E. Genes Dev 20:2605–2617. doi:10.1101/gad.1461606.16980588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>27.VakulskasCA, LengY, AbeH, AmakiT, OkayamaA, BabitzkeP, SuzukiK, RomeoT 2016 Antagonistic control of the turnover pathway for the global regulatory sRNA CsrB by the CsrA and CsrD proteins. Nucleic Acids Res 44:7896–7910. doi:10.1093/nar/gkw484.27235416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>28.SuzukiK, WangX, WeilbacherT, PernestigAK, MeleforsO, GeorgellisD, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2002 Regulatory circuitry of the CsrA/CsrB and BarA/UvrY systems of Escherichia coli. J Bacteriol 184:5130–5140. doi:10.1128/jb.184.18.5130-5140.2002.12193630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>29.PannuriA, VakulskasCA, ZereT, McGibbonLC, EdwardsAN, GeorgellisD, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2016 Circuitry linking the catabolite repression and Csr global regulatory systems of Escherichia coli. J Bacteriol 198:3000–3015. doi:10.1128/JB.00454-16.27551019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>30.WeiB, ShinS, LaPorteD, WolfeAJ, RomeoT 2000 Global regulatory mutations in csrA and rpoS cause severe central carbon stress in Escherichia coli in the presence of acetate. J Bacteriol 182:1632–1640. doi:10.1128/JB.182.6.1632-1640.2000.10692369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>31.EnjalbertB, Cocaign-BousquetM, PortaisJC, LetisseF 2015 Acetate exposure determines the diauxic behavior of Escherichia coli during the glucose-acetate transition. J Bacteriol 197:3173–3181. doi:10.1128/JB.00128-15.26216845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>32.EsquerréT, LaguerreS, TurlanC, CarpousisAJ, GirbalL, Cocaign-BousquetM 2014 Dual role of transcription and transcript stability in the regulation of gene expression in Escherichia coli cells cultured on glucose at different growth rates. Nucleic Acids Res 42:2460–2472. doi:10.1093/nar/gkt1150.24243845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>33.MercanteJ, SuzukiK, ChengX, BabitzkeP, RomeoT 2006 Comprehensive alanine-scanning mutagenesis of Escherichia coli CsrA defines two subdomains of critical functional importance. J Biol Chem 281:31832–31842. doi:10.1074/jbc.M606057200.16923806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>34.EnjalbertB, JourdanF, PortaisJC 2011 Intuitive visualization and analysis of multi-omics data and application to Escherichia coli carbon metabolism. PLoS One 6:e21318. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0021318.21731702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>35.ChapmanAG, FallL, AtkinsonDE 1971 Adenylate energy charge in Escherichia coli during growth and starvation. J Bacteriol 108:1072–1086.4333317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>36.FeistAM, HenryCS, ReedJL, KrummenackerM, JoyceAR, KarpPD, BroadbeltLJ, HatzimanikatisV, PalssonBØ 2007 A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction for Escherichia coli K-12 MG1655 that accounts for 1260 ORFs and thermodynamic information. Mol Syst Biol 3:121. doi:10.1038/msb4100155.17593909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>37.CamachoMI, AlvarezAF, ChavezRG, RomeoT, MerinoE, GeorgellisD 2015 Effects of the global regulator CsrA on the BarA/UvrY two-component signaling system. J Bacteriol 197:983–991. doi:10.1128/JB.02325-14.25535275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>38.ZhengDL, ConstantinidouC, HobmanJL, MinchinSD 2004 Identification of the CRP regulon using in vitro and in vivo transcriptional profiling. Nucleic Acids Res 32:5874–5893. doi:10.1093/nar/gkh908.15520470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>39.BettenbrockK, SauterT, JahreisK, KremlingA, LengelerJW, GillesED 2007 Correlation between growth rates, EIIACrr phosphorylation, and intracellular cyclic AMP levels in Escherichia coli K-12. J Bacteriol 189:6891–6900. doi:10.1128/JB.00819-07.17675376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>40.PreissJ 1984 Bacterial glycogen synthesis and its regulation. Annu Rev Microbiol 38:419–458. doi:10.1146/annurev.mi.38.100184.002223.6093684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>41.EydallinG, MonteroM, AlmagroG, SesmaMT, VialeAM, MuñozFJ, RahimpourM, Baroja-FernándezE, Pozueta-RomeroJ 2010 Genome-wide screening of genes whose enhanced expression affects glycogen accumulation in Escherichia coli. DNA Res 17:61–71. doi:10.1093/dnares/dsp028.20118147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>42.YamamotoyaT, DoseH, TianZ, FauréA, ToyaY, HonmaM, IgarashiK, NakahigashiK, SogaT, MoriH, MatsunoH 2012 Glycogen is the primary source of glucose during the lag phase of E. coli proliferation. Biochim Biophys Acta 1824:1442–1448. doi:10.1016/j.bbapap.2012.06.010.22750467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>43.WangL, WiseMJ 2011 Glycogen with short average chain length enhances bacterial durability. Naturwissenschaften 98:719–729. doi:10.1007/s00114-011-0832-x.21808975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>44.BabaT, AraT, HasegawaM, TakaiY, OkumuraY, BabaM, DatsenkoKA, TomitaM, WannerBL, MoriH 2006 Construction of Escherichia coli K-12 in-frame, single-gene knockout mutants: the Keio collection. Mol Syst Biol 2:2006.0008. doi:10.1038/msb4100050. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>45.Taymaz-NikerelH, de MeyM, RasC, ten PierickA, SeifarRM, van DamJC, HeijnenJJ, van GulikWM 2009 Development and application of a differential method for reliable metabolome analysis in Escherichia coli. Anal Biochem 386:9–19. doi:10.1016/j.ab.2008.11.018.19084496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>46.CinquemaniE, LarouteV, Cocaign-BousquetM, de JongH, RopersD 2017 Estimation of time-varying growth, uptake and excretion rates from dynamic metabolomics data. Bioinformatics 33:i301–i310. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btx250.28881984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>47.ZhouK, ZhouL, LimQ', ZouR, StephanopoulosG, TooHP 2011 Novel reference genes for quantifying transcriptional responses of Escherichia coli to protein overexpression by quantitative PCR. BMC Mol Biol 12:18. doi:10.1186/1471-2199-12-18.21513543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>48.ParrouJL, FrançoisJ 1997 A simplified procedure for a rapid and reliable assay of both glycogen and trehalose in whole yeast cells. Anal Biochem 248:186–188. doi:10.1006/abio.1997.2138.9177741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>49.SchellenbergerJ, QueR, FlemingRM, ThieleI, OrthJD, FeistAM, ZielinskiDC, BordbarA, LewisNE, RahmanianS, KangJ, HydukeDR, PalssonBØ 2011 Quantitative prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox v2.0. Nat Protoc 6:1290–1307. doi:10.1038/nprot.2011.308.21886097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
