<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1741-7015</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5317055</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-016-0775-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Pain relief that matters to patients: systematic review of empirical studies assessing the minimum clinically important difference in acute pain </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5742-6403</contrib-id><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>Mette Frahm</given-names></name><address><email>meo@nexs.ku.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bjerre</surname><given-names>Eik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>Maria Damkjær</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>Jørgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Landler</surname><given-names>Nino Emanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tendal</surname><given-names>Britta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hróbjartsson</surname><given-names>Asbjørn</given-names></name><address><email>Asbjorn.Hrobjartsson@rsyd.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Nordic Cochrane Centre, Rigshospitalet, Blegdamsvej 9, Department 7811, 2100 Copenhagen Ø, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>University Hospitals’ Centre for Health Research (UCSF), Rigshospitalet, Blegdamsvej 9, Department 9701, 2100 Copenhagen Ø, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0646 8261</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415046.2</institution-id><institution/><institution>Frederiksberg Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Nordre Fasanvej 57, 2000 Frederiksberg, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 042X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5254.6</institution-id><institution/><institution>Section of Biostatistics, University of Copenhagen, </institution></institution-wrap>Østre Farigmagsgade 5, 114 Copenhagen Ø, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Cardiology, Herlev-Gentofte Hospital, Kildegårdsvej 28, 2900 Hellerup, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Centre for Evidence-Based Medicine, University of Southern Denmark &amp; Odense University Hospital, Sdr. Boulevard 29, Gate 50 (Videncenteret), 5000 Odense C, Denmark </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>35</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) is used to interpret the clinical relevance of results reported by trials and meta-analyses as well as to plan sample sizes in new studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, there is a lack of consensus about the size of MCID in acute pain, which is a core symptom affecting patients across many clinical conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We identified and systematically reviewed empirical studies of MCID in acute pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We searched PubMed, EMBASE and Cochrane Library, and included prospective studies determining MCID using a patient-reported anchor and a one-dimensional pain scale (e.g. 100 mm visual analogue scale). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We summarised results and explored reasons for heterogeneity applying meta-regression, subgroup analyses and individual patient data meta-analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We included 37 studies (8479 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Thirty-five studies used a mean change approach, i.e. MCID was assessed as the mean difference in pain score among patients who reported a minimum degree of improvement, while seven studies used a threshold approach, i.e. MCID was assessed as the threshold in pain reduction associated with the best accuracy (sensitivity and specificity) for identifying improved patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Meta-analyses found considerable heterogeneity between studies (absolute MCID: I2 = 93%, relative MCID: I2 = 75%) and results were therefore presented qualitatively, while analyses focused on exploring reasons for heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The reported absolute MCID values ranged widely from 8 to 40 mm (standardised to a 100 mm scale) and the relative MCID values from 13% to 85%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>From analyses of individual patient data (seven studies, 918 patients), we found baseline pain strongly associated with absolute, but not relative, MCID as patients with higher baseline pain needed larger pain reduction to perceive relief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Subgroup analyses showed that the definition of improved patients (one or several categories improvement or meaningful change) and the design of studies (single or multiple measurements) also influenced MCID values. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The MCID in acute pain varied greatly between studies and was influenced by baseline pain, definitions of improved patients and study design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>MCID is context-specific and potentially misguiding if determined, applied or interpreted inappropriately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Explicit and conscientious reflections on the choice of a reference value are required when using MCID to classify research results as clinically important or trivial. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pain</kwd><kwd>Minimum clinically important difference</kwd><kwd>Systematic review</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Nordic Cochrane Centre</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It can be challenging to decide whether a modest effect in a randomised clinical trial, or a meta-analysis of several such trials, is clinically relevant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Statistical tests inform on the probability of a result being a chance finding; however, they convey no information on whether a given effect will be experienced as important by patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The degree of pain reduction that is considered clinically relevant has an impact on which analgesic interventions are regarded clinically useful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This interpretation problem for clinical relevance has been at the core of debates of the importance of several types of interventions intended for reducing acute pain, for example, paracetamol [1–3], non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [4, 5], morphine or synthetic opiates [6], corticosteroids [7], muscle relaxants [4], laser therapy [8], transcranial direct current stimulation [9], EMLA cream [10], and acupuncture [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A related challenge involves the calculation of sample sizes for clinical trials, where researchers need to know the smallest clinically important effect that the trial should not miss to be able to determine an adequate sample size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Jaeschke et al. [12] characterised the concept of minimum clinically relevant difference in 1989 as “the smallest difference in score in the domain of interest which participants perceive as beneficial and which would mandate, in the absence of troublesome side effects and costs, a change in the patient’s management”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The strength of the concept is that it defines a relevant effect size based on clinical considerations and not only statistical significance [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It has subsequently been supplemented by a related concept – the substantial (and not only minimum) clinically relevant difference [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) is sometimes chosen on the basis of expert consensus judgement [16], statistical models [17] or objective criteria [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, in acute pain, it seems reasonable to anchor clinical relevance to the patients’ experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This approach is in accordance with the increasing awareness of the relevance of patient-reported outcomes in clinical research [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Several such empirical studies have been conducted to determine the MCID in acute pain, but they differ with regard to methodology, clinical condition and findings, and have not yet been systematically reviewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Since acute pain is a core symptom in healthcare, an assessment of the MCID and a clarification of the causes for its variation will have broad interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that baseline pain influences absolute values of MCID, but study reports have been conflicting [20, 21], and it remains unclear which other clinical or methodological factors are of importance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We therefore decided to systematically review empirical studies of the MCID in acute pain relief and to examine possible causes for variation between study results, especially their likely dependency on baseline pain levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We also reviewed studies of the substantial clinically important difference in acute pain relief as well as clinically important differences for worsening of pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Eligibility criteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We included prospective studies of patients with acute pain, regardless of age, clinical condition, and intervention, in which pain intensity was assessed on a one-dimensional scale, e.g. a 100 mm visual analogue scale (VAS) or a 0–10 point numerical rating scale (NRS), and in which the MCID was determined using an anchor-based method using patients’ perception of change to determine clinical importance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Pain was considered acute when its duration was less than 1 month or, if duration was not indicated, when it was described as such in a study report. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Studies were excluded if they were not clinical (i.e. used healthy volunteers) or determined the MCID from objective criteria (e.g. return to work), the distribution of data (e.g. the minimum detectable difference) or expert consensus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A typical eligible study would ask patients to score their pain intensity, e.g. using a VAS, at baseline and follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>At follow-up, patients were also asked to categorise their change in pain intensity using response options such as ‘no change’, ‘a little better’/‘somewhat better’, and ‘a lot better’/‘much better’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The MCID was then determined from the change in scores on the pain scale among patients having categorised their change as ‘a little better’ (or a similar expression indicating a minimum clinically important improvement). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We included studies with two types of analytical approaches (1) the ‘mean change approach’, i.e. the mean difference in pain scores among patients who reported a minimum degree of pain relief [22]; or (2) the ‘threshold approach’, i.e. the threshold value for pain score change which most accurately (yield﻿i﻿ng best sensitivity and specificity) identified patients experiencing relevant pain relief in analogy with a diagnostic test where the gold standard is patients’ perception of change [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Search strategy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We searched PubMed, EMBASE and Cochrane Library until August 2016 with no language restrictions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The core search string was: (minimal OR minimally OR minimum OR ‘clinically significant’ OR ‘clinically important’ OR ‘clinically meaningful’ OR ‘clinically relevant’) AND (difference OR change OR relief OR reduction) AND (‘pain measurement*’ OR ‘visual analog scale’ OR ‘numeric rating scale’) AND (pain) with variations according to the specific database (Appendix 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The reference lists of all included studies and relevant review papers were read systematically to identify further studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Screening of titles and abstracts to determine the eligibility of studies was done by the primary author (MFO), while the selected full-text records were examined by two researchers independently (MFO and either EB, NEL, BT, or MDH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Any disagreement was solved by discussion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Data extraction and retrieval </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Data extraction was conducted by two researchers independently (MFO and EB, BT, or NEL) using pretested data extraction forms generated in EpiData (EpiData Association, Odense, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Any disagreements were solved by discussion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>For each study, we extracted descriptive data including publication year, study design, setting, clinical condition, type of intervention, sampling method, sample size, and definition of patients with relevant change (see Appendix 2 for complete list). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>For studies using a mean change approach, we extracted the following outcome data: the MCID for pain relief (absolute values in mm or points and relative value in percent change from baseline) and for pain worsening (absolute and relative values), as well as the substantial clinically important difference for relief and worsening of pain (absolute and relative values). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We extracted MCIDs as the mean change in pain score among patients who indicated a one-category improvement (e.g. ‘a little better’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>If unavailable, we extracted the mean change among patients who were minimally improved by authors’ definition (e.g. some authors defined minimum important change as the mean change in pain score among patients with either a one- or two-category improvement). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Similarly, we extracted the substantial clinically important differences as the mean change among patients with a two-category improvement or used the authors’ definition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We extracted the point estimate of outcomes with their corresponding standard error or, if unavailable, other measures of variation such as standard deviation or 95% confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>For studies using a threshold approach, we extracted information about definition of responders (i.e. patients with relevant change) and non-responders and the cut-off point with its corresponding sensitivity (i.e. percentage of responders correctly classified as such) and specificity (i.e. percentage of non-responders correctly classified as such). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>If studies reported pain scores from several concurrent pain assessments (e.g. back pain and leg pain), we extracted the assessment where more data were available or, if no difference found, we randomly selected which to extract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>All scales were standardised to a 0–100 mm scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>When studies reported pain assessments based on both VAS and NRS, we used the assessment based on VAS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>If the primary outcome or other key variables were unclear or incompletely reported from a study, we contacted the corresponding author. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In cases where authors provided individual patient data, we first checked whether we could replicate a main result of the published paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We then calculated estimates of absolute and relative MCIDs and their corresponding standard error. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For each study, we assessed risk of attrition bias (studies were considered low risk when attrition &lt; 10%) and risk of non-representative study sample (studies were considered low risk if using consecutive or random sampling). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Data synthesis and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For each study, we extracted or calculated the MCID for pain relief (absolute and relative change), and noted results of any study-based exploration of causes for variation, e.g. baseline pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We then summarised results qualitatively as there was considerable clinical and methodological variation between studies and heterogeneity in their results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To provide an overview, we first reported the range of results for all studies and then the range and median results with inter-quartile ranges (IQR) of studies according to analytical strategy (mean change or threshold approach). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>To facilitate exploration of reasons for heterogeneity, we then pooled results of studies using mean change approach with inverse-variance meta-analysis using random effects models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We studied the association with baseline pain scores in three different analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>First, we explored the impact of the average population baseline pain in a mixed-effects meta-regression (acknowledging the limitations of aggregated data-level analysis [24]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Second, we pooled individual patient data to estimate the MCID (absolute and relative changes) using a two-stage individual participant data meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In these models, MCIDs were first estimated in each individual study using a mixed model based on all repeated measurements and participant specific random effects to capture the serial correlation within each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Results were then pooled using random-effects inverse-variance meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Third, we used the same model to derive outcomes measured at different time points in studies with multiple measurements per patients (i.e. the use of a ‘moving baseline’). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>We furthermore used subgroup analyses to explore whether between-study variation was explained by differences in other clinical and methodological factors including clinical condition, type of pain scale (VAS vs. NRS), directionality of global transition scale (one-sided vs. two-sided scale), definition of minimum clinically important change (one category vs. several categories improvement vs. distinction between meaningful and non-meaningful change), number of pain assessments per patients (single vs. multiple assessments adjusted for correlation vs. multiple unadjusted assessments), risk of attrition bias (low vs. high or unclear) and risk of non-representative sample (low vs. high or unclear). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Finally, we used the same analysis strategy for the substantial clinically important difference for pain relief (absolute and relative change) and the minimum and substantial clinically important differences for worsening of pain (absolute and relative change). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>All data analyses were done using Stata/IC version 13. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Study selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We screened 1553 database records and read 273 full-text publications (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>We excluded 237 publications, mostly because they included patients with chronic pain (n = 63) or multi-dimensional pain scales (n = 53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Thus, we included 36 publications [21, 25–59] reporting 37 studies (8479 patients).Fig. 1Flow chart of study identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>MCID = Minimal Clinically Important Difference, aAdditional records identified through “related papers” function in databases and reference lists of screened papers, bTwo records include both acute and chronic pain studies, cIncludes studies in which MCID was not based on subjective patient-reported assessment of pain relief </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of included studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The majority of studies were based in emergency departments and included a mix of patients with acute pain of both traumatic and non-traumatic origin (10 studies) or unspecified pain (7 studies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Additional studies included patients with post-operative pain, cancer-related pain, sickle cell crisis, rheumatic pain, abdominal pain, low back pain, or headache (Tables 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>All studies were published in English.Table 1Studies determining minimal clinically important difference as a mean changea (35 studies, 7894 patients)StudynPatient characteristicsMethodological characteristicsMCIDClinical conditionAge, years (range)b Male sex, %Baseline pain, mmPain scaleTransition scale (directionality, categories)Follow-up (Analysis adjusted)c Category defining MCIDAbsoluted mm (95% CI)Relativee % (95% CI)Aicher [25]1743Headache38h (16–72)2464VAS1-sided, 4 catSingleLess good efficacy27 (25–29)NRBailey [26]202Mixedg 12 (8–17)57NRNRS2-sided, 5 catSingleA little better10 (0–20)h NRBarton 2002 (reported in Jensen 2002 [43])125Post-operation pain (laparotomy)410NRVAS1-sided, 5 catMultiple (unclear)A little relief9 (7–12)13 (8–17)Bernstein [27]135Unspecified42 (21–65)45100h NRS1-sided, 5 catSingleA little relief21 (18–24)NRBijur [28]f 108Unspecified44 (21–85)4073VAS + NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain16 (11–21)22 (15–28)Bijur [29]f 195Unspecified742774NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A little less pain15 (14–17)24 (21–27)Bijur [30]f 214Unspecified743486NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A little less pain14 (12–15)22 (19–25)Bird [31]77Isolated extremity trauma386252VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain20 (15–25)NRBulloch [32]121Mixedg (65% traumatic, 35% non-traumatic)10 (5–16)5660h VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain17 (11–23)NRCepeda [33]700Post-operation pain (mixed)41 (16–88)3879NRS1-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)Minimal improvement17 (10–20)h 20 (13–30)h Chow [34]105Pain flare after radiotherapy70h 5650NRS2-sided, 3 catMultiple (no)Better23 (20–26)NRDegerli [35]306Thoraco-abdominal pain (non-traumatic)42 (17–83)4067VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain25 (23–26)NRFarrar [36]134Cancer-related breakthrough pain55 (21–87)53NRNRS1-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)Slight relief13–19j 16–34j Fosnocht [37]1490Mixedg 36 (18–89)4763VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain21 (19–23)NRGallagher [38]f 96Mixedg 37 (19–71)4564VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A little less pain15 (11–18)17 (6–29)Gallagher [39]f 101Abdominal pain40 (15–88)3965VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A little less pain18 (14–21)23 (12–33)Grilo [40]50Rheumatic conditions49 (16–85)4478VAS1-sided, 5 catSingleModerate relief40i NRGrotle [41]54Acute low back pain382739VAS + NRS2-sided, 6 catSingleSlightly improved34 (20–48)Holdgate [42]f 79Unspecified53 (21–93)NR54VAS + NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A bit better16 (12–20)34 (27–41)Kelly [44]Kelly [45, 46]156Mixedg (43% traumatic, 57% non-traumatic)44 (16–97)5651VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (unclear)A little better8 (4–12)NRKendrick 2005 [47]356Mixedg (35% traumatic, 65% non-traumatic)41h 4266NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain15 (13–16)NRLopez [21]74Sickle cell crisisNRNR79VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little better14 (11–16)h,k NRMark [48]186Unspecified49 (15–87)3865VAS2-sided, 5 catSingleA little better17 (14–20)k NRMartin [49]95Third molar extraction304033VAS2-sided, 7 catSingleMuch improved or best ever23i 72i Martin [49]63Third molar extraction254035DoDoDoDo25i 69i Martin [49]62Third molar extraction275030DoDoDoDo29i 85i McConahay [50]126Mixedg (48% traumatic, 52% non-traumatic)9 (5–12)5683VAS2-sided, 5 catSingleA little less pain24 (17–31)NRMohan [51]f 125Unspecified35h 4446VAS + NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A bit better13 (9–17)18 (1–35)Myrvik [52]28Sickle cell crisis15 (8–18)5075h VAS + NRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (unclear)A little better10 (4–15)NRPowell [53]73Mixed (63% traumatic, 37% non-traumatic)12 (8–15)NR60VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A bit better11i NRRasmussen 2002 (reported in Jensen 2002 [43])123Post-operation pain (knee surgery)6534NRVAS1-sided, 5 catMultiple (unclear)A little relief13 (10–17)18 (14–22)Sloman [54]150Post-operation pain (mixed)47 (14–89)5367NRS1-sided, 5 catSingleMinimal relief18i 36 (21–51)Stahmer [55]81Mixedg (31% traumatic, 69% non-traumatic)38 (16–87)4468NRS1-sided, 5 catSingleSome relief or partial reliefNR30 (18–42)Todd [56]48Trauma35h (17–76)6956VAS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (no)A little less pain16 (10–22)NRVoepel-Lewis [59]113Post-operation pain (e.g. spinal fusion, splenectomy)13 (7–16)43NRNRS2-sided, 5 catMultiple (yes)A little better10 (5–15)NR aMean change in pain score among patients with minimum improvement of pain bMean (range) if not otherwise indicated, cEstimate based on single or multiple follow-up measurements (were standard errors adjusted for dependency between multiple measurements?) dAbsolute = mm reduction on a 100 mm scale eRelative = % reduction from baseline fIndividual patient data provided by authors gMixed patient population recruited at Hospital Emergency Department hData is median (inter-quartile range) i95% CI unavailable jEstimates for subgroups with different baseline pain kPatients with minimal improvement and worsening of pain were combined MCID minimum clinically important difference, VAS visual analogue scale, NRS numeric rating scale, CI confidence interval, NR not reported Table 2Studies determining minimal clinically important difference as a threshold valuea (7 studies, 2602 patients)StudynPatient characteristicsMethodological characteristicsMCIDClinical conditionAge, yearsb Male sex, %Baseline pain, mmPain scaleTransition scale (directionality, categories)Anchor questionCategories defining respondersAbsolute, mm (sensitivity, specificity)Relative, % (sensitivity, specificity)Aicher [25]1743Headache38b (16–72)2464VAS1-sided, 4 cat (0 to +4 points)"How do you assess the efficacy of your tablets?"Good (+3) or very good (+4)35 (76%, 76%)NRGrotle [41]54Acute low back pain382739VAS + NRS2-sided, 6 cat (–1 to +4 points)"To which extent has your back problem changed?"Slightly improved (+1), much better (+2), very much better (+3), or completely gone (+4)10 (87%, 81%)NRMartin [49]63Post-operation pain (third molar extraction)304033VAS2-sided, 7 cat (–3 to +3 points)Assessment of recovery following treatmentMuch improved (+2) or best ever (+3)10 (70%, 82%)50 (82%, 82%)Martin [49]62Post-operation pain (third molar extraction)254035DoDoDoDo10 (71%, 71%)50 (83%, 86%)Martin [49]95Post-operation pain (third molar extraction)275030DoDoDoDo10 (87%, 69%)50 (97%, 82%)Tsze [57]314Mixedd 1050NRVAS2-sided, 5 cat (–2 to +2 points)Assessment of change in pain following treatmentA little better (+1)10 (76%, 74%)15 (78%, 79%)Tubach [58]271Rotator cuff syndrome483868NRS2-sided, 15 cat (–7 to +7 points)Assessment of response to treatmentA good deal better (+5) or a great deal better (+6)34–63c (75%, NR)NR MCID minimum clinically important difference (mm change on a 100 mm scale), VAS visual analogue scale, NRS numeric rating scale, NR not reported aThreshold in pain reduction associated with the best accuracy (sensitivity and specificity) for identifying improved patients bData is median (range) cEstimates for subgroups with different baseline pain cMixed patient population recruited at Hospital Emergency Department </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Twenty studies assessed pain using a 100 mm VAS (or the similar Color Analog Scale), and 12 studies used an 11-point NRS (0–10), while five studies used both scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In 32 studies, patients compared their current pain intensity with pain at their previous assessment, while they were asked to assess the effect of their treatment in five studies [25, 49, 58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Transition scales were either two-sided (29 studies) with 3–15 response categories for both improvement and deterioration, or one-sided (8 studies) with five response categories addressing only improvement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>For studies using the mean change approach, the majority defined the minimum clinically important improvement as a one-category improvement on the transition scale (31 studies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The response categories were similar with wordings such as ‘a little less pain’, ‘a bit better’, ‘slightly improved’, or ‘slight relief’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In four studies, the MCID was defined as the mean change in pain score among patients with a one- or two-category improvement, thereby combing patients answering ‘some relief’ and ‘partial relief’ [55], or ‘much improved’ and ‘best ever’ [49–51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Finally, two studies differentiated between non-important and important change, using the categories ‘inadequate relief’ and ‘moderate relief’ in one study [40], and ‘poor’ and ‘less good’ efficiency of treatment in another [25] (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Studies using the threshold approach had large variation in transition scales and definitions of responders versus non-responders; patients were regarded as importantly improved if they indicated a one-category relief in two studies [41, 57], while they needed a five-category improvement in another [58] (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Pain intensity was assessed at baseline and a single follow-up measurement in 14 studies, while it was assessed at multiple (from 2 to 16) follow-ups with intervals between 10 and 45 minutes in 23 studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The latter group then derived their outcome as the summarised mean difference in pain score from the patients’ previous pain assessment when they reported minimum relief (i.e. a series of ‘moving baselines’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In eight of these studies, the P values of analyses were adjusted for correlation between estimates, for example, with Generalised Estimation Equation, while the remaining studies either made no adjustment or did not report this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Access to individual patient data increased the number of studies with adjusted estimates to 11. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In 10 studies, the MCID was defined as a numeric change for all patients with minimum change, regardless of whether pain had improved or worsened. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>After contacting authors, separate estimates for pain relief were available from eight of these. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>MCID regardless of analytical approach </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Standardised to a 100-mm scale, the absolute MCID in 30 studies ranged from 8 to 40 mm, and the relative difference in 15 studies ranged from 13% to 85%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>MCIDs in studies using the mean change approach </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The determination of the MCID was based on a mean change approach in 35 studies, of which 30 (6598 patients) were included in our analyses and five were disregarded (see below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Twenty-nine studies (6517 patients) reported absolute values ranging from 8 to 40 mm, with a median of 17 mm (IQR 14–23 mm) (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Only nine of the 30 studies reported relative MCIDs, but access to individual patient data made relative values available from 14 studies (1617 patients) ranging from 13% to 85%, with a median of 23% (IQR 18–36%) (Fig. 2b).Fig. 2 a Range of absolute minimal clinically important differences in acute pain assessed by the mean change approach* (29 studies, 6517 patients). *MCID assessed as the mean change in pain score among patients with minimal improvement of pain, MCID = Minimal Clinically Important Difference (mm reduction on a 100 mm scale), Studies where standard error (or data for obtaining this) was unavailable are presented as point estimates without 95% CI (NA = not applicable). b Range of relative minimal clinically important differences in acute pain assessed by the mean change approach* (14 studies, 1617 patients). *MCID assessed as the mean change in pain score among patients with minimal improvement of pain, MCID = Minimal Clinically Important Difference (% reduction from baseline), Studies where standard error (or data for obtaining this) was unavailable are presented as point estimates without 95% CI (NA = not applicable) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>For data syntheses, we did not include results from five of the 35 studies (1567 patients) as they did not differentiate between pain relief and pain worsening [21, 48], because median (and not mean) differences in pain were reported [26, 33], or because outcomes were reported for subgroups and no overall estimate could be derived [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The range of MCID in these studies was comparable to the included studies: 10–19 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>An additional six studies (493 patients) were not included in meta-analysis since information about standard error of estimates was unavailable [40, 49, 53, 54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The results from these studies ranged from 11 to 40 mm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>We had data usable for meta-analyses from 23 studies (6024 patients) reporting absolute values and 11 studies (1397 patients) reporting relative values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Meta-analyses of both the absolute and relative values showed considerable heterogeneity: I2 = 93%, P &lt; 0.001 and I2 = 75%, P &lt; 0.001 (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We present the meta-analyses for completeness and as a basis for exploring reasons for the heterogeneity, but stress that medians and interquartile ranges are more appropriate descriptors of the results.Table 3Clinically important differences in acute painAnalysis of mediansa Analysis of pooled averageClinically important differenceRangeNumber of studies (patientsb)MCID median (IQR)Number of studies (patientsb)MCID pooled average (95% CI), I2 c Minimum clinically important difference for pain relief Absolute change, mm  Mean change approach8 to 4029 (6517)17 (14 to 23)23 (6024)17 (15 to 19), 93%  Threshold approach10 to 356 (2331)10 (10 to 10)NANA Relative change, %  Mean change approach13 to 8514 (1617)23 (18 to 36)11 (1397)22 (19 to 26), 75%  Threshold approach15 to 504 (534)50 (33 to 50)NANASubstantial clinically important difference for pain relief Absolute change, mm  Mean change approach18 to 5423 (6114)32 (24 to 38)21 (5891)32 (27 to 38), 97% Relative change, %  Mean change approach36 to 7811 (1397)57 (45 to 65)11 (1397)57 (47 to 67), 94%Minimum clinically important difference for pain worsening Absolute change, mm  Mean change approach−21 to –818 (3822)−11 (–13 to –10)16 (3644)−12 (–14 to –11), 62% Relative change, %  Mean change approach−89 to –177 (918)−44 (–90 to –16)7 (918)−35 (–47 to –23), 67%Substantial clinically important difference for pain worsening Absolute change, mm  Mean change approach−66 to 016 (3663)−21 (–28 to –16)14 (3464)−24 (–29 to –18), 71% Relative change, %  Mean change approach−292 to –187 (918)−83 (–292 to –18)7 (918)−34 (–49 to –19), 20% MCID minimum clinically important difference (mm or % reduction on a 100 mm scale), SCID substantial clinically important difference (mm or % reduction on a 100 mm scale), IQR inter-quartile range, NA not applicable aThe median is based on studies included in the pooled average as well as studies with unavailable standard errors bTotal number of patients in the included studies cI2 is the percentage of the variability in results that is due to heterogeneity rather than sampling error (chance); I2 of 0% to 40% might not be important, 30% to 60% may represent moderate heterogeneity, 50% to 90% may represent substantial heterogeneity, and 75% to 100% represents considerable heterogeneity </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>MCID in studies using the threshold approach </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Seven of the 37 included studies (2602 patients) determined clinically important differences as a threshold to differentiate between patients with or without relevant pain relief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Absolute thresholds ranged from 10 to 35 mm in six studies (2331 patients) with a median of 10 mm, and the relative threshold ranged from 15% to 50% in four studies (534 patients) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In one additional study [58], patients were defined as responders if they indicated at least a five-category improvement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The corresponding clinically important differences were thus higher (34 to 63 mm depending on baseline pain) than in studies where patients only needed a one- [41, 57], two- [49], or three-category improvement [25], respectively, to be defined as responders (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Impact of baseline pain scores on the MCID </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Eleven studies had assessed the possible influence of baseline pain on minimum clinically improvement (Appendix 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Of nine studies assessing absolute change, seven reported an association [31, 33, 36, 43, 58, 59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The two remaining studies found no association, but these were disregarded since they determined the MCID without differentiating between pain relief and pain worsening [21, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Six studies assessed the association between baseline pain and relative change and either found the association to be non-significant or found it to be weaker than for absolute change. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Based on meta-regression, we found no association between baseline pain and either absolute (20 studies, P = 0.70) nor relative (9 studies, P = 0.83) estimates of MCIDs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>However, based on individual patient data meta-analysis from seven studies (918 patients), we found a strong association between baseline pain and absolute MCID, showing that patients with higher baseline pain need larger pain reduction to reach a minimum clinically relevant difference compared to patients with lower baseline pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>For each 10 mm increase in baseline pain, MCID increased by 3.1 mm (95% confidence interval, 2.8–3.5 mm, P &lt; 0.001, I2 = 0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Thus, for patients with initial pain levels &lt; 40, 40–70, and &gt; 70 mm, the MCIDs were 6 (4–8) mm, 13 (11–14) mm, and 21 (20–23) mm, respectively (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The corresponding relative estimates of MCIDs did not differ significantly: 17 (4–30) %, 23 (20–25) %, and 24 (22–26) %, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In contrast, we found that patients with more severe pain perceived worsening of their status with smaller increases of pain intensity: the absolute MCID was 2.3 mm less for each 10 mm increase in baseline pain (1.4–3.0, P &lt; 0.001, I2 = 67%).Fig. 3Minimum clinically important difference by baseline pain (individual patient data from 7 studies, 918 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>MCID assessed as the mean change in pain score among patients with minimal improvement of pain, MCID = Minimal Clinically Important Difference (mm reduction on a 100 mm scale). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Forest plot of mean pain difference in 723 episodes where patients reported pain to be “a little better” in 7 studies including a total of 918 patients </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>From individual patient data, we also found that the MCID decreased with increasing time from baseline, from 17 (12 to 21) mm at 30 minutes to 11 (8 to 14) mm at 120 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>However, patients’ pain level declined accordingly during the multiple follow-ups and estimates expressed as a relative change from the previous assessment therefore did not decline. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Impact of other clinical and methodological factors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Other causes for variation in the MCID were addressed in 10 studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>These included sex [33, 35, 36, 44–48, 51, 54, 57, 59], age [33, 35, 36, 44–46, 48, 51, 54, 57, 59], education level [35, 48, 51, 54], ethnicity [54, 57], primary language (English or Spanish) [57], and religion [54], as well as cause (traumatic or non-traumatic) [44–48, 57], duration [35] and location [35] of pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>None of the studies found associations except for one [48], which reported higher MCIDs for men compared to women and for non-traumatic pain compared to traumatic pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>However, these analyses were not adjusted for differences in baseline pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The MCIDs of subgroups are presented as medians and pooled averages, respectively (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>For most clinical and methodological factors, the number of studies in each subgroup was too small to ensure detection of relevant differences between them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, although only few studies defined the MCID as the mean pain reduction among patients with several categories of improvement, or patients with ‘meaningful’ (and not just ‘minimum’) change, it was clear that these studies found higher MCIDs (medians 25 (IQR 23–29) and 34 (IQR 27–40), respectively) than studies where it was defined as the mean pain reduction among patients with a one-category improvement (median 16 (IQR 13–21)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>It was also clear that the MCID was higher when based on a single assessment involving one fixed baseline value (median 25 (IQR 23–29)), than when summarised from multiple assessments with the previous assessment applied as a ‘moving baseline’ (medians 15 (IQR 13–16) and 16 (IQR 10–21), respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Subgroups of studies among patients with various clinical conditions were underpowered to detect relevant differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The comparison of one- and two-sided transition scales was also underpowered, but the difference in scales did not seem to affect study results, while the comparison of VAS and NRS included enough studies to conclude that type of pain scale did not influence the MCID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Finally, we did not find differences in outcomes relating to the risk of attrition bias or risk of non-representative samples.Table 4Subgroup analyses of absolute minimum clinically important differences (MCIDs) for pain reliefSubgroupAnalysis of mediansAnalysis of pooled averageRange, mmNumber of studiesa (patientsb)MCID Median, mm (IQR)Number of studies (patientsb)MCID pooled average, mm (95% CI), I2 c All studies8–4029 (6517)17 (14–23)23 (6024)17 (15–19), 93%Clinical conditions Post-operation paind 9–297 (731)18 (10–25)3 (361)11 (8–14), 42% Trauma16–202 (125)18 (16–20)2 (125)18 (15–22), 11% Abdominal pain18–252 (407)21 (18–25)2 (407)21 (15–28), 91% Mixed patients at ED8–247 (2418)15 (11–21)6 (2345)16 (12–20), 90% Othere 10–405 (1980)27 (23–34)4 (1930)22 (15–29), 92% Unspecified13–216 (856)16 (14–16)6 (856)16 (14–18), 72%Definition of MCID One category improvement8–3424 (4504)16 (13–21)22 (4281)16 (14–18), 91% Several categories improvement23–293 (220)25 (23–29)NANA Meaningful change27–402 (1793)34 (27–40)1 (1743)27 (25–29), NADirectionality of transition scale One-sided9–405 (538)18 (13–21)3 (383)15 (8–21), 93% Two-sided8–2519 (3962)16 (13–20)18 (3844)16 (14–19), 91%Pain scale Visual Analogue Scale8–4017 (3232)17 (13–25)15 (3109)16 (13–19), 91% Numeric Rating Scale10–237 (1268)15 (14–21)6 (1118)16 (14–19), 91%Measurements per patient Single18–404 (461)25 (23–29)4 (2058)22 (19–25), 0% Multiple  With adjustment10–189 (1104)15 (13–16)8 (1031)15 (13–16), 34%  Without Adjustment/unclear8–2511 (2935)16 (10–21)11 (2935)16 (13–20), 95%Risk of attrition bias Low8–408 (1249)19 (15–25)8 (1249)16 (14–18), 81% High or unclear9–2516 (3251)16 (12–19)13 (2978)16 (13–19), 93%Risk of non-representative sampling Low8–256 (1187)16 (10–21)6 (1187)16 (11–21), 96% High or unclear9–4018 (3313)18 (14–24)15 (3040)16 (14–18), 87% IQR inter-quartile range, ED Emergency department, NA not applicable aThe median is based on studies included in the pooled average as well as studies with unavailable standard errors bTotal number of patients in studies cI2 is the percentage of the variability in results that is due to heterogeneity rather than sampling error (chance); I2 of 0% to 40% might not be important, 30% to 60% may represent moderate heterogeneity, 50% to 90% may represent substantial heterogeneity, and 75% to 100% represents considerable heterogeneity dIncludes knee surgery, laparotomy, third molar extraction and mixed surgery (e.g. spinal fusion and splenectomy) eIncludes headache, low back pain, sickle cell crisis, rheumatic condition, and pain flare after external beam radiotherapy for bone metastases </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Supplementary outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The supplementary outcomes for pain relief and worsening were only reported from studies using the mean change approach (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The results showed similarly high heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The substantial clinically important difference for pain relief ranged from 18 to 54 mm (23 studies), while minimum and substantial clinically important differences for worsening of pain ranged from 8 to 21 mm increase (18 studies) and from 0 to 66 mm increase (16 studies), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We included 37 studies (8479 patients) assessing the MCID in acute pain, of which 35 used the mean change approach and seven used the threshold approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Meta-analyses found considerable heterogeneity between studies and, consequently, no single value of minimum clinical important difference could be meaningfully determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Study results ranged widely both when they were reported as absolute change (from 8 to 40 mm) and as relative change from baseline (from 13 to 85%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The median of study results based on the mean change approach was 17 (IQR 14 to 23) mm and 23 (IQR 18 to 36) % for absolute and relative values, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Reasons for heterogeneity were explored and baseline pain was identified as a cause of variation in absolute, but not relative, outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In addition, the definition of minimum clinically important change and the use of multiple assessments per patient influenced study results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>High heterogeneity was also found for assessments of substantial clinically important difference as well as for worsening of pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Strengths and limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this is the first systematic review of MCIDs in acute pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>We identified 37 studies involving over 8000 patients and a broad range of clinical conditions, study approaches and pain scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We gained access to unpublished data from 10 studies, including individual patient data from seven studies (918 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>This ensured high data quality and uniform analysis, and enabled an adequate assessment of the association with baseline pain avoiding the risk of ecological fallacy [24] inherent to aggregated study-level data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The median results of studies providing individual patient data was comparable with the remaining studies and we have no reason to believe these studies were not representative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Association with baseline pain has been reported from individual studies [31, 33, 36, 43, 57–59], but the present review is the first comprehensive assessment of the impact of baseline pain across studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In addition, we identified variation in study designs (single or multiple assessments) and definitions of patients with minimum relief as factors influencing the MCID. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>However, we were not able to fully explain the large heterogeneity among studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We found no effects of pain scale, but for the comparison of clinical conditions and directionality of transition scale, subgroups involved too few studies to ensure detection of all relevant associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In addition, our ability to assess clinical condition was limited by the fact that many studies included a mixed patient group and we did not have access to individual patient diagnoses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the studies included a variety of analgesia and other treatments which did not allow an assessment of potential impact of interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Regarding the risk of attrition bias and non-representative sampling, the majority of studies were categorised as unclear and potential impact could therefore not be assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, acknowledging the association with baseline pain, it would have been more accurate to base subgroup analyses on relative outcomes, but the data available only allowed comparison of absolute outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>We could not assess impact of various description of pain (e.g. “intensity”) or the follow-up time between measurements since there was not enough variation between studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the available data did not allow an assessment of the potential influence of pre-existing pain level (e.g. if patients are affected by chronic pain in addition to their current episode of acute pain), pre-existing use of pain relief or the psychological state of patients, since this was not reported by any of the studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Finally, we cannot dismiss the risk of recall bias in studies where patients simultaneously assess their pain status and perceived change [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Differences in baseline pain or other methodological or clinical factors may influence subgroup analyses of study-level data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Thus, better access to individual patient data would greatly improve the chances of identifying causes of heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Other studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Only few systematic reviews of the minimum clinically relevant change have been published despite a vast number of primary studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Stauffer [20] and Erdogan [61] reviewed studies of minimum clinically relevant change in pain scales used for chronic rheumatologic conditions, but we have not identified any systematic reviews focusing on acute pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The problem of variability in results of studies of minimum clinically relevant change has previously been addressed primarily when attempting to reconcile dissimilar results from different approaches, e.g. anchor-based and distribution-based studies [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Our study demonstrates considerable unexplained variation also within anchor-based approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In line with our findings, Terwee [63] found variability between results of five studies of minimum clinically important change on the Western Ontario and McMaster University pain subscale for osteoarthritis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In a systematic review of the minimum clinical important difference in chronic pain, we have found similar issues of high study variability (manuscript in preparation). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Mechanisms and perspectives </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>We included studies with a patient-reported anchor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>While some find that using a patient-reported criterion as an anchor for a patient-reported score is circular and basically flawed [64], we would argue that pain intensity is essentially a subjective experience best expressed by and anchored to those experiencing it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Other observer-based anchors may be used when the outcome of interest is return to work or daily level of activity [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The varying content of the patient-reported anchors is, however, problematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The applied transition scales were either one- or two-sided, allowing patients to report their degree of change (or only relief) by choosing between anywhere from three to 15 response categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The majority of studies then determined the MCID as a mean change in pain score among everyone reporting a one-category pain relief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>However, this value does not apply to all individuals in the group, since their differences in pain are distributed around the mean [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MCIDs expressed as threshold values are derived with the intention of obtaining the best possible discrimination between patients with and without relevant relief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The frequency of false-positive and false-negative results may be reduced but is not eliminated by this approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Therefore, caution is always merited when bringing an overall estimate of important change to the level of interpretation for an individual patient [66, 67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The studies we included varied considerably both in methods and analytical approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>As would be expected, differences in the definition of patients with minimum important change impacted study results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>We also found that the use of multiple measurements per patient resulted in lower outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This corresponded with the finding that outcomes decreased during several follow-ups as patients’ pain declined over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, one in four of the reviewed studies did not differentiate between minimum relief and minimum worsening of pain in their original study reports. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The practice of combining groups with minimum change, regardless of its direction, is sometimes based on a seemingly similar distribution of data in the two groups [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>However, although they may be similar at one point, the MCID for pain relief and worsening will change in opposite directions with variations of baseline pain (since patients with higher baseline pain require larger pain reduction to perceive relief, but smaller increase to perceive worsening of their condition). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The association between MCID and baseline pain may to some extent be explained by ‘regression towards the mean’ as patients are likely to score closer to the mean if their initial scores were more extreme because of chance [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>However, it is also very plausible that patients with higher pain require greater decrease to perceive relief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Relative changes are therefore more stable indicators of clinically important differences, although they lack interval scale properties at the scale extremes, e.g. when baseline values are close to zero and small degrees of pain change result in very large relative changes [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>From this review, however, it is clear that the advantage of relative values is largely overlooked, since only 10 of 37 studies (27%) reported relative change. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>This review included studies that determined MCID from an anchor-based method using patients’ perception of change to determine clinical importance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Although this is the most common approach, it is just one among a wide range of alternative methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Revicki noted that retrospective self-reports of pain relief tend to correlate more strongly with the end-level of pain than the start level, implying that the current status matters to patients more than the degree of improvement [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This has led to the development of the concept of ‘patient acceptable symptom state’, defined as the level of symptoms which patients feel is acceptable [71, 72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Patient acceptable symptom state corresponds with the dominant aim of clinical patient care to reduce pain to an acceptable level [73] and could be a strong candidate for an alternative to MCID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Other promising approaches have integrated intervention costs and side effects [74–77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>It is likely that the challenges of MCID, apparent for acute pain, may not be isolated to that specific research area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Acute pain stands out because of the many studies that have been conducted, reflecting the status of acute pain as a core symptom in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Our study can thus be seen as a model for a more general challenge with empirical assessments of the MCID. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The methodological challenges embedded in the empirical assessment of MCID are of such an extent that merits caution for its use and interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>It is clearly inappropriate to use and interpret MCID as a kind of clinical scale constant – a characteristic which, once empirically determined, is universally valid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>This is, however, often the practice seen [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, there is a strong and reasonable demand for a structured approach for evaluating whether effects of interventions are clinically meaningful to patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Implications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The choice of a reference value has large consequences for the number of patients needed in a trial, e.g. four times as many patients will be included, if researchers accept a MCID value of 12 mm as compared to 24 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Further, the conclusion about the clinical relevance of a trial result is often based on whether a mean difference exceeds a chosen reference value, but with the large span of MCIDs available in the literature, it is highly problematic to randomly pick one or a few single assessments for guidance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The considerable variation means that it is necessary to conscientiously and explicitly reflect on the span of results in relation to context-specific clinical and methodological factors, as presented in this review, with a particular focus of the baseline pain of patients, whether repeated measurements were used, and how minimum relief was defined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>A starting point for such an exercise by individual clinicians or researchers, or by consensus building committees, could very well be our overview of studies and their results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In future studies there is a clear need for uniform guidelines for standardised conduct, analyses and reporting of the MCID, especially for how transition scales and questions are structured and how data are analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We strongly encourage using values relative to baseline pain – also for multiple measurements where the patient’s last assessment should be applied as a ‘moving baseline’, standardising the definition of relevant pain relief, and distinguishing clearly between improvement and worsening of pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In addition, since the influence of clinical and methodological factors is difficult to identify from aggregated data, we encourage improved access to individual patient data to enable further exploration of the causes of heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The MCID in acute pain varied greatly between studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Absolute MCID ranged from 8 to 40 mm in 29 studies, and relative values ranged from 13% to 85% in 14 studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Baseline pain was strongly associated with absolute, but not relative, values and variation in definitions of minimum relief and study designs influenced study results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Due to the heterogeneity between study results, no meaningful overall value of minimum clinically important change can be concluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Instead, we recommend that MCIDs are considered context-specific and take account of baseline pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The MCID in acute pain is central for the interpretation of results of randomised trials and meta-analyses and for determining appropriate sample sizes for new trials, but it is potentially misguiding if determined, applied or interpreted inappropriately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Explicit and conscientious reflections on the choice of a MCID value are required, when using it to classify research results as clinically important or trivial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec22"><title>Appendix 1</title><p>Search strategy</p><p>Last search conducted August 2016:</p><p>PubMed: (Minimal OR minimally OR minimum OR “clinically significant” OR “clinically important” OR “clinically meaningful” OR “clinically relevant” [Title/Abstract]) AND (Difference OR change OR relief OR reduction [Title/Abstract]) AND ((“Pain Measurement*” OR “Visual Analog Scale”[MeSH Terms]) OR (“numeric rating scale” [Title/abstract])) AND (Pain [MeSH Terms] AND pain [Title]) OR ((correlation AND change AND “visual analog scale” AND “pain relief”[Title]) OR (“minimum clinically significant change” AND pain) OR (“pain intensity ratings” AND “change scores”) OR (“pain assessment tools” AND “acute pain”) OR (“changes in pain intensity correlate with pain relief”) OR (“minimally important difference” AND “pain measurement”) OR (“Minimally important change” AND pain) OR (“minimum clinically important difference” AND pain) OR (“meaningful change” AND pain [title]) OR (“assessing change” AND pain [title]) OR (“minimum clinically important difference” AND “patient-reported outcome”) OR (“detect changes” AND “pain intensity”)).</p><p>
<italic>Filters: Humans</italic>
</p><p>EMBASE: ((Minimal or minimally or minimum or clinically significant or clinically important or clinically meaningful or clinically relevant).ti. or (Minimal or minimally or minimum or clinically significant or clinically important or clinically meaningful or clinically relevant).ab. or (Minimal or minimally or minimum or clinically significant or clinically important or clinically meaningful or clinically relevant).kw.) AND ((Difference or change or relief or reduction).ti. or (Difference or change or relief or reduction).ab. or (Difference or change or relief or reduction).kw.) AND ((exp pain assessment/) OR (exp visual analog scale/) OR (exp rating scale/)) AND exp pain/dm, dt, ep, th [Disease Management, Drug Therapy, Epidemiology, Therapy].</p><p>
<italic>Limit to human, Limit to exclude MEDLINE journals</italic>
</p><p>Cochrane Library: (Minimal OR minimally OR minimum OR “clinically significant” OR “clinically important” OR “clinically meaningful” OR “clinically relevant”:ti,ab,kw in Cochrane Reviews (Reviews and Protocols), Other Reviews, Trials and Methods Studies) AND (Difference OR change OR relief OR reduction:ti,ab,kw in Cochrane Reviews (Reviews and Protocols), Other Reviews, Trials and Methods Studies) AND (“Pain Measurement” OR “Visual Analog Scale” OR “numeric rating scale”:ti,ab,kw in Cochrane Reviews (Reviews and Protocols), Other Reviews, Trials and Methods Studies) AND (Pain:ti in Cochrane Reviews (Reviews and Protocols), Other Reviews, Trials and Methods Studies) (Word variations have been searched).</p></sec></app><app id="App2"><sec id="Sec23"><title>Appendix 2</title><p>Data extraction</p><p>Descriptive data</p><p>For each study we extracted the following data: Publication year, study design, setting, type of intervention, sample size, sex, age and clinical condition of patients, pain level at baseline, type of pain scale (VAS, NRS or other) and scale dimensions, type of anchor including wording of the transition question, concept (e.g. perception of pain relief, overall status or treatment effect), directionality (one- or two-sided), number of discriminating subcategories, wording of items used to obtain minimal clinically important difference, method of data collection including follow-up time, number of follow-up measurements per participant, whether analysis was adjusted for dependency between measurements and applied method, sampling method (e.g. consecutive, random or convenience), attrition rate, and information about any subgroup analysis that had been undertaken in the studies.</p><p>Outcome data</p><p>For studies assessing clinically important differences using the mean difference approach, we extracted the following outcomes as mean change scores with corresponding standard error or, if unavailable, other measures of variation such as standard deviation or 95% confidence interval:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The minimal clinically important difference for pain relief (mean absolute and relative change)</p></list-item><list-item><p>The substantial clinically important difference for pain relief (mean absolute and relative change)</p></list-item><list-item><p>The minimal clinically important difference for pain worsening (mean absolute and relative change)</p></list-item><list-item><p>The substantial clinically important difference for pain relief (mean absolute and relative change)</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>For studies assessing clinically important differences using the threshold approach, we extracted information about the definition of responders (patients with relevant pain relief) and non-responders and the cut-off point that differentiated between them with its corresponding sensitivity and specificity.</p></sec></app><app id="App3"><sec id="Sec24"><title>Appendix 3</title><p>
<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Relationship between baseline pain and the minimum clinically important differencea </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Study </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Subgroups by baseline pain, mm </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Absolute MCID mm (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Relative MCID % (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Studies assessing MCID stratified by baseline pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Stahmer [55] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>≤50&gt; 50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>NRNR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>25 (SE: 10)b 35 (SE: 6)b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Voepel-Lewis [59] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>&lt;50≥ 50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>0 (−30 to 20)20 (13 to 25) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>NRNR </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Bird [31] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>&lt;3434–66&gt; 66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>11 (7 to 15)17 (13 to 21)30 (17 to 43) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>NRNRNR </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Cepeda [33] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Moderate (median: 60)Severe (median: 80) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>13 (12 to 14)18 (17 to 19) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>20 (18 to 22)20 (19 to 22) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Tsze [57] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>&lt;4040–69≥ 70 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>NRNRNR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>13 (0 to 29)16 (10 to 23)18 (11 to 29) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Tubach [58] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Low (mean: 55)Intermediate (mean: 70)High (mean: 85) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>34 (29 to 38)c 45c 63 (54 to 68)c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>NRNRNR </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Studies assessing correlation between MCID and baseline pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Barton 2002 (reported in Jensen 2002 [43]) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Correlation with baseline pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>0.48 (P &lt; 0.001) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>0.35 (P &lt; 0.01) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Rasmussen 2002 (reported in Jensen 2002 [43]) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Correlation with baseline pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>0.52 (P &lt; 0.001) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>0.34 (P &lt; 0.01) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Farrar [36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Correlation with baseline pain </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Patients with higher baseline pain reported greater relief (e.g. 90 vs. 40 mm, P = 0.048) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>No significant differences in degree of pain relief </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Two additional studies are not included, since they did not differentiate between pain relief and worsening when assessing the relationship between baseline pain and MCID (Kelly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and Lopez [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>])</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>Patients answering ‘some’ or ‘partial’ relief</p><p>
<sup>c</sup>Data is 75th percentile among patients answering ‘a great deal better’ (13) or ‘a good deal better’ (14) on a 15 category scale</p><p>
<italic>MCID</italic> minimum clinically important difference, <italic>NR</italic> not reported, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag>
</p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AH</term><def><p>Asbjørn Hróbjartsson</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BT</term><def><p>Britta Tendal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EB</term><def><p>Eik Bjerre</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JH</term><def><p>Jørgen Hilden</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCID</term><def><p>Minimal clinically important differences</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDH</term><def><p>Maria Damkjær Hansen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MFO</term><def><p>Mette Frahm Olsen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NEL</term><def><p>Nino Emmanuel Landler</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NRS</term><def><p>Numerical rating scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAS</term><def><p>Visual analogue scale</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the following authors for sharing unpublished data with us: Individual patient data: Polly Bijur, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, NY; Anna Holdgate, Liverpool Hospital; Helen Mohan, UCD School of Medicine and Medical Science, Belfield, Dublin; and Yu Fai Choi, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, Hong Kong. Additional data: John Farrar, Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of Pennsylvania; Blake Bulloch, University of Arizona College of Medicine, Phoenix; Knox H Todd, University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center; and Terri Voepel-Lewis, Department of Anesthesiology, University of Michigan.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>The study was funded by the Nordic Cochrane Centre.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The dataset analysed during the current study is available from the corresponding author upon request. The review protocol has been submitted to <italic>BMC Medicine</italic> and can be obtained from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>AH, BT and MFO conceptualised the study. MFO, EB, MDH, NEL and BT contributed to the acquisition of data. Data was analysed by MFO with the assistance of JH. MFO, JH and AH contributed to the interpretation of results. MFO drafted the manuscript, all co-authors contributed to reviewing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>No ethics committee approval was needed for this systematic review.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>1.SinatraRSJahrJSReynoldsLGroudineSBRoyalMABreitmeyerJBIntravenous acetaminophen for pain after major orthopedic surgery: an expanded analysisPain Pract2012123576510.1111/j.1533-2500.2011.00514.x<?supplied-pmid 22008309?>22008309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>2.StocklerMVardyJPillaiAWarrDAcetaminophen (paracetamol) improves pain and well-being in people with advanced cancer already receiving a strong opioid regimen: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled cross-over trialJ Clin Oncol20042233899410.1200/JCO.2004.09.122<?supplied-pmid 15310785?>15310785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>3.DaltonJDSchweinleJERandomized controlled noninferiority trial to compare extended release acetaminophen and ibuprofen for the treatment of ankle sprainsAnn Emerg Med2006486152310.1016/j.annemergmed.2006.05.015<?supplied-pmid 17052565?>17052565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>4.FriedmanBWDymAADavittMHoldenLSolorzanoCEssesDNaproxen with cyclobenzaprine, oxycodone/acetaminophen, or placebo for treating acute low back pain: a randomized clinical trialJAMA201531415728010.1001/jama.2015.13043<?supplied-pmid 26501533?>26501533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>5.JonesPDalzielSRLamdinRMiles-ChanJLFramptonCOral non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs versus other oral analgesic agents for acute soft tissue injuryCochrane Database Syst Rev20157CD007789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>6.FarahmandSShiralizadehSTalebianM-TBagheri-HaririSArbabMBasirghafouriHNebulized fentanyl vs intravenous morphine for ED patients with acute limb pain: a randomized clinical trialAm J Emerg Med2014321011510.1016/j.ajem.2014.05.051<?supplied-pmid 25027194?>25027194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>7.ChauJKMSeikalyHRHarrisJRVilla-RoelCBrickCRoweBHCorticosteroids in peritonsillar abscess treatment: a blinded placebo-controlled clinical trialLaryngoscope20141249710310.1002/lary.24283<?supplied-pmid 23794382?>23794382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>8.SantamatoASolfrizziVPanzaFTondiGFrisardiVLegginBGShort-term effects of high-intensity laser therapy versus ultrasound therapy in the treatment of people with subacromial impingement syndrome: a randomized clinical trialPhys Ther2009896435210.2522/ptj.20080139<?supplied-pmid 19482902?>19482902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>9.LuedtkeKRushtonAWrightCGeissBJuergensTPMayATranscranial direct current stimulation for the reduction of clinical and experimentally induced pain: a systematic review and meta-analysisClin J Pain2012284526110.1097/AJP.0b013e31823853e3<?supplied-pmid 22569218?>22569218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>10.BiranVGourrierECimermanPWalter-NicoletEMitanchezDCarbajalRAnalgesic effects of EMLA cream and oral sucrose during venipuncture in preterm infantsPediatrics2011128e637010.1542/peds.2010-1287<?supplied-pmid 21669894?>21669894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>11.MadsenMVGøtzschePCHróbjartssonAAcupuncture treatment for pain: systematic review of randomised clinical trials with acupuncture, placebo acupuncture, and no acupuncture groupsBMJ2009338a311510.1136/bmj.a3115<?supplied-pmid 19174438?>19174438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>12.JaeschkeRSingerJGuyattGHMeasurement of health status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Ascertaining the minimal clinically important differenceControl Clin Trials1989104071510.1016/0197-2456(89)90005-6<?supplied-pmid 2691207?>2691207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>13.CrosbyRDKolotkinRLWilliamsGRDefining clinically meaningful change in health-related quality of lifeJ Clin Epidemiol20035639540710.1016/S0895-4356(03)00044-1<?supplied-pmid 12812812?>12812812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>14.DworkinRHTurkDCWyrwichKWBeatonDCleelandCSFarrarJTInterpreting the clinical importance of treatment outcomes in chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendationsJ Pain200891052110.1016/j.jpain.2007.09.005<?supplied-pmid 18055266?>18055266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>15.GlassmanSDCopayAGBervenSHPollyDWSubachBRCarreonLYDefining substantial clinical benefit following lumbar spine arthrodesisJ Bone Joint Surg Am20089018394710.2106/JBJS.G.01095<?supplied-pmid 18762642?>18762642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>16.OsteloRWJGDeyoRAStratfordPWaddellGCroftPVon KorffMInterpreting change scores for pain and functional status in low back pain: towards international consensus regarding minimal important changeSpine20083390410.1097/BRS.0b013e31815e3a10<?supplied-pmid 18165753?>18165753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>17.AuleleyG-RBenbouazzaKSpoorenbergACollantesEHajjaj-HassouniNvan der HeijdeDEvaluation of the smallest detectable difference in outcome or process variables in ankylosing spondylitisArthritis Rheum200247582710.1002/art.10798<?supplied-pmid 12522830?>12522830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>18.ChansirinukorWMaherCGLatimerJHushJComparison of the functional rating index and the 18-item Roland-Morris Disability Questionnaire: responsiveness and reliabilitySpine200530141510.1097/00007632-200501010-00023<?supplied-pmid 15626994?>15626994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>19.BlackNPatient reported outcome measures could help transform healthcareBMJ2013346f16710.1136/bmj.f167<?supplied-pmid 23358487?>23358487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>20.StaufferMETaylorSDWatsonDJPelosoPMMorrisonADefinition of nonresponse to analgesic treatment of arthritic pain: an analytical literature review of the smallest detectable difference, the minimal detectable change, and the minimal clinically important difference on the pain visual analog scaleInt J Inflamm2011201123192610.4061/2011/231926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>21.LopezBLFlendersPDavis-MoonLCorbinTBallasSKClinically significant differences in the visual analog pain scale in acute vasoocclusive sickle cell crisisHemoglobin2007314273210.1080/03630260701587810<?supplied-pmid 17994376?>17994376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>22.GuyattGHOsobaDWuAWWyrwichKWNormanGRClinical Significance Consensus Meeting GroupMethods to explain the clinical significance of health status measuresMayo Clin Proc2002773718310.4065/77.4.371<?supplied-pmid 11936935?>11936935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>23.DeyoRACentorRMAssessing the responsiveness of functional scales to clinical change: an analogy to diagnostic test performanceJ Chronic Dis19863989790610.1016/0021-9681(86)90038-X<?supplied-pmid 2947907?>2947907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>24.LambertPCSuttonAJAbramsKRJonesDRA comparison of summary patient-level covariates in meta-regression with individual patient data meta-analysisJ Clin Epidemiol200255869410.1016/S0895-4356(01)00414-0<?supplied-pmid 11781126?>11781126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>25.AicherBPeilHPeilBDienerH-CResponsiveness of efficacy endpoints in clinical trials with over the counter analgesics for headacheCephalalgia Int J Headache2012329536210.1177/0333102412452047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>26.BaileyBDaoustRDoyon-TrottierEDauphin-PierreSGravelJValidation and properties of the verbal numeric scale in children with acute painPain20101492162110.1016/j.pain.2009.12.008<?supplied-pmid 20188471?>20188471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>27.BernsteinSLBijurPEGallagherEJRelationship between intensity and relief in patients with acute severe painAm J Emerg Med200624162610.1016/j.ajem.2005.08.007<?supplied-pmid 16490644?>16490644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>28.BijurPELatimerCTGallagherEJValidation of a verbally administered numerical rating scale of acute pain for use in the emergency departmentAcad Emerg Med200310390210.1111/j.1553-2712.2003.tb01355.x<?supplied-pmid 12670856?>12670856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>29.BijurPEChangAKEssesDGallagherEJIdentifying the minimum clinically significant difference in acute pain in the elderlyAnn Emerg Med20105651752110.1016/j.annemergmed.2010.02.007<?supplied-pmid 20303199?>20303199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>30.BijurPEChangAKEssesDGallagherEJProblems with measurement of the minimum clinically significant difference in acute pain in eldersAcad Emerg Med201118135910.1111/j.1553-2712.2010.00988.x<?supplied-pmid 21314771?>21314771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>31.BirdSBDicksonEWClinically significant changes in pain along the visual analog scaleAnn Emerg Med2001386394310.1067/mem.2001.118012<?supplied-pmid 11719742?>11719742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>32.BullochBTenenbeinMAssessment of clinically significant changes in acute pain in childrenAcad Emerg Med2002919920210.1111/j.1553-2712.2002.tb00244.x<?supplied-pmid 11874775?>11874775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>33.CepedaMSAfricanoJMPoloRAlcalaRCarrDBWhat decline in pain intensity is meaningful to patients with acute pain?Pain2003105151710.1016/S0304-3959(03)00176-3<?supplied-pmid 14499431?>14499431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>34.ChowELingADavisLPanzarellaTDanjouxCPain flare following external beam radiotherapy and meaningful change in pain scores in the treatment of bone metastasesRadiother Oncol20057564910.1016/j.radonc.2004.12.016<?supplied-pmid 15878102?>15878102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>35.DegerliVKarciogluOLarkinGLKaradumanSKorkmazTTuncMAThe minimum clinically significant difference in acute nontraumatic thoracoabdominal pain in adult emergency department patients in TurkeyJ Emerg Med20121931716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>36.FarrarJTPolomanoRCBerlinJAStromBLA comparison of change in the 0-10 numeric rating scale to a pain relief scale and global medication performance scale in a short-term clinical trial of breakthrough pain intensityAnesthesiology201011214647210.1097/ALN.0b013e3181de0e6d<?supplied-pmid 20463579?>20463579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>37.FosnochtDEChapmanCRSwansonERDonaldsonGWCorrelation of change in visual analog scale with pain relief in the EDAm J Emerg Med20052355910.1016/j.ajem.2004.09.024<?supplied-pmid 15672339?>15672339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>38.GallagherEJLiebmanMBijurPEProspective validation of clinically important changes in pain severity measured on a visual analog scaleAnn Emerg Med200138633810.1067/mem.2001.118863<?supplied-pmid 11719741?>11719741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>39.GallagherEJBijurPELatimerCSilverWReliability and validity of a visual analog scale for acute abdominal pain in the EDAm J Emerg Med2002202879010.1053/ajem.2002.33778<?supplied-pmid 12098173?>12098173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>40.GriloRMTrevesRPreuxPMVergne-SallePBertinPClinically relevant VAS pain score change in patients with acute rheumatic conditionsJt Bone Spine Rev Rhum2007743586110.1016/j.jbspin.2006.06.019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>41.GrotleMBroxJIVøllestadNKConcurrent comparison of responsiveness in pain and functional status measurements used for patients with low back painSpine200429E49250110.1097/01.brs.0000143664.02702.0b<?supplied-pmid 15507789?>15507789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>42.HoldgateAAshaSCraigJThompsonJComparison of a verbal numeric rating scale with the visual analogue scale for the measurement of acute painEmerg Med (Fremantle)200315441610.1046/j.1442-2026.2003.00499.x14992058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>43.JensenMPChenCBruggerAMPostsurgical pain outcome assessmentPain200299101910.1016/S0304-3959(02)00063-5<?supplied-pmid 12237188?>12237188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>44.KellyAMDoes the clinically significant difference in visual analog scale pain scores vary with gender, age, or cause of pain?Acad Emerg Med1998510869010.1111/j.1553-2712.1998.tb02667.x<?supplied-pmid 9835471?>9835471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>45.KellyAMThe minimum clinically significant difference in visual analogue scale pain score does not differ with severity of painEmerg Med2001182057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>46.KellyAMSetting the benchmark for research in the management of acute pain in emergency departmentsEmerg Med200113576010.1046/j.1442-2026.2001.00179.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>47.Kendrick DB, Strout TD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>The minimum clinically significant difference in patient-assigned numeric scores for pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Am J Emerg Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>2005;23:828–32. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>48.MarkMAuTChoiYWongTThe minimum clinically significant difference in visual analogue scale pain score in a local emergency settingHong Kong J Emerg Med2009162336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>49.MartinWJAshton-JamesCSkorpilNHeymansMForouzanfarTWhat constitutes a clinically important pain reduction in patients after third molar surgery?Pain Res Manag2013183192210.1155/2013/742468<?supplied-pmid 23957018?>23957018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>50.McConahayTBrysonMBullochBClinically significant changes in acute pain in a pediatric ED using the Color Analog ScaleAm J Emerg Med2007257394210.1016/j.ajem.2006.12.010<?supplied-pmid 17870473?>17870473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="?"><plain>51.MohanHRyanJWhelanBWakaiAThe end of the line? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The Visual Analogue Scale and Verbal Numerical Rating Scale as pain assessment tools in the emergency departmentEmerg Med J201027372510.1136/emj.2007.048611<?supplied-pmid 20442167?>20442167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>52.MyrvikMPBrandowAMDrendelALYanKHoffmannRGPanepintoJAClinically meaningful measurement of pain in children with sickle cell diseasePediatr Blood Cancer20136016899510.1002/pbc.24624<?supplied-pmid 23776145?>23776145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>53.PowellCVKellyAMWilliamsADetermining the minimum clinically significant difference in visual analog pain score for childrenAnn Emerg Med200137283110.1067/mem.2001.111517<?supplied-pmid 11145767?>11145767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>54.SlomanRWrubleAWRosenGRomMDetermination of clinically meaningful levels of pain reduction in patients experiencing acute postoperative painPain Manag Nurs20067153810.1016/j.pmn.2006.09.001<?supplied-pmid 17145489?>17145489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>55.StahmerSAShoferFSMarinoAShepherdSAbbuhlSDo quantitative changes in pain intensity correlate with pain relief and satisfaction?Acad Emerg Med19985851710.1111/j.1553-2712.1998.tb02811.x<?supplied-pmid 9754496?>9754496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>56.ToddKHFunkJPThe minimum clinically important difference in physician-assigned visual analog pain scoresAcad Emerg Med19963142610.1111/j.1553-2712.1996.tb03402.x<?supplied-pmid 8808375?>8808375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>57.TszeDSHirschfeldGvon BaeyerCLBullochBDayanPSClinically significant differences in acute pain measured on self-report pain scales in childrenAcad Emerg Med2015224152210.1111/acem.12620<?supplied-pmid 25773461?>25773461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>58.TubachFDougadosMFalissardBBaronGLogeartIRavaudPFeeling good rather than feeling better matters more to patientsArthritis Rheum2006555263010.1002/art.22110<?supplied-pmid 16874795?>16874795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>59.Voepel-LewisTBurkeCNJeffreysNMalviyaSTaitARDo 0-10 numeric rating scores translate into clinically meaningful pain measures for children?Anesth Analg20111124152110.1213/ANE.0b013e318203f495<?supplied-pmid 21127278?>21127278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>60.GuyattGHTownsendMKellerJLSingerJShould study subjects see their previous responses: data from a randomized control trialJ Clin Epidemiol1989429132010.1016/0895-4356(89)90105-4<?supplied-pmid 2778469?>2778469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>61.Doganay ErdoganBLeungYYPohlCTennantAConaghanPGMinimal clinically important difference as applied in rheumatology: an OMERACT Rasch Working Group systematic review and critiqueJ Rheumatol20164319420210.3899/jrheum.141150<?supplied-pmid 26034156?>26034156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>62.WyrwichKWMetzSMKroenkeKTierneyWMBabuANWolinskyFDTriangulating patient and clinician perspectives on clinically important differences in health-related quality of life among patients with heart diseaseHealth Serv Res2007426 Pt 122577410.1111/j.1475-6773.2007.00733.x<?supplied-pmid 17995565?>17995565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>63.TerweeCBRoordaLDDekkerJBierma-ZeinstraSMPeatGJordanKPMind the MIC: large variation among populations and methodsJ Clin Epidemiol2010635243410.1016/j.jclinepi.2009.08.010<?supplied-pmid 19926446?>19926446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>64.GatchelRJMayerTGTesting minimal clinically important difference: consensus or conundrum?Spine J201010321710.1016/j.spinee.2009.10.015<?supplied-pmid 20362248?>20362248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>65.Glassman SD, Carreon L, Dimar JR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Outcome of lumbar arthrodesis in patients sixty-five years of age or older. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Surgical technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>J Bone Joint Surg Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>2010;92 Suppl 1 Pt 1:77–84. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>66.HagemanWJArrindellWAEstablishing clinically significant change: increment of precision and the distinction between individual and group level of analysisBehav Res Ther19993711699310.1016/S0005-7967(99)00032-7<?supplied-pmid 10596464?>10596464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>67.Beaton DE, Bombardier C, Katz JN, Wright JG, Wells G, Boers M, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Looking for important change/differences in studies of responsiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>OMERACT MCID Working Group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Outcome Measures in Rheumatology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Minimal Clinically Important Difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>J Rheumatol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>2001;28:400–5. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>68.CopayAGSubachBRGlassmanSDPollyDWJrSchulerTCUnderstanding the minimum clinically important difference: a review of concepts and methodsSpine J20077541610.1016/j.spinee.2007.01.008<?supplied-pmid 17448732?>17448732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>69.RouquetteABlanchinMSébilleVGuilleminFCôtéSMFalissardBThe minimal clinically important difference determined using item response theory models: an attempt to solve the issue of the association with baseline scoreJ Clin Epidemiol20146744334010.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.10.009<?supplied-pmid 24447591?>24447591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>70.RevickiDHaysRDCellaDSloanJRecommended methods for determining responsiveness and minimally important differences for patient-reported outcomesJ Clin Epidemiol200861102910.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.03.012<?supplied-pmid 18177782?>18177782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>71.MercadanteSAdileCTortaRVarettoAFulfaroFGiarratanoAMeaningful cut-off pain intensity for breakthrough pain changes in advanced cancer patientsCurr Med Res Opin20132993710.1185/03007995.2012.755120<?supplied-pmid 23198976?>23198976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>72.TubachFRavaudPBaronGFalissardBLogeartIBellamyNEvaluation of clinically relevant states in patient reported outcomes in knee and hip osteoarthritis: the patient acceptable symptom stateAnn Rheum Dis20056434710.1136/ard.2004.023028<?supplied-pmid 15130902?>15130902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>73.MooreRAStraubeSAldingtonDPain measures and cut-offs - “no worse than mild pain” as a simple, universal outcomeAnaesthesia2013684001210.1111/anae.12148<?supplied-pmid 23347230?>23347230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>74.FerreiraMLHerbertRDFerreiraPHLatimerJOsteloRWGrotleMThe smallest worthwhile effect of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and physiotherapy for chronic low back pain: a benefit-harm trade-off studyJ Clin Epidemiol201366139740410.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.02.018<?supplied-pmid 24021611?>24021611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>75.FerreiraMLFerreiraPHHerbertRDLatimerJPeople with low back pain typically need to feel “much better” to consider intervention worthwhile: an observational studyAust J Physiother200955123710.1016/S0004-9514(09)70042-X<?supplied-pmid 19463083?>19463083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>76.BarrettBSufficiently important difference: concepts, caveats, and challengesMed Decis Mak2013338697410.1177/0272989X13476764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>77.CarrageeEJThe rise and fall of the “minimum clinically important difference”Spine J201010283410.1016/j.spinee.2010.02.013<?supplied-pmid 20362245?>20362245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>78.Ruyssen-WitrandATubachFRavaudPSystematic review reveals heterogeneity in definition of a clinically relevant difference in painJ Clin Epidemiol2011644637010.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.06.008<?supplied-pmid 21109400?>21109400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
