<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5617383</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28977823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">18490</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.18490</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Priority Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Intraductal cisplatin treatment in a BRCA-associated breast cancer mouse model attenuates tumor development but leads to systemic tumors in aged female mice </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>Jolien S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Diest</surname><given-names>Paul J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Amersfoort</surname><given-names>Miranda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vlug</surname><given-names>Eva J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Xiaojuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>ter Hoeve</surname><given-names>Natalie D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosing</surname><given-names>Hilde</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beijnen</surname><given-names>Jos H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>Sameh A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>Alain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>Jos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van der Wall</surname><given-names>Elsken</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Derksen</surname><given-names>Patrick W.B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Pathology, University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Pharmacy and Pharmacology, Netherlands Cancer Institute, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Department of Pathobiology, Dutch Molecular Pathology Center, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A5"><sup>5</sup> Department of Pediatrics, Division of Molecular Genetics, University Medical Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A6"><sup>6</sup> Department of Molecular Pathology, Netherlands Cancer Institute, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A7"><sup>7</sup> Department of Medical Oncology, University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence to</italic></bold><italic>: Patrick W.B. Derksen,</italic><email>P.W.B.Derksen@umcutrecht.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>37</issue><fpage>60750</fpage><lpage>60763</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2017 de Groot et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> 3.0 (CC BY 3.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>BRCA deficiency predisposes to the development of invasive breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In BRCA mutation carriers this risk can increase up to 80%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Currently, bilateral prophylactic mastectomy and prophylactic bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy are the only preventive, albeit radical invasive strategies to prevent breast cancer in BRCA mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>An alternative non-invasive way to prevent BRCA1-associated breast cancer may be local prophylactic treatment via the nipple. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Using a non-invasive intraductal (ID) preclinical intervention strategy, we explored the use of combined cisplatin and poly (ADP)-ribose polymerase 1 (PARP1) inhibition to prevent the development of hereditary breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We show that ID cisplatin and PARP-inhibition can successfully ablate mammary epithelial cells, and this approach attenuated tumor onset in a mouse model of Brca1-associated breast cancer from 153 to 239 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Long-term carcinogenicity studies in 150 syngeneic wild-type mice demonstrated that tumor incidence was increased in the ID treated mammary glands by 6.3% due to systemic exposure to cisplatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Although this was only evident in aged mice (median age = 649 days), we conclude that ID cisplatin treatment only presents a safe and feasible local prevention option if systemic exposure to the chemotherapy used can be avoided. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>BRCA</kwd><kwd>intraductal</kwd><kwd>cisplatin</kwd><kwd>olaparib</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Breast cancer risk increases dramatically in women carrying mutations in a breast cancer susceptibility gene, most frequently BRCA1 or BRCA2 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Depending on the type of mutation and the presence of genetic modifiers, this risk can increase to more than 80% [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Mammary gland architecture is dynamic and changes during puberty, pregnancy, lactation and involution post partum and post menopause [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>At puberty, the mouse mammary ductal system starts growing from the nipple to fill up the mammary fat pad at the age of 3-12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The epithelial lining consists of luminal cells that produce milk, and myoepithelial cells that are responsible for contraction during lactation [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Different theories regarding the mammary stem cell exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>One model proposes the existence of basal stem cells with the property of generating both luminal and basal/myoepithelial lineages [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Another hypothesis is that luminal and basal/myoepithelial are generated by a committed lineage-restricted progenitor cell [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Although controversy still surrounds the field, current evidence points to a scenario whereby a luminal progenitor may be at the origin of basal-like BRCA-associated breast cancer [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Standard treatment of BRCA1-associated breast cancer does not differ from other types of breast cancer, although targeted approaches are emerging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, because BRCA-deficient cells are unable to correct stalled DNA replication forks via homologous repair, these cells are sensitive to platinum-based chemotherapeutics that arrest replication [11-15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, BRCA-deficient cells are more sensitive to poly (ADP)-ribose polymerase 1 (PARP1) inhibition, which is involved in base excision repair [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Clinical trials have already tested the efficacy of pharmacological inhibition of PARP with overall promising results [17-24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The only effective preventive options for BRCA mutation carriers are currently bilateral prophylactic mastectomy (PM) and prophylactic bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy (PBSO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>PM yields a risk reducing effect of more than 90-100% in healthy BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers [25-27] and PBSO decreases breast cancer risk in BRCA mutation carriers without prior breast cancer approximately by 50% [26, 28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>An alternative and less invasive preventive strategy option is the use of hormonal therapy as chemo prevention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of estrogen receptor function decreases breast cancer risk in healthy BRCA2 mutation carriers, but not in BRCA1 mutation carriers [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, cancer-related mortality in BRCA mutation carriers may be managed through intensive surveillance using mammography and MRI, or biomarkers in nipple fluid like methylation [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Efficiency of this approach however is limited because of high breast tissue density in young women and the aggressive, fast developing nature of BRCA-associated breast tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Annual MRI detects the majority of breast cancers at an early and favorable stage [32, 33], but a drawback of MRI is the higher rate of false-positive results leading to biopsies of non-diseased tissue and distress [34-37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>An alternative and attractive way to prevent breast cancer development in BRCA mutation carriers may be the local administration of ablative agents to the mammary ductal system via the nipple. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Preclinical studies in which chemotherapeutics were used intraductally (ID), such as pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD), 5-fluorouracil, carboplatin, methotrexate, and paclitaxel, show promising results [38-40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>ID chemotherapy was also explored in phase I trials in women with ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) and invasive breast cancer prior to mastectomy, where ID administration of PLD and cisplatin was well tolerated with mild adverse events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Moreover, pathological changes could be found in the treated ducts [40-42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Here, we explored the efficacy and safety of ID cisplatin treatment as an alternative prophylactic therapy in the prevention of BRCA1-associated breast cancer formation, in combination with PARP-inhibition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2_1"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Intraductal cisplatin reduces repopulating capacity of the mammary gland </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>To test the effect of ID administered platinum on ductal outgrowth, we injected post-breeder wild type mice (ranging in age between 12-30 weeks; primiparous; average litter size of 7; mean time post weaning of 42 days) twice with ID cisplatin in gland number 3, 4, and 5 on the right side and with control on the left side with a 4-week interval (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>One week after the second treatment, we isolated mouse mammary epithelial cells (MMECs) from the 3rd and 4th mammary glands that were injected into the cleared mammary fat pad of 3-week old syngeneic recipient mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin significantly lowered outgrowth after transplantation compared to control injection (p = 0.010; Figure 1B; 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Whole mount analysis showed ductal outgrowth in 17 of 18 (94.4%) transplantations of the control-treated mammary glands and in 11 of 19 transplantations in the cisplatin-treated glands (57.9%), of which 2 showed only rudimentary duct formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin treatment reduces epithelial viability and leads to an inhibition of mammary gland repopulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>A. Experimental set-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Post-breeder mice were subjected to 2 ID cisplatin treatments with a 4-week interval in the right-sided glands number 3, 4, and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The contralateral corresponding mammary glands served as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Next, MMECs were harvested and transplanted into syngeneic mice (upper part) or analyzed by FACS (lower part). B. and C. Cisplatin inhibits the mammary repopulating capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Depicted are representative samples of whole mount analyses, showing complete outgrowth after control treatment (B; left), rudimentary outgrowth (B; middle), or no outgrowth (B; right) after ID cisplatin treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Quantifications of the control (left pie chart) and ID cisplatin treated glands (right pie chart) are shown in (C). D. and E. ID cisplatin treatment leads to an overall reduction of MMECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Representative plots of the basal and luminal cell populations using FACS analysis after control (D; left dot plot), or ID cisplatin treatment (D; right dot plot). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Quantifications of basal and luminal MMECs are shown in (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Basal MMECs were defined as DAPI-;CD45-;Sca-;CD24+/low and luminal MMECs as DAPI-;CD45-;Sca-or+;CD24+/hi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Shown is an average of 9 mice per condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent SEM; * = p &lt; 0.05. F. Cisplatin-treated glands showed morphological changes matching apoptosis and an induction of cleaved caspase 3 expression in the epithelial lining of the mammary duct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Representative pictures of H&amp;E and cleaved caspase 3 stainings of mammary gland tissue slides after ID cisplatin treatment are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Scale bar is 100 μm, upper right pictures are blow-ups of caspase 3 positive cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Next, we performed FACS analysis, which indicated that ID administered cisplatin induced a significant and uniform reduction in the basal and luminal populations (p = 0.008 compared to control for luminal, and p &lt; 0.001 for basal population in n = 9 analyzed glands; Figure 1D; 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The effect of cisplatin appeared to specifically reduce the epithelial mammary cells, since the number of non-epithelial cells was not decreased proportionally after ID treatment (Figure 1D; upper left quadrant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Further, we observed that cisplatin-treated glands showed an induction of cleaved caspase 3 expression in the epithelial lining of the mammary duct (Figure 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We therefore conclude that ID cisplatin treatment reduces the repopulating capacity of the wild type mammary gland. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Intraductal cisplatin impairs lobulo-alveolar development </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>To assess the effect of treatment on pregnancy-associated lobulo-alveolar development, we analyzed mammary gland whole mounts after ID treatment of both non-pregnant and pregnant mice (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin reduced ductulo-lobular outgrowth in both non-pregnant and pregnant mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Representative whole mounts and corresponding H&amp;E and β-casein stainings are shown in Figure 2B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In all control mammary glands from both non-pregnant and pregnant mice, ductal outgrowth and alveolar differentiation was uniform and complete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin showed no effect in 13 glands of 23 non-pregnant mice (56.6%), partial effect in 5 (21.7%), subtotal in 4 (17.4%), and total effect in 1 (4.3%) (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In pregnant mice ID cisplatin did not lead to an inhibition of alveolar development in 12 of 21 mice (57.1%), while we observed a partial response in 2 (9.5%), subtotal in 4 (19.0%), and total response in 3 (14.3%) glands (Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In summary, ID cisplatin administration induced a significant reduction in ductal outgrowth (defined as (sub) total effect) in both non-pregnant and pregnant mice (p = 0.018 and 0.004, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Functional effect of ID cisplatin on the mammary gland and pregnancy-induced lobulo-alveolar development </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A. Experimental set-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Post-breeder mice were subjected to two ID cisplatin treatments with a 4-week interval in the right-sided glands number 3, 4, and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The contralateral corresponding mammary glands served as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Next, whole mounts were analyzed at day 17.5 of pregnancy or at a similar time point in non-pregnant mice. B. Representative pictures showing no effect in control (first column) or partial (second column), subtotal (third column), or total effect (fourth column) after ID cisplatin treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The top two rows show whole mount analyses, followed by H&amp;E stainings, and β-casein IHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Scale bar is 100 μm in lower magnifications and 50 μm in higher magnifications. C. ID cisplatin reduces ductal outgrowth in non-pregnant mice (n = 23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Quantifications of mammary ductal outgrowth after control (left chart) or ID cisplatin treatment (right chart). D. ID cisplatin reduces lobulo-alveolar development in pregnant mice (n = 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Quantifications of mammary ductal outgrowth after control (left chart) or ID cisplatin treatment (right chart). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Intraductal cisplatin and olaparib increase tumor-free latency in a mouse model of BRCA1-associated human breast cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>We next investigated the preventive effect of ID cisplatin in a mouse model for BRCA1-associated human breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Since tumors in a K14cre-driven variant of this model were highly sensitive to a combination of cisplatin and the PARP-inhibitor olaparib [14], we tested both prophylactic monotherapies and the combination of ID cisplatin and olaparib in the whey acidic protein (WAP)cre-driven tumor model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>We chose the WAPcre model for our studies because the overt induction of skin tumors in the K14cre models interferes with the analysis of mammary tumor formation [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Tumor latency and incidence in the WAPCre;Brca1F/F;Trp53F/F model are shown in Supplementary Figure S1 and PCR results of tumors in Supplemental Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Female virgin WAPcre;Brca1F/F;Trp53F/F mice were injected twice in glands 3 and 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Either all third and fourth glands were treated with control or all 4 treated glands were injected with cisplatin at the age of 12 and 16 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Prior, during and post ID cisplatin treatment, mice were daily injected intraperitoneally (IP) with control or olaparib and followed for tumor formation (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin monotherapy significantly increased the median tumor-free latency (T50) in ID injected glands from 153 days in control to 210 days in cisplatin treated mice (p &lt; 0.0001; Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>IP treatment using olaparib monotherapy also led to an increase in tumor-free latency (T50 = 203 versus 153 days; p &lt; 0.001; Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Moreover, using a combination therapy of ID cisplatin and IP olaparib, we observed an increase in T50 from 153 to 239 days (p &lt; 0.001; Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Dual therapy using ID cisplatin and olaparib led to a longer tumor-free latency compared to olaparib monotherapy (p = 0.004) but not compared to cisplatin monotherapy (p = 0.506). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Combined prophylactic cisplatin and olaparib treatment in a WAPCre;Brca1F/F;Trp53F/F sporadic mouse model leads to a later onset of breast tumor formation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A. Experimental set-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Virgin WAPCre;Brca1F/F;Trp53F/F were treated twice in glands number 3 and 4 with either control or cisplatin at the age of 12 and 16 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>During the ID treatments, mice were IP injected with control or olaparib on a daily basis from the age of 10 to 18 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In total 4 treatment groups were analyzed, i.e. control (n = 24), ID cisplatin monotherapy (n = 20), IP olaparib monotherapy (n = 29) and ID cisplatin combined with IP olaparib combination therapy (n = 27). B. Kaplan-Meier curves showing the tumor-free latency post treatment of mammary glands tumor in the treated (glands number 3 and 4; left graph) and untreated mammary glands (glands number 1, 2, and 5; right graph). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, similar effects were obtained when analyzing untreated mammary glands, i.e. glands number 1, 2 and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Here, the T50 increased significantly from 157 days in control to 225 days in cisplatin treated animals (p &lt; 0.0001; Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Olaparib induced an increase in T50 to 219 days (p &lt; 0.0001), and combination treatment led to T50 of 241 days (p &lt; 0.0001; Figure 3B), suggesting that local ID treatment results in systemic exposure and subsequent inhibition of tumor development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin reduced tumor incidence in the locally treated gland to 85.0% (p = 0.086 compared to control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>For olaparib this was 89.7% (p = 0.242), and in the combination group tumor incidence was 81.5% (p = 0.052). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Monotherapy with cisplatin ID did not significantly differ from olaparib monotherapy regarding tumor incidence (p = 0.677). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Also, a dual ID cisplatin and olaparib treatment was not significantly better than either monotherapies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Tumor incidence of the untreated glands decreased to 85.0% in cisplatin (p = 0.086), 75.9% in olaparib (p = 0.012), and 66.7% in the combination treatment group (p = 0.002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Metastases formation did not significantly change between different treatment groups (Supplementary Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In short, a combination of ID cisplatin with systemic olaparib increases tumor-free latency in a mouse model of Brca1-associated breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>However, ID injection leads to systemic exposure of cisplatin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Pharmacokinetics of intraductal cisplatin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>To determine the extent of systemic exposure to platinum after ID injection, we harvested plasma samples after ID treatment with cisplatin injection of the 3rd and 4th mammary glands of 12 week old wild type mice (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Highest plasma concentrations were measured 15 minutes after treatment with an average of 4.6 μg/ml (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>After 5 minutes, platinum was detected in plasma with a mean concentration of 1.0 μg/ml when injecting one mammary gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After 96 hours the AUC value was 45.6 μg•ml/h, comparable to a reported AUC of 47.9 μg•ml/h after intra-tumoral (IT) injection of a similar dose of cisplatin [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Pharmacokinetics of the ID cisplatin treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A. Experimental set-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Virgin wild type mice were treated with ID cisplatin in glands number 3 and 4 at the age of 12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Mice were sacrificed at different time points after ID injections (see text for details, n = 3 mice per time point) and plasma and mammary gland tissue samples were harvested. B. Plasma platinum concentrations after ID treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Shown are the average concentrations per time point with SEM. C. Mammary gland platinum concentrations after ID cisplatin treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The black line shows the concentrations in untreated glands (gland number 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The pink line depicts the concentrations in the treated mammary glands (gland number 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Shown are the average concentrations per time point with SEM; * = p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We also determined platinum tissue concentrations in locally treated and distant untreated mammary glands (4th and 2nd mammary glands, respectively, see Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Concentrations peaked at 15 minutes with a mean platinum concentration of 3.32 μg/ml in locally treated versus 0.99 μg/ml in the untreated glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Platinum concentrations in the untreated glands were significantly lower than in locally treated glands (p = 0.015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>After 96 hours the AUC value of locally treated glands was 18.75 μg•ml/h compared to 4.73 μg•ml/h in systemically treated glands, which is 25.2% of the locally exposed glands. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Long-term local and systemic effects of intraductal cisplatin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>To serve as an alternative prophylaxis in young BRCA-mutation carriers, long-term carcinogenicity of ID cisplatin must be minimal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To test this, we ID injected the 3rd and 4th mammary glands of post-pubertal wild type mice at the age of 12 and 16 weeks with either control (n = 67) or cisplatin (n = 86), which were followed longitudinally until death or disease (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Due to early death caused by mammary tumor formation in the mouse model carrying conditional homozygous Trp53 alleles we, used allogeneic wild-type mice for long-term carcinogenicity studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Although ID treatment of cisplatin induced a shorter tumor-free latency based on histopathology data, the reduction in latency was only observed in aged (&gt;560 days) mice (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Also, we observed an effect on overall survival when comparing treated versus control female mice (p = 0.019; Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Mammary tumors developed more often in the ID cisplatin treated mammary glands (21 of 336 locally treated glands (6.3%)) than in control mice (0 of 252 locally treated glands; p &lt; 0.001; Figure 5C and 5D), albeit in aged female mice (679 days after the second ID injection), which did not lead to an increase metastatic dissemination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Importantly, tumor incidence in distant untreated glands was increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Cisplatin treated mice developed breast tumors in untreated glands in 3.6% (18 of 504 glands) compared to 0.8% in control mice (3 of 378 glands; p = 0.007; Figure 5C and 5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Finally, primary adenocarcinomas of the lung were found in 48.9% in cisplatin versus 29.7% in control treated mice (p = 0.019; Figure 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The incidence of gynecological, lymphoproliferative and other tumors did not significantly differ between both treatment groups (p = 0.741, 0.493 and 0.692, respectively; Figure 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Benign pathology of the aged female mice is shown in Supplementary Table S2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Long-term effects of ID cisplatin treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A. Experimental-set up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Virgin F1 (FVB/N;Ola129Hsd) mice were treated twice in glands 3 and 4 with either cisplatin or control at the age of 12 and 16 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Next, mice were followed in time for tumor development. B. Kaplan-Meier curves showing overall survival of control (black line; n = 67) or ID cisplatin (pink line; n = 86) treated mice. C. Table showing the incidence of malignancies in control and ID cisplatin treated mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The category ‘other tumors’ consisted of sarcoma of unknown origin, hemangiosarcoma of the spleen, carcinoma of the oral cavity, and squamous carcinoma in the anogenital region in control mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In ID cisplatin treated mice ‘other tumors’ comprised hepatocellular carcinoma (n = 2), carcinoma of the salivary gland, and angiosarcoma in the mammary gland. D. Bar graph showing the breast tumor incidence in control and ID cisplatin treated mice per mammary gland. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Given the increase in both local and systemic tumor incidence in mice, we conclude that ID administration of cisplatin under these conditions cannot upfront be regarded as a safe alternative prophylactic therapy to prevent BRCA1-associated breast cancer formation in humans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>ID cisplatin treatment leads to a uniform reduction of the epithelial mammary cells and thereby prolongs breast tumor-free latency in a conditional BRCA1-associated mouse model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, our results also show that the success rate of ID treatment using cisplatin is variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Multiple functional assays, including whole mount and transplantation assays, resulted in a successful ablation in approximately half of the recipient mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This partial effect can be explained by e.g. incomplete injection penetrance, whereby not all ductal branches have been exposed to cisplatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the progenitor cell leading to cancer is presumably a low proliferating cell and as such less susceptible to platinum-based drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Another explanation could be the that proliferative differences due to estrus cycling may influence the effectiveness of cisplatin [45, 46], which suggests that ID treatment should be tailored to specific estrus stages for successful cisplatin-based prophylaxis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>To our surprise, ID cisplatin prolonged tumor-free latency in untreated mammary glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Since Brca1 inactivation and subsequent tumor formation in the WAPcre-driven model occurs during the first estrus cycle (independent of pregnancy-induced WAP activation) [43], we anticipate that this is probably due to the fact that prior to treatment, WAPcre;Brca1F/F;Trp53F/F female mice contain Brca1-deficient mammary epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Also, because Brca-/- mouse embryonic stem cell lines are 5-fold more sensitive to cisplatin than Brca+/+ wild type cells [11], it is likely that Brca1 loss underpins the observed sensitivity to cisplatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Although rapid systemic distribution of platinum drugs is evident after ID treatment (our data and [41]), we also showed that platinum levels in the circulation and untreated glands were lower than can be expected after systemic treatment [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>A study using intra tumor (IT) injection of cisplatin and found a comparable AUC to the value we found after ID injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Compared to IP injection, IT administration led to lower plasma concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Systemic exposure to platinum after IT injection was calculated to be 65-75% of the exposure after systemic administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Since IT and ID cisplatin administration showed a similar pharmacokinetic profile, we expect that also ID cisplatin will lead to lower systemic platinum levels compared to systemic treatment [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Our findings are in agreement with studies showing that ID treatment with other chemotherapeutics also leads to systemic exposure [39, 40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Long-term carcinogenicity is a major point of concern in prophylactic treatments using chemotherapeutics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The same cytotoxic agent can be used to treat cancer, but can also drive carcinogenesis [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>ID PLD is reported to induce malignant mammary gland tumors in wild type mice after a follow-up of 42 weeks [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>When MMECs were isolated from mice treated with ID PLD, recipients developed tumors [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Our current study shows that cisplatin leads to tumor formation in 6.3% of treated mammary glands more than 95 weeks post treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The induction of late tumors also affected overall survival after cisplatin treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The induction of secondary malignancies may be explained by platinum release from regenerating tissue leading to circulating plasma platinum levels up to 20 years after treatment [49, 50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Ovarian cancer survivors show an increased breast cancer risk, however the influence of chemotherapy was either not investigated or not convincingly shown [51, 52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Genetic and reproductive factors predisposing to ovarian cancer may also have contributed to breast cancer development [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In contrast to our findings in mice, it was shown that long-term testicular and ovarian cancer survivors have no increased lung cancer risk [51-53], and testicular cancer patients treated with chemotherapy only do not develop more lung tumors during follow-up [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Despite the obvious species differences in rodents and humans that may underlie the long-term tumor formation after intraductal cisplatin in our used preclinical models, we think that ID administration of solvable cisplatin cannot upfront be regarded as a safe alternative to prevent BRCA-associated breast cancer in genetic carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Possible alternative ways of delivering an immobilized yet locally active chemotherapy should be developed to prevent systemic exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Since intraductal PLD also induced mammary tumors, we feel that this precludes the use of ID chemotherapy in general for preventive purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Using local therapy intraductally however seems to be feasible and effective and could be combined with the use of nanocarriers [55], liposomes [56], or antidotes [57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Olaparib was already shown to be effective in breast cancer treatment [17-21, 23, 24], but now we also demonstrate the prophylactic effect of systemic PARP-inhibition in Brca1-associated breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Combining ID cisplatin and olaparib led to an additional effect in breast tumor incidence compared to both monotherapies without increasing toxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Future studies are needed to investigate the optimal dosages of combination treatment and the long-term safety of olaparib treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we demonstrate that although ID treatment using cisplatin, especially in combination with PARP-inhibition successfully attenuates tumor formation in a clinically relevant mouse model of BRCA1-associated breast cancer, it leads to long-term local and systemic secondary malignancies in mice and may not be safe in humans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4_1"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>F1 Wild type mice were derived from crossings between FVB/NCrl (Charles River) and 129P2/OlaHsd (Harlan). WAPcre;BrcaF/F;Trp53F/F mice were generated by crossing Brca1F/F conditional female mice [58] with male WAPcre;Trp53F/F mice [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Female mice in a model using WAPCre as a promoter, develop mammary tumors for which the onset, incidence and metastasis are pregnancy and lactation-independent [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Genotyping and deletion status of the Trp53F, Trp53Δ, Brca1F, Brca1Δ and WAPcre alleles was done as described [43, 58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Onset of tumor growth was monitored twice weekly from the age of 4 months onward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Mammary tumor volume was determined by caliper measurements using the following formula: 4/3*((3.14)*((length+width)/4)^3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Animals were euthanized if mammary tumors reached a size of 1000 mm3 or in case of severe discomfort otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Animals were scored as having a tumor when there was a tumor palpable or based on post mortem histological assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Tumor-free latency was calculated as the number of days after the second ID injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>All animal experiments were performed according to institutional guidelines and national regulations (DEC2010.III.08.102, 2011.III.04.050, 2012.III.01.005, 2012.III.09.086). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Cisplatin (1 mg/mL in saline, Pharmachemie B.V.) was administered ID in a total volume of 50 μl per mammary gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>To visualize extravasation or incorrect injection, cisplatin or control was mixed with 0.05% methylene blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Olaparib was synthesized by Syncom with a purity of more than 99% by HPLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Olaparib was used by diluting 50 mg/ml stocks in DMSO with 10% 2-hydroxyl-propyl-β-cyclodextrine/PBS such that the final volume administered intraperitoneally (IP) was 10 μL/g of body weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Saline 0.9% (Fresenius Kabi) was used as control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Intraductal injection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Mice were anesthetized by isoflurane and 100 μl (0.03 mg/ml) Temgesic (buprenorphine) was injected subcutaneously (SC) as analgesic treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Mammary ducts were cannulated using a 1.0-cm, 33G, blunt-ended needle (Hamilton, 66780305) attached to a 50 μl glass syringe (Hamilton 66765501). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Drugs or control were injected into the mammary gland while visualizing the nipple opening under a dissection microscope [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Orthotopic transplantation MMECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Primary mouse mammary epithelium cells (MMECs) were obtained from mammary glands after removal of the intra-mammary lymph nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Tissue was finely chopped three times using a McIlwain tissue chopper (The Mickle Laboratory Engineering Co.) and digested for 1 hr at 37°C in serum-free DMEM-F12 medium (Invitrogen Life Technologies) containing 0.1 mg/ml porcine pancreatic trypsin (Gibco) and 0.2 mg/ml collagenase A (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed and fibroblasts were allowed to adhere for 1 hr at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Non-adherent epithelial cells were collected, washed, pelleted in 40 μl serum-free DMEM-F12 and kept on ice until transplantation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>MMECs were transplanted in 3-week-old wild type syngeneic female recipient mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Recipient mice were anesthetized by isoflurane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Temgesic (buprenorphine; 100 μl (0.03 mg/ml)) was injected SC as analgesic treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The fourth (inguinal) mammary gland was exposed and endogenous mammary epithelial tissue was removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Next, MMECs were injected in the cleared fat pad using a 50 μl Hamilton syringe, after which the animals were sutured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Whole mount analysis was performed 8 weeks after transplantation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>FACS analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>After enzymatic digestion of the mammary tissue, cells were incubated with red blood cell lysis buffer (8.26 g NH4Cl, 1 g NaHCO3, 0.0378 g EDTA in 1 L dH20) to remove erythrocytes (15 minutes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed and fibroblasts were allowed to adhere for 1 hr at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Non-adherent epithelial cells were collected, washed in 0.02% EDTA-PBS solution, pelleted and resuspended in 0.25% w/v trypsin/0.2% w/v EDTA in PBS for incubation at 37°C for 2 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Cells were dissociated through a 70 μm cell strainer and resuspended in fresh RPMI/10% FCS for quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated with primary antibodies for 45 minutes on ice (FITC-conjugated anti-CD24 (clone M1/69, BD Biosciences, 0.5 μg/ml), PE-Cy5-conjugated anti-CD45 (clone 30-F11, BD Biosciences, 0.25 μg/ml), and PE-conjugated anti-Sca-1 (clone D7, 0.5 μg/ml; BD Biosciences, 0.5 μg/ml)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Before FACS analysis, cells were incubated with 0.01% 4’, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI) for 15 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Analyses were carried out on a BD FACSVantageSE DiVa (BD Biosciences) and gating was performed as described [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Flow Jo software version 10 was used for analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Whole mount analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Mammary glands were dissected and stretched on a glass slide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Glands were fixed in a mixture of methanol:1, 1, 1-trichloroethane:acetic acid (6:3:1) for 4 hours and stained overnight with carmine aluminium staining solution (2 g/l carmine, 5 g/l aluminium potassium sulphate dissolved in water). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>After stepwise dehydration in 70%, 95% and 100% ethanol, glands were cleared in xylene for 10 minutes and photographs were taken with a Zeiss Stemi 2000-C stereo microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We defined effect size as follows: total effect (0% outgrowth), subtotal (up to 25% outgrowth), partial (more than 25% outgrowth), and no effect (100% outgrowth). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Histological analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Tissues were isolated and fixed in 4% formaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Tissues were dehydrated, cut into 4 μm sections, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>For immunohistochemical stainings, fixed sections were rehydrated and incubated with primary antibodies against β-casein (Santa-Cruz SC-30042, FL-231, rabbit, 1:100) and cleaved caspase 3 (Cell Signaling 9661, rabbit, 1:500). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Endogenous peroxidases were blocked with 3% H2O2 and biotin-conjugated secondary antibodies were used, followed by incubation with HRP-conjugated streptavidin-biotin complex (DAKO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Substrate was developed with DAB (DAKO) and pictures were made using a Nikon Eclipse E800 with a Nikon digital camera DXM1200. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Appropriate positive and negative controls were used throughout. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Pharmacokinetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Mice were euthanized at 5 minutes, 15 minutes, 30 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 and 96 hour intervals after ID injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Blood was collected via cardiac puncture and tissue was isolated and frozen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Platinum concentrations were measured by a validated Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometry (ICPMS) method as described by Brouwers et al. [60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>For statistical analyses IBM SPSS Statistics Version 20 was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>For dichotomous variables Chi square tests were used; for continuous variables t-test (normal distribution), Mann Whitney test (no normal distribution, no paired data) or Wilcoxon signed rank test (no normal distribution, paired data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>For survival analysis Kaplan-Meier curves and Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) tests were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>A two-sided p-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS FIGURES AND TABLES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1059" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-60750-s002.docx" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1061" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Author contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>JSG, PJD, JHB, JJ, EW and PWBD conceived study design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>JSG, PJD, MA, EJV, XP, NDH, and HR carried out experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>JSG, PJD, HR, SAY, AB and PWBD analyzed data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>All authors were involved in writing the paper and had final approval of the submitted and published versions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>We would like to acknowledge S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Sukumar and Y.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Chun, Department of Oncology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD for help and advice. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>1NjiajuUOOlopadeOIGenetic determinants of breast cancer risk: a review of current literature and issues pertaining to clinical applicationBreast J2012184364222957996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>2CouchFJWangXMcGuffogLLeeAOlswoldCKuchenbaeckerKBSoucyPFredericksenZBarrowdaleDDennisJGaudetMMDicksEKoselMGenome-wide association study in BRCA1 mutation carriers identifies novel loci associated with breast and ovarian cancer riskPLoS Genet20139e100321223544013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>3GaudetMMKuchenbaeckerKBVijaiJKleinRJKirchhoffTMcGuffogLBarrowdaleDDunningAMLeeADennisJHealeySDicksESoucyPIdentification of a BRCA2-specific modifier locus at 6p24 related to breast cancer riskPLoS Genet20139e100317323544012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>4BuckleyNEMullanPBBRCA1--conductor of the breast stem cell orchestra: the role of BRCA1 in mammary gland development and identification of cell of origin of BRCA1 mutant breast cancerStem Cell Rev201289829322426855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>5VisvaderJEStinglJMammary stem cells and the differentiation hierarchy: current status and perspectivesGenes Dev20142811435824888586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>6RiosACFuNYLindemanGJVisvaderJEIn situ identification of bipotent stem cells in the mammary glandNature2014506322724463516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>7PraterMDPetitVRussellIAGiraddiRRShehataMMenonSSchulteRKalajzicIRathNOlsonMFMetzgerDFaraldoMMDeugnierMAMammary stem cells have myoepithelial cell propertiesNat Cell Biol20141617,942–50 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>8KeymeulenA VanRochaASOussetMBeckBBouvencourtGRockJSharmaNDekoninckSBlanpainCDistinct stem cells contribute to mammary gland development and maintenanceNature20114791899321983963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>9LimEVaillantFWuDForrestNCPalBHartAHAsselin-LabatMLGyorkiDEWardTPartanenAFeleppaFHuschtschaLIThorneHJAberrant luminal progenitors as the candidate target population for basal tumor development in BRCA1 mutation carriersNat Med2009159071319648928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>10MolyneuxGGeyerFCMagnayFAMcCarthyAKendrickHNatrajanRMackayAGrigoriadisATuttAAshworthAReis-FilhoJSSmalleyMJBRCA1 basal-like breast cancers originate from luminal epithelial progenitors and not from basal stem cellsCell Stem Cell201074031720804975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>11BhattacharyyaAEarUSKollerBHWeichselbaumRRBishopDKThe breast cancer susceptibility gene BRCA1 is required for subnuclear assembly of Rad51 and survival following treatment with the DNA cross-linking agent cisplatinJ Biol Chem20002752389990310843985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>12TassonePTagliaferriPPerricelliABlottaSQuaresimaBMartelliMLGoelABarbieriVCostanzoFBolandCRVenutaSBRCA1 expression modulates chemosensitivity of BRCA1-defective HCC1937 human breast cancer cellsBr J Cancer20038812859112698198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>13SgagiasMKWagnerKUHamikBStoegerSSpiekerRHuberLJChodoshLACowanKHBrca1-deficient murine mammary epithelial cells have increased sensitivity to CDDP and MMSCell Cycle200431451615492509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>14RottenbergSNygrenAOPajicMvan LeeuwenFWvan der HeijdenIvan de WeteringKLiuXde VisserKEGilhuijsKGvan TellingenOSchoutenJPJonkersJBorstPSelective induction of chemotherapy resistance of mammary tumors in a conditional mouse model for hereditary breast cancerProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2007104121172217626183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>15ByrskiTHuzarskiTDentRMarczykEJasiowkaMGronwaldJJakubowiczJCybulskiCWisniowskiRGodlewskiDLubinskiJNarodSAPathologic complete response to neoadjuvant cisplatin in BRCA1-positive breast cancer patientsBreast Cancer Res Treat2014147401525129345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>16FarmerHMcCabeNLordCJTuttANJohnsonDARichardsonTBSantarosaMDillonKJHicksonIKnightsCMartinNMJacksonSPSmithGCTargeting the DNA repair defect in BRCA mutant cells as a therapeutic strategyNature20054349172115829967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>17FongPCBossDSYapTATuttAWuPMergui-RoelvinkMMortimerPSwaislandHLauAO’ConnorMJAshworthACarmichaelJKayeSBInhibition of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase in tumors from BRCA mutation carriersN Engl J Med20093611233419553641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>18FongPCYapTABossDSCardenCPMergui-RoelvinkMGourleyCDeGreve JLubinskiJShanleySMessiouCA’HernRTuttAAshworthAPoly(ADP)-ribose polymerase inhibition: frequent durable responses in BRCA carrier ovarian cancer correlating with platinum-free intervalJ Clin Oncol2010282512920406929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>19AudehMWCarmichaelJPensonRTFriedlanderMPowellBBell-McGuinnKMScottCWeitzelJNOakninALomanNLuKSchmutzlerRKMatulonisUOral poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitor olaparib in patients with BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations and recurrent ovarian cancer: a proof-of-concept trialLancet20103762455120609468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>20TuttARobsonMGarberJEDomchekSMAudehMWWeitzelJNFriedlanderMArunBLomanNSchmutzlerRKWardleyAMitchellGEarlHOral poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitor olaparib in patients with BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations and advanced breast cancer: a proof-of-concept trialLancet20103762354420609467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>21GelmonKATischkowitzMMackayHSwenertonKRobidouxATonkinKHirteHHuntsmanDClemonsMGilksBYerushalmiRMacphersonECarmichaelJOlaparib in patients with recurrent high-grade serous or poorly differentiated ovarian carcinoma or triple-negative breast cancer: a phase 2, multicentre, open-label, non-randomised studyThe LancetOncology20111285261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>22ThoolenBMaronpotRRHaradaTNyskaARousseauxCNolteTMalarkeyDEKaufmannWKüttlerKDeschlUNakaeDGregsonRVinloveMPProliferative and nonproliferative lesions of the rat and mouse hepatobiliary systemToxicol Pathol2010385S81S10.1177/019262331038649921191096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>23KaufmanBShapira-FrommerRSchmutzlerRKAudehMWFriedlanderMBalmañaJMitchellGFriedGStemmerSMHubertARosengartenOSteinerMLomanNOlaparib monotherapy in patients with advanced cancer and a germline BRCA1/2 mutationJ Clin Oncol2015332445010.1200/JCO.2014.56.272825366685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>24DomchekSMAghajanianCShapira-FrommerRSchmutzlerRKAudehMWFriedlanderMBalmañaJMitchellGFriedGStemmerSMHubertARosengartenOLomanNEfficacy and safety of olaparib monotherapy in germline BRCA1/2 mutation carriers with advanced ovarian cancer and three or more lines of prior therapyGynecol Oncol201614019920310.1016/j.ygyno.2015.12.02026723501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>25RebbeckTRFriebelTLynchHTNeuhausenSLvan ’t VeerLGarberJEEvansGRNarodSAIsaacsCMatloffEDalyMBOlopadeOIWeberBLBilateral prophylactic mastectomy reduces breast cancer risk in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers: the PROSE Study GroupJ Clin Oncol20042210556214981104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>26DomchekSMFriebelTMSingerCFEvansDGLynchHTIsaacsCGarberJENeuhausenSLMatloffEEelesRPichertGt’veerL VanTungNAssociation of risk-reducing surgery in BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation carriers with cancer risk and mortalityJama20103049677520810374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>27KaasRVerhoefSWesselingJRookusMAOldenburgHSPeetersMJRutgersEJProphylactic mastectomy in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers: very low risk for subsequent breast cancerAnn Surg20102514889220134318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>28KauffNDSatagopanJMRobsonMEScheuerLHensleyMHudisCAEllisNABoydJBorgenPIBarakatRRNortonLCastielMNafaKRisk-reducing salpingo-oophorectomy in women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutationN Engl J Med200234616091512023992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>29RebbeckTRLynchHTNeuhausenSLNarodSAVeerLVGarberJEEvansGIsaacsCDalyMBMatloffEOlopadeOIWeberBLPreventionProphylactic oophorectomy in carriers of BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutationsN Engl J Med200234616162212023993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>30KingMCWieandSHaleKLeeMWalshTOwensKTaitJFordLDunnBKCostantinoJWickerhamLWolmarkNFisherBTamoxifen and breast cancer incidence among women with inherited mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2: National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP-P1) Breast Cancer Prevention TrialJama20012862251611710890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>31de GrootJSMoelansCBEliasSGJo FacklerMvan DomselaarRSuijkerbuijkKPMWitkampAJSukumarSvan DiestPJvan der WallEDNA promoter hypermethylation in nipple fluid: a potential tool for early breast cancer detectionOncotarget20167247789110.18632/oncotarget.835227028854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>32WarnerEHillKCauserPPlewesDJongRYaffeMFoulkesWDGhadirianPLynchHCouchFWongJWrightFSunPProspective study of breast cancer incidence in women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation under surveillance with and without magnetic resonance imagingJ Clin Oncol2011291664921444874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>33PassaperumaKWarnerECauserPAHillKAMessnerSWongJWJongRAWrightFCYaffeMJRamsayEABalasinghamSVerityLEisenALong-term results of screening with magnetic resonance imaging in women with BRCA mutationsBr J Cancer2012107243022588560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>34KriegeMBrekelmansCTBoetesCBesnardPEZonderlandHMObdeijnIMManoliuRAKokTPeterseHTilanus-LinthorstMMMullerSHMeijerSOosterwijkJCEfficacy of MRI and mammography for breast-cancer screening in women with a familial or genetic predispositionN Engl J Med20043514273715282350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>35WarnerEPlewesDBHillKACauserPAZubovitsJTJongRACutraraMRDeBoerGYaffeMJMessnerSJMeschinoWSPironCANarodSASurveillance of BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers with magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasound, mammography, and clinical breast examinationJama200429213172515367553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>36LeachMOBoggisCRDixonAKEastonDFEelesRAEvansDGGilbertFJGriebschIHoffRJKessarPLakhaniSRMossSMNerurkarAScreening with magnetic resonance imaging and mammography of a UK population at high familial risk of breast cancer: a prospective multicentre cohort study (MARIBS)Lancet200536517697815910949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>37KuhlCKSchradingSLeutnerCCMorakkabati-SpitzNWardelmannEFimmersRKuhnWSchildHHMammography, breast ultrasound, and magnetic resonance imaging for surveillance of women at high familial risk for breast cancerJ Clin Oncol20052384697616293877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>38OkugawaHYamamotoDUemuraYSakaidaNTananoATanakaKKamiyamaYEffect of perductal paclitaxel exposure on the development of MNU-induced mammary carcinoma in female S-D ratsBreast Cancer Res Treat200591293415868429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>39MurataSKominskySLValiMZhangZGarrett-MayerEKorzDHusoDBakerSDBarberJJaffeeEReillyRTSukumarSDuctal access for prevention and therapy of mammary tumorsCancer Res2006666384516423990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>40StearnsVMoriTJacobsLKKhouriNFGabrielsonEYoshidaTKominskySLHusoDLJeterSPowersPTarpinianKBrownRJLangeJRPreclinical and clinical evaluation of intraductally administered agents in early breast cancerSci Transl Med20113106ra108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>41LoveSMZhangWGordonEJRaoJYangHLiJZhangBWangXChenGZhangBA feasibility study of the intraductal administration of chemotherapyCancer Prev Res (Phila)2013651823169924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>42MahoneyMEGordonEJRaoJYJinYHyltonNLoveSMIntraductal therapy of ductal carcinoma in situ: a presurgery studyClin Breast Cancer201313280623664819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>43DerksenPWBraumullerTMvan der BurgEHornsveldMMesmanEWesselingJKrimpenfortPJonkersJMammary-specific inactivation of E-cadherin and p53 impairs functional gland development and leads to pleomorphic invasive lobular carcinoma in miceDis Model Mech201143475821282721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>44DeurlooMJKopWvan TellingenOBartelinkHBeggACIntratumoural administration of cisplatin in slow-release devices: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Pharmacokinetics and intratumoural distributionCancer Chemother Pharmacol199127347531998994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>45SchedinPMitrengaTKaeckMEstrous cycle regulation of mammary epithelial cell proliferation, differentiation, and death in the Sprague-Dawley rat: a model for investigating the role of estrous cycling in mammary carcinogenesisJ Mammary Gland Biol Neoplasia200052112511149574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>46HvidHThorupISjogrenIOleksiewiczMBJensenHEMammary gland proliferation in female rats: effects of the estrous cycle, pseudo-pregnancy and ageExp Toxicol Pathol2012643213220951558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>47BlagosklonnyMVCarcinogenesis, cancer therapy and chemopreventionCell Death Differ20051259260210.1038/sj.cdd.440161015818400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>48ChunYSYoshidaTMoriTHusoDLZhangZStearnsVPerkinsBJonesRJSukumarSIntraductally administered pegylated liposomal doxorubicin reduces mammary stem cell function in the mammary gland but in the long term, induces malignant tumorsBreast Cancer Res Treat2012135201822752247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>49GietemaJAMeinardiMTMesserschmidtJGelevertTAltFUgesDRSleijferDTCirculating plasma platinum more than 10 years after cisplatin treatment for testicular cancerLancet20003551075610744098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>50BrouwersEEHuitemaADBeijnenJHSchellensJHLong-term platinum retention after treatment with cisplatin and oxaliplatinBMC Clin Pharmacol20088718796166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>51BergfeldtKEinhornSRosendahlIHallPIncreased risk of second primary malignancies in patients with gynecological cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>A Swedish record-linkage studyActa Oncol19953477177576744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>52TravisLBCurtisREBoiceJDJrPlatzCEHankeyBFFraumeniJFJrSecond malignant neoplasms among long-term survivors of ovarian cancerCancer Res1996561564708603403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>53van den Belt-DuseboutAWde WitRGietemaJAHorenblasSLouwmanMWRibotJGHoekstraHJOuwensGMAlemanBMvan LeeuwenFETreatment-specific risks of second malignancies and cardiovascular disease in 5-year survivors of testicular cancerJ Clin Oncol2007254370817906202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>54FungCFossaSDMilanoMTOldenburgJTravisLBSolid tumors after chemotherapy or surgery for testicular nonseminoma: a population-based studyJ Clin Oncol20133138071424043737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>55HamelersIHStaffhorstRWVoortmanJde KruijffBReedijkJvan Bergen en Henegouwen PM, de Kroon AI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>High cytotoxicity of cisplatin nanocapsules in ovarian carcinoma cells depends on uptake by caveolae-mediated endocytosisClin Cancer Res20091512596819228729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>56CasagrandeNDePaoli MCelegatoMBorgheseCMongiatMColombattiAAldinucciDPreclinical evaluation of a new liposomal formulation of cisplatin, lipoplatin, to treat cisplatin-resistant cervical cancerGynecol Oncol20131317445224029417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>57DickeyDTWuYJMuldoonLLNeuweltEAProtection against cisplatin-induced toxicities by N-acetylcysteine and sodium thiosulfate as assessed at the molecular, cellular, and in vivo levelsJ Pharmacol Exp Ther20053141052815951398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>58LiuXHolstegeHvan der GuldenHTreur-MulderMZevenhovenJVeldsAKerkhovenRMvan VlietMHWesselsLFPeterseJLBernsAJonkersJSomatic loss of BRCA1 and p53 in mice induces mammary tumors with features of human BRCA1-mutated basal-like breast cancerProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200710412111617626182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>59SleemanKEKendrickHRobertsonDIsackeCMAshworthASmalleyMJDissociation of estrogen receptor expression and in vivo stem cell activity in the mammary glandJ Cell Biol2007176192617190790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>60BrouwersEETibbenMMRosingHHillebrandMJJoergerMSchellensJHBeijnenJHSensitive inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry assay for the determination of platinum originating from cisplatin, carboplatin, and oxaliplatin in human plasma ultrafiltrateJ Mass Spectrom20064111869416929560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
