<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Clin. Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research : CR</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0392-9078</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-9966</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5637056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-017-0611-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The α-melanocyte stimulating hormone/peroxisome proliferator activated receptor-γ pathway down-regulates proliferation in melanoma cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flori</surname><given-names>Enrica</given-names></name><address><email>enrica.flori@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>Eleonora</given-names></name><address><email>eleonora.rosati82@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cardinali</surname><given-names>Giorgia</given-names></name><address><email>giorgia.cardinali@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><address><email>daniela.kovacs@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bellei</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><address><email>barbara.bellei@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Picardo</surname><given-names>Mauro</given-names></name><address><email>mauro.picardo@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Maresca</surname><given-names>Vittoria</given-names></name><address><email>vittoria.maresca@ifo.gov.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414603.4</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Cutaneous Physiopathology and Integrated Center of Metabolomics Research, San Gallicano Dermatologic Institute (IRCCS), </institution></institution-wrap>Via Elio Chianesi 53, 00144 Rome, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>36</volume><elocation-id>142</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The α-Melanocyte Stimulating Hormone (αMSH)/Melanocortin-1 receptor (MC1R) interaction promotes melanogenesis through the cAMP/PKA pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The direct induction of this pathway by Forskolin (FSK) is also known to enhance melanocyte proliferation. αMSH acts as a mitogenic agent in melanocytes and its effect on proliferation of melanoma cells is less known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We previously identified the αMSH/Peroxisome Proliferator Activated Receptor (PPARγ) pathway as a new pathway on the B16-F10 mouse melanoma cell line. αMSH induced the translocation of PPARγ into the nucleus as an active transcription factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This effect was independent of the cAMP/PKA pathway and was mediated by the activation of the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway, a pathway which we have described to be triggered by the αMSH-dependent MC1R stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in the same study, preliminary experiments showed that mouse melanoma cells responded to αMSH by reducing proliferation and that PPARγ was involved in this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Due to its key role in the control of cell proliferation, PPARγ agonists are used in therapeutic models for different forms of cancer, including melanoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this study was: (a) to confirm the different proliferative behavior in response to αMSH in healthy and in melanoma condition; (b) to verify whether the cAMP/PKA pathway and the PLC/PPARγ pathway could exert an antagonistic function in the control of proliferation; (c) to deepen the knowledge of the molecular basis responsible for the down-proliferative response of melanoma cells after exposure to αMSH. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We employed B16-F10 cell line, a human melanoma cell line (Mel 13) and two primary cultures of human melanocytes (NHM 1 and NHM 2, respectively), all expressing a wild type MC1R and responding to the αMSH in terms of pigmentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We evaluated cell proliferation through: a) cell counting, b) cell cycle analysis c) protein expression of proliferation modulators (p27, p21, cyclin D1 and cyclin E). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The αMSH acted as a mitogenic agent in primary cultures of human melanocytes, whereas it determined a slow down of proliferation in melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>FSK, as an inducer of the cAMP/PKA pathway, reproduced the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in NHMs but it did not mimic the αMSH effect on proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, 3 M3-FBS (3 M3), as an inducer of PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway, reproduced the αMSH proliferative effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Further experiments, treating melanoma cell lines with αMSH in the presence/absence of GW9662, as an inhibitor of PPARγ, confirmed the key role of this transcription factor in decreasing cell proliferation in response to the hormone exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In both melanoma cell lines, αMSH determined the reduction of proliferation through the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway, employing PPARγ as an effector element. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These evidence could offer perspectives for new therapeutic approaches for melanoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13046-017-0611-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>αMSH</kwd><kwd>MC1R</kwd><kwd>PPARγ</kwd><kwd>cAMP/PKA pathway, Phosphatidylinositol signaling pathway</kwd><kwd>Proliferation</kwd><kwd>Cell cycle, melanocytes, Melanoma</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The Melanocortin-1 receptor (MC1R), expressed on the surface of melanocytes and melanoma cells, and its ligand, the α-Melanocyte Stimulating Hormone (αMSH), represent a key interaction in the control of melanogenesis [1–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>MC1R activation stimulates cAMP synthesis via G-protein, which in turn mediates the phosphorylation of the cAMP responsive element-binding protein (CREB) transcription factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In turn, CREB participates in the activation of Micropthalmia Transcription Factor (MITF), the crucial transcription factor for melanocyte differentiation and melanogenesis [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>We previously identified a new pathway between αMSH and Peroxisome Proliferator Activated Receptor (PPARγ) on B16-F10 mouse melanoma cell line [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the same work we demonstrated that αMSH induced the translocation of PPARγ into the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This effect was not reproduced by Forskolin (FSK) (a direct activator of the cAMP/PKA pathway by [8]) and was dependent on the activation of the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a preliminary experiment showed that the B10-F10 cell line responded to αMSH by reducing proliferation and that PPARγ was directly involved in this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>PPARγ is a transcription factor capable of promoting pleyotropic effects, including the control of proliferation [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In fact, many studies in cancer therapy employ pharmacological agonists of PPARγ with the aim of promoting a slow down of the cell cycle [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Only sporadic and very old studies have dealt with the capacity of activated MC1R to modulate proliferation in melanoma cells and melanocytes: transformed cells respond to αMSH by proliferating or down-regulating proliferation, according to the degree of pigmentation and the progression of the pathology [13, 14]; primary cultures of human melanocytes respond to αMSH with a hyper-proliferative behaviour [1, 3, 15–17] and some authors have defined αMSH as a mitogenic agent for melanocytes [1, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The mechanism promoting hyper-proliferation in melanocytes could be recognized in the cAMP/PKA pathway itself (the canonical pathway triggered by the activation of MC1R). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In fact, cAMP elevating agents, such as FSK, enhance the proliferation and melanogenesis of cultured human melanocytes [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Here we worked on B16-F10 murine melanoma, on Mel 13 human melanoma cell line and on primary human melanocytes NHM 1 and NHM 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>All human cell lines were set up in our laboratory starting from biopsy explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>All cell lines expressed a wild type MC1R and responded to αMSH in terms of pigmentation (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We aimed to confirm the different proliferative effects, in response to αMSH, in melanoma and in healthy condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Moreover we proposed to verify whether the cAMP/PKA pathway and the PLC/PPARγ pathway could exert an antagonistic function in the control of proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we aimed to deepen the knowledge of the mechanism responsible for the down-proliferative response of melanoma cells after exposure to αMSH, by analyzing cell proliferation and protein levels of p27, p21, cyclin D1 and E, as typical proliferation modulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Cyclin D1 and E and their associated cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs: CDK4 and CDK6 for cyclin D1; CDK2 for cyclin E) are central mediators in transition from G1 and S phase [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, p21 and p27 represents two G1-check point CDK inhibitors [23–25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Our previous study mainly underlined the existence of the αMSH/PPARγ pathway in association with the canonical cAMP/PKA, but only started to deal with its effects on proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it essentially employed the B16-F10 murine melanoma cell line [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The present study extended the analysis of the αMSH/PPARγ pathway to human cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The novelty of this work was to focus on the PLC/PPARγ and cAMP/PKA pathways on cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In summary, on cell lines expressing a wild type MC1R and responding to αMSH in terms of pigmentation, this study confirmed the hyper-proliferative effect of αMSH in primary cultures of melanocytes and the opposite effect in melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it associated an antagonistic function to the cAMP/PKA and the PLC/PPARγ pathways in the control of proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Finally, it highlighted that the reduction of proliferation, observed in melanoma cell lines exposed to αMSH, showed characteristics of cell cycle withdrawal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>A more in-depth analysis of these mechanisms could provide useful information for the development of innovative therapeutic strategies for melanoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Cell lines and treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>B16-F10 cell line is a classical melanoma cell line widely employed in pigmentation studies, because it expresses a wild type MC1R, with an intact transduction machinery, which is activated in response to receptor stimulation [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>B16-F10 mouse melanoma cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) supplemented with heat-inactivated 7% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and antibiotics (all products purchased by EuroClone, Milan, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The human Mel13-SM melanoma cell line (Mel 13) was isolated in our laboratory as previously reported [27], exclusively from excess parts of the biopsy collected for histological examination, without compromising the standard diagnostic procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Mel 13 derived from a skin metastasis removed from the leg of a 52-year-old male (pT3bN0M1, stage IV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Mel 13 cell line was grown in OptiMEM (Invitrogen Life Technologies Italia, Monza, Italy) medium containing 10% FBS and antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>All the experiments were performed at low cell culture passage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Two primary human melanocyte cultures, NHM 1 and NHM 2 respectively (NHMs), were set up in our laboratory from neonatal foreskin in accordance with a previously described procedure [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>NHMs were selectively grown in the defined medium M254 (Invitrogen Life Technologies Italia, Monza, Italy) and Human melanocyte growth supplements (HMGS) (Invitrogen Life Technologies Italia, Monza, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>NHMs were sub-cultured once a week and experiments carried out on cells between passages 2 to 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>B16-F10 cell cultures and human melanoma cells were plated and 24 h later were stimulated with chemicals in fresh medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Primary human melanocytes were plated and 24 h later were stimulated with chemicals in a fresh medium deprived of bovine pituitary extract (BPE) and phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The following doses of chemicals were employed: 10−7 M αMSH (Sigma-Aldrich Srl, Milan, Italy); 3 μM GW9662 (Sigma-Aldrich Srl, Milan, Italy) a potent and irreversible antagonist of PPARγ [29]; 15 μM 3 M3-FBS (3 M3) (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany), a PLC inducer [30]; 1 μM Forskolin (FSK) (Sigma- Sigma-Aldrich Srl, Milan, Italy), a cAMP-stimulating agent [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Ethical statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Institute Research Ethics Committee (IFO) approval was obtained to collect samples of human material for research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The Declaration of Helsinki Principles was followed, and patients gave written informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>For biopsies obtained from minors written consent was given by the parents or legal guardians. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and quantitative real-time RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated using the Aurum™ Total RNA Mini kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl, Milan, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Following DNAse I treatment, cDNA was synthesized using oligo-dT primers and using ImProm-II™ Reverse Transcriptase (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real time RT-PCR was performed in a total volume of 15 μl with SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl) and 200 nM concentration of each primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences were as follows: hMC1R sense: 5′-CCTGAAGACCTCACTAGG -3′ and antisense: 5′-CATCTTGTAGAGCCTGAG-3′; mMC1R sense: 5′-CAAGGAGGTGCTGCTGTG-3 and antisense: 5′-TAGACAAATGGAGATCAGGAAGG-3′, β-actin sense: 5′-GACAGGATGCAGAAGGAGATTACT -3′ and antisense 5′-TGATCCACATCTGCTGGAAGGT-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Reactions were carried out in triplicate using the Real-Time Detection System iQ5 (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl) supplied with iCycler IQ5 optical system software version 2.0 (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Melt curve analysis was performed to confirm the specificity of the amplified products. β-actin was used as an endogenous control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Cells grown on coverslips previously coated with 2% gelatin on 24-well plates were treated with 3 M3 (15 μM) for 1, 3 and 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>For immunolabelling with anti-PPARγ rabbit antibody (1:50 in PBS) (Cell Signalling Tecnology, New England Biolabs, UK) cells were fixed in methanol for 4 min. at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The primary antibody was visualized by using anti-rabbit IgG- Alexa Fluor 555 conjugated antibody (1:800 in PBS) (Cell Signaling, Tecnology, New England Biolabs, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were visualized with DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich Srl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence signals were analyzed by scanning cells in a series of sequential sections with an ApoTome System (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany); image analysis was performed by the Axiovision software (Zeiss) and 3D reconstruction of a selection of three central optical sections was shown in each image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Quantitative analysis of the extent of PPARγ/DAPI colocalization was determined using Axiovision colocalization module (Zeiss) analyzing 100 cells for each condition randomly taken from 10 different microscopic fields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as fold increase of colocalization signals with respect to the values obtained in untreated cells and are reported as mean values ± SD (%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Three distinct experiments were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For immunolabelling with anti-MC1R (N-19) goat antibody (1:50 in PBS) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, INC) cells were fixed in PFA 4% for 15 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The primary antibody was visualized using anti-goat IgG-Alexa Fluor 488 conjugated antibody (1:800 in PBS) (ThermoFisher Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were visualized with DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich Srl). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Cells were lysed in denaturing conditions supplemented with a protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The protein concentration of extracts was estimated with Bradford reagent (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl, Milan, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Equal amounts of proteins were then separated on acrylammide SDS-PAGE, transferred onto nitrocellulose (Amersham Biosciences, Milan, Italy) and then treated overnight at 4 °C with: anti-tyrosinase antibody, anti-cyclin E antibody (1:1000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA); anti-p27 antibody, anti-p21 antibody, anti-cyclin D1 antibody (all 1:1000; Cell Signalling Technology, New England Biolabs, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse (1:3000; Cell Signalling Technology) or anti-rabbit IgG (1:8000; Cell Signalling Technology) were used as secondary antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Antibody complexes were visualized using the an enhanced chemiluminescence reagent (ECL) (Amersham Biosciences, Milan, Italy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A subsequent hybridization with anti-GAPDH or anti-HSP70 (both 1:5000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA) was used to estimate the equal protein loading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Densitometric analysis was performed using a GS-800 Calibrated Image Densitometer (Bio-Rad Laboratories Srl, Milan, Italy) or with UVITEC Imaging System (Cambridge, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Cell number analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Cells were plated in a 12 well plate at a density of 1 X 104 cells/well and were grown overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Cells were treated with 10−7 M αMSH, 3 μM GW9662, 15 μM 3 M3 and 1 μM FSK at different time points, in accordance with the experimental design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Cell number was determined by cell counting using a phase contrast microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>None of the employed doses of chemicals determined positivity to the Trypan blue exclusion assay test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The results presented are the average of three experiments in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometric analysis of cell cycle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Cells were harvested by treatment with 0.25% trypsin, fixed with ice-cold 70% ethanol solution, and stained in PBS containing propidium iodide (100 μg/ml) and RNase A (90 μg/ml) overnight at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The DNA content of the cells was measured by FACScalibur flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A total number of 104 cells for each sample were acquired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometric histograms were analyzed by defining borders between pre-G1, G1, S and G2 + M phase populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Cell Quest Software was used to analyze data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Transfection and luciferase assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Cells were transfected with pGL3-(Jwt) 3TKLuc reporter construct [31] using specific Amaxa® Nucleofector kits (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>24 h after treatment with 10−7 M αMSH or 15 μM 3 M3, cells were harvested in 100 μl lysis buffer and 20 μl of the extract were assayed for luciferase activity using Promega’s Dual Luciferase (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The renilla luciferase plasmid was also transfected as an internal control for monitoring transfection efficiency and for normalizing the firefly luciferase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The luciferase activity was expressed as fold of the activity obtained in cells treated with the different molecules divided by luciferase activity from non-stimulated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The pGL3-(Jwt)3TKLuc reporter construct is described elsewhere [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The results represent the average of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as means ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The Student’s t-test was used to analyze differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Values of p &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>αMSH reduced melanoma cell proliferation while it exerted a mitogenic effect in primary human melanocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>We investigated the capacity of αMSH to modulate proliferation in primary human melanocytes NHM 1 and NHM 2, in B16-F10 murine melanoma cell line and in the Mel 13 human melanoma cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>All these cell lines were characterized by the genetic nature of MC1R, expressing a wild type MC1R and responding to αMSH in terms of pigmentation (see Additional file 1 and Additional file 2: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The duplication time of primary cultures of human melanocytes is significantly longer with respect to that of B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell line (30/40 h vs 18/24 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Thus, we planned to perform evaluations at suitable times to highlight variations in treated samples in comparison with untreated ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The exposure to 10−7 M αMSH for 3 and 6 days, significantly increased the cell number in both NHMs (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, 48 h hrs of treatment with the hormone significantly decreased the proportion of cells distributed in the G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle (Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Instead, αMSH was unable to act as a mitogenic agent either in B16-F10 or Mel 13 cell lines, and it even reduced the cell number. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>This effect was already significant after 24 h of treatment (Fig. 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In compliance with these results, 24 h of treatment with αMSH determined a significant increase in the proportion of cells which were distributed in the G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle (Fig. 1d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In order to corroborate the αMSH effect on proliferation slow down, we evaluated the expression levels of G1 phase related proteins (p27, p21, cyclin D1 and E), in response to the hormone exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In preliminary experiments, expression levels of p27, p21, cyclin D1 and E, after exposure to αMSH, or alternative stimuli (see below), were followed at 4, 6, 12, 24, 36 and 48 h (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Here, and in the subsequent experiments (also see following paragraphs), we reported data associated with times of maximal proteins modulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In both melanoma cell lines, the expression level of the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p27 already resulted significantly up-regulated after 4 h of treatment with αMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The same treatment determined a significant induction of the expression level of the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p21 after 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Consistently, αMSH exposure significantly down-regulated the expression of both cyclin D1 and E after 6 h (Fig. 1e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Thus, these results indicate that αMSH exerted a mitogenic effect in primary human melanocytes while it reduced melanoma cell proliferation.Fig. 1αMSH acts as a mitogenic agent in NHMs, whereas it determined a slow down of proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. a Analysis of cell number performed on NHM 1 and NHM 2, after treatment with 10−7 M αMSH for 72 h and 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison to the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). b Cell-cycle distribution was evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on NHM 1 and NHM 2, after treatment for 48 h with 10−7 M αMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). c Analysis of cell number performed on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment with 10−7 M αMSH for 24 and 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison to the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells). d Cell-cycle distribution evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment for 24 h with 10−7 M αMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). e Western blot analysis of p27 (4 h), p21 (48 h), cyclin D1 and cyclin E (6 h) protein expression on cell lysate of B16-F10 and Mel 13, treated with 10−7 M αMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>GAPDH or HSP70 were used as an equal loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Representative blots are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Densitometric scanning of band intensities was performed to quantify the change of protein expression (control value taken as one fold in each case). * p &lt; 0,01 (vs untreated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Analysis of cAMP/PKA pathway in the control of NHMs and melanoma cell line proliferation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The cAMP/PKA pathway is the pathway through which the MC1R is universally known to promote melanin synthesis [2, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>FSK, as a cAMP elevating agent, mimics the effects of αMSH on melanogenesis [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, FSK is employed in defined cell culture media to promote the proliferation of melanocytes [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Here, we verified whether FSK was able to mimic the effects induced by αMSH on proliferation in NHMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In both NHMs, the treatment for 3 and 6 days with 1 μM FSK promoted a significant increase in cell number, similar to that produced by αMSH in the same experimental conditions (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In compliance with these results, the exposure to FSK promoted a significant decrease in the proportion of cells distributed in the G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle (Fig. 2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Thus, these results indicate that the αMSH-dependent mechanism was able to promote hyper-proliferation in NHMs can be recognized in the cAMP/PKA pathway.Fig. 2The direct induction of the cAMP/PKA pathway by Forskolin mimics the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in NHMs but it does not reproduce the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. a Analysis of cell number performed on NHM 1 and NHM 2, after treatment with 10−7 M αMSH or 1 μM FSK for 72 h and 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison to the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). b Cell-cycle distribution evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on NHM 1 and NHM 2, after treatment for 48 h with 10−7 M αMSH or 1 μM FSK . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells). c Analysis of cell number performed on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment with 10−7 M αMSH or 1 μM FSK for 24 and 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison with the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells). d Cell-cycle distribution evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment for 24 h with 10−7 M αMSH or 1 μM FSK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). e Western blot analysis of Cyclin D1 protein expression on cell lysate of B16-F10 and Mel 13, treated with FSK for 1, 2, 4 and 6 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>HSP70 was used as an equal loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Representative blots are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Densitometric scanning of band intensities was performed to quantify the change of protein expression (control value taken as one fold in each case). * p &lt; 0,01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In our previous study on B16-F10, in a preliminary experiment of cell counting, we demonstrated that αMSH induce a slow down of proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This effect was mediated by the αMSH/PPARγ pathway, a pathway independent of the cAMP/PKA canonical pathway [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Here, we proposed to exclude the involvement of the cAMP/PKA pathway in mediating the proliferation slow down induced by αMSH in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Both in B16-F10 and Mel 13, the treatment for 24 an 48 h with 1 μM FSK caused an increase in cell number, producing an opposite effect in comparison to that promoted by αMSH (Fig. 2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The analysis of cell cycle phase distribution, after 24 h of treatment with FSK, corroborated these results (Fig. 2d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a Western blot analysis of cyclin D1 showed a rapid induction of this key regulator of cell cycle progression (Fig. 2e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These results, confirmed our initial hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In fact, they excluded the involvement of the cAMP/PKA pathway in mediating the αMSH-mediated slow down of proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The direct induction of the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway by 3 M3 mimics the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In an attempt to find an alternative pathway which could justify the proliferation slow down induced by αMSH in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines, our attention focused on the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>PPARγ is a tumour suppressor gene [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Here we show that the treatment with αMSH promoted a significant induction of PPARγ transcriptional activity after 24 h of exposure, in B16-F10, Mel 13 and NHMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this effect was consistently higher in melanoma cell lines compared to NHMs (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The αMSH/PPARγ connection is mediated by the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In turn, this pathway can be directly activated by 3 M3 [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Thus, we tried to understand whether the treatment with 3 M3 was able to mimic the down-proliferation induced by αMSH in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cells.Fig. 3Analysis of PPARγ transcriptional activity in response to αMSH exposure in B16-F10, Mel 13 and NHMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Cells were transfected with pGL3-(Jwt)3TKLuc reporter construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>After 24 h of transfection, cells were treated with 10−7 M αMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The measurement of luciferase activity was carried out 30 min, 1, 3 and 6 h after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The variability of transfection was normalized with renilla luciferase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The results were expressed as fold change with respect to untreated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate, *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Preliminary checks: first, we verified the capacity of 3 M3 to promote: (a) calcium fluxes (Additional file 3: Figure S2), (b) PPARγ translocation into the nucleus (Fig. 4a–c) and (c) PPARγ transcriptional activity by luciferase assay (Fig. 4d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(a) Concerning the analysis of calcium fluxes, the cells previously loaded with fluo-3-AM, responded to 3 M3 treatment with an increased intra-cytoplasmic calcium, which was significant at all time points evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This increase consisted in an initial response, which reached a peak after 2 min, followed by a subsequent decline to plateau value after 10 min (Additional file 3: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>(b) We also evaluated the PPARγ nuclear translocation in response to 3 M3 at different time points: 1, 3 and 6 h, by immunofluorescence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We observed a positive signal for PPARγ in both cytoplasm and nucleus, in untreated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>We observed an increase of PPARγ nuclear staining in cells exposed to 3 M3, demonstrating a translocation of this transcription factor from the cytoplasm to the nucleus (Fig. 4a,b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This observation was also confirmed by the analysis of the extent of PPARγ/DAPI colocalization signals in the nucleus (Fig. 4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>(c) Luciferase assay, using the pGL3-(Jwt)3TKLuc reporter construct [31], consistently showed a significant induction of the PPARγ transcriptional activity after 24 h of 3 M3 treatment (Fig. 4d).Fig. 4Analysis of PPARγ translocation into the nucleus and activity in response to 3 M3 exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>(a, b, c) Immunofluorescence analysis of PPARγ localization in untreated cells (A-C, G-I) and in cells treated with 15 μM 3 M3 for 3 h (D-F, J-L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Immunolabeling with anti-PPARγ antibody and nuclear staining with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 20 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>(c) Quantitative analysis of the PPARγ/DAPI colocalization signal in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Results are express as fold increase of colocalization signal with respect to the values obtained in untreated cells and are reported as mean value ± SD (%) (*p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>(d) Transcriptional activity of PPARγ (fold change) by luciferase activity assay in B16-F10 and Mel 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Cells were transfected with pGL3-(Jwt)3TKLuc reporter construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>After 24 h of transfection, cells were treated with 15 μM 3 M3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The measurement of luciferase activity was carried out 24 h after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The variability of transfection was normalized with β-Gal activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The results were expressed as fold change with respect to untreated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Then, we tried to understand whether the treatment with 3 M3 was able to reproduce the effects of αMSH on cell number and proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The exposure to 3 M3 for 24 and 48 h determined a significant decrease of cell number in both melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This decrease was fully comparable to that promoted by αMSH (Fig. 5a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the exposure to 3 M3 for 24 h, promoted a significant increase in the proportion of cells distributed in the G0/G1 phase of cell cycle (Fig. 5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The expression level of p27 was already significantly induced after 4 h of treatment with 3 M3, in both melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The same treatment determined a significant up-regulation of p21 protein expression after 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Consistently, 3 M3 exposure significantly down-regulated the levels of both cyclin D1 and cyclin E after 6 h (Fig. 5c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Thus, the direct induction of the pathway by 3 M3 is able to reproduce the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines.Fig. 5The direct induction of the pathway by 3 M3 mimics the αMSH mediated effect on proliferation in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. a Analysis of cell number performed on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment with 15 μM 3 m3 for 24 and 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison with the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells). b Cell-cycle distribution evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment for 24 h with 15 μM 3 m3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). c Western blot analysis of p27 (4 h), p21 (48 h), cyclin D1 and cyclin E (6 h) protein expression on cell lysate of B16-F10 and Mel 13, treated with 15 μM 3 m3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>GAPDH or HSP70 were used as an equal loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Representative blots are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Densitometric scanning of band intensities was performed to quantify the change of protein expression (control value taken as one fold in each case). * p &lt; 0,01 (vs untreated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The PPARγ acts as an effector element in determining the reduction of cell number induced by the activation of PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In order to strengthen the role of PPARγ in mediating the reduction in the number of cells induced by the stimulation of “PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway”, both B16-F10 cells and Mel 13 human melanoma cells were stimulated with 3 M3, for 24 and 48 h, in the presence or absence of GW9662, as an inhibitor of PPARγ [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This pattern of stimulation was compared to that represented by cells treated with αMSH, in the presence or absence of GW9662. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In both cell lines, the exposure of cells to 3 M3 or αMSH led to a significant decrease of number of cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Whereas, the same treatments, in the presence of GW9662, significantly hindered the effectiveness of 3 M3 or αMSH in reducing the cell number after 24 h of treatment (Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Consistently with these results, the exposure of B16-F10 and Mel 13 for 24 h to 3 M3 or αMSH, was able to promote a significant increase in the proportion of cells distributed in the G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle and the co-treatment with GW9962 counteracted the effects of both the agents (Fig. 6b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the inhibition of PPARγ by GW9662 reverted the effects on cell cycle modulators (p27, p21, Cyclin D1 and cyclin E) promoted by αMSH in both melanoma cell lines (Fig. 6c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>All together, these results underline the key role of PPARγ in mediating the αMSH dependent effect on proliferation slow down.Fig. 6The PPARγ acts as an effector element in determining the reduction of cell number induced by the activation of PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines. a Analysis of cell number performed on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment for 24 and 48 h with 15 μM 3 m3 or 10−7 M αMSH in the presence or absence of 3 μM GW9662. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In the combined treatment αMSH/GW9662 or 3 m3/GW9662, cells underwent a pre-treatment with GW9662 for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Cell number was expressed as a percent variation in comparison to the value of untreated control cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.001 (vs untreated cells); $ p &lt; 0.01 (vs 3 m3-treated cells); § p &lt; 0.01 (vs αMSH-treated cells). b Cell-cycle distribution evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on B16-F10 and Mel 13, after treatment for 24 h with 15 μM 3 m3 or 10−7 M αMSH in the presence or absence of 3 μM GW9662. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>In the combined treatment αMSH/GW9662 or 3 M3/GW9662, cells underwent a pre-treatment with GW9662 for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The bar graph shows the distribution of cells among the different phases of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Data are mean values ± SD of three independent experiments performed in duplicate. *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells); $ p &lt; 0.01 (vs 3 m3-treated cells); § p &lt; 0.01 (vs αMSH-treated cells). c Western blot analysis of p27 (4 h), p21 (48 h), cyclin D1 and cyclin E (6 h) protein expression on cell lysate of B16-F10 and Mel 13, treated with 10−7 M αMSH in the presence or absence of 3 μM GW9662. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In the combined treatment αMSH/GW9662, cells underwent a pre-treatment with GW9662 for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>GAPDH or HSP70 were used as an equal loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Representative blots are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Densitometric scanning of band intensities was performed to quantify the change of protein expression (control value taken as one fold in each case). * p &lt; 0,01 (vs untreated cells), $ p &lt; 0,01 (vs αMSH-treated cells) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>MC1R is primarily located on the surface of melanocytes and plays an important role in the control of normal pigmentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>However, as a member of “G protein-coupled receptors” family, MC1R exerts a role in the control of proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Studies on this topic are sporadic ad provide evidence that the activated receptor appears to be influenced by the physiological state and/or transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>This study tried to confirm the different proliferative behavior, in response to MSH, in healthy and then in melanoma condition and to deepen the knowledge of the molecular basis responsible for the down-proliferative response of melanoma cells after exposure to αMSH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The first series of experiments evidenced that while in primary cultures of human melanocytes the αMSH acted as a mitogenic agent [1, 3], in Mel 13 human melanoma cell line and in the B16-F10 murine melanoma cell line, this hormone did not exert the same effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In the case of melanocyte cultures, the hyper-proliferation in response to αMSH stimulus can be found in literature [1, 3, 15–17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>This kind of response contravenes one of the axioms of cell biology, which associates the differentiation process with a decrease in proliferation rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This proliferative reduction is usually considered necessary, in order to store energy, which can be employed to accomplish differentiation itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Whereas, in the case of melanocytes, the hyper-proliferative response to the hormone may be interpreted as a necessity for melanocytes to increase their number, to produce more melanin and better protect the skin from ultraviolet radiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, melanoma cells have a basal sustained rate of proliferation, and our results highlight the ability of αMSH to trigger a mechanism capable of counteracting this biological feature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>In fact, the slow down of proliferation that we previously described in B16-F10 [7], was confirmed on the Mel 13 human melanoma cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Thus, the effect promoted by αMSH on proliferation seems to be associated with the pathological state and not with the animal species which the culture derives from. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In order to find the pathway driving the αMSH mediated effects on proliferation in our cell lines, we treated cells with FSK, which is able to by-pass the MC1R receptor and to stimulate the overall cAMP/PKA cell potential [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that in our cell lines FKS determined uniquely a hyper-proliferative response, both in NHMs and in melanoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>This result, which requires in depth study, may be ascribed to a CREB mediated mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>In fact, this transcription factor, one of the major PKA substrates, binds to the promoter of cell cycle regulators, such as cyclin D1, activating their transcription [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the comparison between the response of melanocytes and transformed cells to FSK showed a quantitative rather than a qualitative difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The hyper-proliferative response to FSK appeared more marked in primary cultures of melanocytes than in the transformed condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In fact, PKA is active in basal conditions and supported the rate of basal proliferation, in melanoma cells [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Therefore PKA activity cannot be further enhanced by additional stimulation, such as that due to FSK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>To define an alternative pathway which could justify the proliferation slow down induced by αMSH in B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines, our attention focused on the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This lipid involving pathway was in fact promoted in response to αMSH exposure in B16-F10 and was directly involved in the PPARγ activation [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>When the PPARγ transcription factor is activated with lipid ligands or pharmacological activators, it promotes differentiation, anti-inflammatory effects and a slow down in the rate of cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>For this reasons it is considered a good candidate in the creation of possible innovative biological anticancer therapies [11, 12, 34–36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>First, we verified that the direct stimulation of PLC was able to promote PPARγ translocation into the nucleus as an active transcription factor, on B16-F10 and Mel 13 cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Then we found that the direct induction of the PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway was able to reproduce the αMSH mediated effects on proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Subsequent experiments, carried out by stimulating the cells with 3 M3 (or αMSH), after inhibition of PPARγ with GW9662, led to similar results in the two conditions, thereby highlighting the role of PPARγ as an effector element (triggered by the active PI(4,5)P2/PLC pathway) capable of mediating the phenomenon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>For what concerns the molecular nature of the proliferation slow down consequent to the activation of the αMSH/PPARγ connection, we showed that it is due to cell cycle withdrawal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Cell cycle progression is coordinated by the expression and activity of key regulators, such as cyclin dependent kinase (CDKs) and cyclins, including cyclin D, cyclin E [21, 22] and CDKs-inhibitors, like p21 and p27 [24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Our analyses showed that the G0/G1 arrest, mediated by the αMSH/PPARγ axis, is associated with an up-regulation of p21 and p27 and down-modulation of cyclin D1 and cyclin E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with previous reports, employing natural and synthetic PPARγ agonists [34, 37–39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>p27 and p21 are transcriptional repressors of the same genes and associate with the same multi-protein complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>It has recently been demonstrated that p27 and p21 collaborate in a sequential manner in gene repression during G1 phase [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The peaks of expression of p27 and p21, which we have observed at different times (4 h for p27 and 48 h for p21), could reflect their sequential function over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>This work dealt with the analysis of the αMSH/MC1R interaction for its ability to influence proliferation in healthy melanocytes and in melanoma cells, an aspect that has already been investigated in the past in preliminary and sporadic studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>This study attributes an opposite functional significance to the cAMP/PKA pathway and to the PLC/PPARγ axis, respectively, in the control of proliferation, giving the former a role in stimulating hyper-proliferation and the latter a function in promoting down-proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>This evidence attributes a dynamic role to the activated MC1R which is able to transducer effects on proliferation through these pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The αMSH dependent cAMP/PKA pathway activation favors hyper-proliferation and ensures the promotion of melanogenesis, in healthy melanocytes, which are poorly represented within the skin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>In melanoma cells, in which the cAMP/PKA pathway is already active and correlates with their basal rate of proliferation, the PLC-PPARγ pathway emerged with particular emphasis, showing it exerts an opposite effect on proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The PLC/PPARγ connection has both an anti-inflammatory and anti-cancer potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>In fact, acting as a transcription factor, PPARγ, is capable of enhancing both these activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>In summary, these results provide information on the biology of MC1R and the ability of this receptor to control extra-pigmentary functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The PLC/PPARγ axis, inside the MC1R transduction machinery, could represent an element which potentially offers new therapeutic approaches for melanoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Additional files </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec19"><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1:Supplementary Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 11 kb) Additional file 2: Figure S1.Expression and functionality of MC1R in NHMs, B16-F10 and Mel 13 melanoma cell lines (a) Expression of MC1R mRNA evaluated by quantitative real-time RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Values are normalized against the expression of β-actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The values reported represent means ± SD of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>(b) Immunofluorescence analysis of MC1-R in NHM 1, NHM 2, B16-F10 and Mel 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Nuclear staining with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 20 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>(c) Western blot analysis of tyrosinase protein expression on cell lysate of NHM1 and NHM2 primary cultures of human melanocytes, B16-F10 and Mel 13, treated with 10−7 M αMSH for 72 h in NHM 1 and NHM 2, for 24 h in B16-F10 cells and for 48 h in Mel 13, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>GAPDH was used as an equal loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Results refer to three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Representative blots are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Densitometric scanning of band intensities was performed to quantify the change of protein expression (control value taken as one fold in each case). *p &lt; 0.01 (vs untreated cells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>(PDF 9380 kb) Additional file 3: Figure S2.Analysis of 3 M3 mediated calcium fluxes in (a) B16-F10 cells and (b) Mel 13 The profile of the intra-cytoplasm calcium fluxes in response to stimulation with 15 μM 3 M3 was obtained using a fluorimetric detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The analysis was followed for 30 min by monitoring calcium fluxes each minute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The calcium fluxes promoted by 3 M3 were significantly higher (p &lt; 0.01) than the baseline of untreated cells (100%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Results represent the mean ± SD of six experiments performed in exaplicate and are expressed as the percentage of fluo-3 fluorescence with respect to untreated cells (100%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>(PDF 525 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>FSK</term><def><p id="Par5">Forskolin</p><p id="Par6">MC1R, Melanocortin-1 Receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPARγ</term><def><p id="Par7">Peroxisome Proliferator Activated receptor-gamma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS-PAGE</term><def><p id="Par8">Sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>αMSH</term><def><p id="Par9">alpha Melanocyte Stimulating Hormone</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13046-017-0611-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The pGL3-(Jwt)3TKLuc reporter construct was kindly provided by Dr. R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Ballotti and Dr. S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Rocchi (Université de Nice Sophia Antipolis, INSERM U895, Biologie et Pathologie des Cellules Mélanocytaires: de la Pigmentation Cutanée au Mélanome, Nice, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>We thank Miss Alexia Cazan for the language revision. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par39"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by public funds from the Italian Ministry of Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar1"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par38"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Human melanoma cell lines and primary cultures of human melanocytes were set up by the researchers involved in the study and were available to the research team for the development of the experiments reported in the text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>They are still available to the research team for further analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the raw data generated in this study are available to the research team. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>EF: designed the study, performed in vitro experiments and critically interpreted the results. ER: performed in vitro experiments and analyzed the results. GC: performed experiments and investigations in immunofluorescence<bold>.</bold> Moreover, she critically interpreted the results. DK: performed the original isolation of the human melanoma line used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and contributed to its maintenance in culture. Moreover, she critically interpreted the results. BB: performed the original isolation of the human melanoma line used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and contributed to its maintenance in culture. She also carried out the evaluation for the presence of any polymorphisms of MC1R in primary cultures of human melanocytes and melanoma cell lines employed. Moreover, she critically interpreted the results. MP: designed the study and critically interpreted the results. VM: designed the study, performed in vitro experiments, critically interpreted the results and wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par40">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par41">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>1.Abdel-MalekZSwopeVBSuzukiIAkcaliCHarrigerMDBoyceSTMitogenic and melanogenic stimulation of normal human melanocytes by melanotropic peptidesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1995921789179310.1073/pnas.92.5.1789<?supplied-pmid 7878059?>7878059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>2.García-BorrónJCAbdel-MalekZJiménez-CervantesCMC1R, the cAMP pathway, and the response to solar UV: extending the horizonbeyond pigmentationPigment Cell Melanoma Res.20142769972010.1111/pcmr.12257<?supplied-pmid 24807163?>24807163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>3.Swope VB, Abdel-Malek ZA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Significance of the Melanocortin 1 and Endothelin B receptors in melanocyte homeostasis and prevention of sun-induced Genotoxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Front Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>2016; doi: 10.3389/fgene.2016.00146. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>4.Wolf Horrell EM, Boulanger MC, D'Orazio JA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Melanocortin 1 receptor: structure, function, and regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Front Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>2016; doi: 10.3389/fgene.2016.00095. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>5.BuscàRBallottiRCyclicAMPA key messenger in the regulation of skin pigmentationPigment Cell Res200013606910.1034/j.1600-0749.2000.130203.x<?supplied-pmid 10841026?>10841026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>6.CheliYOhannaMBallottiRBertolottoCFifteen-year quest for microphthalmia-associated transcription factor target genesPigment Cell Melanoma Res201023274010.1111/j.1755-148X.2009.00653.x<?supplied-pmid 19995375?>19995375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>7.MarescaVFloriECameraEBelleiBAspiteNLudoviciMLinking αMSH with PPARγ in B16-F10 melanomaPigment Cell Melanoma Res.20132611312710.1111/j.1755-148X.2012.01042.x<?supplied-pmid 22863076?>22863076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>8.BertolottoCBilleKOrtonneJPBallottiRRegulation of tyrosinase gene expression by cAMP in B16 melanoma cells involves two CATGTG motifs surrounding the TATA box: implication of the microphthalmia gene productJ Cell Biol199613474775510.1083/jcb.134.3.747<?supplied-pmid 8707852?>8707852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>9.Derosa G, Sahebkar A, Maffioli P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The role of various peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors and their ligands in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>J Cell Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>2017; doi: 10.1002/jcp.25804. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>10.KeshamouniVGReddyRCArenbergDAJoelBThannickalVJKalemkerianGPPeroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma activation inhibits tumor progression in non-small-cell lung cancerOncogene20042310010810.1038/sj.onc.1206885<?supplied-pmid 14712215?>14712215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>11.Lin CF, Young KC, Bai CH, BC Y, Ma CT, Chien YC, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Rosiglitazone regulates anti-inflammation and growth inhibition via PTEN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Biomed Res Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>2014;787924 doi: 10.1155/2014/787924. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>12.ZhaoHGuHZhangHLiJHZhaoWEPPARγ-dependent pathway in the growth-inhibitory effects of K562 cells by carotenoids in combination with rosiglitazoneBiochim Biophys Acta2014184054555510.1016/j.bbagen.2013.09.005<?supplied-pmid 24036327?>24036327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>13.HalabanRLernerABThe dual effect of melanocyte-stimulating hormone (αMSH) on the growth of cultured mouse melanoma cellsExp Cell Res197710811111710.1016/S0014-4827(77)80016-5<?supplied-pmid 196867?>196867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>14.PawelekJMEvidence suggesting that a cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase is a positive regulator of proliferation in Cloudman S91 melanoma cellsJ Cell Physiol19799861962510.1002/jcp.1040980320<?supplied-pmid 220273?>220273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>15.BockFOnderkaJBraunGSchneiderACBachmannBOCursiefenCIdentification of novel endogenous anti(lymph)angiogenic factors in the aqueous humorInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci2016576554656010.1167/iovs.15-18526<?supplied-pmid 27918829?>27918829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>16.ImSMoroOPengFMedranoEECorneliusJBabcockGActivation of the cyclic AMP pathway by alpha-melanotropin mediates the response of human melanocytes to ultraviolet B radiationCancer Res1998584754<?supplied-pmid 9426056?>9426056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>17.NovosadovaEVManuilovaESArsenyevaELAndreevaLALebedevaOSGrivennikovIAInvestigation of the effect of α-melanocyte-stimulating hormone on proliferation and early stages of differentiation of human induced pluripotent stem cellsDokl Biochem Biophys201646714114410.1134/S1607672916020174<?supplied-pmid 27193719?>27193719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>18.Abdel-MalekZSwopeVBPallasJKrugKNordlundJJMitogenic, melanogenic, and cAMP responses of cultured neonatal human melanocytes to commonly used mitogensJ Cell Physiol199215041642510.1002/jcp.1041500226<?supplied-pmid 1370843?>1370843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>19.EisingerMMarkoOSelective proliferation of normal human melanocytes in vitro in the presence of phorbol ester and cholera toxinProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1982792018202210.1073/pnas.79.6.2018<?supplied-pmid 6952249?>6952249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>20.HalabanRGhoshSDurayPKirkwoodJMLernerABHuman melanocytes cultured from nevi and melanomasJ Invest Dermatol.19868719510110.1111/1523-1747.ep12523594<?supplied-pmid 2425008?>2425008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>21.HocheggerHTakedaSHuntTCyclin-dependent kinases and cell-cycle transitions: does one fit all?Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol2008991091610.1038/nrm2510<?supplied-pmid 18813291?>18813291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>22.ZagouriFKotoulaVKouvatseasGSotiropoulouMKoletsaTGavresseaTProtein expression patterns of cell cycle regulators in operable breast cancerPLoS One2017128e018048910.1371/journal.pone.0180489<?supplied-pmid 28797035?>28797035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>23.ChenKPerez-StableCD'IppolitoGSchillerPCRoosBAHowardGAHuman bone marrow-derived stem cell proliferation is inhibited by hepatocyte growth factor via increasing the cell cycle inhibitors p53, p21 and p27Bone2011491194120410.1016/j.bone.2011.08.023<?supplied-pmid 21907315?>21907315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>24.Ilyin GP, Glaise D, Gilot D, Baffet G, Guguen-Guillouzo C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Regulation and role of p21 and p27 cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitors during hepatocyte differentiation and growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>2003 Jul;285(1):G115–27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Epub 2003 Mar 19 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>25.Orlando S, Gallastegui E, Besson A, Abril G, Aligué R, Pujol MJ et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>p27Kip1 and p21Cip1 collaborate in the regulation of transcription by recruiting cyclin-Cdk complexes on the promoters of target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res 2015 Aug 18;43(14):6860–6873. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkv593. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Epub 2015 Jun 13. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>26.RuscianoDLorenzoniPBurgerMMRegulation of c-met expression in B16 murine melanoma cells by melanocyte stimulating hormoneJ Cell Sci1999112623630<?supplied-pmid 9973597?>9973597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>27.KovacsDMiglianoEMuscardinLSilipoVCatricalàCPicardoMThe role of Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway in melanomam epithelial-to-mesenchymal-like switching: evidences from patients-derived cell linesOncotarget20167432954331410.18632/oncotarget.9232<?supplied-pmid 27175588?>27175588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>28.MarescaVFloriEBrigantiSMastrofrancescoAFabbriCMileoAMCorrelation between melanogenic and catalase activity in in vitro human melanocytes: a synergic strategy against oxidative stressPigment Cell Melanoma Res.20082120020510.1111/j.1755-148X.2007.00432.x<?supplied-pmid 18426413?>18426413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>29.LeesnitzerLMParksDJBledsoeRKCobbJECollinsJLConslerTGFunctional consequences of cysteine modification in the ligand binding sites of peroxisome proliferator activated receptors by GW9662Biochemistry2002416640665010.1021/bi0159581<?supplied-pmid 12022867?>12022867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>30.BaeYSLeeTGParkJCHurJHKimYHeoKIdentification of a compound that directly stimulates phospholipase C activityMol Pharmacol2003631043105010.1124/mol.63.5.1043<?supplied-pmid 12695532?>12695532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>31.RocchiSPicardFVamecqJGelmanLPotierNZeyerDA unique PPARγ ligand with potent insulin-sensitizing yet weak adipogenic activityMol Cell2001873774710.1016/S1097-2765(01)00353-7<?supplied-pmid 11684010?>11684010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>32.LonzeBEGintyDDFunction and regulation of CREB family transcription factors in the nervous systemNeuron20023560562310.1016/S0896-6273(02)00828-0<?supplied-pmid 12194863?>12194863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>33.MantovaniGBondioniSLaniaAGRodolfoMPeverelliEPolentaruttiNHigh expression of PKA regulatory subunit 1A protein is related to proliferation of human melanoma cellsOncogene2008271834184310.1038/sj.onc.1210831<?supplied-pmid 17906691?>17906691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>34.BottonTPuissantABahadoranPAnnicotteJSFajasLOrtonneJPVitro and in vivo anti-melanoma effects of ciglitazoneJ Invest Dermatol20091291208121810.1038/jid.2008.346<?supplied-pmid 19177142?>19177142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>35.SerraDAlmeidaLMDinisTCAnti-inflammatory protection afforded by cyanidin-3-glucoside and resveratrol in human intestinal cells via Nrf2 and PPARγ: comparison with 5-aminosalicylic acidChem Biol Interact201626010210910.1016/j.cbi.2016.11.003<?supplied-pmid 27818126?>27818126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>36.VargaTCzimmererZNagyLPPARAre a unique set of fatty acid regulated transcription factors controlling both lipid metabolism and inflammationBiochim Biophys Acta201118121007102210.1016/j.bbadis.2011.02.014<?supplied-pmid 21382489?>21382489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>37.GrommesCLandrethGEHenekaMTAntineoplastic effects of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ agonists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Thelancet Oncol2004541942910.1016/S1470-2045(04)01509-8<?supplied-pmid 15231248?>15231248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>38.Sikka S, Chen L, Sethi G, Kumar AP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Targeting PPARγ signaling cascade for prevention of treatment of prostate cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>PPAR Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>2012; doi: 10.1155/2012/968040. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>39.VellaVNicolosiMLGiulianoSBellomoMBelfioreAMalaguarneraRPPARγ agonists as antineoplastic agent in cancers with dysregulated IGF axisFront Endocrinol (Lausanne)201783128275367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
