<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Evol. Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5921292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1184</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-018-1184-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Host genotype and environment affect the trade-off between horizontal and vertical transmission of the parasite Edhazardia aedis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4448-3118</contrib-id><name><surname>Zilio</surname><given-names>Giacomo</given-names></name><address><email>gcm.zilio@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thiévent</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koella</surname><given-names>Jacob C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 7718</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10711.36</institution-id><institution>Institute of Biology, </institution><institution>University of Neuchâtel, </institution></institution-wrap>Rue Emile-Argand 11, 2000 Neuchâtel, Switzerland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>59</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="?"><plain>If a parasite is able to transmit horizontally or vertically, which transmission mode will it choose? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We investigated how the growth conditions and the genotype of the mosquito Aedes aegypti affect the transmission mode of the parasite Edhazardia aedis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In poor conditions the parasites were more likely to be transmitted horizontally, whereas in favourable conditions they were more likely to be transmitted vertically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Unfavourable conditions delayed emergence, giving the parasite more time to produce its horizontally transmitted stage; in more favourable conditions mosquitoes have greater reproductive success, increasing the effectiveness of vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In addition, the parasite’s ability to transmit vertically was influenced by the genetic background of the host (i.e., its full-sib family), giving a genetic correlation between the host’s life-history and which of the parasite’s transmission mode it enables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In particular, genotypes with large bodies (and therefore high fecundity) were more likely to enable vertical transmission than genotypes with small bodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This led to a trade-off among the host’s families (which can be interpreted as a genetic correlation) for the parasite’s transmission mode. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Since horizontal transmission is linked to higher virulence than vertical transmission, the host’s contribution to transmission mode has important consequences for the evolution of parasites with mixed-mode transmission. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Mixed-mode transmission</kwd><kwd>Trade-off</kwd><kwd>Genetic correlation</kwd><kwd>Parasite</kwd><kwd>Virulence</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The rate of transmission and the severity of symptoms (i.e. virulence) determine a parasite’s damage to a population of hosts, and they are the center of most modern ideas about the evolution of parasites [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Ideas about virulence, for example, are often based on a link between virulence and rate of transmission, and explain virulence as an unavoidable side-product of selection for more transmission [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Virulence is also predicted to change according to the mode of transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Horizontal transmission can be associated with high virulence, if the strong exploitation of the host increases the rate of transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In contrast vertical transmission is expected to be associated with low virulence, for the parasite and the host share to a large degree their evolutionary interests [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>While the role of transmission mode on the evolution of virulence is often studied, relatively little attention has been given to how transmission mode evolves [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Theoretical exceptions predict the conditions that enable vertical and horizontal transmission to coexist and their resulting levels of virulence [7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>These models can be applied to many parasites with mixed modes of transmission such as the medically important viruses HIV, human papilloma virus, and hepatitis B and C viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In many parasites with such mixed-mode transmission, the two transmission modes are physiologically, developmentally or evolutionarily linked [9–12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In many cases, this link means that transmitting with one mode, either vertically or horizontally, reduces transmission with the other [6], but vertical and horizontal transmission can also be positively correlated [13–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>When a trade-off between the two transmission modes is present, it strongly influences the parasite’s evolution and dynamics [7, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>For example, the nature of virulence of the horizontal component (additional mortality or reduced fecundity in the host) may impose constraints on the shape of the trade-off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Only a convex shape of the trade-off will allow the coexistence of the two transmission modes, while a concave one will lead to the fixation of either one or the other [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This implies that the trade-off between the two transmission modes is an important part of a parasite’s epidemiology [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In most cases we know little about what controls this trade-off, and in particular about the genetic basis of the trade-off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Although several studies have measured the trade-off between horizontal and vertical transmission, almost all of them have focused on the variation due to the environment rather than to the host’s or parasite’s genotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>One example is the bacterium Holospora undulata that infects the ciliate Paramecium caudatum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The bacterium has a reproductive stage that is used to infect the daughter nuclei of infected cells, and it has an infectious stage that can be transmitted horizontally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>If the system is maintained in a situation enabling high replication rates of the host, the parasite remains mainly in the reproductive stage and is passed on vertically to the daughter cells of mitotically dividing paramecia; in contrast, at low population growth rate, the parasite differentiates into infectious forms and is transmitted horizontally [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A second example is the microsporidian Edhazardia aedis that infects the mosquito Aedes aegypti. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The parasite has two forms of spores: binucleate spores that infect the eggs of infected females and are transmitted vertically, and uninucleate spores that can kill infected larvae and are transmitted horizontally among larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>There is an obvious trade-off in this system: horizontal transmission requires the death of larvae, so that it precludes vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The investment in the two spore types is regulated in a way that horizontal transmission becomes more likely as food conditions deteriorate and therefore larvae grow more slowly [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>An adaptive explanation is that only good food conditions enable the host to lay many eggs and therefore the parasite to have efficient vertical transmission; the potential for vertical transmission decreases as larval growth slows, making the mosquitoes more attractive to exploitation for horizontal transmission [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Such an adaptive explanation requires that the transmission mode is ultimately controlled by the parasite’s genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Parasitic control has indeed been shown in a number of cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Thus, differences among strains of the fungus Atkinsonella hypoxylon differ in the production of the fruiting bodies responsible for horizontal transmission [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Moreover, manipulating levels of horizontal and vertical transmission have led to evolutionary changes of the pathogen’s transmission mode in several studies, for example bacteriophages [21], barley stripe virus infecting Hordeum vulgare [22], and the bacterium Holospora undulata infecting Paramecium caudatum [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>While there are thus a few suggestions of the parasite’s genes control of its transmission mode, we may expect that the transmission mode and the trade-off between horizontal and vertical transmission are also influenced by the host’s genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Thus, selection for delayed pupation of the mosquito brings with it more vertical and less horizontal transmission of E. aedis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>[20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, several traits of host-parasite interactions are governed by a combination of host and parasite genotypes [23–26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The interaction between host and parasite genotypes govern, for example, the variability of the virulence and transmission of Holospora undulata [26], and the production of the fruiting bodies of the fungus Epichloë elymi depends on the genotype of the grass Elymus hystrix on which the fungus is growing [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A different genetic background of a parasite’s host may therefore promote divergent evolutionary trajectories for the parasite, for each host will cause a particular selection pressure on the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Parasites infecting populations of hosts with different genetic background may therefore experience different selection pressures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Such a host-parasite interaction may consequently shape spatial gradients of local adaptation in accordance with the idea of the geographic mosaic of co-evolution [28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In this study, we investigated how the host’s genotype and food environment interact to influence the horizontal and vertical transmission of E. aedis. We expected that lower food availability would favour horizontal over vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We further expected that the mosquito’s genotypes enabling large size and long life would favour vertical transmission, while genotypes with a long development would favour horizontal transmission, and that these associations would be more apparent when food is scarce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Finally, we expected to find a trade-off in the host’s potential to transmit the parasite horizontally or vertically. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Mosquitoes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Aedes aegypti, a mosquito that occurs throughout the tropics and subtropics, is the main vector of yellow, dengue and chikungunya fevers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Its physiology, genetics, and ecology have been intensively studied [30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The larvae of Ae. aegypti grow in natural or artificial containers and their development depends on many environmental factors [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Two aspects that make it suitable for lab work is that its eggs can be stored for a long period and that a single mating lets the female lay eggs throughout her life [33, 34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We used the UGAL strain of the mosquito Ae. aegypti (obtained from P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Guérin, University of Neuchâtel), an undocumented strain that was established in the 1970s [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The mosquitoes were maintained at 26 °C, 70% humidity, 12 h:12 h light:dark photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Microsporidia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Edhazardia aedis was provided by J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Becnel at the United States Department of Agriculture (Gainesville, Florida). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>This microsporidium, a specific parasite of Ae. aegypti, has a complex life cycle (Fig. 1) involving horizontal and vertical transmission [36–40] and using two types of morphologically distinguishable spores: uninucleate spores for horizontal transmission and binucleate spores for vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Mosquito larvae are infected when they ingest uninucleate spores suspended in water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>After a period of development the parasite produces binucleate spores in adult females; these are responsible for vertical (transovarial) transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Males provide no opportunity for vertical transmission, so adult males are a dead-end for the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Once the infected eggs hatch the parasite develops into uninucleate spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>These vertically infected mosquitoes die as juveniles and release the uninucleate spores into the water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>These uninucleate spores are eaten by larvae to complete the life-cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Thus, larvae that acquire the spores horizontally usually go on to transmit vertically, while larvae that are infected vertically die as larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Occasionally, as illustrated in Fig. 1, horizontally infected larvae die before emergence, which can result in a second round of horizontal transmission without the requirement of vertical transmission [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Note that underlying this sequence of transmission is a fixed developmental sequence (though not necessarily fixed timing) of the parasite that alternates the production of binucleate and uninucleate spores [36, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Thus, if the horizontally infected individuals die for a second round of horizontal transmission, the parasite has switched from uninucleate to binucleate and then back to uninucleate spores.Fig. 1Life cycle of the microsporidia Edhazardia aedis infecting the mosquito Aedes aegypti. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Usually (solid line), the parasite alternate vertical and horizontal transmission using two types of spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Repeated horizontal transmission is possible (dashed line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Since the parasite’s life-cycle involves a strict alternation of binucleate and uninucleate spores, repeated horizontal transmission implies that the parasite goes through its complete developmental sequence – producing first binucleate and the uninucleate spores – within a juvenile mosquito. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(Modified from [42]) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Experimental design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Our main goal was to see how the host’s genotype and environment affect the developmental trade-off between horizontal and vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We approximated genetic variation with the variation among full-sib families, where we minimized the maternal effects by rearing the mosquitoes of the parental generation individually in identical environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>We chose as environmental factor the amount of food given to the larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We exposed the larvae to a standard concentration of uninucleate spores, and then followed the mosquito and parasite’s development to evaluate the potential for horizontal and vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Full-sib families </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In order to synchronize the hatching and thus obtain larvae of the same age, we hatched uninfected eggs from the colony at low air pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The larvae were moved to and individually reared in 12-well tissue-culture plates filled with 3 mL of deionized water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>They were fed daily with TetraMin™ fish food (age 0 (day of hatching, day 0): 0.06 mg/larva, age 1: 0.08 mg, age 2: 0.16 mg, age 3: 0.32 mg, age 4: 0.64 mg, from age 5 onwards: 0.32 mg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Each pupa was placed into a 180-mL plastic cup covered with bed-netting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Three days after emergence, two males were transferred into each of 100 cups all containing one female. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Two days later, the males were removed, the females were allowed to blood feed on GZ’s arms for 10 min, and then given the opportunity to lay eggs on a filter paper for 5 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The filter paper with the eggs was then stored in a petri dish at the same laboratory conditions as the colony. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The cycle of blood-feeding and egg-collecting was repeated for 10 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>During this period, adults were also provided with a cotton ball soaked with 10% sugar solution, which was changed every 2 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>All the eggs collected from one female during her lifespan represented a full-sib family (since females only mate with one male), for a total of 100 full-sib families. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Main experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The eggs were gently brushed into petri dishes and rehydrated in deionised water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Thirty of hundred families were synchronously hatched under partial vacuum, twelve of the families with enough larvae were haphazardly chosen for the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The larvae were reared individually in 12-well tissue-culture plates filled with 3 mL of deionized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Each plate contained an individual from each family. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Each family experienced two larval food treatments (50% or 100% of our standardized ration of TetraMin Baby™ fish food (see above)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Seventy-two hours after hatching, the larvae were exposed in their wells to 500 uninucleate spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The spores had been harvested from vertically infected larvae hatched 7 days earlier than the day of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Twenty of these vertically infected larvae were crushed and homogenized in an Eppendorf tube adding 1 mL of deionized water, and the concentration of the uninucleate spores was determined with a hemocytometer and a phase-contrast microscope (Zeiss Axio Lab.A1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Pupae were individually transferred to Falcon tubes, and the emerging adults were provided with a cotton ball soaked with 10% sugar solution that was changed every 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The survival was checked daily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The dead larvae, pupae and adults were stored in 2 mL plastic tubes at − 20 °C until further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We measured the spore load for each of the collected individuals after adding 0.1 mL of deionized water and homogenizing the samples with a TissueLyser LT - QIAGEN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The numbers of uninucleate and binucleate spores in the obtained solution were counted with a hemocytometer placed under a phase contrast microscope (Zeiss Axio Lab.A1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The treatment conditions and the family origin of the samples were unknown during the counting of the spores, a total amount of 1904 individuals were used for the analysis [41] with a median of 155 individuals per family. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We considered that mosquitoes enabled horizontal transmission, if they died before emerging and harbored uninucleate spores, and that they did not enable horizontal transmission either if they carried no uninucleate spores or did not die as juveniles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We considered that mosquitoes enabled vertical transmission, if adult females carried binucleate spores, and that they did not enable vertical transmission otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Note that we used these qualitative measures of transmission rather than quantitative measures involving the number of spores for two reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>First it is not known how the number of spores relates to transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Second, most of the mosquitoes do not carry any spores (in particular uninucleate spores), so that any quantitative measure would strongly resemble the qualitative one. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We first evaluated the effects of food, full-sib family and their interaction on each transmission mode with a generalized linear mixed effect model with binomial distribution and on age at pupation, wing length and longevity with an ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>For each trait we considered food treatment and family as fixed factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>If the interaction was not significant, we show the results of the analysis that includes only the main effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Note that we considered family as fixed rather than random, because we were not interested in the variation among families within our colony. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Rather, we wanted to check for differences among the families of our study that we could then analyze in the next step of the analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Genetic correlation and trade-off </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The potential genetic correlation between transmission success (proportion of individuals enabling horizontal or vertical transmission) and life-history traits was analyzed with regressions of the family means. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>We looked at the correlation with juvenile developmental period (days spent in the aquatic environment before emergence as an adult), adult size (wing length), and longevity after emergence in the different food treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We investigated a possible trade-off between vertical and horizontal transmission with a linear regression with the family-means of the horizontal and vertical transmission at each food condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Finally, we evaluated the correlation of vertical transmission of the families between the two food regimes with a linear model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(The analogous analysis for horizontal transmission would be meaningless, for almost all families allowed no horizontal transmission in the good-food environment.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>All the statistical analyses were performed with R version 3.4.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Effects of food and family on transmission </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Families ranged from 11% survival up to emergence (at low food) to 97% (at high food). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The effect of food was highly significant for the potential horizontal and vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Although 9% of the mosquitoes that fed the high-food diet and 76% of the low-food mosquitoes died before emerging, only 2% and 6% of these, respectively, harbored uninucleate spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The potential for horizontal transmission (the proportion of mosquitoes that died before emergence and harboured uninucleate spores) at high and low food was thus 0.2% and 5% of the exposed individuals (χ2 = 54.1, df = 1, p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Among the mosquitoes that emerged as adult females, 91% and 95% harboured binucleate spores at high and low food, and respectively 42% and 7% of the these females enabled vertical transmission (χ2 = 350, df = 1, p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 2).Fig. 2Proportion of potential for vertical and horizontal transmission for low and high food conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The bars representthe proportion (± 95% confidence intervals) of the individuals enabling horizontal or vertical transmission according to their developmental stage (adults harbouring binucleates spores for vertical and juvenile harbouring uninucleate spores for horizontal transmission) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Families ranged from 0% (at high food) to 15% (at low food) horizontal transmission and from 1% (at low food) to 54% (at high food) vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The effect of the full-sib families was significant for both the vertical (χ2 = 29.4, df = 11, p = 0.002) and the horizontal transmission mode (χ2 = 33.5, df = 11, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The interactions between food and family (so, whether the effect of food on the success of the two transmission modes depended on the full-sib families) was significant for vertical transmission (χ2 = 25.7, df = 11, p = 0.007) but not for horizontal transmission (χ2 = 5.6, df = 11, p = 0.90). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Effects of food and family on life history traits </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Average age at emergence ranged from 6.2 for one of the families reared with high food to 9.7 days, with highly significant effects of family (F11,990 = 28.3, p &lt; 0.001) and food level (F1,990 = 222, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Average wing length ranged from 2.82 mm at high food to 2.32 mm at low food (family: F11,990 = 3.34, p &lt; 0.001; food: F1,990 = 432, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Average longevity after emergence ranged from 12 days at high food to 0.6 days at low food (family: F11,990 = 2.08, p = 0.019; food: F1,990 = 160, p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Genetic correlations of transmission and life-history </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The proportion of the family that enabled horizontal transmission (proportion of individuals within the family enabling horizontal transmission) was higher in low food than in high food conditions (F = 35.5, p &lt; 0.001) and increased with the average juvenile developmental period of the family (F = 36.5, p &lt; 0.001), as shown in Fig. 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>There was a tendency for the relationship between the family’s potential for horizontal transmission and juvenile development to be affected by food (food* juvenile development: F = 3.51, p = 0.098). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Neither body size (F = 1.4, p = 0.27), longevity (F = 0.4, p = 0.556) or other interactions (all p-values &gt; 0.13) affected the family’s potential for horizontal transmission.Fig. 3Relationship between horizontal transmission and juvenile development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Dots represent the proportion of horizontal transmission per family (proportion of individuals whithin the family enabling horizontal transmission) as a function of the time spent as juvenile at low (closed symbols) and high food (open symbols). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The lines represent the regression of the linear model for each food treatment and the bars the±95% confidence intervals </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The proportion of the family that enables vertical transmission (proportion of individuals within the family enabling vertical transmission) was higher in high food than in low food conditions (F = 96.8, p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>It increased with mean body size (F = 29.8, p &lt; 0.001) and longevity (F = 5.3, p = 0.049) and it decreased with juvenile developmental period (F = 8.1, p = 0.022). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Food modified the effect of body size (food*body size: F = 13.5, p = 0.006) and the interaction between mean juvenile development and longevity (juvenile developmental period*longevity: F = 5.8, p = 0.043; food*juvenile developmental period*longevity: F = 6.5, p = 0.033). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In addition, there was a tendency for an interaction between mean body size and mean juvenile development to affect a family’s potential for vertical transmission (F = 4.3, p = 0.071), but no other interactions were significant (all p-values &gt; 0.28).Fig. 4Relationship between vertical transmission and wing length (proxy for adult size). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Dots represent the proportion of vertical transmission (proportion of individuals whithin the family enabling vertical transmission) as a function of the size of the wings at low (closed symbols) and high food (open symbols). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The lines represent the regression of the linear model for the two food treatments and the bars the±95% confidence intervals </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Trade-off between vertical and horizontal transmission </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The mean potential within families for the parasite to be transmitted vertically was negatively correlated with the average potential of horizontal transmission (F = 23.1, df = 1, r2 = 0.49, p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Although food treatment had no significant effect on the trade-off between vertical and horizontal transmission (F = 1.19, p = 0.285), this result is difficult to interpret because of the limited horizontal transmission at the high food level.Fig. 5Potential for vertical transmission as a function of the potential for horizontal transmission in Edhazardia aedis at low food (closed symbols) and high food (open symbols). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Each symbol represents the proportion of individuals within the family enabling vertical and horizontal transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The lines show the regression of the means, the bars represent the±95% confidence intervals </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Correlation between environments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The potential of a family for vertical transmission was uncorrelated between the two food treatments (F1,10 = 0.0291, p = 0.868) (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The analogous analysis for horizontal transmission would be meaningless, for almost all families allowed no horizontal transmission in the good-food environment.Fig. 6Correlation between the potential for vertical transmission (proportion of individuals whithin the family enabling vertical transmission) in high and low food conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Each dot represents the mean per family, the dashed line the regression line of the model and the barsthe ±95% confidence intervals </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Our results confirm that the transmission mode of E. aedis is affected by the growth conditions of the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>They also highlight the role of the host’s genotype in linking its life-history to the parasite’s transmission and in influencing the trade-offs underlying transmission mode. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Corroborating earlier studies [19, 20], the parasite shows an adaptive response to changes of the host’s development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Food conditions that slow growth increased the potential for horizontal transmission whereas favorable conditions (high food) increased vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>If growth is slow, adults are small and have low fecundity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Vertical transmission is therefore inefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>However, poor food conditions also delay pupation, giving the parasite more time to complete its development from binucleate to uninucleate spores within a single larva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This enables the parasite to achieve a high load of horizontally transmitted spores, and thus to kill its host [20] and being transmitted efficiently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>If growth is fast, in contrast, the parasite can expect that its host will lay many eggs; it therefore puts more emphasis on vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Even if the rapid development does not allow the parasite to develop many spores, vertical transmission can be efficient, for only a few spores are necessary to infect all of the mosquito’s eggs [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Transmission mode thus appears to be controlled by the production of uninucleate spores and the associated risk of larval mortality rather than by different allocation to the production of binucleate spores. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Note that our use of the phrase ‘adaptive response’ refers to (non-genetic) changes of the parasite’s transmission mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This does not imply that the parasite alters its development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Indeed, at least part of the adaptive response is simply a consequence of the timing of the parasite’s fixed developmental pattern in the host’s development, The parasite cannot produce a new generation of uninucleate spores without first going through a generation of binucleate spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Uninucleate spores are therefore more likely to be found in more slowly developing larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>An interesting implication of this idea is that the parasite has evolved its fixed developmental pattern in a way that optimises its transmission in its very variable environment (that is, host). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In addition to the response of the parasite to the host’s environment, we found that the parasite changed its response according to the host’s genetic background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The mosquito families differed with regard to the potential for transmission mode thus showing the presence of a genetic variation in the host for the transmission mode of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Genetic variation of a host for the transmission mode of a parasite has also been detected in the grass Elymus hystrix infected by the endophyte Epichloë elymi [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In our case, the genetic basis for vertical transmission corroborates an experiment where artificial selection of the mosquito for more rapid or slower development affected the parasite’s transmission mode [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Our data go further by suggesting that the parasite’s transmission mode changes according to the genetic basis of several life-history traits such as larval survival, adult size and longevity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>These genetic differences in life-history traits represent in themselves a first defence of the host against parasite threats, influencing the transmission mode which determines how parasites infect and exploit the hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The variation in the life-history traits of the host therefore has important consequences not only for the parasite but also for host’s fitness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In particular, the families with the largest and longest-living individuals were most likely to enable vertical transmission (low virulence and higher fitness for the host), while the families with the slowest development were most likely to enable horizontal transmission (high virulence and lower fitness for the host). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Although molecular and physiological effects were not measured, our results therefore suggest that several life-history traits are genetically linked to the complex infection-related and immunity genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Such a trade-off between life-history traits and immune response is often assumed [43] and supported by empirical studies [44, 45], including in our host-parasite system [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>But the results also support the idea that the parasites switch in an adaptive way their transmission mode according not only to the environment, but also to the genotype of the host they are infecting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In families whose genetic background suggests high expected reproductive success, the parasite transmits vertically; in families with low reproductive success and long development the parasite switches to horizontal transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This switch according to genetic background is necessary to let the parasite to achieve high success, for the families that permit more vertical transmission permit less horizontal transmission (at least in the low-food conditions, where it was possible to investigate this trade-off). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The trade-off between vertical and horizontal transmission has important consequences for the evolution of, both, the parasite and the host, in particular because horizontal transmission is associated with higher virulence than vertical transmission [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>For E. aedis, this association is necessary because of the parasite’s life-cycle, and more generally this trade-off is predicted by evolutionary theory [7, 8, 16, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>First, there should be selection for hosts that enable more vertical and less horizontal transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This could lead in the long-term to the loss of horizontal transmission and therefore more effective vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Indeed, this has been observed in an evolutionary experiment involving P. caudatum and H. undulata [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Second, since the host’s genetic structure affects the ability of the parasite to transmit horizontally, it also affects the evolution of the parasite’s virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In particular, with the expected selection of the host towards less damaging vertical transmission, we would expect a correlated response of the parasite to lower virulence thus reinforcing the evolution to vertical transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Third, while at high food hosts develop rapidly and almost always enable vertical transmission, we expect at low food and in the absence of parasite pressure that the host’s life-history evolves to delayed age at maturity [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Introducing parasites pressure impedes this evolution towards an optimal strategy by forcing the host towards vertical transmission with early maturity, although the associated low fecundity is not beneficial for either the host or the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Under parasite pressure indeed, slow development hosts are more likely to die, whereas fast development host are favored but with a smaller size than the optimum and consequently with a cost in fecundity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>We confirmed a response of E. aedis in its transmission strategy according to environmental conditions and the host’s genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>This response may be considered to be adaptive, for it leads to effective vertical transmission when the host is expected to achieve high fecundity and to more horizontal transmission when the host has a slow rate of development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Since mode of transmission is linked to the evolution of the parasite’s virulence, the host’s contribution to the trade-offs underlying transmission can influence considerably the epidemiology and evolution of parasites with mixed-mode transmission. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We thank G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Hauser, A.R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Mora and A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Belli for comments on earlier versions of the article and J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Hamley and M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Zeller for suggestions and discussion on the design of the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par41"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The data set underlying the results of this article is available in the Dryad Digital repository, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://datadryad.org//resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.p3g8r54">https://datadryad.org//resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.p3g8r54</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>GZ and KT carried out the experiment and the acquisition of the data. GZ and JK designed the study, analyzed the data and drafted the manuscript. All authors read and contributed to the manuscript, and approve the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par42">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par43">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par44">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>1.GandonSJansenVAAvan BaalenMHost life history and the evolution of parasite virulenceEvolution2001551056106210.1554/0014-3820(2001)055[1056:HLHATE]2.0.CO;2<?supplied-pmid 11430642?>11430642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>2.LeggettHCBucklingALongGHBootsMGeneralism and the evolution of parasite virulenceTrends Ecol Evol20132859259610.1016/j.tree.2013.07.002<?supplied-pmid 23968968?>23968968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3.AlizonSHurfordAMideoNvan BaalenMVirulence evolution and the trade-off hypothesis: history, current state of affairs and the futureJ Evol Biol20092224525910.1111/j.1420-9101.2008.01658.x<?supplied-pmid 19196383?>19196383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>4.FrankSAModels of parasite virulenceQ Rev Biol199671377710.1086/419267<?supplied-pmid 8919665?>8919665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>5.EbertDThe epidemiology and evolution of symbionts with mixed-mode transmissionAnnu Rev Ecol Evol Syst20034462364310.1146/annurev-ecolsys-032513-100555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>6.AntonovicsJWilsonAJForbesMRHauffeHCKallioERLeggettHLongdonBOkamuraBSaitSMWebsterJThe evolution of transmission modePhilos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sc20173722016008310.1098/rstb.2016.008328289251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>7.LipsitchMSillerSNowakMAThe evolution of virulence in pathogens with vertical and horizontal transmissionEvolution1996501729174110.1111/j.1558-5646.1996.tb03560.x<?supplied-pmid 28565576?>28565576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>8.FerdynJBGodelleBDiversification of transmission modes and the evolution of mutualismAm Nat200516661362710.1086/49179916224726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>9.EbertDManginKLThe influence of host demography on the evolution of virulence of a microsporidian gut parasiteEvolution1997511828183710.1111/j.1558-5646.1997.tb05106.x<?supplied-pmid 28565099?>28565099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>10.MessengerSLMolineuxIJBullJJVirulence evolution in a virus obeys a trade-offProc R Soc Lond B199926639740410.1098/rspb.1999.0651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>11.MagalonHNideletTMartinGKaltzOHost growth conditions influence experimental evolution of life history and virulence of a parasite with vertical and horizontal transmissionEvolution20106421262138<?supplied-pmid 20163449?>20163449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>12.DusiEGougat-BarberaCBerendonkTUKaltzOLong-term selection experiment produces breakdown of horizontal transmissibility in parasite with mixed transmission modeEvolution2015691069107610.1111/evo.12638<?supplied-pmid 25756600?>25756600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>13.de RoodeJCChiJRarickRMAltizer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Strength in numbers: high parasite burdens increase transmission of a protozoan parasite of monarch butterflies (Danaus plexippus)Oecologia2009161677510.1007/s00442-009-1361-6<?supplied-pmid 19418070?>19418070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>14.KoverPXClayKTrade-off between virulence and vertical transmission and the maintenance of a virulent plant pathogenAm Nat1998152165175<?supplied-pmid 18811383?>18811383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>15.van FrankenhuyzenKNystromCLiuYVertical transmission of Nosema fumiferanae (microsporidia: Nosematidae) and consequences for distribution, post-diapause emergence and dispersal of second-instar larvae of the spruce budworm, Choristoneura fumiferana (Clem.) (Lepidoptera: Tortricidae)J Invert Pathol20079617318210.1016/j.jip.2007.03.017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>16.LipsitchMNowakMAEbertDMayRMThe population dynamics of vertically and horizontally transmitted parasitesProc R Soc Lond B199526032132710.1098/rspb.1995.0099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>17.van BaalenMPoulinRMorandSSkorpingAParent-to-offspring infection and the struggle for transmissionEvolutionary biology of host-parasite relationships: theory meets reality2000AmsterdamElsevier Sci97115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>18.KaltzOKoellaJCHost growth conditions regulate the plasticity of horizontal and vertical transmission in Holospora undulata, a bacterial parasite of the protozoan Paramecium caudatumEvolution2003571535154210.1111/j.0014-3820.2003.tb00361.x<?supplied-pmid 12940358?>12940358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>19.KoellaJCAgnewPMichalakisYCoevolutionary interactions between host life histories and parasite life cyclesParasitology1998116475510.1017/S0031182000084936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>20.AgnewPKoellaJCLife history interactions with environmental conditions in a host-parasite relationship and the parasite’s mode of transmissionEvol Ecol199913678910.1023/A:1006586131235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>21.BullJJMolineuxIJRiceWRSelection of benevolence in a host–parasite systemEvolution19914587588210.1111/j.1558-5646.1991.tb04356.x<?supplied-pmid 28564051?>28564051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>22.StewartADLogsdonJMKelleySEAn empirical study of the evolution of virulence under both horizontal and vertical transmissionEvolution20055973073910.1111/j.0014-3820.2005.tb01749.x<?supplied-pmid 15926685?>15926685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>23.CasadevallAPirofskiLAMicrobial virulence results from the interaction between host and microorganismTrends Microbiol20031115715810.1016/S0966-842X(03)00008-8<?supplied-pmid 12706990?>12706990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>24.LambrechtsLFellousSKoellaJCCoevolutionary interactions between host and parasite genotypesTrends Parasitol200622121610.1016/j.pt.2005.11.008<?supplied-pmid 16310412?>16310412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>25.RefardtDRaineyPTuning a genetic switch: experimental evolution and natural variation of prophage inductionEvolution2010641086109710.1111/j.1558-5646.2009.00882.x<?supplied-pmid 19891623?>19891623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>26.RestifOKaltzOCondition-dependent virulence in a horizontally and vertically transmitted bacterial parasiteOikos200611414815810.1111/j.2006.0030-1299.14611.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>27.TintjerTLeuchtmannAClayKVariation in horizontal and vertical transmission of the endophyte Epichloe elymi infecting the grass Elymus hystrixNew Phytol200817923624610.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02441.x<?supplied-pmid 18422901?>18422901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>28.ThompsonJNSpecific hypotheses on the geographic mosaic of coevolutionAm Nat1999153S1S1410.1086/303208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>29.ThompsonJNThe geographic mosaic of coevolution2006ChicagoUniv. of Chicago Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>30.ChristophersSAëdes aegypti (L.) the yellow fever mosquito: its life history, bionomics and structure1960CambridgeCambridge University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>31.NeneVWortmanJRLawsonDHaasBKodiraCGenome sequence of Aedes aegypti, a major arbovirus vectorScience20073161718172310.1126/science.1138878<?supplied-pmid 17510324?>17510324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>32.ChanKLHoBCChanYCAedes aegypti (L.) and Aedes albopictus (Skuse) in Singapore CityBull World Health Organization197144629633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>33.MunstermannLECramptonJMBeardCBChristosLCare and maintenance of Aedes Mosquito coloniesThe molecular biology of insect disease vectors1997DordrechtSpringer1320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>34.OlivaCFDamiensDBenedictMQMale reproductive biology of Aedes mosquitoesActa Trop2014132121910.1016/j.actatropica.2013.11.021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>35.KunoGEarly history of laboratory breeding of Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae) focusing on the origins and use of selected strainsJ Med Entomol2010495797110.1603/ME10152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>36.BecnelJJSpragueVFukudaTHazardEIDevelopment of Edhazardia aedis (kudo, 1930) n. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>G., n. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Comb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>(Microsporida: Amblyosporidae) in the mosquito Aedes aegypti (L.) (Diptera: Culicidae)J Protozool19893611913010.1111/j.1550-7408.1989.tb01057.x<?supplied-pmid 2724178?>2724178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>37.BecnelJJGarciaJJJohnsonMAEdhazardia aedis (Microspora: Culicosporidae) effects on the reproductive capacity of Aedes aegyptiJ Med Entomol19953254955310.1093/jmedent/32.4.549<?supplied-pmid 7650718?>7650718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>38.JohnsonMABecnelJJUndeenAHA new sporulation sequence in Edhazardia aedis (microsporidia: Culicosporidae), a parasite of the mosquito Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae)J Invertebr Pathol199770697510.1006/jipa.1997.4678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>39.DesjardinsCAContrasting host-pathogen interactions and genome evolution in two generalist and specialist microsporidian pathogens of mosquitoesNat Commun20156712110.1038/ncomms8121<?supplied-pmid 25968466?>25968466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>40.NasciRSTangKHBecnelJJFukudaTEffect of per os Edhazardia aedis (Microsporida: amblyosporidae) infection on Aedes aegypti mortality and body sizeJ Am Mosq Control Assoc19928131136<?supplied-pmid 1431854?>1431854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>41.Zilio G, Thiévent K, Koella J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Data from: host genotype and environment affect the trade-off between horizontal and vertical transmission of the parasite Edhazardia aedis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Dryad Digital Repository. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>10.5061/dryad.p3g8r54. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>42.KoellaJCAgnewPA correlated response of a parasite’s virulence and life cycle to selection on its host’s life historyJ Evol Biol199912707910.1046/j.1420-9101.1999.00010.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>43.Lee AK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Linking immune defenses and life history at the levels of the individual and the species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Integr Comp Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>2017;46:1000–15. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>44.Soler JJ, Neve Ld, Perez-Contreras T, Soler M, Sorci G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Trade-off between immunocompetence and growth in magpies: an experimental study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Proc R Soc B Biol Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>2003;270(1512):241-8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>45.Kirschman LJ, Quade AH, Zera AJ, Warne RW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Immune function trade-offs in response to parasite threats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>J Insect Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>2017;98:199-204. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>46.Ebert D, Herre EA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The evolution of parasitic diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Parasitol Today. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>1996;12(3):96-101. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>47.Day T, Proulx SR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>A General Theory for the Evolutionary Dynamics of Virulence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Am Natural. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>2004;163(4):E40-E63. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>48.Stearns SC, Koella JC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The evolution of phenotypic plasticity in life-history traits: predictions of reaction norms for age and size at maturity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>1986;40(5):893-913. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
