<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin capmc?><?iso-abbr Diseases?><?submitter-system camss?><?submitter-userid 6711?><?submitter-authority CAPMC?><?submitter-login mojgan.rastegar@umanitoba.ca?><?submitter-name Mojgan Rastegar?><?domain capmc?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101636232</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">42828</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diseases</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diseases</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diseases (Basel, Switzerland)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2079-9721</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5298922</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diseases2010045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">capmc6493</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>MeCP2-Related Diseases and Animal Models </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ezeonwuka</surname><given-names>Chinelo D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rastegar</surname><given-names>Mojgan</given-names></name><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Regenerative Medicine Program, Department of Biochemistry and Medical Genetics, Faculty of Medicine, University of Manitoba, 745 Bannatyne Avenue, Winnipeg, Manitoba, R3E 0J9, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; <email>rastegar@cc.umanitoba.ca</email>; Tel.: +204-272-3108; Fax: +204-789-3900</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The role of epigenetics in human disease has become an area of increased research interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Collaborative efforts from scientists and clinicians have led to a better understanding of the molecular mechanisms by which epigenetic regulation is involved in the pathogenesis of many human diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Several neurological and non-neurological disorders are associated with mutations in genes that encode for epigenetic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>One of the most studied proteins that impacts human disease and is associated with deregulation of epigenetic processes is Methyl CpG binding protein 2 (MeCP2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is an epigenetic regulator that modulates gene expression by translating epigenetic DNA methylation marks into appropriate cellular responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In order to highlight the importance of epigenetics to development and disease, we will discuss how MeCP2 emerges as a key epigenetic player in human neurodevelopmental, neurological, and non-neurological disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We will review our current knowledge on MeCP2-related diseases, including Rett Syndrome, Angelman Syndrome, Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder, Hirschsprung disease, and Cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we will briefly discuss about the existing MeCP2 animal models that have been generated for a better understanding of how MeCP2 impacts certain human diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>MeCP2</kwd><kwd>DNA methylation</kwd><kwd>Rett Syndrome</kwd><kwd>Autism Spectrum Disorders</kwd><kwd>Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders</kwd><kwd>Rheumatoid arthritis</kwd><kwd>animal models</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P2"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Methyl CpG binding protein 2 (MeCP2) was first identified and characterized as a DNA binding protein that specifically binds to methyl-CpG dinucleotides [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The MECP2 gene is localized on the X-chromosome and contains complex regulatory elements that control its precise expression levels [2–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In both human and mouse, the MECP2/Mecp2 gene consists of four exons encoding for two different protein isoforms, MeCP2E1 and MeCP2E2 [6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The two Mecp2/MeCP2 isoforms show differential temporal and brain region-specific differences in their distribution [7], and we previously showed that MeCP2E1 isoform is similarly distributed compared to total MeCP2 in murine brain cells [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The main functional protein domains of MeCP2 include the methyl binding domain (MBD), the transcriptional repression domain (TRD), the C-terminal domain (CTD), and the inter domain (ID) [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The MBD facilitates binding to methylated CpG dinucleotides and the preference for adjacent A/T-rich motifs [9,11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It is also capable of binding to non-methylated DNA sequences such as the four-way DNA junctions [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The TRD domain mediates the transcriptional repressor role of MeCP2, and interacts with co-repressor complexes, such as c-Ski, mSin3A, HDAC1, and HDAC2 [5,9,14,15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The CTD is suggested to be important for MeCP2 function and its chromatin binding activities [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Inter domain interactions significantly impacts MeCP2 structure and increases the stability of the protein [16,17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P3"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is a nuclear protein that is mainly localized to methylated pericentromeric heterochromatin, referred to as chromocenters [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is widely expressed in several tissues, and is suggested to mediate transcriptional regulation through association with 5-methyl cytosine (5mC) and 5-hydroxymethlcytosine (5hmC), the two major types of DNA modifications [19–21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 binding to 5mC is associated with repressive functions through its interaction with co-repressor complexes, while binding to 5hmC is suggested to facilitate gene expression through the organization of dynamic chromatin [15,22–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Research studies on MeCP2 have shown diverse functions of this protein including transcriptional repression, transcriptional activation [25–27], RNA splicing [28,29], long range chromatin remodeling [30,31], modulation of chromatin architecture, and maintenance of DNA methylation [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This diversity in the function of MeCP2 underscores its role in many disorders. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P4"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is a multifunctional epigenetic regulator that is involved in transcriptional regulation as well as modulating chromatin structure [17,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Epigenetics control gene expression without altering the corresponding DNA sequences and impact development and disease [21,34–36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Epigenetic mechanisms control the expression of many neurodevelopmentally important genes through chromatin remodeling, histone modifications and DNA methylation [37–41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The prevailing view of MeCP2 as an epigenetic modulator is related to its ability to associate with different epigenetic marks (either through direct DNA binding or recruiting other transcription factors). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Thus, MeCP2 acts as an ‘epigenetic reader’ that contributes in the establishment of functional states of chromatin structure, a process that is fundamental for normal cellular function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, it is still not fully understood whether MeCP2 acts as a genome-wide epigenetic regulator or as a gene-specific transcriptional modulator, and evidence exists in favor of both mechanisms [15,42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P5"><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 protein is highly expressed in the brain compared to other tissues [18,43,44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The protein expression pattern within the brain follows a defined pattern, with early appearing structures, such as brainstem and thalamus, expressing the protein before more rostral structures, such as the cortex [18,43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Temporally, MeCP2 protein expression profile is low at birth, and increases dramatically at specific time periods coinciding with the process of neuronal maturation and synaptogenesis in different parts of the brain [43,45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Cell type-specific studies have revealed that MeCP2 levels are highest in mature neurons, while astrocytes and immature neurons express lower levels of MeCP2 [8,46,47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The increased levels of MeCP2 expression in mature neurons are maintained throughout adulthood, implying a requirement for postmitotic neuronal function [47–49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In neurons, MeCP2 is involved in neuronal maturation, dendrite formation, and synaptic functions [15,49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Studies of mouse models lacking Mecp2 expression in neurons further demonstrate the critical role of MeCP2 for normal brain function, especially with regard to synaptic modulation and maintenance [18,51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P6"><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Most MeCP2 mutations are de novo and can be grouped into three general categories; severe loss-of-function mutations, mild loss-of-function mutations and a broad group of duplications and other non-coding mutations [52,53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Each category of mutation is associated with (a) subset(s) of neurological symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Genotype-phenotype analyses have shown that there is no direct and simple correlation with the type of observed mutations and the resulting disease phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The difficulty in attributing a particular type of mutation to a specific phenotype might be in part due to the pattern of X-chromosome inactivation (XCI) [54,55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P7"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Overall, MeCP2-related diseases that are associated with protein dysfunction are mainly characterized by cognitive impairment and intellectual disabilities [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>However, dysregulation of the protein are also frequently observed in cases of inherited disorders and autoimmune diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In this review, we will primarily focus on human diseases that are associated with MeCP2 dysfunction, and will aim to highlight the role of MeCP2 in neurological/neuropsychiatric and non-neurological disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In addition, animal models that have enabled a better understanding of the mechanism of MeCP2 action will be discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The Role of MeCP2 in Neurological Disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Rett Syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P8"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Rett Syndrome (RTT) is a progressive X-linked neurological disorder that mainly affects young girls with an incidence rate of 1:10,000–1:15,000 [15,57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>RTT is, perhaps, the most common cause of mental retardation in females [58,59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Although it was initially thought to occur exclusively in females, males have also been identified with classic RTT [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In approximately 90% of RTT cases, the disease is due to MECP2 gene mutations [61]. MECP2 mutations that cause classical RTT in females typically result in neonatal encephalopathy and death in the first year of life in males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>However, similar MECP2 mutations may result in RTT phenotypes in males with Kleinfelter syndrome (47, XXY), or somatic mosaicism [62,63]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P9"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>There is the classic RTT as well as atypical forms of RTT that deviate from the classical clinical presentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Classic RTT is noticed primarily during infancy and can be divided into four stages that reflect the characteristic abnormalities displayed in RTT patients [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The first stage takes place after a period of normal development, during the first 6–18 months after birth, when developmental progression ceases and acquisition of new skills is delayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>General motor performance such as crawling, sitting, and walking are also severely impaired at this stage [58,65,66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The second stage of RTT starts at approximately one to four years, with developmental stagnation accompanied by general growth retardation, loss of purposeful hand movements and speech, tongue protrusion, abnormal facial expression, weight loss, and gait ataxia/apraxia [58,64,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Autonomic dysfunction such as irregular breathing patterns, forced expulsion of air and saliva, and apnea can also be observed at this stage [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The duration of this stage is from weeks to approximately a year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The third RTT stage is regarded as a relatively ‘quiet’ period as stabilization of some of the symptoms occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, neuromotor regression and stereotypic hand movements still persists [58,64,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A defining feature at this stage is the occurrence of seizures, which ranges from easily controlled to intractable epilepsy [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The duration of this stage is usually from years to decades [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The last RTT stage takes place from ages 5–15 years and beyond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Motor deterioration continues and results in loss of mobility and dependence on wheel chair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Additional abnormalities include dystonia, severe constipation, oropharyngeal dysfunction, and cardiac abnormalities [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>As patients become older they often develop Parkinson’s-like features [64,68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The duration of this stage varies with individuals, and usually lasts for decades. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P10"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Atypical forms of RTT deviate from classic RTT with respect to age of disease onset, clinical profile and severity of symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>These forms of RTT occur due to skewing of XCI, and may range from milder forms to more severe manifestations than classic RTT [70,71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Mild variants of RTT are characterized by a later age of onset, typically occurring between one to three years of age and display mild stereotypic movements and neurologic symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The preserved speech or the Zappella variant is a mild variant of RTT characterized by the ability of patients to speak a few words. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Patients with this variant have a normal head size and are usually overweight [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The more severe variants include the congenital form (also known as the Rolando variant) that lack the early period of normal development, and a form of classical RTT with early onset seizures before the age of six months (also known as the Hanefeld variant) [73,74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Mutations in cyclin-dependent kinase-like 5 (CDKL5) are associated with the early-onset seizure variant form of RTT, while mutations in forkhead box protein G1 (FOXG1) are associated with congenital RTT Syndrome variant [75,76]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P11"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and autopsy examination have shown that major morphological abnormalities detected in the central nervous system of RTT patients include an overall decrease in the size of the brain and of individual neurons [77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The reduction in brain size is distributed throughout the brain and affects both white, and to a greater extent the grey matter in different brain regions [78,79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Cortical and cerebellar degeneration have also been demonstrated to progressively occur with increasing age in RTT patients [80]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>MECP2 Duplication Disorder </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P12"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>MECP2 duplication syndrome was predicted by the observation that mice engineered to overexpress MECP2 develop a progressive neurological disorder including stereotyped and repetitive movements, epilepsy, spasticity, hypoactivity, and early death [81,82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>This gain of function mutation occurs mostly in males [83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Males with this disorder present clinical features, such as infantile hypotonia, severe to profound mental retardation, poor speech development, recurrent infections, epilepsy, and progressive spasticity [84,85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The incidence rate of MECP2 duplication disorder is estimated to be 1% of unexplained X-linked diseases and most of the reported cases are inherited [86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>However, de novo cases have also been documented [87]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>There is considerable clinical overlap in patients with classic RTT and MECP2 duplication disorder specifically in behavioral phenotypes, such as stereotypic hand/body movements, anxiety, and social avoidance [88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>However, in contrast to RTT, immunodeficiency is observed in patients with MECP2 duplication disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>It remains unclear if this phenotype occurs due to secondary effects from increased dosage of MeCP2 protein [89]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Approximately 40% of males with MECP2 duplication reported so far have died before their 25th birthday, usually from respiratory infections [90]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Angelman Syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P13"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>MECP2 mutations that cause RTT have also been reported in cases of Angelman Syndrome (AS) [91–93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Angelman Syndrome is primarily caused by mutations or imprinting errors of the UBE3A gene located on chromosome 15, and is characterized by intellectual disability; severe speech impairment and gait ataxia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Considerable phenotypic overlap exists between AS and RTT; however they differ with respect to timing of symptom onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Angelman Syndrome has an earlier onset and patients are characterized with low hypotonicity at birth [91]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>X-linked Mental Retardation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P14"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>X-linked mental retardation (XLMR) is a genetic disorder arising from mutations or duplication of genes across the X chromosome, including the MECP2 gene. MECP2 point mutations have been identified in up to 2% of individuals with XLMR and duplications of the gene are also implicated in approximately 1% to 2% of XLMR cases [86,94]. MECP2 mutations that cause RTT or severe neonatal encephalopathy are not identified in XLMR patients and vice versa [86,95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In addition, the molecular lesions underlying MECP2 duplications that result in XLMR are different from those observed in MECP2 duplication syndrome [96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Males with XLMR show phenotypes, such as severe intellectual disability, speech impairment, and motor abnormalities, whereas females display mild intellectual disability or are unaffected [86]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Severe Neonatal Encephalopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P15"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Males with a normal karyotype and a mutation in the MECP2 gene present with a distinct clinical condition, and severe neonatal encephalopathy (SNE) [97]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Severe neonatal encephalopathy is a disorder characterized by a static encephalopathy, severe developmental delays and respiratory abnormalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The mutations are usually inherited from mothers with favorable XCI skewing that display mild/no RTT symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Males with SNE often die within the first years of their life due to autonomic dysfunction [95,98]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Some MECP2 mutations that do not cause RTT in females have also been implicated in moderate to profound mental retardation, deficits in language and motor skills, obesity, autistic features, and psychiatric disorders in males [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Autism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P16"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Autism and RTT are similar developmental disorders that belong to the spectrum of autism disorders classified as pervasive developmental disorders, or Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) [99]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Although they are similar developmental disorders, autism differs from RTT with respect to its genetic basis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>While RTT is caused by MECP2 mutations, the genetic basis of autism is not fully clear and is proposed to involve multiple genes [100]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the MECP2 regulatory elements (resulting in decreased expression of the protein) are commonly associated with autism [101]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Reduced expression of MeCP2 protein has been shown to occur frequently in the frontal cortex of autistic patients and is correlated with increased MECP2 promoter DNA methylation [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The silencing of autism-related genes through promoter DNA hypermethylation is commonly associated with autism, and drugs that can demethylate promoters might be useful in activating these genes [103,104]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In a recent study, we show that reduced DNA demethylation at the Mecp2 promoter and intron 1 regulatory elements treated with Decitabine is associated with increased Mecp2 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Our results provide insight on use of such drugs for future therapeutic interventions of autism [105]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Moreover, MECP2 mutations that are associated with classic RTT have been identified in a number of autistic females who do not meet the diagnostic criteria for RTT [100]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>This makes it difficult to determine if a MECP2 mutation that is associated with autism diagnosis is a different disorder from RTT, or if both disorders are simply different representations on a spectrum associated with MECP2 mutations. MECP2 mutations have also been reported in patients with mild cognitive and motor difficulties and early-onset schizophrenia [106]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S9"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P17"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Prenatal exposure to alcohol is associated with adverse effects on neurodevelopment, and results in a set of severe neurodevelopmental disorders known as fetal alcohol spectrum disorders (FASD) [107,108]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The incidence of FASD is estimated to be as high as 1 in 100 births and this disorder commonly manifests as cognitive and intellectual disabilities [108]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Accumulating evidence-implicating MeCP2 in FASD pathogenesis further reinforces the critical role of MeCP2 for central nervous system function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated aberrant expression levels of MeCP2 in rodent FASD models, and this is suggested to be an important epigenetic determinant in FASD [109,110]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>For example, prenatal exposure to ethanol has been demonstrated to significantly decrease MeCP2 expression in both prefrontal cortex and striatum of rodent offspring [109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Research in animal models suggests that the global epigenetic changes due to ethanol are related to variations in the levels, duration as well as time of exposure [108,111]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Further supporting the potential role of MeCP2 in FASD, RTT-causing mutations have been reported in a FASD patient [112]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 has been also shown to modulate the alcohol intake and sensitivity to alcohol, demonstrating the role of MeCP2 in alcoholism [113]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S10"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Huntington’s Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P18"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Huntington’s disease (HD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disorder that affects muscle coordination and results in cognitive decline and psychiatric disorders [114,115]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>It is one of several tri-nucleotide repeat disorders caused by the length of a repeated section of a gene exceeding a normal range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Expansion of a CAG triplet repeat stretch within the Huntingtin gene (HTT) results in a mutant form of the protein, which gradually damages brain cells [114,116]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional dysregulation has been suggested to play major roles in HD pathology, and it was recently demonstrated that the huntingtin protein (Htt) directly interacts with MeCP2 in mouse and cellular models of HD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Aberrant interactions between Htt and MeCP2 is suggested to contribute to aberrant transcription in Huntington’s disease by regulating brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) levels [117]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P19"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The implication of MeCP2 in such diverse range of neurological disorders necessitates a complete understanding of its relationship to brain development and function, as well as its interaction with other epigenetic factors that mediate dysregulation of normal epigenetic program of the brain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="S11"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Non-Neurological Disorders Associated with MeCP2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S12"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P20"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Apart from to its role in neurological disorders, MeCP2 has also been shown to play a role in many cancers such as breast, colorectal, lung, liver, and prostate cancer [118–123]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 role in cancer is related to the epigenetic regulation of cancer-related genes, particularly mechanisms that involve hypermethylation of gene promoters [118]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The growth-promoting role of MeCP2 in prostate cancer cells has been demonstrated previously, where it was shown to control mechanisms, such as cell proliferation and apoptosis [119]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In gastric cancer, the depth of invasion has been shown to be associated with MeCP2 protein levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In gastric carcinoma cells, microRNA miR-212 was shown to suppress translation of MECP2 transcripts, which in turn resulted in reduced depth of cellular invasion [124]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In addition, MeCP2 has been linked to other cancers, such as myeloma [125], hematological malignancies [126], ductal carcinomas [127], and cervical cancers [128]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S13"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P21"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a systemic autoimmune disease that affects multiple organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The disease predominantly affects females, with a female to male ratio that ranges from 4.3–13.6 to 1 [56,129]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Although the cause of SLE is still not clear, evidence supports an important role for abnormal T cell DNA methylation in the pathogenesis of SLE, as methylation sensitive genes show increased expression in T cells of SLE patients [130]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In active SLE T-cells, the expression of DNA methyltransferase 1 (DNMT1), the main enzyme that maintains DNA methylation during cell division, is reduced, resulting in promoter hypomethylation of these methylation-sensitive genes [56,131,132]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is suggested to play an important role in this process as it is critical for the epigenetic regulation of methylation-sensitive genes, and genetic polymorphisms in MECP2 have also been identified in patients with SLE [56,133,134]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Moreover, MeCP2 associates with DNMT1, the association of which is required to maintain DNA methylation [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The association between MeCP2, DNMT, and methylation-sensitive genes suggests an important role for epigenetic regulation in the pathogenesis of SLE and other autoimmune diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S14"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Rheumatoid Arthritis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P22"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a systemic autoimmune disease that results in chronic inflammation and destruction of many tissues and organs, primarily flexible synovial joints [135–137]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>It is characterized by the presence of auto antibodies, which may be detected in the blood long before the onset of disease [138,139]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Increasing evidence suggests that DNA methylation and histone modifications regulate the progression of Rheumatoid arthritis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, it has been shown that MeCP2 expression levels were up-regulated in rodent models of RA, and it is hypothesized that the increased MeCP2 protein levels play a role in the pathogenesis of RA through the canonical Wnt pathway [140,141]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S15"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Hirschsprung’s Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P23"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Hirschsprung’s disease (HSCR) is a congenital disorder of the colon characterized by the absence of certain nerve cells known as ganglion cells [142,143]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The incidence of HSCR is about 1:2000–5000, with males being affected 4 times more frequently than females [144]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The lack of ganglion cells is associated with impaired craniocaudal migration of neural crest cells, and results in severe constipation or intestinal obstruction [145,146]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Defects in the differentiation of neuroblasts into ganglion cells may also contribute to the disorder [142]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>A recent study implicating MeCP2 in the pathogenesis of HSCR suggests that aberrant reduced levels of MeCP2 may play an important role in suppressing the proliferative ability of cells in patients with Hirschsprung’s disease [147]. Table 1 represents a list of MeCP2-associated diseases and the genders that are mostly affected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Animal Models of MeCP2 Dysfunction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P24"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Several animal models have been generated in order to better understand the molecular mechanisms, progression and pathology of disorders that are associated with MeCP2 dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These include mostly rodent models (particularly mouse models) as well as zebrafish and Drosophila models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Different strategies are often employed to alter the expression and function of MeCP2 in these animal models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="S17"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 Null Mouse Models </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P25"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 knockout mice have been generated using the Cre recombinase-loxP system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These mice appear normal until approximately three to four weeks of age, when they begin to exhibit behavioral phenotypes such as unusual gait, hindlimb clasping, seizures, tremors, anxiety, learning and memory deficits, and irregular breathing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Brain neuropathology observed in Mecp2 knockout mice is similar to that observed in RTT individuals. Mecp2 knockout mice have smaller densely packed neurons, reduced dendritic spine density, deficits in axonal fasciculation and reduced number of mature synapses. Mecp2 knockout mice die at approximately 10 weeks of life [150–152]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The reactivation of Mecp2 in the brains of Mecp2 null mice rescued many RTT-phenotypes seen in the null mice, including delayed disease progression, increased life span, deceased mortality, and restored neurological functions [153,154]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S18"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 Mutant Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P26"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 mutant mice differ from the above-mentioned knockout mice as they express a truncated/mutant MeCP2 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>One of such mutant mice is the Jaenisch strain (Mecp2tm1.1jae), generated by deletion of exon 3 of the Mecp2 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Jaenisch mice display behavioral phenotypes similar to the Mecp2 knockout mice, although the phenotype is slightly milder and the lifespan is longer (12 weeks) [82,155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Another Mecp2 mutant mouse model has been generated that expresses a protein truncated at amino acid 308 (Mecp2308). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>It is assumed that the truncated MeCP2 protein produced in these mice has residual unknown functions. Mecp2308 mice appear normal until approximately six weeks of age when they develop similar but milder neurological phenotype as Mecp2 knockout mice [156]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S19"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 Conditional-Mutant Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P27"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Brain-specific deletion of Mecp2 in neural precursor cells, beginning at embryonic day 12 (Nestin-cre line), results in mice that display phenotypes similar to Mecp2 knockout mice [150,155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This suggests that MeCP2 dysfunction in the CNS is sufficient to cause phenotypes observed in RTT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Selective loss of Mecp2 in hypothalamic and amygdala neurons (Sim1-cre line) results in mice that display similar abnormal physiological stress response as that observed in brain-specific conditional mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>These mice were also obese and aggressive, suggesting a role for MeCP2 in regulating social and feeding behaviors [157]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Deletion of Mecp2 in other parts of the brain such as in brainstem neurons (TH-cre line) significantly affects locomotor activity, with no effect on social interaction, breathing patterns, learning and memory [158,159]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Mice Overexpressing MECP2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P28"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Mice overexpressing human MECP2 at approximately twice the endogenous levels exhibit delayed neurological symptoms at approximately 10 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>These symptoms include enhanced motor learning and synaptic plasticity in the hippocampus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However at 20 weeks, these mice develop seizures and become hypoactive and the majority of them die by approximately one year of age [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Increased MeCP2 expression in other transgenic lines also results in motor abnormalities and neurological symptoms [160]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>These transgenic mice mimic MECP2 duplication syndrome that is observed in humans, and reinforces the notion of a critical requirement for precise dosage of MeCP2 protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S21"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Mouse Models Carrying Rett Syndrome-Associated Mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P29"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>A mouse model of Rett syndrome was generated by introducing a premature STOP codon at the amino acid position 168, and resulted in a truncated MeCP2 protein (Mecp2R168X). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These mice display neurological phenotypes such as hind limb clasping and breathing irregularities similar to other mouse models [161]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Another RTT mouse model is the A140V Mecp2 mutant mice (Mecp2A140V). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This MeCP2 mutation has also been described in cases of X-linked mental retardation and manic-depressive behaviors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>A140V mutant mice produce a mutant MeCP2 protein that lacks the ability to bind to Alpha thalassemia/mental retardation syndrome X-linked (ATRX) protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>These mice have an apparently normal life span, and lack specific phenotypes that are displayed in other mouse models including seizures, tremors, and breathing irregularities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>However they show increased cellular packing and reduced dendrite branching similar to what is observed in autopsy brains from RTT individuals [162]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 partners with ATRX and is involved in the silencing of imprinted genes in brain [163]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Recently, a Mecp2e1-deficient mouse model was developed with a point mutation in exon 1 changing translational start site of the first exon from “ATG” into “TTG”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>These mice show many phenotypes observed in Mecp2 null mice including hindlimb clasping, forelimb stereotypy, and excessive grooming followed by death within 7 to 31 weeks [164]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In order to demonstrate the functions of neuronal activity-dependent phosphorylation at S80, S421 and S424, two knock-in mice models were generated; Mecp2S80A and Mecp2S421A;S424A abolishing the phosphorylation at S80 and S421 sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The Mecp2S80A mice showed reduced locomotion while opposite locomotors behaviors were seen in Mecp2S421A;S424A, providing insights on the functions of S80 phosphorylation in resting neurons and S421 in active neurons [165]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P30"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A rat model of Rett Syndrome was also generated with reduced Mecp2 expression in the brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This RTT rodent model revealed reduced expression of Bdnf, with no significant phenotypes that mimic RTT [166]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Other RTT animal models include the Drosophila and zebrafish models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The Drosophila RTT model was generated by overexpressing known RTT mutations such as R294X and R106W, which resulted in locomotary dysfunction [167]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The recently reported zebrafish model of RTT was generated by introducing a C to T transition-mutation at position 187 of the Mecp2 coding sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This resulted in a nonsense mutation and a truncation of the MeCP2 protein at the position 63 (Mecp2Q63*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>RTT zebrafish model display altered motor behaviors, although the phenotype is weaker in comparison to other Mecp2-deficient animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>In contrast to MeCP2-null mouse models, Mecp2-null zebrafish are viable and fertile [168]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P31"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Other than animal models, in vitro cellular models of Mecp2 dysfunction have also been established in order to better understand the how the effects of MeCP2 deficiency impairs normal brain function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Loss of Mecp2 from cultured neuronal cell populations obtained from embryonic or postnatal Mecp2-deficient mice indicate biochemical and morphological abnormalities similar to Mecp2 null animals [49,159,169]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Moreover, other studies have revealed putative roles of MeCP2 in astrocytes and microglia despite the low levels of MeCP2 in these cell types. Mecp2-deficient astrocytes and microglia have been demonstrated to produce aberrant levels of soluble factors, such as glutamate, which inhibit dendrite branching from co-cultured neurons in vitro [47,48,170]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In addition, loss of Mecp2 from astrocytes has been demonstrated to affect astrocytic gap junction function, thereby resulting in their failure to adequately support dendritic development [48]. Table 2 presents an overview of animal models that are developed to study the molecular function of MeCP2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="S22"><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Closing Remarks </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P32"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Epigenetic regulation of gene expression is fundamental for proper organism development and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 is a multifunctional epigenetic regulator and the malleability in its function underscores its role in many human diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Since its discovery, significant progress has been made to understand its dynamic molecular properties, and increasing evidence reveals its central position in many neurological, neurodevelopmental, neuropsychiatric and non-neurological disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Despite tremendous progress in understanding the molecular mechanisms by which dysregulation of MeCP2 expression and function results in these disorders, we are still far from translating this knowledge towards effective therapeutic approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The availability of excellent animal models promises, not only hope, but also a better strategy to overcome the challenge of translational research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>It is very likely that the number of diseases associated with MeCP2 dysfunction will grow rapidly in near future, thus, a better understanding of how MeCP2 functions in complex regulatory networks will pave the way for the discovery of better disease biomarkers as well as novel targets for treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="S23"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We apologize that many excellent papers are not included in this paper due to space limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank members of the Rastegar laboratory (specially Vichithra RB Liyanage) for helpful discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The research of M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Rastegar is supported by funds from the Scottish Rites Charitable Foundation of Canada (SRCFC, Grant 10110), Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC Discovery Grant 372405-2009), Canadian Institute of Health Research (CIHR) Grants TEC-128094 and CEN-132383, as well as Health Sciences Centre Foundation (HSCF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>CD Ezeonwuka was a recipient of MHRC-UMGF studentship award. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Conflicts of Interest </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary id="GL"><title>List of Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="G1">AS</term><def><p>Angelman Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">ASD</term><def><p>Autism Spectrum Disorders</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">ATRX</term><def><p>Alpha Thalassemia/Mental Retardation Syndrome X-linked</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">BDNF</term><def><p>Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">CDKL5</term><def><p>Cyclin-Dependent Kinase-Like 5</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">CTD</term><def><p>C-Terminal Domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">DNMT</term><def><p>DNA Methyl Transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">FASD</term><def><p>Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">FOXG1</term><def><p>Forkhead Box Protein G1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">HD</term><def><p>Huntington’s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">HSCR</term><def><p>Hirschsprung’s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12"><italic>HTT</italic></term><def><p>Huntingtin Gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">Htt</term><def><p>Huntingtin Protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G14">MBD</term><def><p>Methyl Binding Domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G15">MeCP2</term><def><p>Methyl CpG Binding Protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G16"><italic>MECP2</italic></term><def><p>Human <italic>MECP2</italic> Gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G17"><italic>Mecp2</italic></term><def><p>Mouse <italic>Mecp2</italic> Gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G18">miRNA</term><def><p>microRNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G19">RA</term><def><p>Rheumatoid Arthritis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G20">RTT</term><def><p>Rett Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G21">SLE</term><def><p>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G22">TRD</term><def><p>Transcription Repression Domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G23">XCI</term><def><p>X Chromosome Inactivation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G24">XLMR</term><def><p>X-linked Mental Retardation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G25">5mC</term><def><p>5-methylcytosine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G26">5hmC</term><def><p>5-hyrdoxymethylcytosine</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>1LewisJDMeehanRRHenzelWJMaurer-FogyIJeppesenPKleinFBirdAPurification, sequence, and cellular localization of a novel chromosomal protein that binds to methylated DNACell1992699059141606614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>2ReichwaldKThiesenJWieheTWeitzelJPoustkaWARosenthalAPlatzerMStratlingWHKioschisPComparative sequence analysis of the mecp2-locus in human and mouse reveals new transcribed regionsMamm Genome20001118219010723722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>3LiuJFranckeUIdentification of cis-regulatory elements for mecp2 expressionHum Mol Genet2006151769178216613900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>4D’EspositoMQuaderiNACiccodicolaABruniPEspositoTD’UrsoMBrownSDIsolation, physical mapping, and northern analysis of the x-linked human gene encoding methyl cpg-binding protein, mecp2Mamm Genome199675335358672133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>5SinghJSaxenaAChristodoulouJRavineDMecp2 genomic structure and function: Insights from encodeNucleic Acids Res2008366035604718820302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>6MnatzakanianGNLohiHMunteanuIAlfredSEYamadaTMacLeodPJJonesJRSchererSWSchanenNCFriezMJA previously unidentified mecp2 open reading frame defines a new protein isoform relevant to rett syndromeNat Genet20043633934115034579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>7KriaucionisSBirdAThe major form of mecp2 has a novel n-terminus generated by alternative splicingNucleic Acids Res2004321818182315034150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>8ZachariahRMOlsonCOEzeonwukaCRastegarMNovel mecp2 isoform-specific antibody reveals the endogenous mecp2e1 expression in murine brain, primary neurons and astrocytesPLoS One20127e4976323185431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>9HiteKCAdamsVHHansenJCRecent advances in mecp2 structure and functionBiochem Cell Biol20098721922719234536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>10AdamsVHMcBryantSJWadePAWoodcockCLHansenJCIntrinsic disorder and autonomous domain function in the multifunctional nuclear protein, mecp2J Biol Chem2007282150571506417371874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>11KloseRJSarrafSASchmiedebergLMcDermottSMStanchevaIBirdAPDNA binding selectivity of mecp2 due to a requirement for a/t sequences adjacent to methyl-cpgMol Cell20051966767816137622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>12HansenJCGhoshRPWoodcockCLBinding of the rett syndrome protein, mecp2, to methylated and unmethylated DNA and chromatinIUBMB life20106273273821031501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>13GalvaoTCThomasJOStructure-specific binding of mecp2 to four-way junction DNA through its methyl cpg-binding domainNucleic Acids Res2005336603660916314321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>14KokuraKKaulSCWadhwaRNomuraTKhanMMShinagawaTYasukawaTColmenaresCIshiiSThe ski protein family is required for mecp2-mediated transcriptional repressionJ Biol Chem2001276341153412111441023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>15ZachariahRMRastegarMLinking epigenetics to human disease and rett syndrome: The emerging novel and challenging concepts in mecp2 researchNeural Plast2012201241582522474603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>16GhoshRPNikitinaTHorowitz-SchererRAGieraschLMUverskyVNHiteKHansenJCWoodcockCLUnique physical properties and interactions of the domains of methylated DNA binding protein 2Biochemistry2010494395441020405910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>17StussDPCheemaMNgMKMartinez de PazAWilliamsonBMissiaenKCosmanJDMcPheeDEstellerMHendzelMImpaired in vivo binding of mecp2 to chromatin in the absence of its DNA methyl-binding domainNucleic Acids Res2013414888490023558747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>18ShahbazianMDAntalffyBArmstrongDLZoghbiHYInsight into rett syndrome: Mecp2 levels display tissue- and cell-specific differences and correlate with neuronal maturationHum Mol Genet20021111512411809720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>19JakovcevskiMAkbarianSEpigenetic mechanisms in neurological diseaseNat Med2012181194120422869198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>20LiyanageVRBZachariahRMDelcuveGPDavieJRRastegarMNew developments in chromatin research: An epigenetic perspectiveNew Developments in Chromatin ResearchSimpsonNMStewartVJNova Science PublishersHauppauge, NY, USA20122958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>21DelcuveGPRastegarMDavieJREpigenetic controlJ Cell Physiol200921924325019127539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>22MellenMAyataPDewellSKriaucionisSHeintzNMecp2 binds to 5hmc enriched within active genes and accessible chromatin in the nervous systemCell20121511417143023260135 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>23NanXNgHHJohnsonCALahertyCDTurnerBMEisenmanRNBirdATranscriptional repression by the methyl-cpg-binding protein mecp2 involves a histone deacetylase complexNature19983933863899620804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>24JonesPLVeenstraGJWadePAVermaakDKassSULandsbergerNStrouboulisJWolffeAPMethylated DNA and mecp2 recruit histone deacetylase to repress transcriptionNat Genet1998191871919620779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>25JordanCLiHHKwanHCFranckeUCerebellar gene expression profiles of mouse models for rett syndrome reveal novel mecp2 targetsBMC Med Genet2007811617227582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>26ChahrourMJungSYShawCZhouXWongSTQinJZoghbiHYMecp2, a key contributor to neurological disease, activates and represses transcriptionScience20083201224122918511691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>27YasuiDHPeddadaSBiedaMCValleroROHogartANagarajanRPThatcherKNFarnhamPJLasalleJMIntegrated epigenomic analyses of neuronal mecp2 reveal a role for long-range interaction with active genesProc Natl Acad Sci US A20071041941619421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>28JefferyLNakielnySComponents of the DNA methylation system of chromatin control are rna-binding proteinsJ Biol Chem2004279494794948715342650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>29YoungJIHongEPCastleJCCrespo-BarretoJBowmanABRoseMFKangDRichmanRJohnsonJMBergetSRegulation of rna splicing by the methylation-dependent transcriptional repressor methyl-cpg binding protein 2Proc Natl Acad Sci US A20051021755117558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>30NikitinaTShiXGhoshRPHorowitz-SchererRAHansenJCWoodcockCLMultiple modes of interaction between the methylated DNA binding protein mecp2 and chromatinMol Cell Biol20072786487717101771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>31SkenePJIllingworthRSWebbSKerrARJamesKDTurnerDJAndrewsRBirdAPNeuronal mecp2 is expressed at near histone-octamer levels and globally alters the chromatin stateMol Cell20103745746820188665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>32KimuraHShiotaKMethyl-cpg-binding protein, mecp2, is a target molecule for maintenance DNA methyltransferase, dnmt1J Biol Chem20032784806481212473678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>33GosMEpigenetic mechanisms of gene expression regulation in neurological diseasesActa Neurobiol Exp2013731937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>34OlynikBMRastegarMThe genetic and epigenetic journey of embryonic stem cells into mature neural cellsFront Genet201238111622303408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>35BarberBARastegarMEpigenetic control of hox genes during neurogenesis, development, and diseaseAnn Anat201019226127420739155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>36RastegarMDelcuveGPDavieJREpigenetic analysis of pluripotent cellsHuman Stem Cell Technology and Biology: A Research Guide and Laboratory Manual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Perspectives in Human Stem Cell Technologies1Wiley-BlackwellNew Jersey, NY, USA2011273288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>37RastegarMKobrossyLKovacsENRambaldiIFeatherstoneMSequential histone modifications at hoxd4 regulatory regions distinguish anterior from posterior embryonic compartmentsMol Cell Biol2004248090810315340071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>38NolteCRastegarMAmoresABouchardMGroteDMaasRKovacsENPostlethwaitJRambaldiIRowanSStereospecificity and pax6 function direct hoxd4 neural enhancer activity along the antero-posterior axisDev Biol200629958259317010333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>39HuangHRastegarMBodnerCGohSLRambaldiIFeatherstoneMMeis c termini harbor transcriptional activation domains that respond to cell signalingJ Biol Chem2005280101191012715654074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>40KobrossyLRastegarMFeatherstoneMInterplay between chromatin and trans-acting factors regulating the hoxd4 promoter during neural differentiationJ Biol Chem2006281259262593916757478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>41BarberBALiyanageVRZachariahRMOlsonCOBaileyMARastegarMDynamic expression of meis1 homeoprotein in e14.5 forebrain and differentiated forebrain-derived neural stem cellsAnn Anat201319543144023756022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>42GuyJChevalHSelfridgeJBirdAThe role of mecp2 in the brainAnnu Rev Cell Dev Biol20112763165221721946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>43LaSalleJMGoldstineJBalmerDGrecoCMQuantitative localization of heterogeneous methyl-cpg-binding protein 2 (mecp2) expression phenotypes in normal and rett syndrome brain by laser scanning cytometryHum Mol Genet2001101729174011532982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>44BalmerDGoldstineJRaoYMLaSalleJMElevated methyl-cpg-binding protein 2 expression is acquired during postnatal human brain development and is correlated with alternative polyadenylationJ Mol Med200381616812545250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>45MullaneyBCJohnstonMVBlueMEDevelopmental expression of methyl-cpg binding protein 2 is dynamically regulated in the rodent brainNeuroscience200412393994914751287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>46YasuiDHXuHDunawayKWLasalleJMJinLWMaezawaIMecp2 modulates gene expression pathways in astrocytesMol Autism2013411123311570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>47BallasNLioyDTGrunseichCMandelGNon-cell autonomous influence of mecp2-deficient glia on neuronal dendritic morphologyNat Neurosci20091231131719234456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>48MaezawaISwanbergSHarveyDLaSalleJMJinLWRett syndrome astrocytes are abnormal and spread mecp2 deficiency through gap junctionsJ Neurosci2009295051506119386901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>49RastegarMHottaAPasceriPMakaremMCheungAYElliottSParkKJAdachiMJonesFSClarkeIDMecp2 isoform-specific vectors with regulated expression for rett syndrome gene therapyPLoS One20094e681019710912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>50WoodLGrayNWZhouZGreenbergMEShepherdGMSynaptic circuit abnormalities of motor-frontal layer 2/3 pyramidal neurons in an rna interference model of methyl-cpg-binding protein 2 deficiencyJ Neurosci200929124401244819812320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>51AkbarianSChenRZGribnauJRasmussenTPFongHJaenischRJonesEGExpression pattern of the rett syndrome gene mecp2 in primate prefrontal cortexNeurobiol Dis2001878479111592848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>52TrappeRLacconeFCobilanschiJMeinsMHuppkePHanefeldFEngelWMecp2 mutations in sporadic cases of rett syndrome are almost exclusively of paternal originAm J Hum Genet2001681093110111309679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>53WanMLeeSSZhangXHouwink-ManvilleISongHRAmirREBuddenSNaiduSPereiraJLLoIFRett syndrome and beyond: Recurrent spontaneous and familial mecp2 mutations at cpg hotspotsAm J Hum Genet1999651520152910577905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>54ChahrourMZoghbiHYThe story of rett syndrome: From clinic to neurobiologyNeuron20075642243717988628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>55DragichJHouwink-ManvilleISchanenCRett syndrome: A surprising result of mutation in mecp2Hum Mol Genet200092365237511005791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>56SawalhaAHWebbRHanSKellyJAKaufmanKMKimberlyRPAlarcon-RiquelmeMEJamesJAVyseTJGilkesonGSCommon variants within mecp2 confer risk of systemic lupus erythematosusPLoS One20083e172718320046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>57RettAon a unusual brain atrophy syndrome in hyperammonemia in childhoodWiener medizinische Wochenschrift19661167237265300597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>58ShahbazianMDZoghbiHYRett syndrome and mecp2: Linking epigenetics and neuronal functionAm J Hum Genet2002711259127212442230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>59BurdLGasconGGRett syndrome: Review and discussion of current diagnostic criteriaJ Child Neurol198832632683058782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>60JanMMDooleyJMGordonKEMale rett syndrome variant: Application of diagnostic criteriaPediatr Neurol19992023824010207936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R61"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>61AmirREVan den VeyverIBWanMTranCQFranckeUZoghbiHYRett syndrome is caused by mutations in x-linked mecp2, encoding methyl-cpg-binding protein 2Nat Genet19992318518810508514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R62"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>62BuddenSSDorseyHCSteinerRDClinical profile of a male with rett syndromeBrain Dev200527Suppl 1S69S7116182490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R63"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>63DayerAGBottaniABouchardyIFlussJAntonarakisSEHaenggeliCAMorrisMAMecp2 mutant allele in a boy with rett syndrome and his unaffected heterozygous motherBrain Dev200729475016844334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R64"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>64HagbergBHanefeldFPercyASkjeldalOAn update on clinically applicable diagnostic criteria in rett syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Comments to rett syndrome clinical criteria consensus panel satellite to european paediatric neurology society meeting, baden baden, germany, 11 september 2001Euro J Paediatr Neurol20026293297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R65"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>65NomuraYSegawaMNatural history of rett syndromeJ Child Neurol20052076476816225833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R66"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>66SegawaMNomuraYRett syndromeCurr Opin Neurol2005189710415791137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R67"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>67HagbergBWitt-EngerstromIRett syndrome: A suggested staging system for describing impairment profile with increasing age towards adolescenceAm J Med Genet Supplement198614759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R68"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>68HagbergBRett syndrome: Long-term clinical follow-up experiences over four decadesJ Child Neurol20052072272716225825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R69"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>69JianLNagarajanLde KlerkNRavineDBowerCAndersonAWilliamsonSChristodoulouJLeonardHPredictors of seizure onset in rett syndromeJ Pediatr200614954254717011329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R70"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>70YoungJIZoghbiHYX-chromosome inactivation patterns are unbalanced and affect the phenotypic outcome in a mouse model of rett syndromeAm J Hum Genet20047451152014973779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R71"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>71AmirREVan den VeyverIBSchultzRMalickiDMTranCQDahleEJPhilippiATimarLPercyAKMotilKJInfluence of mutation type and x chromosome inactivation on rett syndrome phenotypesAnn Neurol20004767067910805343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R72"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>72ZappellaMMeloniILongoIHayekGRenieriAPreserved speech variants of the rett syndrome: Molecular and clinical analysisAmerican J Med Genet20011041422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R73"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>73ArianiFHayekGRondinellaDArtusoRMencarelliMASpanhol-RossetoAPollazzonMBuoniSSpigaORicciardiSFoxg1 is responsible for the congenital variant of rett syndromeAm J Hum Genet200883899318571142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R74"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>74MariFAzimontiSBertaniIBologneseFColomboECaselliRScalaELongoIGrossoSPescucciCCdkl5 belongs to the same molecular pathway of mecp2 and it is responsible for the early-onset seizure variant of rett syndromeHum Mol Genet2005141935194615917271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R75"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>75ChenQZhuYCYuJMiaoSZhengJXuLZhouYLiDZhangCTaoJCdkl5, a protein associated with rett syndrome, regulates neuronal morphogenesis via rac1 signalingJ Neurosci201030127771278620861382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R76"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>76EllawayCJHoGBettellaEKnapmanACollinsFHackettAMcKenzieFDarmanianAPetersGBFaganK14q12 microdeletions excluding foxg1 give rise to a congenital variant rett syndrome-like phenotypeEur J Hum Genet20132152252722968132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R77"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>77SubramaniamBNaiduSReissALNeuroanatomy in rett syndrome: Cerebral cortex and posterior fossaNeurology1997483994079040729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R78"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>78ArmstrongDDNeuropathology of rett syndromeJ Child Neurol20052074775316225830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R79"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>79JellingerKArmstrongDZoghbiHYPercyAKNeuropathology of rett syndromeActa Neuropathol1988761421582900587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R80"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>80OldforsASouranderPArmstrongDLPercyAKWitt-EngerstromIHagbergBARett syndrome: Cerebellar pathologyPediatr Neurol199063103142242172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R81"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>81CollinsALLevensonJMVilaythongAPRichmanRArmstrongDLNoebelsJLDavid SweattJZoghbiHYMild overexpression of mecp2 causes a progressive neurological disorder in miceHum Mol Genet2004132679268915351775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R82"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>82SamacoRCFryerJDRenJFyffeSChaoHTSunYGreerJJZoghbiHYNeulJLA partial loss of function allele of methyl-cpg-binding protein 2 predicts a human neurodevelopmental syndromeHum Mol Genet2008171718172718321864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R83"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>83MeinsMLehmannJGerresheimFHerchenbachJHagedornMHameisterKEpplenJTSubmicroscopic duplication in xq28 causes increased expression of the mecp2 gene in a boy with severe mental retardation and features of rett syndromeJ Med Genet200542e1215689435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R84"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>84del GaudioDFangPScagliaFWardPACraigenWJGlazeDGNeulJLPatelALeeJAIronsMIncreased mecp2 gene copy number as the result of genomic duplication in neurodevelopmentally delayed malesGenet Med2006878479217172942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R85"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>85FriezMJJonesJRClarksonKLubsHAbueloDBierJAPaiSSimensenRWilliamsCGiampietroPFRecurrent infections, hypotonia, and mental retardation caused by duplication of mecp2 and adjacent region in xq28Pediatrics2006118e1687169517088400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R86"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>86LugtenbergDKleefstraTOudakkerARNillesenWMYntemaHGTzschachARaynaudMRatingDJournelHChellyJStructural variation in xq28: Mecp2 duplications in 1% of patients with unexplained xlmr and in 2% of male patients with severe encephalopathyEur J Hum Genet20091744445318985075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R87"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>87SmykMObersztynENowakowskaBNawaraMCheungSWMazurczakTStankiewiczPBocianEDifferent-sized duplications of xq28, including mecp2, in three males with mental retardation, absent or delayed speech, and recurrent infectionsAm J Med Genet B2008147B799806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R88"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>88MorettiPZoghbiHYMecp2 dysfunction in rett syndrome and related disordersCurr Opin in Genet Dev20061627628116647848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R89"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>89RamockiMBTavyevYJPetersSUThe mecp2 duplication syndromeAm J Med Genet A2010152A1079108820425814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R90"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>90RamockiMBPetersSUTavyevYJZhangFCarvalhoCMSchaafCPRichmanRFangPGlazeDGLupskiJRAutism and other neuropsychiatric symptoms are prevalent in individuals with mecp2 duplication syndromeAnn Neurol20096677178220035514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R91"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>91WatsonPBlackGRamsdenSBarrowMSuperMKerrBClayton-SmithJAngelman syndrome phenotype associated with mutations in mecp2, a gene encoding a methyl cpg binding proteinJ Med Genet20013822422811283202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R92"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>92TurnerHMacDonaldFWarburtonSLatifFWebbTDevelopmental delay and the methyl binding genesJ Med Genet200340E1312566531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R93"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>93MilaniDPantaleoniCD’ArrigoSSelicorniARivaDAnother patient with mecp2 mutation without classic rett syndrome phenotypePediatr Neurol20053235535715866439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R94"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>94CouvertPBienvenuTAquavivaCPoirierKMoraineCGendrotCVerloesAAndresCLe FevreACSouvilleIMecp2 is highly mutated in x-linked mental retardationHum Mol Genet20011094194611309367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R95"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>95GonzalesMLLaSalleJMThe role of mecp2 in brain development and neurodevelopmental disordersCurr Psychiat Rep201012127134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R96"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>96Van EschHBautersMIgnatiusJJansenMRaynaudMHollandersKLugtenbergDBienvenuTJensenLRGeczJDuplication of the mecp2 region is a frequent cause of severe mental retardation and progressive neurological symptoms in malesAm J Hum Genet20057744245316080119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R97"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>97SchanenNCKurczynskiTWBrunelleDWoodcockMMDureLStPercyAKNeonatal encephalopathy in two boys in families with recurrent rett syndromeJ Child Neurol1998132292319620015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R98"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>98VillardLKpebeACardosoCChellyPJTardieuPMFontesMTwo affected boys in a rett syndrome family: Clinical and molecular findingsNeurology2000551188119311071498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R99"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>99JohnsonCPMyersSMAmerican Academy of Pediatrics Council on Children With DIdentification and evaluation of children with autism spectrum disordersPediatrics20071201183121517967920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R100"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>100CarneyRMWolpertCMRavanSAShahbazianMAshley-KochACuccaroMLVanceJMPericak-VanceMAIdentification of mecp2 mutations in a series of females with autistic disorderPediatr Neurol20032820521112770674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R101"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>101ShibayamaACookEHJrFengJGlanzmannCYanJCraddockNJonesIRGoldmanDHestonLLSommerSSMecp2 structural and 3’-utr variants in schizophrenia, autism and other psychiatric diseases: A possible association with autismAm J Med Genet B2004128B5053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R102"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>102NagarajanRPHogartARGwyeYMartinMRLaSalleJMReduced mecp2 expression is frequent in autism frontal cortex and correlates with aberrant mecp2 promoter methylationEpigenetics20061e1e1117486179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R103"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>103ChiurazziPPomponiMGWillemsenROostraBANeriGIn vitro reactivation of the fmr1 gene involved in fragile x syndromeHum Mol Genet199871091139384610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R104"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>104NguyenARauchTAPfeiferGPHuVWGlobal methylation profiling of lymphoblastoid cell lines reveals epigenetic contributions to autism spectrum disorders and a novel autism candidate gene, rora, whose protein product is reduced in autistic brainFASEB J2010243036305120375269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R105"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>105LiyanageVRZachariahRMRastegarMDecitabine alters the expression of mecp2 isoforms via dynamic DNA methylation at the mecp2 regulatory elements in neural stem cellsMol Autism2013412123311570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R106"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>106AdegbolaAAGonzalesMLChessALaSalleJMCoxGFA novel hypomorphic mecp2 point mutation is associated with a neuropsychiatric phenotypeHum Genet200912461562318989701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R107"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>107AstleySJFetal alcohol syndrome prevention in washington state: Evidence of successPaediatr Perinat Ep200418344351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R108"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>108HaycockPCFetal alcohol spectrum disorders: The epigenetic perspectiveBiol Reprod20098160761719458312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R109"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>109KimPParkJHChoiCSChoiIJooSHKimMKKimSYKimKCParkSHKwonKJEffects of ethanol exposure during early pregnancy in hyperactive, inattentive and impulsive behaviors and mecp2 expression in rodent offspringNeurochem Res20133862063123283698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R110"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>110Tunc-OzcanEUllmannTMShuklaPKRedeiEELow-dose thyroxine attenuates autism-associated adverse effects of fetal alcohol in male offspring’s social behavior and hippocampal gene expressionAlcohol Clin Exp Res2013371986199523763370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R111"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>111Romano-LopezAMendez-DiazMRuiz-ContrerasAECarrisozaRProspero-GarciaOMaternal separation and proclivity for ethanol intake: A potential role of the endocannabinoid system in ratsNeuroscience201222329630422890080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R112"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>112ZollBHuppkePWesselABartelsILacconeFFetal alcohol syndrome in association with rett syndromeGenet Couns20041520721215287421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R113"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>113Repunte-CanonigoVChenJLefebvreCKawamuraTKreifeldtMBassonORobertsAJSannaPPMecp2 regulates ethanol sensitivity and intakeAddict Biol201310.1111/adb.12047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R114"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>114WalkerFOHuntington’s diseaseLancet200736921822817240289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R115"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>115van der BurgJMBjorkqvistMBrundinPBeyond the brain: Widespread pathology in huntington’s diseaseLancet Neurol2009876577419608102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R116"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>116MyersRHHuntington’s disease geneticsNeuroRx2004125526215717026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R117"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>117McFarlandKNHuizengaMNDarnellSBSangreyGRBerezovskaOChaJHOuteiroTFSadri-VakiliGMecp2: A novel huntingtin interactorHum Mol Genet2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R118"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>118ParryLClarkeARThe roles of the methyl-cpg binding proteins in cancerGenes Cancer2011261863021941618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R119"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>119PulukuriSMPatibandlaSPatelJEstesNRaoJSEpigenetic inactivation of the tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-2 (timp-2) gene in human prostate tumorsOncogene2007265229523717325663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R120"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>120PampalakisGProsnikliEAgaliotiTVlahouAZoumpourlisVSotiropoulouGA tumor-protective role for human kallikrein-related peptidase 6 in breast cancer mediated by inhibition of epithelial-to-mesenchymal transitionCancer Res2009693779378719383923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R121"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>121PancioneMSabatinoLFucciACarafaVNebbiosoAForteNFebbraroAParenteDAmbrosinoCNormannoNEpigenetic silencing of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma is a biomarker for colorectal cancer progression and adverse patients’ outcomePLoS One20105e1422921151932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R122"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>122LinRKHsuHSChangJWChenCYChenJTWangYCAlteration of DNA methyltransferases contributes to 5’cpg methylation and poor prognosis in lung cancerLung Cancer20075520521317140695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R123"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>123ShinJEParkSHJangYKEpigenetic up-regulation of leukemia inhibitory factor (lif) gene during the progression to breast cancerMol Cells20113118118921191816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R124"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>124WadaRAkiyamaYHashimotoYFukamachiHYuasaYMir-212 is downregulated and suppresses methyl-cpg-binding protein mecp2 in human gastric cancerInt J Cancer20101271106111420020497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R125"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>125WangZZhangJZhangYSrivenugopalKSLimSHSpan-xb core promoter sequence is regulated in myeloma cells by specific cpg dinucleotides associated with the mecp2 proteinInt J Cancer20061192878288417036333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R126"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>126MeklatFLiZWangZZhangYZhangJJewellALimSHCancer-testis antigens in haematological malignanciesBr J Haematol200713676977617223912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R127"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>127XuXJinHLiuYLiuLWuQGuoYYuLLiuZZhangTZhangXThe expression patterns and correlations of claudin-6, methy-cpg binding protein 2, DNA methyltransferase 1, histone deacetylase 1, acetyl-histone h3 and acetyl-histone h4 and their clinicopathological significance in breast invasive ductal carcinomasDiagn Pathol201273322455563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R128"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>128WangJTWuTTBaiLDingLHaoMWangYeffect of folate in modulating the expression of DNA methyltransferase 1 and methyl-cpg-bingding protein 2 in cervical cancer cell linesZhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi20133417317723751476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R129"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>129FortunaGBrennanMTSystemic lupus erythematosus: Epidemiology, pathophysiology, manifestations, and managementDent Clin North Am20135763165524034070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R130"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>130OkadaMOgasawaraHKanekoHHishikawaTSekigawaIHashimotoHMaruyamaNKanekoYYamamotoNRole of DNA methylation in transcription of human endogenous retrovirus in the pathogenesis of systemic lupus erythematosusJ Rheumatol2002291678168212180729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R131"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>131LuQWuATesmerLRayDYousifNRichardsonBDemethylation of cd40lg on the inactive x in t cells from women with lupusJ Immunol20071796352635817947713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R132"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>132DengCKaplanMJYangJRayDZhangZMcCuneWJHanashSMRichardsonBCDecreased ras-mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling may cause DNA hypomethylation in t lymphocytes from lupus patientsArthritis Rheum20014439740711229472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R133"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>133LiuKZhangLChenJHuZCaiGHongQAssociation of mecp2 (rs2075596, rs2239464) genetic polymorphisms with systemic lupus erythematosus: A meta-analysisLupus20132290891823857988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R134"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>134WebbRWrenJDJeffriesMKellyJAKaufmanKMTangYFrankMBMerrillJKimberlyRPEdbergJCVariants within mecp2, a key transcription regulator, are associated with increased susceptibility to lupus and differential gene expression in patients with systemic lupus erythematosusArthritis Rheum2009601076108419333917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R135"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>135ChoyEUnderstanding the dynamics: Pathways involved in the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritisRheumatology201251Suppl 5v31122718924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R136"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>136CoolesFAIsaacsJDPathophysiology of rheumatoid arthritisCurr Opin Rheum201123233240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R137"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>137BallestarEEpigenetic alterations in autoimmune rheumatic diseasesNat Rev Rheumatol2011726327121343899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R138"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>138DarrahERosenAGilesJTAndradeFPeptidylarginine deiminase 2, 3 and 4 have distinct specificities against cellular substrates: Novel insights into autoantigen selection in rheumatoid arthritisAnn Rheum Dis201271929821859690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R139"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>139ChandrashekaraSSachinSMeasures in rheumatoid arthritis: Are we measuring too many parametersInt J Rheum Dis20121523924822709486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R140"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>140MiaoCGHuangCHuangYYangYYHeXZhangLLvXWJinYLiJMecp2 modulates the canonical wnt pathway activation by targeting sfrp4 in rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes in ratsCell Signalling20132559860823200852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R141"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>141MiaoCGYangYYHeXLiJNew advances of DNA methylation and histone modifications in rheumatoid arthritis, with special emphasis on mecp2Cell Signalling20132587588223277203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R142"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>142WormanSGaniatsTGHirschsprung’s disease: A cause of chronic constipation in childrenAm Fam Physician1995514874947840044 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R143"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>143MartuccielloGCeccheriniILeroneMJasonniVPathogenesis of hirschsprung’s diseaseJ Pediatr Surg2000351017102510917288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R144"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>144MartuccielloGHirschsprung’s disease, one of the most difficult diagnoses in pediatric surgery: A review of the problems from clinical practice to the benchEur J Pediatr Surg20081814014918493886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R145"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>145BadnerJASieberWKGarverKLChakravartiAA genetic study of hirschsprung diseaseAm J Hum Genet1990465685802309705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R146"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>146ParisiMAKapurRPGenetics of hirschsprung diseaseCurr Opin Pediatr20001261061711106284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R147"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>147ZhouZQinJTangJLiBGengQJiangWWuWRehanVTangWXuXDown-regulation of mecp2 in hirschsprung’s diseaseJ Pediatr Surg2013482099210524094964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R148"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>148JedeleKBThe overlapping spectrum of rett and angelman syndromes: A clinical reviewSeminars in Pediatr Neurol200714108117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R149"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>149SohnBHParkIYLeeJJYangSJJangYJParkKCKimDJLeeDCSohnHAKimTWFunctional switching of tgf-beta1 signaling in liver cancer via epigenetic modulation of a single cpg site in ttp promoterGastroenterology20101381898190820038433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R150"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>150GuyJHendrichBHolmesMMartinJEBirdAA mouse mecp2-null mutation causes neurological symptoms that mimic rett syndromeNat Genet20012732232611242117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R151"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>151PelkaGJWatsonCMRadziewicTHaywardMLahootiHChristodoulouJTamPPMecp2 deficiency is associated with learning and cognitive deficits and altered gene activity in the hippocampal region of miceBrain200612988789816467389 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R152"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>152CalfaGPercyAKPozzo-MillerLExperimental models of rett syndrome based on mecp2 dysfunctionExp Biol Med2011236319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R153"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>153GuyJGanJSelfridgeJCobbSBirdAReversal of neurological defects in a mouse model of rett syndromeScience20073151143114717289941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R154"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>154GiacomettiELuikenhuisSBeardCJaenischRPartial rescue of mecp2 deficiency by postnatal activation of mecp2Proc Natl Acad Sci US A200710419311936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R155"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>155ChenRZAkbarianSTudorMJaenischRDeficiency of methyl-cpg binding protein-2 in cns neurons results in a rett-like phenotype in miceNat Genet20012732733111242118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R156"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>156ShahbazianMYoungJYuva-PaylorLSpencerCAntalffyBNoebelsJArmstrongDPaylorRZoghbiHMice with truncated mecp2 recapitulate many rett syndrome features and display hyperacetylation of histone h3Neuron20023524325412160743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R157"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>157FyffeSLNeulJLSamacoRCChaoHTBen-ShacharSMorettiPMcGillBEGouldingEHSullivanETecottLHDeletion of mecp2 in sim1-expressing neurons reveals a critical role for mecp2 in feeding behavior, aggression, and the response to stressNeuron20085994795818817733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R158"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>158LindebergJUsoskinDBengtssonHGustafssonAKylbergASoderstromSEbendalTTransgenic expression of cre recombinase from the tyrosine hydroxylase locusGenesis200440677315452869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R159"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>159SamacoRCMandel-BrehmCChaoHTWardCSFyffe-MaricichSLRenJHylandKThallerCMaricichSMHumphreysPLoss of mecp2 in aminergic neurons causes cell-autonomous defects in neurotransmitter synthesis and specific behavioral abnormalitiesProc Natl Acad Sci US A20091062196621971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R160"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>160LuikenhuisSGiacomettiEBeardCFJaenischRExpression of mecp2 in postmitotic neurons rescues rett syndrome in miceProc Natl Acad Sci US A200410160336038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R161"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>161Lawson-YuenALiuDHanLJiangZITsaiGEBasuACPickerJFengJCoyleJTUbe3a mrna and protein expression are not decreased in mecp2r168x mutant miceBrain Res200711801617936729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R162"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>162JentarraGMOlfersSLRiceSGSrivastavaNHomanicsGEBlueMNaiduSNarayananVAbnormalities of cell packing density and dendritic complexity in the mecp2 a140v mouse model of rett syndrome/x-linked mental retardationBMC Neurosci2010111920163734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R163"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>163KernohanKDJiangYTremblayDCBonvissutoACEubanksJHMannMRBerubeNGAtrx partners with cohesin and mecp2 and contributes to developmental silencing of imprinted genes in the brainDev Cell20101819120220159591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R164"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>164YasuiDHGonzalesMLAflatooniJOCraryFKHuDJGavinoBJGolubMSVincentJBCarolyn SchanenNOlsonCOMice with an isoform-ablating mecp2 exon 1 mutation recapitulate the neurologic deficits of rett syndromeHum Mol Genet201410.1093/hmg/ddt640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R165"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>165TaoJHuKChangQWuHShermanNEMartinowichKKloseRJSchanenCJaenischRWangWPhosphorylation of mecp2 at serine 80 regulates its chromatin association and neurological functionProc Natl Acad Sci US A200910648824887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R166"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>166JinJBaoXWangHPanHZhangYWuXRnai-induced down-regulation of mecp2 expression in the rat brainInt J Dev Neurosci20082645746518396005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R167"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>167CukierHNPerezAMCollinsALZhouZZoghbiHYBotasJGenetic modifiers of mecp2 function in drosophilaPLoS Genet20084e100017918773074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R168"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>168PietriTRomanACGuyonNRomanoSAWashbournePMoensCBde PolaviejaGGSumbreGThe first mecp2-null zebrafish model shows altered motor behaviorsFront Neural Circuits2013711823874272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R169"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>169ChaoHTChenHSamacoRCXueMChahrourMYooJNeulJLGongSLuHCHeintzNDysfunction in gaba signalling mediates autism-like stereotypies and rett syndrome phenotypesNature201046826326921068835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R170"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>170MaezawaIJinLWRett syndrome microglia damage dendrites and synapses by the elevated release of glutamateJ Neurosci2010305346535620392956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R171"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>171GemelliTBertonONelsonEDPerrottiLIJaenischRMonteggiaLMPostnatal loss of methyl-cpg binding protein 2 in the forebrain is sufficient to mediate behavioral aspects of rett syndrome in miceBiol Psychiat20065946847616199017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R172"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>172EbertDHGabelHWRobinsonNDKastanNRHuLSCohenSNavarroAJLystMJEkiertRBirdAPActivity-dependent phosphorylation of mecp2 threonine 308 regulates interaction with ncorNature201349934134523770587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R173"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>173LystMJEkiertREbertDHMerusiCNowakJSelfridgeJGuyJKastanNRRobinsonNDde Lima AlvesFRett syndrome mutations abolish the interaction of mecp2 with the ncor/smrt co-repressorNat Neurosci20131689890223770565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R174"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>174GoffinDAllenMZhangLAmorimMWangITReyesARMercado-BertonAOngCCohenSHuLRett syndrome mutation mecp2 t158a disrupts DNA binding, protein stability and erp responsesNat Neurosci201215274283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Human diseases associated with Methyl CpG binding protein 2 (MeCP2) and gender mostly affected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Gender mostly affected </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>References </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Rett Syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Females (also males with kleinfelter syndrome 47 XXY, or somatic mosaicism) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>[15,62,63,148] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>MECP2 duplication disorder </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>[81–83] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Angelman Syndrome </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Females </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>[91,93] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>X-linked mental retardation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>[86,94,95] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Severe neonatal encephalopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>[95,97,98] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Autism </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Both </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>[100–102] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Both (Studies from animal models only) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>[109,110,113] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Huntington’s disease </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Both </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>[117] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Early-onset schizophrenia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Both </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>[106] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Cancers </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Both </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>[119–128,149] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Systemic lupus erythematosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Females </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>[56,133,134] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Rheumatoid arthritis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Females </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>[140,141] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Hirschsprung’s disease </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>[147] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Animal models of MeCP2 dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="cols"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Animal models </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Description </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>References </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Mouse  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 null mouse models: </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Exon 3 and 4 deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 expression and function are abolished </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Unusual gait, hindlimb clasping, seizures, irregular breathing </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>[150,151] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Mecp2tm1.1bird </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Mecp2tm1.Tam </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Mecp2lox Stop/y or Mecp2tm2.bird </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Gene silencing by Cre recombinase insertion into intron 2.No protein is detected (behaves as a null allele) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Phenotypes similar to the null mice with abnormal behavior, RTT-like phenotypes and breathing irregularities. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>[153] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 mutant mice: </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Mecp2tm1.1jae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Exon 3 deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>MeCP2 expression and function are abolished. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Neurological phenotype similar to Mecp2 null mice, however lifespan is longer. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>[155] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Mecp2308 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Introduction of a premature STOP codon in exon 4.Truncated MeCP2 protein with residual unknown function </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Milder neurological phenotype compared to Mecp2 null mice </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>[156] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 conditional-mutant mice: </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>Nestin-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Brain-specific deletion </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Similar to Mecp2 null mice except for breathing phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>[150,155] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Sim 1-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Selective deletion in neurons of hypothalamus and amygdala </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Abnormal stress response, stranger aggression </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>[157] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>TH-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Selective deletion in dopaminergic and noradrenergic neurons. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Hypoactivity, reduced expression of tyrosine hydroxylase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>[158,159] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>CamKII-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Forebrain-specific deletion </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Impaired motor co-ordination, anxiety </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>[171] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>Pet1-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>Selective deletion in serotonergic neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Increased aggression, hyperactivity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>[159] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Viaat-cre knockout </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>Selective deletion in GABAergic neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>Reduced lifespan, self-mutilation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>[169] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Mice overexpressing MECP2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>MeCP2Tg1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>MECP2 overexpression in all cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Seizures, premature death, abnormal social behaviors, hypoactivity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>[160] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>Tau-MECP2-rescue </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>MECP2 overexpression in neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>Hypoactivity, impaired cognition </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>[81] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>Rett Syndrome mouse models: </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Mecp2R168X </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Premature STOP codon at amino acid 168 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Hindlimb clasping, breathing irregularities </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>[161] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>Mecp2A140V </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Missense mutation that produces mutant MeCP2 protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>Normal life span, reduced dendrite branching </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>[162] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>Mecp2T308A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Knock-in mutation that causes loss of interaction with NCoR complex </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>Motor abnormalities, hindlimb clasping </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>[172] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>Mecp2R306C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Knock-in mutation that causes loss of interaction with NCoR/SMRT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Impaired motor function, hindlimb clasping </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>[173] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>Mecp2T158A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Knock-in mutation that disrupts protein stability </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Developmental regression, hypoactivity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>[174] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>Mecp2-e1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>Point mutation of ATG in exon 1 to TTG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>Forelimb stereotypy, hindlimb clasping, excessive grooming, and hypoactivity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>[164] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>Mecp2S80A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>Knock-in mouse model with abolished phosphorylation at S80. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>Reduced locomotion similar to that of Mecp2 null mice and RTT patients </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>[165] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>Mecp2S421A;S424A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>Double mutant mouse model which lacks phosphorylation at both S421A and S424A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>Phenotypes opposite to Mecp2S80A mice (increased locomotion) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>[165] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>Mecp2 Mouse models of phenotypic rescue </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>Mecp2lox Stop/y;cre ER </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>Activation of Mecp2 gene in Mecp2l°x St°p/y mouse model by cre-ER and Tamoxifen injections. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>Rescued majority of RTT phenotypes including increased lifespan, delayed disease progression </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>[153] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Mecp2+/ ; CAGGS LSL Mecp2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>Conditional activation (rescue) of Mecp2 gene in brain using synthetic CAGGS promoter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>Partial rescue of RTT phenotypes, including delayed disease progression, reduced lethality and improved behaviors </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>[154] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>Rat  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>Mecp2-sh-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>Viral mediated RNAi-induced downregulation of Mecp2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>Transient neurobehavioral abnormalities, reduced Bdnf expression in hippocampus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>[166] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>Zebrafish  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>Mecp2Q63 *. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>Nonsense mutation and a truncation of MeCP2 at position 63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>Altered motor behaviors, however viable and fertile </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>[168] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>Drosophila  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>GMR-Gal4:UAS-MeCP2 R106W/+.GMR-Gal4:UAS-MeCP2 R294X/+. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of mutant MeCP2 protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>Locomotar dysfunction, external eye disruption </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>[167] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
