<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Qual Life Outcomes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Qual Life Outcomes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7525</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6035403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">963</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-018-0963-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Effect of low-normal and high-normal IGF-1 levels on memory and wellbeing during growth hormone replacement therapy: a randomized clinical trial in adult growth hormone deficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0006-7726</contrib-id><name><surname>van Bunderen</surname><given-names>Christa C.</given-names></name><address><phone>0031 (0) 204444444</phone><email>c.vanbunderen@vumc.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deijen</surname><given-names>Jan Berend</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drent</surname><given-names>Madeleine L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0435 165X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16872.3a</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, section of Endocrinology, Neuroscience Campus Amsterdam, </institution><institution>VU University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>De Boelelaan 1117, 1081 HV Amsterdam, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1754 9227</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12380.38</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Neuropsychology, </institution><institution>VU University, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, the Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to investigate the effect of low-normal and high-normal levels of IGF-1 in growth hormone (GH) deficient adults on cognition and wellbeing during GH treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>A randomized, open-label, clinical trial including 32 subjects receiving GH therapy for at least 1 year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Subjects were randomized to receive either a decrease (IGF-1 target level of − 2 to − 1 SDS) or an increase of their daily GH dose (IGF-1 target level of 1 to 2 SDS) for a period of 24 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Memory was measured by the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery, selecting the Pattern Recognition Memory task and the Spatial Working Memory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Wellbeing was measured as mood by the Profile of Moods States questionnaire, and quality of life by the Nottingham Health Profile and QoL Assessment in GH Deficiency in Adults questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Data from 30 subjects (65.6% male, mean age 46.6 (9.9 SD) years), who fulfilled the target levels, were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Females in the low dose treatment arm were found to have a better working memory and a better strategic memory control after 24 weeks as opposed to the females in the high treatment arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>With respect to mood, the decrease in IGF-1 levels in females within the low treatment arm was associated with more fatigue and less vigor. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The adjustment of GH dose in female patients seems to have a narrow window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A dose too high may impair prefrontal cognitive functioning, while a dose too low may result in decreased vigor. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par5"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This study is registered with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, number NCT01877512. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Growth hormone deficiency</kwd><kwd>Growth hormone treatment</kwd><kwd>Cognition</kwd><kwd>Memory</kwd><kwd>Mood</kwd><kwd>Insulin-like growth factor-1</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001826</institution-id><institution>ZonMw</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>92003591</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>van Bunderen</surname><given-names>Christa C.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004319</institution-id><institution>Pfizer</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Growth hormone (GH) deficiency in adults may lead to a broad range of detrimental physical and/or psychological effects [1], while there is evidence that GH treatment has a positive effect on body composition, lipid profile, hypertension, bone density, and quality of life (QoL) [2–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>With respect to psychological functions, GH deficiency has been found to be associated with cognitive deficits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For example, specific cognitive deficits observed are lapses of attention, difficulty in concentrating, forgetfulness, impaired spatial learning and lower perceptual speed [6–9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Also, GH deficiency is accompanied with subnormal IQ scores, memory impairment, and a low educational level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>These manifestations are associated with a low insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) concentration, suggesting that subnormal cognitive performance is related to GH deficiency [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Beyond cognitive impairment, GH deficiency has been found to worsen wellbeing as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In several studies, GH deficient patients were found to show emotional instability, a lack of energy, difficulties in social and sexual functioning, and to suffer from sleeping problems [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In clinical studies, GH replacement therapy appeared to improve the impaired cognitive and wellbeing in GH deficient adults [11–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, in several studies an absence of any GH treatment effect on cognitive functions has also been observed [16–19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Studies on the effects of GH treatment on wellbeing also show conflicting results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>For instance, there are reports that GH therapy improves self-perceived wellbeing, increases energy and decreases pain, anxiety and depression [14, 15, 20–23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, no changes in psychological wellbeing or QoL after GH treatment have been found as well [13, 16, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Whether this is tested by generic or disease-specific questionnaire should not be discarded when interpreting these negative results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Also, a linear association of psychological impairment with circulating IGF-1 level is demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Indeed, higher IGF-1 levels in GH deficient patients and healthy subjects have been found to be associated with a better cognitive functioning [25–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>With respect to mood, higher IGF-1 levels in adults with GH deficiency were found to be associated with less depression, fatigue, tension, anxiety and with more vigor [28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The effect of GH and IGF-1 on cognitive functioning and wellbeing may be mediated through mechanisms involving the stimulation of the GH and IGF-1 receptors in the brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>GH and IGF-1 can pass the blood-brain barrier and there are binding-sites for GH and IGF-1 in discrete regions of the brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>GH binding sites have been demonstrated in the choroid plexus, hypothalamus, hippocampus and frontal cortex [30, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Also for IGF-1 there are specific binding sites identified, such as in the choroid plexus, frontal cortex, putamen, hippocampus, cerebellum, amygdala, thalamus and substantia nigra [32, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Currently, there is substantial evidence that IGF-1 is involved in neuroprotection, regeneration and brain plasticity [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Anabolic hormones may also have direct effect on cells producing ß-endorphin and this could be one of the mechanisms behind the improvement of wellbeing seen during GH treatment [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The above cited studies did not distinguish between males and females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>However, it may be important to take gender differences into account. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Although healthy females secrete 2–3 fold greater amounts of GH than males their IGF-1 levels are similar to those of males [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>As the cognitive effects of GH treatment may be dependent on the levels of both GH and IGF-1 obtained by GH treatment, cognitive effects may be expected to be different in males and females. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The aim of the present study was to investigate the effect of low-normal and high-normal levels of IGF-1 in GH deficient adults on cognition and wellbeing during GH treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that higher levels of IGF-1 would improve memory and wellbeing, with different effects in females than in males. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This study presents outcome data on cognition and wellbeing from a randomized, open-label, clinical trial conducted at one university hospital (VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands) which compared de- and increasing GH dose for 24 weeks with low-normal and high-normal IGF-1 target levels for efficacy and safety measures of GH replacement therapy [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>At entry, subjects were receiving GH treatment according to general clinical practice (daily subcutaneous injections of somatropin using automated pen systems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Subjects were selected on having an IGF-1 concentration between − 1 and 1 standard deviation score (SDS) during GH replacement therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Randomization was done by a computer-generated random sequence and was stratified by gender. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Subjects were randomized to receive either a decrease of their regular dose of GH treatment (IGF-1 target level of − 2 to − 1 SDS) (low dose = LD group), or an increase of their regular dose (IGF-1 target level of 1 to 2 SDS) (high dose = HD group), for 24 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>After 4 weeks adjustment of GH dose was initiated when the target level of IGF-1 was not reached. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>At visit one (baseline) and visit two (after 24 weeks) blood samples were drawn and measurements were performed to assess cognition and wellbeing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The study group consisted of 32 adult patients with documented severe GH deficiency and more than 1 year of GH treatment, with an IGF-1 level between − 1 and 1 SD score (SDS), stable for at least 6 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Other pituitary hormone deficiencies had to be substituted when indicated and be stable for at least 6 months and during follow up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Severe GH deficiency was diagnosed prior to the study and defined according to the consensus guidelines of the GH Research Society for the diagnosis and treatment of adults with GH deficiency [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Patients were not eligible if they had a recent or current malignancy, craniopharyngioma as cause of hypopituitarism, were (planning on becoming) pregnant, or had a cardiovascular event within 1 year before recruitment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Patients were included after oral information and signed informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The study was performed according to Good Clinical Practice and the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This study is registered with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, number NCT01877512 [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Biochemical methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were drawn after an overnight fast prior to every visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Total IGF-1 was measured by a non-competitive (sandwich), chemiluminescence immunoassay (Liaison, DiaSorin S.p.A., Italy). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Memory </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Cognition was tested by two tasks for visual memory and executive function using the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB) [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Subjects were tested individually in a sound attenuated room by the same investigator at the same time period of the day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The whole test procedure took about 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The CANTAB tests were conducted using a 17" ELO touch screen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A short motor screening task was performed to ensure participants were unimpaired in their ability to respond to the stimuli, and to familiarize them with the computerized procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The performance on the following tests was evaluated: 1) the Pattern Recognition Memory (PRM) task to investigate visual pattern recognition memory in a 2-choice forced discrimination paradigm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The PRM task involves temporal lobe function [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The outcome measure is the percentage of correctly recalled visual patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>2) The Spatial Working Memory (SWM) task to investigate executive function, working memory, and planning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>As these functions are all associated with the frontal area of the brain the SWM is considered to involve frontal lobe function [41, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The selected outcome measures were the number of errors made during the test (total errors) and a score for the use of a strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A high strategy score represents poor strategy use [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Wellbeing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>To assess mood the Profile of Moods States (POMS) questionnaire was administered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A shortened Dutch version of 32 items was used for measuring depression, anger, fatigue, tension, and vigor [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The POMS answers are graded on a 5-point scale ranging from ‘not at all’ (scale 0) to ‘extremely’ (scale 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Higher scores for depression (scores 0–32), anger (scores 0–28), fatigue (scores 0–24) and tension (scores 0–24) reflect a negative mood; higher scores for vigor (scores 0–20) reflect a better mood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>QoL was assessed by using two different questionnaires, one disease-specific and one general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The disease-specific questionnaire was the Dutch version of the QoL Assessment of GH deficiency in Adults (QoL-AGHDA) including 25 questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The general questionnaire was the Nottingham Health Profile (NHP), a frequently used health status instrument with 38 dichotomous items that measures physical, emotional, and social distress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>It yields an overall score and sub-section scores (physical mobility, energy, pain, emotional reactions, sleep, and social isolation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>High scores indicate a poor QoL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Categorical baseline data are expressed as percentage and continuous data as mean (SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Categorical data were analyzed by means of chi square tests and continuous data by means of independent t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>For between-group differences for change over time General Linear Model for repeated measures was used with Group (HD versus LD) and Gender as between subjects factor, and Measurement (baseline versus week 24) as repeated measures factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>If an interaction between Group, Measurement and Gender was observed, separate ANOVAs per gender with Group as between subjects factor and Measurement as repeated measures factor were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>For the different outcome measures baseline values served as covariates to adjust for regression to the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Moreover, at baseline the LD and HD male groups differed with respect to childhood onset (CO) and adult onset (AO) GH deficiency and IGF-1 SDS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>As a t-test indicated that the mean IGF-1 SDS in the CO group was significant higher than that in the AO group (mean IGF-1 SDS in CO: 0.24 and in AO: − 0.47, t(15) = 3.20, p = 0.006), IGF-1 SDS was also used as covariate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Two sided P values 0.05 or less were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In case of hypotheses with expected results in one direction one-tailed t-tests (which is indicated in the text) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were performed by the statistical software package IBM SPSS statistics 20.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Between May 31, 2013, and April 11, 2014, we enrolled 32 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>An invitation was send to 92 eligible patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Reasons for not participating were lack of time, travel distance, or reluctance to risk deterioration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Table 1 shows the baseline characteristics of the study groups stratified by gender. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The groups were mostly comparable, except for two significant differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>First, the presence of males with CO GH deficiency in the LD group was higher than that in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Second, the IGF-1 SDS of the males was higher in the LD group than in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Most prevalent underlying diagnosis of GH deficiency was a pituitary tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Off all 13 pituitary tumors, six were a non-secreting adenoma, five a prolactinoma, and two were an ACTH producing adenoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Other etiologies included radiotherapy for other brain tumors, pituitary apoplexia, empty sella, head trauma, idiopathic, or congenital GH deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The medical history (for CVD and diabetes mellitus), smoking habits and alcohol use was similar between all groups.Table 1Baseline characteristics for males and females of the low dose group (IGF-1 target level between − 2 and − 1 SDS) and the high dose group (IGF-1 target level between 1 and 2 SDS)MalesFemalesLow Dosen = 10High Dosen = 11Low Dosen = 6High Dosen = 5Age (years)46.3 (11.2)47.4 (8.9)49.1 (10.7)44.3 (10.9)CO GH deficiency (%)8027*330Duration GH treatment (years)18.6 (9.4)13.4 (6.3)8.9 (5.3)4.8 (1.8)IGF-1 in SDS0.29 (0.62)−0.38 (0.38)**−0.08 (0.57)− 0.03 (0.42)BMI (kg/m2)25.6 (3.4)28.6 (3.8)33 (14.5)29 (5.2)Cranial radiotherapy (%)101800Pituitary surgery (%)10541740Isolated GH deficiency (%)2026330LH/FSH deficiency (%)80453340TSH deficiency (%)70641780ACTH deficiency (%)80643360ADH deficiency (%)03600Diabetes mellitus (%)100330CVD (%)0185040Married (%)60738360Education 10–13 years (%)30181640Education &gt; 13 years (%)70828360Values are mean (SD) unless stated otherwiseCO childhood onset GH deficiency, GH growth hormone, IGF-1 in SDS insulin like growth factor-1 in standard deviation score, BMI body mass index, LH/FSH luteinising hormone/follicle stimulating hormone, TSH thyroid stimulating hormone, ACTH adrenocorticotropic hormone, ADH antidiuretic hormone, CVD cardiovascular disease*p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 (low dose versus high dose) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Follow up </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>After start of the study one subject withdrew due to personal reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>One subject was excluded from the analyses due to the inability to reach the proper IGF-1 target level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The final analyses were conducted with 15 subjects in the LD group and 15 subjects in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In males, the IGF-1 concentration decreased from 23.11 (SD 5.18) at baseline to 12.98 (SD 2.0) nmol/L (p &lt; 0.001) after 24 weeks in the LD group, and increased from 18.40 (SD 3.31) to 28.2 (SD 5.27) nmol/L (p = 0.002) in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In females, the IGF-1 concentration decreased from 18.83 (SD 3.19) at baseline to 11.62 (SD 2.56) nmol/L (p = 0.02) after 24 weeks in the LD group, and increased from 18.80 (SD 1.48) to 28.0 (SD 5.52) nmol/L (p = 0.01) in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 shows the IGF-1 levels in standard deviation scores (SDS) during follow up for both treatment regimes stratified by gender. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows the different GH doses stratified by gender before and after follow up.Fig. 1Mean serum total IGF-1 level in SD score (± SEM) at baseline, after 4 weeks of GH treatment and at end of follow up in the low dose (LD) and high dose (HD) female and male groupTable 2Different GH doses stratified by gender at baseline and after follow upLow DoseHigh DoseGH dose at baseline (mg/day)Male0.20(0.25)0.13(0.23)female0.38(0.39)0.50(0.30)GH dose at week 24 (mg/day)Male0.08(0.06)0.40(0.28)female0.15(0.21)1.00(0.83)Values are median (interquartile range) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Memory </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>With respect to SWM Total Errors, there was a significant interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender, F(1,26) = 19.23, p &lt; 0.001, partial η2 = 0.42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Analyses performed separately for each gender with SWM Total Errors score and IGF-1 SDS at baseline as covariate, revealed in the female group a significant interaction between Group and Measurement, F(1,7) = 10.99, p = 0.02, partial η2 = 0.61. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Post hoc t-tests indicated a significant lower SWM Total Errors score of the females in the LD group at week 24 as compared to baseline, t(5) = 4.14, p = 0.009. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>No significant effect was found in males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that females in the LD group perform better on the SWM task after 24 weeks of treatment compared to the HD group, and compared to baseline (Fig. 2).Fig. 2Mean (± SEM) and individual SWM Total Error scores of females and males in the low dose (dashed line) and high dose (solid line) groups at baseline and at week 24 (lower scores meaning better performance). * p &lt; 0.05 for mean score at week 24 compared to baseline per group </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>With respect to SWM Strategy, there was a significant interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender, F(1,26) = 4,22, p = 0.05, partial η2 = 0.14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Analyses performed separately for each gender with SWM Strategy score and IGF-1 SDS at baseline as covariate, revealed in the female group, but not in the male group, a marginally significant interaction between Group and Measurement, F(1,7) = 5.16, p = 0.057, partial η2 = 0.42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Post hoc t-tests did not indicate a significant lower SWM Strategy score of the females in the LD nor in the HD group at week 24 as compared to baseline (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that females in the LD group perform better on the SWM task after 24 weeks of treatment compared to the HD group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>With respect to the PRM test scores no significant results were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>All means (SD) of the memory tests are summarized in Table 3.Table 3Mean (SD) of cognitive tests and mood scales in males and females at baseline and week 24 for the low and high dose groupMalesFemalesLow Dosen = 9High Dosen = 10Low Dosen = 6High Dosen = 5BaselineWeek 24BaselineWeek 24BaselineWeek 24BaselineWeek 24MEMORY PRM (%)91.2 (8.7)92.6 (5.8)85.8 (15.2)91.2 (8.2)88.9 (8.2)90.3 (10.1)91.7 (8.3)91.7 (11.4) SWM TE15.3 (19.7)16.8 (14.7)28 (24.7)21.7 (17.2)42 (24.9)26(23.3)**27.4 (9.4)34.4 (14.3) SWM STR38.3 (11.1)36.3 (8.8)43.3 (9)40.1(7.8)**44.3 (6.4)40.8 (9.4)43.4 (2.1)46 (3.5)MOOD Depression2.9 (3.2)4.1 (6.7)2.6 (3.3)1.2 (2.5)4.3 (4.9)7 (7.3)5.2 (3.1)5 (6) Anger5.4 (6.2)4.9 (5.4)4.8 (4.7)4.2 (4.2)9 (7.7)7 (5.8)5.2 (5.7)5.6 (7.2) Fatigue5.4 (6)5.3 (6.6)3.9 (3.4)3 (1.8)9.8 (7.5)13.2 (3.7)4.4 (4.7)3.6 (3.8) Tension3 (2.9)3.7 (4)4.5 (4.6)3.7 (3.6)4.5 (4.6)7.8 (5.3)6.2 (5.5)5 (5.4)* Vigor11.3 (4.1)12.8 (4.8)12.5 (3.4)11.8 (3.9)11.5 (5.2)7.8 (4)*12.8 (1.5)12 (2.7)PRM (%) = Pattern Recognition Memory (percent correct)SWM TE Spatial Working Memory Total Errors, SWM STR Spatial Working Memory Strategy* p &lt; 0.05, ** p ≤ 0.01; week 24 versus baseline </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Wellbeing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>With respect to mood scores for Anger, Depression and Tension no significant interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender and Measurement x Group per gender was found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>All means (SD) of the mood scales are shown in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>With respect to Fatigue, there was a significant interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender with Fatigue score and IGF-1 SDS at baseline as covariates, F(1,24) = 5.97, p = 0.02, partial η2 = 0.20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>ANOVAs separately performed for males and females with Fatigue score and IGF-1 SDS at baseline as covariates yielded no significant interaction effect in males between Group and Measurement on Fatigue (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In females, a significant interaction was found between Group and Measurement, F(1,7) = 7.9, p = 0.03, partial η2 = 0.53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Post hoc t-tests did not indicate any significant difference in Fatigue score of the females in the LD or HD group at week 24 as compared to baseline (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Thus, females within the LD group show a higher increase in Fatigue after 24 weeks of treatment relative to females in the HD group (Fig. 3).Fig. 3Mean (± SEM) and individual POMS Fatigue and Vigor scores of females and males in the low dose (dashed line) and high dose (solid line) groups at baseline and at week 24 (higher scores meaning more fatigue and more vigor). * p &lt; 0.05 for mean score at week 24 compared to baseline per group </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>With respect to Vigor, the interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender approached significance, F(1,26) = 3.79, p = 0.06, partial η2 = 0.13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Therefore analyses were performed separately for males and females with Vigor score and IGF-1 SDS at baseline as covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>With respect to males no significant interaction effect between Group and Measurement was found (p &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In females, a significant interaction was found between Group and Measurement, F(1,7) = 29.8, p = 0.001, partial η2 = 0.81. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Post hoc t-tests indicated a significant lower Vigor score of the females in the LD group at week 24 as compared to baseline, t(5) = 3.38, p = 0.02. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Thus, females within the LD group show a reduced Vigor after 24 weeks of treatment compared to the HD group, and compared to baseline (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>With respect to QoL outcome scores no significant interaction for Measurement x Group x Gender and Measurement x Group per gender was found. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The present study demonstrated that, with respect to cognitive functioning as well as to wellbeing, gender appeared to render different effects of low and high dose GH treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Notably, these effects were not observed in all cognitive domains studied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The PRM subtest is a visual recognition memory task relying on medial temporal lobe functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the SWM task establishes working memory and strategic memory control, which functions rely on frontal lobe functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In the present study no differential effects of the low and high dose GH treatment were found in males nor in females, with respect to PRM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it may be concluded that the change in GH treatment did not specifically affect medial temporal lobe functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In contrast, SWM was affected by the different GH doses, but only in females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In males the low and high dose groups did not have a different effect on SWM, while in females a clear distinction could be made between the effects of the low and the high dose group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Females in the LD group were found to have a better working memory after 24 weeks as opposed to the females in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In addition, the females in the LD group showed better strategic memory control after 24 weeks, as opposed to the females in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>These results clearly indicate that in females cognitive performance relying on frontal lobe functioning benefits from a LD GH treatment, but not from an increased GH dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>At the moment that the GH dose was decreased or increased the GH-deficient patients in the present study were already treated with GH for more than 1 year (and IGF-1 levels being between − 1 and 1 SDS for at least 6 months). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As a decrease of the previously given dose benefits the cognitive functioning in females, the original dose may have also been too high to be optimal for cognitive function, in particular frontal lobe mediated memory processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>It may well be true that the IGF-1 levels obtained during long-term GH administration are too high to preserve or improve memory functions, and may even result in memory impairment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In a former study on the cognitive effects of GH treatment in adult survivors of childhood leukaemia, the increase in IGF-1 during the first treatment year was accompanied by a decrease in short-term memory performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Notably, the decrease in IGF-1 in the second treatment year was accompanied by an improvement of memory performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The authors conclude that if the increase in GH-induced IGF-1 levels is too high memory functions may be impaired, whereas this memory impairment may be halted when IGF-1 levels are decreased [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The results of the present study in females seem to have some similarity with those findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Thus, the chronically given GH dose may have impaired memory functions, while reducing the dose counteracted the harmful effects on memory function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The finding that specifically frontal memory function is affected may be explained by different IGF-1 receptor densities in temporal and frontal brain area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The highest densities of IGF-1 receptors have been found in the hippocampus, amygdala and parahippocampal gyrus, while intermediate densities were observed in the cerebral cortex [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Thus, the lower amount of IGF-1 receptors in the frontal cortex compared to that of IGF-1 receptors in the temporal area may account for a different effect of reduced IGF-1 levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It may be that higher levels of IGF-1 result in downregulation, and lower levels of IGF-1 in upregulation of IGF-1 receptors in the frontal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The latter leads to a more sensitive neuronal system which may account for better cognitive function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The density of IGF-1 receptors in the temporal lobe may be that high, that the sensitivity of the neuronal system has already reached its upper limit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>However, more basic research is needed to verify this theory. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>With respect to wellbeing, and in particular to mood, the findings were opposite to those concerning cognition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Females in the LD group were found to have a reduced vigor and increased fatigue after 24 weeks as opposed to the females in the HD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In males no differences were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>It may thus be concluded that the decrease of GH dose is detrimental for the subjectively perceived vitality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Vigor has been found to be quite closely associated with IGF-1 levels [28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The present finding that the decrease in IGF-1 levels is associated with more fatigue and less vigor is in line with these former findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, we observed these negative effects of decreased IGF-1 levels on these mood states only in females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>One explanation for the lack of effect in the male patients could be the adaptation phenomenon observed in GH deficiency, since CO GH deficiency was more prevalent in the male group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Patients with GH deficiency since childhood might not experience the effect of changing GH dose on mood and QoL as patients with adult onset GH deficiency might since the latter have experienced a better mood before. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Also, because interrelations between sleep and GH regulation are well documented [46, 47], the low energy and fatigue frequently seen in subjects with GH deficiency could partly reflect alterations of sleep quality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Women report a poorer sleep quality than men across a wide age range [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The perception of poorer sleep quality in women may be influenced by affective disorders, which are more common in women and may contribute to a higher incidence of insomnia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Women are at a 40% greater risk for developing insomnia, and the risk ratio grows with age [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Indeed, in the present study females reported a larger percentage of sleep problems (NHP) at baseline than males (36% versus 11%, p = 0.04, one-tailed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the percentage of reported sleep problems was larger compared to baseline in females in LD group (37% versus 27%, p = 0.04, one-tailed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Because especially women appear to suffer from sleep disturbances, their sleep quality may benefit most by GH treatment and be most impaired by lowering the GH dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>All together, the reduced vigor may be the consequence of an increase in sleep disturbances in particularly females in the LD group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In the present study no differential effects of the low and high dose GH treatment were found in males nor in females, with respect to QoL scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>A beneficial effect of GH treatment on QoL has been demonstrated in several (mainly long duration) studies reviewed by Hazem et al. [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Follow up duration and sample size of the present study might have been insufficient to monitor significant differential effects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The strength of the present study is that the effect of changing the GH dose was examined concerning memory and wellbeing, separately in females and males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In addition, the effect sizes of the results for memory and vigor appeared to be quite high, indicating that the effects of lowering the GH dose are quite substantial and may be assumed to have clinical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A limitation of the study is that the distinction between males and females resulted in quite small sample sizes, with a relative heterogeneous aspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it may be possible that more subtle differences in memory or wellbeing in the low and high dose group could not be observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Next to the sample size, an important limitation is the open-label design, in particular when investigating wellbeing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>We recommend that in future research the effects of GH treatment on memory and wellbeing will be studied in larger samples of male and female patient groups in blinded randomized clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The present results indicate that changing the regular GH dose may have a considerable impact on psychological functioning of female patients with GH deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>As could be expected, lowering the dose can result in decreased vigor, which may be associated with a deteriorated sleep quality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, a lower dose in females seems to improve prefrontal memory functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This could be the consequence of a maintenance dose too high for optimal cognitive functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Taking these differential effects on cognition and mood into account, the adjustment of GH dose in female patients seems to have a narrow window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A dose too high may impair prefrontal cognitive functioning, while a dose too low may result in decreased vigor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Thus, the present results suggest that a “fine-tuned” intermediate dose may be the best option for maintaining an optimal mental status in female patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>We direct special gratitude to all participating patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p id="Par31"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par32"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>CCVB is supported by an AGIKO grant of The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development (ZonMw) (grant number: 92003591). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>This work was partly supported by an investigator-initiated grant from Pfizer bv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The funding sources had no involvement in study design, collection, analysis and interpretation of data, writing of the report, and in the decision to submit the article for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>All authors contributed equally to this work. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Competing interest</title><p id="Par33">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par34">Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam. All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par36">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>1.de BoerHBlokGJVan der VeenEAClinical aspects of growth hormone deficiency in adultsEndocr Rev199516638610.1210/er.16.1.63<?supplied-pmid 7758433?>7758433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>2.AbsRFeldt-RasmussenUMattssonAFMonsonJPBengtssonBAGothMIDeterminants of cardiovascular risk in 2589 hypopituitary GH-deficient adults - a KIMS database analysisEur J Endocrinol2006155799010.1530/eje.1.02179<?supplied-pmid 16793953?>16793953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>3.AttanasioAFBatesPCHoKKYWebbSMRossRJStrasburgerCJHuman growth hormone replacement in adult hypopituitary patients: long-term effects on body composition and lipid status--3-year results from the HypoCCS databaseJ Clin Endocrinol Metab20028716001606<?supplied-pmid 11932289?>11932289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>4.MaisonPGriffinSNicoue-BeglahMHaddadNBalkauBChansonPImpact of growth hormone (GH) treatment on cardiovascular risk factors in GH-deficient adults: a Metaanalysis of blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled trialsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2004892192219910.1210/jc.2003-030840<?supplied-pmid 15126541?>15126541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>5.SalomonFCuneoRCHespRSonksenPHThe effects of treatment with recombinant human growth hormone on body composition and metabolism in adults with growth hormone deficiencyN Engl J Med19893211797180310.1056/NEJM198912283212605<?supplied-pmid 2687691?>2687691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>6.BulowBHagmarLOrbaekPOsterbergKErfurthEMHigh incidence of mental disorders, reduced mental well-being and cognitive function in hypopituitary women with GH deficiency treated for pituitary diseaseClin Endocrinol20025618319310.1046/j.0300-0664.2001.01461.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>7.HuntSMMcKennaSPDowardLCPreliminary report on the development of a disease-specific instrument for assessing quality of life of adults with growth hormone deficiencyActa Endocrinol1993128Suppl 23740<?supplied-pmid 8342391?>8342391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>8.McGauleyGCuneoRSalomonFSonksenPHGrowth hormone deficiency and quality of lifeHorm Res199645343710.1159/000184756<?supplied-pmid 8742116?>8742116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>9.RosenTWirenLWilhelmsenLWiklundIBengtssonBADecreased psychological well-being in adult patients with growth hormone deficiencyClin Endocrinol19944011111610.1111/j.1365-2265.1994.tb02452.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>10.DeijenJBde BoerHBlokGJVan der VeenEACognitive impairments and mood disturbances in growth hormone deficient menPsychoneuroendocrinology19962131332210.1016/0306-4530(95)00050-X<?supplied-pmid 8817729?>8817729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>11.AlmqvistOThorenMSaafMErikssonOEffects of growth hormone substitution on mental performance in adults with growth hormone deficiency: a pilot studyPsychoneuroendocrinology19861134735210.1016/0306-4530(86)90020-X<?supplied-pmid 3786639?>3786639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>12.ArwertLIVeltmanDJDeijenJBvan DamPSDrentMLEffects of growth hormone substitution therapy on cognitive functioning in growth hormone deficient patients: a functional MRI studyNeuroendocrinology200683121910.1159/000093337<?supplied-pmid 16707911?>16707911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>13.DeijenJBde BoerHVan der VeenEACognitive changes during growth hormone replacement in adult menPsychoneuroendocrinology199823455510.1016/S0306-4530(97)00092-9<?supplied-pmid 9618751?>9618751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>14.SartorioAMolinariERivaGContiAMorabitoFFagliaGGrowth hormone treatment in adults with childhood onset growth hormone deficiency: effects on psychological capabilitiesHorm Res19954461110.1159/000184582<?supplied-pmid 7649527?>7649527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>15.SoaresCNMusolinoNRCunha NetoMCairesMARosenthalMCCamargoCPBronsteinMDImpact of recombinant human growth hormone (RH-GH) treatment on psychiatric, neuropsychological and clinical profiles of GH deficient adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>A placebo-controlled trialArq Neuropsiquiatr19995718218910.1590/S0004-282X1999000200003<?supplied-pmid 10412515?>10412515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>16.BaumHBKatznelsonLShermanJCBillerBMHaydenDLSchoenfeldDAEffects of physiological growth hormone (GH) therapy on cognition and quality of life in patients with adult-onset GH deficiencyJ Clin Endocrinol Metab19988331843189<?supplied-pmid 9745423?>9745423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>17.DegerbladMAlmkvistOGrunditzRHallKKaijserLKnutssonEPhysical and psychological capabilities during substitution therapy with recombinant growth hormone in adults with growth hormone deficiencyActa Endocrinol1990123185193<?supplied-pmid 2220259?>2220259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>18.OertelHSchneiderHJStallaGKHolsboerFZihlJThe effect of growth hormone substitution on cognitive performance in adult patients with hypopituitarismPsychoneuroendocrinology20042983985010.1016/S0306-4530(03)00151-3<?supplied-pmid 15177699?>15177699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>19.SathiavageeswaranMBurmanPLawrenceDHarrisAGFalletiMGMaruffPWassJEffects of GH on cognitive function in elderly patients with adult-onset GH deficiency: a placebo-controlled 12-month studyEur J Endocrinol200715643944710.1530/eje.1.02346<?supplied-pmid 17389458?>17389458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>20.BurmanPBromanJEHettaJWiklundIErfurthEMHaggEKarlssonFAQuality of life in adults with growth hormone (GH) deficiency: response to treatment with recombinant human GH in a placebo-controlled 21-month trialJ Clin Endocrinol Metab1995803585359010.1210/jcem.80.12.8530603<?supplied-pmid 8530603?>8530603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>21.CarrollPVLittlewoodRWeissbergerAJBogalhoPMcGauleyGSonksenPHRussell-JonesDLThe effects of two doses of replacement growth hormone on the biochemical, body composition and psychological profiles of growth hormone-deficient adultsEur J Endocrinol199713714615310.1530/eje.0.1370146<?supplied-pmid 9272102?>9272102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>22.CuneoRCJuddSWallaceJDPerry-KeeneDBurgerHLim-TioSThe Australian multicenter trial of growth hormone (GH) treatment in GH-deficient adultsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab199883107116<?supplied-pmid 9435425?>9435425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>23.WirenLJohannssonGBengtssonBAA prospective investigation of quality of life and psychological well-being after the discontinuation of GH treatment in adolescent patients who had GH deficiency during childhoodJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2001863494349810.1210/jcem.86.8.7709<?supplied-pmid 11502769?>11502769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>24.ArwertLIDeijenJBWitloxJDrentMLThe influence of growth hormone (GH) substitution on patient-reported outcomes and cognitive functions in GH-deficient patients: a meta-analysisGrowth Hormon IGF Res200515475410.1016/j.ghir.2004.11.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>25.Al-DelaimyWKvon MuhlenDBarrett-ConnorEInsulinlike growth factor-1, insulinlike growth factor binding protein-1, and cognitive function in older men and womenJ Am Geriatr Soc2009571441144610.1111/j.1532-5415.2009.02343.x<?supplied-pmid 19515112?>19515112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>26.AlemanAde VriesWRKoppeschaarHPOsman-DualehMVerhaarHJSamsonMMRelationship between circulating levels of sex hormones and insulin-like growth factor-1 and fluid intelligence in older menExp Aging Res20012728329110.1080/036107301300208718<?supplied-pmid 11441649?>11441649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>27.RolleroAMurialdoGFonziSGarroneSGianelliMVGazzerroERelationship between cognitive function, growth hormone and insulin-like growth factor I plasma levels in aged subjectsNeuropsychobiology199838737910.1159/000026520<?supplied-pmid 9732206?>9732206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>28.ArwertLIDeijenJBMullerMDrentMLLong-term growth hormone treatment preserves GH-induced memory and mood improvements: a 10-year follow-up study in GH-deficient adult menHorm Behav20054734334910.1016/j.yhbeh.2004.11.015<?supplied-pmid 15708764?>15708764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>29.StouthartPJHMDeijenJBRoffelMDelemarre-van de WaalHAQuality of life of growth hormone (GH) deficient young adults during discontinuation and restart of GH therapyPsychoneuroendocrinology20032861262610.1016/S0306-4530(02)00045-8<?supplied-pmid 12727130?>12727130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>30.NybergFGrowth hormone in the brain: characteristics of specific brain targets for the hormone and their functional significanceFront Neuroendocrinol20002133034810.1006/frne.2000.0200<?supplied-pmid 11013068?>11013068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>31.NybergFHallbergMGrowth hormone and cognitive functionNat Rev Endocrinol2013935736510.1038/nrendo.2013.78<?supplied-pmid 23629538?>23629538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>32.AdemAJossanSSd'ArgyRGillbergPGNordbergAWinbladBSaraVInsulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) receptors in the human brain: quantitative autoradiographic localizationBrain Res198950329930310.1016/0006-8993(89)91678-8<?supplied-pmid 2557967?>2557967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>33.De KeyserJWilczakNDe BackerJPHerroelenLVauquelinGInsulin-like growth factor-I receptors in human brain and pituitary gland: an autoradiographic studySynapse19941719620210.1002/syn.890170309<?supplied-pmid 7974203?>7974203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>34.IsgaardJAbergDNilssonMProtective and regenerative effects of the GH/IGF-I axis on the brainMinerva Endocrinol200732103113<?supplied-pmid 17557036?>17557036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>35.JohanssonPRayAZhouQHuangWKarlssonKNybergFAnabolic androgenic steroids increase beta-endorphin levels in the ventral tegmental area in the male rat brainNeurosci Res19972718518910.1016/S0168-0102(96)01141-8<?supplied-pmid 9100262?>9100262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>36.BurmanPJohanssonAGSiegbahnAVessbyBKarlssonFAGrowth hormone (GH)-deficient men are more responsive to GH replacement therapy than womenJ Clin Endocrinol Metab199782550555<?supplied-pmid 9024252?>9024252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>37.van BunderenCCLipsPKramerMHDrentMLComparison of low-normal and high-normal IGF-1 target levels during growth hormone replacement therapy: a randomized clinical trial in adult growth hormone deficiencyEur J Intern Med201631889310.1016/j.ejim.2016.03.026<?supplied-pmid 27118206?>27118206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>38.HoKKYConsensus guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of adults with GH deficiency II: a statement of the GH research society in association with the European Society for Pediatric Endocrinology, Lawson Wilkins society, European Society of Endocrinology, Japan Endocrine Society, and Endocrine Society of AustraliaEur J Endocrinol200715769570010.1530/EJE-07-0631<?supplied-pmid 18057375?>18057375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>39.RobbinsTWJamesMOwenAMSahakianBJMcInnesLRabbittPCambridge neuropsychological test automated battery (CANTAB): a factor analytic study of a large sample of normal elderly volunteersDementia19945266281<?supplied-pmid 7951684?>7951684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>40.SahakianBJMorrisRGEvendenJLHealdALevyRPhilpotMRobbinsTWA comparative study of visuospatial memory and learning in Alzheimer-type dementia and Parkinson's diseaseBrain1988111Pt 369571810.1093/brain/111.3.695<?supplied-pmid 3382917?>3382917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>41.OwenAMDownesJJSahakianBJPolkeyCERobbinsTWPlanning and spatial working memory following frontal lobe lesions in manNeuropsychologia1990281021103410.1016/0028-3932(90)90137-D<?supplied-pmid 2267054?>2267054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>42.RobbinsTWJamesMOwenAMSahakianBJLawrenceADMcInnesLRabbittPMA study of performance on tests from the CANTAB battery sensitive to frontal lobe dysfunction in a large sample of normal volunteers: implications for theories of executive functioning and cognitive aging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated BatteryJ Int Neuropsychol Soc1998447449010.1017/S1355617798455073<?supplied-pmid 9745237?>9745237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>43.CANTABeclipseTest Administration Guide2011CambridgeCambridge Cognition Limited Ed </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>44.ShachamSA shortened version of the profile of mood statesJ Pers Assess19834730530610.1207/s15327752jpa4703_14<?supplied-pmid 6886962?>6886962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>45.HuismanJAukemaEJDeijenJBvan CoeverdenSCKaspersGJLvan der PalHJHDelemarre-van de WaalHThe usefulness of growth hormone treatment for psychological status in young adult survivors of childhood leukaemia: an open-label studyBMC Pediatr200882510.1186/1471-2431-8-25<?supplied-pmid 18570650?>18570650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>46.CopinschiGNedeltchevaALeproultRMorselliLLSpiegelKMartinoESleep disturbances, daytime sleepiness, and quality of life in adults with growth hormone deficiencyJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2010952195220210.1210/jc.2009-2080<?supplied-pmid 20332249?>20332249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>47.MorselliLLNedeltchevaALeproultRSpiegelKMartinoELegrosJJImpact of GH replacement therapy on sleep in adult patients with GH deficiency of pituitary originEur J Endocrinol201316876377010.1530/EJE-12-1037<?supplied-pmid 23447518?>23447518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>48.MongJABakerFCMahoneyMMPaulKNSchwartzMDSembaKSilverRSleep, rhythms, and the endocrine brain: influence of sex and gonadal hormonesJ Neurosci201131161071611610.1523/JNEUROSCI.4175-11.2011<?supplied-pmid 22072663?>22072663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>49.ZhangBWingYKSex differences in insomnia: a meta-analysisSleep200629859310.1093/sleep/29.1.85<?supplied-pmid 16453985?>16453985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>50.HazemAElaminMBBancosIMalagaGPrutskyGDomecqJPBody composition and quality of life in adults treated with GH therapy: a systematic review and meta-analysisEur J Endocrinol2012166132010.1530/EJE-11-0558<?supplied-pmid 21865409?>21865409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
