<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6037156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Paleontology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Fossil eggshell cuticle elucidates dinosaur nesting ecology </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Tzu-Ruei</given-names></name><email>tryang@uni-bonn.de</email><email>lereage@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Ying-Hsuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wiemann</surname><given-names>Jasmina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spiering</surname><given-names>Beate</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>P. Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Bereich Paläontologie, Steinmann-Institut für Geologie, Mineralogie und Paläontologie, Universität Bonn</institution>, <city>Bonn</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Max-Planck-Institut für Eisenforschung</institution>, <city>Düsseldorf</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Geology and Geophysics, Yale University</institution>, <city>New Haven</city>, <state>CT</state>, <country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label><institution>Bereich Mineralogie, Steinmann-Institut für Geologie, Mineralogie und Paläontologie, Universität Bonn</institution>, <city>Bonn</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff-5"><label>5</label><institution>Dinosaur Institute, Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County</institution>, <city>Los Angeles</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country>United States of America</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Piñeiro</surname><given-names>Graciela</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2018-07-06"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e5144</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-15"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-06-07"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©2018 Yang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yang et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/5144"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer consisting mainly of lipids and hydroxyapatite (HAp) atop the mineralized avian eggshell is a protective structure that prevents the egg from dehydration and microbial invasions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Previous ornithological studies have revealed that the cuticle layer is also involved in modulating the reflectance of eggshells in addition to pigments (protoporphyrin and biliverdin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Thus, the cuticle layer represents a crucial trait that delivers ecological signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>While present in most modern birds, direct evidence for cuticle preservation in stem birds and non-avian dinosaurs is yet missing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Here we present the first direct and chemical evidence for the preservation of the cuticle layer on dinosaur eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We analyze several theropod eggshells from various localities, including oviraptorid Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshells from the Late Cretaceous deposits of Henan, Jiangxi, and Guangdong in China and alvarezsaurid Triprismatoolithus eggshell from the Two Medicine Formation of Montana, United States, with the scanning electron microscope (SEM), electron probe micro-analysis (EPMA), and Raman spectroscopy (RS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The elemental analysis with EPMA shows high concentration of phosphorus at the boundary between the eggshell and sediment, representing the hydroxyapatitic cuticle layer (HAp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Depletion of phosphorus in sediment excludes the allochthonous origin of the phosphorus in these eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The chemometric analysis of Raman spectra collected from fossil and extant eggs provides further supportive evidence for the cuticle preservation in oviraptorid and probable alvarezsaurid eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In accordance with our previous discovery of pigments preserved in Cretaceous oviraptorid dinosaur eggshells, we validate the cuticle preservation on dinosaur eggshells through deep time and offer a yet unexplored resource for chemical studies targeting the evolution of dinosaur nesting ecology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Our study also suggests that the cuticle structure can be traced far back to maniraptoran dinosaurs and enhance their reproductive success in a warm and mesic habitat such as Montana and southern China during the Late Cretaceous. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Chemometrics</kwd><kwd>Dinosaur reproduction</kwd><kwd>Soft tissue preservation</kwd><kwd>Elemental analysis</kwd><kwd>Raman spectroscopy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Ministry of Education, Taiwan</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Jurassic Foundation</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-3"><funding-source>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funding-source><award-id>348043586</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This research is supported by the scholarship for studying abroad from the Ministry of Education, Taiwan and research grant from the Jurassic Foundation to Tzu-Ruei Yang. Tzu-Ruei Yang and P. Martin Sander are both funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemein-schaft (DFG, German Research Foundation)—project number 348043586. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Cuticle structures and functions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>An avian egg is an evolutionary invention that protects the developing embryo against mechanical damage, dehydration, and microbial invasion (Romanoff &amp; Romanoff, 1949; Board &amp; Fuller, 1974). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This multi-functionality is contributed to by both mineralized and non-mineralized organic layers, which exhibit unique biomaterial properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The avian eggshell forms inside the uterus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The final layer to be deposited, the eggshell cuticle, represents the interface between the embryo inside and its outside environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Many bird eggs are equipped with a cuticle layer; however, this structure is absent in some clades such as parrots, petrels, and pigeons (D’Alba et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer is often described as “waxy” due to its high amount of lipids, which keep the internal fluids from evaporating and therefore protect the encased embryo from desiccation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In addition to lipids, the avian cuticle contains proteins, polysaccharides, calcium carbonate (vaterite), calcium phosphates (hydroxyapatite, HAp), and pigments (Wedral, Vadehra &amp; Baker, 1974; Nys et al., 1991; Packard &amp; DeMarco, 1991; Dennis et al., 1996; Mikhailov &amp; British Ornithologists’ Club, 1997; Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon, 1999; Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel, 2003; Igic et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer varies in thickness (up to 12 µm) and has a patchy distribution on the eggshell (Board &amp; Halls, 1973). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Basically, the cuticle is divided into two distinct layers, including an amorphous HAp/vaterite inner layer and a proteinaceous outer layer (Simons, 1971; Dennis et al., 1996; Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The inner cuticle layer is composed of needle-like HAp/vaterite crystals on some avian eggs but present in the form of nanospherical HAp/vaterite on other avian eggs (Dennis et al., 1996; D’Alba et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A recent study suggested that the circular mineral nanospheres on eggshells serve an antimicrobial function for species nesting in humid environment (D’Alba et al., 2016). D’Alba et al. (2016) also proposed that eggs in humid environments tend to have more cuticular nanospheres to prevent flooding and microbial invasions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Conversely, in arid environments, lacking a cuticle layer would be beneficial for embryos in eggs with low conductance, as Deeming (1987) suggested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, in an extreme environment such as the Antarctic, Adélie penguin eggs have a thick cuticle layer to reduce water loss (Thompson &amp; Goldie, 1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Besides, the intactness of the cuticle is an indicator for the freshness of an egg (Rodríguez-Navarro et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Several studies suggested that the cuticle functions as a lubricant that facilitates egg rotation in the uterus (Rahman et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a recent study shows that the cuticle also modulates ultraviolet reflectance of avian eggshells (Fecheyr-Lippens et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For instance, an extremely smooth cuticle produces glossiness and iridescence in tinamou eggs (Igic et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The cuticle is commonly observed on most calcified eggshells, but it shows different structures and characteristics between reptilian and avian eggshells (Ferguson, 1982). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The cuticle on reptilian eggshells is no longer present after two weeks of laying (Ferguson, 1982); hence, the author concluded that the reptilian cuticle is not equivalent to the cuticle present on avian eggshells. Ferguson (1982) hypothesized that a true cuticle layer is not present on alligator eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Conversely, avian eggshells exhibit an inner cuticle layer composed of HAp/vaterite granules or amorphous needle-like HAp/vaterite crystals, which are absent on reptilian eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Several studies on extant eggshell have identified cuticle presence by means of the scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) (Fink et al., 1993; Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon, 1999). Kusada et al. (2011) used energy dispersive X-ray analysis (EDX) to map the phosphorus (P) and calcium (Ca) distribution in several extant avian eggshells and discovered that P is confined to the cuticle layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Although the P concentration in the cuticle varies greatly between different bird species, P is a distinct marker for identifying the cuticle layer in case of P depletion in sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Although it is still not clear how P functions during the eggshell formation, a study suggested that the inclusion of P in the biomineral terminates eggshell growth since it competes with calcium during the eggshell crystallization (Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel, 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Discoveries of fossilized organic membranes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Since the cuticle is composed of proteins, polysaccharides, lipids, calcium carbonate, calcium phosphates, and pigments, it is seemingly unlikely to preserve during the fossilization process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>A previous report concerning spherical (Oölithus spheroides) and elongated (Oölithus elongatus) eggs from Laiyang, Shandong, China, suggested that the cuticle is preserved in elongated eggs but not in spherical ones (Chow, 1954). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Another similar report on ornithoid eggshells from Naran-Bulak, Mongolia also described possible cuticle preservations (Sochava, 1971), but no diagnostic chemical data were obtained. Kohring &amp; Hirsch (1996) studied the crocodilian and ornithoid eggshells from the Middle Eocene of the Geiseltal, Germany, and suggested possible cuticle and shell membrane preservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Later, with the SEM, several studies on dinosaur eggshells, Cretaceous bird eggshells, and fossil moa eggshells showed the potential of cuticle preservation (Mikhailov, 1991; Varricchio &amp; Jackson, 2004; Jackson &amp; Varricchio, 2010; Oskam et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Although these studies provided a new avenue to understanding soft-part preservation, all previous studies described possible cuticle preservation only based on micro-structural comparisons with the cuticle of extant avian eggshells. Jackson &amp; Varricchio (2010) described a new ootaxon—Triprismatoolithus stephensi—of probable alvarezsaurid affinities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>These authors reported a cracked and amorphous surface overlying the external layer and suggested that it might be a layer of cuticle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, they did not further investigate the possible cuticle layer by means of any other analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Therefore, all previous reports regarding the cuticle preservation were constrained to micro-morphological observations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The only chemical evidence supporting the fossilization potential of cuticle through deep time is offered by a study on oviraptorid eggshells focusing on the two main eggshell pigments, biliverdin and protoporphyrin (Wiemann et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The protoporphyrin is deposited predominantly in the cuticle layer (Schwartz et al., 1975; Nys et al., 1991; Mikšík et al., 2007; Nys &amp; Guyot, 2011), thus providing indirect evidence of cuticle preservation in the preservation of endogenous protoporphyrin (Wiemann et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Although Wilson et al. (2017) demonstrated that there is no codependence of the deposition of pigment and cuticle, the preserved pigments in the oviraptorid eggshell could derive from the eggshell or the preserved cuticle layer and in the latter instance would be indicative of cuticle preservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Hence, we posited that the cuticle was completely, or partially, preserved on the oviraptorid eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In addition to the cuticle layer, the membrana testacea (eggshell membranes), a proteinaceous meshwork that underlies the mineralized eggshell and separates egg yolk and eggshell, is also a crucial membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Unlike the cuticle layer, the preservation of membrana testacea has been reported from titanosaurid and Lufengosaurus eggs (Grellet-Tinner, 2005; Reisz et al., 2013), yet never in theropod eggs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Nesting ecology of dinosaurs and modern birds </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Dinosaur nesting ecology is a long-standing and intriguing research topic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Among all dinosaurs, the nesting type of titanosaur, troodontid, and oviraptorid dinosaurs are comparatively well documented (Jackson, 2007; Varricchio et al., 2013; Wiemann et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>These dinosaurs adopted different nesting strategies in their clutch arrangement, nest architecture, and nesting mode. Deeming (2006) and Tanaka, Zelenitsky &amp; Therrien (2015) roughly categorized two nesting modes in dinosaurs, including open and buried nesting modes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Most birds build open nests, while the buried nesting mode is only observed in megapode birds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In a wet incubation environment such as a buried megapode nest, eggs are exposed to a higher risk of asphyxiation and microbial infection (Board &amp; Fuller, 1974; Board, 1982; D’Alba et al., 2017). D’Alba et al. (2016) provided the first report regarding the association between the cuticular nanospheres and nesting modes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>These authors discovered that the birds nesting in more mesic environments tend to lay eggs yielding cuticular nanospheres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The nanospheres in the cuticle layer, therefore, represents a structural adaptation that prevents eggs from microbial invasions (D’Alba et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>However, eggs of Adélie penguins are also encapsulated by a thick cuticle layer that prevents eggs from water loss in the severe cold Antarctic environment (Thompson &amp; Goldie, 1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>These lines of evidence suggest that the cuticle layer is an evolutionarily labile structure and thus varies greatly in accordance with the nesting environment. D’Alba et al. (2016) further suggested that cuticular nanospheres are an ancestral trait; however, this trait has been lost multiple times and is absent in some avian clades. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In dinosaurs, it was suggested that titanosaurs also employed the buried nesting mode (Sander et al., 1998; Grellet-Tinner &amp; Fiorelli, 2010; Sander et al., 2008; Vila et al., 2010; Hechenleitner, Grellet-Tinner &amp; Fiorelli, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The low porosity of titanosaur eggs from Auca Mahuevo, however, suggested that the titanosaurs from Auca Mahuevo did not bury their eggs (Jackson, 2007; Sander et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The Auca Mahuevo exception demonstrates that the eggshell is a labile structure, which alters according to the environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In comparison with the well-documented titanosaur nesting ecology, the nesting ecology of theropods has remained uncertain until recent times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A nesting Nemegtomaia discovered in Mongolia indicated a semi-open nesting mode based on sedimentological evidence (Fanti, Currie &amp; Demchig, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The discovery of pigmentation in oviraptorid eggshells strongly suggested that the oviraptorid eggs were laid in an at least partially open nest (Wiemann et al., 2017). Yang et al. (2015) (see also Wiemann et al., 2017) further supported the semi-open nesting mode according to the heterogeneous distribution of porosity in an oviraptorid egg and taphonomic evidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>While there is no evidence of pigmentation in troodontid eggshells because these have not been analyzed chemically so far, the heterogeneous distribution of porosity suggests that the troodontid dinosaurs might also have laid their eggs in a semi-open nest (Varricchio et al., 1997; Varricchio et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The goal of this study is to present further evidence of cuticle preservation on dinosaur eggshells by means of SEM imaging, elemental analysis, and RS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In particular, we analyzed theropod eggshells from the Nanxiong Group in China and the Two Medicine Formation in Montana, USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Both the Nanxiong Group and Two Medicine Formation represent fluvial deposits, indicating a probable humid climate in both areas during the Late Cretaceous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In addition, nesting on the ground or in a mound in a wet environment increases the risk of microbial invasions (D’Alba et al., 2016), a cuticle layer should thus be prevalent on eggshells of ground nesting theropods in a humid climate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Material and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In order to standardize our following analyses, domestic chicken eggshell (Gallus gallus domesticus) was obtained from a commercial source (supermarket). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Two extant crocodilian eggshells (Crocodylus porosus and Tomistoma schlegelii) were sampled from the collection of the NMNS as negative controls (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The fossil materials include oviraptorid and probable alvarezsaurid dinosaur eggshells (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Eggshells analyzed in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The ootaxonomic/taxonomic assignments, stratigraphic and locality information, and catalog numbers of the eggshells analyzed in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Oospecies or species </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Stratigraphy </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Locality </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Catalog number </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Reference </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Macroolithus yaotunensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Tangbian Formation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Hongcheng Basin, Jiangxi Province, China </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>NMNS CYN-2004-DINO-05-I </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Wiemann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>(2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Macroolithus yaotunensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Hugang Formation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Liquanqiao Basin, Henan Province, China </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>STIPB-E131 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Wiemann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>(2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Macroolithus yaotunensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Pingling Formation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Nanxiong Basin, Guangdong Province, China </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>STIPB-E66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Wiemann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(2017) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Triprismatoolithus stephensi </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Lower portion of the Upper Cretaceous (Campanian) Two Medicine Formation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Dave and Joel Site, Sevenmile Hill outcrops, Teton County, Montana </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>MOR ES101 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Jackson &amp; Varricchio (2010) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Gallus gallus domesticus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Bonn, Germany </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Crocodylus porosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Taichung, Taiwan </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>uncatalogued specimen in NMNS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Tomistoma schlegelii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Taichung, Taiwan </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>uncatalogued specimen in NMNS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>– </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>We studied three oviraptorid eggshell specimens that were collected from the Late Cretaceous Nanxiong Group of three localities in China (Henan Province, Jiangxi Province, and Guangdong Province) and are housed at the NMNS and STIPB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Based on eggshell microstructure, all specimens were assignable to Macroolithus yaotunensis, which was laid by the oviraptorid Heyuannia huangi (Cheng et al., 2008). Macroolithus yaotunensis is characterized by an undulating boundary between two crystalline layers, i.e., the outer prismatic layer and the inner mammillary layer (Supplemental Information; Zhao, 1975). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The first Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshell was taken from specimen NMNS CYN-2004-DINO-05-I, which was collected from the Late Cretaceous Tangbian Formation of the Hongcheng Basin in Jiangxi Province, China (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The Tangbian Formation is characterized by fine-grained brownish-reddish sediments with dispersed coarse clasts and conglomerates, representing a fluvial/alluvial environment with occasional stream flooding during the Campanian stage (Chen et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The second Macroolithus yaotunensis sample was collected as isolated shell fragments from the Late Cretaceous Hugang Formation in the Liguanqiao Basin near Nanyang, southwestern Henan Province, China (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>This sample has been housed in STIPB since 1985 and was described in Erben (1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The Hugang Formation is composed of dark grayish red breccia with interbeds of calcareous sandstone, indicating a fluvial/alluvial environment (Zhang, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The third Macroolithus yaotunensis sample was also obtained as isolated shell fragments from the Late Cretaceous fluvial deposits of the Pingling Section of the Shanghu Formation in the Nanxiong Basin, located in the northwestern part of Guangdong Province, China (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The NE-SW striking Nanxiong Basin, which is filled with dark purplish silty mudstone with interbeds of conglomerate, has produced numerous theropod egg clutches and eggshell fragments (Erben, 1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshells (MOR ES101), probably attributable to alvarezsaurids (Agnolin et al., 2012; Varricchio &amp; Jackson, 2016), were collected as isolated shell fragments in the lower portion of the Two Medicine Formation in the Sevenmile Hill outcrops, Teton County, Montana, USA (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell has three crystalline layers, including an external layer, prismatic layer, and mammillary layer, from outermost to innermost (Varricchio &amp; Jackson, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The Two Medicine Formation is mostly composed of sandstone, deposited by rivers and deltas on the western shoreline of the Late Cretaceous Interior Seaway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Chemical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For the chemical analyses, we first used a VEGA TS5130 LM (Tescan) SEM at the STIPB to locate and image plausible cuticle preservation on the studied eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The eggshells were naturally broken fragments and coated with gold for SEM observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The operating conditions for the SEM were set as 20 kV accelerating voltage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>All samples were cleaned with ethanol before chemical analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We then performed elemental analyses using the EPMA equipped with a WDS at the Section of Mineralogy of the STIPB to elucidate the P distribution in the radial section of dinosaur eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>All samples were polished, fixed on a glass slide with araldite histological resin, and then coated with carbon for the elemental analysis with EPMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The elemental analyses were performed with a JEOL SUPERPROBE 8900 EPMA at the same lab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The operating conditions for the EPMA were set as 1 µm beam diameter, 15 kV accelerating voltage, and 15 nA specimen current. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The ZAF correction scheme was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Natural and synthetic minerals were used as standards. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We performed two rounds of RS using two Raman spectrometers at the MPIE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>For the first round, Raman Analysis I (referred hereafter as RI), we analyzed the domestic chicken eggshell from a commercial source with a WITec Alpha300 system with 532 nm wavelength laser light and a confocal 50× objective, each for 20 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Since the cuticle on the chicken eggshell was easily identified with the naked eye, as well as under the SEM (Figs. 1C and 1D), the first round confirmed the detectability by Raman spectroscopy of the HAp of the cuticle layer (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>1E–1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Due to the incomplete preservation of the cuticle in the chicken eggshell, we performed Raman surface mapping on the area where we found possible cuticle remains using the SEM and EPMA previously. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Raman analysis II (referred to as RII hereafter) was performed using the Horiba Jobin Yvon GmbH LabRam Raman spectrometer equipped with a 632 nm laser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>All results were obtained using the 10× objective of the integrated Olympus microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>While the 10× objective is not strongly sensitive to rare compounds, it provides a larger field of view for faster qualitative detection of HAp on eggshell sample than in RI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In order to distinguish HAp and calcite from sediments, we collected Raman spectra of the fresh chicken eggshell, the studied fossil eggshells and their associated sediments (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>All Raman spectra of eggshells and their associated sediments during RII were imported into the statistics software R and normalized with the R package “ChemoSpec” (Hanson, 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We performed principle component analysis (PCA) on the spectral area of 500 to 1,500 cm−1 using the same package (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer on the Gallus eggshell was easily observed with the naked eye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The RI Raman spectrum from the Gallus eggshell shows a significant peak at 1,087 cm−1 that arises from the calcite, which is the major component of eggshell (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Another intense peak at 967 cm−1 was assigned to the v3 symmetric stretching vibrations (Walters et al., 1990; Gergely et al., 2010; Frost et al., 2014; Igic et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Targeting the 967 cm−1 peak, the Raman surface scan shows the patchy distribution of the HAp layer overlying the calcitic eggshell (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The result demonstrates detectability of the inner HAp layer of the cuticle by RS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Cross-sectional view, SEM images, and Raman imaging and spectrum of a Gallus gallus domesticus egg and eggshell. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The Raman image and spectrum were collected using 532 nm excitation wavelength and a 50x objective with RI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(A) The generalized anatomy of an egg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(B) The chicken eggshell comprises three crystalline layers, including the mammillary layer, prismatic layer, and external layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer overlying the calcareous eggshell is further divided to two layers, including a HAp inner layer and a proteinaceous outer layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The shell membrane, namely membrane testacea, is also characterized by two layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>(C) SEM image of the cuticle on the surface of the Gallus eggshell, showing a patchy and cracked pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(D) SEM image of the radial section of the Gallus eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The white arrow indicates the cuticle layer that lies on the calcitic eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(E) Raman chemical image with peak targeting at 967 cm−1 which is attributed to HAp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The yellow area represents the patchy distribution of the inner HAp cuticle layer on the Gallus eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The calcitic eggshell that is not covered by the inner HAp cuticle layer is shown in the brown area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The dotted circle corresponds to the spectrum shown in (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>(F) Spectrum collected in the dotted-circle area of the Raman chemical image shown in (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Two significant peaks at 967 cm−1 and 1,087 cm−1 represent HAp and calcite, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Credit of the SEM images and drawings: Tzu-Ruei Yang (Universität Bonn). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Raman spectra and chemometric analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>(A) Raman spectra derived from chicken, crocodilian, fossil dinosaur eggshells, and surrounding sediments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The peaks around 972–986 cm−1 and 1,063–1,097 cm−1 are marked by yellow bars, indicating the calcite and phosphate bonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(B) The principle component chemometric analysis on the spectral area of 800–1,200 cm−1 shown in (A) demonstrates significant disparities between dinosaur/chicken eggshells, crocodilian eggshells, and sediments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Credit of the drawings: Tzu-Ruei Yang (Universität Bonn). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>On the outside of Macroolithus yaotunensis and Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell fragments, we also found peaks in these spectral regions (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>RII showed two intense broad peaks that are located between 1,063–1,097 cm−1 and 972–986 cm−1 in the spectra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The spectral range of 1,063–1,097 cm−1 can be assigned to the C–O bond of calcite, which is observable in the spectra from all eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The 972–986 cm−1 spectral ranges arose possibly from the phosphate (\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}${\mathrm{PO}}_{4}^{3-}$\end{document}PO43−) or hydrogen phosphate \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$({\mathrm{HPO}}_{4}^{2-})$\end{document}HPO42− (Sauer et al., 1994; Crane et al., 2006; Igic et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the 972–986 cm−1 spectral ranges are present in the spectra from the chicken and dinosaur eggshells but absent in the ones from the crocodilian eggshells and surrounding sediments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The chemometric analysis using ChemoSpec suggests that both chicken and dinosaur eggshells show similar spectral pattern between 800 cm−1 and 1,200 cm−1 (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In addition, the spectra from the crocodilian eggshells and surrounding sediments occupy different chemospaces from the ones of dinosaur and chicken eggshells (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Under the polarizing microscope, the Macroolithus eggshell from the Hongcheng Basin of Jiangxi, China, displayed distinct two crystalline layers overlain by an enigmatic layer and surrounding sediment (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>These features are also present in the other two Macroolithus eggshells (see Supplemental Information). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The uneven thickness of the prismatic layer in the Jiangxi Macroolithus eggshells was a result of unpolished natural fracture surface of the section (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>A possible patchy and flake-like cuticle layer was observed with SEM on the outer surface of the Macroolithus and Triprismatoolithus eggshells (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>3C &amp; 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, an enigmatic protruding fiber-like structure was recognized in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>4C–4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The diameter of the fiber-like structure is approximately 3 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Microscopic images of Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshell from Henan, Jiangxi, and Guangdong and their line-scan spectra. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>(A) The Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshell (NMNS CYN-2004-DINO-05-I) from Jiangxi under the polarized light microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The red arrows indicate the indistinct boundary between the sediment and an enigmatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This enigmatic layer probably was formed by the interaction between organics of the egg and surrounding sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The location of the EPMA line-scan spectra in (D) is indicated by the white solid line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In this eggshell image, a smooth boundary between the prismatic and mammillary layers (PL and ML, seen as dark and light zones) is clearly observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>(B) SEM image of radial untreated fracture of the Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The boundary between the sediment and prismatic layer is marked by yellow dashed line based on their distinct structural features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The boundary between ML and PL is marked by the red dashed line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The ML shows the distinct vertical mammillae structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>(C) Close-up image of the area in white box in (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Possible preservation of cuticle is indicated by the white arrow, showing patchy and flaky structures similar to the cuticle on the modern chicken eggshell (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>1C and 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>(D, F, H) The microscopic image shows the radial cut section of studied Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshells seen in the SEM coupled with the EPMA and elemental line-scan track marked as black lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>(D) The spectra illustrate the distribution of Ca and P across the eggshell from the Hongcheng Basin in Jiangxi shown in (A), from innermost (left) to outermost, as indicated by the white line in the microscopic image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The Ca spectrum clearly marks the extent of the calcitic eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>A significant peak that is marked by a black arrow demonstrates a relatively high concentration of P, indicating the possible preservation of the cuticular HAp layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>(G) The spectra illustrate the distribution of Ca and P across the eggshell from the Liguangqiao Basin in Henan, from innermost (left) to outermost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The Ca spectrum clearly marks the extent of the calcitic eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>A slightly higher amount of P near the interface between the eggshell and sediments, as indicated by a black arrow, is observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>(I) The spectra illustrate the distribution of Ca and P across the eggshell from the Nanxiong Basin in Guangdong, from innermost (left) to outermost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>A significant peak that is marked by a black arrow demonstrates a relatively high concentration of P, indicating the possible preservation of the cuticular HAp layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>ML, mammillary layer; PL, prismatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Credit of the SEM images and drawings: Tzu-Ruei Yang (Universität Bonn). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>SEM images of the Triprismatoolithus eggshell and EPMA line-scan spectra. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>(A) The radial cut section of studied Triprismatoolithus eggshell in the SEM coupled with the EPMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>(B) The probable flake-like cuticle structure atop the eggshell, marked by the white arrow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The red dotted line marks the outermost boundary of the prismatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>(C) An enigmatic structure (white arrow) protruding from the mammillary layer, possibly a fiber of the membrana testacea extending into the mammillary layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>(D) Enlargement of the possible fiber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>(E) Line scans across eggshell in (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The scan shows a high concentration of P at the boundary between the eggshell and surrounding sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Two other peaks of P were observed on the boundary between the external and prismatic layer and in the sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The P concentration does not differ between the mammillary and prismatic layers; however, the external layer showed a significantly lower concentration of P than the mammillary and prismatic layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>EL, external layer; ML, mammillary layer; PL, prismatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Credit of the SEM images and drawings: Tzu-Ruei Yang (Universität Bonn). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>We performed ten elemental line-mappings on each eggshell with EPMA and targeted phosphorus of the HAp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Of the of total 30 line mappings on the three Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshell, only two of them, which were from the Jiangxi and Guangdong specimens, show a significant phosphorus peak on the boundary between the eggshell and surrounding sediment (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>3D &amp; 3F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The elemental analysis also indicates the scarcity of the phosphorus in the surrounding sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>In addition, the P concentration increases from the mammillary layer to the prismatic layer in all analyzed oviraptorid eggshells (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>3D–3F and raw data in the Supplemental Information). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>In the EPMA line-scan on the Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell, three significant peaks for P were observed (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The peak on the boundary between the eggshell and surrounding sediment indicates possible cuticle preservation (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>However, the other two peaks were seen in the sediment and on the boundary between the external layer and prismatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The variation of P concentration between different eggshell layers was also observed in Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell (Fig. 4E and Supplemental Information). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Although the P concentration within the mammillary and prismatic layers shows little variation, the external layer has a significantly lower concentration of P than the mammillary and prismatic layers (Fig. 4E &amp; raw data in the Supplemental Information). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Elemental analysis of theropod eggshells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>While previous studies have reported possible preservation of cuticle and membrana testacea (Chow, 1954; Kohring &amp; Hirsch, 1996; Grellet-Tinner, 2005; Jackson &amp; Varricchio, 2010; Reisz et al., 2013; Yang et al., 2015), none of these studies employed chemical analyses to test this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In this study, elemental analysis suggests the preservation of the inner hydroxyapatitic cuticle layer based on the high concentration of P at the boundary between eggshell and sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>However, the peak that corresponds to a high concentration of P is not always present in each elemental line-scan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>For instance, on the M. yaotunensis eggshell sample from the Liguangqiao Basin (Fig. 3E), a probable P-rich zone, instead of an abrupt peak, is shown near the boundary between the eggshell and surrounding sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>RS analysis indeed revealed the existence of phosphates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Since RS scans a larger area than EPMA does, we suggest that the absence of an abrupt peak for a P-rich zone in those 28 line-scans is a result of incomplete preservation of the cuticle layer or a sampling bias during the EPMA analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The elemental analysis also shows that P is rare in the surrounding sediment from both the Nanxiong Group of China and the Two Medicine Formation of Montana, United States. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The deficiency of P in the sediment thus argues against an allochthonous origin of the P in the outermost part of the eggshell (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>3D–3F &amp; 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The chemometric comparison of the spectra derived from sediments also suggests the depletion of phosphate minerals in the sediments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the peak in the sediment surrounding the Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell might be derived from the eggshell specimen itself. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The enigmatic fiber-like structure near the base of the mammillary layer in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell (Fig. 4D) may be a capillary vessel of the chorioallantoic membrane or a fiber of the membrana testacea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The elemental analyses cannot provide evidence for the preservation of the capillary vessels of the chorioallantoic membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>SEM images show that the vessels in the chorioallantoic membrane of modern chicken eggshells range in size from 3 to 10 µm (Maiber et al., 2016), similar to the fiber-like structure we observed in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>However, the fiber-like structure in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell does not appear to be hollow, unlike a blood vessel (Schweitzer et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>It is therefore possible that the enigmatic fiber-like structure in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell represents a part of fossilized membrana testacea, which has never been described in theropod dinosaurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The membrana testacea fibers in a chicken egg occasionally penetrate through the mammillary base (Ahmed, Suso &amp; Hincke, 2017) and are of the same size of around 3 µm as the fiber-like structure we observed in the Triprismatoolithus egg (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>However, the hypothesis of fossilized membrana testacea requires more supporting evidence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Variation of P concentration in eggshells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Despite numerous studies on element distribution in modern avian and reptilian eggshells, dinosaur eggshells were rarely investigated from a chemical perspective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Several studies posited that P is a critical element that regulates eggshell growth (Fink et al., 1993; Dennis et al., 1996; Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon, 1999; Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In Gallus gallus domesticus eggshells, a pattern of increasing P concentration from the mammillary layer to the prismatic layer has been reported (Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>This pattern is similar to what we observed in oviraptorid eggshells (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>3D–3F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The deficiency of P in the surrounding sediments demonstrates that the distribution pattern of P in the studied eggshells is endogenous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Since ornithological research had suggested that P is an inhibitor of calcite growth during eggshell formation (Fink et al., 1993; Dennis et al., 1996; Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon, 1999; Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel, 2003), the similarity of P distribution between oviraptorid dinosaur and modern avian eggshells suggests that the oviraptorid dinosaurs studied by us already possessed a similar eggshell formation mechanism to that of extant birds. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel (2003) also observed that the P concentration increases more sharply between the mammillary and prismatic layers in the eggshell of younger birds than in those of older birds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the difference in P distribution between young and older birds can probably help paleontologists decipher whether an oviraptorid clutch was laid by a single female or by several females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>If the whole clutch was produced by a single female or by several females of a similar age, all eggs should exhibit a similar pattern of P concentration increase from the mammillary layer to the prismatic layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Conversely, different patterns of increase would suggest that females of different ages contributed to a single clutch. Varricchio et al. (2008) compared the ratio of clutch mass to adult mass and proposed that an oviraptorid clutch was produced by several females. Yang et al. (2016) have provided preliminary supportive results based on statistical analyses of eggshell P distribution and external morphology in the same oviraptorid clutch. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, in the Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell, P concentration varies slightly between the mammillary and prismatic layer but decreases significantly from the prismatic layer to the external layer (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Such a pattern of P distribution differs from the one in oviraptorid or modern bird eggshells we discussed previously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Moreover, unlike a single peak of high P concentration in oviraptorid and modern eggshells, three distinctive peaks of high P concentration are present in the Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Based on the general deficiency of P in the surrounding sediment, we posit that the P peak in the sediment surrounding the Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggshell is a result of a detached cuticle layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The peak at the boundary between the external layer and surrounding sediment represent the putative cuticle layer (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>However, the peak at the boundary between the prismatic and external layers was not reported previously in any avian eggshells (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>If the sequestration of P is a crucial factor in the termination of calcite growth, the high concentration of P on the boundary between the prismatic and external layers represents a possible temporal hiatus between the prismatic and external layers in the Triprismatoolithus eggshell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Interpretation of Raman spectra </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In the Raman study of the fossil eggshells, the peak at 967 cm−1 of Gallus eggshell was not seen in all spectra, but a broad peak ranging from 972–986 cm−1 was detected instead (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The broad peak ranging from 972–986 cm−1 represent the phosphate groups, as indicated in Igic et al. (2015) (see also Supplemental Information). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Three hypotheses can be formulated to explain the different spectral patterns from 960 cm−1 to 980 cm−1 in extant cuticle vs. the fossil eggshells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>First, theropod dinosaurs might have used whitlockite, a phosphate mineral containing hydrogen phosphate anions \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$({\mathrm{HPO}}_{4}^{2-})$\end{document}HPO42−, to form the inner cuticle layer instead of HAp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Whitlockite is the second most abundant mineral in biological calcified tissues, accounting for around 20% of bone mineral (Driessens &amp; Verbeeck, 1990; Jang et al., 2014; Jang et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that the HAp of the inner cuticle layer is in a non-stoichiometric form, and hence part of the phosphate anion (\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}${\mathrm{PO}}_{4}^{3-}$\end{document}PO43−) is occupied by hydrogen phosphate \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$({\mathrm{HPO}}_{4}^{2-})$\end{document}HPO42− (Rey et al., 2011; De La Pierre et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Second, the original HAp of the inner cuticle layer could have been transformed to whitlockite. Jang et al. (2014) showed that HAp transforms into dicalcium phosphate dihydrate (DCPD, CaHPO4⋅2H2O) at 70 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The DCPD is then converted into whitlockite (Ca9(MgFe)(PO4)6PO3OH) by incorporating Mg2+ or Fe2+ when the pH decreases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>In natural environments, such as the Nanxiong Formation and Two Medicine Formation, burial and diagenetic temperatures over 70 °C are unlikely except by an intrusion of igneous origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>However, geological investigations did not provide any evidence for such igneous intrusions in the Nanxiong Basin (Erben, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>At the Sevenmile Hill outcrops in Montana, United States, Foreman et al. (2008) reported an altered volcanic ash layer (bentonite) that is depleted in P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>However, the volcanic ash layer was deposited prior to the eggshells (Jackson &amp; Varricchio, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Third, the P we detected might be derived from the surrounding sediments during diagenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>This is inconsistent with the preservation of pigments in the Nanxiong Basin eggshells and absence of igneous intrusions in both localities, which suggests that the eggshells we studied experienced very little diagenesis (Erben, 1995; Foreman et al., 2008; Wiemann et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Pigmentation on theropod eggshells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>As noted above, the discovery of protoporphyrin (Wiemann et al., 2017) in oviraptorid dinosaur eggshells from all three localities where the eggshells for this study were collected (Table 1) is consistent with the cuticle preservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Although Wilson et al. (2017) indicated that pigment deposition and cuticle formation are not codependent, the preserved protoporphyrin pigments was probably from the cuticle layer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Thomas et al. (2015) performed Raman spectroscopy and mass spectrometry to show the detectability of pigments in extant avian eggshells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Our Raman analyses also demonstrate detectability of pigments in fossil eggshells; however, the peaks in the spectra do not completely correspondent with the ones shown in Thomas et al. (2015), suggesting further Raman studies using mass spectrometry on dinosaur eggshells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Nesting ecology of oviraptorid dinosaurs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>As noted, two nesting modes are recognized in birds, open and buried nesting (Varricchio &amp; Jackson, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Most birds build open nests either on the tree or on the ground (ostriches or emus), while the megapode birds bury their eggs in a mound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Therefore, all open-nesting birds have eggshells of low porosity (Tanaka, Zelenitsky &amp; Therrien, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>However, an intermediate mode, semi-open nests in oviraptorid dinosaurs, was recently proposed based on detection of pigments and porosity evaluation (Yang et al., 2015; Wiemann et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Pigmented eggshells strongly suggest an open nesting mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>However, the porosity evaluation revealed a heterogeneous distribution of porosity—highest porosity in the lower middle part (buried) and lowest porosity in the blunt end (open) (Yang et al., 2015; Wiemann et al., 2017), thus indicating a semi-open nesting mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>This intermediate mode is consistent with the fluvial environment inferred by sedimentological investigations in the Nanxiong Basin (Erben, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>In such a humid fluvial environment, the risk of microbial invasions was much higher. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The cuticular nanospheres, which are associated with humid environments and protect extant eggs from microbial invasions, were likely present in the oviraptorid and alvarezsaurid dinosaur eggs from these fossil humid environments as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Although we did not detect cuticular nanospheres in the dinosaur eggshell, our detection of a cuticle layer suggests it to have been an adaptation the oviraptorid and alvarezsaurid dinosaurs nesting in a humid fluvial environment (D’Alba et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, it was inferred that Mongolian oviraptorid clutches were deposited in a xeric environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The evidence is the eolian nature (sand dune deposits) in the Baruungoyot and the Djadokhta formations (Norell et al., 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Although no Mongolian oviraptorid eggshells were included in our study, it appears likely that Mongolian oviraptorid eggs were also cuticle-coated for the prevention of water loss as in Adélie penguin eggs (Thompson &amp; Goldie, 1990). Fanti, Currie &amp; Demchig (2012) documented clutches of the oviraptorid Nemegtomaia from both the Nemegt and Baruungoyot formations, that represent mesic and xeric habitats, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Moreover, they also provided evidence for the lateral coexistence of mesic and xeric habitats in the Baruungoyot Formation and posited that Nemegtomaia and other Mongolian oviraptorid dinosaurs nested near permanent or seasonal streams. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>In such a variable environment, the cuticle-coated eggs, therefore, would have been an adaptive trait that enhanced reproductive success of oviraptorid dinosaurs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>While it is uncertain that the alvarezsaurid eggshells were pigmented without further chemical studies, it is possible that alvarezsaurid dinosaur exploited similar nesting strategies as oviraptorid dinosaurs did. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Taphonomic implications for cuticle preservation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer is a labile, easily lost structure that appears unlikely to be preserved during the fossilization process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="?"><plain>Our study thus raises an important taphonomic question, i.e., how did the cuticle layer get preserved? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Since the cuticle preservation observed by us appears to pertain to eggshell from clutches and not from dispersed eggshell, cuticle preservation probably is facilitated by fossilization of eggs in clutches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a layer of secondary diagenetic calcite is commonly observed on eggshells from fluvial deposits (Fig. 3A; Jackson &amp; Varricchio, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>This layer of secondary calcite may have been a rigid shield that protected the cuticle layer from mechanical removal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we hypothesize that the in situ preservation and the coverage of secondary calcite possibly protect the cuticle layer from being washed away or removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>More detailed microscopic observation of the association between the cuticle, secondary calcite layers, and surrounding sediment will possibly elucidate the taphonomic processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Our study suggests preservation of the inner cuticle layer in Macroolithus yaotunensis and Triprismatoolithus stephensi eggs based on elemental analysis and RS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The cuticle layer and a semi-open nesting mode in humid environments may be key adaptations to protect the eggs from microbial invasions in a humid environment such as a fluvial plain, as does the cuticle layer of extant birds nesting in humid environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>In combination with the previous discovery of pigments in oviraptorid dinosaur eggshells, this study provides further evidence for preservation of soft tissues in the fluvial deposits, especially in the Cretaceous red bed basins of China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Further chemical studies on dinosaur eggshells will shed additional light on the reproductive biology of dinosaurs, as well as on taphonomic questions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Institutional and technical abbreviations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> EPMA</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Electron probe microanalysis </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MOR</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Museum of the Rockies, Bozeman, Montana, U.S.A </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MPIE</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Max-Planck-Institute for Iron Research, Dusseldorf, Germany </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> NMNS</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>National Museum of Natural Sciences, Taichung, Taiwan </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> RS</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Raman spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> SEM</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> STIPB</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Bereich Paläontologie, Steinmann-Institut für Geologie, Mineralogie und Paläontologie, Universität Bonn, Bonn, Germany </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> TEM</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> WDS</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Wavelength dispersive spectrometer </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ZAF</term><def><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Matrix correction factors: Z, atomic number correction; A, absorption correction; F, characteristic fluorescence correction </plain></SENT>
</text></p></def></def-item></def-list></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Detailed descriptions of the applied methodology and further material information. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-s001.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/supp-2</object-id><label>Data S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Dataset from elemental analyses of EPMA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Raw data from elemental analyses of Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshells from Jiangxi, Henan, and Guangdong Provinces of China, and Triprismatoolithus eggshell from Montana, USA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-s002.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5144/supp-3</object-id><label>Data S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Dataset from Raman analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Raw data from Raman analyses of Macroolithus yaotunensis eggshells from Jiangxi, Henan, and Guangdong Provinces of China, Triprismatoolithus eggshell from Montana, USA, and the associated sediments to each eggshell samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Two crocodilian eggshells from Crocodylia porosus and Tomistoma schlegelii are also included in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5144-s003.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><p>The SEM observations and EPMA analyses were performed at the Steinmann-Institute of the University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany. Prof. Dr. Andreas Erbe and Ms. Petra Ebbinghaus kindly provided the access to the WItec Raman and Horiba Jobin Yvon Raman spectrometers at the MPIE. Fossil eggshell samples were provided by Prof. Dr. David Varricchio at the Montana State University, Bozeman, MT, USA. Dr. Georg Heumann at the STIPB, and Prof. Dr. Yen-Nien Cheng at the NMNS. This is contribution number 1 of DFG Research Unit 2685 “The Limits of the Fossil Record: Analytical and Experimental Approaches to Fossilization.” The authors would also like to thank Daniel Lawver and two anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments.</p></ack></SecTag><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>The authors declare there are no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></SecTag><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Tzu-Ruei Yang conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Ying-Hsuan Chen and Beate Spiering performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, approved the final draft. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Jasmina Wiemann conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Martin Sander conceived and designed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, manuscript editing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>The following information was supplied regarding data availability: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The raw data are provided in the Supplemental Files. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></sec><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Agnolin et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>(2012)AgnolinFLPowellJENovasFEKundrátM2012New alvarezsaurid (Dinosauria, Theropoda) from uppermost Cretaceous of north-western Patagonia with associated eggsCretaceous Research35335610.1016/j.cretres.2011.11.014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-2"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Ahmed, Suso &amp; Hincke (2017)AhmedTAESusoH-PHinckeMT2017In-depth comparative analysis of the chicken eggshell membrane proteomeJournal of Proteomics155496210.1016/j.jprot.2017.01.00228087451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-3"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Board (1982)BoardRG1982Properties of avian egg shells and their adaptive valueBiological Reviews5712810.1111/j.1469-185X.1982.tb00362.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-4"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Board &amp; Fuller (1974)BoardRGFullerR1974Non-specific antimicrobial defences of the avian egg, embryo, and neonateBiological Reviews49154910.1111/j.1469-185X.1974.tb01297.x4594672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-5"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Board &amp; Halls (1973)BoardRGHallsNA1973The cuticle: a barrier to liquid and particle penetration of the shell of the hen’s eggBritish Poultry Science14699710.1080/00071667308415999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-6"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Chen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>(2017)ChenLSteelRJGuoFOlariuCGongC2017Alluvial fan facies of the Yongchong Basin: implications for tectonic and paleoclimatic changes during Late Cretaceous in SE ChinaJournal of Asian Earth Sciences134375410.1016/j.jseaes.2016.10.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-7"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Cheng et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>(2008)ChengY-NJiCWuXShanH-Y2008Oviraptorosaurian eggs (Dinosauria) with embryonic skeletons discovered for the first time in ChinaActa Geologica Sinica821089109410.1111/j.1755-6724.2008.tb00708.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-8"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Chow (1954)ChowM1954Additional notes on the microstructure of the supposed dinosaurian eggshells from Laiyang, ShantungActa Palaeontologica Sinica2389394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-9"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Crane et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>(2006)CraneNJPopescuVMorrisMDSteenhuisPIgnelziMA2006Raman spectroscopic evidence for octacalcium phosphate and other transient mineral species deposited during intramembranous mineralizationBone3943444210.1016/j.bone.2006.02.05916627026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-10"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Cusack, Fraser &amp; Stachel (2003)CusackMFraserACStachelT2003Magnesium and phosphorus distribution in the avian eggshellComparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B: Biochemistry and Molecular Biology134636910.1016/S1096-4959(02)00185-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-11"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>D’Alba et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>(2014)D’AlbaLJonesDNBadawyHTEliasonCMShawkeyMD2014Antimicrobial effects of a nanostructured eggshell in a compost-nesting birdJournal of Experimental Biology2171116112110.1111/ibi.1252724311808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-12"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>D’Alba et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>(2016)D’AlbaLMaiaRHauberMEShawkeyMD2016The evolution of eggshell cuticle in relation to nesting ecologyProceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences2832016068710.1098/rspb.2016.068727488648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-13"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>D’Alba et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="?"><plain>(2017)D’AlbaLTorresRWaterhouseGINEliasonCHauberMEShawkeyMD2017What does the eggshell cuticle do? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>A functional comparison of avian eggshell cuticlesPhysiological and Biochemical Zoology9058859910.1086/69343428745930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-14"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>De La Pierre et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(2014)De La PierreMCarteretCMaschioLAndréEOrlandoRDovesiR2014The Raman spectrum of CaCO3 polymorphs calcite and aragonite: a combined experimental and computational studyThe Journal of Chemical Physics14016450910.1063/1.487190024784289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-15"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Deeming (1987)DeemingDC1987Effect of cuticle removal on the water vapour conductance of egg shells of several species of domestic birdBritish Poultry Science2823123710.1080/00071668708416957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-16"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Deeming (2006)DeemingDC2006Ultrastructural and functional morphology of eggshells supports the idea that dinosaur eggs were incubated buried in a substratePalaeontology4917118510.1111/j.1475-4983.2005.00536.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-17"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Dennis et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>(1996)DennisJEXiaoSQAgarwalMFinkDJHeuerAHCaplanAI1996Microstructure of matrix and mineral components of eggshells from White Leghorn chickens (Gallus gallus)Journal of Morphology22828730610.1002/(SICI)1097-4687(199606)228:3&lt;287::AID-JMOR2&gt;3.0.CO;2-#29852681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-18"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Driessens &amp; Verbeeck (1990)DriessensFCMVerbeeckRK1990BiomineralsCRC PressBoca Raton </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-19"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Erben (1995)ErbenHK1995Die Kreide/Tertiär-Grenze im Nanxiong-Becken: Kontinentalfazies, SüdostchinaFranz Steiner Verlag GmbHStuttgart </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-20"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Fanti, Currie &amp; Demchig (2012)FantiFCurriePJDemchigB2012New specimens of Nemegtomaia from the Baruungoyot and Nemegt formations (Late Cretaceous) of MongoliaPLOS ONE7e3133010.1371/journal.pone.003133022347465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-21"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Fecheyr-Lippens et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(2015)Fecheyr-LippensDCIgicBD’AlbaLHanleyDVerdesAHolfordMWaterhouseGINGrimTHauberMEShawkeyMD2015The cuticle modulates ultraviolet reflectance of avian eggshellsBiology Open475375910.1242/bio.01221125964661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-22"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Ferguson (1982)FergusonMWJ1982The structure and composition of the eggshell and embryonic membranes of Alligator mississippiensisThe Transactions of the Zoological Society of London369915210.1111/j.1096-3642.1982.tb00064.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-23"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Fink et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(1993)FinkDJKuhnLTCaplanAIHuerAH1993Eggshell assembly, a model for biomimetic ceramic productionFifth European symposium on the quality of egg and egg productsToursWPSAp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>A1-A6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-24"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Foreman et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>(2008)ForemanBZRogersRRDeinoALWirthKRTholeJT2008Geochemical characterization of bentonite beds in the Two Medicine Formation (Campanian, Montana), including a new 40Ar/39Ar ageCretaceous Research2937338510.1016/j.cretres.2007.07.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-25"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Fraser, Bain &amp; Solomon (1999)FraserACBainMMSolomonSE1999Transmission electron microscopy of the vertical crystal layer and cuticle of the eggshell of the domestic fowlBritish Poultry Science4062663110.1080/00071669987016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-26"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Frost et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>(2014)FrostRLScholzRLópezAXiY2014A vibrational spectroscopic study of the phosphate mineral whiteite CaMn++Mg2Al2(PO4)4(OH)2⋅8(H2O)Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy12424324810.1016/j.saa.2014.01.053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-27"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Gergely et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(2010)GergelyGWéberFLukácsITóthALHorváthZEMihályJBalázsiC2010Preparation and characterization of hydroxyapatite from eggshellCeramics International3680380610.1016/j.ceramint.2009.09.020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-28"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Grellet-Tinner (2005)Grellet-TinnerG2005Membrana testacea of titanosaurid dinosaur eggs from Auca Mahuevo (Argentina): implications for exceptional preservation of soft tissue in LagerstättenJournal of Vertebrate Paleontology259910610.1671/0272-4634(2005)025[0099:mtotde]2.0.co;2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-29"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Grellet-Tinner &amp; Fiorelli (2010)Grellet-TinnerGFiorelliLE2010A new Argentinean nesting site showing neosauropod dinosaur reproduction in a Cretaceous hydrothermal environmentNature Communications13210.1038/ncomms1031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-30"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Hanson (2017)HansonBA2017ChemoSpec: exploratory chemometrics for spectroscopyR package version 4.4.97https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ChemoSpec/index.html </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-31"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Hechenleitner, Grellet-Tinner &amp; Fiorelli (2015)HechenleitnerEMGrellet-TinnerGFiorelliLE2015What do giant titanosaur dinosaurs and modern Australasian megapodes have in common?PeerJ3e134110.7717/peerj.134126623184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-32"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Igic et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>(2015)IgicBFecheyr-LippensDXiaoMChanAHanleyDBrennanPRLGrimTWaterhouseGINHauberMEShawkeyMD2015A nanostructural basis for gloss of avian eggshellsJournal of The Royal Society Interface122014121010.1098/rsif.2014.1210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-33"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Jackson (2007)JacksonFD2007Titanosaur reproductive biology: comparison of the Auca Mahuevo titanosaur nesting locality (Argentina), to the Pinyes Megaloolithus nesting locality (Spain)Ph.D thesisMontana State University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-34"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Jackson &amp; Varricchio (2010)JacksonFDVarricchioDJ2010Fossil eggs and eggshell from the lowermost Two Medicine Formation of western Montana, Sevenmile Hill localityJournal of Vertebrate Paleontology301142115610.1080/02724634.2010.483537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-35"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Jang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>(2014)JangHLJinKLeeJKimYNahmSHHongKSNamKT2014Revisiting whitlockite, the second most abundant biomineral in bone: nanocrystal synthesis in physiologically relevant conditions and biocompatibility evaluationACS Nano863464110.1021/nn405246h24299655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-36"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Jang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>(2015)JangHLLeeHKJinKAhnH-YLeeH-ENamKT2015Phase transformation from hydroxyapatite to the secondary bone mineral, whitlockiteJournal of Materials Chemistry B31342134910.1039/c4tb01793e </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-37"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Kohring &amp; Hirsch (1996)KohringRHirschKF1996Crocodilian and avian eggshells from the Middle Eocene of the Geiseltal, Eastern GermanyJournal of Vertebrate Paleontology16678010.1080/02724634.1996.10011285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-38"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Kusada et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>(2011)KusadaSIwasawaADoiOOhyaYYoshizakiN2011Diversity of the cuticle layer of avian eggshellsJournal of Poultry Science4811912410.2141/jpsa.010103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-39"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Maiber et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>(2016)MaiberMReglinBNitzscheBXiangWRongWWHoffmannBDjonovVSecombTWPriesAR2016Structure and hemodynamics of vascular networks in the chorioallantoic membrane of the chickenAmerican Journal of Physiology31191392610.1152/ajpheart.00786.2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-40"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Mikhailov (1991)MikhailovKE1991Classification of fossil eggshells of amniotic vertebratesActa Palaeontologica Polonica36193238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-41"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Mikhailov &amp; British Ornithologists’ Club (1997)MikhailovKEBritish Ornithologists’ Club1997Avian eggshells: an atlas of scanning electron micrographsBritish Ornithologists’ ClubTring </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-42"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Mikšík et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>(2007)MikšíkIEckhardtASedlákováPMikulikovaK2007Proteins of insoluble matrix of avian (Gallus gallus) eggshellConnective Tissue Research481810.1080/0300820060100311617364661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-43"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Norell et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(1995)NorellMAClarkJMChiappeLMDashzevegD1995A nesting dinosaurNature37877477610.1038/378774a0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-44"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Nys &amp; Guyot (2011)NysYGuyotN2011Egg formation and chemistryImproving the safety and quality of eggs and egg productsWoodhead PublishingCambridgeNysYBainMvan ImmerseelF83132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-45"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Nys et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>(1991)NysYZawadzkiJGautronJMillsA1991Whitening of brown-shelled eggs: mineral composition of uterine fluid and rate of protoporphyrin depositionPoultry Science701236124510.3382/ps.0701236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-46"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Oskam et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>(2010)OskamCLHaileJMcLayERigbyPAllentoftMEOlsenMEBengtssonCMillerGHSchwenningerJ-LJacombCWalterRBaynesADortchJParker-PearsonMGilbertMTPHoldawayRNWillerslevEBunceM2010Fossil avian eggshell preserves ancient DNAProceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences2771991200010.1098/rspb.2009.2019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-47"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Packard &amp; DeMarco (1991)PackardMJDeMarcoVG1991Eggshell structure and formation in eggs of oviparous reptilesEgg incubation: its effects on embryonic development in birds and reptilesCambridge University PressCambridgeDeemingCDFergusonMWJ </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-48"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Rahman et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>(2009)RahmanMAMoriyamaAIwasawaAYoshizakiN2009Cuticle formation in quail eggsZoological Science2649649910.2108/zsj.26.49619663645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-49"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Reisz et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>(2013)ReiszRRHuangTDRobertsEMPengSSullivanCSteinKLeBlancARHShiehDChangRChiangCYangCZhongS2013Embryology of Early Jurassic dinosaur from China with evidence of preserved organic remainsNature49621021410.1038/nature1197823579680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-50"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Rey et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>(2011)ReyCCombesCDrouetCGrossinD2011Bioactive ceramics: physical chemistryComprehensive biomaterialsOxfordElsevierDucheynePHealyKHutmacherDGraingerDEKirkpatrickJ187221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-51"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Rodríguez-Navarro et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>(2013)Rodríguez-NavarroABDomínguez-GascaNMuñozAOrtega-HuertasM2013Change in the chicken eggshell cuticle with hen age and egg freshnessPoultry Science923026303510.3382/ps.2013-03230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-52"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Romanoff &amp; Romanoff (1949)RomanoffALRomanoffAJ1949The avian eggJohn Wiley &amp; Sons IncHoboken </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-53"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Sander et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>(1998)SanderPMPeitzCGallemiJCousinR1998Dinosaur nesting on a red beach?Comptes Rendus de l’Académie des Sciences3276774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-54"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Sander et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>(2008)SanderPMPeitzCJacksonFDChiappeLM2008Upper Cretaceous titanosaur nesting sites and their implications for sauropod dinosaur reproductive biologyPalaeontographica Abteilung A28469107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-55"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Sauer et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>(1994)SauerGRZunicWBDurigJRWuthierRE1994Fourier transform Raman spectroscopy of synthetic and biological calcium phosphatesCalcified Tissue International5441442010.1007/bf003055298062160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-56"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Schwartz et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>(1975)SchwartzSStephensonBDSarkarDHBrachoMR1975Red, white, and blue eggs as models of porphyrin and heme metabolismAnnals of the New York Academy of Sciences24457058810.1111/j.1749-6632.1975.tb41555.x1056177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-57"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Schweitzer et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>(2005)SchweitzerMHWittmeyerJLHornerJRToporskiJK2005Soft-tissue vessels and cellular preservation in Tyrannosaurus rexScience3071952195510.1126/science.110839715790853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-58"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Simons (1971)SimonsPCM1971Ultrastructure of hen’s egg physiological interpretationPh.D DissertationAgricultural University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-59"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Sochava (1971)SochavaAV1971Two types of egg shells of Senonian dinosaursPaleontologicheskii Zhurnal38088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-60"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Tanaka, Zelenitsky &amp; Therrien (2015)TanakaKZelenitskyDKTherrienF2015Eggshell porosity provides insight on evolution of nesting in dinosaursPLOS ONE10e014282910.1371/journal.pone.014282926605799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-61"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Thomas et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>(2015)ThomasDBHauberMEHanleyDWaterhouseGINFraserSGordonKC2015Analysing avian eggshell pigments with Raman spectroscopyThe Journal of Experimental Biology2182670267410.1242/jeb.12491726113138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-62"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Thompson &amp; Goldie (1990)ThompsonMBGoldieKN1990Conductance and structure of eggs of Adelie penguins, Pygoscelis adeliae, and its implications for incubationThe Condor9230431210.2307/1368228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-63"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Varricchio &amp; Jackson (2004)VarricchioDJJacksonFD2004A phylogenetic assessment of prismatic dinosaur eggs from the Cretaceous Two Medicine Formation of MontanaJournal of Vertebrate Paleontology2493193710.1671/0272-4634(2004)024[0931:apaopd]2.0.co;2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-64"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Varricchio &amp; Jackson (2016)VarricchioDJJacksonFD2016Reproduction in Mesozoic birds and evolution of the modern avian reproductive modeThe Auk13365468410.1642/auk-15-216.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-65"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Varricchio et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>(1997)VarricchioDJJacksonFBorkowskiJJHornerJR1997Nest and egg clutches of the dinosaur Troodon formosus and the evolution of avian reproductive traitsNature38524725010.1038/385247a0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-66"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Varricchio et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>(2013)VarricchioDJJacksonFDJacksonRAZelenitskyDK2013Porosity and water vapor conductance of two Troodon formosus eggs: an assessment of incubation strategy in a maniraptoran dinosaurPaleobiology3927829610.1666/11042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-67"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Varricchio et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>(2008)VarricchioDJMooreJREricksonGMNorellMAJacksonFDBorkowskiJJ2008Avian paternal care had dinosaur originScience3221826182810.1126/science.116324519095938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-68"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Vila et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>(2010)VilaBJacksonFDFortunyJSellésAGGalobartÀ20103-D modelling of megaloolithid clutches: insights about nest construction and dinosaur behaviourPLOS ONE5e1036210.1371/journal.pone.001036220463953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-69"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Walters et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>(1990)WaltersMALeungYCBlumenthalNCKonskerKALeGerosRZ1990A Raman and infrared spectroscopic investigation of biological hydroxyapatiteJournal of Inorganic Biochemistry3919320010.1016/0162-0134(90)84002-72168470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-70"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Wedral, Vadehra &amp; Baker (1974)WedralEMVadehraDVBakerRC1974Chemical composition of the cuticle, and the inner and outer shell membranes from eggs of Gallus gallusComparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B: Comparative Biochemistry4763164010.1016/0305-0491(74)90011-X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-71"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Wiemann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>(2017)WiemannJYangT-RSanderPNSchneiderMEngeserMKath-SchorrSMüllerCESanderPM2017Dinosaur origin of egg color: oviraptors laid blue-green eggsPeerJ5e132310.7717/peerj.3706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-72"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Wilson et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>(2017)WilsonPWSutherCSBainMMIckenWJonesAQuinlan-PluckFOloriVGautronJDunnIC2017Understanding avian egg cuticle formation in the oviduct: a study of its origin and depositionBiology of Reproduction97394910.1093/biolre/iox07028859284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-73"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Yang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>(2015)YangT-RSanderPMWiemannJChengY-N2015Reproductive biology of the oviraptorid dinosaurs revealed by the interpreted egg inner structuresProgram and abstracts book of the third international symposium of paleohistologyBonn, GermanyCanovillePMitchelJ SteinKKonietzko-MeierDTeschnerEvan HeterenASanderPMp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-74"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Yang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>(2016)YangT-Rvan HeterenAWiemannJChenC-JSpieringB2016Communal nesting behavior of dinosaurs revealed by statistical analyses of phosphorus distribution in, and external morphology of, eggshellsProgram and abstracts book of the 76th SVP annual meetingSociety of Vertebrate PaleontologySalt Lake City, Utah, United Statesp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>255FarkeAMacKenzieAMiller-CampJ </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-75"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Zhang (2009)ZhangS2009Hugang formationGeological formation names of China (1866–2000)Springer VerlagBerlinp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>466ZhangS </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-76"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Zhao (1975)ZhaoZ1975Microstructures of the dinosaurian eggshells of Nanxiong, Guangdong, and the problems in egg classificationVertebrata Palasiatica132105117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
