<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Belg Soc Radiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Belg Soc Radiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2514-8281</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of the Belgian Society of Radiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2514-8281</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Ubiquity Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6032655</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/jbsr.1536</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Renal Angiomyolipoma: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name><email>nicolas.vos@uzleuven.be</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oyen</surname><given-names>Raymond</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label>University Hospitals Leuven, BE</aff><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2018-04-20"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>41</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-11"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-04-04"><day>04</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2018 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. See <uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://jbsr.be/articles/10.5334/jbsr.1536/"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Angiomyolipomas (AMLs) are the most common benign renal tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Most of these neoplasms are found incidentally on imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, symptomatic presentation does exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Renal AMLs are typically composed of smooth muscle, blood vessels, and adipose tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Because of the abundant fat tissue, they give a characteristic appearance on imaging and are therefore easily diagnosed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>However, sometimes they contain too little fat to be detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This increases the difficulty in differentiating them from renal cell carcinoma (RCC). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Management of AML is based on clinical presentation and should be individualized for every patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Treatment modalities range from active surveillance to more invasive approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>angiomyolipoma</kwd><kwd>renal</kwd><kwd>tuberous sclerosis complex</kwd><kwd>imaging</kwd><kwd>therapy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Angiomyolipomas (AMLs) are the most frequent benign renal tumour, with a prevalence varying between 0.2% and 0.6% and a strong female predilection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>They occur as sporadic, isolated entities in 80% of cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The remaining 20% of AMLs develop in association with tuberosclerosis complex (TSC) or pulmonary lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>AMLs are considered as a heterogeneous group of neoplasms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Many types display different pathology, radiological features, and clinical behaviour, although they all consist of variable proportions of the same three elements: smooth muscle, blood vessels, and adipose tissue [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Imaging plays a central role in the diagnosis and management of renal AMLs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The detection of adipose tissue is the fundamental diagnostic criterion of a classic AML [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, a minority of AMLs lack visually detectable fat on imaging, making it harder to distinguish from renal cell carcinoma (RCC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Therefore, accurate preoperative diagnosis of renal AMLs is critical to prevent unnecessary nephrectomies and preserve renal functions [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this review is to provide a radiological classification of renal AML that contributes to the understanding and diagnosis of the different types and the appropriate therapeutic management and follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Classifications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Clinical Classification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>About 80% of AMLs present as isolated entities, most commonly manifesting in middle-aged women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>They tend to be single and small and rarely progress to cause significant morbidity [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In the remainder 20% of cases, AMLs occur in association with TSC or, less commonly, as part of LAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Relative to the sporadic form of AML, these hereditary lesions affect both genders equally and manifest at a younger age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>They are likely to be multiple, large, and bilateral, and are prone to grow and be more aggressive [357]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>AMLs are observed in approximately 75% of patients with TSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>TSC is an autosomal dominant multisystem disorder characterized by the development of benign tumours (hamartomas) in multiple organs throughout the body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The main organs involved are the brain, skin, lung, and kidney [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>TSC is caused by mutations in one of two genes, TSC1 and TSC2, which encode the proteins hamartin and tuberin, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These proteins interact with each other to form a tumour suppressor complex, which inhibits the mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This pathway is important for angiogenesis, protein synthesis, and cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Defective or deficient TSC1 or TSC2 activity leads to unchecked activation of mTOR and formation of characteristic hamartomas [267]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>AMLs may also develop in patients with LAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This rare disorder may occur sporadically, in the absence of other diseases, but is common in patients with TSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>It is characterized by diffuse interstitial proliferation of smooth muscle cells (LAM cells) and the presence of thin-walled cysts distributed throughout the lungs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>These LAM cells have mutations in the same TSC1 and TSC2 genes [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Histological Classification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Renal AML can be classified histologically as typical (triphasic) or atypical (monophasic or epithelioid) [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Most AMLs contain all three components, namely dilated blood vessels (angio), smooth muscle cells (myo), and mature adipocytes (lipo), in various proportions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>They are classified as triphasic tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, some tumours consist almost exclusively of one component, while other elements are present in very small amounts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>They are called monophasic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>At last, the epithelioid variant of AML contains numerous epithelioid muscle cells with abundant eosinophilic and granular cytoplasm and few or no fat cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These tumours have a tendency toward malignant transformation and can be locally aggressive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Histologically, they can resemble and be misdiagnosed as RCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>However, distinction of epithelioid AMLs from RCC is possible by the presence of immunohistochemistry markers, such as smooth muscle markers (caldesmon and smooth muscle actin) and melanocytic markers (HMB-45 antigen and melan-A) [2345]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Radiological Classification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>There is a growing body of literature describing findings and techniques that may be used to distinguish renal AMLs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A lack of a generally accepted and standardized terminology or classification of AML fuels the persisting confusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In this review, a radiological classification reported by two groups of authors will be discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A recent article hypothesized that renal AMLs can be classified according to CT and MRI findings using quantitative values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>They classified these tumours as fat-rich, fat-poor, or fat- invisible, based on the amount of fat detected on imaging studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To distinguish these different types, a region of interest (ROI) was placed in the most hypodense area of the lesion to measure the attenuation value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>A lesion was defined as fat-rich when the ROI measured ≤ –10 Hounsfield units (HU) on unenhanced CT (UECT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>However, UECT could not differentiate fat-poor from fat-invisible AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Therefore chemical shift imaging (CSI) MRI was introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>This modality provides a higher sensitivity for fat detection than UECT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>As in UECT, the most signal-dropped area was detected and a ROI was placed within. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>On CSI-MRI, fat-poor AML was characterized when the tumour-to-spleen ratio (TSR) was &lt; 0.71 or the signal intensity index (SII) was &gt; 16.5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Because of too little fat, fat-invisible AML was defined having a TSR ≥ 0.71 and a SII ≤ 16.5% [910]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This classification showed an almost perfect inter-reader agreement, which means it is feasible for radiologists to apply in practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to understand that detection of the most hypodense area on CT or most signal-dropped area on MRI and placement of the ROI within is crucial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A mislocation or inappropriate size of the ROI may change the type of AML, with misclassification and unwanted procedures as a result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Another disadvantage is the fact that different CT and MR scanners may produce different attenuation numbers and signal intensities, leading to a wrong classification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For example, if an AML is measured –9 HU at one CT scanner, it will be classified as fat-poor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>However, if another scanner describes the lesion as –11 HU, it will be classified as fat-rich. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Although the difference of 2 HU is very minimal and probably insignificant, the management is completely different [910]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Another review article proposed a classification based on clinical, histologic, and imaging features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>First, the authors divided renal AMLs into sporadic and hereditary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Histologically, they classified sporadic AMLs into benign triphasic type and potentially malignant epithelioid type [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Benign triphasic type was further divided into fat-rich and fat-poor AML using imaging modalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>While fat-rich AML contained enough fat to be detected on UECT (ROI ≤ –10 HU), fat-poor AML did not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Fat-poor AML was further classified into three subtypes, based on the amount and distribution of adipocytes within the lesion and other imaging features: hyperattenuating AML, isoattenuating AML, and AML with epithelial cysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Hyperattenuating AML was hyperattenuating compared to renal parenchyma on UECT (&gt; 45 HU), homogeneously enhancing on contrast enhanced CT, and T2-hypointense on MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, isoattenuating AML was characterized by attenuation numbers close to renal parenchyma on UECT (between –10 and 45 HU). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>These lower attenuation levels were caused by the presence of fat cells, sufficient in quantity to lower the overall attenuation relative to hyperattenuating AMLs, but too few in one area to be detected on regular imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Finally, AMLs with epithelial cysts could be distinguished by the presence of epithelial cysts, with the non-cystic parts appearing similar to hyperattenuating AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Radiological features of this rare subtype could not be fully described, due to the lack of data [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Epithelioid AMLs, that can be potentially malignant and metastasize, showed hyperattenuation on UECT, heterogeneously enhancement on contrast enhanced CT, and T2-hypointensity on MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>These findings were caused by the epithelioid muscle component and the intratumoral haemorrhage and necrosis [3410]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>There are limitations associated with the classification described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>First, the requirement of clinical and pathological information makes it difficult for radiologists to use in daily practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Second, there are problems in applying the imaging criteria for classifying isoattenuating AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The authors reported isoattenuating AML being an AML with attenuation values between –10 and 45 HU on UECT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>However, simple renal cysts have attenuation numbers ranging between –10 and 10 and appear definitely hypoattenuating, while renal masses measuring &gt; 40 HU frequently appear hyperattenuating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>So, because of the wide range of AML attenuation values, “isoattenuating AML” does not seem to be an appropriate term. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the authors did not suggest a quantitative threshold for CSI-MRI, which means that radiologists cannot classify AML using TSR or SII [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the classification first described is the most easily applicable in practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Radiologists can categorize renal AMLs as fat-rich, fat-poor, and fat-invisible, according to the amount of fat detected on UECT or CSI-MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>However, attention should be paid to fit the ROI within the right area of the fat tissue, otherwise many fat-rich or fat-poor AMLs may be misclassified as fat-poor or fat-invisible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Table 1 summarizes the features of this classification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Radiological classification of renal AML [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>UECT Region of interest (ROI) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>MRI-CSI Tumour-to-spleen ratio (TSR) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>MRI-CSI Signal intensity index (SII) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Fat-rich AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>≤ –10 HU </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>&lt; 0.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>&gt; 16.5% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Fat-poor AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>&gt; –10 HU </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>&lt; 0.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>&gt; 16.5% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Fat-invisible AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>&gt; –10 HU </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>≥ 0.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>≤ 16.5% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Diagnosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Clinical Presentation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The increased use of cross-sectional imaging and advances in imaging technology explain that the majority (&gt; 80%) of AMLs are now incidentally found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Most patients are asymptomatic when they receive the diagnosis of an AML [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Symptomatic presentation is most frequently related to spontaneous retroperitoneal haemorrhage, although this is seen in less than 15% of cases [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>This may lead to shock in one-third of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Therefore, risk of a life-threatening bleeding is the main clinical concern in a patient diagnosed with AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Other symptoms and signs include a palpable mass, flank pain, haematuria, anaemia, urinary tract infection, or renal failure [1112]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the benign prognosis of classic renal AMLs, the epithelioid variant may undergo malignant transformation, although this is rare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>This is manifested by local aggressiveness, including lymphadenopathy, and distal metastases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The larger the tumour, the more likely it is to spread [311]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In TSC and LAM, the disease process tends to be more aggressive compared to the sporadic form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This implicates that symptomatic presentation is more common in this subgroup [612]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In TSC, hamartomas are formed in multiple organs throughout the body, leading to a variety of symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>About 90% of patients with TSC have skin manifestations, with a range from facial angiofibromas to hypomelanotic macules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Neurological symptoms, including epilepsy, behavioural problems, and cognitive impairment, occur in up to 85% of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Renal AMLs are present in approximately 75% of patients with TSC and manifest as bilateral and multiple tumours, with a high tendency to grow and cause spontaneous bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>LAM, in association with TSC or in the sporadic form, is characterised by cystic changes within the lung parenchyma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>This may lead to chylous pleural effusions, recurrent pneumothoraces, and cystic lung disease [2678]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Imaging Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Typical renal AML can be diagnosed accurately based on imaging findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The demonstration of macroscopic fat within a lesion is the hallmark feature on all modalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, AML represent a diagnostic challenge for every imaging method in case of haemorrhage, calcification, necrosis, or low fat content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>All imaging features of renal AML are summarized in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Imaging features of renal AML [23491011]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>US </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>UECT </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>MRI-T1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>MRI-T2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>MRI-CSI </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Fat-rich AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Markedly hyperechoic </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Hypoattenuating </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Signal loss on FS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Hyperintense </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Decrease in signal intensity </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Fat-poor AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Slightly hyperechoic </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneously isoattenuating or hyperattenuating </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>+/– signal loss on FS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneously or homogeneosly hypointense </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Decrease in signal intensity </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Fat- invisible AML </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Isoechoic </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Homogeneously hyperattenuating </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>No signal loss on FS </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Homogeneously hypointense </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>No decrease in signal intensity </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Note: FS = fat suppression; +/– = loss of signal on fat-suppressed MRI may or may not be present. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Ultrasound </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The classical appearance of a fat-rich AML on ultrasound (US) is that of a hyperechoic lesion with a posterior acoustic shadow (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The hyperechoic nature of a classic AML is the result of the combination of its fat, blood vessel, and muscle contents, while the shadowing is due to the multiple tissue interfaces between those different elements [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The echogenicity of the mass is the same as or greater than that of the renal sinus [234]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, this hyperechogenicity is not a constant finding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>As the amount of fat deceases, the echogenicity of the lesion decreases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Fat-poor AML has a mixed echotexture, being hyperechoic and isoechoic compared with renal parenchyma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Fat-invisible AML is homogenously isoechoic with respect to renal parenchyma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The echogenicity of both tumours is less than that of the renal sinus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>It is challenging to differentiate them from other renal lesions such as RCC, which has an echogenicity that is also less than that of the renal sinus [3410]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The lack of sensitivity of US at defining small renal masses implicates that the diagnostic reliability of this imaging modality is not high enough to allow it to be used for diagnosing renal AMLs in daily practice [211]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Additional imaging studies may be needed to confirm the diagnosis, i.e. the presence of fat. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>US image showing a fat-rich AML (arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The tumour is more hyperechoic than the right renal sinus (asterisk) [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbsr-102-1-1536-g1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Computed Tomography </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The imaged-based detection of fat generally starts with CT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>As on US, the characteristics of AMLs on UECT may vary due to variable quantities of angiogenic, myogenic, and fatty elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The presence of ROIs containing attenuations of –10 HU or less is a reliable sign of an area of adipose tissue [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Therefore, detecting fat is feasible in most fat-rich AMLs (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>However, some fat-rich AMLs contain very small areas of fat, which may not be recognized at CT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the acquisition of thin slice sections (1.5–3.0 mm) and obtaining attenuation measurements using small ROIs or even pixel values may be needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Several authors reported a higher sensitivity for detecting small foci of fat when using pixel mapping, using a line or square of four pixels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In fat-poor AMLs, UECT cannot show a hypoattenuating area measuring less than –10 HU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The attenuation values of such lesions range widely, according to the size or location of a ROI: when a ROI is placed in a region of muscle cells and vessels, the lesion attenuation will be higher than when a ROI is placed in an area that consists mostly of fat cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>For this reason, fat-poor AMLs are heterogeneously isoattenuating or hyperattenuating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, fat-invisible AMLs appear homogenously hyperattenuating (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Because they contain too little fat cells, UECT is not able to show any fat attenuation in these lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>So wherever a ROI is placed in fat-invisible AMLs, their attenuation numbers tend to be higher and fairly constant compared with those of fat-poor AMLs [91011]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>UECT showing bilateral and multiple AMLs in a patient with TSC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Each lesion contains attenuation numbers less than –10 HU, consistent with fat-rich AML [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbsr-102-1-1536-g2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>UECT demonstrating a left solid renal lesion (arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It appears homogeneously hyperdense and has attenuation values as high as 44 HU, consistent with fat-invisible AML [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbsr-102-1-1536-g3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>There are several other variants in which an AML can appear on UECT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Frequently, a perirenal or intratumoural haemorrhage is present (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This hyperdense collection may obscure the fat, leading to misdiagnosing a simple AML as a renal cancer [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Lesions that contain fat and calcifications also represent a diagnostic challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>As the presence of adipose tissue is highly suggestive of AML, the presence of calcification raises the possibility of renal cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>However, several authors reported the existence of both AMLs with calcification and RCCs having fat without calcification [111314]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Another, less frequent appearance is that of necrosis within a lesion, being rather typical for epithelioid AMLs [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Contrast-enhanced CT showing two features: a perirenal hematoma and enhancing lesion with aneurysm formation (arrowhead) and a thrombus in the IVC (arrow) [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbsr-102-1-1536-g4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Contrast-enhanced CT is not routinely indicated in diagnosing renal AMLs, but should be performed in selected cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Frequently, large AMLs contain dilated blood vessels that have the potential of rupturing and bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Whenever tumour bleeding is suspected, it is essential to identify the tortuous vessels using contrast-enhanced CT, before therapeutic embolization can be scheduled [1015]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Magnetic Resonance Imaging </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In the diagnosis of AML, MRI is equivalent in accuracy to CT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Several MRI sequences can be used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The classical approach is to locate fat within a mass by comparing T1-weighted images with and without frequency selective fat suppression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A classic fat-rich AML appears T1-hypointense with and T1-hyperintense without fat suppression [234]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>However, this T1-hyperintensity is not a specific characteristic of AML and can also be present in RCC and haemorrhagic cysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Moreover, fat-invisible AMLs contain too little fat to show any hypointensity on fat-suppressed T1-weighted images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In such cases, other techniques may help in differentiating between those entities [1116]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>More recently, the application of MRI artefacts has been suggested to evaluate fat in renal tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>One of them, the chemical shift artefact, is due to the differences between resonance frequencies of fat and water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This results in alternating high and low signals in the frequency encoding direction on opposed-phase imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>This out-of-phase cancellation effect between fat and water gives rise to another MRI artefact, called the black boundary or India ink artefact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>This artificially created black line is located at the junction of fat (present in AML cells) and water (present in renal parenchyma) and results in a sharp delineation of the muscle-fat boundary (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This sign is indicative of an AML [341116]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>It is especially useful in fat-poor AMLs and very small lesions, in which the typical T1 features may not be noticeable [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>However, fat-invisible AMLs do not show this decrease in signal intensity, because they contain too little fat cells [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Opposed-phase T1-weighted MR image with a hyperintense renal mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The India ink artefact (arrow) is present at the interface of the lesion with the kidney [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbsr-102-1-1536-g5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>T2-weighted images can also be used for diagnosing AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Fat-rich AML typically is hyperintense with respect to renal parenchyma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>It has hyperintense foci within a hypointense background, because areas of fat are distributed among blood vessels and muscle cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Fat-poor AML is either homogeneous or heterogeneous hypointense compared with renal tissue, depending on the distribution of its areas of fat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>If these areas are small but diffuse, the signal intensity is homogeneous, while it is heterogeneous when fat cells are located focal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Finally, fat-invisible AML is homogeneously hypointense in comparison to renal parenchyma on T2, because of the dominance of the muscle component and the paucity of adipose tissue [23410]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Contrast-enhanced MRI has a limited role in the diagnosis of AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>After intravenous administration of gadolinium, renal AMLs show hypointense compared to renal parenchyma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, these enhancement characteristics appear to be similar to those of hypovascular RCCs [1117]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Percutaneous Biopsy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Most AMLs can be diagnosed with imaging by identifying intralesional fat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>However, in select cases, the use of imaging alone is insufficient and percutaneous renal biopsy may be necessary for correctly diagnosing the renal mass, thus avoiding unnecessary treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, percutaneous biopsy is increasingly used to differentiate between benign and malignant renal lesions [1819]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Currently, percutaneous renal biopsy is recommended only for differentiating fat-invisible AML from RCC, if both CT and MR images are inconclusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A fat-invisible AML typically appears as a hyperattenuating mass that enhance homogenously on UECT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Although this presentation is uncommon for a RCC, both pathologies may appear identical on imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In these cases, the mass should be evaluated with MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>While a fat-invisible AML is homogenously hypointense on T2-weighted MR images, clear cell RCC appears hyperintense [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>However, the papillary subtype of RCC appears also hypointense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Therefore, percutaneous biopsy is required to differentiate fat-invisible AML and papillary RCC when a small (less than 3 cm), T2-hypointense renal mass without evidence of intratumoural fat is encountered [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>If the lesion is larger (more than 3 cm) or if there is evidence of haemorrhage, percutaneous biopsy may be skipped. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Proceeding directly to a suitable treatment may be a more appropriate option, both to avoid further bleeding and because epithelioid AML and RCC are more presumable [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Differential Diagnosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Over the last decades, the detection of small renal masses definitely increased by the increased use of cross-sectional imaging studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>A lot of these incidentally found renal lesions are usually presumed to be RCC and are treated as such. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>However, a recent study showed that 21.5% of those lesions turned out to be benign after surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>AML accounted for nearly half of this group of benign masses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This shows that the differentiation between AML and RCC remains difficult in routine practice [202122]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>As already repeatedly stated above, classic AML can be distinguished from RCC by the presence of macroscopic fat in sufficient quantity to be detected on UECT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, in 4–5% of AML cases, no fat can be visualized on CT, increasing the difficulty in differentiating it from RCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Correctly diagnosing this fat-poor and fat-invisible AML requires sufficient clinical and imaging information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Clinical information supporting a diagnosis of AML includes a younger age, female sex, and asymptomatic presentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Imaging findings that should raise the suspicion of AML include the absence of calcification, the absence of perinephric collateral vessels, multiple lesions, hyperattenuation in comparison to renal parenchyma on UECT, and hypointensity on T2-weighted MRI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>However, because these characteristic features are not present in every AML and exceptions do exist, no single finding or modality is perfectly accurate [2021222324]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>As most renal AMLs are diagnosed incidentally in asymptomatic patients, therapeutic interventions are required in a minority of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Potential interventions include selective renal artery embolization, nephron-sparing surgery, complete nephrectomy, cryo- and radiofrequency ablation, and treatment with mTOR inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Indications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Historically, the main indications for intervention have been the presence of symptoms, the presence in women of childbearing age, suspicion of malignancy, and size larger than 4 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The use of a 4 cm tumour size as a criterion for treatment comes from a frequently quoted review published in 1986 [21119]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The authors of this review reported that 82% of patients with renal AMLs larger than 4 cm experienced symptoms and 51% of them presented with active retroperitoneal haemorrhage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Other early series showed that patients with tumours larger than 4 cm had interval growth and needed treatment more often. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>They all suggested 4 cm as the limit above which an intervention should be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>This threshold has been widely adopted for many years, although the understanding of the biology and management of the disease have changed significantly since then [252627]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>However, this threshold has recently been questioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Recent studies do not support the 4 cm size criterion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>One author found that only 30% of AMLs larger than 4 cm were symptomatic [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Another one showed that using a cut-off of 4 cm as predictor of haemorrhage has a lower specificity than an aneurysm size of 5 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In other series, the angiographic appearance of AMLs was used for analysing them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>They found that lesions with high vascularity (multiple, large, tortuous vessels) were more likely to require intervention for bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>All this evidence would suggest that, although tumour diameter is important, the size of related aneurysms and the vascularity of the AML may ultimately be more significant [1127]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>As most AMLs now are found incidentally, physicians are challenged by a treatment dilemma when an AML in an asymptomatic patient reaches the 4-cm threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>They are worried that these “large” lesions may rupture and cause life-threatening bleeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Consequently, AMLs are often imaged intensively and repeatedly, and treated empirically once they attain a diameter of 4 cm [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The current guidelines of the European Association of Urology recommend intervention in well-selected cases, including symptomatic tumours, large lesions, presence in women of childbearing age, and poor access to follow-up or emergency care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>A size threshold for treatment, however, remains controversial [2242526]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Active Surveillance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Once the initial diagnostic evaluations are completed and indications for treatment are not present, active surveillance should be used to monitor progression of known tumours and development of new ones [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>For sporadic AML, there are currently no guidelines on the frequency of imaging studies neither on which modality should be used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>These decisions are likely to be institution dependent and should be guided by the individual clinical scenario [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Annual repeat of imaging seems to be appropriate for small, solitary lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>For hereditary AML, the International Tuberous Sclerosis Complex Consensus recommends the use of MRI, because of its increased sensitivity in the detection of adipose tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Annual clinical evaluation of renal function and blood pressure is also required in these cases [192830]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Embolization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Historically, there was a greater tendency towards surgery in the treatment of renal AMLs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>They were often excised because malignancy could not be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>However, this has shifted, as AMLs can now be confidently recognized at imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Selective transarterial embolization is now the first-line treatment option, especially in the event of acute bleeding or hemodynamic instability [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Many clinicians favour embolization and reserve surgery for patients with uncontrollable symptoms, vascular malformations, failure of embolization, and rare diagnostic uncertainty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>When surgery needs to be performed, preoperative embolization of the lesion may be taken into consideration in reducing the difficulty and complications of tumourectomy or nephrectomy [11192732]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Embolization is associated with a relatively high percentage of side effects (42.8%), although most of these are post-embolization syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>This self-limiting condition is characterized by fever, flank pain, leucocytosis, nausea, and vomiting within the first three days after the procedure, and it is managed conservatively with standard supportive care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Routine prophylaxis, including antipyretics, antiemetics and analgesia, may play a role in periprocedural management [227]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Other complications, including non-target embolization of normal parenchyma or renal infarction with abscess forming, are uncommon [111932]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>In general though, arterial embolization is a well-tolerated procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Although it is now seen as the first-line treatment for patients with AMLs, both regrowth and repeated haemorrhage after embolization remain a concern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The effect of embolization may vary, because of the varying amounts of adipose, vascular, and smooth muscle tissue in the lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Different authors showed in their series a need for reembolization varying from 17% till 37% [323334]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Surgery </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Surgical excision in the form of partial or radical nephrectomy is the only treatment that completely removes the renal mass, although recurrence from other parts of the kidney may occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Every surgery should rely on a nephron sparing approach whenever possible [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Parenchymal preservation is even more important in patients with TSC or LAM, because of the multifocal disease pattern and the higher recurrence rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Nephrectomy is indicated only when a renal AML is very large, when suspicion of malignancy is high, and when other treatment options cannot be performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>However, in an emergency setting, a nephrectomy can be lifesaving [3132]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Ablation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>When comparing current treatment methods, cryoablation and percutaneous radiofrequency ablation appear to be attractive alternatives to embolization or surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Different series demonstrate good efficacy with minimal complications, few repeat treatments, and no recurrences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>However, reports of the use of these minimal invasive techniques are confined to small and asymptomatic lesions [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Little evidence is available on the application in larger or symptomatic tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Overall, ablation has shown some promise in the treatment of a specific AML group that some would say should be managed by active surveillance [23334]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The identification of mutations in TSC1 and TSC2 and the existence of a licensed drug targeting the mTOR pathway, lead to rapid translation of mTOR inhibitors to patients with TSC and LAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>These medicines interrupt further tumour progression and promote reversion of existing lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Sirolimus, also known as rapamycin, was the first mTOR inhibitor analysed in treating hereditary AML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>It was originally developed as immunosuppressant for use in organ transplantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Overall, sirolimus was well tolerated in these early studies, with mouth ulcers, skin lesions, dyslipidaemia, and proteinuria as most commonly encountered side effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>It is now approved for treatment of LAM [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Everolimus, another mTOR inhibitor and rapamycine derivative, has been studied the most. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Currently, the Food and Drug Administration and European Medicines Agency approve this agent for treating AML in the setting of TSC [323536]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The position of mTOR inhibitors in the management of sporadic AML still remains to be determined [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>For asymptomatic AMLs in TSC and LAM that are enlarging and larger than 3 cm, recent guidelines suggest that mTOR inhibition currently is the most effective first-line treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>The demonstrated tolerability so far to date is superior to the renal impairment caused by AML progression and is preferable to other treatment modalities [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Another concern for treating physicians is how long the treatment with those drugs should continue, as the effect of mTOR inhibition is reversible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>To continue the treatment for AML, consideration should be given to long-term complications, cost, and safety, compared with other treatment options [3236]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Renal AML is the most prevalent benign neoplasm of the kidney. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>It has a variable and heterogeneous nature, with the potential to pose serious diagnostic challenges in clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of classic AMLs are well described, but the radiological distinction between non-classic AMLs and RCCs continues to be difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Knowledge of the different types, their classification, and their radiologic appearance will help radiologists in making a correct diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>When an AML is considered in the differential diagnosis of a renal lesion that does not demonstrate classical features, confirmatory imaging, percutaneous renal biopsy, or surgical excision should be performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Several invasive, non-invasive, and pharmacologic treatment options exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Careful surveillance before and after treatment is necessary, particularly for patients with TSC or LAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Without proper management, renal AML may have serious consequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors have no competing interests to declare.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>1Fittschen, A, Wendlik, I, Oeztuerk, S, et al. Prevalence of sporadic renal angiomyolipoma: A retrospective analysis of 61,389 in- and out-patients. Abdom Imaging. 2014; 39(5): 1009–1013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/s00261-014-0129-624705668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>2Flum, AS, Hamoui, N, Said, MA, et al. Update on the diagnosis and management of renal angiomyolipoma. J Urol. 2017; 195(4): 834–846. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.juro.2015.07.126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>3Jinzaki, M, Silverman, SG, Akita, H, Nagashima, Y, Mikami, S and Oya, M. Renal angiomyolipoma: A radiological classification and update on recent developments in diagnosis and management. Abdom Imaging. 2014; 39(3): 588–604. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/s00261-014-0083-324504542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>4Jinzaki, M, Silverman, SG, Akita, H, Mikami, S and Oya, M. Diagnosis of renal angiomyolipomas: Classic, Fat-Poor, and Epithelioid types. Semin Ultrasound CT MR. 2017; 38(1): 37–46. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1053/j.sult.2016.11.00128237279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>5Lane, BR, Aydin, H, Danforth, TL, et al. Clinical correlates of renal angiomyolipoma subtypes in 209 patients: Classic, fat poor, tuberous sclerosis associated and epithelioid. J Urol. 2008; 180(3): 836–843. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.juro.2008.05.04118635231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>6Johnson, SR, Taveira-DaSilva, AM and Moss, J. Lymphangioleiomyomatosis. Clin Chest Med. 2016; 37(3): 389–403. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.ccm.2016.04.00227514586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>7von Ranke, FM, Faria, IM, Zanetti, G, Hochhegger, B, Souza, AS, Jr. and Marchiori, E. Imaging of tuberous sclerosis complex: A pictorial review. Radiol Bras. 2017; 50(1): 48–54. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1590/0100-3984.2016.002028298732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>8Pirson, Y. Tuberous sclerosis complex-associated kidney angiomyolipoma: From contemplation to action. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2013; 28(7): 1680–1685. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1093/ndt/gft00923413089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>9Song, S, Park, BK and Park, JJ. New radiologic classification of renal angiomyolipomas. Eur J Radiol. 2016; 85(10): 1835–1842. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.ejrad.2016.08.01227666625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>10Park, BK. Renal Angiomyolipoma: Radiologic Classification and Imaging Features According to the Amount of Fat. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2017; 209(4): 826–835. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/AJR.17.1797328726505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>11Halpenny, D, Snow, A, McNeill, G and Torreggiani, WC. The radiological diagnosis and treatment of renal angiomyolipoma-current status. Clin Radiol. 2010; 65(2): 99–108. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.crad.2009.09.01420103431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>12Logue, LG, Acker, RE and Sienko, AE. Best cases from the AFIP: Angiomyolipomas in tuberous sclerosis. Radiographics. 2003; 23(1): 241–246. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1148/rg.23102510912533658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>13Merran, S, Vieillefond, A, Peyromaure, M and Dupuy, C. Renal angiomyolipoma with calcification: CT-pathology correlation. Br J Radiol. 2004; 77(921): 782–783. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1259/bjr/3377617315447968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>14Schuster, TG, Ferguson, MR, Baker, DE, Schaldenbrand, JD and Solomon, MH. Papillary renal cell carcinoma containing fat without calcification mimicking angiomyolipoma on CT. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2004; 183(5): 1402–1404. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/ajr.183.5.183140215505311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>15Li, HM, Yeh, LR and Lu, K. Renal angiomyolipoma with coexistent hemorrhagic aneurysm formation and fatty thrombus in inferior vena cava: a rare presentation. Abdom Imaging. 2013; 38(1): 180–183. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/s00261-012-9886-222450723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>16Israel, GM, Hindman, N, Hecht, E and Krinsky, G. The use of opposed-phase chemical shift MRI in the diagnosis of renal angiomyolipomas. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2005; 184(6): 1868–1872. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/ajr.184.6.0184186815908544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>17Scialpi, M, Di Maggio, A, Midiri, M, Loperfido, A, Angelelli, G and Rotondo, A. Small renal masses: Assessment of lesion characterization and vascularity on dynamic contrast-enhanced MR imaging with fat suppression. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2000; 175(3): 751–757. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/ajr.175.3.175075110954462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>18Sahni, VA and Silverman, ST. Biopsy of renal masses: When and why. Cancer Imaging. 2009; 9(1): 44–55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1102/1470-7330.2009.000519602467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>19Kiefer, RM and Stavropoulos, SW. The Role of Interventional Radiology Techniques in the Management of Renal Angiomyolipomas. Curr Urol Rep. 2017; 18(5): 36 DOI: 10.1007/s11934-017-0687-628299630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>20Potretzke, AM, Potretzke, TA, Bauman, TM, et al. Computed Tomography and Magnetic Resonance Findings of Fat-Poor Angiomyolipomas. J Endourol. 2017; 31(2): 119–128. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1089/end.2016.021927897036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>21Jeon, HG, Lee, SR, Kim, KH, et al. Benign lesions after partial nephrectomy for presumed renal cell carcinoma in masses 4 cm or less: Prevalence and predictors in Korean patients. Urology. 2017; 76(3): 574–579. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.urology.2009.11.082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>22Yang, CW, Shen, SH, Chang, YH, et al. Are there useful CT features to differentiate renal cell carcinoma from lipid-poor renal angiomyolipoma? AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2013; 201(5): 1017–1028. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/AJR.12.1020424147472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>23Krishna, S, Murray, CA, McInnes, MD, et al. CT imaging of solid renal masses: pitfalls and solutions. Clin Radiol. 2017; 72(9): 708–721. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.crad.2017.05.00328592361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>24Kang, SK, Huang, WC, Pandharipande, PV and Chandarana, H. Solid renal masses: What the numbers tell us. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2017; 202(6): 1196–1206. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2214/AJR.14.12502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>25Kuusk, T, Biancari, F, Lane, B, et al. Treatment of renal angiomyolipoma: Pooled analysis of individual patient data. BMC Urol. 2015; 15: 123 DOI: 10.1186/s12894-015-0118-226710923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>26Bhatt, JR, Richard, PO, Kim, NS, et al. Natural History of Renal Angiomyolipoma (AML): Most Patients with Large AMLs &gt;4 cm Can Be Offered Active Surveillance as an Initial Management Strategy. Eur Urol. 2016; 70(1): 85–90. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.eururo.2016.01.04826873836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>27Murray, TE, Doyle, F and Lee, M. Transarterial Embolization of Angiomyolipoma: A Systematic Review. J Urol. 2017; 194(3): 635–639. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.juro.2015.04.081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>28Krueger, DA and Northrup, H. Tuberous sclerosis complex surveillance and management: Recommendations of the 2012 international tuberous sclerosis complex consensus conference. Pediatr Neurol. 2013; 49(4): 255–265. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2013.08.00224053983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>29Maclean, DFW, Sultana, R, Radwan, R, McKnight, L and Khastgir, J. Is the follow-up of small renal angiomyolipomas a necessary precaution? Clin Radiol. 69(8): 822–826. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.crad.2014.03.016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>30Eijkemans, MJ, van der Wal, W, Reijnders, JJ, et al. Long-term Follow-up Assessing Renal Angiomyolipoma Treatment Patterns, Morbidity, and Mortality: An Observational Study in Tuberous Sclerosis Complex Patients in the Netherlands. Am J Kidney Dis. 2015; 66(4): 638–645. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2015.05.01626165440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>31Urciuoli, P, D’Orazi, V, Livadoti, G, et al. Treatment of renal angiomyolipoma: surgery versus angioembolization. G Chir. 2013; 34(11–12): 326–331.24342162 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>32Seyam, RM, Alkhudair, WK, Kattan, SA, Alotaibi, MF, Alzahrani, HM and Altaweel, WM. The Risks of Renal Angiomyolipoma: Reviewing the evidence. J Kidney Cancer VHL. 2017; 4(4): 13–25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.15586/jkcvhl.2017.9729090118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>33Prevoo, W, van den Bosch, MAAJ and Horenblas, S. Radiofrequency ablation for treatment of sporadic angiomyolipoma. Urology. 2017; 72(1): 188–191. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.urology.2008.02.059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>34Makki, A, Graumann, O, Søren, S, et al. J Endourol. 2017; 31(11): 1117–1122. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1089/end.2017.037628830229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>35Bissler, JJ and Kingswood, JC. Optimal treatment of tuberous sclerosis complex associated renal angiomyolipomata: A systematic review. Ther Adv Urol. 2016; 8(4): 279–290. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1177/175628721664135327928430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>36Coombs, EJ. Role of mTOR inhibition in the treatment of patients with renal angiomyolipomas. J Am Assoc Nurse Pract. 2013; 25(11): 588–596. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1002/2327-6924.1208124170533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
