<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Circadian Rhythms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Circadian Rhythms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">1740-3391</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Circadian Rhythms</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1740-3391</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Ubiquity Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6083812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30210565</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/jcr.156</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Time of Administration of Acute or Chronic Doses of Imipramine Affects its Antidepressant Action in Rats </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6631-7682</contrib-id><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names><prefix>Dr.</prefix></name><email>hkawai@josai.ac.jp</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kodaira</surname><given-names>Natsumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Chika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>Takuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>Naomi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>Yoichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsumoto</surname><given-names>Atsushi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Josai University, 1-1 Keyakidai, Sakado, Saitama 350-0295, JP</aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Josai International Universit, 1 Gumyo, Togane, Chiba 283-8555, JP</aff><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2018-05-10"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>5</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-01-20"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-03-24"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2018 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. See <uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jcircadianrhythms.com/articles/10.5334/jcr.156/"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The pathogenesis and therapeutics of depression are linked to the operation of the circadian system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here, we studied the chronopharmacological action of a tricyclic antidepressant, imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Male adult Wistar–Hannover rats were administered imipramine acutely or chronically in the morning or in the evening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The antidepressant action of imipramine was analyzed using the forced swim test (FST). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>A single dose of imipramine (30 mg/kg) in the morning, but not in the evening, reduced immobility and increased climbing in the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The plasma concentrations of imipramine and its metabolite, desipramine, were slightly higher in the morning than in the evening, which might explain the dosing time-dependent action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Next, we analyzed the effect of chronic imipramine treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Rats received imipramine in the morning or in the evening for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The morning treatment resulted in larger effects in the FST than the evening treatment, and was effective at a dose that was ineffective when administered acutely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The levels of brain α-adrenergic receptors tended to decrease after chronic imipramine treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Imipramine might interact with noradrenergic neurons, and this interaction might chronically alter receptor expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This alteration seemed greater in the morning than in the evening, which might explain the dosing time-dependent action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Chronopharmacology</kwd><kwd>Imipramine</kwd><kwd>Forced swim test</kwd><kwd>Noradrenaline</kwd><kwd>α-Adrenergic receptor</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The pharmacological action of many substances is dependent on the circadian system, and a drug’s dosing time can affect both its therapeutic and toxic effects [12345]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Some drugs work better in the daytime, while other drugs work better at night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The best timing for a treatment depends on the chronopharmacological profile of the drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Therefore, precise knowledge of the chronopharmacological profile of a drug is essential to provide effective medication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Depression is strongly associated with the circadian system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Patients with depression often show a disturbance of the circadian rhythm of various physiological functions (e.g., a sleep disturbance). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Depression and circadian disturbance may be physiologically linked and deteriorate synergistically [678]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, the circadian system has been linked not only to the pathogenesis of depression but also to its therapeutics [910111213]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Wehr et al. reported that the circadian phase was advanced and desynchronized with the sleep-wake cycle in patients with depression, and that phase advance of the sleep-wake cycle exerted an antidepressant effect [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Phase entrainment by bright light in the morning is also effective to improve depressive symptoms [1112]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Chronotherapy of depression by the combination of sleep deprivation, sleep phase advance, and bright light treatment induces rapid amelioration in patients with depression [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Some antidepressants can interact with and modify the biological clock [141516171819]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, some antidepressants show dosing time-dependent action in animal models [2021] and in clinical settings [2223]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, the therapeutic significance of these actions remains to be clarified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Further research on the relationship between the circadian system and depression could lead to the development of an effective therapy for depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The forced swim test (FST) is one of the most common behavioral tests in rodents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Since the FST has high predictive validity, reliability, and robustness, it is useful for screening and analysis of antidepressant activity [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, there is an inconsistency between the effects of antidepressants in the FST and those in clinical settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A single dose or 2–3 injections of the antidepressant within 24 hours induce reduction of immobility indicative of antidepressant activity in the FST [252627], whereas most antidepressants are ineffective when administered acutely or subacutely in clinical settings, usually taking several weeks to show therapeutic effects in patients [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Chronic antidepressant treatment alters brain function by regulating receptor expression levels, which might contribute to alleviating the depressive symptoms [282930]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Those changes are not detectable in acute treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In order to analyze the biochemical alterations related to antidepressant activity, an animal model of chronic treatment would be necessary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Several animal and clinical studies have reported the chronopharmacological action of antidepressants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Amitriptyline, fluvoxamine, and milnacipran show dosing time-dependent antidepressant activity in rodents [2021]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, these studies have used an acute treatment model with the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Several clinical studies analyzed the chronopharmacology of chronic antidepressant treatment [223132]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>However, no such analysis has been performed in animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we aimed to develop a chronic animal model to analyze the chronopharmacological action of the antidepressant imipramine and to reveal the biochemical alterations that contribute to the chronopharmacological action of this antidepressant in this model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The present study analyzed the dosing time-dependent action of imipramine in an acute and chronic treatment model using the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We also analyzed the dosing time-dependent imipramine metabolism in the acute model and the dosing time-dependent effects of the chronic imipramine treatment on the brain levels of the α1 adrenergic receptor (α1AR) and α2 adrenergic receptor (α2AR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the circadian fluctuation of imipramine metabolism may induce dosing time-dependent changes in the efficiency of the interaction between imipramine and the adrenergic system, a target system of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Repeated interaction caused by chronic imipramine treatment may induce a dosing time-dependent alteration of adrenergic receptors protein expression, which might contribute to the chronopharmacological antidepressant action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Chemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Imipramine and other chemicals were obtained from Wako Pure Chemical Industries (Osaka, Japan), unless otherwise described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Pentobarbital was obtained from Kyoritsu Seiyaku (Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Protease inhibitor cocktail and anti-β-actin antibody (A5441) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Anti-α2-adrenergic receptor antibody (sc-28983) was obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Anti-α1-adrenergic receptor antibody (ab137123), anti-rabbit immunoglobulin G (IgG) horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (ab97051), and anti-mouse IgG horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (ab79023) were obtained from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Male adult Wistar–Hannover rats (weighing 200–250 g) were obtained from CLEA Japan (Tokyo), and were maintained in an air-conditioned room at 24 ± 2°C with a 12/12-hour light/dark cycle (lights on at 7:00 a.m.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The rats had free access to food and water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The time of the day is expressed as the zeitgeber time (ZT), defined as follows: the light onset time (7:00 a.m. clock time) is ZT0; the dark onset time (7:00 p.m. clock time) is ZT12; and ZT24 is the ZT0 of the next day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Animal maintenance and treatments were in accordance with the general recommendations of animal protection legislation in Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>All procedures were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Josai International University (approval numbers: 32 and 57). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Schedule for the analysis of the effects of acute imipramine treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>One day before measurement, rats were exposed to the FST apparatus as described below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Twenty-three hours after the first exposure, rats were intraperitoneally administered 10, 20, 30, or 50 mg/kg of imipramine (as a hydrochloride salt) at 8:00 a.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(ZT1) or 8:00 p.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(ZT13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Control rats were administered saline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>One hour after administration, the FST was carried out. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Schedule for the analysis of the effects of chronic imipramine treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Rats were exposed to the FST apparatus as described below, and the drug treatment was started the next day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The rats were intraperitoneally administered saline or imipramine for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>To equalize the number and the timing of the intraperitoneal injections among the groups, all rats were injected twice a day as shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Control rats were administered saline at ZT1 and ZT13; the morning group was administered imipramine at ZT1 and saline at ZT13; and the evening group was administered saline at ZT1 and imipramine at ZT13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Two days after the last administration, the rats were administered imipramine at a low dose (10 mg/kg) during the early light period (ZT1–3), and 1 hour after the administration, the FST was carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The rats were returned to their home cage after the FST, and they were sacrificed for biochemical analysis on the next day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Daily administration schedule for the analysis of chronic imipramine treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Administration time </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>ZT1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>ZT13 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Saline </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Saline </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Morning (imipramine at ZT1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Imipramine </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Saline </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Evening (imipramine at ZT13) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Saline </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Imipramine </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Forced swim test (FST) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We used a modified FST according to the method of Detke et al. [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>On the day before the first treatment of imipramine or saline, each rat was individually placed in a tank made of an opaque plastic cylinder (24 cm in diameter, 50 cm in height) filled with room-temperature water (24 ± 2°C) to a depth of 30 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The rat was left in the tank for 10 minutes, then removed from the cylinder, allowed to dry in a clean cage, and returned to its home cage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>On the day of measurement, the rat was again placed in the tank of room-temperature water, and its behaviors were analyzed for 5 minutes: at regular 5-second intervals, trained observers recorded which of the following three behaviors was predominant: immobility, swimming, or climbing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The total counts for each behavior over the 5-minute test session were analyzed as the FST score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>All tests were observed and scored by two or more trained observers to prevent scoring errors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Analysis of plasma imipramine concentration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Rats were administered intraperitoneally with 30 mg/kg of imipramine at ZT1 or ZT13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>One hour after administration, the rats were anesthetized with pentobarbital, and blood samples were removed from the postcaval vein with a heparinized needle attached to a heparinized syringe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The blood samples were centrifuged at 1,200 × g for 10 minutes to obtain plasma, which were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept at –80°C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Diazepam at 10 nmol was added to 1 mL of plasma as an internal standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The sample was alkalinized with 0.1 mL of 5 M NaOH and extracted twice with 1 mL of n-hexane/methanol (4/1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The organic layer was extracted twice with 0.1 mL of 0.05% phosphoric acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The extract was filtered through a 0.45-μm filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A portion of the filtrate was subjected to high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Imipramine and desipramine were analyzed with HPLC-UV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>An LC-10AD/SPD-10A system (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Separation was performed on Gemini ODS (2.1 mm in inner diameter × 150 mm, Phenomenex, Torrance, CA, USA) with a precolumn (SecurityGuard, Phenomenex) at 40°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The eluents were 80% 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 3.8), 20% acetonitrile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The flow rate was maintained at 0.2 mL/minute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Compounds were detected at 254 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Analysis of protein in the brain by western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Rats were anesthetized with pentobarbital and sacrificed by decapitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The brain was rapidly dissected out and divided into sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hippocampus were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept at –80°C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The brain tissues were homogenized in 5 volumes of lysis buffer (50 mM Tris HCl buffer [pH 7.4], 150 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate [SDS], 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, 1 mM NaF, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride [PMSF], 2 μL/mL of protease inhibitor cocktail), and centrifuged at 20,000 × g for 20 minutes at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The protein contents of the supernatant were determined using the bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of the supernatant was used to prepare the SDS sample (1 μg protein/μL in SDS loading buffer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The SDS samples were incubated at 95°C for 2 minutes, and loaded at 10 μg protein onto 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Proteins were separated at 60 V and then blotted to PVDF membranes in Tris-glycine transfer buffer at 100 V for 2 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The membrane was incubated with 5% skim milk in phosphate-buffered saline containing 0.1% Tween-20 (PBS-T) for 1 hour at room temperature, primary antibody overnight at 4°C, and horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody for 1 hour at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The membrane was washed with PBS-T 3 times for 5 minutes after the incubation with the primary and secondary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The membrane was developed with the ECL prime western blotting detection reagent (Amersham, Piscataway, NJ, USA), and analyzed using an imaging analyzer LAS-3000 (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Blots with anti-β-actin antibody were used as loading control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as the means ± standard error of the mean (SEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Dose-dependent changes against the control group were analyzed using the Williams test (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Differences between two groups were analyzed with Student’s t-test (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Effects of two factors were analyzed using 2-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Multiple pairwise comparisons among three or more groups were analyzed with Tukey’s test (Figures 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The significance level was set at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The JMP procedure (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) was applied for statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Imipramine exerts dose-dependent antidepressant actions in rats. The rats received imipramine intraperitoneally, after which they were subjected to the forced swim test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM) (n = 6 – 8). *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 vs. control by Williams test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcr-16-156-g1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Acute imipramine treatment produces dosing time-dependent effects in the forced swim test (FST). The rats were administered imipramine at ZT1 (A) or ZT13 (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>One hour after imipramine administration, the rats were subjected to the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM) (n = 10 – 13). *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 by Student’s t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcr-16-156-g2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Dosing time affects the plasma levels of imipramine and desipramine following acute imipramine treatment. Imipramine (30 mg/kg) was administered at ZT1 or ZT13, and the plasma concentrations of imipramine and desipramine were measured 1 hour later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM) (n = 3). *p &lt; 0.05 by 2-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcr-16-156-g3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Chronic imipramine treatment produces dosing time-dependent effects in the forced swim test (FST). The rats were administered imipramine at ZT1 or ZT13 for 2 weeks, and then subjected to the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The effects of chronic imipramine treatment at 10 mg/kg (A) and 30 mg/kg (B) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Each column represents the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM) (n = 8 – 18). *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 by Tukey’s test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcr-16-156-g4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Chronic imipramine treatment alters the protein level of adrenergic receptors. Imipramine (30 mg/kg) was chronically administered at ZT1 or ZT13, and the protein levels of α1AR and α2AR were analyzed with western blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The levels of α1AR (A, B) and α2AR (C, D) in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) (A, C) and hippocampus (B, D) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Each column shows the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM) (n = 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>No statistically significant difference was detected between groups by Tukey’s test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jcr-16-156-g5"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Effects of acute imipramine treatment on the FST </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The effects of acute imipramine treatment at various doses on the FST are shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In this experiment, imipramine was administered at ZT1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Williams test detected a significant reduction of immobility and a significant increase of climbing at doses equal to or higher than 20 mg/kg of imipramine (immobility: p = 0.0210, 0.0197, and 0.0275 for 20, 30, and 50 mg/kg, respectively; climbing: p = 0.0245, 0.0068, and 0.0078 for 20, 30, and 50 mg/kg, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Since the effect at 30 mg/kg was larger than the effect at other doses, we used imipramine at 30 mg/kg in the following analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The rats treated with imipramine at ZT1 or ZT13 were subjected to the FST in order to analyze the effect of dosing time on antidepressant activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The results are shown in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Imipramine significantly reduced immobility and increased climbing when administered at ZT1 (p = 0.0009 and p = 0.0126, respectively) (Figure 2A), but not at ZT13 (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Plasma concentration of imipramine </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The plasma concentrations of imipramine and its metabolite, desipramine, following imipramine treatment are shown in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Two-way ANOVA detected no interaction (F1,8 = 0.0013, p = 0.9719). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The main effect in compound, imipramine and desipramine, was significant (F1,8 = 34.0154, p = 0.0004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Although the main effect in dosing time was not significant (F1,8 = 3.8042, p = 0.0869), both imipramine and desipramine were slightly increased at ZT1 compared to ZT13. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Effects of chronic imipramine treatment on the FST </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The effects of chronic imipramine treatment on the FST are shown in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In this experiment, imipramine was administered at ZT1 or ZT13 for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>We used two doses: the same dose as in the acute treatment (30 mg/kg), and the dose that was not effective in the acute treatment (10 mg/kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>At low dose, the ZT1 group showed 24% reduction in immobility and 116% increase in climbing against the control (p = 0.0126 and p = 0.0144, respectively) (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The differences between ZT1 and ZT13 were not significant (p = 0.1359 for immobility, p = 0.1778 for climbing). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>At high dose, significant differences in immobility and climbing were detected in the ZT1 and ZT13 groups against the control (p = 0.0001 and p = 0.0030 for immobility, p &lt; 0.0001 and p = 0.0006 for climbing, respectively) (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The differences between ZT1 and ZT13 were not significant (p = 0.4310 for immobility, p = 0.0883 for climbing). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Effects of chronic imipramine administration on adrenergic receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate the alterations of the noradrenergic system induced by chronic treatment of imipramine, the protein levels of α1AR and α2AR were analyzed with western blotting (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>No significant differences were detected in the levels of α1AR and α2AR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, the mean values of imipramine-treated groups were lower than those of the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In particular, imipramine at ZT1 resulted in 37% reduction of α2AR in the hippocampus against the control, although the difference was not significant (p = 0.1018 vs. control, p = 0.6794 vs. ZT13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The present study examined the chronopharmacological effects of acute and chronic imipramine treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>We showed that imipramine works more efficiently in the morning than in the evening in rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The antidepressant effect was observed in the morning (ZT1), but not in the evening (ZT13) with a single dose of 30 mg/kg of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The same trend was observed in the chronic treatment model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Chronic imipramine in the morning induced antidepressant effects in the FST even when the dose was lower than the effective dose in the acute treatment model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Chronic imipramine might increase the drug susceptibility of the rat brain most efficiently in the morning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this is the first report that shows the chronopharmacological effects of an antidepressant in a chronic treatment model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Since antidepressants are usually used chronically in clinical settings, this model could be a useful model to analyze the chronopharmacological profile of antidepressants and the underlying mechanism of their chronopharmacological activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In the chronic treatment model, the rats were administered a low dose (10 mg/kg) of imipramine one hour before the FST as described in the Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Since imipramine was ineffective at this dose when administered acutely (Figure 1), the reduction of immobility and the increase of climbing observed in Figure 4 could not be because of the acute effect of the last low dose administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the chronic imipramine treatment caused these antidepressant effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Chronic imipramine treatment might induce alterations of the adrenergic system (target system of imipramine) such as an enhancement of noradrenergic neurons’ susceptibility to imipramine, which would induce the antidepressant effects seen after the administration of a low dose of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Chronopharmacological effects can be induced by the circadian fluctuation of the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of a drug [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Various drugs show dosing time-dependent pharmacokinetics [23333435]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Imipramine is metabolized to desipramine by CYP1A2, 3A4, and 2C19, and imipramine and desipramine are hydroxylated to the 2-OH form by CYP2D6 [3637]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Both imipramine and desipramine have antidepressant activity, while the 2-OH form of both compounds does not have antidepressant activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Therefore, intra-day fluctuation of the activity of CYP2D6 could explain the chronopharmacological action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The expression of CYPs is controlled by biological clocks, and their expression and activity show a circadian rhythm [383940414243]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The expression of CYP2D9, the murine homolog of human CYP2D6, shows a circadian rhythm with a peak at night in the mouse liver [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows that the plasma concentrations of imipramine and desipramine were 17–37% higher at ZT1 than at ZT13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Although the difference (p = 0.0869) did not meet the criteria of statistical significance, we suspect that the circadian fluctuation of CYP2D9 might have caused the difference in imipramine concentrations between ZT1 and ZT13, which might contribute to the chronopharmacological action of imipramine to some extent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Pharmacodynamics should also be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In brain monoaminergic systems, the contents of neurotransmitters and the expression of receptors and transporters show circadian rhythm [202144]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Since imipramine exerts antidepressant activity by its interaction with the serotonergic and noradrenergic systems, the circadian rhythm of these neuronal systems could cause the chronopharmacological action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In the modified FST, the increase of swimming and climbing is related to the activation of serotonergic and noradrenergic activity in the brain, respectively [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Imipramine increased climbing in the present study, suggesting that the noradrenergic system should dominantly contribute to the antidepressant activity of imipramine in rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>We suspected that desipramine played a major role in this noradrenergic effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Imipramine and desipramine inhibit both the serotonin transporter (SERT) and the noradrenaline transporter (NAT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However, the selectivity was different between imipramine and desipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The inhibitory action of imipramine is 27 times more potent on SERT than on NAT, whereas that of desipramine is 21 times more potent on NAT than on SERT [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Since the plasma concentration of desipramine was higher than that of imipramine (Figure 3), the effects of desipramine might appear dominantly in the FST. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Most antidepressants are effective only after chronic treatment in clinical settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Chronic treatment with antidepressants induces alterations in the brain function, which may lead to the alleviation of depressive symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The involvement of α2AR has been reported both in animal and clinical studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Brain α2AR density is upregulated in patients with depression [3046]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Chronic treatment with a tricyclic antidepressant induces the downregulation of α2AR in various brain regions of model animals [3047]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The present results are consistent with those of previous studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Although we could not detect significant differences, the protein levels of α1AR and α2AR tended to be reduced following chronic imipramine treatment (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Comparing ZT1 and ZT3 groups, the reduction seemed larger in the ZT1 group, especially for α2AR in the hippocampus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Since α2AR exists in the presynaptic neurons and negatively modulates noradrenaline release [30], the downregulation of the α2AR might lead to increased noradrenergic neural transmission, which might induce antidepressant effects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>There are some concerns about the validity of the FST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In this study, a low dose (10 mg/kg) of imipramine was sufficient for an antidepressant effect in the chronic model; however, a higher dose was necessary to have an antidepressant effect in the acute model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with previous studies looking at other drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Amitriptyline, mianserin, desipramine, and fluoxetine have an antidepressant effect in the FST when chronically administered at a particular dose, but this same dose does not have an antidepressant effect when administered acutely [4849]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Another study indicated that some drugs, such as mepyramine and promethazine, are effective with acute treatment but not with chronic treatment [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that the mechanism involved in the imipramine-induced anti-immobility effect in the FST is different in the chronic and acute models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Since chronic treatment is usually necessary for effective antidepressant therapy in clinical settings [24], the physiological changes observed in the acute model may be different from the changes seen in human depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The FST used in the acute model may not be a good model for the analysis of the mechanisms involved in human depression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>However, the acute FST is a useful tool for high throughput screening and analysis of antidepressant activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>There are some inconsistencies about the chronopharmacological profile of antidepressant between the present results and those of previous studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>A tricyclic antidepressant, amitriptyline, shows circadian activity rhythm with a peak at early night in an acute mouse model [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>A serotonin noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor (SNRI), milnacipran, induces a large increase in climbing at ZT13 rather than at ZT1 in an acute rat model [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In the present study, imipramine induced a large reduction in immobility and an increase in climbing in the morning (ZT1) in an acute rat model (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>We are unable to explain these inconsistencies based on the available data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>However, we suspect that differences in the mechanism of action might contribute to the different chronopharmacological profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Although amitriptyline, milnacipran, and imipramine inhibit both SERT and NAT, the relative activity to SERT and NAT is different among these compounds [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Since serotonergic and noradrenergic systems show circadian activity rhythms with different peak times [2144], the relative activity of different antidepressants on these neurons may be an important factor that determines their chronopharmacological profiles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>There are limitations to the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>(1) The chronopharmacological effect was analyzed with only two time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>(2) The contributions of neuronal systems other than the noradrenergic system were not addressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>(3) Antidepressant activity was evaluated only with the FST and by using normal naïve rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Firstly, it is impossible to determine the exact time point at which imipramine shows maximal antidepressant activity during the day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Although we observed higher antidepressant activity in the morning than in the evening, the data could not exclude the possibility that imipramine shows maximal antidepressant activity during the afternoon or at midnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Chronopharmacological analysis with three or more time points should be important to discuss the precise chronopharmacological profiles of imipramine and other antidepressants, as well as to clarify the relationships between the chronopharmacological profile and the mechanism of action of antidepressants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Secondly, the present study analyzed the effect of chronic imipramine administration only on the adrenergic receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>However, other neuronal systems such as the serotonergic, dopaminergic, and glutamatergic systems may also play an important role in the action of antidepressants [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We could not exclude the possibility that these systems show larger circadian fluctuations of the activity compared to the adrenergic system, and that these fluctuations are crucial in the chronopharmacological action of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The effects of antidepressants on these systems and their circadian system functionality should be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Thirdly, the chronopharmacological effects of antidepressants in depression patients or depressive-like animals are still unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Some physiological functions in depressive-like animals may be impaired and different from those in normal animals, which may alter the chronopharmacological effects of the antidepressants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Some drugs cannot induce antidepressant effects in animal models of depression even though they have antidepressant effects in normal animals [5253]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Patients with depression and animal models of depression sometimes show disturbances in circadian system functionality [678545556]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Chronopharmacological profiles of antidepressant activity in depressive-like animals could be different from those in normal animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Analyses using animal models of depression may clarify the chronopharmacological effects of antidepressants on behavior and brain monoaminergic systems in the depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>In this study, we revealed the chronopharmacological activity of imipramine in rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In particular, we found that chronic imipramine treatment produced dosing time-dependent antidepressant effects at a dose that was ineffective when given acutely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In the FST, imipramine showed greater antidepressant effects in the morning than in the evening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Imipramine could interact with noradrenergic neurons more effectively in the morning than in the evening, and the chronic interaction with the neurons might induce the alterations of the receptor expression, which might explain the dosing time-dependent antidepressant effects of imipramine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>This low-dose chronic model using the FST might be a useful model for the chronopharmacological analysis of antidepressants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>We are grateful for the assistance given by A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Suzuki, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Furuya, and A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Igari. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Editage for English language editing. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors have no competing interests to declare.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>1Levi, F and Schibler, U. Circadian rhythms: mechanisms and therapeutic implications. Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol. 2007; 47: 593–628. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.47.120505.10520817209800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>2Ohdo, S. Chronopharmaceutics: Pharmaceutics focused on biological rhythm. Biol Pharm Bull. 2010; 33: 159–167. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1248/bpb.33.15920118534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>3Dallmann, R, Brown, SA and Gachon, F. Chronopharmacology: new insights and therapeutic implications. Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol. 2014; 54: 339–361. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1146/annurev-pharmtox-011613-13592324160700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>4Ben-Cherif, W, Dridi, I, Aouam, K, Ben-Attia, M, Alain Reinberg, A and Boughattas, NA. Chronotolerance study of the antiepileptic drug valproic acid in mice. J Circadian Rhythms. 2012; 10: Art. 3 DOI: 10.1186/1740-3391-10-322574933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>5Miura, N, Ashimori, A, Takeuchi, A, Ohtani, K, Takada, N, Yanagiba, Y, Mita, M, Togawa, M and Hasegawa, T. Mechanisms of cadmium-induced chronotoxicity in mice. J Toxicol Sci. 2013; 38: 947–957. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.2131/jts.38.94724284284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>6Kaneita, Y, Ohida, T, Uchiyama, M, Takemura, S, Kawahara, K, Yokoyama, E, Miyake, T, Harano, S, Suzuki, K and Fujita, T. The relationship between depression and sleep disturbances: a Japanese nationwide general population survey. J Clin Psychiatry. 2006; 67: 196–203. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.4088/JCP.v67n020416566613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>7Ford, DE and Kamerow, DB. Epidemiologic study of sleep disturbances and psychiatric disorders: An opportunity for prevention? JAMA. 1989; 262: 1479–1484. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1001/jama.1989.034301100690302769898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>8Bechtel, W. Circadian rhythms and mood disorders: Are the phenomena and mechanisms causally related? Front Psychiatry. 2015; 6 DOI: 10.3389/fpsyt.2015.00118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>9Benedetti, F. Antidepressant chronotherapeutics for bipolar depression. Dialogues Clin Neurosci. 2012; 14: 401–411.23393416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>10Wehr, TA, Wirz-Justice, A, Goodwin, FK, Duncan, W and Gillin, JC. Phase advance of the circadian sleep-wake cycle as an antidepressant. Science. 1979; 206: 710–713. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1126/science.227056227056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>11Golden, RN, Gaynes, BN, Ekstrom, RD, Hamer, RM, Jacobsen, FM, Suppes, T, Wisner, KL and Nemeroff, CB. The efficacy of light therapy in the treatment of mood disorders: A review and meta-analysis of the evidence. Am J Psychiatry. 2005; 162: 656–662. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1176/appi.ajp.162.4.65615800134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>12Tuunainen, A, Kripke, DF and Endo, T. Light therapy for non-seasonal depression. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2004; 2 DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD004050.pub2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>13Voderholzer, U, Valerius, G, Schaerer, L, Riemann, D, Giedke, H, Schwarzler, F, Berger, M and Wiegand, M. Is the antidepressive effect of sleep deprivation stabilized by a three day phase advance of the sleep period? Eur Arch Psychiat Clin Neurosci. 2003; 253: 68–72. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>14Schaufler, J, Ronovsky, M, Savalli, G, Cabatic, M, Sartori, SB, Singewald, N and Pollak, DD. Fluoxetine normalizes disrupted light-induced entrainment, fragmented ultradian rhythms and altered hippocampal clock gene expression in an animal model of high trait anxiety- and depression-related behavior. Ann Med. 2016; 48: 17–27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.3109/07853890.2015.112221626679264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>15Greco, AM, Gambardella, P, Sticchi, R, D’Aponte, D and De Franciscis, P. Tricyclic imipramine modification of the circadian rhythms of hypothalamic serotonin, its precursors and acid catabolite in individually housed rats. Chronobiol Int. 1988; 5: 217–225. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.3109/074205288090795632464441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>16Rosenwasser, AM and Hayes, MJ. Neonatal desipramine treatment alters free-running circadian drinking rhythms in rats. Psychopharmacology. 1994; 115: 237–244. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/BF022447777862900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>17Yannielli, PC, Cutrera, RA, Cardinali, DP and Golombek, DA. Neonatal clomipramine treatment of Syrian hamsters: effect on the circadian system. Eur J Pharmacol. 1998; 349: 143–150. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0014-2999(98)00208-89671091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>18Sprouse, J, Braselton, J and Reynolds, L. Fluoxetine modulates the circadian biological clock via phase advances of suprachiasmatic nucleus neuronal firing. Biol Psychiatry. 2006; 60: 896–899. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.03.00316631132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>19Yoshikawa, T and Honma, S. Lithium lengthens circadian period of cultured brain slices in area specific manner. Behav Brain Res. 2016; 314: 30–37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.bbr.2016.07.04527478137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>20Ushijima, K, Sakaguchi, H, Sato, Y, To, H, Koyanagi, S, Higuchi, S and Ohdo, S. Chronopharmacological study of antidepressants in forced swimming test of mice. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2005; 315: 764–770. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1124/jpet.105.08884916079297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>21Kawai, H, Machida, M, Ishibashi, T, Kudo, N, Kawashima, Y and Mitsumoto, A. Chronopharmacological analysis of antidepressant activity of a dual-action serotonin noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor (SNRI), milnacipran, in rats. Biol Pharm Bull. 2018; 41: 213–219. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1248/bpb.b17-0073329386481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>22Nagayama, H, Nagano, K, Ikezaki, A and Tashiro, T. Double-blind study of the chronopharmacotherapy of depression. Chronobiol Int. 1991; 8: 203–209. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.3109/074205291090639271794158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>23Nakano, S and Hollister, LE. Chronopharmacology of amitriptyline. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 1983; 33: 453–459. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1038/clpt.1983.616831823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>24Slattery, DA and Cryan, JF. Using the rat forced swim test to assess antidepressant-like activity in rodents. Nat Protocols. 2012; 7: 1009–1014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1038/nprot.2012.04422555240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>25Porsolt, RD, Le Pichon, M and Jalfre, M. Depression: a new animal model sensitive to antidepressant treatments. Nature. 1977; 266: 730–732. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1038/266730a0559941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>26Detke, MJ, Rickels, M and Lucki, I. Active behaviors in the rat forced swimming test differentially produced by serotonergic and noradrenergic antidepressants. Psychopharmacology. 1995; 121: 66–72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/BF022455928539342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>27Cryan, JF, Markou, A and Lucki, I. Assessing antidepressant activity in rodents: recent developments and future needs. Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2002; 23: 238–245. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0165-6147(02)02017-512008002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>28Cottingham, C and Wang, Q. α2 adrenergic receptor dysregulation in depressive disorders: Implications for the neurobiology of depression and antidepressant therapy. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2012; 36: 2214–2225. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.07.01122910678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>29Sugrue, MF. Chronic antidepressant therapy and associated changes in central monoaminergic receptor functioning. Pharmacol Ther. 1983; 21: 1–33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/0163-7258(83)90065-76312466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>30Hertz, L, Rothman, DL, Li, B and Peng, L. Chronic SSRI stimulation of astrocytic 5-HT2B receptors change multiple gene expressions/editings and metabolism of glutamate, glucose and glycogen: a potential paradigm shift. Front Behav Neurosci. 2015; 9 DOI: 10.3389/fnbeh.2015.00025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>31Usher, RW, Beasley, CM Jr. and Bosomworth, JC. Efficacy and safety of morning versus evening fluoxetine administration. J Clin Psychiatry. 1991; 52: 134–136.2005078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>32Marathe, PH, Lee, JS, Greene, DS and Barbhaiya, RH. Comparison of the steady-state pharmacokinetics of nefazodone after administration of 200 mg twice daily or 400 mg once daily in the morning or evening. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 1996; 41: 21–27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1111/j.1365-2125.1996.tb00154.x8824689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>33Bougerolle, AM, Chabard, JL, Jbilou, M, Dordain, G, Eschalier, A, Aumaitre, O, Gaillot, J, Piron, JJ, Petet, J and Berger, JA. Chronopharmacokinetic and bioequivalence studies of two formulations of trimipramine after oral administration in man. Eur J Drug Metab Pharmacokinet. 1989; 14: 139–144. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/BF031908542591418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>34Fujimura, A, Ohashi, K, Sugimoto, K, Kumagai, Y and Ebihara, A. Chronopharmacological study of nitrendipine in healthy subjects. J Clin Pharmacol. 1989; 29: 909–915. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1002/j.1552-4604.1989.tb03253.x2592583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>35Shiga, T, Fujimura, A, Tateishi, T, Ohashi, K and Ebihara, A. Differences of chronopharmacokinetic profiles between propranolol and atenolol in hypertensive subjects. J Clin Pharmacol. 1993; 33: 756–761. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1002/j.1552-4604.1993.tb05620.x8408738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>36Brosen, K, Zeugin, T and Meyer, UA. Role of P450IID6, the target of the sparteine-debrisoquin oxidation polymorphism, in the metabolism of imipramine. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 1991; 49: 609–617. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1038/clpt.1991.772060250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>37Lemoine, A, Gautier, JC, Azoulay, D, Kiffel, L, Belloc, C, Guengerich, FP, Maurel, P, Beaune, P and Leroux, JP. Major pathway of imipramine metabolism is catalyzed by cytochromes P-450 1A2 and P-450 3A4 in human liver. Mol Pharmacol. 1993; 43: 827–832.8502233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>38Gachon, F, Olela, FF, Schaad, O, Descombes, P and Schibler, U. The circadian PAR-domain basic leucine zipper transcription factors DBP, TEF, and HLF modulate basal and inducible xenobiotic detoxification. Cell Metab. 2006; 4: 25–36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.cmet.2006.04.01516814730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>39Baraldo, M. The influence of circadian rhythms on the kinetics of drugs in humans. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol. 2008; 4: 175–192. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1517/17425255.4.2.17518248311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>40Radzialowski, FM and Bousquet, WF. Daily rhythmic variation in hepatic drug metabolism in the rat and mouse. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1968; 163: 229–238.4970604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>41Zhang, YK, Yeager, RL and Klaassen, CD. Circadian expression profiles of drug-processing genes and transcription factors in mouse liver. Drug Metab Dispos. 2009; 37: 106–115. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1124/dmd.108.02417418838502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>42Ohno, M, Yamaguchi, I, Ito, T, Saiki, K, Yamamoto, I and Azuma, J. Circadian variation of the urinary 6beta-hydroxycortisol to cortisol ratio that would reflect hepatic CYP3A activity. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2000; 55: 861–865. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1007/s00228005070810805065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>43Matsunaga, N, Inoue, M, Kusunose, N, Kakimoto, K, Hamamura, K, Hanada, Y, Toi, A, Yoshimura, Y, Sato, F, Fujimoto, K, Koyanagi, S and Ohdo, S. Time-dependent interaction between DEC2 and C/EBPα underlies the circadian expression of CYP2D6 in serum-shocked HepG2 cells. Mol Phramacol. 2012; 81: 739–747. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1124/mol.111.076406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>44Nagayama, H. Influences of biological rhythms on the effects of psychotropic drugs. Psychosom Med. 1999; 61: 618–629. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1097/00006842-199909000-0000610511012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>45Tatsumi, M, Groshan, K, Blakely, RD and Richelson, E. Pharmacological profile of antidepressants and related compounds at human monoamine transporters. Eur J Pharmacol. 1997; 340: 249–258. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0014-2999(97)01393-99537821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>46De Paermentier, F, Maugera, JM, Lowthera, S, Cromptonb, MR, Katonac, CLE and Hortona, RW. Brain α-adrenoceptors in depressed suicides. Brain Res. 1997; 757: 60–68. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0006-8993(97)00138-89200499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>47Subhash, MN, Nagaraja, MR, Sharada, S and Vinod, KY. Cortical alpha-adrenoceptor downregulation by tricyclic antidepressants in the rat brain. Neurochem Int. 2003; 43: 603–609. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0197-0186(03)00097-412892647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>48Detke, MJ, Johnson, J and Lucki, I. Acute and chronic antidepressant drug treatment in the rat forced swimming test model of depression. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 1997; 5: 107–112. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1037/1064-1297.5.2.1079234045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>49Kitada, Y, Miyauchi, T, Satoh, A and Satoh, S. Effects of antidepressants in the rat forced swimming test. Eur J Pharmacol. 1981; 72: 145–152. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/0014-2999(81)90269-77195816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>50Delini-Stula, A, Radeke, E and van Riezen, H. Enhanced functional responsiveness of the dopaminergic system – the mechanism of anti-immobility effects of antidepressants in the behavioural despair test in the rat. Neuropharmacol. 1988; 27: 943–947. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/0028-3908(88)90122-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>51Nestler, EJ, Barrot, M, DiLeone, RJ, Eisch, AJ, Gold, SJ and Monteggia, LM. Neurobiology of depression. Neuron. 2002; 34: 13–25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0896-6273(02)00653-011931738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>52Kitamura, Y, Araki, H and Gomita, Y. Influence of ACTH on the effects of imipramine, desipramine and lithium on duration of immobility of rats in the forced swim test. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2002; 71: 63–69. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/S0091-3057(01)00625-611812508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>53Vijaya Kumar, K, Rudra, A, Sreedhara, MV, Siva Subramani, T, Prasad, DS, Das, ML, Murugesan, S, Yadav, R, Trivedi, RK, Louis, JV, Li, Y-W, Bristow, LJ, Naidu, PS and Vikramadithyan, RK. Bacillus Calmette–Guérin vaccine induces a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI)-resistant depression like phenotype in mice. Brain Behav Immun. 2014; 42: 204–211. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.bbi.2014.06.20525016199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>54Christiansen, SL, Bouzinova, EV, Fahrenkrug, J and Wiborg, O. Altered expression pattern of clock genes in a rat model of depression. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol. 2016; DOI: 10.1093/ijnp/pyw061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>55Logan, RW, Edgar, N, Gillman, AG, Hoffman, D, Zhu, X and McClung, CA. Chronic stress induces brain region-specific alterations of molecular rhythms that correlate with depression-like behavior in mice. Biol Psychiat. 2015; 78: 249–258. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.01.01125771506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>56Jiang, W-G, Li, S-X, Zhou, S-J, Sun, Y and Shi, J, Lu, L. Chronic unpredictable stress induces a reversible change of PER2 rhythm in the suprachiasmatic nucleus. Brain Res. 2011; 1399: 25–32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1016/j.brainres.2011.05.00121621196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
